<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE learningContent
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Learning Content//EN" "learningContent.dtd">
<learningContent id="SEC001">
   <title>1 Introducing cosmology</title>
   <learningContentbody>
      <section>
        
        
        <p>General relativity has a very different conceptual basis from that of Newtonian
          mechanics. Its success in accounting for the precession of Mercury's orbit, and the
          bending of light by massive objects like the Sun, gives us confidence that our picture of
          space and time should be Einstein's rather than Newton's. In this and the following units,
          we turn our attention to the study of the large-scale structure of spacetime. We see how
          spacetime as a whole is curved by the gross distribution of mass and energy in the
          Universe. This distribution, together with the question of how the Universe has developed
          over time, is the subject of <i>cosmology</i>.</p>
        
        <p>Astronomy and cosmology are subjects that merge into one another with the single
          combined aim of understanding the structure and history of the Universe. The basis and
          motivation for the whole subject area comes ultimately from astronomers’
          observations. Since the days of Galileo, optical telescopes of ever greater size have been
          made. In the last 60 years, it has been possible to study an increasing range of the
          electromagnetic spectrum as different types of telescope have become available. The first
          radio telescopes were made just before World War II. Infrared, ultraviolet, X-ray and
          gamma ray telescopes then followed, often operating from spacecraft above the Earth's
          atmosphere. These methods have become so complicated that we have attempted to outline
          only certain results; a far longer course would have been necessary to do anything like
          justice to the delicacy and sophistication of the techniques involved.</p>
        <p>What have we learned from these new techniques? Firstly, matter has been detected
          in a wide variety of forms – interstellar gas as well as the stars themselves, for
          instance. Secondly, it has become possible to perform detailed studies of the radiation
          from the very ancient Universe. These developments have given cosmologists a more
          comprehensive list of the forms of mass and energy that govern the spacetime of the
          Universe. Next, matter has been detected at much greater distances – the more
          distant view providing cosmologists with more telling tests of their models. Then there
          has been the increasingly detailed information on spectra, with its evidence on the
          compositions of the emitting bodies. This information is of particular concern to the
          astrophysicist, who tries to understand the evolution of stars and other types of matter.
          Such evolution is governed by stellar dynamics and the processes of nuclear physics. The
          latter will be touched on later, though with reference more to nuclear reactions taking
          place in the very early Universe than to those occurring in the stars today.</p>
        <p>We hope to build a bridge between the two extremes –
          the raw data obtained by the astronomer, and the metric parameters derived by the
          cosmologist. Thus, we examine the reasons for believing that the Universe had its origins
          in the big bang. We shall find that there are three independent pieces of evidence all
          pointing to the same conclusion. Sections 2 to 4 introduce you to the first of
          these.</p>
      </section>
   </learningContentbody>
</learningContent>