<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<chapter id="d5e2"><title>Towards the Future of Documentation</title><prolog/><body><p><image href="../images/chapter01.png" width="5in" placement="inline"/></p><epigram>Tell me… and I will forget. Show me… and I will remember. <br/>Involve me… and I will
        understand.<br/>—Confucius</epigram><p>As writers and content creators we are witnesses to the age of information shifting to the
      age of interaction. One week of content from the New York Times contains as much information
      as a person could get in a lifetime in the 18th century, according to information architect
      Richard Saul <indexterm>Wurman, Richard Saul</indexterm>Wurman in <i>Information Anxiety,</i>
      written in 1989. The speed at which we access this information is constantly improving—with
      fiber optic technology you can receive an amount of information equal to 10 full CDs per
      second. Filling a CD with that much text would take twelve years typing 100 words per minute!
      The only way people can handle this much information is to build relationships and act as
      filters for each other.</p><p>Some content creators do not yet see a link between <i>online help</i> and the blogs, wikis,
      and forum posts with which users are finding <i>help online</i>, ironically. I have seen in
      writers’ email lists such quotes as “Sorry, I absolutely refuse to discuss anything, even
      cats, on a blog!” or “I’d rather not trust an encyclopedia that would accept me as a
        <indexterm>community-generated content<indexterm>distrust
      of</indexterm></indexterm>contributor.” Even if the Groucho Marx reference was meant in jest,
      how can we learn from the age-old <indexterm>content<indexterm>community-generated</indexterm></indexterm>community behaviors that are now being applied
      to documentation?</p><p>Documentation as conversation means getting closer to users and helping them perform well.
        <indexterm>user-centered design</indexterm>User-centered design has been touted as one of
      the most important ideas developed in the last twenty years of workplace writing.<fn>
        <p> http://owl.english.purdue.edu/owl/resource/624/01/</p>
      </fn>
      <indexterm>Web 2.0<indexterm>role in user-centered design</indexterm></indexterm>Web 2.0 gives
      users a chance to interact with information and other users. </p><p>Now, writers can take the idea of user-centered design a step further by starting
      conversations with users and enabling user assistance in interactions. Writers have more
      conversation-starting tools at their disposal than at any other time in history. Tools may
      include blogs, wikis, forums, and social networking sites, but may also involve photos, simple
      stick figure illustrations, videos, virtual worlds, or instant messaging<indexterm>instant
        messaging (IM)</indexterm>.</p></body></chapter>
