<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE learningContent
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Learning Content//EN" "learningContent.dtd">
<learningContent id="SEC004_001">
   <title>4.1 Hubble's discoveries</title>
   <learningContentbody>
      <section>
          
          <p>In this section, we bring together two important features of galaxies –
            their redshifts and their distances.</p>
          <p>This crucial development owes its origins to Edwin Hubble. His pioneering work
            in 1923 first led to the confirmation that certain of the fuzzy patches in the sky,
            loosely called ‘nebulae’, were in fact galaxies like our own.</p>
          <fig>
            <title>
              <b>Figure 14</b>: (a) Nebula NGC 6514, a cloud of gas and dust in our own Galaxy; (b)
              Hubble showed that objects like M31 (NGC 224, now called the Andromeda galaxy) were
              galaxies like our own, and they ceased to be called nebulae. The two large bright
              patches near M31 are satellite galaxies, NGC 205 and NGC 221</title>
            <image href="../../media/S357_1_012i.jpg"/>
            <p outputclass="SourceReference">Source: (a) courtesy of Uppsala University; (b) Hale Observatories <data name="ItemRights">
                  <data name="OwnerRef"/>
                  <data name="ItemRef"/>
                  <data name="ItemAcknowledgement">(a) courtesy of Uppsala University; (b) Hale
                  Observatories</data>
              </data>
            </p>
            <p/>
         </fig>
          
          <p>It was immediately realised that the Universe was enormously bigger than had
            previously been thought. Also the number of galaxies was large. In fact, it is now known
            that the number of galaxies accessible to our telescopes is comparable with the number
            of stars in our Galaxy – about 100 billion (i.e. 10<sup>11</sup>).</p>
          <p>A second significant discovery made by Hubble concerned the spectra of
            galaxies, nearly all of which are redshifted. This redshift was a systematic shift of
              <i>all</i> the lines to the red end of the spectrum (it was discovered by another US
            astronomer, Vesto Slipher). Using his measurements of distance, Hubble showed that the
              <i>redshift increased with distance</i>. As far as he could tell, the redshift of a
            galaxy was proportional to its distance.</p>
          <fig>
            <title>
              <b>Figure 15</b>: The redshift–distance relationship for galaxies, as plotted
              by Hubble in 1929. The solid line represents the relationship inferred from individual
              galaxies (solid circles), the dashed line the relationship when the galaxies are
              combined into groups (open circles). Hubble's distance scale has been omitted since it
              is now known that it was in error.</title>
            <image href="../../media/S357_1_013i.jpg"/>
            <p outputclass="SourceReference">Source: based on E. P. Hubble (1929) in <i>Proc. Nat. Acad. Sci.</i>, 15, 168
                <data name="ItemRights">
                  <data name="OwnerRef"/>
                  <data name="ItemRef"/>
                  <data name="ItemAcknowledgement">based on E. P. Hubble (1929) in <i>Proc. Nat. Acad. Sci.</i>,
                  15, 168</data>
              </data>
            </p>
            <p/>
         </fig>
          <p>Hubble's original measurements, shown in <xref href="#FIG001_013">Figure 15</xref>, exhibited a large scatter about a straight
            line. This was partly due to the inevitable observational uncertainties, especially in
            distance measurements. But even if one were able to remove the observational
            uncertainties, there would still have been a considerable scatter about a straight line.
            This comes from the fact that most of the galaxies Hubble looked at were members of
            clusters, and each was moving about within its cluster. Because the galaxies were rather
            close to us, the speeds associated with this random motion were comparable to the
            recessional speed Hubble was trying to measure. Sometimes the motion of the galaxy
            relative to the cluster centre was directed towards us (giving a blueshift component),
            sometimes away from us (adding a further redshift component). If the structure of the
            cluster were well enough known, these effects could, in principle, be estimated and a
            correction applied. Allowance must also be made for small gravitational redshifts (see <xref href="#SAQ001_002">Question 2</xref>). Finally, the motion of the Earth with
            respect to our Local Group must be subtracted. (This will be discussed in <xref href="#SEC006_002_004">Section 6.2.4</xref>.) Suppose that <i>all</i> these
            corrections could be perfectly made in all cases. Then a redshift (<i>z</i>) against
            distance (<i>r</i>) plot would, as far as we know, appear as in <xref href="#FIG001_014">Figure 16</xref>.</p>
          
          <fig>
            <title>
              <b>Figure 16</b>: An idealised Hubble diagram with all sources of scatter
              removed</title>
            <image href="../../media/S357_1_014i.jpg"/>
            <p/>
         </fig>
          <p>The straight line in <xref href="#FIG001_014">Figure 16</xref> would represent the underlying cosmological
            redshift. Thus, for this <i>cosmological redshift</i>, we have</p>
          <fig outputclass="Equation">
            <image href="../../media/S357_1_e003i.gif"/>
            <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
         </fig>
          
          
          
          <p>Interpreting the observed redshift as a Doppler shift implies that each galaxy
            is receding at a speed proportional to its distance from us. To see this, consider the
            Doppler shift formula
            and
            the relationship between redshift, wavelength change and frequency shift given in the
            answer to <xref href="#SAQ001_003">Question 3</xref>
            . It follows that the redshift, <i>z</i>, is given by</p>
          <fig outputclass="Equation">
            <image href="../../media/S357_1_e004i.gif"/>
            <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
         </fig>
          <p>Hence, Equations 3 and 4 together imply that</p>
          <fig outputclass="Equation">
            <image href="../../media/S357_1_e005i.gif"/>
            <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
         </fig>
          <p>This provides the basis for one of the common ways of writing <i>Hubble's
              law</i>,</p>
          <fig outputclass="Equation">
            <image href="../../media/S357_1_e006i.gif"/>
            <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
         </fig>
          <p>The factor of proportionality, <i>H</i>, is sometimes called the <i>Hubble
              constant</i>. But the term <i>parameter</i> is perhaps preferable since the word
            ‘constant’ might lead one to think that it should remain constant in time
            – instead of being a constant of proportionality between two variables <i>as
              those variables are at a particular point in time. H</i> must, we now realise, vary
            slowly with time.</p>
          <p>If the speed of recession is proportional to distance, this implies <i>all</i>
            distances between galaxies are increasing at the same rate. Not only do all clusters of
            galaxies appear to be receding from us here on Earth, they would appear to be receding
            in exactly the same manner from whatever vantage point an observer adopted.</p>
          <p>Hubble's work has been continued, refined, and extended to much more distant
            and fainter galaxies.</p>
          
          <sectiondiv outputclass="SAQ">
            <p outputclass="Heading">
               <b>Question 6</b>
            </p>
            <sectiondiv outputclass="saq.question">
              <p>Taking typical intercluster distances to be approximately
                  2 × 10<sup>8</sup> ly, and the value of <i>H</i> to be about
                  2 × 10<sup>−18</sup> s<sup>−1</sup>, estimate the
                minimum <i>z</i> value that can reliably be ascribed to the expansion of the
                Universe. Compare this with the redshifts measured by Hubble in <xref href="#FIG001_013">Figure 15</xref>.</p>
            </sectiondiv>
            <sectiondiv outputclass="saq.answer">
              <p>To get a redshift that can confidently be regarded as due to expansion, we
                must look to another cluster.</p>
              <p>Intercluster distances are approximately</p>
              <fig outputclass="Equation">
                  <image href="../../media/S357_1_ue031i.gif"/>
                  <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
               </fig>
              <p>The Hubble constant is about 2 × 10<sup>−18</sup>
                  s<sup>−1</sup>
               </p>
              <p>Hence the cosmological redshift of a neighbouring cluster is</p>
              <fig outputclass="Equation">
                  <image href="../../media/S357_1_ue032i.gif"/>
                  <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
               </fig>
              <p>Compare this with <xref href="#FIG001_013">Figure 15</xref> – Hubble was not able to look far
                enough!</p>
            </sectiondiv>
          </sectiondiv>
          <p>Since it is hard to measure the distance to a far-off galaxy, it is not
            surprising that there has been a good deal of controversy about the reliability of
            distance estimates. The redshift measurements are much easier to make and are more
            direct, so there has been much less uncertainty over them. Nevertheless, it is useful to
            have a check, and this has been provided by radio astronomers measuring the redshift of
            lines in the radio spectrum, such as that due to the emission of hydrogen at a
            wavelength of 21 cm. This confirms that the redshift is the same over a large range of
            frequencies.</p>
          <p>Based on a range of recent results, the value of <i>H</i> is currently reckoned
            to be 2.3 × 10<sup>−18</sup> s<sup>−1</sup>, with an
            observational uncertainty of about 10%.</p>
          <p>Hubble, who interpreted redshifts in terms of recessional velocities, would
            quote this as 23 km s<sup>−1</sup> for every million light-years of distance of a
            galaxy. Estimates of <i>H</i> are often quoted in terms of km s<sup>−1</sup>
              Mpc<sup>−1</sup>. In these units, <i>H</i> is about 70 km s<sup>−1</sup>
              Mpc<sup>−1</sup>.</p>
          <p>It has become common usage to write
            <i>H</i> = <i>h</i> × 100 km s<sup>−1</sup>
              Mpc<sup>−1</sup>, in which case <i>h</i> currently has a best estimate of
            0.7.</p>
          <p>We end this section with a more up-to-date version of the Hubble diagram (<xref href="#FIG001_015">Figure 17</xref>) for some galaxies and clusters of
            galaxies.</p>
          <fig>
            <title>
              <b>Figure 17</b>: A plot of redshift against distance for a selection of galaxies and
              clusters of galaxies</title>
            <image href="../../media/S357_1_015i.jpg"/>
            <p outputclass="SourceReference">Source: adapted from A. Sandage (1970) <i>Physics Today</i>, vol. 34, February
              1970, American Institute of Physics <data name="ItemRights">
                  <data name="OwnerRef"/>
                  <data name="ItemRef"/>
                  <data name="ItemAcknowledgement">adapted from A. Sandage (1970) <i>Physics Today</i>, vol. 34,
                  February 1970, American Institute of Physics</data>
              </data>
            </p>
            <p/>
         </fig>
          
          <sectiondiv outputclass="SAQ">
            <p outputclass="Heading">
               <b>Question 7</b>
            </p>
            <sectiondiv outputclass="saq.question">
              <p>Use the sum of the shifts calculated for the star specified in <xref href="#SAQ001_002">Question 2</xref> to give an estimate of the uncertainty in
                the cosmological redshift <i>z</i> for a star in a galaxy at
                  4 × 10<sup>6</sup> ly from us. (This may be an overestimate because
                the centre of a line can be estimated quite well even if the line is fuzzy. However,
                in a real galactic spectrum there will be a further component of broadening due to
                galactic rotation.)</p>
            </sectiondiv>
            <sectiondiv outputclass="saq.answer">
              <p>From <xref href="#SAQ001_002">Question 2</xref>(b), parts (ii) and (iii), the minimum
                width of the lines is</p>
              <fig outputclass="Equation">
                  <image href="../../media/S357_1_ue033i.gif"/>
                  <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
               </fig>
              <p>with a systematic fractional shift of about
                  −2 × 10<sup>−6</sup> (<xref href="#SAQ001_002">Question 2</xref>(b), (i)). Thus the contributions to
                  Δ<i>f</i>/<i>f</i> due to turbulence, rotation and gravitational redshift
                vary between (+20 + 7 − 2) × 10<sup>−6</sup> and
                (−20 – 7 – 2) × 10<sup>−6</sup>. This
                gives an error of about ±3 × 10<sup>−5</sup>. For a
                galaxy at 4 × 10<sup>6</sup> ly
                  (≈4 × 10<sup>6</sup> × 10<sup>16</sup> m),
                the expected cosmological redshift is</p>
              <fig outputclass="Equation">
                  <image href="../../media/S357_1_ue034i.gif"/>
                  <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
               </fig>
              <p>Thus the line-broadening effects are approximately a fraction</p>
              <fig outputclass="Equation">
                  <image href="../../media/S357_1_ue035i.gif"/>
                  <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
               </fig>
              <p>of the expected cosmological shift.</p>
              <p>Notice that a distance of 4 × 10<sup>6</sup> ly corresponds
                to nearby galaxies in our Local Group and the relative uncertainties in redshift
                will <i>decrease</i> with distance. They are commonly less than 1%. The
                uncertainties in distance, however, will increase with distance, because less
                accurate estimation procedures have to be used. Also note that a distance of
                  4 × 10<sup>6</sup> ly may be unreasonably small for cosmological
                consideration.</p>
            </sectiondiv>
          </sectiondiv>
          
          <sectiondiv outputclass="SAQ">
            <p outputclass="Heading">
               <b>Question 8</b>
            </p>
            <sectiondiv outputclass="saq.question">
              <p>By taking appropriate readings off the graph of <xref href="#FIG001_015">Figure 17</xref>, estimate the value of the Hubble
                constant, <i>H</i>, indicated by this set of data.</p>
            </sectiondiv>
            <sectiondiv outputclass="saq.answer">
              <p>One can use any pair of points on the straight line graph that has been
                drawn, but to minimise reading errors we take the extreme points. The difference in
                  <i>z</i> is 1.0000 − 0.0025 = 0.9975. The difference in distance,
                  <i>r</i>, is 4000 − 10 = 3990 Mpc.</p>
              <p>Thus</p>
              <fig outputclass="Equation">
                  <image href="../../media/S357_1_ue036i.gif"/>
                  <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
               </fig>
              <p>But</p>
              <fig outputclass="Equation">
                  <image href="../../media/S357_1_ue037i.gif"/>
                  <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
               </fig>
              <p>So</p>
              <fig outputclass="Equation">
                  <image href="../../media/S357_1_ue038i.gif"/>
                  <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
               </fig>
            </sectiondiv>
          </sectiondiv>
        </section>
   </learningContentbody>
</learningContent>