<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE learningContent
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Learning Content//EN" "learningContent.dtd">
<learningContent id="SEC004_002">
   <title>4.2 Evidence for a big bang</title>
   <learningContentbody>
      <section>
          
          <p>Having interpreted the redshift as indicating a recessional speed proportional
            to distance, one may extrapolate into the future to predict how the positions of the
            galaxies will evolve with time. One can also run the sequence backwards, so to speak, to
            discuss what their positions were in the past. Clearly, at former times the galaxies
            were closer to each other.</p>
          <p>But not only that. Because of the proportional relationship between speed and
            distance (Equation 6), at a certain time in the past, all the matter of the Universe
            must have been together at a point of extraordinarily high density. It was from this
            condition that it subsequently expanded giving the matter of the Universe its
            present-day distribution. This is our first indication that the history of the Universe
            featured an explosive event.</p>
          
          <p>This has become known as the <i>big bang</i>. It is believed to have marked the
            beginning of the Universe. (Actually the phrase ‘big bang’ is used in two
            ways: (i) to denote the instant at which cosmic expansion begins; and (ii) to refer to
            that instant plus the sequence of events immediately following. It is usually clear from
            the context which of these meanings is intended.)</p>
          <p>It is possible to deduce much about the nature of the big bang and how long ago
            it took place – in other words, how old the Universe is. But we need to be sure
            that there really <i>was</i> a big bang. What we seek is evidence that is independent of
            the observation of moving galaxies. The remainder of this unit is devoted to describing
            just such confirmatory observations. Not only do they add to our confidence that the
            Universe did indeed have a definite beginning, they also inform us that the beginning
            was exceedingly violent – the big bang was hot. This indication assumes great
            importance when we seek to get some understanding of the varying types of process that
            must have been taking place during the initial stages of expansion – during the
            first years, minutes, even fractions of a second after the instant of the big
            bang.</p>
        </section>
   </learningContentbody>
</learningContent>