<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:shakespear:dtd:act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-2">
   <title>ACT II</title>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  A plain near Mortimer's Cross in Herefordshire.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>A march. Enter EDWARD, RICHARD, and their power</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>I wonder how our princely father 'scaped,</line>
            <line>Or whether he be 'scaped away or no</line>
            <line>From Clifford's and Northumberland's pursuit:</line>
            <line>Had he been ta'en, we should have heard the news;</line>
            <line>Had he been slain, we should have heard the news;</line>
            <line>Or had he 'scaped, methinks we should have heard</line>
            <line>The happy tidings of his good escape.</line>
            <line>How fares my brother? why is he so sad?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD</speaker>
            <line>I cannot joy, until I be resolved</line>
            <line>Where our right valiant father is become.</line>
            <line>I saw him in the battle range about;</line>
            <line>And watch'd him how he singled Clifford forth.</line>
            <line>Methought he bore him in the thickest troop</line>
            <line>As doth a lion in a herd of neat;</line>
            <line>Or as a bear, encompass'd round with dogs,</line>
            <line>Who having pinch'd a few and made them cry,</line>
            <line>The rest stand all aloof, and bark at him.</line>
            <line>So fared our father with his enemies;</line>
            <line>So fled his enemies my warlike father:</line>
            <line>Methinks, 'tis prize enough to be his son.</line>
            <line>See how the morning opes her golden gates,</line>
            <line>And takes her farewell of the glorious sun!</line>
            <line>How well resembles it the prime of youth,</line>
            <line>Trimm'd like a younker prancing to his love!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>Dazzle mine eyes, or do I see three suns?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD</speaker>
            <line>Three glorious suns, each one a perfect sun;</line>
            <line>Not separated with the racking clouds,</line>
            <line>But sever'd in a pale clear-shining sky.</line>
            <line>See, see! they join, embrace, and seem to kiss,</line>
            <line>As if they vow'd some league inviolable:</line>
            <line>Now are they but one lamp, one light, one sun.</line>
            <line>In this the heaven figures some event.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>'Tis wondrous strange, the like yet never heard of.</line>
            <line>I think it cites us, brother, to the field,</line>
            <line>That we, the sons of brave Plantagenet,</line>
            <line>Each one already blazing by our meeds,</line>
            <line>Should notwithstanding join our lights together</line>
            <line>And over-shine the earth as this the world.</line>
            <line>Whate'er it bodes, henceforward will I bear</line>
            <line>Upon my target three fair-shining suns.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD</speaker>
            <line>Nay, bear three daughters: by your leave I speak it,</line>
            <line>You love the breeder better than the male.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter a Messenger</stagedir>
            <line>But what art thou, whose heavy looks foretell</line>
            <line>Some dreadful story hanging on thy tongue?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>Ah, one that was a woful looker-on</line>
            <line>When as the noble Duke of York was slain,</line>
            <line>Your princely father and my loving lord!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>O, speak no more, for I have heard too much.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD</speaker>
            <line>Say how he died, for I will hear it all.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>Environed he was with many foes,</line>
            <line>And stood against them, as the hope of Troy</line>
            <line>Against the Greeks that would have enter'd Troy.</line>
            <line>But Hercules himself must yield to odds;</line>
            <line>And many strokes, though with a little axe,</line>
            <line>Hew down and fell the hardest-timber'd oak.</line>
            <line>By many hands your father was subdued;</line>
            <line>But only slaughter'd by the ireful arm</line>
            <line>Of unrelenting Clifford and the queen,</line>
            <line>Who crown'd the gracious duke in high despite,</line>
            <line>Laugh'd in his face; and when with grief he wept,</line>
            <line>The ruthless queen gave him to dry his cheeks</line>
            <line>A napkin steeped in the harmless blood</line>
            <line>Of sweet young Rutland, by rough Clifford slain:</line>
            <line>And after many scorns, many foul taunts,</line>
            <line>They took his head, and on the gates of York</line>
            <line>They set the same; and there it doth remain,</line>
            <line>The saddest spectacle that e'er I view'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>Sweet Duke of York, our prop to lean upon,</line>
            <line>Now thou art gone, we have no staff, no stay.</line>
            <line>O Clifford, boisterous Clifford! thou hast slain</line>
            <line>The flower of Europe for his chivalry;</line>
            <line>And treacherously hast thou vanquish'd him,</line>
            <line>For hand to hand he would have vanquish'd thee.</line>
            <line>Now my soul's palace is become a prison:</line>
            <line>Ah, would she break from hence, that this my body</line>
            <line>Might in the ground be closed up in rest!</line>
            <line>For never henceforth shall I joy again,</line>
            <line>Never, O never shall I see more joy!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD</speaker>
            <line>I cannot weep; for all my body's moisture</line>
            <line>Scarce serves to quench my furnace-burning heart:</line>
            <line>Nor can my tongue unload my heart's great burthen;</line>
            <line>For selfsame wind that I should speak withal</line>
            <line>Is kindling coals that fires all my breast,</line>
            <line>And burns me up with flames that tears would quench.</line>
            <line>To weep is to make less the depth of grief:</line>
            <line>Tears then for babes; blows and revenge for me</line>
            <line>Richard, I bear thy name; I'll venge thy death,</line>
            <line>Or die renowned by attempting it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>His name that valiant duke hath left with thee;</line>
            <line>His dukedom and his chair with me is left.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD</speaker>
            <line>Nay, if thou be that princely eagle's bird,</line>
            <line>Show thy descent by gazing 'gainst the sun:</line>
            <line>For chair and dukedom, throne and kingdom say;</line>
            <line>Either that is thine, or else thou wert not his.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>March. Enter WARWICK, MONTAGUE, and their army</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>How now, fair lords! What fare? what news abroad?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD</speaker>
            <line>Great Lord of Warwick, if we should recount</line>
            <line>Our baleful news, and at each word's deliverance</line>
            <line>Stab poniards in our flesh till all were told,</line>
            <line>The words would add more anguish than the wounds.</line>
            <line>O valiant lord, the Duke of York is slain!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>O Warwick, Warwick! that Plantagenet,</line>
            <line>Which held three dearly as his soul's redemption,</line>
            <line>Is by the stern Lord Clifford done to death.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Ten days ago I drown'd these news in tears;</line>
            <line>And now, to add more measure to your woes,</line>
            <line>I come to tell you things sith then befall'n.</line>
            <line>After the bloody fray at Wakefield fought,</line>
            <line>Where your brave father breathed his latest gasp,</line>
            <line>Tidings, as swiftly as the posts could run,</line>
            <line>Were brought me of your loss and his depart.</line>
            <line>I, then in London keeper of the king,</line>
            <line>Muster'd my soldiers, gather'd flocks of friends,</line>
            <line>And very well appointed, as I thought,</line>
            <line>March'd toward Saint Alban's to intercept the queen,</line>
            <line>Bearing the king in my behalf along;</line>
            <line>For by my scouts I was advertised</line>
            <line>That she was coming with a full intent</line>
            <line>To dash our late decree in parliament</line>
            <line>Touching King Henry's oath and your succession.</line>
            <line>Short tale to make, we at Saint Alban's met</line>
            <line>Our battles join'd, and both sides fiercely fought:</line>
            <line>But whether 'twas the coldness of the king,</line>
            <line>Who look'd full gently on his warlike queen,</line>
            <line>That robb'd my soldiers of their heated spleen;</line>
            <line>Or whether 'twas report of her success;</line>
            <line>Or more than common fear of Clifford's rigour,</line>
            <line>Who thunders to his captives blood and death,</line>
            <line>I cannot judge: but to conclude with truth,</line>
            <line>Their weapons like to lightning came and went;</line>
            <line>Our soldiers', like the night-owl's lazy flight,</line>
            <line>Or like an idle thresher with a flail,</line>
            <line>Fell gently down, as if they struck their friends.</line>
            <line>I cheer'd them up with justice of our cause,</line>
            <line>With promise of high pay and great rewards:</line>
            <line>But all in vain; they had no heart to fight,</line>
            <line>And we in them no hope to win the day;</line>
            <line>So that we fled; the king unto the queen;</line>
            <line>Lord George your brother, Norfolk and myself,</line>
            <line>In haste, post-haste, are come to join with you:</line>
            <line>For in the marches here we heard you were,</line>
            <line>Making another head to fight again.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>Where is the Duke of Norfolk, gentle Warwick?</line>
            <line>And when came George from Burgundy to England?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Some six miles off the duke is with the soldiers;</line>
            <line>And for your brother, he was lately sent</line>
            <line>From your kind aunt, Duchess of Burgundy,</line>
            <line>With aid of soldiers to this needful war.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD</speaker>
            <line>'Twas odds, belike, when valiant Warwick fled:</line>
            <line>Oft have I heard his praises in pursuit,</line>
            <line>But ne'er till now his scandal of retire.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Nor now my scandal, Richard, dost thou hear;</line>
            <line>For thou shalt know this strong right hand of mine</line>
            <line>Can pluck the diadem from faint Henry's head,</line>
            <line>And wring the awful sceptre from his fist,</line>
            <line>Were he as famous and as bold in war</line>
            <line>As he is famed for mildness, peace, and prayer.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD</speaker>
            <line>I know it well, Lord Warwick; blame me not:</line>
            <line>'Tis love I bear thy glories makes me speak.</line>
            <line>But in this troublous time what's to be done?</line>
            <line>Shall we go throw away our coats of steel,</line>
            <line>And wrap our bodies in black mourning gowns,</line>
            <line>Numbering our Ave-Maries with our beads?</line>
            <line>Or shall we on the helmets of our foes</line>
            <line>Tell our devotion with revengeful arms?</line>
            <line>If for the last, say ay, and to it, lords.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Why, therefore Warwick came to seek you out;</line>
            <line>And therefore comes my brother Montague.</line>
            <line>Attend me, lords. The proud insulting queen,</line>
            <line>With Clifford and the haught Northumberland,</line>
            <line>And of their feather many more proud birds,</line>
            <line>Have wrought the easy-melting king like wax.</line>
            <line>He swore consent to your succession,</line>
            <line>His oath enrolled in the parliament;</line>
            <line>And now to London all the crew are gone,</line>
            <line>To frustrate both his oath and what beside</line>
            <line>May make against the house of Lancaster.</line>
            <line>Their power, I think, is thirty thousand strong:</line>
            <line>Now, if the help of Norfolk and myself,</line>
            <line>With all the friends that thou, brave Earl of March,</line>
            <line>Amongst the loving Welshmen canst procure,</line>
            <line>Will but amount to five and twenty thousand,</line>
            <line>Why, Via! to London will we march amain,</line>
            <line>And once again bestride our foaming steeds,</line>
            <line>And once again cry 'Charge upon our foes!'</line>
            <line>But never once again turn back and fly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD</speaker>
            <line>Ay, now methinks I hear great Warwick speak:</line>
            <line>Ne'er may he live to see a sunshine day,</line>
            <line>That cries 'Retire,' if Warwick bid him stay.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>Lord Warwick, on thy shoulder will I lean;</line>
            <line>And when thou fail'st--as God forbid the hour!--</line>
            <line>Must Edward fall, which peril heaven forfend!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>No longer Earl of March, but Duke of York:</line>
            <line>The next degree is England's royal throne;</line>
            <line>For King of England shalt thou be proclaim'd</line>
            <line>In every borough as we pass along;</line>
            <line>And he that throws not up his cap for joy</line>
            <line>Shall for the fault make forfeit of his head.</line>
            <line>King Edward, valiant Richard, Montague,</line>
            <line>Stay we no longer, dreaming of renown,</line>
            <line>But sound the trumpets, and about our task.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD</speaker>
            <line>Then, Clifford, were thy heart as hard as steel,</line>
            <line>As thou hast shown it flinty by thy deeds,</line>
            <line>I come to pierce it, or to give thee mine.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>Then strike up drums: God and Saint George for us!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter a Messenger</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>How now! what news?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>The Duke of Norfolk sends you word by me,</line>
            <line>The queen is coming with a puissant host;</line>
            <line>And craves your company for speedy counsel.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Why then it sorts, brave warriors, let's away.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
            <line>3 KING HENRY VI</line>
         </speech>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  Before York.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Flourish. Enter KING HENRY VI, QUEEN MARGARET,
PRINCE EDWARD, CLIFFORD, and NORTHUMBERLAND, with
drum and trumpets</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Welcome, my lord, to this brave town of York.</line>
            <line>Yonder's the head of that arch-enemy</line>
            <line>That sought to be encompass'd with your crown:</line>
            <line>Doth not the object cheer your heart, my lord?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Ay, as the rocks cheer them that fear their wreck:</line>
            <line>To see this sight, it irks my very soul.</line>
            <line>Withhold revenge, dear God! 'tis not my fault,</line>
            <line>Nor wittingly have I infringed my vow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLIFFORD</speaker>
            <line>My gracious liege, this too much lenity</line>
            <line>And harmful pity must be laid aside.</line>
            <line>To whom do lions cast their gentle looks?</line>
            <line>Not to the beast that would usurp their den.</line>
            <line>Whose hand is that the forest bear doth lick?</line>
            <line>Not his that spoils her young before her face.</line>
            <line>Who 'scapes the lurking serpent's mortal sting?</line>
            <line>Not he that sets his foot upon her back.</line>
            <line>The smallest worm will turn being trodden on,</line>
            <line>And doves will peck in safeguard of their brood.</line>
            <line>Ambitious York doth level at thy crown,</line>
            <line>Thou smiling while he knit his angry brows:</line>
            <line>He, but a duke, would have his son a king,</line>
            <line>And raise his issue, like a loving sire;</line>
            <line>Thou, being a king, blest with a goodly son,</line>
            <line>Didst yield consent to disinherit him,</line>
            <line>Which argued thee a most unloving father.</line>
            <line>Unreasonable creatures feed their young;</line>
            <line>And though man's face be fearful to their eyes,</line>
            <line>Yet, in protection of their tender ones,</line>
            <line>Who hath not seen them, even with those wings</line>
            <line>Which sometime they have used with fearful flight,</line>
            <line>Make war with him that climb'd unto their nest,</line>
            <line>Offer their own lives in their young's defence?</line>
            <line>For shame, my liege, make them your precedent!</line>
            <line>Were it not pity that this goodly boy</line>
            <line>Should lose his birthright by his father's fault,</line>
            <line>And long hereafter say unto his child,</line>
            <line>'What my great-grandfather and his grandsire got</line>
            <line>My careless father fondly gave away'?</line>
            <line>Ah, what a shame were this! Look on the boy;</line>
            <line>And let his manly face, which promiseth</line>
            <line>Successful fortune, steel thy melting heart</line>
            <line>To hold thine own and leave thine own with him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Full well hath Clifford play'd the orator,</line>
            <line>Inferring arguments of mighty force.</line>
            <line>But, Clifford, tell me, didst thou never hear</line>
            <line>That things ill-got had ever bad success?</line>
            <line>And happy always was it for that son</line>
            <line>Whose father for his hoarding went to hell?</line>
            <line>I'll leave my son my virtuous deeds behind;</line>
            <line>And would my father had left me no more!</line>
            <line>For all the rest is held at such a rate</line>
            <line>As brings a thousand-fold more care to keep</line>
            <line>Than in possession and jot of pleasure.</line>
            <line>Ah, cousin York! would thy best friends did know</line>
            <line>How it doth grieve me that thy head is here!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>My lord, cheer up your spirits: our foes are nigh,</line>
            <line>And this soft courage makes your followers faint.</line>
            <line>You promised knighthood to our forward son:</line>
            <line>Unsheathe your sword, and dub him presently.</line>
            <line>Edward, kneel down.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Edward Plantagenet, arise a knight;</line>
            <line>And learn this lesson, draw thy sword in right.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE</speaker>
            <line>My gracious father, by your kingly leave,</line>
            <line>I'll draw it as apparent to the crown,</line>
            <line>And in that quarrel use it to the death.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLIFFORD</speaker>
            <line>Why, that is spoken like a toward prince.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter a Messenger</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>Royal commanders, be in readiness:</line>
            <line>For with a band of thirty thousand men</line>
            <line>Comes Warwick, backing of the Duke of York;</line>
            <line>And in the towns, as they do march along,</line>
            <line>Proclaims him king, and many fly to him:</line>
            <line>Darraign your battle, for they are at hand.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLIFFORD</speaker>
            <line>I would your highness would depart the field:</line>
            <line>The queen hath best success when you are absent.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Ay, good my lord, and leave us to our fortune.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Why, that's my fortune too; therefore I'll stay.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>Be it with resolution then to fight.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>My royal father, cheer these noble lords</line>
            <line>And hearten those that fight in your defence:</line>
            <line>Unsheathe your sword, good father; cry 'Saint George!'</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>March. Enter EDWARD, GEORGE, RICHARD, WARWICK,
NORFOLK, MONTAGUE, and Soldiers</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>Now, perjured Henry! wilt thou kneel for grace,</line>
            <line>And set thy diadem upon my head;</line>
            <line>Or bide the mortal fortune of the field?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Go, rate thy minions, proud insulting boy!</line>
            <line>Becomes it thee to be thus bold in terms</line>
            <line>Before thy sovereign and thy lawful king?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>I am his king, and he should bow his knee;</line>
            <line>I was adopted heir by his consent:</line>
            <line>Since when, his oath is broke; for, as I hear,</line>
            <line>You, that are king, though he do wear the crown,</line>
            <line>Have caused him, by new act of parliament,</line>
            <line>To blot out me, and put his own son in.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLIFFORD</speaker>
            <line>And reason too:</line>
            <line>Who should succeed the father but the son?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD</speaker>
            <line>Are you there, butcher? O, I cannot speak!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLIFFORD</speaker>
            <line>Ay, crook-back, here I stand to answer thee,</line>
            <line>Or any he the proudest of thy sort.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD</speaker>
            <line>'Twas you that kill'd young Rutland, was it not?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLIFFORD</speaker>
            <line>Ay, and old York, and yet not satisfied.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD</speaker>
            <line>For God's sake, lords, give signal to the fight.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>What say'st thou, Henry, wilt thou yield the crown?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Why, how now, long-tongued Warwick! dare you speak?</line>
            <line>When you and I met at Saint Alban's last,</line>
            <line>Your legs did better service than your hands.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Then 'twas my turn to fly, and now 'tis thine.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLIFFORD</speaker>
            <line>You said so much before, and yet you fled.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>'Twas not your valour, Clifford, drove me thence.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>No, nor your manhood that durst make you stay.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD</speaker>
            <line>Northumberland, I hold thee reverently.</line>
            <line>Break off the parley; for scarce I can refrain</line>
            <line>The execution of my big-swoln heart</line>
            <line>Upon that Clifford, that cruel child-killer.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLIFFORD</speaker>
            <line>I slew thy father, call'st thou him a child?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD</speaker>
            <line>Ay, like a dastard and a treacherous coward,</line>
            <line>As thou didst kill our tender brother Rutland;</line>
            <line>But ere sunset I'll make thee curse the deed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Have done with words, my lords, and hear me speak.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Defy them then, or else hold close thy lips.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>I prithee, give no limits to my tongue:</line>
            <line>I am a king, and privileged to speak.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLIFFORD</speaker>
            <line>My liege, the wound that bred this meeting here</line>
            <line>Cannot be cured by words; therefore be still.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD</speaker>
            <line>Then, executioner, unsheathe thy sword:</line>
            <line>By him that made us all, I am resolved</line>
            <line>that Clifford's manhood lies upon his tongue.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>Say, Henry, shall I have my right, or no?</line>
            <line>A thousand men have broke their fasts to-day,</line>
            <line>That ne'er shall dine unless thou yield the crown.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>If thou deny, their blood upon thy head;</line>
            <line>For York in justice puts his armour on.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>If that be right which Warwick says is right,</line>
            <line>There is no wrong, but every thing is right.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD</speaker>
            <line>Whoever got thee, there thy mother stands;</line>
            <line>For, well I wot, thou hast thy mother's tongue.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>But thou art neither like thy sire nor dam;</line>
            <line>But like a foul mis-shapen stigmatic,</line>
            <line>Mark'd by the destinies to be avoided,</line>
            <line>As venom toads, or lizards' dreadful stings.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD</speaker>
            <line>Iron of Naples hid with English gilt,</line>
            <line>Whose father bears the title of a king,--</line>
            <line>As if a channel should be call'd the sea,--</line>
            <line>Shamest thou not, knowing whence thou art extraught,</line>
            <line>To let thy tongue detect thy base-born heart?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>A wisp of straw were worth a thousand crowns,</line>
            <line>To make this shameless callet know herself.</line>
            <line>Helen of Greece was fairer far than thou,</line>
            <line>Although thy husband may be Menelaus;</line>
            <line>And ne'er was Agamemnon's brother wrong'd</line>
            <line>By that false woman, as this king by thee.</line>
            <line>His father revell'd in the heart of France,</line>
            <line>And tamed the king, and made the dauphin stoop;</line>
            <line>And had he match'd according to his state,</line>
            <line>He might have kept that glory to this day;</line>
            <line>But when he took a beggar to his bed,</line>
            <line>And graced thy poor sire with his bridal-day,</line>
            <line>Even then that sunshine brew'd a shower for him,</line>
            <line>That wash'd his father's fortunes forth of France,</line>
            <line>And heap'd sedition on his crown at home.</line>
            <line>For what hath broach'd this tumult but thy pride?</line>
            <line>Hadst thou been meek, our title still had slept;</line>
            <line>And we, in pity of the gentle king,</line>
            <line>Had slipp'd our claim until another age.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GEORGE</speaker>
            <line>But when we saw our sunshine made thy spring,</line>
            <line>And that thy summer bred us no increase,</line>
            <line>We set the axe to thy usurping root;</line>
            <line>And though the edge hath something hit ourselves,</line>
            <line>Yet, know thou, since we have begun to strike,</line>
            <line>We'll never leave till we have hewn thee down,</line>
            <line>Or bathed thy growing with our heated bloods.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>And, in this resolution, I defy thee;</line>
            <line>Not willing any longer conference,</line>
            <line>Since thou deniest the gentle king to speak.</line>
            <line>Sound trumpets! let our bloody colours wave!</line>
            <line>And either victory, or else a grave.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Stay, Edward.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>No, wrangling woman, we'll no longer stay:</line>
            <line>These words will cost ten thousand lives this day.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
            <line>3 KING HENRY VI</line>
         </speech>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  A field of battle between Towton and Saxton, in Yorkshire.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Alarum. Excursions. Enter WARWICK</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Forspent with toil, as runners with a race,</line>
            <line>I lay me down a little while to breathe;</line>
            <line>For strokes received, and many blows repaid,</line>
            <line>Have robb'd my strong-knit sinews of their strength,</line>
            <line>And spite of spite needs must I rest awhile.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter EDWARD, running</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>Smile, gentle heaven! or strike, ungentle death!</line>
            <line>For this world frowns, and Edward's sun is clouded.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>How now, my lord! what hap? what hope of good?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter GEORGE</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GEORGE</speaker>
            <line>Our hap is loss, our hope but sad despair;</line>
            <line>Our ranks are broke, and ruin follows us:</line>
            <line>What counsel give you? whither shall we fly?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>Bootless is flight, they follow us with wings;</line>
            <line>And weak we are and cannot shun pursuit.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter RICHARD</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD</speaker>
            <line>Ah, Warwick, why hast thou withdrawn thyself?</line>
            <line>Thy brother's blood the thirsty earth hath drunk,</line>
            <line>Broach'd with the steely point of Clifford's lance;</line>
            <line>And in the very pangs of death he cried,</line>
            <line>Like to a dismal clangour heard from far,</line>
            <line>'Warwick, revenge! brother, revenge my death!'</line>
            <line>So, underneath the belly of their steeds,</line>
            <line>That stain'd their fetlocks in his smoking blood,</line>
            <line>The noble gentleman gave up the ghost.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Then let the earth be drunken with our blood:</line>
            <line>I'll kill my horse, because I will not fly.</line>
            <line>Why stand we like soft-hearted women here,</line>
            <line>Wailing our losses, whiles the foe doth rage;</line>
            <line>And look upon, as if the tragedy</line>
            <line>Were play'd in jest by counterfeiting actors?</line>
            <line>Here on my knee I vow to God above,</line>
            <line>I'll never pause again, never stand still,</line>
            <line>Till either death hath closed these eyes of mine</line>
            <line>Or fortune given me measure of revenge.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>O Warwick, I do bend my knee with thine;</line>
            <line>And in this vow do chain my soul to thine!</line>
            <line>And, ere my knee rise from the earth's cold face,</line>
            <line>I throw my hands, mine eyes, my heart to thee,</line>
            <line>Thou setter up and plucker down of kings,</line>
            <line>Beseeching thee, if with they will it stands</line>
            <line>That to my foes this body must be prey,</line>
            <line>Yet that thy brazen gates of heaven may ope,</line>
            <line>And give sweet passage to my sinful soul!</line>
            <line>Now, lords, take leave until we meet again,</line>
            <line>Where'er it be, in heaven or in earth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD</speaker>
            <line>Brother, give me thy hand; and, gentle Warwick,</line>
            <line>Let me embrace thee in my weary arms:</line>
            <line>I, that did never weep, now melt with woe</line>
            <line>That winter should cut off our spring-time so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Away, away! Once more, sweet lords farewell.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GEORGE</speaker>
            <line>Yet let us all together to our troops,</line>
            <line>And give them leave to fly that will not stay;</line>
            <line>And call them pillars that will stand to us;</line>
            <line>And, if we thrive, promise them such rewards</line>
            <line>As victors wear at the Olympian games:</line>
            <line>This may plant courage in their quailing breasts;</line>
            <line>For yet is hope of life and victory.</line>
            <line>Forslow no longer, make we hence amain.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
            <line>3 KING HENRY VI</line>
         </speech>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-4">
      <title>SCENE IV.  Another part of the field.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Excursions. Enter RICHARD and CLIFFORD</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD</speaker>
            <line>Now, Clifford, I have singled thee alone:</line>
            <line>Suppose this arm is for the Duke of York,</line>
            <line>And this for Rutland; both bound to revenge,</line>
            <line>Wert thou environ'd with a brazen wall.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLIFFORD</speaker>
            <line>Now, Richard, I am with thee here alone:</line>
            <line>This is the hand that stabb'd thy father York;</line>
            <line>And this the hand that slew thy brother Rutland;</line>
            <line>And here's the heart that triumphs in their death</line>
            <line>And cheers these hands that slew thy sire and brother</line>
            <line>To execute the like upon thyself;</line>
            <line>And so, have at thee!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>They fight. WARWICK comes; CLIFFORD flies</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD</speaker>
            <line>Nay Warwick, single out some other chase;</line>
            <line>For I myself will hunt this wolf to death.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
            <line>3 KING HENRY VI</line>
         </speech>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-5">
      <title>SCENE V.  Another part of the field.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Alarum. Enter KING HENRY VI alone</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>This battle fares like to the morning's war,</line>
            <line>When dying clouds contend with growing light,</line>
            <line>What time the shepherd, blowing of his nails,</line>
            <line>Can neither call it perfect day nor night.</line>
            <line>Now sways it this way, like a mighty sea</line>
            <line>Forced by the tide to combat with the wind;</line>
            <line>Now sways it that way, like the selfsame sea</line>
            <line>Forced to retire by fury of the wind:</line>
            <line>Sometime the flood prevails, and then the wind;</line>
            <line>Now one the better, then another best;</line>
            <line>Both tugging to be victors, breast to breast,</line>
            <line>Yet neither conqueror nor conquered:</line>
            <line>So is the equal of this fell war.</line>
            <line>Here on this molehill will I sit me down.</line>
            <line>To whom God will, there be the victory!</line>
            <line>For Margaret my queen, and Clifford too,</line>
            <line>Have chid me from the battle; swearing both</line>
            <line>They prosper best of all when I am thence.</line>
            <line>Would I were dead! if God's good will were so;</line>
            <line>For what is in this world but grief and woe?</line>
            <line>O God! methinks it were a happy life,</line>
            <line>To be no better than a homely swain;</line>
            <line>To sit upon a hill, as I do now,</line>
            <line>To carve out dials quaintly, point by point,</line>
            <line>Thereby to see the minutes how they run,</line>
            <line>How many make the hour full complete;</line>
            <line>How many hours bring about the day;</line>
            <line>How many days will finish up the year;</line>
            <line>How many years a mortal man may live.</line>
            <line>When this is known, then to divide the times:</line>
            <line>So many hours must I tend my flock;</line>
            <line>So many hours must I take my rest;</line>
            <line>So many hours must I contemplate;</line>
            <line>So many hours must I sport myself;</line>
            <line>So many days my ewes have been with young;</line>
            <line>So many weeks ere the poor fools will ean:</line>
            <line>So many years ere I shall shear the fleece:</line>
            <line>So minutes, hours, days, months, and years,</line>
            <line>Pass'd over to the end they were created,</line>
            <line>Would bring white hairs unto a quiet grave.</line>
            <line>Ah, what a life were this! how sweet! how lovely!</line>
            <line>Gives not the hawthorn-bush a sweeter shade</line>
            <line>To shepherds looking on their silly sheep,</line>
            <line>Than doth a rich embroider'd canopy</line>
            <line>To kings that fear their subjects' treachery?</line>
            <line>O, yes, it doth; a thousand-fold it doth.</line>
            <line>And to conclude, the shepherd's homely curds,</line>
            <line>His cold thin drink out of his leather bottle.</line>
            <line>His wonted sleep under a fresh tree's shade,</line>
            <line>All which secure and sweetly he enjoys,</line>
            <line>Is far beyond a prince's delicates,</line>
            <line>His viands sparkling in a golden cup,</line>
            <line>His body couched in a curious bed,</line>
            <line>When care, mistrust, and treason waits on him.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Alarum. Enter a Son that has killed his father,
dragging in the dead body</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Son</speaker>
            <line>Ill blows the wind that profits nobody.</line>
            <line>This man, whom hand to hand I slew in fight,</line>
            <line>May be possessed with some store of crowns;</line>
            <line>And I, that haply take them from him now,</line>
            <line>May yet ere night yield both my life and them</line>
            <line>To some man else, as this dead man doth me.</line>
            <line>Who's this? O God! it is my father's face,</line>
            <line>Whom in this conflict I unwares have kill'd.</line>
            <line>O heavy times, begetting such events!</line>
            <line>From London by the king was I press'd forth;</line>
            <line>My father, being the Earl of Warwick's man,</line>
            <line>Came on the part of York, press'd by his master;</line>
            <line>And I, who at his hands received my life, him</line>
            <line>Have by my hands of life bereaved him.</line>
            <line>Pardon me, God, I knew not what I did!</line>
            <line>And pardon, father, for I knew not thee!</line>
            <line>My tears shall wipe away these bloody marks;</line>
            <line>And no more words till they have flow'd their fill.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>O piteous spectacle! O bloody times!</line>
            <line>Whiles lions war and battle for their dens,</line>
            <line>Poor harmless lambs abide their enmity.</line>
            <line>Weep, wretched man, I'll aid thee tear for tear;</line>
            <line>And let our hearts and eyes, like civil war,</line>
            <line>Be blind with tears, and break o'ercharged with grief.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter a Father that has killed his son, bringing in the body</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Father</speaker>
            <line>Thou that so stoutly hast resisted me,</line>
            <line>Give me thy gold, if thou hast any gold:</line>
            <line>For I have bought it with an hundred blows.</line>
            <line>But let me see: is this our foeman's face?</line>
            <line>Ah, no, no, no, it is mine only son!</line>
            <line>Ah, boy, if any life be left in thee,</line>
            <line>Throw up thine eye! see, see what showers arise,</line>
            <line>Blown with the windy tempest of my heart,</line>
            <line>Upon thy words, that kill mine eye and heart!</line>
            <line>O, pity, God, this miserable age!</line>
            <line>What stratagems, how fell, how butcherly,</line>
            <line>Erroneous, mutinous and unnatural,</line>
            <line>This deadly quarrel daily doth beget!</line>
            <line>O boy, thy father gave thee life too soon,</line>
            <line>And hath bereft thee of thy life too late!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Woe above woe! grief more than common grief!</line>
            <line>O that my death would stay these ruthful deeds!</line>
            <line>O pity, pity, gentle heaven, pity!</line>
            <line>The red rose and the white are on his face,</line>
            <line>The fatal colours of our striving houses:</line>
            <line>The one his purple blood right well resembles;</line>
            <line>The other his pale cheeks, methinks, presenteth:</line>
            <line>Wither one rose, and let the other flourish;</line>
            <line>If you contend, a thousand lives must wither.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Son</speaker>
            <line>How will my mother for a father's death</line>
            <line>Take on with me and ne'er be satisfied!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Father</speaker>
            <line>How will my wife for slaughter of my son</line>
            <line>Shed seas of tears and ne'er be satisfied!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>How will the country for these woful chances</line>
            <line>Misthink the king and not be satisfied!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Son</speaker>
            <line>Was ever son so rued a father's death?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Father</speaker>
            <line>Was ever father so bemoan'd his son?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Was ever king so grieved for subjects' woe?</line>
            <line>Much is your sorrow; mine ten times so much.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Son</speaker>
            <line>I'll bear thee hence, where I may weep my fill.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit with the body</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Father</speaker>
            <line>These arms of mine shall be thy winding-sheet;</line>
            <line>My heart, sweet boy, shall be thy sepulchre,</line>
            <line>For from my heart thine image ne'er shall go;</line>
            <line>My sighing breast shall be thy funeral bell;</line>
            <line>And so obsequious will thy father be,</line>
            <line>Even for the loss of thee, having no more,</line>
            <line>As Priam was for all his valiant sons.</line>
            <line>I'll bear thee hence; and let them fight that will,</line>
            <line>For I have murdered where I should not kill.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit with the body</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Sad-hearted men, much overgone with care,</line>
            <line>Here sits a king more woful than you are.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Alarums: excursions. Enter QUEEN MARGARET, PRINCE
EDWARD, and EXETER</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>Fly, father, fly! for all your friends are fled,</line>
            <line>And Warwick rages like a chafed bull:</line>
            <line>Away! for death doth hold us in pursuit.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Mount you, my lord; towards Berwick post amain:</line>
            <line>Edward and Richard, like a brace of greyhounds</line>
            <line>Having the fearful flying hare in sight,</line>
            <line>With fiery eyes sparkling for very wrath,</line>
            <line>And bloody steel grasp'd in their ireful hands,</line>
            <line>Are at our backs; and therefore hence amain.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EXETER</speaker>
            <line>Away! for vengeance comes along with them:</line>
            <line>Nay, stay not to expostulate, make speed;</line>
            <line>Or else come after: I'll away before.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Nay, take me with thee, good sweet Exeter:</line>
            <line>Not that I fear to stay, but love to go</line>
            <line>Whither the queen intends. Forward; away!</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
            <line>3 KING HENRY VI</line>
         </speech>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-6">
      <title>SCENE VI.  Another part of the field.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>A loud alarum. Enter CLIFFORD, wounded</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLIFFORD</speaker>
            <line>Here burns my candle out; ay, here it dies,</line>
            <line>Which, whiles it lasted, gave King Henry light.</line>
            <line>O Lancaster, I fear thy overthrow</line>
            <line>More than my body's parting with my soul!</line>
            <line>My love and fear glued many friends to thee;</line>
            <line>And, now I fall, thy tough commixture melts.</line>
            <line>Impairing Henry, strengthening misproud York,</line>
            <line>The common people swarm like summer flies;</line>
            <line>And whither fly the gnats but to the sun?</line>
            <line>And who shines now but Henry's enemies?</line>
            <line>O Phoebus, hadst thou never given consent</line>
            <line>That Phaethon should cheque thy fiery steeds,</line>
            <line>Thy burning car never had scorch'd the earth!</line>
            <line>And, Henry, hadst thou sway'd as kings should do,</line>
            <line>Or as thy father and his father did,</line>
            <line>Giving no ground unto the house of York,</line>
            <line>They never then had sprung like summer flies;</line>
            <line>I and ten thousand in this luckless realm</line>
            <line>Had left no mourning widows for our death;</line>
            <line>And thou this day hadst kept thy chair in peace.</line>
            <line>For what doth cherish weeds but gentle air?</line>
            <line>And what makes robbers bold but too much lenity?</line>
            <line>Bootless are plaints, and cureless are my wounds;</line>
            <line>No way to fly, nor strength to hold out flight:</line>
            <line>The foe is merciless, and will not pity;</line>
            <line>For at their hands I have deserved no pity.</line>
            <line>The air hath got into my deadly wounds,</line>
            <line>And much effuse of blood doth make me faint.</line>
            <line>Come, York and Richard, Warwick and the rest;</line>
            <line>I stabb'd your fathers' bosoms, split my breast.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>He faints</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Alarum and retreat. Enter EDWARD, GEORGE, RICHARD,
MONTAGUE, WARWICK, and Soldiers</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>Now breathe we, lords: good fortune bids us pause,</line>
            <line>And smooth the frowns of war with peaceful looks.</line>
            <line>Some troops pursue the bloody-minded queen,</line>
            <line>That led calm Henry, though he were a king,</line>
            <line>As doth a sail, fill'd with a fretting gust,</line>
            <line>Command an argosy to stem the waves.</line>
            <line>But think you, lords, that Clifford fled with them?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>No, 'tis impossible he should escape,</line>
            <line>For, though before his face I speak the words</line>
            <line>Your brother Richard mark'd him for the grave:</line>
            <line>And wheresoe'er he is, he's surely dead.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>CLIFFORD groans, and dies</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>Whose soul is that which takes her heavy leave?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD</speaker>
            <line>A deadly groan, like life and death's departing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>See who it is: and, now the battle's ended,</line>
            <line>If friend or foe, let him be gently used.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD</speaker>
            <line>Revoke that doom of mercy, for 'tis Clifford;</line>
            <line>Who not contented that he lopp'd the branch</line>
            <line>In hewing Rutland when his leaves put forth,</line>
            <line>But set his murdering knife unto the root</line>
            <line>From whence that tender spray did sweetly spring,</line>
            <line>I mean our princely father, Duke of York.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>From off the gates of York fetch down the head,</line>
            <line>Your father's head, which Clifford placed there;</line>
            <line>Instead whereof let this supply the room:</line>
            <line>Measure for measure must be answered.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>Bring forth that fatal screech-owl to our house,</line>
            <line>That nothing sung but death to us and ours:</line>
            <line>Now death shall stop his dismal threatening sound,</line>
            <line>And his ill-boding tongue no more shall speak.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>I think his understanding is bereft.</line>
            <line>Speak, Clifford, dost thou know who speaks to thee?</line>
            <line>Dark cloudy death o'ershades his beams of life,</line>
            <line>And he nor sees nor hears us what we say.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD</speaker>
            <line>O, would he did! and so perhaps he doth:</line>
            <line>'Tis but his policy to counterfeit,</line>
            <line>Because he would avoid such bitter taunts</line>
            <line>Which in the time of death he gave our father.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GEORGE</speaker>
            <line>If so thou think'st, vex him with eager words.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD</speaker>
            <line>Clifford, ask mercy and obtain no grace.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>Clifford, repent in bootless penitence.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Clifford, devise excuses for thy faults.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GEORGE</speaker>
            <line>While we devise fell tortures for thy faults.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD</speaker>
            <line>Thou didst love York, and I am son to York.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>Thou pitied'st Rutland; I will pity thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GEORGE</speaker>
            <line>Where's Captain Margaret, to fence you now?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>They mock thee, Clifford: swear as thou wast wont.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD</speaker>
            <line>What, not an oath? nay, then the world goes hard</line>
            <line>When Clifford cannot spare his friends an oath.</line>
            <line>I know by that he's dead; and, by my soul,</line>
            <line>If this right hand would buy two hour's life,</line>
            <line>That I in all despite might rail at him,</line>
            <line>This hand should chop it off, and with the</line>
            <line>issuing blood</line>
            <line>Stifle the villain whose unstanched thirst</line>
            <line>York and young Rutland could not satisfy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Ay, but he's dead: off with the traitor's head,</line>
            <line>And rear it in the place your father's stands.</line>
            <line>And now to London with triumphant march,</line>
            <line>There to be crowned England's royal king:</line>
            <line>From whence shall Warwick cut the sea to France,</line>
            <line>And ask the Lady Bona for thy queen:</line>
            <line>So shalt thou sinew both these lands together;</line>
            <line>And, having France thy friend, thou shalt not dread</line>
            <line>The scatter'd foe that hopes to rise again;</line>
            <line>For though they cannot greatly sting to hurt,</line>
            <line>Yet look to have them buzz to offend thine ears.</line>
            <line>First will I see the coronation;</line>
            <line>And then to Brittany I'll cross the sea,</line>
            <line>To effect this marriage, so it please my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>Even as thou wilt, sweet Warwick, let it be;</line>
            <line>For in thy shoulder do I build my seat,</line>
            <line>And never will I undertake the thing</line>
            <line>Wherein thy counsel and consent is wanting.</line>
            <line>Richard, I will create thee Duke of Gloucester,</line>
            <line>And George, of Clarence: Warwick, as ourself,</line>
            <line>Shall do and undo as him pleaseth best.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD</speaker>
            <line>Let me be Duke of Clarence, George of Gloucester;</line>
            <line>For Gloucester's dukedom is too ominous.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Tut, that's a foolish observation:</line>
            <line>Richard, be Duke of Gloucester. Now to London,</line>
            <line>To see these honours in possession.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
            <line>3 KING HENRY VI</line>
         </speech>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>