<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net/doctypes/dita/shakespear/dtd/act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-1">
   <title>ACT I</title>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  London. The Parliament-house.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Alarum. Enter YORK, EDWARD, RICHARD, NORFOLK, MONTAGUE, WARWICK, and Soldiers</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>I wonder how the king escaped our hands.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>While we pursued the horsemen of the north,</line>
            <line>He slily stole away and left his men:</line>
            <line>Whereat the great Lord of Northumberland,</line>
            <line>Whose warlike ears could never brook retreat,</line>
            <line>Cheer'd up the drooping army; and himself,</line>
            <line>Lord Clifford and Lord Stafford, all abreast,</line>
            <line>Charged our main battle's front, and breaking in</line>
            <line>Were by the swords of common soldiers slain.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>Lord Stafford's father, Duke of Buckingham,</line>
            <line>Is either slain or wounded dangerously;</line>
            <line>I cleft his beaver with a downright blow:</line>
            <line>That this is true, father, behold his blood.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MONTAGUE</speaker>
            <line>And, brother, here's the Earl of Wiltshire's blood,</line>
            <line>Whom I encounter'd as the battles join'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD</speaker>
            <line>Speak thou for me and tell them what I did.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Throwing down SOMERSET's head</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>Richard hath best deserved of all my sons.</line>
            <line>But is your grace dead, my Lord of Somerset?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Such hope have all the line of John of Gaunt!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD</speaker>
            <line>Thus do I hope to shake King Henry's head.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>And so do I. Victorious Prince of York,</line>
            <line>Before I see thee seated in that throne</line>
            <line>Which now the house of Lancaster usurps,</line>
            <line>I vow by heaven these eyes shall never close.</line>
            <line>This is the palace of the fearful king,</line>
            <line>And this the regal seat: possess it, York;</line>
            <line>For this is thine and not King Henry's heirs'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>Assist me, then, sweet Warwick, and I will;</line>
            <line>For hither we have broken in by force.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORFOLK</speaker>
            <line>We'll all assist you; he that flies shall die.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>Thanks, gentle Norfolk: stay by me, my lords;</line>
            <line>And, soldiers, stay and lodge by me this night.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>They go up</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>And when the king comes, offer no violence,</line>
            <line>Unless he seek to thrust you out perforce.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>The queen this day here holds her parliament,</line>
            <line>But little thinks we shall be of her council:</line>
            <line>By words or blows here let us win our right.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD</speaker>
            <line>Arm'd as we are, let's stay within this house.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>The bloody parliament shall this be call'd,</line>
            <line>Unless Plantagenet, Duke of York, be king,</line>
            <line>And bashful Henry deposed, whose cowardice</line>
            <line>Hath made us by-words to our enemies.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>Then leave me not, my lords; be resolute;</line>
            <line>I mean to take possession of my right.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Neither the king, nor he that loves him best,</line>
            <line>The proudest he that holds up Lancaster,</line>
            <line>Dares stir a wing, if Warwick shake his bells.</line>
            <line>I'll plant Plantagenet, root him up who dares:</line>
            <line>Resolve thee, Richard; claim the English crown.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Flourish. Enter KING HENRY VI, CLIFFORD,
NORTHUMBERLAND, WESTMORELAND, EXETER, and the rest</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>My lords, look where the sturdy rebel sits,</line>
            <line>Even in the chair of state: belike he means,</line>
            <line>Back'd by the power of Warwick, that false peer,</line>
            <line>To aspire unto the crown and reign as king.</line>
            <line>Earl of Northumberland, he slew thy father.</line>
            <line>And thine, Lord Clifford; and you both have vow'd revenge</line>
            <line>On him, his sons, his favourites and his friends.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>If I be not, heavens be revenged on me!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLIFFORD</speaker>
            <line>The hope thereof makes Clifford mourn in steel.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WESTMORELAND</speaker>
            <line>What, shall we suffer this? let's pluck him down:</line>
            <line>My heart for anger burns; I cannot brook it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Be patient, gentle Earl of Westmoreland.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLIFFORD</speaker>
            <line>Patience is for poltroons, such as he:</line>
            <line>He durst not sit there, had your father lived.</line>
            <line>My gracious lord, here in the parliament</line>
            <line>Let us assail the family of York.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>Well hast thou spoken, cousin: be it so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Ah, know you not the city favours them,</line>
            <line>And they have troops of soldiers at their beck?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EXETER</speaker>
            <line>But when the duke is slain, they'll quickly fly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Far be the thought of this from Henry's heart,</line>
            <line>To make a shambles of the parliament-house!</line>
            <line>Cousin of Exeter, frowns, words and threats</line>
            <line>Shall be the war that Henry means to use.</line>
            <line>Thou factious Duke of York, descend my throne,</line>
            <line>and kneel for grace and mercy at my feet;</line>
            <line>I am thy sovereign.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>I am thine.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EXETER</speaker>
            <line>For shame, come down: he made thee Duke of York.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>'Twas my inheritance, as the earldom was.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EXETER</speaker>
            <line>Thy father was a traitor to the crown.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Exeter, thou art a traitor to the crown</line>
            <line>In following this usurping Henry.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLIFFORD</speaker>
            <line>Whom should he follow but his natural king?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>True, Clifford; and that's Richard Duke of York.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>And shall I stand, and thou sit in my throne?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>It must and shall be so: content thyself.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Be Duke of Lancaster; let him be king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WESTMORELAND</speaker>
            <line>He is both king and Duke of Lancaster;</line>
            <line>And that the Lord of Westmoreland shall maintain.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>And Warwick shall disprove it. You forget</line>
            <line>That we are those which chased you from the field</line>
            <line>And slew your fathers, and with colours spread</line>
            <line>March'd through the city to the palace gates.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>Yes, Warwick, I remember it to my grief;</line>
            <line>And, by his soul, thou and thy house shall rue it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WESTMORELAND</speaker>
            <line>Plantagenet, of thee and these thy sons,</line>
            <line>Thy kinsman and thy friends, I'll have more lives</line>
            <line>Than drops of blood were in my father's veins.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLIFFORD</speaker>
            <line>Urge it no more; lest that, instead of words,</line>
            <line>I send thee, Warwick, such a messenger</line>
            <line>As shall revenge his death before I stir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Poor Clifford! how I scorn his worthless threats!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>Will you we show our title to the crown?</line>
            <line>If not, our swords shall plead it in the field.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>What title hast thou, traitor, to the crown?</line>
            <line>Thy father was, as thou art, Duke of York;</line>
            <line>Thy grandfather, Roger Mortimer, Earl of March:</line>
            <line>I am the son of Henry the Fifth,</line>
            <line>Who made the Dauphin and the French to stoop</line>
            <line>And seized upon their towns and provinces.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Talk not of France, sith thou hast lost it all.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>The lord protector lost it, and not I:</line>
            <line>When I was crown'd I was but nine months old.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD</speaker>
            <line>You are old enough now, and yet, methinks, you lose.</line>
            <line>Father, tear the crown from the usurper's head.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>Sweet father, do so; set it on your head.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MONTAGUE</speaker>
            <line>Good brother, as thou lovest and honourest arms,</line>
            <line>Let's fight it out and not stand cavilling thus.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD</speaker>
            <line>Sound drums and trumpets, and the king will fly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>Sons, peace!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Peace, thou! and give King Henry leave to speak.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Plantagenet shall speak first: hear him, lords;</line>
            <line>And be you silent and attentive too,</line>
            <line>For he that interrupts him shall not live.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Think'st thou that I will leave my kingly throne,</line>
            <line>Wherein my grandsire and my father sat?</line>
            <line>No: first shall war unpeople this my realm;</line>
            <line>Ay, and their colours, often borne in France,</line>
            <line>And now in England to our heart's great sorrow,</line>
            <line>Shall be my winding-sheet. Why faint you, lords?</line>
            <line>My title's good, and better far than his.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Prove it, Henry, and thou shalt be king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Henry the Fourth by conquest got the crown.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>'Twas by rebellion against his king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  I know not what to say; my title's weak.--</line>
            <line>Tell me, may not a king adopt an heir?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>What then?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>An if he may, then am I lawful king;</line>
            <line>For Richard, in the view of many lords,</line>
            <line>Resign'd the crown to Henry the Fourth,</line>
            <line>Whose heir my father was, and I am his.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>He rose against him, being his sovereign,</line>
            <line>And made him to resign his crown perforce.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Suppose, my lords, he did it unconstrain'd,</line>
            <line>Think you 'twere prejudicial to his crown?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EXETER</speaker>
            <line>No; for he could not so resign his crown</line>
            <line>But that the next heir should succeed and reign.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Art thou against us, Duke of Exeter?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EXETER</speaker>
            <line>His is the right, and therefore pardon me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>Why whisper you, my lords, and answer not?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EXETER</speaker>
            <line>My conscience tells me he is lawful king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  All will revolt from me, and turn to him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>Plantagenet, for all the claim thou lay'st,</line>
            <line>Think not that Henry shall be so deposed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Deposed he shall be, in despite of all.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>Thou art deceived: 'tis not thy southern power,</line>
            <line>Of Essex, Norfolk, Suffolk, nor of Kent,</line>
            <line>Which makes thee thus presumptuous and proud,</line>
            <line>Can set the duke up in despite of me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLIFFORD</speaker>
            <line>King Henry, be thy title right or wrong,</line>
            <line>Lord Clifford vows to fight in thy defence:</line>
            <line>May that ground gape and swallow me alive,</line>
            <line>Where I shall kneel to him that slew my father!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>O Clifford, how thy words revive my heart!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>Henry of Lancaster, resign thy crown.</line>
            <line>What mutter you, or what conspire you, lords?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Do right unto this princely Duke of York,</line>
            <line>Or I will fill the house with armed men,</line>
            <line>And over the chair of state, where now he sits,</line>
            <line>Write up his title with usurping blood.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>He stamps with his foot and the soldiers show
themselves</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>My Lord of Warwick, hear me but one word:</line>
            <line>Let me for this my life-time reign as king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>Confirm the crown to me and to mine heirs,</line>
            <line>And thou shalt reign in quiet while thou livest.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>I am content: Richard Plantagenet,</line>
            <line>Enjoy the kingdom after my decease.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLIFFORD</speaker>
            <line>What wrong is this unto the prince your son!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>What good is this to England and himself!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WESTMORELAND</speaker>
            <line>Base, fearful and despairing Henry!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLIFFORD</speaker>
            <line>How hast thou injured both thyself and us!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WESTMORELAND</speaker>
            <line>I cannot stay to hear these articles.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>Nor I.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLIFFORD</speaker>
            <line>Come, cousin, let us tell the queen these news.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WESTMORELAND</speaker>
            <line>Farewell, faint-hearted and degenerate king,</line>
            <line>In whose cold blood no spark of honour bides.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>Be thou a prey unto the house of York,</line>
            <line>And die in bands for this unmanly deed!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLIFFORD</speaker>
            <line>In dreadful war mayst thou be overcome,</line>
            <line>Or live in peace abandon'd and despised!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt NORTHUMBERLAND, CLIFFORD, and WESTMORELAND</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Turn this way, Henry, and regard them not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EXETER</speaker>
            <line>They seek revenge and therefore will not yield.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Ah, Exeter!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Why should you sigh, my lord?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Not for myself, Lord Warwick, but my son,</line>
            <line>Whom I unnaturally shall disinherit.</line>
            <line>But be it as it may: I here entail</line>
            <line>The crown to thee and to thine heirs for ever;</line>
            <line>Conditionally, that here thou take an oath</line>
            <line>To cease this civil war, and, whilst I live,</line>
            <line>To honour me as thy king and sovereign,</line>
            <line>And neither by treason nor hostility</line>
            <line>To seek to put me down and reign thyself.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>This oath I willingly take and will perform.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Long live King Henry! Plantagenet embrace him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>And long live thou and these thy forward sons!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>Now York and Lancaster are reconciled.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EXETER</speaker>
            <line>Accursed be he that seeks to make them foes!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Sennet. Here they come down</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>Farewell, my gracious lord; I'll to my castle.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>And I'll keep London with my soldiers.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORFOLK</speaker>
            <line>And I to Norfolk with my followers.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MONTAGUE</speaker>
            <line>And I unto the sea from whence I came.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt YORK, EDWARD, EDMUND, GEORGE, RICHARD,
WARWICK, NORFOLK, MONTAGUE, their Soldiers, and
Attendants</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>And I, with grief and sorrow, to the court.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter QUEEN MARGARET and PRINCE EDWARD</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EXETER</speaker>
            <line>Here comes the queen, whose looks bewray her anger:</line>
            <line>I'll steal away.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Exeter, so will I.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Nay, go not from me; I will follow thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Be patient, gentle queen, and I will stay.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Who can be patient in such extremes?</line>
            <line>Ah, wretched man! would I had died a maid</line>
            <line>And never seen thee, never borne thee son,</line>
            <line>Seeing thou hast proved so unnatural a father</line>
            <line>Hath he deserved to lose his birthright thus?</line>
            <line>Hadst thou but loved him half so well as I,</line>
            <line>Or felt that pain which I did for him once,</line>
            <line>Or nourish'd him as I did with my blood,</line>
            <line>Thou wouldst have left thy dearest heart-blood there,</line>
            <line>Rather than have that savage duke thine heir</line>
            <line>And disinherited thine only son.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>Father, you cannot disinherit me:</line>
            <line>If you be king, why should not I succeed?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Pardon me, Margaret; pardon me, sweet son:</line>
            <line>The Earl of Warwick and the duke enforced me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Enforced thee! art thou king, and wilt be forced?</line>
            <line>I shame to hear thee speak. Ah, timorous wretch!</line>
            <line>Thou hast undone thyself, thy son and me;</line>
            <line>And given unto the house of York such head</line>
            <line>As thou shalt reign but by their sufferance.</line>
            <line>To entail him and his heirs unto the crown,</line>
            <line>What is it, but to make thy sepulchre</line>
            <line>And creep into it far before thy time?</line>
            <line>Warwick is chancellor and the lord of Calais;</line>
            <line>Stern Falconbridge commands the narrow seas;</line>
            <line>The duke is made protector of the realm;</line>
            <line>And yet shalt thou be safe? such safety finds</line>
            <line>The trembling lamb environed with wolves.</line>
            <line>Had I been there, which am a silly woman,</line>
            <line>The soldiers should have toss'd me on their pikes</line>
            <line>Before I would have granted to that act.</line>
            <line>But thou preferr'st thy life before thine honour:</line>
            <line>And seeing thou dost, I here divorce myself</line>
            <line>Both from thy table, Henry, and thy bed,</line>
            <line>Until that act of parliament be repeal'd</line>
            <line>Whereby my son is disinherited.</line>
            <line>The northern lords that have forsworn thy colours</line>
            <line>Will follow mine, if once they see them spread;</line>
            <line>And spread they shall be, to thy foul disgrace</line>
            <line>And utter ruin of the house of York.</line>
            <line>Thus do I leave thee. Come, son, let's away;</line>
            <line>Our army is ready; come, we'll after them.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Stay, gentle Margaret, and hear me speak.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Thou hast spoke too much already: get thee gone.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Gentle son Edward, thou wilt stay with me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Ay, to be murder'd by his enemies.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>When I return with victory from the field</line>
            <line>I'll see your grace: till then I'll follow her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Come, son, away; we may not linger thus.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt QUEEN MARGARET and PRINCE EDWARD</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Poor queen! how love to me and to her son</line>
            <line>Hath made her break out into terms of rage!</line>
            <line>Revenged may she be on that hateful duke,</line>
            <line>Whose haughty spirit, winged with desire,</line>
            <line>Will cost my crown, and like an empty eagle</line>
            <line>Tire on the flesh of me and of my son!</line>
            <line>The loss of those three lords torments my heart:</line>
            <line>I'll write unto them and entreat them fair.</line>
            <line>Come, cousin you shall be the messenger.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EXETER</speaker>
            <line>And I, I hope, shall reconcile them all.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
            <line>3 KING HENRY VI</line>
         </speech>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  Sandal Castle.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter RICHARD, EDWARD, and MONTAGUE</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD</speaker>
            <line>Brother, though I be youngest, give me leave.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>No, I can better play the orator.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MONTAGUE</speaker>
            <line>But I have reasons strong and forcible.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter YORK</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>Why, how now, sons and brother! at a strife?</line>
            <line>What is your quarrel? how began it first?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>No quarrel, but a slight contention.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>About what?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD</speaker>
            <line>About that which concerns your grace and us;</line>
            <line>The crown of England, father, which is yours.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>Mine boy? not till King Henry be dead.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD</speaker>
            <line>Your right depends not on his life or death.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>Now you are heir, therefore enjoy it now:</line>
            <line>By giving the house of Lancaster leave to breathe,</line>
            <line>It will outrun you, father, in the end.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>I took an oath that he should quietly reign.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>But for a kingdom any oath may be broken:</line>
            <line>I would break a thousand oaths to reign one year.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD</speaker>
            <line>No; God forbid your grace should be forsworn.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>I shall be, if I claim by open war.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD</speaker>
            <line>I'll prove the contrary, if you'll hear me speak.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>Thou canst not, son; it is impossible.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD</speaker>
            <line>An oath is of no moment, being not took</line>
            <line>Before a true and lawful magistrate,</line>
            <line>That hath authority over him that swears:</line>
            <line>Henry had none, but did usurp the place;</line>
            <line>Then, seeing 'twas he that made you to depose,</line>
            <line>Your oath, my lord, is vain and frivolous.</line>
            <line>Therefore, to arms! And, father, do but think</line>
            <line>How sweet a thing it is to wear a crown;</line>
            <line>Within whose circuit is Elysium</line>
            <line>And all that poets feign of bliss and joy.</line>
            <line>Why do we finger thus? I cannot rest</line>
            <line>Until the white rose that I wear be dyed</line>
            <line>Even in the lukewarm blood of Henry's heart.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>Richard, enough; I will be king, or die.</line>
            <line>Brother, thou shalt to London presently,</line>
            <line>And whet on Warwick to this enterprise.</line>
            <line>Thou, Richard, shalt to the Duke of Norfolk,</line>
            <line>And tell him privily of our intent.</line>
            <line>You Edward, shall unto my Lord Cobham,</line>
            <line>With whom the Kentishmen will willingly rise:</line>
            <line>In them I trust; for they are soldiers,</line>
            <line>Witty, courteous, liberal, full of spirit.</line>
            <line>While you are thus employ'd, what resteth more,</line>
            <line>But that I seek occasion how to rise,</line>
            <line>And yet the king not privy to my drift,</line>
            <line>Nor any of the house of Lancaster?</line>
            <stagedir>Enter a Messenger</stagedir>
            <line>But, stay: what news? Why comest thou in such post?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>The queen with all the northern earls and lords</line>
            <line>Intend here to besiege you in your castle:</line>
            <line>She is hard by with twenty thousand men;</line>
            <line>And therefore fortify your hold, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>Ay, with my sword. What! think'st thou that we fear them?</line>
            <line>Edward and Richard, you shall stay with me;</line>
            <line>My brother Montague shall post to London:</line>
            <line>Let noble Warwick, Cobham, and the rest,</line>
            <line>Whom we have left protectors of the king,</line>
            <line>With powerful policy strengthen themselves,</line>
            <line>And trust not simple Henry nor his oaths.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MONTAGUE</speaker>
            <line>Brother, I go; I'll win them, fear it not:</line>
            <line>And thus most humbly I do take my leave.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
            <stagedir>Enter JOHN MORTIMER and HUGH MORTIMER</stagedir>
            <line>Sir John and Sir Hugh Mortimer, mine uncles,</line>
            <line>You are come to Sandal in a happy hour;</line>
            <line>The army of the queen mean to besiege us.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOHN MORTIMER</speaker>
            <line>She shall not need; we'll meet her in the field.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>What, with five thousand men?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD</speaker>
            <line>Ay, with five hundred, father, for a need:</line>
            <line>A woman's general; what should we fear?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>A march afar off</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>I hear their drums: let's set our men in order,</line>
            <line>And issue forth and bid them battle straight.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>Five men to twenty! though the odds be great,</line>
            <line>I doubt not, uncle, of our victory.</line>
            <line>Many a battle have I won in France,</line>
            <line>When as the enemy hath been ten to one:</line>
            <line>Why should I not now have the like success?</line>
            <stagedir>Alarum. Exeunt</stagedir>
            <line>3 KING HENRY VI</line>
         </speech>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  Field of battle betwixt Sandal Castle and Wakefield.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Alarums. Enter RUTLAND and his Tutor</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RUTLAND</speaker>
            <line>Ah, whither shall I fly to 'scape their hands?</line>
            <line>Ah, tutor, look where bloody Clifford comes!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter CLIFFORD and Soldiers</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLIFFORD</speaker>
            <line>Chaplain, away! thy priesthood saves thy life.</line>
            <line>As for the brat of this accursed duke,</line>
            <line>Whose father slew my father, he shall die.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Tutor</speaker>
            <line>And I, my lord, will bear him company.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLIFFORD</speaker>
            <line>Soldiers, away with him!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Tutor</speaker>
            <line>Ah, Clifford, murder not this innocent child,</line>
            <line>Lest thou be hated both of God and man!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit, dragged off by Soldiers</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLIFFORD</speaker>
            <line>How now! is he dead already? or is it fear</line>
            <line>That makes him close his eyes? I'll open them.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RUTLAND</speaker>
            <line>So looks the pent-up lion o'er the wretch</line>
            <line>That trembles under his devouring paws;</line>
            <line>And so he walks, insulting o'er his prey,</line>
            <line>And so he comes, to rend his limbs asunder.</line>
            <line>Ah, gentle Clifford, kill me with thy sword,</line>
            <line>And not with such a cruel threatening look.</line>
            <line>Sweet Clifford, hear me speak before I die.</line>
            <line>I am too mean a subject for thy wrath:</line>
            <line>Be thou revenged on men, and let me live.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLIFFORD</speaker>
            <line>In vain thou speak'st, poor boy; my father's blood</line>
            <line>Hath stopp'd the passage where thy words should enter.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RUTLAND</speaker>
            <line>Then let my father's blood open it again:</line>
            <line>He is a man, and, Clifford, cope with him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLIFFORD</speaker>
            <line>Had thy brethren here, their lives and thine</line>
            <line>Were not revenge sufficient for me;</line>
            <line>No, if I digg'd up thy forefathers' graves</line>
            <line>And hung their rotten coffins up in chains,</line>
            <line>It could not slake mine ire, nor ease my heart.</line>
            <line>The sight of any of the house of York</line>
            <line>Is as a fury to torment my soul;</line>
            <line>And till I root out their accursed line</line>
            <line>And leave not one alive, I live in hell.</line>
            <line>Therefore--</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Lifting his hand</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RUTLAND</speaker>
            <line>O, let me pray before I take my death!</line>
            <line>To thee I pray; sweet Clifford, pity me!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLIFFORD</speaker>
            <line>Such pity as my rapier's point affords.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RUTLAND</speaker>
            <line>I never did thee harm: why wilt thou slay me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLIFFORD</speaker>
            <line>Thy father hath.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RUTLAND</speaker>
            <line>But 'twas ere I was born.</line>
            <line>Thou hast one son; for his sake pity me,</line>
            <line>Lest in revenge thereof, sith God is just,</line>
            <line>He be as miserably slain as I.</line>
            <line>Ah, let me live in prison all my days;</line>
            <line>And when I give occasion of offence,</line>
            <line>Then let me die, for now thou hast no cause.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLIFFORD</speaker>
            <line>No cause!</line>
            <line>Thy father slew my father; therefore, die.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Stabs him</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RUTLAND</speaker>
            <line>Di faciant laudis summa sit ista tuae!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Dies</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLIFFORD</speaker>
            <line>Plantagenet! I come, Plantagenet!</line>
            <line>And this thy son's blood cleaving to my blade</line>
            <line>Shall rust upon my weapon, till thy blood,</line>
            <line>Congeal'd with this, do make me wipe off both.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
            <line>3 KING HENRY VI</line>
         </speech>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-4">
      <title>SCENE IV.  Another part of the field.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Alarum. Enter YORK</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>The army of the queen hath got the field:</line>
            <line>My uncles both are slain in rescuing me;</line>
            <line>And all my followers to the eager foe</line>
            <line>Turn back and fly, like ships before the wind</line>
            <line>Or lambs pursued by hunger-starved wolves.</line>
            <line>My sons, God knows what hath bechanced them:</line>
            <line>But this I know, they have demean'd themselves</line>
            <line>Like men born to renown by life or death.</line>
            <line>Three times did Richard make a lane to me.</line>
            <line>And thrice cried 'Courage, father! fight it out!'</line>
            <line>And full as oft came Edward to my side,</line>
            <line>With purple falchion, painted to the hilt</line>
            <line>In blood of those that had encounter'd him:</line>
            <line>And when the hardiest warriors did retire,</line>
            <line>Richard cried 'Charge! and give no foot of ground!'</line>
            <line>And cried 'A crown, or else a glorious tomb!</line>
            <line>A sceptre, or an earthly sepulchre!'</line>
            <line>With this, we charged again: but, out, alas!</line>
            <line>We bodged again; as I have seen a swan</line>
            <line>With bootless labour swim against the tide</line>
            <line>And spend her strength with over-matching waves.</line>
            <stagedir>A short alarum within</stagedir>
            <line>Ah, hark! the fatal followers do pursue;</line>
            <line>And I am faint and cannot fly their fury:</line>
            <line>And were I strong, I would not shun their fury:</line>
            <line>The sands are number'd that make up my life;</line>
            <line>Here must I stay, and here my life must end.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter QUEEN MARGARET, CLIFFORD, NORTHUMBERLAND,
PRINCE EDWARD, and Soldiers</stagedir>
            <line>Come, bloody Clifford, rough Northumberland,</line>
            <line>I dare your quenchless fury to more rage:</line>
            <line>I am your butt, and I abide your shot.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>Yield to our mercy, proud Plantagenet.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLIFFORD</speaker>
            <line>Ay, to such mercy as his ruthless arm,</line>
            <line>With downright payment, show'd unto my father.</line>
            <line>Now Phaethon hath tumbled from his car,</line>
            <line>And made an evening at the noontide prick.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>My ashes, as the phoenix, may bring forth</line>
            <line>A bird that will revenge upon you all:</line>
            <line>And in that hope I throw mine eyes to heaven,</line>
            <line>Scorning whate'er you can afflict me with.</line>
            <line>Why come you not? what! multitudes, and fear?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLIFFORD</speaker>
            <line>So cowards fight when they can fly no further;</line>
            <line>So doves do peck the falcon's piercing talons;</line>
            <line>So desperate thieves, all hopeless of their lives,</line>
            <line>Breathe out invectives 'gainst the officers.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>O Clifford, but bethink thee once again,</line>
            <line>And in thy thought o'er-run my former time;</line>
            <line>And, if though canst for blushing, view this face,</line>
            <line>And bite thy tongue, that slanders him with cowardice</line>
            <line>Whose frown hath made thee faint and fly ere this!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLIFFORD</speaker>
            <line>I will not bandy with thee word for word,</line>
            <line>But buckle with thee blows, twice two for one.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Hold, valiant Clifford! for a thousand causes</line>
            <line>I would prolong awhile the traitor's life.</line>
            <line>Wrath makes him deaf: speak thou, Northumberland.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>Hold, Clifford! do not honour him so much</line>
            <line>To prick thy finger, though to wound his heart:</line>
            <line>What valour were it, when a cur doth grin,</line>
            <line>For one to thrust his hand between his teeth,</line>
            <line>When he might spurn him with his foot away?</line>
            <line>It is war's prize to take all vantages;</line>
            <line>And ten to one is no impeach of valour.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>They lay hands on YORK, who struggles</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLIFFORD</speaker>
            <line>Ay, ay, so strives the woodcock with the gin.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>So doth the cony struggle in the net.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>So triumph thieves upon their conquer'd booty;</line>
            <line>So true men yield, with robbers so o'ermatch'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>What would your grace have done unto him now?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Brave warriors, Clifford and Northumberland,</line>
            <line>Come, make him stand upon this molehill here,</line>
            <line>That raught at mountains with outstretched arms,</line>
            <line>Yet parted but the shadow with his hand.</line>
            <line>What! was it you that would be England's king?</line>
            <line>Was't you that revell'd in our parliament,</line>
            <line>And made a preachment of your high descent?</line>
            <line>Where are your mess of sons to back you now?</line>
            <line>The wanton Edward, and the lusty George?</line>
            <line>And where's that valiant crook-back prodigy,</line>
            <line>Dicky your boy, that with his grumbling voice</line>
            <line>Was wont to cheer his dad in mutinies?</line>
            <line>Or, with the rest, where is your darling Rutland?</line>
            <line>Look, York: I stain'd this napkin with the blood</line>
            <line>That valiant Clifford, with his rapier's point,</line>
            <line>Made issue from the bosom of the boy;</line>
            <line>And if thine eyes can water for his death,</line>
            <line>I give thee this to dry thy cheeks withal.</line>
            <line>Alas poor York! but that I hate thee deadly,</line>
            <line>I should lament thy miserable state.</line>
            <line>I prithee, grieve, to make me merry, York.</line>
            <line>What, hath thy fiery heart so parch'd thine entrails</line>
            <line>That not a tear can fall for Rutland's death?</line>
            <line>Why art thou patient, man? thou shouldst be mad;</line>
            <line>And I, to make thee mad, do mock thee thus.</line>
            <line>Stamp, rave, and fret, that I may sing and dance.</line>
            <line>Thou wouldst be fee'd, I see, to make me sport:</line>
            <line>York cannot speak, unless he wear a crown.</line>
            <line>A crown for York! and, lords, bow low to him:</line>
            <line>Hold you his hands, whilst I do set it on.</line>
            <stagedir>Putting a paper crown on his head</stagedir>
            <line>Ay, marry, sir, now looks he like a king!</line>
            <line>Ay, this is he that took King Henry's chair,</line>
            <line>And this is he was his adopted heir.</line>
            <line>But how is it that great Plantagenet</line>
            <line>Is crown'd so soon, and broke his solemn oath?</line>
            <line>As I bethink me, you should not be king</line>
            <line>Till our King Henry had shook hands with death.</line>
            <line>And will you pale your head in Henry's glory,</line>
            <line>And rob his temples of the diadem,</line>
            <line>Now in his life, against your holy oath?</line>
            <line>O, 'tis a fault too too unpardonable!</line>
            <line>Off with the crown, and with the crown his head;</line>
            <line>And, whilst we breathe, take time to do him dead.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLIFFORD</speaker>
            <line>That is my office, for my father's sake.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Nay, stay; lets hear the orisons he makes.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>She-wolf of France, but worse than wolves of France,</line>
            <line>Whose tongue more poisons than the adder's tooth!</line>
            <line>How ill-beseeming is it in thy sex</line>
            <line>To triumph, like an Amazonian trull,</line>
            <line>Upon their woes whom fortune captivates!</line>
            <line>But that thy face is, vizard-like, unchanging,</line>
            <line>Made impudent with use of evil deeds,</line>
            <line>I would assay, proud queen, to make thee blush.</line>
            <line>To tell thee whence thou camest, of whom derived,</line>
            <line>Were shame enough to shame thee, wert thou not shameless.</line>
            <line>Thy father bears the type of King of Naples,</line>
            <line>Of both the Sicils and Jerusalem,</line>
            <line>Yet not so wealthy as an English yeoman.</line>
            <line>Hath that poor monarch taught thee to insult?</line>
            <line>It needs not, nor it boots thee not, proud queen,</line>
            <line>Unless the adage must be verified,</line>
            <line>That beggars mounted run their horse to death.</line>
            <line>'Tis beauty that doth oft make women proud;</line>
            <line>But, God he knows, thy share thereof is small:</line>
            <line>'Tis virtue that doth make them most admired;</line>
            <line>The contrary doth make thee wonder'd at:</line>
            <line>'Tis government that makes them seem divine;</line>
            <line>The want thereof makes thee abominable:</line>
            <line>Thou art as opposite to every good</line>
            <line>As the Antipodes are unto us,</line>
            <line>Or as the south to the septentrion.</line>
            <line>O tiger's heart wrapt in a woman's hide!</line>
            <line>How couldst thou drain the life-blood of the child,</line>
            <line>To bid the father wipe his eyes withal,</line>
            <line>And yet be seen to bear a woman's face?</line>
            <line>Women are soft, mild, pitiful and flexible;</line>
            <line>Thou stern, obdurate, flinty, rough, remorseless.</line>
            <line>Bids't thou me rage? why, now thou hast thy wish:</line>
            <line>Wouldst have me weep? why, now thou hast thy will:</line>
            <line>For raging wind blows up incessant showers,</line>
            <line>And when the rage allays, the rain begins.</line>
            <line>These tears are my sweet Rutland's obsequies:</line>
            <line>And every drop cries vengeance for his death,</line>
            <line>'Gainst thee, fell Clifford, and thee, false</line>
            <line>Frenchwoman.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>Beshrew me, but his passion moves me so</line>
            <line>That hardly can I cheque my eyes from tears.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>That face of his the hungry cannibals</line>
            <line>Would not have touch'd, would not have stain'd with blood:</line>
            <line>But you are more inhuman, more inexorable,</line>
            <line>O, ten times more, than tigers of Hyrcania.</line>
            <line>See, ruthless queen, a hapless father's tears:</line>
            <line>This cloth thou dip'dst in blood of my sweet boy,</line>
            <line>And I with tears do wash the blood away.</line>
            <line>Keep thou the napkin, and go boast of this:</line>
            <line>And if thou tell'st the heavy story right,</line>
            <line>Upon my soul, the hearers will shed tears;</line>
            <line>Yea even my foes will shed fast-falling tears,</line>
            <line>And say 'Alas, it was a piteous deed!'</line>
            <line>There, take the crown, and, with the crown, my curse;</line>
            <line>And in thy need such comfort come to thee</line>
            <line>As now I reap at thy too cruel hand!</line>
            <line>Hard-hearted Clifford, take me from the world:</line>
            <line>My soul to heaven, my blood upon your heads!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>Had he been slaughter-man to all my kin,</line>
            <line>I should not for my life but weep with him.</line>
            <line>To see how inly sorrow gripes his soul.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>What, weeping-ripe, my Lord Northumberland?</line>
            <line>Think but upon the wrong he did us all,</line>
            <line>And that will quickly dry thy melting tears.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLIFFORD</speaker>
            <line>Here's for my oath, here's for my father's death.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Stabbing him</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>And here's to right our gentle-hearted king.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Stabbing him</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>Open Thy gate of mercy, gracious God!</line>
            <line>My soul flies through these wounds to seek out Thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Dies</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Off with his head, and set it on York gates;</line>
            <line>So York may overlook the town of York.</line>
            <stagedir>Flourish. Exeunt</stagedir>
            <line>3 KING HENRY VI</line>
         </speech>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>