<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:shakespear:dtd:act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-3">
   <title>ACT III</title>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  A forest in the north of England.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter two Keepers, with cross-bows in their hands</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Keeper</speaker>
            <line>Under this thick-grown brake we'll shroud ourselves;</line>
            <line>For through this laund anon the deer will come;</line>
            <line>And in this covert will we make our stand,</line>
            <line>Culling the principal of all the deer.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Keeper</speaker>
            <line>I'll stay above the hill, so both may shoot.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Keeper</speaker>
            <line>That cannot be; the noise of thy cross-bow</line>
            <line>Will scare the herd, and so my shoot is lost.</line>
            <line>Here stand we both, and aim we at the best:</line>
            <line>And, for the time shall not seem tedious,</line>
            <line>I'll tell thee what befell me on a day</line>
            <line>In this self-place where now we mean to stand.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Keeper</speaker>
            <line>Here comes a man; let's stay till he be past.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter KING HENRY VI, disguised, with a prayerbook</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>From Scotland am I stol'n, even of pure love,</line>
            <line>To greet mine own land with my wishful sight.</line>
            <line>No, Harry, Harry, 'tis no land of thine;</line>
            <line>Thy place is fill'd, thy sceptre wrung from thee,</line>
            <line>Thy balm wash'd off wherewith thou wast anointed:</line>
            <line>No bending knee will call thee Caesar now,</line>
            <line>No humble suitors press to speak for right,</line>
            <line>No, not a man comes for redress of thee;</line>
            <line>For how can I help them, and not myself?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Keeper</speaker>
            <line>Ay, here's a deer whose skin's a keeper's fee:</line>
            <line>This is the quondam king; let's seize upon him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Let me embrace thee, sour adversity,</line>
            <line>For wise men say it is the wisest course.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Keeper</speaker>
            <line>Why linger we? let us lay hands upon him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Keeper</speaker>
            <line>Forbear awhile; we'll hear a little more.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>My queen and son are gone to France for aid;</line>
            <line>And, as I hear, the great commanding Warwick</line>
            <line>Is thither gone, to crave the French king's sister</line>
            <line>To wife for Edward: if this news be true,</line>
            <line>Poor queen and son, your labour is but lost;</line>
            <line>For Warwick is a subtle orator,</line>
            <line>And Lewis a prince soon won with moving words.</line>
            <line>By this account then Margaret may win him;</line>
            <line>For she's a woman to be pitied much:</line>
            <line>Her sighs will make a battery in his breast;</line>
            <line>Her tears will pierce into a marble heart;</line>
            <line>The tiger will be mild whiles she doth mourn;</line>
            <line>And Nero will be tainted with remorse,</line>
            <line>To hear and see her plaints, her brinish tears.</line>
            <line>Ay, but she's come to beg, Warwick to give;</line>
            <line>She, on his left side, craving aid for Henry,</line>
            <line>He, on his right, asking a wife for Edward.</line>
            <line>She weeps, and says her Henry is deposed;</line>
            <line>He smiles, and says his Edward is install'd;</line>
            <line>That she, poor wretch, for grief can speak no more;</line>
            <line>Whiles Warwick tells his title, smooths the wrong,</line>
            <line>Inferreth arguments of mighty strength,</line>
            <line>And in conclusion wins the king from her,</line>
            <line>With promise of his sister, and what else,</line>
            <line>To strengthen and support King Edward's place.</line>
            <line>O Margaret, thus 'twill be; and thou, poor soul,</line>
            <line>Art then forsaken, as thou went'st forlorn!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Keeper</speaker>
            <line>Say, what art thou that talk'st of kings and queens?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>More than I seem, and less than I was born to:</line>
            <line>A man at least, for less I should not be;</line>
            <line>And men may talk of kings, and why not I?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Keeper</speaker>
            <line>Ay, but thou talk'st as if thou wert a king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Why, so I am, in mind; and that's enough.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Keeper</speaker>
            <line>But, if thou be a king, where is thy crown?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>My crown is in my heart, not on my head;</line>
            <line>Not decked with diamonds and Indian stones,</line>
            <line>Nor to be seen: my crown is called content:</line>
            <line>A crown it is that seldom kings enjoy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Keeper</speaker>
            <line>Well, if you be a king crown'd with content,</line>
            <line>Your crown content and you must be contented</line>
            <line>To go along with us; for as we think,</line>
            <line>You are the king King Edward hath deposed;</line>
            <line>And we his subjects sworn in all allegiance</line>
            <line>Will apprehend you as his enemy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>But did you never swear, and break an oath?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Keeper</speaker>
            <line>No, never such an oath; nor will not now.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Where did you dwell when I was King of England?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Keeper</speaker>
            <line>Here in this country, where we now remain.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>I was anointed king at nine months old;</line>
            <line>My father and my grandfather were kings,</line>
            <line>And you were sworn true subjects unto me:</line>
            <line>And tell me, then, have you not broke your oaths?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Keeper</speaker>
            <line>No;</line>
            <line>For we were subjects but while you were king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Why, am I dead? do I not breathe a man?</line>
            <line>Ah, simple men, you know not what you swear!</line>
            <line>Look, as I blow this feather from my face,</line>
            <line>And as the air blows it to me again,</line>
            <line>Obeying with my wind when I do blow,</line>
            <line>And yielding to another when it blows,</line>
            <line>Commanded always by the greater gust;</line>
            <line>Such is the lightness of you common men.</line>
            <line>But do not break your oaths; for of that sin</line>
            <line>My mild entreaty shall not make you guilty.</line>
            <line>Go where you will, the king shall be commanded;</line>
            <line>And be you kings, command, and I'll obey.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Keeper</speaker>
            <line>We are true subjects to the king, King Edward.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>So would you be again to Henry,</line>
            <line>If he were seated as King Edward is.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Keeper</speaker>
            <line>We charge you, in God's name, and the king's,</line>
            <line>To go with us unto the officers.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>In God's name, lead; your king's name be obey'd:</line>
            <line>And what God will, that let your king perform;</line>
            <line>And what he will, I humbly yield unto.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
            <line>3 KING HENRY VI</line>
         </speech>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  London. The palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter KING EDWARD IV, GLOUCESTER, CLARENCE, and
LADY GREY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>Brother of Gloucester, at Saint Alban's field</line>
            <line>This lady's husband, Sir Richard Grey, was slain,</line>
            <line>His lands then seized on by the conqueror:</line>
            <line>Her suit is now to repossess those lands;</line>
            <line>Which we in justice cannot well deny,</line>
            <line>Because in quarrel of the house of York</line>
            <line>The worthy gentleman did lose his life.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Your highness shall do well to grant her suit;</line>
            <line>It were dishonour to deny it her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>It were no less; but yet I'll make a pause.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside to CLARENCE</stagedir>  Yea, is it so?</line>
            <line>I see the lady hath a thing to grant,</line>
            <line>Before the king will grant her humble suit.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside to GLOUCESTER</stagedir>  He knows the game: how true</line>
            <line>he keeps the wind!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside to CLARENCE</stagedir>  Silence!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>Widow, we will consider of your suit;</line>
            <line>And come some other time to know our mind.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY GREY</speaker>
            <line>Right gracious lord, I cannot brook delay:</line>
            <line>May it please your highness to resolve me now;</line>
            <line>And what your pleasure is, shall satisfy me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside to CLARENCE</stagedir>  Ay, widow? then I'll warrant</line>
            <line>you all your lands,</line>
            <line>An if what pleases him shall pleasure you.</line>
            <line>Fight closer, or, good faith, you'll catch a blow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside to GLOUCESTER</stagedir>  I fear her not, unless she</line>
            <line>chance to fall.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside to CLARENCE</stagedir> God forbid that! for he'll</line>
            <line>take vantages.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>How many children hast thou, widow? tell me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside to GLOUCESTER</stagedir>  I think he means to beg a</line>
            <line>child of her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside to CLARENCE</stagedir>  Nay, whip me then: he'll rather</line>
            <line>give her two.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY GREY</speaker>
            <line>Three, my most gracious lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside to CLARENCE</stagedir>  You shall have four, if you'll</line>
            <line>be ruled by him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>'Twere pity they should lose their father's lands.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY GREY</speaker>
            <line>Be pitiful, dread lord, and grant it then.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>Lords, give us leave: I'll try this widow's wit.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside to CLARENCE</stagedir>  Ay, good leave have you; for</line>
            <line>you will have leave,</line>
            <line>Till youth take leave and leave you to the crutch.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>GLOUCESTER and CLARENCE retire</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>Now tell me, madam, do you love your children?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY GREY</speaker>
            <line>Ay, full as dearly as I love myself.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>And would you not do much to do them good?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY GREY</speaker>
            <line>To do them good, I would sustain some harm.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>Then get your husband's lands, to do them good.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY GREY</speaker>
            <line>Therefore I came unto your majesty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>I'll tell you how these lands are to be got.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY GREY</speaker>
            <line>So shall you bind me to your highness' service.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>What service wilt thou do me, if I give them?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY GREY</speaker>
            <line>What you command, that rests in me to do.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>But you will take exceptions to my boon.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY GREY</speaker>
            <line>No, gracious lord, except I cannot do it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>Ay, but thou canst do what I mean to ask.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY GREY</speaker>
            <line>Why, then I will do what your grace commands.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside to CLARENCE</stagedir>  He plies her hard; and much rain</line>
            <line>wears the marble.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside to GLOUCESTER</stagedir>  As red as fire! nay, then</line>
            <line>her wax must melt.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY GREY</speaker>
            <line>Why stops my lord, shall I not hear my task?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>An easy task; 'tis but to love a king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY GREY</speaker>
            <line>That's soon perform'd, because I am a subject.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>Why, then, thy husband's lands I freely give thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY GREY</speaker>
            <line>I take my leave with many thousand thanks.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside to CLARENCE</stagedir>  The match is made; she seals it</line>
            <line>with a curtsy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>But stay thee, 'tis the fruits of love I mean.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY GREY</speaker>
            <line>The fruits of love I mean, my loving liege.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>Ay, but, I fear me, in another sense.</line>
            <line>What love, think'st thou, I sue so much to get?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY GREY</speaker>
            <line>My love till death, my humble thanks, my prayers;</line>
            <line>That love which virtue begs and virtue grants.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>No, by my troth, I did not mean such love.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY GREY</speaker>
            <line>Why, then you mean not as I thought you did.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>But now you partly may perceive my mind.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY GREY</speaker>
            <line>My mind will never grant what I perceive</line>
            <line>Your highness aims at, if I aim aright.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>To tell thee plain, I aim to lie with thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY GREY</speaker>
            <line>To tell you plain, I had rather lie in prison.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>Why, then thou shalt not have thy husband's lands.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY GREY</speaker>
            <line>Why, then mine honesty shall be my dower;</line>
            <line>For by that loss I will not purchase them.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>Therein thou wrong'st thy children mightily.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY GREY</speaker>
            <line>Herein your highness wrongs both them and me.</line>
            <line>But, mighty lord, this merry inclination</line>
            <line>Accords not with the sadness of my suit:</line>
            <line>Please you dismiss me either with 'ay' or 'no.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>Ay, if thou wilt say 'ay' to my request;</line>
            <line>No if thou dost say 'no' to my demand.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY GREY</speaker>
            <line>Then, no, my lord. My suit is at an end.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside to CLARENCE</stagedir>  The widow likes him not, she</line>
            <line>knits her brows.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside to GLOUCESTER</stagedir>  He is the bluntest wooer in</line>
            <line>Christendom.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  Her looks do argue her replete with modesty;</line>
            <line>Her words do show her wit incomparable;</line>
            <line>All her perfections challenge sovereignty:</line>
            <line>One way or other, she is for a king;</line>
            <line>And she shall be my love, or else my queen.--</line>
            <line>Say that King Edward take thee for his queen?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY GREY</speaker>
            <line>'Tis better said than done, my gracious lord:</line>
            <line>I am a subject fit to jest withal,</line>
            <line>But far unfit to be a sovereign.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>Sweet widow, by my state I swear to thee</line>
            <line>I speak no more than what my soul intends;</line>
            <line>And that is, to enjoy thee for my love.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY GREY</speaker>
            <line>And that is more than I will yield unto:</line>
            <line>I know I am too mean to be your queen,</line>
            <line>And yet too good to be your concubine.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>You cavil, widow: I did mean, my queen.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY GREY</speaker>
            <line>'Twill grieve your grace my sons should call you father.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>No more than when my daughters call thee mother.</line>
            <line>Thou art a widow, and thou hast some children;</line>
            <line>And, by God's mother, I, being but a bachelor,</line>
            <line>Have other some: why, 'tis a happy thing</line>
            <line>To be the father unto many sons.</line>
            <line>Answer no more, for thou shalt be my queen.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside to CLARENCE</stagedir>  The ghostly father now hath done</line>
            <line>his shrift.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside to GLOUCESTER</stagedir>  When he was made a shriver,</line>
            <line>'twas for shift.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>Brothers, you muse what chat we two have had.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>The widow likes it not, for she looks very sad.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>You'll think it strange if I should marry her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>To whom, my lord?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>Why, Clarence, to myself.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>That would be ten days' wonder at the least.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>That's a day longer than a wonder lasts.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>By so much is the wonder in extremes.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>Well, jest on, brothers: I can tell you both</line>
            <line>Her suit is granted for her husband's lands.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter a Nobleman</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Nobleman</speaker>
            <line>My gracious lord, Henry your foe is taken,</line>
            <line>And brought your prisoner to your palace gate.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>See that he be convey'd unto the Tower:</line>
            <line>And go we, brothers, to the man that took him,</line>
            <line>To question of his apprehension.</line>
            <line>Widow, go you along. Lords, use her honourably.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt all but GLOUCESTER</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Ay, Edward will use women honourably.</line>
            <line>Would he were wasted, marrow, bones and all,</line>
            <line>That from his loins no hopeful branch may spring,</line>
            <line>To cross me from the golden time I look for!</line>
            <line>And yet, between my soul's desire and me--</line>
            <line>The lustful Edward's title buried--</line>
            <line>Is Clarence, Henry, and his son young Edward,</line>
            <line>And all the unlook'd for issue of their bodies,</line>
            <line>To take their rooms, ere I can place myself:</line>
            <line>A cold premeditation for my purpose!</line>
            <line>Why, then, I do but dream on sovereignty;</line>
            <line>Like one that stands upon a promontory,</line>
            <line>And spies a far-off shore where he would tread,</line>
            <line>Wishing his foot were equal with his eye,</line>
            <line>And chides the sea that sunders him from thence,</line>
            <line>Saying, he'll lade it dry to have his way:</line>
            <line>So do I wish the crown, being so far off;</line>
            <line>And so I chide the means that keeps me from it;</line>
            <line>And so I say, I'll cut the causes off,</line>
            <line>Flattering me with impossibilities.</line>
            <line>My eye's too quick, my heart o'erweens too much,</line>
            <line>Unless my hand and strength could equal them.</line>
            <line>Well, say there is no kingdom then for Richard;</line>
            <line>What other pleasure can the world afford?</line>
            <line>I'll make my heaven in a lady's lap,</line>
            <line>And deck my body in gay ornaments,</line>
            <line>And witch sweet ladies with my words and looks.</line>
            <line>O miserable thought! and more unlikely</line>
            <line>Than to accomplish twenty golden crowns!</line>
            <line>Why, love forswore me in my mother's womb:</line>
            <line>And, for I should not deal in her soft laws,</line>
            <line>She did corrupt frail nature with some bribe,</line>
            <line>To shrink mine arm up like a wither'd shrub;</line>
            <line>To make an envious mountain on my back,</line>
            <line>Where sits deformity to mock my body;</line>
            <line>To shape my legs of an unequal size;</line>
            <line>To disproportion me in every part,</line>
            <line>Like to a chaos, or an unlick'd bear-whelp</line>
            <line>That carries no impression like the dam.</line>
            <line>And am I then a man to be beloved?</line>
            <line>O monstrous fault, to harbour such a thought!</line>
            <line>Then, since this earth affords no joy to me,</line>
            <line>But to command, to cheque, to o'erbear such</line>
            <line>As are of better person than myself,</line>
            <line>I'll make my heaven to dream upon the crown,</line>
            <line>And, whiles I live, to account this world but hell,</line>
            <line>Until my mis-shaped trunk that bears this head</line>
            <line>Be round impaled with a glorious crown.</line>
            <line>And yet I know not how to get the crown,</line>
            <line>For many lives stand between me and home:</line>
            <line>And I,--like one lost in a thorny wood,</line>
            <line>That rends the thorns and is rent with the thorns,</line>
            <line>Seeking a way and straying from the way;</line>
            <line>Not knowing how to find the open air,</line>
            <line>But toiling desperately to find it out,--</line>
            <line>Torment myself to catch the English crown:</line>
            <line>And from that torment I will free myself,</line>
            <line>Or hew my way out with a bloody axe.</line>
            <line>Why, I can smile, and murder whiles I smile,</line>
            <line>And cry 'Content' to that which grieves my heart,</line>
            <line>And wet my cheeks with artificial tears,</line>
            <line>And frame my face to all occasions.</line>
            <line>I'll drown more sailors than the mermaid shall;</line>
            <line>I'll slay more gazers than the basilisk;</line>
            <line>I'll play the orator as well as Nestor,</line>
            <line>Deceive more slily than Ulysses could,</line>
            <line>And, like a Sinon, take another Troy.</line>
            <line>I can add colours to the chameleon,</line>
            <line>Change shapes with Proteus for advantages,</line>
            <line>And set the murderous Machiavel to school.</line>
            <line>Can I do this, and cannot get a crown?</line>
            <line>Tut, were it farther off, I'll pluck it down.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
            <line>3 KING HENRY VI</line>
         </speech>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  France. KING LEWIS XI's palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Flourish. Enter KING LEWIS XI, his sister BONA,
his Admiral, called BOURBON, PRINCE EDWARD, QUEEN
MARGARET, and OXFORD. KING LEWIS XI sits, and
riseth up again</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEWIS XI</speaker>
            <line>Fair Queen of England, worthy Margaret,</line>
            <line>Sit down with us: it ill befits thy state</line>
            <line>And birth, that thou shouldst stand while Lewis doth sit.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>No, mighty King of France: now Margaret</line>
            <line>Must strike her sail and learn awhile to serve</line>
            <line>Where kings command. I was, I must confess,</line>
            <line>Great Albion's queen in former golden days:</line>
            <line>But now mischance hath trod my title down,</line>
            <line>And with dishonour laid me on the ground;</line>
            <line>Where I must take like seat unto my fortune,</line>
            <line>And to my humble seat conform myself.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEWIS XI</speaker>
            <line>Why, say, fair queen, whence springs this deep despair?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>From such a cause as fills mine eyes with tears</line>
            <line>And stops my tongue, while heart is drown'd in cares.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEWIS XI</speaker>
            <line>Whate'er it be, be thou still like thyself,</line>
            <line>And sit thee by our side:</line>
            <stagedir>Seats her by him</stagedir>
            <line>Yield not thy neck</line>
            <line>To fortune's yoke, but let thy dauntless mind</line>
            <line>Still ride in triumph over all mischance.</line>
            <line>Be plain, Queen Margaret, and tell thy grief;</line>
            <line>It shall be eased, if France can yield relief.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Those gracious words revive my drooping thoughts</line>
            <line>And give my tongue-tied sorrows leave to speak.</line>
            <line>Now, therefore, be it known to noble Lewis,</line>
            <line>That Henry, sole possessor of my love,</line>
            <line>Is of a king become a banish'd man,</line>
            <line>And forced to live in Scotland a forlorn;</line>
            <line>While proud ambitious Edward Duke of York</line>
            <line>Usurps the regal title and the seat</line>
            <line>Of England's true-anointed lawful king.</line>
            <line>This is the cause that I, poor Margaret,</line>
            <line>With this my son, Prince Edward, Henry's heir,</line>
            <line>Am come to crave thy just and lawful aid;</line>
            <line>And if thou fail us, all our hope is done:</line>
            <line>Scotland hath will to help, but cannot help;</line>
            <line>Our people and our peers are both misled,</line>
            <line>Our treasures seized, our soldiers put to flight,</line>
            <line>And, as thou seest, ourselves in heavy plight.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEWIS XI</speaker>
            <line>Renowned queen, with patience calm the storm,</line>
            <line>While we bethink a means to break it off.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>The more we stay, the stronger grows our foe.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEWIS XI</speaker>
            <line>The more I stay, the more I'll succor thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>O, but impatience waiteth on true sorrow.</line>
            <line>And see where comes the breeder of my sorrow!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter WARWICK</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEWIS XI</speaker>
            <line>What's he approacheth boldly to our presence?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Our Earl of Warwick, Edward's greatest friend.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEWIS XI</speaker>
            <line>Welcome, brave Warwick! What brings thee to France?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>He descends. She ariseth</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Ay, now begins a second storm to rise;</line>
            <line>For this is he that moves both wind and tide.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>From worthy Edward, King of Albion,</line>
            <line>My lord and sovereign, and thy vowed friend,</line>
            <line>I come, in kindness and unfeigned love,</line>
            <line>First, to do greetings to thy royal person;</line>
            <line>And then to crave a league of amity;</line>
            <line>And lastly, to confirm that amity</line>
            <line>With a nuptial knot, if thou vouchsafe to grant</line>
            <line>That virtuous Lady Bona, thy fair sister,</line>
            <line>To England's king in lawful marriage.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  If that go forward, Henry's hope is done.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>To BONA</stagedir>  And, gracious madam, in our king's behalf,</line>
            <line>I am commanded, with your leave and favour,</line>
            <line>Humbly to kiss your hand, and with my tongue</line>
            <line>To tell the passion of my sovereign's heart;</line>
            <line>Where fame, late entering at his heedful ears,</line>
            <line>Hath placed thy beauty's image and thy virtue.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>King Lewis and Lady Bona, hear me speak,</line>
            <line>Before you answer Warwick. His demand</line>
            <line>Springs not from Edward's well-meant honest love,</line>
            <line>But from deceit bred by necessity;</line>
            <line>For how can tyrants safely govern home,</line>
            <line>Unless abroad they purchase great alliance?</line>
            <line>To prove him tyrant this reason may suffice,</line>
            <line>That Henry liveth still: but were he dead,</line>
            <line>Yet here Prince Edward stands, King Henry's son.</line>
            <line>Look, therefore, Lewis, that by this league and marriage</line>
            <line>Thou draw not on thy danger and dishonour;</line>
            <line>For though usurpers sway the rule awhile,</line>
            <line>Yet heavens are just, and time suppresseth wrongs.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Injurious Margaret!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>And why not queen?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Because thy father Henry did usurp;</line>
            <line>And thou no more are prince than she is queen.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OXFORD</speaker>
            <line>Then Warwick disannuls great John of Gaunt,</line>
            <line>Which did subdue the greatest part of Spain;</line>
            <line>And, after John of Gaunt, Henry the Fourth,</line>
            <line>Whose wisdom was a mirror to the wisest;</line>
            <line>And, after that wise prince, Henry the Fifth,</line>
            <line>Who by his prowess conquered all France:</line>
            <line>From these our Henry lineally descends.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Oxford, how haps it, in this smooth discourse,</line>
            <line>You told not how Henry the Sixth hath lost</line>
            <line>All that which Henry Fifth had gotten?</line>
            <line>Methinks these peers of France should smile at that.</line>
            <line>But for the rest, you tell a pedigree</line>
            <line>Of threescore and two years; a silly time</line>
            <line>To make prescription for a kingdom's worth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OXFORD</speaker>
            <line>Why, Warwick, canst thou speak against thy liege,</line>
            <line>Whom thou obeyed'st thirty and six years,</line>
            <line>And not bewray thy treason with a blush?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Can Oxford, that did ever fence the right,</line>
            <line>Now buckler falsehood with a pedigree?</line>
            <line>For shame! leave Henry, and call Edward king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OXFORD</speaker>
            <line>Call him my king by whose injurious doom</line>
            <line>My elder brother, the Lord Aubrey Vere,</line>
            <line>Was done to death? and more than so, my father,</line>
            <line>Even in the downfall of his mellow'd years,</line>
            <line>When nature brought him to the door of death?</line>
            <line>No, Warwick, no; while life upholds this arm,</line>
            <line>This arm upholds the house of Lancaster.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>And I the house of York.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEWIS XI</speaker>
            <line>Queen Margaret, Prince Edward, and Oxford,</line>
            <line>Vouchsafe, at our request, to stand aside,</line>
            <line>While I use further conference with Warwick.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>They stand aloof</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Heavens grant that Warwick's words bewitch him not!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEWIS XI</speaker>
            <line>Now Warwick, tell me, even upon thy conscience,</line>
            <line>Is Edward your true king? for I were loath</line>
            <line>To link with him that were not lawful chosen.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Thereon I pawn my credit and mine honour.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEWIS XI</speaker>
            <line>But is he gracious in the people's eye?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>The more that Henry was unfortunate.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEWIS XI</speaker>
            <line>Then further, all dissembling set aside,</line>
            <line>Tell me for truth the measure of his love</line>
            <line>Unto our sister Bona.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Such it seems</line>
            <line>As may beseem a monarch like himself.</line>
            <line>Myself have often heard him say and swear</line>
            <line>That this his love was an eternal plant,</line>
            <line>Whereof the root was fix'd in virtue's ground,</line>
            <line>The leaves and fruit maintain'd with beauty's sun,</line>
            <line>Exempt from envy, but not from disdain,</line>
            <line>Unless the Lady Bona quit his pain.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEWIS XI</speaker>
            <line>Now, sister, let us hear your firm resolve.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BONA</speaker>
            <line>Your grant, or your denial, shall be mine:</line>
            <stagedir>To WARWICK</stagedir>
            <line>Yet I confess that often ere this day,</line>
            <line>When I have heard your king's desert recounted,</line>
            <line>Mine ear hath tempted judgment to desire.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEWIS XI</speaker>
            <line>Then, Warwick, thus: our sister shall be Edward's;</line>
            <line>And now forthwith shall articles be drawn</line>
            <line>Touching the jointure that your king must make,</line>
            <line>Which with her dowry shall be counterpoised.</line>
            <line>Draw near, Queen Margaret, and be a witness</line>
            <line>That Bona shall be wife to the English king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>To Edward, but not to the English king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Deceitful Warwick! it was thy device</line>
            <line>By this alliance to make void my suit:</line>
            <line>Before thy coming Lewis was Henry's friend.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEWIS XI</speaker>
            <line>And still is friend to him and Margaret:</line>
            <line>But if your title to the crown be weak,</line>
            <line>As may appear by Edward's good success,</line>
            <line>Then 'tis but reason that I be released</line>
            <line>From giving aid which late I promised.</line>
            <line>Yet shall you have all kindness at my hand</line>
            <line>That your estate requires and mine can yield.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Henry now lives in Scotland at his ease,</line>
            <line>Where having nothing, nothing can he lose.</line>
            <line>And as for you yourself, our quondam queen,</line>
            <line>You have a father able to maintain you;</line>
            <line>And better 'twere you troubled him than France.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Peace, impudent and shameless Warwick, peace,</line>
            <line>Proud setter up and puller down of kings!</line>
            <line>I will not hence, till, with my talk and tears,</line>
            <line>Both full of truth, I make King Lewis behold</line>
            <line>Thy sly conveyance and thy lord's false love;</line>
            <line>For both of you are birds of selfsame feather.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Post blows a horn within</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEWIS XI</speaker>
            <line>Warwick, this is some post to us or thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter a Post</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Post</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>To WARWICK</stagedir>  My lord ambassador, these letters are for you,</line>
            <line>Sent from your brother, Marquess Montague:</line>
            <stagedir>To KING LEWIS XI</stagedir>
            <line>These from our king unto your majesty:</line>
            <stagedir>To QUEEN MARGARET</stagedir>
            <line>And, madam, these for you; from whom I know not.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>They all read their letters</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OXFORD</speaker>
            <line>I like it well that our fair queen and mistress</line>
            <line>Smiles at her news, while Warwick frowns at his.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>Nay, mark how Lewis stamps, as he were nettled:</line>
            <line>I hope all's for the best.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEWIS XI</speaker>
            <line>Warwick, what are thy news? and yours, fair queen?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Mine, such as fill my heart with unhoped joys.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Mine, full of sorrow and heart's discontent.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEWIS XI</speaker>
            <line>What! has your king married the Lady Grey!</line>
            <line>And now, to soothe your forgery and his,</line>
            <line>Sends me a paper to persuade me patience?</line>
            <line>Is this the alliance that he seeks with France?</line>
            <line>Dare he presume to scorn us in this manner?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>I told your majesty as much before:</line>
            <line>This proveth Edward's love and Warwick's honesty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>King Lewis, I here protest, in sight of heaven,</line>
            <line>And by the hope I have of heavenly bliss,</line>
            <line>That I am clear from this misdeed of Edward's,</line>
            <line>No more my king, for he dishonours me,</line>
            <line>But most himself, if he could see his shame.</line>
            <line>Did I forget that by the house of York</line>
            <line>My father came untimely to his death?</line>
            <line>Did I let pass the abuse done to my niece?</line>
            <line>Did I impale him with the regal crown?</line>
            <line>Did I put Henry from his native right?</line>
            <line>And am I guerdon'd at the last with shame?</line>
            <line>Shame on himself! for my desert is honour:</line>
            <line>And to repair my honour lost for him,</line>
            <line>I here renounce him and return to Henry.</line>
            <line>My noble queen, let former grudges pass,</line>
            <line>And henceforth I am thy true servitor:</line>
            <line>I will revenge his wrong to Lady Bona,</line>
            <line>And replant Henry in his former state.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Warwick, these words have turn'd my hate to love;</line>
            <line>And I forgive and quite forget old faults,</line>
            <line>And joy that thou becomest King Henry's friend.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>So much his friend, ay, his unfeigned friend,</line>
            <line>That, if King Lewis vouchsafe to furnish us</line>
            <line>With some few bands of chosen soldiers,</line>
            <line>I'll undertake to land them on our coast</line>
            <line>And force the tyrant from his seat by war.</line>
            <line>'Tis not his new-made bride shall succor him:</line>
            <line>And as for Clarence, as my letters tell me,</line>
            <line>He's very likely now to fall from him,</line>
            <line>For matching more for wanton lust than honour,</line>
            <line>Or than for strength and safety of our country.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BONA</speaker>
            <line>Dear brother, how shall Bona be revenged</line>
            <line>But by thy help to this distressed queen?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Renowned prince, how shall poor Henry live,</line>
            <line>Unless thou rescue him from foul despair?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BONA</speaker>
            <line>My quarrel and this English queen's are one.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>And mine, fair lady Bona, joins with yours.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEWIS XI</speaker>
            <line>And mine with hers, and thine, and Margaret's.</line>
            <line>Therefore at last I firmly am resolved</line>
            <line>You shall have aid.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Let me give humble thanks for all at once.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEWIS XI</speaker>
            <line>Then, England's messenger, return in post,</line>
            <line>And tell false Edward, thy supposed king,</line>
            <line>That Lewis of France is sending over masquers</line>
            <line>To revel it with him and his new bride:</line>
            <line>Thou seest what's past, go fear thy king withal.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BONA</speaker>
            <line>Tell him, in hope he'll prove a widower shortly,</line>
            <line>I'll wear the willow garland for his sake.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Tell him, my mourning weeds are laid aside,</line>
            <line>And I am ready to put armour on.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Tell him from me that he hath done me wrong,</line>
            <line>And therefore I'll uncrown him ere't be long.</line>
            <line>There's thy reward: be gone.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit Post</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEWIS XI</speaker>
            <line>But, Warwick,</line>
            <line>Thou and Oxford, with five thousand men,</line>
            <line>Shall cross the seas, and bid false Edward battle;</line>
            <line>And, as occasion serves, this noble queen</line>
            <line>And prince shall follow with a fresh supply.</line>
            <line>Yet, ere thou go, but answer me one doubt,</line>
            <line>What pledge have we of thy firm loyalty?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>This shall assure my constant loyalty,</line>
            <line>That if our queen and this young prince agree,</line>
            <line>I'll join mine eldest daughter and my joy</line>
            <line>To him forthwith in holy wedlock bands.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Yes, I agree, and thank you for your motion.</line>
            <line>Son Edward, she is fair and virtuous,</line>
            <line>Therefore delay not, give thy hand to Warwick;</line>
            <line>And, with thy hand, thy faith irrevocable,</line>
            <line>That only Warwick's daughter shall be thine.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>Yes, I accept her, for she well deserves it;</line>
            <line>And here, to pledge my vow, I give my hand.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>He gives his hand to WARWICK</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEWIS XI</speaker>
            <line>Why stay we now? These soldiers shall be levied,</line>
            <line>And thou, Lord Bourbon, our high admiral,</line>
            <line>Shalt waft them over with our royal fleet.</line>
            <line>I long till Edward fall by war's mischance,</line>
            <line>For mocking marriage with a dame of France.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt all but WARWICK</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>I came from Edward as ambassador,</line>
            <line>But I return his sworn and mortal foe:</line>
            <line>Matter of marriage was the charge he gave me,</line>
            <line>But dreadful war shall answer his demand.</line>
            <line>Had he none else to make a stale but me?</line>
            <line>Then none but I shall turn his jest to sorrow.</line>
            <line>I was the chief that raised him to the crown,</line>
            <line>And I'll be chief to bring him down again:</line>
            <line>Not that I pity Henry's misery,</line>
            <line>But seek revenge on Edward's mockery.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
            <line>3 KING HENRY VI</line>
         </speech>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>