<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:shakespear:dtd:act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-4">
   <title>ACT IV</title>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  London. The palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter GLOUCESTER, CLARENCE, SOMERSET, and MONTAGUE</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Now tell me, brother Clarence, what think you</line>
            <line>Of this new marriage with the Lady Grey?</line>
            <line>Hath not our brother made a worthy choice?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>Alas, you know, 'tis far from hence to France;</line>
            <line>How could he stay till Warwick made return?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SOMERSET</speaker>
            <line>My lords, forbear this talk; here comes the king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>And his well-chosen bride.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>I mind to tell him plainly what I think.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Flourish. Enter KING EDWARD IV, attended; QUEEN
ELIZABETH, PEMBROKE, STAFFORD, HASTINGS, and others</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>Now, brother of Clarence, how like you our choice,</line>
            <line>That you stand pensive, as half malcontent?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>As well as Lewis of France, or the Earl of Warwick,</line>
            <line>Which are so weak of courage and in judgment</line>
            <line>That they'll take no offence at our abuse.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>Suppose they take offence without a cause,</line>
            <line>They are but Lewis and Warwick: I am Edward,</line>
            <line>Your king and Warwick's, and must have my will.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>And shall have your will, because our king:</line>
            <line>Yet hasty marriage seldom proveth well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>Yea, brother Richard, are you offended too?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Not I:</line>
            <line>No, God forbid that I should wish them sever'd</line>
            <line>Whom God hath join'd together; ay, and 'twere pity</line>
            <line>To sunder them that yoke so well together.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>Setting your scorns and your mislike aside,</line>
            <line>Tell me some reason why the Lady Grey</line>
            <line>Should not become my wife and England's queen.</line>
            <line>And you too, Somerset and Montague,</line>
            <line>Speak freely what you think.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>Then this is mine opinion: that King Lewis</line>
            <line>Becomes your enemy, for mocking him</line>
            <line>About the marriage of the Lady Bona.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>And Warwick, doing what you gave in charge,</line>
            <line>Is now dishonoured by this new marriage.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>What if both Lewis and Warwick be appeased</line>
            <line>By such invention as I can devise?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MONTAGUE</speaker>
            <line>Yet, to have join'd with France in such alliance</line>
            <line>Would more have strengthen'd this our commonwealth</line>
            <line>'Gainst foreign storms than any home-bred marriage.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>Why, knows not Montague that of itself</line>
            <line>England is safe, if true within itself?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MONTAGUE</speaker>
            <line>But the safer when 'tis back'd with France.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>'Tis better using France than trusting France:</line>
            <line>Let us be back'd with God and with the seas</line>
            <line>Which He hath given for fence impregnable,</line>
            <line>And with their helps only defend ourselves;</line>
            <line>In them and in ourselves our safety lies.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>For this one speech Lord Hastings well deserves</line>
            <line>To have the heir of the Lord Hungerford.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>Ay, what of that? it was my will and grant;</line>
            <line>And for this once my will shall stand for law.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>And yet methinks your grace hath not done well,</line>
            <line>To give the heir and daughter of Lord Scales</line>
            <line>Unto the brother of your loving bride;</line>
            <line>She better would have fitted me or Clarence:</line>
            <line>But in your bride you bury brotherhood.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>Or else you would not have bestow'd the heir</line>
            <line>Of the Lord Bonville on your new wife's son,</line>
            <line>And leave your brothers to go speed elsewhere.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>Alas, poor Clarence! is it for a wife</line>
            <line>That thou art malcontent? I will provide thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>In choosing for yourself, you show'd your judgment,</line>
            <line>Which being shallow, you give me leave</line>
            <line>To play the broker in mine own behalf;</line>
            <line>And to that end I shortly mind to leave you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>Leave me, or tarry, Edward will be king,</line>
            <line>And not be tied unto his brother's will.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>My lords, before it pleased his majesty</line>
            <line>To raise my state to title of a queen,</line>
            <line>Do me but right, and you must all confess</line>
            <line>That I was not ignoble of descent;</line>
            <line>And meaner than myself have had like fortune.</line>
            <line>But as this title honours me and mine,</line>
            <line>So your dislike, to whom I would be pleasing,</line>
            <line>Doth cloud my joys with danger and with sorrow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>My love, forbear to fawn upon their frowns:</line>
            <line>What danger or what sorrow can befall thee,</line>
            <line>So long as Edward is thy constant friend,</line>
            <line>And their true sovereign, whom they must obey?</line>
            <line>Nay, whom they shall obey, and love thee too,</line>
            <line>Unless they seek for hatred at my hands;</line>
            <line>Which if they do, yet will I keep thee safe,</line>
            <line>And they shall feel the vengeance of my wrath.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  I hear, yet say not much, but think the more.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter a Post</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>Now, messenger, what letters or what news</line>
            <line>From France?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Post</speaker>
            <line>My sovereign liege, no letters; and few words,</line>
            <line>But such as I, without your special pardon,</line>
            <line>Dare not relate.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>Go to, we pardon thee: therefore, in brief,</line>
            <line>Tell me their words as near as thou canst guess them.</line>
            <line>What answer makes King Lewis unto our letters?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Post</speaker>
            <line>At my depart, these were his very words:</line>
            <line>'Go tell false Edward, thy supposed king,</line>
            <line>That Lewis of France is sending over masquers</line>
            <line>To revel it with him and his new bride.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>Is Lewis so brave? belike he thinks me Henry.</line>
            <line>But what said Lady Bona to my marriage?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Post</speaker>
            <line>These were her words, utter'd with mad disdain:</line>
            <line>'Tell him, in hope he'll prove a widower shortly,</line>
            <line>I'll wear the willow garland for his sake.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>I blame not her, she could say little less;</line>
            <line>She had the wrong. But what said Henry's queen?</line>
            <line>For I have heard that she was there in place.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Post</speaker>
            <line>'Tell him,' quoth she, 'my mourning weeds are done,</line>
            <line>And I am ready to put armour on.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>Belike she minds to play the Amazon.</line>
            <line>But what said Warwick to these injuries?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Post</speaker>
            <line>He, more incensed against your majesty</line>
            <line>Than all the rest, discharged me with these words:</line>
            <line>'Tell him from me that he hath done me wrong,</line>
            <line>And therefore I'll uncrown him ere't be long.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>Ha! durst the traitor breathe out so proud words?</line>
            <line>Well I will arm me, being thus forewarn'd:</line>
            <line>They shall have wars and pay for their presumption.</line>
            <line>But say, is Warwick friends with Margaret?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Post</speaker>
            <line>Ay, gracious sovereign; they are so link'd in</line>
            <line>friendship</line>
            <line>That young Prince Edward marries Warwick's daughter.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>Belike the elder; Clarence will have the younger.</line>
            <line>Now, brother king, farewell, and sit you fast,</line>
            <line>For I will hence to Warwick's other daughter;</line>
            <line>That, though I want a kingdom, yet in marriage</line>
            <line>I may not prove inferior to yourself.</line>
            <line>You that love me and Warwick, follow me.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit CLARENCE, and SOMERSET follows</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  Not I:</line>
            <line>My thoughts aim at a further matter; I</line>
            <line>Stay not for the love of Edward, but the crown.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>Clarence and Somerset both gone to Warwick!</line>
            <line>Yet am I arm'd against the worst can happen;</line>
            <line>And haste is needful in this desperate case.</line>
            <line>Pembroke and Stafford, you in our behalf</line>
            <line>Go levy men, and make prepare for war;</line>
            <line>They are already, or quickly will be landed:</line>
            <line>Myself in person will straight follow you.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt PEMBROKE and STAFFORD</stagedir>
            <line>But, ere I go, Hastings and Montague,</line>
            <line>Resolve my doubt. You twain, of all the rest,</line>
            <line>Are near to Warwick by blood and by alliance:</line>
            <line>Tell me if you love Warwick more than me?</line>
            <line>If it be so, then both depart to him;</line>
            <line>I rather wish you foes than hollow friends:</line>
            <line>But if you mind to hold your true obedience,</line>
            <line>Give me assurance with some friendly vow,</line>
            <line>That I may never have you in suspect.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MONTAGUE</speaker>
            <line>So God help Montague as he proves true!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>And Hastings as he favours Edward's cause!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>Now, brother Richard, will you stand by us?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Ay, in despite of all that shall withstand you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>Why, so! then am I sure of victory.</line>
            <line>Now therefore let us hence; and lose no hour,</line>
            <line>Till we meet Warwick with his foreign power.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
            <line>3 KING HENRY VI</line>
         </speech>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  A plain in Warwickshire.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter WARWICK and OXFORD, with French soldiers</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Trust me, my lord, all hitherto goes well;</line>
            <line>The common people by numbers swarm to us.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter CLARENCE and SOMERSET</stagedir>
            <line>But see where Somerset and Clarence come!</line>
            <line>Speak suddenly, my lords, are we all friends?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>Fear not that, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Then, gentle Clarence, welcome unto Warwick;</line>
            <line>And welcome, Somerset: I hold it cowardice</line>
            <line>To rest mistrustful where a noble heart</line>
            <line>Hath pawn'd an open hand in sign of love;</line>
            <line>Else might I think that Clarence, Edward's brother,</line>
            <line>Were but a feigned friend to our proceedings:</line>
            <line>But welcome, sweet Clarence; my daughter shall be thine.</line>
            <line>And now what rests but, in night's coverture,</line>
            <line>Thy brother being carelessly encamp'd,</line>
            <line>His soldiers lurking in the towns about,</line>
            <line>And but attended by a simple guard,</line>
            <line>We may surprise and take him at our pleasure?</line>
            <line>Our scouts have found the adventure very easy:</line>
            <line>That as Ulysses and stout Diomede</line>
            <line>With sleight and manhood stole to Rhesus' tents,</line>
            <line>And brought from thence the Thracian fatal steeds,</line>
            <line>So we, well cover'd with the night's black mantle,</line>
            <line>At unawares may beat down Edward's guard</line>
            <line>And seize himself; I say not, slaughter him,</line>
            <line>For I intend but only to surprise him.</line>
            <line>You that will follow me to this attempt,</line>
            <line>Applaud the name of Henry with your leader.</line>
            <stagedir>They all cry, 'Henry!'</stagedir>
            <line>Why, then, let's on our way in silent sort:</line>
            <line>For Warwick and his friends, God and Saint George!</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
            <line>3 KING HENRY VI</line>
         </speech>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  Edward's camp, near Warwick.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter three Watchmen, to guard KING EDWARD IV's tent</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Watchman</speaker>
            <line>Come on, my masters, each man take his stand:</line>
            <line>The king by this is set him down to sleep.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Watchman</speaker>
            <line>What, will he not to bed?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Watchman</speaker>
            <line>Why, no; for he hath made a solemn vow</line>
            <line>Never to lie and take his natural rest</line>
            <line>Till Warwick or himself be quite suppress'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Watchman</speaker>
            <line>To-morrow then belike shall be the day,</line>
            <line>If Warwick be so near as men report.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Watchman</speaker>
            <line>But say, I pray, what nobleman is that</line>
            <line>That with the king here resteth in his tent?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Watchman</speaker>
            <line>'Tis the Lord Hastings, the king's chiefest friend.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Watchman</speaker>
            <line>O, is it so? But why commands the king</line>
            <line>That his chief followers lodge in towns about him,</line>
            <line>While he himself keeps in the cold field?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Watchman</speaker>
            <line>'Tis the more honour, because more dangerous.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Watchman</speaker>
            <line>Ay, but give me worship and quietness;</line>
            <line>I like it better than a dangerous honour.</line>
            <line>If Warwick knew in what estate he stands,</line>
            <line>'Tis to be doubted he would waken him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Watchman</speaker>
            <line>Unless our halberds did shut up his passage.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Watchman</speaker>
            <line>Ay, wherefore else guard we his royal tent,</line>
            <line>But to defend his person from night-foes?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter WARWICK, CLARENCE, OXFORD, SOMERSET, and
French soldiers, silent all</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>This is his tent; and see where stand his guard.</line>
            <line>Courage, my masters! honour now or never!</line>
            <line>But follow me, and Edward shall be ours.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Watchman</speaker>
            <line>Who goes there?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Watchman</speaker>
            <line>Stay, or thou diest!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>WARWICK and the rest cry all, 'Warwick! Warwick!'
and set upon the Guard, who fly, crying, 'Arm!
arm!' WARWICK and the rest following them</stagedir>
         <stagedir>The drum playing and trumpet sounding, reenter
WARWICK, SOMERSET, and the rest, bringing KING
EDWARD IV out in his gown, sitting in a chair.
RICHARD and HASTINGS fly over the stage</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SOMERSET</speaker>
            <line>What are they that fly there?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Richard and Hastings: let them go; here is The duke.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>The duke! Why, Warwick, when we parted,</line>
            <line>Thou call'dst me king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Ay, but the case is alter'd:</line>
            <line>When you disgraced me in my embassade,</line>
            <line>Then I degraded you from being king,</line>
            <line>And come now to create you Duke of York.</line>
            <line>Alas! how should you govern any kingdom,</line>
            <line>That know not how to use ambassadors,</line>
            <line>Nor how to be contented with one wife,</line>
            <line>Nor how to use your brothers brotherly,</line>
            <line>Nor how to study for the people's welfare,</line>
            <line>Nor how to shroud yourself from enemies?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>Yea, brother of Clarence, are thou here too?</line>
            <line>Nay, then I see that Edward needs must down.</line>
            <line>Yet, Warwick, in despite of all mischance,</line>
            <line>Of thee thyself and all thy complices,</line>
            <line>Edward will always bear himself as king:</line>
            <line>Though fortune's malice overthrow my state,</line>
            <line>My mind exceeds the compass of her wheel.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Then, for his mind, be Edward England's king:</line>
            <stagedir>Takes off his crown</stagedir>
            <line>But Henry now shall wear the English crown,</line>
            <line>And be true king indeed, thou but the shadow.</line>
            <line>My Lord of Somerset, at my request,</line>
            <line>See that forthwith Duke Edward be convey'd</line>
            <line>Unto my brother, Archbishop of York.</line>
            <line>When I have fought with Pembroke and his fellows,</line>
            <line>I'll follow you, and tell what answer</line>
            <line>Lewis and the Lady Bona send to him.</line>
            <line>Now, for a while farewell, good Duke of York.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>They lead him out forcibly</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>What fates impose, that men must needs abide;</line>
            <line>It boots not to resist both wind and tide.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit, guarded</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OXFORD</speaker>
            <line>What now remains, my lords, for us to do</line>
            <line>But march to London with our soldiers?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Ay, that's the first thing that we have to do;</line>
            <line>To free King Henry from imprisonment</line>
            <line>And see him seated in the regal throne.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
            <line>3 KING HENRY VI</line>
         </speech>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-4">
      <title>SCENE IV.  London. The palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter QUEEN ELIZABETH and RIVERS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RIVERS</speaker>
            <line>Madam, what makes you in this sudden change?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>Why brother Rivers, are you yet to learn</line>
            <line>What late misfortune is befall'n King Edward?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RIVERS</speaker>
            <line>What! loss of some pitch'd battle against Warwick?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>No, but the loss of his own royal person.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RIVERS</speaker>
            <line>Then is my sovereign slain?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>Ay, almost slain, for he is taken prisoner,</line>
            <line>Either betray'd by falsehood of his guard</line>
            <line>Or by his foe surprised at unawares:</line>
            <line>And, as I further have to understand,</line>
            <line>Is new committed to the Bishop of York,</line>
            <line>Fell Warwick's brother and by that our foe.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RIVERS</speaker>
            <line>These news I must confess are full of grief;</line>
            <line>Yet, gracious madam, bear it as you may:</line>
            <line>Warwick may lose, that now hath won the day.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>Till then fair hope must hinder life's decay.</line>
            <line>And I the rather wean me from despair</line>
            <line>For love of Edward's offspring in my womb:</line>
            <line>This is it that makes me bridle passion</line>
            <line>And bear with mildness my misfortune's cross;</line>
            <line>Ay, ay, for this I draw in many a tear</line>
            <line>And stop the rising of blood-sucking sighs,</line>
            <line>Lest with my sighs or tears I blast or drown</line>
            <line>King Edward's fruit, true heir to the English crown.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RIVERS</speaker>
            <line>But, madam, where is Warwick then become?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>I am inform'd that he comes towards London,</line>
            <line>To set the crown once more on Henry's head:</line>
            <line>Guess thou the rest; King Edward's friends must down,</line>
            <line>But, to prevent the tyrant's violence,--</line>
            <line>For trust not him that hath once broken faith,--</line>
            <line>I'll hence forthwith unto the sanctuary,</line>
            <line>To save at least the heir of Edward's right:</line>
            <line>There shall I rest secure from force and fraud.</line>
            <line>Come, therefore, let us fly while we may fly:</line>
            <line>If Warwick take us we are sure to die.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
            <line>3 KING HENRY VI</line>
         </speech>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-5">
      <title>SCENE V.  A park near Middleham Castle In Yorkshire.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter GLOUCESTER, HASTINGS, and STANLEY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Now, my Lord Hastings and Sir William Stanley,</line>
            <line>Leave off to wonder why I drew you hither,</line>
            <line>Into this chiefest thicket of the park.</line>
            <line>Thus stands the case: you know our king, my brother,</line>
            <line>Is prisoner to the bishop here, at whose hands</line>
            <line>He hath good usage and great liberty,</line>
            <line>And, often but attended with weak guard,</line>
            <line>Comes hunting this way to disport himself.</line>
            <line>I have advertised him by secret means</line>
            <line>That if about this hour he make his way</line>
            <line>Under the colour of his usual game,</line>
            <line>He shall here find his friends with horse and men</line>
            <line>To set him free from his captivity.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter KING EDWARD IV and a Huntsman with him</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Huntsman</speaker>
            <line>This way, my lord; for this way lies the game.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>Nay, this way, man: see where the huntsmen stand.</line>
            <line>Now, brother of Gloucester, Lord Hastings, and the rest,</line>
            <line>Stand you thus close, to steal the bishop's deer?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Brother, the time and case requireth haste:</line>
            <line>Your horse stands ready at the park-corner.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>But whither shall we then?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>To Lynn, my lord,</line>
            <line>And ship from thence to Flanders.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Well guess'd, believe me; for that was my meaning.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>Stanley, I will requite thy forwardness.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>But wherefore stay we? 'tis no time to talk.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>Huntsman, what say'st thou? wilt thou go along?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Huntsman</speaker>
            <line>Better do so than tarry and be hang'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Come then, away; let's ha' no more ado.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>Bishop, farewell: shield thee from Warwick's frown;</line>
            <line>And pray that I may repossess the crown.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
            <line>3 KING HENRY VI</line>
         </speech>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-6">
      <title>SCENE VI.  London. The Tower.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Flourish. Enter KING HENRY VI, CLARENCE, WARWICK,
SOMERSET, HENRY OF RICHMOND, OXFORD, MONTAGUE, and
Lieutenant of the Tower</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Master lieutenant, now that God and friends</line>
            <line>Have shaken Edward from the regal seat,</line>
            <line>And turn'd my captive state to liberty,</line>
            <line>My fear to hope, my sorrows unto joys,</line>
            <line>At our enlargement what are thy due fees?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lieutenant</speaker>
            <line>Subjects may challenge nothing of their sovereigns;</line>
            <line>But if an humble prayer may prevail,</line>
            <line>I then crave pardon of your majesty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>For what, lieutenant? for well using me?</line>
            <line>Nay, be thou sure I'll well requite thy kindness,</line>
            <line>For that it made my imprisonment a pleasure;</line>
            <line>Ay, such a pleasure as incaged birds</line>
            <line>Conceive when after many moody thoughts</line>
            <line>At last by notes of household harmony</line>
            <line>They quite forget their loss of liberty.</line>
            <line>But, Warwick, after God, thou set'st me free,</line>
            <line>And chiefly therefore I thank God and thee;</line>
            <line>He was the author, thou the instrument.</line>
            <line>Therefore, that I may conquer fortune's spite</line>
            <line>By living low, where fortune cannot hurt me,</line>
            <line>And that the people of this blessed land</line>
            <line>May not be punish'd with my thwarting stars,</line>
            <line>Warwick, although my head still wear the crown,</line>
            <line>I here resign my government to thee,</line>
            <line>For thou art fortunate in all thy deeds.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Your grace hath still been famed for virtuous;</line>
            <line>And now may seem as wise as virtuous,</line>
            <line>By spying and avoiding fortune's malice,</line>
            <line>For few men rightly temper with the stars:</line>
            <line>Yet in this one thing let me blame your grace,</line>
            <line>For choosing me when Clarence is in place.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>No, Warwick, thou art worthy of the sway,</line>
            <line>To whom the heavens in thy nativity</line>
            <line>Adjudged an olive branch and laurel crown,</line>
            <line>As likely to be blest in peace and war;</line>
            <line>And therefore I yield thee my free consent.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>And I choose Clarence only for protector.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Warwick and Clarence give me both your hands:</line>
            <line>Now join your hands, and with your hands your hearts,</line>
            <line>That no dissension hinder government:</line>
            <line>I make you both protectors of this land,</line>
            <line>While I myself will lead a private life</line>
            <line>And in devotion spend my latter days,</line>
            <line>To sin's rebuke and my Creator's praise.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>What answers Clarence to his sovereign's will?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>That he consents, if Warwick yield consent;</line>
            <line>For on thy fortune I repose myself.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Why, then, though loath, yet must I be content:</line>
            <line>We'll yoke together, like a double shadow</line>
            <line>To Henry's body, and supply his place;</line>
            <line>I mean, in bearing weight of government,</line>
            <line>While he enjoys the honour and his ease.</line>
            <line>And, Clarence, now then it is more than needful</line>
            <line>Forthwith that Edward be pronounced a traitor,</line>
            <line>And all his lands and goods be confiscate.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>What else? and that succession be determined.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Ay, therein Clarence shall not want his part.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>But, with the first of all your chief affairs,</line>
            <line>Let me entreat, for I command no more,</line>
            <line>That Margaret your queen and my son Edward</line>
            <line>Be sent for, to return from France with speed;</line>
            <line>For, till I see them here, by doubtful fear</line>
            <line>My joy of liberty is half eclipsed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>It shall be done, my sovereign, with all speed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>My Lord of Somerset, what youth is that,</line>
            <line>Of whom you seem to have so tender care?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SOMERSET</speaker>
            <line>My liege, it is young Henry, earl of Richmond.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Come hither, England's hope.</line>
            <stagedir>Lays his hand on his head</stagedir>
            <line>If secret powers</line>
            <line>Suggest but truth to my divining thoughts,</line>
            <line>This pretty lad will prove our country's bliss.</line>
            <line>His looks are full of peaceful majesty,</line>
            <line>His head by nature framed to wear a crown,</line>
            <line>His hand to wield a sceptre, and himself</line>
            <line>Likely in time to bless a regal throne.</line>
            <line>Make much of him, my lords, for this is he</line>
            <line>Must help you more than you are hurt by me.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter a Post</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>What news, my friend?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Post</speaker>
            <line>That Edward is escaped from your brother,</line>
            <line>And fled, as he hears since, to Burgundy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Unsavoury news! but how made he escape?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Post</speaker>
            <line>He was convey'd by Richard Duke of Gloucester</line>
            <line>And the Lord Hastings, who attended him</line>
            <line>In secret ambush on the forest side</line>
            <line>And from the bishop's huntsmen rescued him;</line>
            <line>For hunting was his daily exercise.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>My brother was too careless of his charge.</line>
            <line>But let us hence, my sovereign, to provide</line>
            <line>A salve for any sore that may betide.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt all but SOMERSET, HENRY OF RICHMOND, and OXFORD</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SOMERSET</speaker>
            <line>My lord, I like not of this flight of Edward's;</line>
            <line>For doubtless Burgundy will yield him help,</line>
            <line>And we shall have more wars before 't be long.</line>
            <line>As Henry's late presaging prophecy</line>
            <line>Did glad my heart with hope of this young Richmond,</line>
            <line>So doth my heart misgive me, in these conflicts</line>
            <line>What may befall him, to his harm and ours:</line>
            <line>Therefore, Lord Oxford, to prevent the worst,</line>
            <line>Forthwith we'll send him hence to Brittany,</line>
            <line>Till storms be past of civil enmity.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OXFORD</speaker>
            <line>Ay, for if Edward repossess the crown,</line>
            <line>'Tis like that Richmond with the rest shall down.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SOMERSET</speaker>
            <line>It shall be so; he shall to Brittany.</line>
            <line>Come, therefore, let's about it speedily.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
            <line>3 KING HENRY VI</line>
         </speech>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-7">
      <title>SCENE VII.  Before York.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Flourish. Enter KING EDWARD IV, GLOUCESTER,
HASTINGS, and Soldiers</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>Now, brother Richard, Lord Hastings, and the rest,</line>
            <line>Yet thus far fortune maketh us amends,</line>
            <line>And says that once more I shall interchange</line>
            <line>My waned state for Henry's regal crown.</line>
            <line>Well have we pass'd and now repass'd the seas</line>
            <line>And brought desired help from Burgundy:</line>
            <line>What then remains, we being thus arrived</line>
            <line>From Ravenspurgh haven before the gates of York,</line>
            <line>But that we enter, as into our dukedom?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>The gates made fast! Brother, I like not this;</line>
            <line>For many men that stumble at the threshold</line>
            <line>Are well foretold that danger lurks within.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>Tush, man, abodements must not now affright us:</line>
            <line>By fair or foul means we must enter in,</line>
            <line>For hither will our friends repair to us.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>My liege, I'll knock once more to summon them.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter, on the walls, the Mayor of York, and his Brethren</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Mayor</speaker>
            <line>My lords, we were forewarned of your coming,</line>
            <line>And shut the gates for safety of ourselves;</line>
            <line>For now we owe allegiance unto Henry.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>But, master mayor, if Henry be your king,</line>
            <line>Yet Edward at the least is Duke of York.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Mayor</speaker>
            <line>True, my good lord; I know you for no less.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>Why, and I challenge nothing but my dukedom,</line>
            <line>As being well content with that alone.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  But when the fox hath once got in his nose,</line>
            <line>He'll soon find means to make the body follow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>Why, master mayor, why stand you in a doubt?</line>
            <line>Open the gates; we are King Henry's friends.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Mayor</speaker>
            <line>Ay, say you so? the gates shall then be open'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>They descend</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>A wise stout captain, and soon persuaded!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>The good old man would fain that all were well,</line>
            <line>So 'twere not 'long of him; but being enter'd,</line>
            <line>I doubt not, I, but we shall soon persuade</line>
            <line>Both him and all his brothers unto reason.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter the Mayor and two Aldermen, below</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>So, master mayor: these gates must not be shut</line>
            <line>But in the night or in the time of war.</line>
            <line>What! fear not, man, but yield me up the keys;</line>
            <stagedir>Takes his keys</stagedir>
            <line>For Edward will defend the town and thee,</line>
            <line>And all those friends that deign to follow me.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>March. Enter MONTGOMERY, with drum and soldiers</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Brother, this is Sir John Montgomery,</line>
            <line>Our trusty friend, unless I be deceived.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>Welcome, Sir John! But why come you in arms?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MONTAGUE</speaker>
            <line>To help King Edward in his time of storm,</line>
            <line>As every loyal subject ought to do.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>Thanks, good Montgomery; but we now forget</line>
            <line>Our title to the crown and only claim</line>
            <line>Our dukedom till God please to send the rest.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MONTAGUE</speaker>
            <line>Then fare you well, for I will hence again:</line>
            <line>I came to serve a king and not a duke.</line>
            <line>Drummer, strike up, and let us march away.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>The drum begins to march</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>Nay, stay, Sir John, awhile, and we'll debate</line>
            <line>By what safe means the crown may be recover'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MONTAGUE</speaker>
            <line>What talk you of debating? in few words,</line>
            <line>If you'll not here proclaim yourself our king,</line>
            <line>I'll leave you to your fortune and be gone</line>
            <line>To keep them back that come to succor you:</line>
            <line>Why shall we fight, if you pretend no title?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Why, brother, wherefore stand you on nice points?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>When we grow stronger, then we'll make our claim:</line>
            <line>Till then, 'tis wisdom to conceal our meaning.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>Away with scrupulous wit! now arms must rule.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>And fearless minds climb soonest unto crowns.</line>
            <line>Brother, we will proclaim you out of hand:</line>
            <line>The bruit thereof will bring you many friends.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>Then be it as you will; for 'tis my right,</line>
            <line>And Henry but usurps the diadem.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MONTAGUE</speaker>
            <line>Ay, now my sovereign speaketh like himself;</line>
            <line>And now will I be Edward's champion.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>Sound trumpet; Edward shall be here proclaim'd:</line>
            <line>Come, fellow-soldier, make thou proclamation.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Flourish</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Soldier</speaker>
            <line>Edward the Fourth, by the grace of God, king of</line>
            <line>England and France, and lord of Ireland, &amp;c.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MONTAGUE</speaker>
            <line>And whosoe'er gainsays King Edward's right,</line>
            <line>By this I challenge him to single fight.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Throws down his gauntlet</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>All</speaker>
            <line>Long live Edward the Fourth!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>Thanks, brave Montgomery; and thanks unto you all:</line>
            <line>If fortune serve me, I'll requite this kindness.</line>
            <line>Now, for this night, let's harbour here in York;</line>
            <line>And when the morning sun shall raise his car</line>
            <line>Above the border of this horizon,</line>
            <line>We'll forward towards Warwick and his mates;</line>
            <line>For well I wot that Henry is no soldier.</line>
            <line>Ah, froward Clarence! how evil it beseems thee</line>
            <line>To flatter Henry and forsake thy brother!</line>
            <line>Yet, as we may, we'll meet both thee and Warwick.</line>
            <line>Come on, brave soldiers: doubt not of the day,</line>
            <line>And, that once gotten, doubt not of large pay.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
            <line>3 KING HENRY VI</line>
         </speech>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-8">
      <title>SCENE VIII.  London. The palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Flourish. Enter KING HENRY VI, WARWICK, MONTAGUE,
CLARENCE, EXETER, and OXFORD</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>What counsel, lords? Edward from Belgia,</line>
            <line>With hasty Germans and blunt Hollanders,</line>
            <line>Hath pass'd in safety through the narrow seas,</line>
            <line>And with his troops doth march amain to London;</line>
            <line>And many giddy people flock to him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Let's levy men, and beat him back again.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>A little fire is quickly trodden out;</line>
            <line>Which, being suffer'd, rivers cannot quench.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>In Warwickshire I have true-hearted friends,</line>
            <line>Not mutinous in peace, yet bold in war;</line>
            <line>Those will I muster up: and thou, son Clarence,</line>
            <line>Shalt stir up in Suffolk, Norfolk, and in Kent,</line>
            <line>The knights and gentlemen to come with thee:</line>
            <line>Thou, brother Montague, in Buckingham,</line>
            <line>Northampton and in Leicestershire, shalt find</line>
            <line>Men well inclined to hear what thou command'st:</line>
            <line>And thou, brave Oxford, wondrous well beloved,</line>
            <line>In Oxfordshire shalt muster up thy friends.</line>
            <line>My sovereign, with the loving citizens,</line>
            <line>Like to his island girt in with the ocean,</line>
            <line>Or modest Dian circled with her nymphs,</line>
            <line>Shall rest in London till we come to him.</line>
            <line>Fair lords, take leave and stand not to reply.</line>
            <line>Farewell, my sovereign.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Farewell, my Hector, and my Troy's true hope.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>In sign of truth, I kiss your highness' hand.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Well-minded Clarence, be thou fortunate!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MONTAGUE</speaker>
            <line>Comfort, my lord; and so I take my leave.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OXFORD</speaker>
            <line>And thus I seal my truth, and bid adieu.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Sweet Oxford, and my loving Montague,</line>
            <line>And all at once, once more a happy farewell.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Farewell, sweet lords: let's meet at Coventry.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt all but KING HENRY VI and EXETER</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Here at the palace I will rest awhile.</line>
            <line>Cousin of Exeter, what thinks your lordship?</line>
            <line>Methinks the power that Edward hath in field</line>
            <line>Should not be able to encounter mine.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EXETER</speaker>
            <line>The doubt is that he will seduce the rest.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>That's not my fear; my meed hath got me fame:</line>
            <line>I have not stopp'd mine ears to their demands,</line>
            <line>Nor posted off their suits with slow delays;</line>
            <line>My pity hath been balm to heal their wounds,</line>
            <line>My mildness hath allay'd their swelling griefs,</line>
            <line>My mercy dried their water-flowing tears;</line>
            <line>I have not been desirous of their wealth,</line>
            <line>Nor much oppress'd them with great subsidies.</line>
            <line>Nor forward of revenge, though they much err'd:</line>
            <line>Then why should they love Edward more than me?</line>
            <line>No, Exeter, these graces challenge grace:</line>
            <line>And when the lion fawns upon the lamb,</line>
            <line>The lamb will never cease to follow him.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Shout within. 'A Lancaster! A Lancaster!'</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EXETER</speaker>
            <line>Hark, hark, my lord! what shouts are these?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter KING EDWARD IV, GLOUCESTER, and soldiers</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>Seize on the shame-faced Henry, bear him hence;</line>
            <line>And once again proclaim us King of England.</line>
            <line>You are the fount that makes small brooks to flow:</line>
            <line>Now stops thy spring; my sea sha$l suck them dry,</line>
            <line>And swell so much the higher by their ebb.</line>
            <line>Hence with him to the Tower; let him not speak.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt some with KING HENRY VI</stagedir>
            <line>And, lords, towards Coventry bend we our course</line>
            <line>Where peremptory Warwick now remains:</line>
            <line>The sun shines hot; and, if we use delay,</line>
            <line>Cold biting winter mars our hoped-for hay.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Away betimes, before his forces join,</line>
            <line>And take the great-grown traitor unawares:</line>
            <line>Brave warriors, march amain towards Coventry.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
            <line>3 KING HENRY VI</line>
         </speech>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>