<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net/doctypes/dita/shakespear/dtd/act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-5">
   <title>ACT V</title>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  The woods. Before Timon's cave.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter Poet and Painter; TIMON watching
them from his cave</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Painter</speaker>
            <line>As I took note of the place, it cannot be far where</line>
            <line>he abides.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Poet</speaker>
            <line>What's to be thought of him? does the rumour hold</line>
            <line>for true, that he's so full of gold?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Painter</speaker>
            <line>Certain: Alcibiades reports it; Phrynia and</line>
            <line>Timandra had gold of him: he likewise enriched poor</line>
            <line>straggling soldiers with great quantity: 'tis said</line>
            <line>he gave unto his steward a mighty sum.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Poet</speaker>
            <line>Then this breaking of his has been but a try for his friends.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Painter</speaker>
            <line>Nothing else: you shall see him a palm in Athens</line>
            <line>again, and flourish with the highest. Therefore</line>
            <line>'tis not amiss we tender our loves to him, in this</line>
            <line>supposed distress of his: it will show honestly in</line>
            <line>us; and is very likely to load our purposes with</line>
            <line>what they travail for, if it be a just true report</line>
            <line>that goes of his having.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Poet</speaker>
            <line>What have you now to present unto him?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Painter</speaker>
            <line>Nothing at this time but my visitation: only I will</line>
            <line>promise him an excellent piece.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Poet</speaker>
            <line>I must serve him so too, tell him of an intent</line>
            <line>that's coming toward him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Painter</speaker>
            <line>Good as the best. Promising is the very air o' the</line>
            <line>time: it opens the eyes of expectation:</line>
            <line>performance is ever the duller for his act; and,</line>
            <line>but in the plainer and simpler kind of people, the</line>
            <line>deed of saying is quite out of use. To promise is</line>
            <line>most courtly and fashionable: performance is a kind</line>
            <line>of will or testament which argues a great sickness</line>
            <line>in his judgment that makes it.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>TIMON comes from his cave, behind</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TIMON</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  Excellent workman! thou canst not paint a</line>
            <line>man so bad as is thyself.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Poet</speaker>
            <line>I am thinking what I shall say I have provided for</line>
            <line>him: it must be a personating of himself; a satire</line>
            <line>against the softness of prosperity, with a discovery</line>
            <line>of the infinite flatteries that follow youth and opulency.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TIMON</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  Must thou needs stand for a villain in</line>
            <line>thine own work? wilt thou whip thine own faults in</line>
            <line>other men? Do so, I have gold for thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Poet</speaker>
            <line>Nay, let's seek him:</line>
            <line>Then do we sin against our own estate,</line>
            <line>When we may profit meet, and come too late.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Painter</speaker>
            <line>True;</line>
            <line>When the day serves, before black-corner'd night,</line>
            <line>Find what thou want'st by free and offer'd light. Come.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TIMON</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  I'll meet you at the turn. What a</line>
            <line>god's gold,</line>
            <line>That he is worshipp'd in a baser temple</line>
            <line>Than where swine feed!</line>
            <line>'Tis thou that rigg'st the bark and plough'st the foam,</line>
            <line>Settlest admired reverence in a slave:</line>
            <line>To thee be worship! and thy saints for aye</line>
            <line>Be crown'd with plagues that thee alone obey!</line>
            <line>Fit I meet them.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Coming forward</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Poet</speaker>
            <line>Hail, worthy Timon!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Painter</speaker>
            <line>Our late noble master!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TIMON</speaker>
            <line>Have I once lived to see two honest men?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Poet</speaker>
            <line>Sir,</line>
            <line>Having often of your open bounty tasted,</line>
            <line>Hearing you were retired, your friends fall'n off,</line>
            <line>Whose thankless natures--O abhorred spirits!--</line>
            <line>Not all the whips of heaven are large enough:</line>
            <line>What! to you,</line>
            <line>Whose star-like nobleness gave life and influence</line>
            <line>To their whole being! I am rapt and cannot cover</line>
            <line>The monstrous bulk of this ingratitude</line>
            <line>With any size of words.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TIMON</speaker>
            <line>Let it go naked, men may see't the better:</line>
            <line>You that are honest, by being what you are,</line>
            <line>Make them best seen and known.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Painter</speaker>
            <line>He and myself</line>
            <line>Have travail'd in the great shower of your gifts,</line>
            <line>And sweetly felt it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TIMON</speaker>
            <line>Ay, you are honest men.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Painter</speaker>
            <line>We are hither come to offer you our service.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TIMON</speaker>
            <line>Most honest men! Why, how shall I requite you?</line>
            <line>Can you eat roots, and drink cold water? no.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Both</speaker>
            <line>What we can do, we'll do, to do you service.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TIMON</speaker>
            <line>Ye're honest men: ye've heard that I have gold;</line>
            <line>I am sure you have: speak truth; ye're honest men.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Painter</speaker>
            <line>So it is said, my noble lord; but therefore</line>
            <line>Came not my friend nor I.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TIMON</speaker>
            <line>Good honest men! Thou draw'st a counterfeit</line>
            <line>Best in all Athens: thou'rt, indeed, the best;</line>
            <line>Thou counterfeit'st most lively.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Painter</speaker>
            <line>So, so, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TIMON</speaker>
            <line>E'en so, sir, as I say. And, for thy fiction,</line>
            <line>Why, thy verse swells with stuff so fine and smooth</line>
            <line>That thou art even natural in thine art.</line>
            <line>But, for all this, my honest-natured friends,</line>
            <line>I must needs say you have a little fault:</line>
            <line>Marry, 'tis not monstrous in you, neither wish I</line>
            <line>You take much pains to mend.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Both</speaker>
            <line>Beseech your honour</line>
            <line>To make it known to us.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TIMON</speaker>
            <line>You'll take it ill.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Both</speaker>
            <line>Most thankfully, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TIMON</speaker>
            <line>Will you, indeed?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Both</speaker>
            <line>Doubt it not, worthy lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TIMON</speaker>
            <line>There's never a one of you but trusts a knave,</line>
            <line>That mightily deceives you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Both</speaker>
            <line>Do we, my lord?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TIMON</speaker>
            <line>Ay, and you hear him cog, see him dissemble,</line>
            <line>Know his gross patchery, love him, feed him,</line>
            <line>Keep in your bosom: yet remain assured</line>
            <line>That he's a made-up villain.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Painter</speaker>
            <line>I know none such, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Poet</speaker>
            <line>Nor I.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TIMON</speaker>
            <line>Look you, I love you well; I'll give you gold,</line>
            <line>Rid me these villains from your companies:</line>
            <line>Hang them or stab them, drown them in a draught,</line>
            <line>Confound them by some course, and come to me,</line>
            <line>I'll give you gold enough.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Both</speaker>
            <line>Name them, my lord, let's know them.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TIMON</speaker>
            <line>You that way and you this, but two in company;</line>
            <line>Each man apart, all single and alone,</line>
            <line>Yet an arch-villain keeps him company.</line>
            <line>If where thou art two villains shall not be,</line>
            <line>Come not near him. If thou wouldst not reside</line>
            <line>But where one villain is, then him abandon.</line>
            <line>Hence, pack! there's gold; you came for gold, ye slaves:</line>
            <stagedir>To Painter</stagedir>
            <line>You have work'd for me; there's payment for you: hence!</line>
            <stagedir>To Poet</stagedir>
            <line>You are an alchemist; make gold of that.</line>
            <line>Out, rascal dogs!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Beats them out, and then retires to his cave</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Enter FLAVIUS and two Senators</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLAVIUS</speaker>
            <line>It is in vain that you would speak with Timon;</line>
            <line>For he is set so only to himself</line>
            <line>That nothing but himself which looks like man</line>
            <line>Is friendly with him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>Bring us to his cave:</line>
            <line>It is our part and promise to the Athenians</line>
            <line>To speak with Timon.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Senator</speaker>
            <line>At all times alike</line>
            <line>Men are not still the same: 'twas time and griefs</line>
            <line>That framed him thus: time, with his fairer hand,</line>
            <line>Offering the fortunes of his former days,</line>
            <line>The former man may make him. Bring us to him,</line>
            <line>And chance it as it may.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLAVIUS</speaker>
            <line>Here is his cave.</line>
            <line>Peace and content be here! Lord Timon! Timon!</line>
            <line>Look out, and speak to friends: the Athenians,</line>
            <line>By two of their most reverend senate, greet thee:</line>
            <line>Speak to them, noble Timon.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>TIMON comes from his cave</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TIMON</speaker>
            <line>Thou sun, that comfort'st, burn! Speak, and</line>
            <line>be hang'd:</line>
            <line>For each true word, a blister! and each false</line>
            <line>Be as cauterizing to the root o' the tongue,</line>
            <line>Consuming it with speaking!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>Worthy Timon,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TIMON</speaker>
            <line>Of none but such as you, and you of Timon.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>The senators of Athens greet thee, Timon.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TIMON</speaker>
            <line>I thank them; and would send them back the plague,</line>
            <line>Could I but catch it for them.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>O, forget</line>
            <line>What we are sorry for ourselves in thee.</line>
            <line>The senators with one consent of love</line>
            <line>Entreat thee back to Athens; who have thought</line>
            <line>On special dignities, which vacant lie</line>
            <line>For thy best use and wearing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Senator</speaker>
            <line>They confess</line>
            <line>Toward thee forgetfulness too general, gross:</line>
            <line>Which now the public body, which doth seldom</line>
            <line>Play the recanter, feeling in itself</line>
            <line>A lack of Timon's aid, hath sense withal</line>
            <line>Of its own fail, restraining aid to Timon;</line>
            <line>And send forth us, to make their sorrow'd render,</line>
            <line>Together with a recompense more fruitful</line>
            <line>Than their offence can weigh down by the dram;</line>
            <line>Ay, even such heaps and sums of love and wealth</line>
            <line>As shall to thee blot out what wrongs were theirs</line>
            <line>And write in thee the figures of their love,</line>
            <line>Ever to read them thine.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TIMON</speaker>
            <line>You witch me in it;</line>
            <line>Surprise me to the very brink of tears:</line>
            <line>Lend me a fool's heart and a woman's eyes,</line>
            <line>And I'll beweep these comforts, worthy senators.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>Therefore, so please thee to return with us</line>
            <line>And of our Athens, thine and ours, to take</line>
            <line>The captainship, thou shalt be met with thanks,</line>
            <line>Allow'd with absolute power and thy good name</line>
            <line>Live with authority: so soon we shall drive back</line>
            <line>Of Alcibiades the approaches wild,</line>
            <line>Who, like a boar too savage, doth root up</line>
            <line>His country's peace.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Senator</speaker>
            <line>And shakes his threatening sword</line>
            <line>Against the walls of Athens.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>Therefore, Timon,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TIMON</speaker>
            <line>Well, sir, I will; therefore, I will, sir; thus:</line>
            <line>If Alcibiades kill my countrymen,</line>
            <line>Let Alcibiades know this of Timon,</line>
            <line>That Timon cares not. But if be sack fair Athens,</line>
            <line>And take our goodly aged men by the beards,</line>
            <line>Giving our holy virgins to the stain</line>
            <line>Of contumelious, beastly, mad-brain'd war,</line>
            <line>Then let him know, and tell him Timon speaks it,</line>
            <line>In pity of our aged and our youth,</line>
            <line>I cannot choose but tell him, that I care not,</line>
            <line>And let him take't at worst; for their knives care not,</line>
            <line>While you have throats to answer: for myself,</line>
            <line>There's not a whittle in the unruly camp</line>
            <line>But I do prize it at my love before</line>
            <line>The reverend'st throat in Athens. So I leave you</line>
            <line>To the protection of the prosperous gods,</line>
            <line>As thieves to keepers.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLAVIUS</speaker>
            <line>Stay not, all's in vain.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TIMON</speaker>
            <line>Why, I was writing of my epitaph;</line>
            <line>it will be seen to-morrow: my long sickness</line>
            <line>Of health and living now begins to mend,</line>
            <line>And nothing brings me all things. Go, live still;</line>
            <line>Be Alcibiades your plague, you his,</line>
            <line>And last so long enough!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>We speak in vain.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TIMON</speaker>
            <line>But yet I love my country, and am not</line>
            <line>One that rejoices in the common wreck,</line>
            <line>As common bruit doth put it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>That's well spoke.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TIMON</speaker>
            <line>Commend me to my loving countrymen,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>These words become your lips as they pass</line>
            <line>thorough them.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Senator</speaker>
            <line>And enter in our ears like great triumphers</line>
            <line>In their applauding gates.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TIMON</speaker>
            <line>Commend me to them,</line>
            <line>And tell them that, to ease them of their griefs,</line>
            <line>Their fears of hostile strokes, their aches, losses,</line>
            <line>Their pangs of love, with other incident throes</line>
            <line>That nature's fragile vessel doth sustain</line>
            <line>In life's uncertain voyage, I will some kindness do them:</line>
            <line>I'll teach them to prevent wild Alcibiades' wrath.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>I like this well; he will return again.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TIMON</speaker>
            <line>I have a tree, which grows here in my close,</line>
            <line>That mine own use invites me to cut down,</line>
            <line>And shortly must I fell it: tell my friends,</line>
            <line>Tell Athens, in the sequence of degree</line>
            <line>From high to low throughout, that whoso please</line>
            <line>To stop affliction, let him take his haste,</line>
            <line>Come hither, ere my tree hath felt the axe,</line>
            <line>And hang himself. I pray you, do my greeting.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLAVIUS</speaker>
            <line>Trouble him no further; thus you still shall find him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TIMON</speaker>
            <line>Come not to me again: but say to Athens,</line>
            <line>Timon hath made his everlasting mansion</line>
            <line>Upon the beached verge of the salt flood;</line>
            <line>Who once a day with his embossed froth</line>
            <line>The turbulent surge shall cover: thither come,</line>
            <line>And let my grave-stone be your oracle.</line>
            <line>Lips, let sour words go by and language end:</line>
            <line>What is amiss plague and infection mend!</line>
            <line>Graves only be men's works and death their gain!</line>
            <line>Sun, hide thy beams! Timon hath done his reign.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Retires to his cave</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>His discontents are unremoveably</line>
            <line>Coupled to nature.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Senator</speaker>
            <line>Our hope in him is dead: let us return,</line>
            <line>And strain what other means is left unto us</line>
            <line>In our dear peril.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>It requires swift foot.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  Before the walls of Athens.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter two Senators and a Messenger</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>Thou hast painfully discover'd: are his files</line>
            <line>As full as thy report?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>have spoke the least:</line>
            <line>Besides, his expedition promises</line>
            <line>Present approach.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Senator</speaker>
            <line>We stand much hazard, if they bring not Timon.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>I met a courier, one mine ancient friend;</line>
            <line>Whom, though in general part we were opposed,</line>
            <line>Yet our old love made a particular force,</line>
            <line>And made us speak like friends: this man was riding</line>
            <line>From Alcibiades to Timon's cave,</line>
            <line>With letters of entreaty, which imported</line>
            <line>His fellowship i' the cause against your city,</line>
            <line>In part for his sake moved.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>Here come our brothers.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter the Senators from TIMON</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Senator</speaker>
            <line>No talk of Timon, nothing of him expect.</line>
            <line>The enemies' drum is heard, and fearful scouring</line>
            <line>Doth choke the air with dust: in, and prepare:</line>
            <line>Ours is the fall, I fear; our foes the snare.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  The woods. Timon's cave, and a rude tomb seen.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter a Soldier, seeking TIMON</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Soldier</speaker>
            <line>By all description this should be the place.</line>
            <line>Who's here? speak, ho! No answer! What is this?</line>
            <line>Timon is dead, who hath outstretch'd his span:</line>
            <line>Some beast rear'd this; there does not live a man.</line>
            <line>Dead, sure; and this his grave. What's on this tomb</line>
            <line>I cannot read; the character I'll take with wax:</line>
            <line>Our captain hath in every figure skill,</line>
            <line>An aged interpreter, though young in days:</line>
            <line>Before proud Athens he's set down by this,</line>
            <line>Whose fall the mark of his ambition is.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-4">
      <title>SCENE IV.  Before the walls of Athens.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Trumpets sound. Enter ALCIBIADES with his powers</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALCIBIADES</speaker>
            <line>Sound to this coward and lascivious town</line>
            <line>Our terrible approach.</line>
            <stagedir>A parley sounded</stagedir>
            <stagedir>Enter Senators on the walls</stagedir>
            <line>Till now you have gone on and fill'd the time</line>
            <line>With all licentious measure, making your wills</line>
            <line>The scope of justice; till now myself and such</line>
            <line>As slept within the shadow of your power</line>
            <line>Have wander'd with our traversed arms and breathed</line>
            <line>Our sufferance vainly: now the time is flush,</line>
            <line>When crouching marrow in the bearer strong</line>
            <line>Cries of itself 'No more:' now breathless wrong</line>
            <line>Shall sit and pant in your great chairs of ease,</line>
            <line>And pursy insolence shall break his wind</line>
            <line>With fear and horrid flight.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>Noble and young,</line>
            <line>When thy first griefs were but a mere conceit,</line>
            <line>Ere thou hadst power or we had cause of fear,</line>
            <line>We sent to thee, to give thy rages balm,</line>
            <line>To wipe out our ingratitude with loves</line>
            <line>Above their quantity.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Senator</speaker>
            <line>So did we woo</line>
            <line>Transformed Timon to our city's love</line>
            <line>By humble message and by promised means:</line>
            <line>We were not all unkind, nor all deserve</line>
            <line>The common stroke of war.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>These walls of ours</line>
            <line>Were not erected by their hands from whom</line>
            <line>You have received your griefs; nor are they such</line>
            <line>That these great towers, trophies and schools</line>
            <line>should fall</line>
            <line>For private faults in them.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Senator</speaker>
            <line>Nor are they living</line>
            <line>Who were the motives that you first went out;</line>
            <line>Shame that they wanted cunning, in excess</line>
            <line>Hath broke their hearts. March, noble lord,</line>
            <line>Into our city with thy banners spread:</line>
            <line>By decimation, and a tithed death--</line>
            <line>If thy revenges hunger for that food</line>
            <line>Which nature loathes--take thou the destined tenth,</line>
            <line>And by the hazard of the spotted die</line>
            <line>Let die the spotted.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>All have not offended;</line>
            <line>For those that were, it is not square to take</line>
            <line>On those that are, revenges: crimes, like lands,</line>
            <line>Are not inherited. Then, dear countryman,</line>
            <line>Bring in thy ranks, but leave without thy rage:</line>
            <line>Spare thy Athenian cradle and those kin</line>
            <line>Which in the bluster of thy wrath must fall</line>
            <line>With those that have offended: like a shepherd,</line>
            <line>Approach the fold and cull the infected forth,</line>
            <line>But kill not all together.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Senator</speaker>
            <line>What thou wilt,</line>
            <line>Thou rather shalt enforce it with thy smile</line>
            <line>Than hew to't with thy sword.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator </speaker>
            <line>Set but thy foot</line>
            <line>Against our rampired gates, and they shall ope;</line>
            <line>So thou wilt send thy gentle heart before,</line>
            <line>To say thou'lt enter friendly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Senator</speaker>
            <line>Throw thy glove,</line>
            <line>Or any token of thine honour else,</line>
            <line>That thou wilt use the wars as thy redress</line>
            <line>And not as our confusion, all thy powers</line>
            <line>Shall make their harbour in our town, till we</line>
            <line>Have seal'd thy full desire.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALCIBIADES</speaker>
            <line>Then there's my glove;</line>
            <line>Descend, and open your uncharged ports:</line>
            <line>Those enemies of Timon's and mine own</line>
            <line>Whom you yourselves shall set out for reproof</line>
            <line>Fall and no more: and, to atone your fears</line>
            <line>With my more noble meaning, not a man</line>
            <line>Shall pass his quarter, or offend the stream</line>
            <line>Of regular justice in your city's bounds,</line>
            <line>But shall be render'd to your public laws</line>
            <line>At heaviest answer.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Both</speaker>
            <line>'Tis most nobly spoken.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALCIBIADES</speaker>
            <line>Descend, and keep your words.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>The Senators descend, and open the gates</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Enter Soldier</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Soldier</speaker>
            <line>My noble general, Timon is dead;</line>
            <line>Entomb'd upon the very hem o' the sea;</line>
            <line>And on his grave-stone this insculpture, which</line>
            <line>With wax I brought away, whose soft impression</line>
            <line>Interprets for my poor ignorance.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALCIBIADES</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Reads the epitaph</stagedir>  'Here lies a</line>
            <line>wretched corse, of wretched soul bereft:</line>
            <line>Seek not my name: a plague consume you wicked</line>
            <line>caitiffs left!</line>
            <line>Here lie I, Timon; who, alive, all living men did hate:</line>
            <line>Pass by and curse thy fill, but pass and stay</line>
            <line>not here thy gait.'</line>
            <line>These well express in thee thy latter spirits:</line>
            <line>Though thou abhorr'dst in us our human griefs,</line>
            <line>Scorn'dst our brain's flow and those our</line>
            <line>droplets which</line>
            <line>From niggard nature fall, yet rich conceit</line>
            <line>Taught thee to make vast Neptune weep for aye</line>
            <line>On thy low grave, on faults forgiven. Dead</line>
            <line>Is noble Timon: of whose memory</line>
            <line>Hereafter more. Bring me into your city,</line>
            <line>And I will use the olive with my sword,</line>
            <line>Make war breed peace, make peace stint war, make each</line>
            <line>Prescribe to other as each other's leech.</line>
            <line>Let our drums strike.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>