<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:shakespear:dtd:act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-3">
   <title>ACT III</title>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  A room in Lucullus' house.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>FLAMINIUS waiting. Enter a Servant to him</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>I have told my lord of you; he is coming down to you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLAMINIUS</speaker>
            <line>I thank you, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter LUCULLUS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>Here's my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCULLUS</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  One of Lord Timon's men? a gift, I</line>
            <line>warrant. Why, this hits right; I dreamt of a silver</line>
            <line>basin and ewer to-night. Flaminius, honest</line>
            <line>Flaminius; you are very respectively welcome, sir.</line>
            <line>Fill me some wine.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit Servants</stagedir>
            <line>And how does that honourable, complete, free-hearted</line>
            <line>gentleman of Athens, thy very bountiful good lord</line>
            <line>and master?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLAMINIUS</speaker>
            <line>His health is well sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCULLUS</speaker>
            <line>I am right glad that his health is well, sir: and</line>
            <line>what hast thou there under thy cloak, pretty Flaminius?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLAMINIUS</speaker>
            <line>'Faith, nothing but an empty box, sir; which, in my</line>
            <line>lord's behalf, I come to entreat your honour to</line>
            <line>supply; who, having great and instant occasion to</line>
            <line>use fifty talents, hath sent to your lordship to</line>
            <line>furnish him, nothing doubting your present</line>
            <line>assistance therein.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCULLUS</speaker>
            <line>La, la, la, la! 'nothing doubting,' says he? Alas,</line>
            <line>good lord! a noble gentleman 'tis, if he would not</line>
            <line>keep so good a house. Many a time and often I ha'</line>
            <line>dined with him, and told him on't, and come again to</line>
            <line>supper to him, of purpose to have him spend less,</line>
            <line>and yet he would embrace no counsel, take no warning</line>
            <line>by my coming. Every man has his fault, and honesty</line>
            <line>is his: I ha' told him on't, but I could ne'er get</line>
            <line>him from't.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter Servant, with wine</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>Please your lordship, here is the wine.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCULLUS</speaker>
            <line>Flaminius, I have noted thee always wise. Here's to thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLAMINIUS</speaker>
            <line>Your lordship speaks your pleasure.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCULLUS</speaker>
            <line>I have observed thee always for a towardly prompt</line>
            <line>spirit--give thee thy due--and one that knows what</line>
            <line>belongs to reason; and canst use the time well, if</line>
            <line>the time use thee well: good parts in thee.</line>
            <stagedir>To Servant</stagedir>
            <line>Get you gone, sirrah.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit Servant</stagedir>
            <line>Draw nearer, honest Flaminius. Thy lord's a</line>
            <line>bountiful gentleman: but thou art wise; and thou</line>
            <line>knowest well enough, although thou comest to me,</line>
            <line>that this is no time to lend money, especially upon</line>
            <line>bare friendship, without security. Here's three</line>
            <line>solidares for thee: good boy, wink at me, and say</line>
            <line>thou sawest me not. Fare thee well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLAMINIUS</speaker>
            <line>Is't possible the world should so much differ,</line>
            <line>And we alive that lived? Fly, damned baseness,</line>
            <line>To him that worships thee!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Throwing the money back</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCULLUS</speaker>
            <line>Ha! now I see thou art a fool, and fit for thy master.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLAMINIUS</speaker>
            <line>May these add to the number that may scald thee!</line>
            <line>Let moulten coin be thy damnation,</line>
            <line>Thou disease of a friend, and not himself!</line>
            <line>Has friendship such a faint and milky heart,</line>
            <line>It turns in less than two nights? O you gods,</line>
            <line>I feel master's passion! this slave,</line>
            <line>Unto his honour, has my lord's meat in him:</line>
            <line>Why should it thrive and turn to nutriment,</line>
            <line>When he is turn'd to poison?</line>
            <line>O, may diseases only work upon't!</line>
            <line>And, when he's sick to death, let not that part of nature</line>
            <line>Which my lord paid for, be of any power</line>
            <line>To expel sickness, but prolong his hour!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  A public place.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter LUCILIUS, with three Strangers</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCILIUS</speaker>
            <line>Who, the Lord Timon? he is my very good friend, and</line>
            <line>an honourable gentleman.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Stranger</speaker>
            <line>We know him for no less, though we are but strangers</line>
            <line>to him. But I can tell you one thing, my lord, and</line>
            <line>which I hear from common rumours: now Lord Timon's</line>
            <line>happy hours are done and past, and his estate</line>
            <line>shrinks from him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCILIUS</speaker>
            <line>Fie, no, do not believe it; he cannot want for money.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Stranger</speaker>
            <line>But believe you this, my lord, that, not long ago,</line>
            <line>one of his men was with the Lord Lucullus to borrow</line>
            <line>so many talents, nay, urged extremely for't and</line>
            <line>showed what necessity belonged to't, and yet was denied.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCILIUS</speaker>
            <line>How!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Stranger</speaker>
            <line>I tell you, denied, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCILIUS</speaker>
            <line>What a strange case was that! now, before the gods,</line>
            <line>I am ashamed on't. Denied that honourable man!</line>
            <line>there was very little honour showed in't. For my own</line>
            <line>part, I must needs confess, I have received some</line>
            <line>small kindnesses from him, as money, plate, jewels</line>
            <line>and such-like trifles, nothing comparing to his;</line>
            <line>yet, had he mistook him and sent to me, I should</line>
            <line>ne'er have denied his occasion so many talents.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter SERVILIUS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SERVILIUS</speaker>
            <line>See, by good hap, yonder's my lord;</line>
            <line>I have sweat to see his honour. My honoured lord,--</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>To LUCIUS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCILIUS</speaker>
            <line>Servilius! you are kindly met, sir. Fare thee well:</line>
            <line>commend me to thy honourable virtuous lord, my very</line>
            <line>exquisite friend.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SERVILIUS</speaker>
            <line>May it please your honour, my lord hath sent--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCILIUS</speaker>
            <line>Ha! what has he sent? I am so much endeared to</line>
            <line>that lord; he's ever sending: how shall I thank</line>
            <line>him, thinkest thou? And what has he sent now?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SERVILIUS</speaker>
            <line>Has only sent his present occasion now, my lord;</line>
            <line>requesting your lordship to supply his instant use</line>
            <line>with so many talents.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCILIUS</speaker>
            <line>I know his lordship is but merry with me;</line>
            <line>He cannot want fifty five hundred talents.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SERVILIUS</speaker>
            <line>But in the mean time he wants less, my lord.</line>
            <line>If his occasion were not virtuous,</line>
            <line>I should not urge it half so faithfully.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCILIUS</speaker>
            <line>Dost thou speak seriously, Servilius?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SERVILIUS</speaker>
            <line>Upon my soul,'tis true, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCILIUS</speaker>
            <line>What a wicked beast was I to disfurnish myself</line>
            <line>against such a good time, when I might ha' shown</line>
            <line>myself honourable! how unluckily it happened, that I</line>
            <line>should purchase the day before for a little part,</line>
            <line>and undo a great deal of honoured! Servilius, now,</line>
            <line>before the gods, I am not able to do,--the more</line>
            <line>beast, I say:--I was sending to use Lord Timon</line>
            <line>myself, these gentlemen can witness! but I would</line>
            <line>not, for the wealth of Athens, I had done't now.</line>
            <line>Commend me bountifully to his good lordship; and I</line>
            <line>hope his honour will conceive the fairest of me,</line>
            <line>because I have no power to be kind: and tell him</line>
            <line>this from me, I count it one of my greatest</line>
            <line>afflictions, say, that I cannot pleasure such an</line>
            <line>honourable gentleman. Good Servilius, will you</line>
            <line>befriend me so far, as to use mine own words to him?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SERVILIUS</speaker>
            <line>Yes, sir, I shall.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCILIUS</speaker>
            <line>I'll look you out a good turn, Servilius.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit SERVILIUS</stagedir>
            <line>True as you said, Timon is shrunk indeed;</line>
            <line>And he that's once denied will hardly speed.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Stranger</speaker>
            <line>Do you observe this, Hostilius?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Stranger</speaker>
            <line>Ay, too well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Stranger</speaker>
            <line>Why, this is the world's soul; and just of the</line>
            <line>same piece</line>
            <line>Is every flatterer's spirit. Who can call him</line>
            <line>His friend that dips in the same dish? for, in</line>
            <line>My knowing, Timon has been this lord's father,</line>
            <line>And kept his credit with his purse,</line>
            <line>Supported his estate; nay, Timon's money</line>
            <line>Has paid his men their wages: he ne'er drinks,</line>
            <line>But Timon's silver treads upon his lip;</line>
            <line>And yet--O, see the monstrousness of man</line>
            <line>When he looks out in an ungrateful shape!--</line>
            <line>He does deny him, in respect of his,</line>
            <line>What charitable men afford to beggars.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Stranger</speaker>
            <line>Religion groans at it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Stranger</speaker>
            <line>For mine own part,</line>
            <line>I never tasted Timon in my life,</line>
            <line>Nor came any of his bounties over me,</line>
            <line>To mark me for his friend; yet, I protest,</line>
            <line>For his right noble mind, illustrious virtue</line>
            <line>And honourable carriage,</line>
            <line>Had his necessity made use of me,</line>
            <line>I would have put my wealth into donation,</line>
            <line>And the best half should have return'd to him,</line>
            <line>So much I love his heart: but, I perceive,</line>
            <line>Men must learn now with pity to dispense;</line>
            <line>For policy sits above conscience.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  A room in Sempronius' house.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter SEMPRONIUS, and a Servant of TIMON's</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SEMPRONIUS</speaker>
            <line>Must he needs trouble me in 't,--hum!--'bove</line>
            <line>all others?</line>
            <line>He might have tried Lord Lucius or Lucullus;</line>
            <line>And now Ventidius is wealthy too,</line>
            <line>Whom he redeem'd from prison: all these</line>
            <line>Owe their estates unto him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>My lord,</line>
            <line>They have all been touch'd and found base metal, for</line>
            <line>They have au denied him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SEMPRONIUS</speaker>
            <line>How! have they denied him?</line>
            <line>Has Ventidius and Lucullus denied him?</line>
            <line>And does he send to me? Three? hum!</line>
            <line>It shows but little love or judgment in him:</line>
            <line>Must I be his last refuge! His friends, like</line>
            <line>physicians,</line>
            <line>Thrive, give him over: must I take the cure upon me?</line>
            <line>Has much disgraced me in't; I'm angry at him,</line>
            <line>That might have known my place: I see no sense for't,</line>
            <line>But his occasion might have woo'd me first;</line>
            <line>For, in my conscience, I was the first man</line>
            <line>That e'er received gift from him:</line>
            <line>And does he think so backwardly of me now,</line>
            <line>That I'll requite its last? No:</line>
            <line>So it may prove an argument of laughter</line>
            <line>To the rest, and 'mongst lords I be thought a fool.</line>
            <line>I'ld rather than the worth of thrice the sum,</line>
            <line>Had sent to me first, but for my mind's sake;</line>
            <line>I'd such a courage to do him good. But now return,</line>
            <line>And with their faint reply this answer join;</line>
            <line>Who bates mine honour shall not know my coin.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>Excellent! Your lordship's a goodly villain. The</line>
            <line>devil knew not what he did when he made man</line>
            <line>politic; he crossed himself by 't: and I cannot</line>
            <line>think but, in the end, the villainies of man will</line>
            <line>set him clear. How fairly this lord strives to</line>
            <line>appear foul! takes virtuous copies to be wicked,</line>
            <line>like those that under hot ardent zeal would set</line>
            <line>whole realms on fire: Of such a nature is his</line>
            <line>politic love.</line>
            <line>This was my lord's best hope; now all are fled,</line>
            <line>Save only the gods: now his friends are dead,</line>
            <line>Doors, that were ne'er acquainted with their wards</line>
            <line>Many a bounteous year must be employ'd</line>
            <line>Now to guard sure their master.</line>
            <line>And this is all a liberal course allows;</line>
            <line>Who cannot keep his wealth must keep his house.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-4">
      <title>SCENE IV.  The same. A hall in Timon's house.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter two Servants of Varro, and the Servant of
LUCIUS, meeting TITUS, HORTENSIUS, and other
Servants of TIMON's creditors, waiting his coming out</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Varro's First Servant</speaker>
            <line>Well met; good morrow, Titus and Hortensius.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS</speaker>
            <line>The like to you kind Varro.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HORTENSIUS</speaker>
            <line>Lucius!</line>
            <line>What, do we meet together?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lucilius' Servant</speaker>
            <line>Ay, and I think</line>
            <line>One business does command us all; for mine Is money.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS</speaker>
            <line>So is theirs and ours.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter PHILOTUS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lucilius' Servant</speaker>
            <line>And Sir Philotus too!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PHILOTUS</speaker>
            <line>Good day at once.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lucilius' Servant</speaker>
            <line>Welcome, good brother.</line>
            <line>What do you think the hour?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PHILOTUS</speaker>
            <line>Labouring for nine.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lucilius' Servant</speaker>
            <line>So much?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PHILOTUS</speaker>
            <line>Is not my lord seen yet?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lucilius' Servant</speaker>
            <line>Not yet.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PHILOTUS</speaker>
            <line>I wonder on't; he was wont to shine at seven.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lucilius' Servant</speaker>
            <line>Ay, but the days are wax'd shorter with him:</line>
            <line>You must consider that a prodigal course</line>
            <line>Is like the sun's; but not, like his, recoverable.</line>
            <line>I fear 'tis deepest winter in Lord Timon's purse;</line>
            <line>That is one may reach deep enough, and yet</line>
            <line>Find little.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PHILOTUS</speaker>
            <line>I am of your fear for that.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS</speaker>
            <line>I'll show you how to observe a strange event.</line>
            <line>Your lord sends now for money.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HORTENSIUS</speaker>
            <line>Most true, he does.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS</speaker>
            <line>And he wears jewels now of Timon's gift,</line>
            <line>For which I wait for money.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HORTENSIUS</speaker>
            <line>It is against my heart.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lucilius' Servant</speaker>
            <line>Mark, how strange it shows,</line>
            <line>Timon in this should pay more than he owes:</line>
            <line>And e'en as if your lord should wear rich jewels,</line>
            <line>And send for money for 'em.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HORTENSIUS</speaker>
            <line>I'm weary of this charge, the gods can witness:</line>
            <line>I know my lord hath spent of Timon's wealth,</line>
            <line>And now ingratitude makes it worse than stealth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Varro's First Servant</speaker>
            <line>Yes, mine's three thousand crowns: what's yours?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lucilius' Servant</speaker>
            <line>Five thousand mine.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Varro's First Servant</speaker>
            <line>'Tis much deep: and it should seem by the sun,</line>
            <line>Your master's confidence was above mine;</line>
            <line>Else, surely, his had equall'd.</line>
            <line>Enter FLAMINIUS.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS</speaker>
            <line>One of Lord Timon's men.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lucilius' Servant</speaker>
            <line>Flaminius! Sir, a word: pray, is my lord ready to</line>
            <line>come forth?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLAMINIUS</speaker>
            <line>No, indeed, he is not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS</speaker>
            <line>We attend his lordship; pray, signify so much.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLAMINIUS</speaker>
            <line>I need not tell him that; he knows you are too diligent.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Enter FLAVIUS in a cloak, muffled</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lucilius' Servant</speaker>
            <line>Ha! is not that his steward muffled so?</line>
            <line>He goes away in a cloud: call him, call him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS</speaker>
            <line>Do you hear, sir?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Varro's Second Servant</speaker>
            <line>By your leave, sir,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLAVIUS</speaker>
            <line>What do ye ask of me, my friend?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS</speaker>
            <line>We wait for certain money here, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLAVIUS</speaker>
            <line>Ay,</line>
            <line>If money were as certain as your waiting,</line>
            <line>'Twere sure enough.</line>
            <line>Why then preferr'd you not your sums and bills,</line>
            <line>When your false masters eat of my lord's meat?</line>
            <line>Then they could smile and fawn upon his debts</line>
            <line>And take down the interest into their</line>
            <line>gluttonous maws.</line>
            <line>You do yourselves but wrong to stir me up;</line>
            <line>Let me pass quietly:</line>
            <line>Believe 't, my lord and I have made an end;</line>
            <line>I have no more to reckon, he to spend.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lucilius' Servant</speaker>
            <line>Ay, but this answer will not serve.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLAVIUS</speaker>
            <line>If 'twill not serve,'tis not so base as you;</line>
            <line>For you serve knaves.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Varro's First Servant</speaker>
            <line>How! what does his cashiered worship mutter?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Varro's Second Servant</speaker>
            <line>No matter what; he's poor, and that's revenge</line>
            <line>enough. Who can speak broader than he that has no</line>
            <line>house to put his head in? such may rail against</line>
            <line>great buildings.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter SERVILIUS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS</speaker>
            <line>O, here's Servilius; now we shall know some answer.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SERVILIUS</speaker>
            <line>If I might beseech you, gentlemen, to repair some</line>
            <line>other hour, I should derive much from't; for,</line>
            <line>take't of my soul, my lord leans wondrously to</line>
            <line>discontent: his comfortable temper has forsook him;</line>
            <line>he's much out of health, and keeps his chamber.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lucilius' Servant</speaker>
            <line>Many do keep their chambers are not sick:</line>
            <line>And, if it be so far beyond his health,</line>
            <line>Methinks he should the sooner pay his debts,</line>
            <line>And make a clear way to the gods.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SERVILIUS</speaker>
            <line>Good gods!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS</speaker>
            <line>We cannot take this for answer, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLAMINIUS</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Within</stagedir>  Servilius, help! My lord! my lord!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter TIMON, in a rage, FLAMINIUS following</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TIMON</speaker>
            <line>What, are my doors opposed against my passage?</line>
            <line>Have I been ever free, and must my house</line>
            <line>Be my retentive enemy, my gaol?</line>
            <line>The place which I have feasted, does it now,</line>
            <line>Like all mankind, show me an iron heart?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lucilius' Servant</speaker>
            <line>Put in now, Titus.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS</speaker>
            <line>My lord, here is my bill.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lucilius' Servant</speaker>
            <line>Here's mine.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HORTENSIUS</speaker>
            <line>And mine, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Both Varro's Servants</speaker>
            <line>And ours, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PHILOTUS</speaker>
            <line>All our bills.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TIMON</speaker>
            <line>Knock me down with 'em: cleave me to the girdle.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lucilius' Servant</speaker>
            <line>Alas, my lord,-</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TIMON</speaker>
            <line>Cut my heart in sums.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS</speaker>
            <line>Mine, fifty talents.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TIMON</speaker>
            <line>Tell out my blood.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lucilius' Servant</speaker>
            <line>Five thousand crowns, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TIMON</speaker>
            <line>Five thousand drops pays that.</line>
            <line>What yours?--and yours?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Varro's First Servant</speaker>
            <line>My lord,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Varro's Second Servant</speaker>
            <line>My lord,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TIMON</speaker>
            <line>Tear me, take me, and the gods fall upon you!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HORTENSIUS</speaker>
            <line>'Faith, I perceive our masters may throw their caps</line>
            <line>at their money: these debts may well be called</line>
            <line>desperate ones, for a madman owes 'em.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Re-enter TIMON and FLAVIUS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TIMON</speaker>
            <line>They have e'en put my breath from me, the slaves.</line>
            <line>Creditors? devils!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLAVIUS</speaker>
            <line>My dear lord,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TIMON</speaker>
            <line>What if it should be so?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLAVIUS</speaker>
            <line>My lord,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TIMON</speaker>
            <line>I'll have it so. My steward!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLAVIUS</speaker>
            <line>Here, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TIMON</speaker>
            <line>So fitly? Go, bid all my friends again,</line>
            <line>Lucius, Lucullus, and Sempronius:</line>
            <line>All, sirrah, all:</line>
            <line>I'll once more feast the rascals.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLAVIUS</speaker>
            <line>O my lord,</line>
            <line>You only speak from your distracted soul;</line>
            <line>There is not so much left, to furnish out</line>
            <line>A moderate table.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TIMON</speaker>
            <line>Be't not in thy care; go,</line>
            <line>I charge thee, invite them all: let in the tide</line>
            <line>Of knaves once more; my cook and I'll provide.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-5">
      <title>SCENE V.  The same. The senate-house. The Senate sitting.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>My lord, you have my voice to it; the fault's</line>
            <line>Bloody; 'tis necessary he should die:</line>
            <line>Nothing emboldens sin so much as mercy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Senator</speaker>
            <line>Most true; the law shall bruise him.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter ALCIBIADES, with Attendants</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALCIBIADES</speaker>
            <line>Honour, health, and compassion to the senate!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>Now, captain?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALCIBIADES</speaker>
            <line>I am an humble suitor to your virtues;</line>
            <line>For pity is the virtue of the law,</line>
            <line>And none but tyrants use it cruelly.</line>
            <line>It pleases time and fortune to lie heavy</line>
            <line>Upon a friend of mine, who, in hot blood,</line>
            <line>Hath stepp'd into the law, which is past depth</line>
            <line>To those that, without heed, do plunge into 't.</line>
            <line>He is a man, setting his fate aside,</line>
            <line>Of comely virtues:</line>
            <line>Nor did he soil the fact with cowardice--</line>
            <line>An honour in him which buys out his fault--</line>
            <line>But with a noble fury and fair spirit,</line>
            <line>Seeing his reputation touch'd to death,</line>
            <line>He did oppose his foe:</line>
            <line>And with such sober and unnoted passion</line>
            <line>He did behave his anger, ere 'twas spent,</line>
            <line>As if he had but proved an argument.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>You undergo too strict a paradox,</line>
            <line>Striving to make an ugly deed look fair:</line>
            <line>Your words have took such pains as if they labour'd</line>
            <line>To bring manslaughter into form and set quarrelling</line>
            <line>Upon the head of valour; which indeed</line>
            <line>Is valour misbegot and came into the world</line>
            <line>When sects and factions were newly born:</line>
            <line>He's truly valiant that can wisely suffer</line>
            <line>The worst that man can breathe, and make his wrongs</line>
            <line>His outsides, to wear them like his raiment,</line>
            <line>carelessly,</line>
            <line>And ne'er prefer his injuries to his heart,</line>
            <line>To bring it into danger.</line>
            <line>If wrongs be evils and enforce us kill,</line>
            <line>What folly 'tis to hazard life for ill!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALCIBIADES</speaker>
            <line>My lord,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>You cannot make gross sins look clear:</line>
            <line>To revenge is no valour, but to bear.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALCIBIADES</speaker>
            <line>My lords, then, under favour, pardon me,</line>
            <line>If I speak like a captain.</line>
            <line>Why do fond men expose themselves to battle,</line>
            <line>And not endure all threats? sleep upon't,</line>
            <line>And let the foes quietly cut their throats,</line>
            <line>Without repugnancy? If there be</line>
            <line>Such valour in the bearing, what make we</line>
            <line>Abroad? why then, women are more valiant</line>
            <line>That stay at home, if bearing carry it,</line>
            <line>And the ass more captain than the lion, the felon</line>
            <line>Loaden with irons wiser than the judge,</line>
            <line>If wisdom be in suffering. O my lords,</line>
            <line>As you are great, be pitifully good:</line>
            <line>Who cannot condemn rashness in cold blood?</line>
            <line>To kill, I grant, is sin's extremest gust;</line>
            <line>But, in defence, by mercy, 'tis most just.</line>
            <line>To be in anger is impiety;</line>
            <line>But who is man that is not angry?</line>
            <line>Weigh but the crime with this.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Senator</speaker>
            <line>You breathe in vain.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALCIBIADES</speaker>
            <line>In vain! his service done</line>
            <line>At Lacedaemon and Byzantium</line>
            <line>Were a sufficient briber for his life.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>What's that?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALCIBIADES</speaker>
            <line>I say, my lords, he has done fair service,</line>
            <line>And slain in fight many of your enemies:</line>
            <line>How full of valour did he bear himself</line>
            <line>In the last conflict, and made plenteous wounds!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Senator</speaker>
            <line>He has made too much plenty with 'em;</line>
            <line>He's a sworn rioter: he has a sin that often</line>
            <line>Drowns him, and takes his valour prisoner:</line>
            <line>If there were no foes, that were enough</line>
            <line>To overcome him: in that beastly fury</line>
            <line>He has been known to commit outrages,</line>
            <line>And cherish factions: 'tis inferr'd to us,</line>
            <line>His days are foul and his drink dangerous.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>He dies.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALCIBIADES</speaker>
            <line>Hard fate! he might have died in war.</line>
            <line>My lords, if not for any parts in him--</line>
            <line>Though his right arm might purchase his own time</line>
            <line>And be in debt to none--yet, more to move you,</line>
            <line>Take my deserts to his, and join 'em both:</line>
            <line>And, for I know your reverend ages love</line>
            <line>Security, I'll pawn my victories, all</line>
            <line>My honours to you, upon his good returns.</line>
            <line>If by this crime he owes the law his life,</line>
            <line>Why, let the war receive 't in valiant gore</line>
            <line>For law is strict, and war is nothing more.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>We are for law: he dies; urge it no more,</line>
            <line>On height of our displeasure: friend or brother,</line>
            <line>He forfeits his own blood that spills another.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALCIBIADES</speaker>
            <line>Must it be so? it must not be. My lords,</line>
            <line>I do beseech you, know me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Senator</speaker>
            <line>How!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALCIBIADES</speaker>
            <line>Call me to your remembrances.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Senator</speaker>
            <line>What!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALCIBIADES</speaker>
            <line>I cannot think but your age has forgot me;</line>
            <line>It could not else be, I should prove so base,</line>
            <line>To sue, and be denied such common grace:</line>
            <line>My wounds ache at you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>Do you dare our anger?</line>
            <line>'Tis in few words, but spacious in effect;</line>
            <line>We banish thee for ever.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALCIBIADES</speaker>
            <line>Banish me!</line>
            <line>Banish your dotage; banish usury,</line>
            <line>That makes the senate ugly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>If, after two days' shine, Athens contain thee,</line>
            <line>Attend our weightier judgment. And, not to swell</line>
            <line>our spirit,</line>
            <line>He shall be executed presently.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt Senators</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALCIBIADES</speaker>
            <line>Now the gods keep you old enough; that you may live</line>
            <line>Only in bone, that none may look on you!</line>
            <line>I'm worse than mad: I have kept back their foes,</line>
            <line>While they have told their money and let out</line>
            <line>Their coin upon large interest, I myself</line>
            <line>Rich only in large hurts. All those for this?</line>
            <line>Is this the balsam that the usuring senate</line>
            <line>Pours into captains' wounds? Banishment!</line>
            <line>It comes not ill; I hate not to be banish'd;</line>
            <line>It is a cause worthy my spleen and fury,</line>
            <line>That I may strike at Athens. I'll cheer up</line>
            <line>My discontented troops, and lay for hearts.</line>
            <line>'Tis honour with most lands to be at odds;</line>
            <line>Soldiers should brook as little wrongs as gods.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-6">
      <title>SCENE VI.  The same. A banqueting-room in Timon's house.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Music. Tables set out: Servants attending.
Enter divers Lords, Senators and others, at
several doors</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>The good time of day to you, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>I also wish it to you. I think this honourable lord</line>
            <line>did but try us this other day.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>Upon that were my thoughts tiring, when we</line>
            <line>encountered: I hope it is not so low with him as</line>
            <line>he made it seem in the trial of his several friends.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>It should not be, by the persuasion of his new feasting.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>I should think so: he hath sent me an earnest</line>
            <line>inviting, which many my near occasions did urge me</line>
            <line>to put off; but he hath conjured me beyond them, and</line>
            <line>I must needs appear.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>In like manner was I in debt to my importunate</line>
            <line>business, but he would not hear my excuse. I am</line>
            <line>sorry, when he sent to borrow of me, that my</line>
            <line>provision was out.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>I am sick of that grief too, as I understand how all</line>
            <line>things go.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>Every man here's so. What would he have borrowed of</line>
            <line>you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>A thousand pieces.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>A thousand pieces!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>What of you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>He sent to me, sir,--Here he comes.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter TIMON and Attendants</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TIMON</speaker>
            <line>With all my heart, gentlemen both; and how fare you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>Ever at the best, hearing well of your lordship.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>The swallow follows not summer more willing than we</line>
            <line>your lordship.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TIMON</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  Nor more willingly leaves winter; such</line>
            <line>summer-birds are men. Gentlemen, our dinner will not</line>
            <line>recompense this long stay: feast your ears with the</line>
            <line>music awhile, if they will fare so harshly o' the</line>
            <line>trumpet's sound; we shall to 't presently.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>I hope it remains not unkindly with your lordship</line>
            <line>that I returned you an empty messenger.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TIMON</speaker>
            <line>O, sir, let it not trouble you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>My noble lord,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TIMON</speaker>
            <line>Ah, my good friend, what cheer?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>My most honourable lord, I am e'en sick of shame,</line>
            <line>that, when your lordship this other day sent to me,</line>
            <line>I was so unfortunate a beggar.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TIMON</speaker>
            <line>Think not on 't, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>If you had sent but two hours before,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TIMON</speaker>
            <line>Let it not cumber your better remembrance.</line>
            <stagedir>The banquet brought in</stagedir>
            <line>Come, bring in all together.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>All covered dishes!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>Royal cheer, I warrant you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Lord</speaker>
            <line>Doubt not that, if money and the season can yield</line>
            <line>it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>How do you? What's the news?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Lord</speaker>
            <line>Alcibiades is banished: hear you of it?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>Alcibiades banished!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Lord</speaker>
            <line>'Tis so, be sure of it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>How! how!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>I pray you, upon what?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TIMON</speaker>
            <line>My worthy friends, will you draw near?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Lord</speaker>
            <line>I'll tell you more anon. Here's a noble feast toward.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>This is the old man still.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Lord</speaker>
            <line>Will 't hold? will 't hold?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>It does: but time will--and so--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Lord</speaker>
            <line>I do conceive.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TIMON</speaker>
            <line>Each man to his stool, with that spur as he would to</line>
            <line>the lip of his mistress: your diet shall be in all</line>
            <line>places alike. Make not a city feast of it, to let</line>
            <line>the meat cool ere we can agree upon the first place:</line>
            <line>sit, sit. The gods require our thanks.</line>
            <line>You great benefactors, sprinkle our society with</line>
            <line>thankfulness. For your own gifts, make yourselves</line>
            <line>praised: but reserve still to give, lest your</line>
            <line>deities be despised. Lend to each man enough, that</line>
            <line>one need not lend to another; for, were your</line>
            <line>godheads to borrow of men, men would forsake the</line>
            <line>gods. Make the meat be beloved more than the man</line>
            <line>that gives it. Let no assembly of twenty be without</line>
            <line>a score of villains: if there sit twelve women at</line>
            <line>the table, let a dozen of them be--as they are. The</line>
            <line>rest of your fees, O gods--the senators of Athens,</line>
            <line>together with the common lag of people--what is</line>
            <line>amiss in them, you gods, make suitable for</line>
            <line>destruction. For these my present friends, as they</line>
            <line>are to me nothing, so in nothing bless them, and to</line>
            <line>nothing are they welcome.</line>
            <line>Uncover, dogs, and lap.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>The dishes are uncovered and seen to be full of
warm water</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Some Speak</speaker>
            <line>What does his lordship mean?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Some Others</speaker>
            <line>I know not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TIMON</speaker>
            <line>May you a better feast never behold,</line>
            <line>You knot of mouth-friends I smoke and lukewarm water</line>
            <line>Is your perfection. This is Timon's last;</line>
            <line>Who, stuck and spangled with your flatteries,</line>
            <line>Washes it off, and sprinkles in your faces</line>
            <line>Your reeking villany.</line>
            <stagedir>Throwing the water in their faces</stagedir>
            <line>Live loathed and long,</line>
            <line>Most smiling, smooth, detested parasites,</line>
            <line>Courteous destroyers, affable wolves, meek bears,</line>
            <line>You fools of fortune, trencher-friends, time's flies,</line>
            <line>Cap and knee slaves, vapours, and minute-jacks!</line>
            <line>Of man and beast the infinite malady</line>
            <line>Crust you quite o'er! What, dost thou go?</line>
            <line>Soft! take thy physic first--thou too--and thou;--</line>
            <line>Stay, I will lend thee money, borrow none.</line>
            <stagedir>Throws the dishes at them, and drives them out</stagedir>
            <line>What, all in motion? Henceforth be no feast,</line>
            <line>Whereat a villain's not a welcome guest.</line>
            <line>Burn, house! sink, Athens! henceforth hated be</line>
            <line>Of Timon man and all humanity!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Re-enter the Lords, Senators, &amp;c</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>How now, my lords!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>Know you the quality of Lord Timon's fury?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Lord</speaker>
            <line>Push! did you see my cap?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fourth Lord</speaker>
            <line>I have lost my gown.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>He's but a mad lord, and nought but humour sways him.</line>
            <line>He gave me a jewel th' other day, and now he has</line>
            <line>beat it out of my hat: did you see my jewel?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Lord</speaker>
            <line>Did you see my cap?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>Here 'tis.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fourth Lord</speaker>
            <line>Here lies my gown.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>Let's make no stay.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>Lord Timon's mad.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Lord</speaker>
            <line>I feel 't upon my bones.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fourth Lord</speaker>
            <line>One day he gives us diamonds, next day stones.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>