<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net/doctypes/dita/shakespear/dtd/act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-5">
   <title>ACT V</title>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  KING JOHN'S palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter KING JOHN, CARDINAL PANDULPH, and Attendants</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>Thus have I yielded up into your hand</line>
            <line>The circle of my glory.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Giving the crown</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL PANDULPH</speaker>
            <line>Take again</line>
            <line>From this my hand, as holding of the pope</line>
            <line>Your sovereign greatness and authority.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>Now keep your holy word: go meet the French,</line>
            <line>And from his holiness use all your power</line>
            <line>To stop their marches 'fore we are inflamed.</line>
            <line>Our discontented counties do revolt;</line>
            <line>Our people quarrel with obedience,</line>
            <line>Swearing allegiance and the love of soul</line>
            <line>To stranger blood, to foreign royalty.</line>
            <line>This inundation of mistemper'd humour</line>
            <line>Rests by you only to be qualified:</line>
            <line>Then pause not; for the present time's so sick,</line>
            <line>That present medicine must be minister'd,</line>
            <line>Or overthrow incurable ensues.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL PANDULPH</speaker>
            <line>It was my breath that blew this tempest up,</line>
            <line>Upon your stubborn usage of the pope;</line>
            <line>But since you are a gentle convertite,</line>
            <line>My tongue shall hush again this storm of war</line>
            <line>And make fair weather in your blustering land.</line>
            <line>On this Ascension-day, remember well,</line>
            <line>Upon your oath of service to the pope,</line>
            <line>Go I to make the French lay down their arms.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>Is this Ascension-day? Did not the prophet</line>
            <line>Say that before Ascension-day at noon</line>
            <line>My crown I should give off? Even so I have:</line>
            <line>I did suppose it should be on constraint:</line>
            <line>But, heaven be thank'd, it is but voluntary.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter the BASTARD</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>All Kent hath yielded; nothing there holds out</line>
            <line>But Dover castle: London hath received,</line>
            <line>Like a kind host, the Dauphin and his powers:</line>
            <line>Your nobles will not hear you, but are gone</line>
            <line>To offer service to your enemy,</line>
            <line>And wild amazement hurries up and down</line>
            <line>The little number of your doubtful friends.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>Would not my lords return to me again,</line>
            <line>After they heard young Arthur was alive?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>They found him dead and cast into the streets,</line>
            <line>An empty casket, where the jewel of life</line>
            <line>By some damn'd hand was robb'd and ta'en away.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>That villain Hubert told me he did live.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>So, on my soul, he did, for aught he knew.</line>
            <line>But wherefore do you droop? why look you sad?</line>
            <line>Be great in act, as you have been in thought;</line>
            <line>Let not the world see fear and sad distrust</line>
            <line>Govern the motion of a kingly eye:</line>
            <line>Be stirring as the time; be fire with fire;</line>
            <line>Threaten the threatener and outface the brow</line>
            <line>Of bragging horror: so shall inferior eyes,</line>
            <line>That borrow their behaviors from the great,</line>
            <line>Grow great by your example and put on</line>
            <line>The dauntless spirit of resolution.</line>
            <line>Away, and glister like the god of war,</line>
            <line>When he intendeth to become the field:</line>
            <line>Show boldness and aspiring confidence.</line>
            <line>What, shall they seek the lion in his den,</line>
            <line>And fright him there? and make him tremble there?</line>
            <line>O, let it not be said: forage, and run</line>
            <line>To meet displeasure farther from the doors,</line>
            <line>And grapple with him ere he comes so nigh.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>The legate of the pope hath been with me,</line>
            <line>And I have made a happy peace with him;</line>
            <line>And he hath promised to dismiss the powers</line>
            <line>Led by the Dauphin.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>O inglorious league!</line>
            <line>Shall we, upon the footing of our land,</line>
            <line>Send fair-play orders and make compromise,</line>
            <line>Insinuation, parley and base truce</line>
            <line>To arms invasive? shall a beardless boy,</line>
            <line>A cocker'd silken wanton, brave our fields,</line>
            <line>And flesh his spirit in a warlike soil,</line>
            <line>Mocking the air with colours idly spread,</line>
            <line>And find no cheque? Let us, my liege, to arms:</line>
            <line>Perchance the cardinal cannot make your peace;</line>
            <line>Or if he do, let it at least be said</line>
            <line>They saw we had a purpose of defence.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>Have thou the ordering of this present time.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>Away, then, with good courage! yet, I know,</line>
            <line>Our party may well meet a prouder foe.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  LEWIS's camp at St. Edmundsbury.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter, in arms, LEWIS, SALISBURY, MELUN, PEMBROKE,
BIGOT, and Soldiers</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEWIS</speaker>
            <line>My Lord Melun, let this be copied out,</line>
            <line>And keep it safe for our remembrance:</line>
            <line>Return the precedent to these lords again;</line>
            <line>That, having our fair order written down,</line>
            <line>Both they and we, perusing o'er these notes,</line>
            <line>May know wherefore we took the sacrament</line>
            <line>And keep our faiths firm and inviolable.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALISBURY</speaker>
            <line>Upon our sides it never shall be broken.</line>
            <line>And, noble Dauphin, albeit we swear</line>
            <line>A voluntary zeal and an unurged faith</line>
            <line>To your proceedings; yet believe me, prince,</line>
            <line>I am not glad that such a sore of time</line>
            <line>Should seek a plaster by contemn'd revolt,</line>
            <line>And heal the inveterate canker of one wound</line>
            <line>By making many. O, it grieves my soul,</line>
            <line>That I must draw this metal from my side</line>
            <line>To be a widow-maker! O, and there</line>
            <line>Where honourable rescue and defence</line>
            <line>Cries out upon the name of Salisbury!</line>
            <line>But such is the infection of the time,</line>
            <line>That, for the health and physic of our right,</line>
            <line>We cannot deal but with the very hand</line>
            <line>Of stern injustice and confused wrong.</line>
            <line>And is't not pity, O my grieved friends,</line>
            <line>That we, the sons and children of this isle,</line>
            <line>Were born to see so sad an hour as this;</line>
            <line>Wherein we step after a stranger march</line>
            <line>Upon her gentle bosom, and fill up</line>
            <line>Her enemies' ranks,--I must withdraw and weep</line>
            <line>Upon the spot of this enforced cause,--</line>
            <line>To grace the gentry of a land remote,</line>
            <line>And follow unacquainted colours here?</line>
            <line>What, here? O nation, that thou couldst remove!</line>
            <line>That Neptune's arms, who clippeth thee about,</line>
            <line>Would bear thee from the knowledge of thyself,</line>
            <line>And grapple thee unto a pagan shore;</line>
            <line>Where these two Christian armies might combine</line>
            <line>The blood of malice in a vein of league,</line>
            <line>And not to spend it so unneighbourly!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEWIS</speaker>
            <line>A noble temper dost thou show in this;</line>
            <line>And great affections wrestling in thy bosom</line>
            <line>Doth make an earthquake of nobility.</line>
            <line>O, what a noble combat hast thou fought</line>
            <line>Between compulsion and a brave respect!</line>
            <line>Let me wipe off this honourable dew,</line>
            <line>That silverly doth progress on thy cheeks:</line>
            <line>My heart hath melted at a lady's tears,</line>
            <line>Being an ordinary inundation;</line>
            <line>But this effusion of such manly drops,</line>
            <line>This shower, blown up by tempest of the soul,</line>
            <line>Startles mine eyes, and makes me more amazed</line>
            <line>Than had I seen the vaulty top of heaven</line>
            <line>Figured quite o'er with burning meteors.</line>
            <line>Lift up thy brow, renowned Salisbury,</line>
            <line>And with a great heart heave away the storm:</line>
            <line>Commend these waters to those baby eyes</line>
            <line>That never saw the giant world enraged;</line>
            <line>Nor met with fortune other than at feasts,</line>
            <line>Full of warm blood, of mirth, of gossiping.</line>
            <line>Come, come; for thou shalt thrust thy hand as deep</line>
            <line>Into the purse of rich prosperity</line>
            <line>As Lewis himself: so, nobles, shall you all,</line>
            <line>That knit your sinews to the strength of mine.</line>
            <line>And even there, methinks, an angel spake:</line>
            <stagedir>Enter CARDINAL PANDULPH</stagedir>
            <line>Look, where the holy legate comes apace,</line>
            <line>To give us warrant from the hand of heaven</line>
            <line>And on our actions set the name of right</line>
            <line>With holy breath.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL PANDULPH</speaker>
            <line>Hail, noble prince of France!</line>
            <line>The next is this, King John hath reconciled</line>
            <line>Himself to Rome; his spirit is come in,</line>
            <line>That so stood out against the holy church,</line>
            <line>The great metropolis and see of Rome:</line>
            <line>Therefore thy threatening colours now wind up;</line>
            <line>And tame the savage spirit of wild war,</line>
            <line>That like a lion foster'd up at hand,</line>
            <line>It may lie gently at the foot of peace,</line>
            <line>And be no further harmful than in show.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEWIS</speaker>
            <line>Your grace shall pardon me, I will not back:</line>
            <line>I am too high-born to be propertied,</line>
            <line>To be a secondary at control,</line>
            <line>Or useful serving-man and instrument,</line>
            <line>To any sovereign state throughout the world.</line>
            <line>Your breath first kindled the dead coal of wars</line>
            <line>Between this chastised kingdom and myself,</line>
            <line>And brought in matter that should feed this fire;</line>
            <line>And now 'tis far too huge to be blown out</line>
            <line>With that same weak wind which enkindled it.</line>
            <line>You taught me how to know the face of right,</line>
            <line>Acquainted me with interest to this land,</line>
            <line>Yea, thrust this enterprise into my heart;</line>
            <line>And come ye now to tell me John hath made</line>
            <line>His peace with Rome? What is that peace to me?</line>
            <line>I, by the honour of my marriage-bed,</line>
            <line>After young Arthur, claim this land for mine;</line>
            <line>And, now it is half-conquer'd, must I back</line>
            <line>Because that John hath made his peace with Rome?</line>
            <line>Am I Rome's slave? What penny hath Rome borne,</line>
            <line>What men provided, what munition sent,</line>
            <line>To underprop this action? Is't not I</line>
            <line>That undergo this charge? who else but I,</line>
            <line>And such as to my claim are liable,</line>
            <line>Sweat in this business and maintain this war?</line>
            <line>Have I not heard these islanders shout out</line>
            <line>'Vive le roi!' as I have bank'd their towns?</line>
            <line>Have I not here the best cards for the game,</line>
            <line>To win this easy match play'd for a crown?</line>
            <line>And shall I now give o'er the yielded set?</line>
            <line>No, no, on my soul, it never shall be said.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL PANDULPH</speaker>
            <line>You look but on the outside of this work.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEWIS</speaker>
            <line>Outside or inside, I will not return</line>
            <line>Till my attempt so much be glorified</line>
            <line>As to my ample hope was promised</line>
            <line>Before I drew this gallant head of war,</line>
            <line>And cull'd these fiery spirits from the world,</line>
            <line>To outlook conquest and to win renown</line>
            <line>Even in the jaws of danger and of death.</line>
            <stagedir>Trumpet sounds</stagedir>
            <line>What lusty trumpet thus doth summon us?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter the BASTARD, attended</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>According to the fair play of the world,</line>
            <line>Let me have audience; I am sent to speak:</line>
            <line>My holy lord of Milan, from the king</line>
            <line>I come, to learn how you have dealt for him;</line>
            <line>And, as you answer, I do know the scope</line>
            <line>And warrant limited unto my tongue.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL PANDULPH</speaker>
            <line>The Dauphin is too wilful-opposite,</line>
            <line>And will not temporize with my entreaties;</line>
            <line>He flatly says he'll not lay down his arms.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>By all the blood that ever fury breathed,</line>
            <line>The youth says well. Now hear our English king;</line>
            <line>For thus his royalty doth speak in me.</line>
            <line>He is prepared, and reason too he should:</line>
            <line>This apish and unmannerly approach,</line>
            <line>This harness'd masque and unadvised revel,</line>
            <line>This unhair'd sauciness and boyish troops,</line>
            <line>The king doth smile at; and is well prepared</line>
            <line>To whip this dwarfish war, these pigmy arms,</line>
            <line>From out the circle of his territories.</line>
            <line>That hand which had the strength, even at your door,</line>
            <line>To cudgel you and make you take the hatch,</line>
            <line>To dive like buckets in concealed wells,</line>
            <line>To crouch in litter of your stable planks,</line>
            <line>To lie like pawns lock'd up in chests and trunks,</line>
            <line>To hug with swine, to seek sweet safety out</line>
            <line>In vaults and prisons, and to thrill and shake</line>
            <line>Even at the crying of your nation's crow,</line>
            <line>Thinking his voice an armed Englishman;</line>
            <line>Shall that victorious hand be feebled here,</line>
            <line>That in your chambers gave you chastisement?</line>
            <line>No: know the gallant monarch is in arms</line>
            <line>And like an eagle o'er his aery towers,</line>
            <line>To souse annoyance that comes near his nest.</line>
            <line>And you degenerate, you ingrate revolts,</line>
            <line>You bloody Neroes, ripping up the womb</line>
            <line>Of your dear mother England, blush for shame;</line>
            <line>For your own ladies and pale-visaged maids</line>
            <line>Like Amazons come tripping after drums,</line>
            <line>Their thimbles into armed gauntlets change,</line>
            <line>Their needles to lances, and their gentle hearts</line>
            <line>To fierce and bloody inclination.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEWIS</speaker>
            <line>There end thy brave, and turn thy face in peace;</line>
            <line>We grant thou canst outscold us: fare thee well;</line>
            <line>We hold our time too precious to be spent</line>
            <line>With such a brabbler.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL PANDULPH</speaker>
            <line>Give me leave to speak.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>No, I will speak.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEWIS</speaker>
            <line>We will attend to neither.</line>
            <line>Strike up the drums; and let the tongue of war</line>
            <line>Plead for our interest and our being here.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>Indeed your drums, being beaten, will cry out;</line>
            <line>And so shall you, being beaten: do but start</line>
            <line>An echo with the clamour of thy drum,</line>
            <line>And even at hand a drum is ready braced</line>
            <line>That shall reverberate all as loud as thine;</line>
            <line>Sound but another, and another shall</line>
            <line>As loud as thine rattle the welkin's ear</line>
            <line>And mock the deep-mouth'd thunder: for at hand,</line>
            <line>Not trusting to this halting legate here,</line>
            <line>Whom he hath used rather for sport than need</line>
            <line>Is warlike John; and in his forehead sits</line>
            <line>A bare-ribb'd death, whose office is this day</line>
            <line>To feast upon whole thousands of the French.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEWIS</speaker>
            <line>Strike up our drums, to find this danger out.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>And thou shalt find it, Dauphin, do not doubt.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  The field of battle.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Alarums. Enter KING JOHN and HUBERT</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>How goes the day with us? O, tell me, Hubert.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HUBERT</speaker>
            <line>Badly, I fear. How fares your majesty?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>This fever, that hath troubled me so long,</line>
            <line>Lies heavy on me; O, my heart is sick!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter a Messenger</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>My lord, your valiant kinsman, Faulconbridge,</line>
            <line>Desires your majesty to leave the field</line>
            <line>And send him word by me which way you go.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>Tell him, toward Swinstead, to the abbey there.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>Be of good comfort; for the great supply</line>
            <line>That was expected by the Dauphin here,</line>
            <line>Are wreck'd three nights ago on Goodwin Sands.</line>
            <line>This news was brought to Richard but even now:</line>
            <line>The French fight coldly, and retire themselves.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>Ay me! this tyrant fever burns me up,</line>
            <line>And will not let me welcome this good news.</line>
            <line>Set on toward Swinstead: to my litter straight;</line>
            <line>Weakness possesseth me, and I am faint.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-4">
      <title>SCENE IV.  Another part of the field.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter SALISBURY, PEMBROKE, and BIGOT</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALISBURY</speaker>
            <line>I did not think the king so stored with friends.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PEMBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Up once again; put spirit in the French:</line>
            <line>If they miscarry, we miscarry too.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALISBURY</speaker>
            <line>That misbegotten devil, Faulconbridge,</line>
            <line>In spite of spite, alone upholds the day.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PEMBROKE</speaker>
            <line>They say King John sore sick hath left the field.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter MELUN, wounded</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MELUN</speaker>
            <line>Lead me to the revolts of England here.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALISBURY</speaker>
            <line>When we were happy we had other names.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PEMBROKE</speaker>
            <line>It is the Count Melun.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALISBURY</speaker>
            <line>Wounded to death.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MELUN</speaker>
            <line>Fly, noble English, you are bought and sold;</line>
            <line>Unthread the rude eye of rebellion</line>
            <line>And welcome home again discarded faith.</line>
            <line>Seek out King John and fall before his feet;</line>
            <line>For if the French be lords of this loud day,</line>
            <line>He means to recompense the pains you take</line>
            <line>By cutting off your heads: thus hath he sworn</line>
            <line>And I with him, and many moe with me,</line>
            <line>Upon the altar at Saint Edmundsbury;</line>
            <line>Even on that altar where we swore to you</line>
            <line>Dear amity and everlasting love.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALISBURY</speaker>
            <line>May this be possible? may this be true?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MELUN</speaker>
            <line>Have I not hideous death within my view,</line>
            <line>Retaining but a quantity of life,</line>
            <line>Which bleeds away, even as a form of wax</line>
            <line>Resolveth from his figure 'gainst the fire?</line>
            <line>What in the world should make me now deceive,</line>
            <line>Since I must lose the use of all deceit?</line>
            <line>Why should I then be false, since it is true</line>
            <line>That I must die here and live hence by truth?</line>
            <line>I say again, if Lewis do win the day,</line>
            <line>He is forsworn, if e'er those eyes of yours</line>
            <line>Behold another day break in the east:</line>
            <line>But even this night, whose black contagious breath</line>
            <line>Already smokes about the burning crest</line>
            <line>Of the old, feeble and day-wearied sun,</line>
            <line>Even this ill night, your breathing shall expire,</line>
            <line>Paying the fine of rated treachery</line>
            <line>Even with a treacherous fine of all your lives,</line>
            <line>If Lewis by your assistance win the day.</line>
            <line>Commend me to one Hubert with your king:</line>
            <line>The love of him, and this respect besides,</line>
            <line>For that my grandsire was an Englishman,</line>
            <line>Awakes my conscience to confess all this.</line>
            <line>In lieu whereof, I pray you, bear me hence</line>
            <line>From forth the noise and rumour of the field,</line>
            <line>Where I may think the remnant of my thoughts</line>
            <line>In peace, and part this body and my soul</line>
            <line>With contemplation and devout desires.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALISBURY</speaker>
            <line>We do believe thee: and beshrew my soul</line>
            <line>But I do love the favour and the form</line>
            <line>Of this most fair occasion, by the which</line>
            <line>We will untread the steps of damned flight,</line>
            <line>And like a bated and retired flood,</line>
            <line>Leaving our rankness and irregular course,</line>
            <line>Stoop low within those bounds we have o'erlook'd</line>
            <line>And cabby run on in obedience</line>
            <line>Even to our ocean, to our great King John.</line>
            <line>My arm shall give thee help to bear thee hence;</line>
            <line>For I do see the cruel pangs of death</line>
            <line>Right in thine eye. Away, my friends! New flight;</line>
            <line>And happy newness, that intends old right.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt, leading off MELUN</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-5">
      <title>SCENE V.  The French camp.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter LEWIS and his train</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEWIS</speaker>
            <line>The sun of heaven methought was loath to set,</line>
            <line>But stay'd and made the western welkin blush,</line>
            <line>When English measure backward their own ground</line>
            <line>In faint retire. O, bravely came we off,</line>
            <line>When with a volley of our needless shot,</line>
            <line>After such bloody toil, we bid good night;</line>
            <line>And wound our tattering colours clearly up,</line>
            <line>Last in the field, and almost lords of it!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter a Messenger</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>Where is my prince, the Dauphin?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEWIS</speaker>
            <line>Here: what news?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>The Count Melun is slain; the English lords</line>
            <line>By his persuasion are again fall'n off,</line>
            <line>And your supply, which you have wish'd so long,</line>
            <line>Are cast away and sunk on Goodwin Sands.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEWIS</speaker>
            <line>Ah, foul shrewd news! beshrew thy very heart!</line>
            <line>I did not think to be so sad to-night</line>
            <line>As this hath made me. Who was he that said</line>
            <line>King John did fly an hour or two before</line>
            <line>The stumbling night did part our weary powers?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>Whoever spoke it, it is true, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEWIS</speaker>
            <line>Well; keep good quarter and good care to-night:</line>
            <line>The day shall not be up so soon as I,</line>
            <line>To try the fair adventure of to-morrow.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-6">
      <title>SCENE VI.  An open place in the neighbourhood of Swinstead Abbey.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter the BASTARD and HUBERT, severally</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HUBERT</speaker>
            <line>Who's there? speak, ho! speak quickly, or I shoot.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>A friend. What art thou?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HUBERT</speaker>
            <line>Of the part of England.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>Whither dost thou go?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HUBERT</speaker>
            <line>What's that to thee? why may not I demand</line>
            <line>Of thine affairs, as well as thou of mine?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>Hubert, I think?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HUBERT</speaker>
            <line>Thou hast a perfect thought:</line>
            <line>I will upon all hazards well believe</line>
            <line>Thou art my friend, that know'st my tongue so well.</line>
            <line>Who art thou?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>Who thou wilt: and if thou please,</line>
            <line>Thou mayst befriend me so much as to think</line>
            <line>I come one way of the Plantagenets.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HUBERT</speaker>
            <line>Unkind remembrance! thou and eyeless night</line>
            <line>Have done me shame: brave soldier, pardon me,</line>
            <line>That any accent breaking from thy tongue</line>
            <line>Should 'scape the true acquaintance of mine ear.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>Come, come; sans compliment, what news abroad?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HUBERT</speaker>
            <line>Why, here walk I in the black brow of night,</line>
            <line>To find you out.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>Brief, then; and what's the news?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HUBERT</speaker>
            <line>O, my sweet sir, news fitting to the night,</line>
            <line>Black, fearful, comfortless and horrible.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>Show me the very wound of this ill news:</line>
            <line>I am no woman, I'll not swoon at it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HUBERT</speaker>
            <line>The king, I fear, is poison'd by a monk:</line>
            <line>I left him almost speechless; and broke out</line>
            <line>To acquaint you with this evil, that you might</line>
            <line>The better arm you to the sudden time,</line>
            <line>Than if you had at leisure known of this.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>How did he take it? who did taste to him?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HUBERT</speaker>
            <line>A monk, I tell you; a resolved villain,</line>
            <line>Whose bowels suddenly burst out: the king</line>
            <line>Yet speaks and peradventure may recover.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>Who didst thou leave to tend his majesty?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HUBERT</speaker>
            <line>Why, know you not? the lords are all come back,</line>
            <line>And brought Prince Henry in their company;</line>
            <line>At whose request the king hath pardon'd them,</line>
            <line>And they are all about his majesty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>Withhold thine indignation, mighty heaven,</line>
            <line>And tempt us not to bear above our power!</line>
            <line>I'll tell tree, Hubert, half my power this night,</line>
            <line>Passing these flats, are taken by the tide;</line>
            <line>These Lincoln Washes have devoured them;</line>
            <line>Myself, well mounted, hardly have escaped.</line>
            <line>Away before: conduct me to the king;</line>
            <line>I doubt he will be dead or ere I come.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-7">
      <title>SCENE VII.  The orchard in Swinstead Abbey.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter PRINCE HENRY, SALISBURY, and BIGOT</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>It is too late: the life of all his blood</line>
            <line>Is touch'd corruptibly, and his pure brain,</line>
            <line>Which some suppose the soul's frail dwelling-house,</line>
            <line>Doth by the idle comments that it makes</line>
            <line>Foretell the ending of mortality.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter PEMBROKE</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PEMBROKE</speaker>
            <line>His highness yet doth speak, and holds belief</line>
            <line>That, being brought into the open air,</line>
            <line>It would allay the burning quality</line>
            <line>Of that fell poison which assaileth him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>Let him be brought into the orchard here.</line>
            <line>Doth he still rage?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit BIGOT</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PEMBROKE</speaker>
            <line>He is more patient</line>
            <line>Than when you left him; even now he sung.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>O vanity of sickness! fierce extremes</line>
            <line>In their continuance will not feel themselves.</line>
            <line>Death, having prey'd upon the outward parts,</line>
            <line>Leaves them invisible, and his siege is now</line>
            <line>Against the mind, the which he pricks and wounds</line>
            <line>With many legions of strange fantasies,</line>
            <line>Which, in their throng and press to that last hold,</line>
            <line>Confound themselves. 'Tis strange that death</line>
            <line>should sing.</line>
            <line>I am the cygnet to this pale faint swan,</line>
            <line>Who chants a doleful hymn to his own death,</line>
            <line>And from the organ-pipe of frailty sings</line>
            <line>His soul and body to their lasting rest.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALISBURY</speaker>
            <line>Be of good comfort, prince; for you are born</line>
            <line>To set a form upon that indigest</line>
            <line>Which he hath left so shapeless and so rude.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter Attendants, and BIGOT, carrying KING JOHN in a chair</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>Ay, marry, now my soul hath elbow-room;</line>
            <line>It would not out at windows nor at doors.</line>
            <line>There is so hot a summer in my bosom,</line>
            <line>That all my bowels crumble up to dust:</line>
            <line>I am a scribbled form, drawn with a pen</line>
            <line>Upon a parchment, and against this fire</line>
            <line>Do I shrink up.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>How fares your majesty?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>Poison'd,--ill fare--dead, forsook, cast off:</line>
            <line>And none of you will bid the winter come</line>
            <line>To thrust his icy fingers in my maw,</line>
            <line>Nor let my kingdom's rivers take their course</line>
            <line>Through my burn'd bosom, nor entreat the north</line>
            <line>To make his bleak winds kiss my parched lips</line>
            <line>And comfort me with cold. I do not ask you much,</line>
            <line>I beg cold comfort; and you are so strait</line>
            <line>And so ingrateful, you deny me that.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>O that there were some virtue in my tears,</line>
            <line>That might relieve you!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>The salt in them is hot.</line>
            <line>Within me is a hell; and there the poison</line>
            <line>Is as a fiend confined to tyrannize</line>
            <line>On unreprievable condemned blood.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter the BASTARD</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>O, I am scalded with my violent motion,</line>
            <line>And spleen of speed to see your majesty!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>O cousin, thou art come to set mine eye:</line>
            <line>The tackle of my heart is crack'd and burn'd,</line>
            <line>And all the shrouds wherewith my life should sail</line>
            <line>Are turned to one thread, one little hair:</line>
            <line>My heart hath one poor string to stay it by,</line>
            <line>Which holds but till thy news be uttered;</line>
            <line>And then all this thou seest is but a clod</line>
            <line>And module of confounded royalty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>The Dauphin is preparing hitherward,</line>
            <line>Where heaven He knows how we shall answer him;</line>
            <line>For in a night the best part of my power,</line>
            <line>As I upon advantage did remove,</line>
            <line>Were in the Washes all unwarily</line>
            <line>Devoured by the unexpected flood.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>KING JOHN dies</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALISBURY</speaker>
            <line>You breathe these dead news in as dead an ear.</line>
            <line>My liege! my lord! but now a king, now thus.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>Even so must I run on, and even so stop.</line>
            <line>What surety of the world, what hope, what stay,</line>
            <line>When this was now a king, and now is clay?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>Art thou gone so? I do but stay behind</line>
            <line>To do the office for thee of revenge,</line>
            <line>And then my soul shall wait on thee to heaven,</line>
            <line>As it on earth hath been thy servant still.</line>
            <line>Now, now, you stars that move in your right spheres,</line>
            <line>Where be your powers? show now your mended faiths,</line>
            <line>And instantly return with me again,</line>
            <line>To push destruction and perpetual shame</line>
            <line>Out of the weak door of our fainting land.</line>
            <line>Straight let us seek, or straight we shall be sought;</line>
            <line>The Dauphin rages at our very heels.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALISBURY</speaker>
            <line>It seems you know not, then, so much as we:</line>
            <line>The Cardinal Pandulph is within at rest,</line>
            <line>Who half an hour since came from the Dauphin,</line>
            <line>And brings from him such offers of our peace</line>
            <line>As we with honour and respect may take,</line>
            <line>With purpose presently to leave this war.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>He will the rather do it when he sees</line>
            <line>Ourselves well sinewed to our defence.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALISBURY</speaker>
            <line>Nay, it is in a manner done already;</line>
            <line>For many carriages he hath dispatch'd</line>
            <line>To the sea-side, and put his cause and quarrel</line>
            <line>To the disposing of the cardinal:</line>
            <line>With whom yourself, myself and other lords,</line>
            <line>If you think meet, this afternoon will post</line>
            <line>To consummate this business happily.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>Let it be so: and you, my noble prince,</line>
            <line>With other princes that may best be spared,</line>
            <line>Shall wait upon your father's funeral.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>At Worcester must his body be interr'd;</line>
            <line>For so he will'd it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>Thither shall it then:</line>
            <line>And happily may your sweet self put on</line>
            <line>The lineal state and glory of the land!</line>
            <line>To whom with all submission, on my knee</line>
            <line>I do bequeath my faithful services</line>
            <line>And true subjection everlastingly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALISBURY</speaker>
            <line>And the like tender of our love we make,</line>
            <line>To rest without a spot for evermore.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>I have a kind soul that would give you thanks</line>
            <line>And knows not how to do it but with tears.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>O, let us pay the time but needful woe,</line>
            <line>Since it hath been beforehand with our griefs.</line>
            <line>This England never did, nor never shall,</line>
            <line>Lie at the proud foot of a conqueror,</line>
            <line>But when it first did help to wound itself.</line>
            <line>Now these her princes are come home again,</line>
            <line>Come the three corners of the world in arms,</line>
            <line>And we shall shock them. Nought shall make us rue,</line>
            <line>If England to itself do rest but true.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>