<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net/doctypes/dita/shakespear/dtd/act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-3">
   <title>ACT III</title>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  The French King's pavilion.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter CONSTANCE, ARTHUR, and SALISBURY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CONSTANCE</speaker>
            <line>Gone to be married! gone to swear a peace!</line>
            <line>False blood to false blood join'd! gone to be friends!</line>
            <line>Shall Lewis have Blanch, and Blanch those provinces?</line>
            <line>It is not so; thou hast misspoke, misheard:</line>
            <line>Be well advised, tell o'er thy tale again:</line>
            <line>It cannot be; thou dost but say 'tis so:</line>
            <line>I trust I may not trust thee; for thy word</line>
            <line>Is but the vain breath of a common man:</line>
            <line>Believe me, I do not believe thee, man;</line>
            <line>I have a king's oath to the contrary.</line>
            <line>Thou shalt be punish'd for thus frighting me,</line>
            <line>For I am sick and capable of fears,</line>
            <line>Oppress'd with wrongs and therefore full of fears,</line>
            <line>A widow, husbandless, subject to fears,</line>
            <line>A woman, naturally born to fears;</line>
            <line>And though thou now confess thou didst but jest,</line>
            <line>With my vex'd spirits I cannot take a truce,</line>
            <line>But they will quake and tremble all this day.</line>
            <line>What dost thou mean by shaking of thy head?</line>
            <line>Why dost thou look so sadly on my son?</line>
            <line>What means that hand upon that breast of thine?</line>
            <line>Why holds thine eye that lamentable rheum,</line>
            <line>Like a proud river peering o'er his bounds?</line>
            <line>Be these sad signs confirmers of thy words?</line>
            <line>Then speak again; not all thy former tale,</line>
            <line>But this one word, whether thy tale be true.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALISBURY</speaker>
            <line>As true as I believe you think them false</line>
            <line>That give you cause to prove my saying true.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CONSTANCE</speaker>
            <line>O, if thou teach me to believe this sorrow,</line>
            <line>Teach thou this sorrow how to make me die,</line>
            <line>And let belief and life encounter so</line>
            <line>As doth the fury of two desperate men</line>
            <line>Which in the very meeting fall and die.</line>
            <line>Lewis marry Blanch! O boy, then where art thou?</line>
            <line>France friend with England, what becomes of me?</line>
            <line>Fellow, be gone: I cannot brook thy sight:</line>
            <line>This news hath made thee a most ugly man.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALISBURY</speaker>
            <line>What other harm have I, good lady, done,</line>
            <line>But spoke the harm that is by others done?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CONSTANCE</speaker>
            <line>Which harm within itself so heinous is</line>
            <line>As it makes harmful all that speak of it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARTHUR</speaker>
            <line>I do beseech you, madam, be content.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CONSTANCE</speaker>
            <line>If thou, that bid'st me be content, wert grim,</line>
            <line>Ugly and slanderous to thy mother's womb,</line>
            <line>Full of unpleasing blots and sightless stains,</line>
            <line>Lame, foolish, crooked, swart, prodigious,</line>
            <line>Patch'd with foul moles and eye-offending marks,</line>
            <line>I would not care, I then would be content,</line>
            <line>For then I should not love thee, no, nor thou</line>
            <line>Become thy great birth nor deserve a crown.</line>
            <line>But thou art fair, and at thy birth, dear boy,</line>
            <line>Nature and Fortune join'd to make thee great:</line>
            <line>Of Nature's gifts thou mayst with lilies boast,</line>
            <line>And with the half-blown rose. But Fortune, O,</line>
            <line>She is corrupted, changed and won from thee;</line>
            <line>She adulterates hourly with thine uncle John,</line>
            <line>And with her golden hand hath pluck'd on France</line>
            <line>To tread down fair respect of sovereignty,</line>
            <line>And made his majesty the bawd to theirs.</line>
            <line>France is a bawd to Fortune and King John,</line>
            <line>That strumpet Fortune, that usurping John!</line>
            <line>Tell me, thou fellow, is not France forsworn?</line>
            <line>Envenom him with words, or get thee gone</line>
            <line>And leave those woes alone which I alone</line>
            <line>Am bound to under-bear.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALISBURY</speaker>
            <line>Pardon me, madam,</line>
            <line>I may not go without you to the kings.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CONSTANCE</speaker>
            <line>Thou mayst, thou shalt; I will not go with thee:</line>
            <line>I will instruct my sorrows to be proud;</line>
            <line>For grief is proud and makes his owner stoop.</line>
            <line>To me and to the state of my great grief</line>
            <line>Let kings assemble; for my grief's so great</line>
            <line>That no supporter but the huge firm earth</line>
            <line>Can hold it up: here I and sorrows sit;</line>
            <line>Here is my throne, bid kings come bow to it.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Seats herself on the ground</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Enter KING JOHN, KING PHILLIP, LEWIS, BLANCH,
QUEEN ELINOR, the BASTARD, AUSTRIA, and Attendants</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING PHILIP</speaker>
            <line>'Tis true, fair daughter; and this blessed day</line>
            <line>Ever in France shall be kept festival:</line>
            <line>To solemnize this day the glorious sun</line>
            <line>Stays in his course and plays the alchemist,</line>
            <line>Turning with splendor of his precious eye</line>
            <line>The meagre cloddy earth to glittering gold:</line>
            <line>The yearly course that brings this day about</line>
            <line>Shall never see it but a holiday.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CONSTANCE</speaker>
            <line>A wicked day, and not a holy day!</line>
            <stagedir>Rising</stagedir>
            <line>What hath this day deserved? what hath it done,</line>
            <line>That it in golden letters should be set</line>
            <line>Among the high tides in the calendar?</line>
            <line>Nay, rather turn this day out of the week,</line>
            <line>This day of shame, oppression, perjury.</line>
            <line>Or, if it must stand still, let wives with child</line>
            <line>Pray that their burthens may not fall this day,</line>
            <line>Lest that their hopes prodigiously be cross'd:</line>
            <line>But on this day let seamen fear no wreck;</line>
            <line>No bargains break that are not this day made:</line>
            <line>This day, all things begun come to ill end,</line>
            <line>Yea, faith itself to hollow falsehood change!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING PHILIP</speaker>
            <line>By heaven, lady, you shall have no cause</line>
            <line>To curse the fair proceedings of this day:</line>
            <line>Have I not pawn'd to you my majesty?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CONSTANCE</speaker>
            <line>You have beguiled me with a counterfeit</line>
            <line>Resembling majesty, which, being touch'd and tried,</line>
            <line>Proves valueless: you are forsworn, forsworn;</line>
            <line>You came in arms to spill mine enemies' blood,</line>
            <line>But now in arms you strengthen it with yours:</line>
            <line>The grappling vigour and rough frown of war</line>
            <line>Is cold in amity and painted peace,</line>
            <line>And our oppression hath made up this league.</line>
            <line>Arm, arm, you heavens, against these perjured kings!</line>
            <line>A widow cries; be husband to me, heavens!</line>
            <line>Let not the hours of this ungodly day</line>
            <line>Wear out the day in peace; but, ere sunset,</line>
            <line>Set armed discord 'twixt these perjured kings!</line>
            <line>Hear me, O, hear me!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUSTRIA</speaker>
            <line>Lady Constance, peace!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CONSTANCE</speaker>
            <line>War! war! no peace! peace is to me a war</line>
            <line>O Lymoges! O Austria! thou dost shame</line>
            <line>That bloody spoil: thou slave, thou wretch, thou coward!</line>
            <line>Thou little valiant, great in villany!</line>
            <line>Thou ever strong upon the stronger side!</line>
            <line>Thou Fortune's champion that dost never fight</line>
            <line>But when her humorous ladyship is by</line>
            <line>To teach thee safety! thou art perjured too,</line>
            <line>And soothest up greatness. What a fool art thou,</line>
            <line>A ramping fool, to brag and stamp and swear</line>
            <line>Upon my party! Thou cold-blooded slave,</line>
            <line>Hast thou not spoke like thunder on my side,</line>
            <line>Been sworn my soldier, bidding me depend</line>
            <line>Upon thy stars, thy fortune and thy strength,</line>
            <line>And dost thou now fall over to my fores?</line>
            <line>Thou wear a lion's hide! doff it for shame,</line>
            <line>And hang a calf's-skin on those recreant limbs.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUSTRIA</speaker>
            <line>O, that a man should speak those words to me!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>And hang a calf's-skin on those recreant limbs.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUSTRIA</speaker>
            <line>Thou darest not say so, villain, for thy life.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>And hang a calf's-skin on those recreant limbs.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>We like not this; thou dost forget thyself.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter CARDINAL PANDULPH</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING PHILIP</speaker>
            <line>Here comes the holy legate of the pope.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL PANDULPH</speaker>
            <line>Hail, you anointed deputies of heaven!</line>
            <line>To thee, King John, my holy errand is.</line>
            <line>I Pandulph, of fair Milan cardinal,</line>
            <line>And from Pope Innocent the legate here,</line>
            <line>Do in his name religiously demand</line>
            <line>Why thou against the church, our holy mother,</line>
            <line>So wilfully dost spurn; and force perforce</line>
            <line>Keep Stephen Langton, chosen archbishop</line>
            <line>Of Canterbury, from that holy see?</line>
            <line>This, in our foresaid holy father's name,</line>
            <line>Pope Innocent, I do demand of thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>What earthy name to interrogatories</line>
            <line>Can task the free breath of a sacred king?</line>
            <line>Thou canst not, cardinal, devise a name</line>
            <line>So slight, unworthy and ridiculous,</line>
            <line>To charge me to an answer, as the pope.</line>
            <line>Tell him this tale; and from the mouth of England</line>
            <line>Add thus much more, that no Italian priest</line>
            <line>Shall tithe or toll in our dominions;</line>
            <line>But as we, under heaven, are supreme head,</line>
            <line>So under Him that great supremacy,</line>
            <line>Where we do reign, we will alone uphold,</line>
            <line>Without the assistance of a mortal hand:</line>
            <line>So tell the pope, all reverence set apart</line>
            <line>To him and his usurp'd authority.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING PHILIP</speaker>
            <line>Brother of England, you blaspheme in this.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>Though you and all the kings of Christendom</line>
            <line>Are led so grossly by this meddling priest,</line>
            <line>Dreading the curse that money may buy out;</line>
            <line>And by the merit of vile gold, dross, dust,</line>
            <line>Purchase corrupted pardon of a man,</line>
            <line>Who in that sale sells pardon from himself,</line>
            <line>Though you and all the rest so grossly led</line>
            <line>This juggling witchcraft with revenue cherish,</line>
            <line>Yet I alone, alone do me oppose</line>
            <line>Against the pope and count his friends my foes.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL PANDULPH</speaker>
            <line>Then, by the lawful power that I have,</line>
            <line>Thou shalt stand cursed and excommunicate.</line>
            <line>And blessed shall he be that doth revolt</line>
            <line>From his allegiance to an heretic;</line>
            <line>And meritorious shall that hand be call'd,</line>
            <line>Canonized and worshipped as a saint,</line>
            <line>That takes away by any secret course</line>
            <line>Thy hateful life.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CONSTANCE</speaker>
            <line>O, lawful let it be</line>
            <line>That I have room with Rome to curse awhile!</line>
            <line>Good father cardinal, cry thou amen</line>
            <line>To my keen curses; for without my wrong</line>
            <line>There is no tongue hath power to curse him right.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL PANDULPH</speaker>
            <line>There's law and warrant, lady, for my curse.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CONSTANCE</speaker>
            <line>And for mine too: when law can do no right,</line>
            <line>Let it be lawful that law bar no wrong:</line>
            <line>Law cannot give my child his kingdom here,</line>
            <line>For he that holds his kingdom holds the law;</line>
            <line>Therefore, since law itself is perfect wrong,</line>
            <line>How can the law forbid my tongue to curse?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL PANDULPH</speaker>
            <line>Philip of France, on peril of a curse,</line>
            <line>Let go the hand of that arch-heretic;</line>
            <line>And raise the power of France upon his head,</line>
            <line>Unless he do submit himself to Rome.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELINOR</speaker>
            <line>Look'st thou pale, France? do not let go thy hand.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CONSTANCE</speaker>
            <line>Look to that, devil; lest that France repent,</line>
            <line>And by disjoining hands, hell lose a soul.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUSTRIA</speaker>
            <line>King Philip, listen to the cardinal.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>And hang a calf's-skin on his recreant limbs.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUSTRIA</speaker>
            <line>Well, ruffian, I must pocket up these wrongs, Because--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>Your breeches best may carry them.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>Philip, what say'st thou to the cardinal?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CONSTANCE</speaker>
            <line>What should he say, but as the cardinal?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEWIS</speaker>
            <line>Bethink you, father; for the difference</line>
            <line>Is purchase of a heavy curse from Rome,</line>
            <line>Or the light loss of England for a friend:</line>
            <line>Forego the easier.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BLANCH</speaker>
            <line>That's the curse of Rome.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CONSTANCE</speaker>
            <line>O Lewis, stand fast! the devil tempts thee here</line>
            <line>In likeness of a new untrimmed bride.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BLANCH</speaker>
            <line>The Lady Constance speaks not from her faith,</line>
            <line>But from her need.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CONSTANCE</speaker>
            <line>O, if thou grant my need,</line>
            <line>Which only lives but by the death of faith,</line>
            <line>That need must needs infer this principle,</line>
            <line>That faith would live again by death of need.</line>
            <line>O then, tread down my need, and faith mounts up;</line>
            <line>Keep my need up, and faith is trodden down!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>The king is moved, and answers not to this.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CONSTANCE</speaker>
            <line>O, be removed from him, and answer well!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUSTRIA</speaker>
            <line>Do so, King Philip; hang no more in doubt.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>Hang nothing but a calf's-skin, most sweet lout.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING PHILIP</speaker>
            <line>I am perplex'd, and know not what to say.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL PANDULPH</speaker>
            <line>What canst thou say but will perplex thee more,</line>
            <line>If thou stand excommunicate and cursed?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING PHILIP</speaker>
            <line>Good reverend father, make my person yours,</line>
            <line>And tell me how you would bestow yourself.</line>
            <line>This royal hand and mine are newly knit,</line>
            <line>And the conjunction of our inward souls</line>
            <line>Married in league, coupled and linked together</line>
            <line>With all religious strength of sacred vows;</line>
            <line>The latest breath that gave the sound of words</line>
            <line>Was deep-sworn faith, peace, amity, true love</line>
            <line>Between our kingdoms and our royal selves,</line>
            <line>And even before this truce, but new before,</line>
            <line>No longer than we well could wash our hands</line>
            <line>To clap this royal bargain up of peace,</line>
            <line>Heaven knows, they were besmear'd and over-stain'd</line>
            <line>With slaughter's pencil, where revenge did paint</line>
            <line>The fearful difference of incensed kings:</line>
            <line>And shall these hands, so lately purged of blood,</line>
            <line>So newly join'd in love, so strong in both,</line>
            <line>Unyoke this seizure and this kind regreet?</line>
            <line>Play fast and loose with faith? so jest with heaven,</line>
            <line>Make such unconstant children of ourselves,</line>
            <line>As now again to snatch our palm from palm,</line>
            <line>Unswear faith sworn, and on the marriage-bed</line>
            <line>Of smiling peace to march a bloody host,</line>
            <line>And make a riot on the gentle brow</line>
            <line>Of true sincerity? O, holy sir,</line>
            <line>My reverend father, let it not be so!</line>
            <line>Out of your grace, devise, ordain, impose</line>
            <line>Some gentle order; and then we shall be blest</line>
            <line>To do your pleasure and continue friends.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL PANDULPH</speaker>
            <line>All form is formless, order orderless,</line>
            <line>Save what is opposite to England's love.</line>
            <line>Therefore to arms! be champion of our church,</line>
            <line>Or let the church, our mother, breathe her curse,</line>
            <line>A mother's curse, on her revolting son.</line>
            <line>France, thou mayst hold a serpent by the tongue,</line>
            <line>A chafed lion by the mortal paw,</line>
            <line>A fasting tiger safer by the tooth,</line>
            <line>Than keep in peace that hand which thou dost hold.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING PHILIP</speaker>
            <line>I may disjoin my hand, but not my faith.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL PANDULPH</speaker>
            <line>So makest thou faith an enemy to faith;</line>
            <line>And like a civil war set'st oath to oath,</line>
            <line>Thy tongue against thy tongue. O, let thy vow</line>
            <line>First made to heaven, first be to heaven perform'd,</line>
            <line>That is, to be the champion of our church!</line>
            <line>What since thou sworest is sworn against thyself</line>
            <line>And may not be performed by thyself,</line>
            <line>For that which thou hast sworn to do amiss</line>
            <line>Is not amiss when it is truly done,</line>
            <line>And being not done, where doing tends to ill,</line>
            <line>The truth is then most done not doing it:</line>
            <line>The better act of purposes mistook</line>
            <line>Is to mistake again; though indirect,</line>
            <line>Yet indirection thereby grows direct,</line>
            <line>And falsehood falsehood cures, as fire cools fire</line>
            <line>Within the scorched veins of one new-burn'd.</line>
            <line>It is religion that doth make vows kept;</line>
            <line>But thou hast sworn against religion,</line>
            <line>By what thou swear'st against the thing thou swear'st,</line>
            <line>And makest an oath the surety for thy truth</line>
            <line>Against an oath: the truth thou art unsure</line>
            <line>To swear, swears only not to be forsworn;</line>
            <line>Else what a mockery should it be to swear!</line>
            <line>But thou dost swear only to be forsworn;</line>
            <line>And most forsworn, to keep what thou dost swear.</line>
            <line>Therefore thy later vows against thy first</line>
            <line>Is in thyself rebellion to thyself;</line>
            <line>And better conquest never canst thou make</line>
            <line>Than arm thy constant and thy nobler parts</line>
            <line>Against these giddy loose suggestions:</line>
            <line>Upon which better part our prayers come in,</line>
            <line>If thou vouchsafe them. But if not, then know</line>
            <line>The peril of our curses light on thee</line>
            <line>So heavy as thou shalt not shake them off,</line>
            <line>But in despair die under their black weight.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUSTRIA</speaker>
            <line>Rebellion, flat rebellion!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>Will't not be?</line>
            <line>Will not a calfs-skin stop that mouth of thine?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEWIS</speaker>
            <line>Father, to arms!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BLANCH</speaker>
            <line>Upon thy wedding-day?</line>
            <line>Against the blood that thou hast married?</line>
            <line>What, shall our feast be kept with slaughter'd men?</line>
            <line>Shall braying trumpets and loud churlish drums,</line>
            <line>Clamours of hell, be measures to our pomp?</line>
            <line>O husband, hear me! ay, alack, how new</line>
            <line>Is husband in my mouth! even for that name,</line>
            <line>Which till this time my tongue did ne'er pronounce,</line>
            <line>Upon my knee I beg, go not to arms</line>
            <line>Against mine uncle.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CONSTANCE</speaker>
            <line>O, upon my knee,</line>
            <line>Made hard with kneeling, I do pray to thee,</line>
            <line>Thou virtuous Dauphin, alter not the doom</line>
            <line>Forethought by heaven!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BLANCH</speaker>
            <line>Now shall I see thy love: what motive may</line>
            <line>Be stronger with thee than the name of wife?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CONSTANCE</speaker>
            <line>That which upholdeth him that thee upholds,</line>
            <line>His honour: O, thine honour, Lewis, thine honour!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEWIS</speaker>
            <line>I muse your majesty doth seem so cold,</line>
            <line>When such profound respects do pull you on.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL PANDULPH</speaker>
            <line>I will denounce a curse upon his head.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING PHILIP</speaker>
            <line>Thou shalt not need. England, I will fall from thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CONSTANCE</speaker>
            <line>O fair return of banish'd majesty!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELINOR</speaker>
            <line>O foul revolt of French inconstancy!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>France, thou shalt rue this hour within this hour.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>Old Time the clock-setter, that bald sexton Time,</line>
            <line>Is it as he will? well then, France shall rue.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BLANCH</speaker>
            <line>The sun's o'ercast with blood: fair day, adieu!</line>
            <line>Which is the side that I must go withal?</line>
            <line>I am with both: each army hath a hand;</line>
            <line>And in their rage, I having hold of both,</line>
            <line>They swirl asunder and dismember me.</line>
            <line>Husband, I cannot pray that thou mayst win;</line>
            <line>Uncle, I needs must pray that thou mayst lose;</line>
            <line>Father, I may not wish the fortune thine;</line>
            <line>Grandam, I will not wish thy fortunes thrive:</line>
            <line>Whoever wins, on that side shall I lose</line>
            <line>Assured loss before the match be play'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEWIS</speaker>
            <line>Lady, with me, with me thy fortune lies.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BLANCH</speaker>
            <line>There where my fortune lives, there my life dies.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>Cousin, go draw our puissance together.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit BASTARD</stagedir>
            <line>France, I am burn'd up with inflaming wrath;</line>
            <line>A rage whose heat hath this condition,</line>
            <line>That nothing can allay, nothing but blood,</line>
            <line>The blood, and dearest-valued blood, of France.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING PHILIP</speaker>
            <line>Thy rage sham burn thee up, and thou shalt turn</line>
            <line>To ashes, ere our blood shall quench that fire:</line>
            <line>Look to thyself, thou art in jeopardy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>No more than he that threats. To arms let's hie!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  The same. Plains near Angiers.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Alarums, excursions. Enter the BASTARD, with
AUSTRIA'S head</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>Now, by my life, this day grows wondrous hot;</line>
            <line>Some airy devil hovers in the sky</line>
            <line>And pours down mischief. Austria's head lie there,</line>
            <line>While Philip breathes.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter KING JOHN, ARTHUR, and HUBERT</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>Hubert, keep this boy. Philip, make up:</line>
            <line>My mother is assailed in our tent,</line>
            <line>And ta'en, I fear.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>My lord, I rescued her;</line>
            <line>Her highness is in safety, fear you not:</line>
            <line>But on, my liege; for very little pains</line>
            <line>Will bring this labour to an happy end.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  The same.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Alarums, excursions, retreat. Enter KING JOHN,
QUEEN ELINOR, ARTHUR, the BASTARD, HUBERT,
and Lords</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>To QUEEN ELINOR</stagedir>  So shall it be; your grace shall</line>
            <line>stay behind</line>
            <line>So strongly guarded.</line>
            <stagedir>To ARTHUR</stagedir>
            <line>Cousin, look not sad:</line>
            <line>Thy grandam loves thee; and thy uncle will</line>
            <line>As dear be to thee as thy father was.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARTHUR</speaker>
            <line>O, this will make my mother die with grief!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>To the BASTARD</stagedir>  Cousin, away for England!</line>
            <line>haste before:</line>
            <line>And, ere our coming, see thou shake the bags</line>
            <line>Of hoarding abbots; imprisoned angels</line>
            <line>Set at liberty: the fat ribs of peace</line>
            <line>Must by the hungry now be fed upon:</line>
            <line>Use our commission in his utmost force.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>Bell, book, and candle shall not drive me back,</line>
            <line>When gold and silver becks me to come on.</line>
            <line>I leave your highness. Grandam, I will pray,</line>
            <line>If ever I remember to be holy,</line>
            <line>For your fair safety; so, I kiss your hand.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ELINOR</speaker>
            <line>Farewell, gentle cousin.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>Coz, farewell.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit the BASTARD</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELINOR</speaker>
            <line>Come hither, little kinsman; hark, a word.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>Come hither, Hubert. O my gentle Hubert,</line>
            <line>We owe thee much! within this wall of flesh</line>
            <line>There is a soul counts thee her creditor</line>
            <line>And with advantage means to pay thy love:</line>
            <line>And my good friend, thy voluntary oath</line>
            <line>Lives in this bosom, dearly cherished.</line>
            <line>Give me thy hand. I had a thing to say,</line>
            <line>But I will fit it with some better time.</line>
            <line>By heaven, Hubert, I am almost ashamed</line>
            <line>To say what good respect I have of thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HUBERT</speaker>
            <line>I am much bounden to your majesty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>Good friend, thou hast no cause to say so yet,</line>
            <line>But thou shalt have; and creep time ne'er so slow,</line>
            <line>Yet it shall come from me to do thee good.</line>
            <line>I had a thing to say, but let it go:</line>
            <line>The sun is in the heaven, and the proud day,</line>
            <line>Attended with the pleasures of the world,</line>
            <line>Is all too wanton and too full of gawds</line>
            <line>To give me audience: if the midnight bell</line>
            <line>Did, with his iron tongue and brazen mouth,</line>
            <line>Sound on into the drowsy race of night;</line>
            <line>If this same were a churchyard where we stand,</line>
            <line>And thou possessed with a thousand wrongs,</line>
            <line>Or if that surly spirit, melancholy,</line>
            <line>Had baked thy blood and made it heavy-thick,</line>
            <line>Which else runs tickling up and down the veins,</line>
            <line>Making that idiot, laughter, keep men's eyes</line>
            <line>And strain their cheeks to idle merriment,</line>
            <line>A passion hateful to my purposes,</line>
            <line>Or if that thou couldst see me without eyes,</line>
            <line>Hear me without thine ears, and make reply</line>
            <line>Without a tongue, using conceit alone,</line>
            <line>Without eyes, ears and harmful sound of words;</line>
            <line>Then, in despite of brooded watchful day,</line>
            <line>I would into thy bosom pour my thoughts:</line>
            <line>But, ah, I will not! yet I love thee well;</line>
            <line>And, by my troth, I think thou lovest me well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HUBERT</speaker>
            <line>So well, that what you bid me undertake,</line>
            <line>Though that my death were adjunct to my act,</line>
            <line>By heaven, I would do it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>Do not I know thou wouldst?</line>
            <line>Good Hubert, Hubert, Hubert, throw thine eye</line>
            <line>On yon young boy: I'll tell thee what, my friend,</line>
            <line>He is a very serpent in my way;</line>
            <line>And whereso'er this foot of mine doth tread,</line>
            <line>He lies before me: dost thou understand me?</line>
            <line>Thou art his keeper.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HUBERT</speaker>
            <line>And I'll keep him so,</line>
            <line>That he shall not offend your majesty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>Death.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HUBERT</speaker>
            <line>My lord?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>A grave.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HUBERT</speaker>
            <line>He shall not live.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>Enough.</line>
            <line>I could be merry now. Hubert, I love thee;</line>
            <line>Well, I'll not say what I intend for thee:</line>
            <line>Remember. Madam, fare you well:</line>
            <line>I'll send those powers o'er to your majesty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ELINOR</speaker>
            <line>My blessing go with thee!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>For England, cousin, go:</line>
            <line>Hubert shall be your man, attend on you</line>
            <line>With all true duty. On toward Calais, ho!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-4">
      <title>SCENE IV.  The same. KING PHILIP'S tent.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter KING PHILIP, LEWIS, CARDINAL PANDULPH,
and Attendants</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING PHILIP</speaker>
            <line>So, by a roaring tempest on the flood,</line>
            <line>A whole armado of convicted sail</line>
            <line>Is scatter'd and disjoin'd from fellowship.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL PANDULPH</speaker>
            <line>Courage and comfort! all shall yet go well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING PHILIP</speaker>
            <line>What can go well, when we have run so ill?</line>
            <line>Are we not beaten? Is not Angiers lost?</line>
            <line>Arthur ta'en prisoner? divers dear friends slain?</line>
            <line>And bloody England into England gone,</line>
            <line>O'erbearing interruption, spite of France?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEWIS</speaker>
            <line>What he hath won, that hath he fortified:</line>
            <line>So hot a speed with such advice disposed,</line>
            <line>Such temperate order in so fierce a cause,</line>
            <line>Doth want example: who hath read or heard</line>
            <line>Of any kindred action like to this?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING PHILIP</speaker>
            <line>Well could I bear that England had this praise,</line>
            <line>So we could find some pattern of our shame.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter CONSTANCE</stagedir>
            <line>Look, who comes here! a grave unto a soul;</line>
            <line>Holding the eternal spirit against her will,</line>
            <line>In the vile prison of afflicted breath.</line>
            <line>I prithee, lady, go away with me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CONSTANCE</speaker>
            <line>Lo, now I now see the issue of your peace.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING PHILIP</speaker>
            <line>Patience, good lady! comfort, gentle Constance!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CONSTANCE</speaker>
            <line>No, I defy all counsel, all redress,</line>
            <line>But that which ends all counsel, true redress,</line>
            <line>Death, death; O amiable lovely death!</line>
            <line>Thou odouriferous stench! sound rottenness!</line>
            <line>Arise forth from the couch of lasting night,</line>
            <line>Thou hate and terror to prosperity,</line>
            <line>And I will kiss thy detestable bones</line>
            <line>And put my eyeballs in thy vaulty brows</line>
            <line>And ring these fingers with thy household worms</line>
            <line>And stop this gap of breath with fulsome dust</line>
            <line>And be a carrion monster like thyself:</line>
            <line>Come, grin on me, and I will think thou smilest</line>
            <line>And buss thee as thy wife. Misery's love,</line>
            <line>O, come to me!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING PHILIP</speaker>
            <line>O fair affliction, peace!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CONSTANCE</speaker>
            <line>No, no, I will not, having breath to cry:</line>
            <line>O, that my tongue were in the thunder's mouth!</line>
            <line>Then with a passion would I shake the world;</line>
            <line>And rouse from sleep that fell anatomy</line>
            <line>Which cannot hear a lady's feeble voice,</line>
            <line>Which scorns a modern invocation.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL PANDULPH</speaker>
            <line>Lady, you utter madness, and not sorrow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CONSTANCE</speaker>
            <line>Thou art not holy to belie me so;</line>
            <line>I am not mad: this hair I tear is mine;</line>
            <line>My name is Constance; I was Geffrey's wife;</line>
            <line>Young Arthur is my son, and he is lost:</line>
            <line>I am not mad: I would to heaven I were!</line>
            <line>For then, 'tis like I should forget myself:</line>
            <line>O, if I could, what grief should I forget!</line>
            <line>Preach some philosophy to make me mad,</line>
            <line>And thou shalt be canonized, cardinal;</line>
            <line>For being not mad but sensible of grief,</line>
            <line>My reasonable part produces reason</line>
            <line>How I may be deliver'd of these woes,</line>
            <line>And teaches me to kill or hang myself:</line>
            <line>If I were mad, I should forget my son,</line>
            <line>Or madly think a babe of clouts were he:</line>
            <line>I am not mad; too well, too well I feel</line>
            <line>The different plague of each calamity.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING PHILIP</speaker>
            <line>Bind up those tresses. O, what love I note</line>
            <line>In the fair multitude of those her hairs!</line>
            <line>Where but by chance a silver drop hath fallen,</line>
            <line>Even to that drop ten thousand wiry friends</line>
            <line>Do glue themselves in sociable grief,</line>
            <line>Like true, inseparable, faithful loves,</line>
            <line>Sticking together in calamity.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CONSTANCE</speaker>
            <line>To England, if you will.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING PHILIP</speaker>
            <line>Bind up your hairs.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CONSTANCE</speaker>
            <line>Yes, that I will; and wherefore will I do it?</line>
            <line>I tore them from their bonds and cried aloud</line>
            <line>'O that these hands could so redeem my son,</line>
            <line>As they have given these hairs their liberty!'</line>
            <line>But now I envy at their liberty,</line>
            <line>And will again commit them to their bonds,</line>
            <line>Because my poor child is a prisoner.</line>
            <line>And, father cardinal, I have heard you say</line>
            <line>That we shall see and know our friends in heaven:</line>
            <line>If that be true, I shall see my boy again;</line>
            <line>For since the birth of Cain, the first male child,</line>
            <line>To him that did but yesterday suspire,</line>
            <line>There was not such a gracious creature born.</line>
            <line>But now will canker-sorrow eat my bud</line>
            <line>And chase the native beauty from his cheek</line>
            <line>And he will look as hollow as a ghost,</line>
            <line>As dim and meagre as an ague's fit,</line>
            <line>And so he'll die; and, rising so again,</line>
            <line>When I shall meet him in the court of heaven</line>
            <line>I shall not know him: therefore never, never</line>
            <line>Must I behold my pretty Arthur more.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL PANDULPH</speaker>
            <line>You hold too heinous a respect of grief.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CONSTANCE</speaker>
            <line>He talks to me that never had a son.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING PHILIP</speaker>
            <line>You are as fond of grief as of your child.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CONSTANCE</speaker>
            <line>Grief fills the room up of my absent child,</line>
            <line>Lies in his bed, walks up and down with me,</line>
            <line>Puts on his pretty looks, repeats his words,</line>
            <line>Remembers me of all his gracious parts,</line>
            <line>Stuffs out his vacant garments with his form;</line>
            <line>Then, have I reason to be fond of grief?</line>
            <line>Fare you well: had you such a loss as I,</line>
            <line>I could give better comfort than you do.</line>
            <line>I will not keep this form upon my head,</line>
            <line>When there is such disorder in my wit.</line>
            <line>O Lord! my boy, my Arthur, my fair son!</line>
            <line>My life, my joy, my food, my all the world!</line>
            <line>My widow-comfort, and my sorrows' cure!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING PHILIP</speaker>
            <line>I fear some outrage, and I'll follow her.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEWIS</speaker>
            <line>There's nothing in this world can make me joy:</line>
            <line>Life is as tedious as a twice-told tale</line>
            <line>Vexing the dull ear of a drowsy man;</line>
            <line>And bitter shame hath spoil'd the sweet world's taste</line>
            <line>That it yields nought but shame and bitterness.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL PANDULPH</speaker>
            <line>Before the curing of a strong disease,</line>
            <line>Even in the instant of repair and health,</line>
            <line>The fit is strongest; evils that take leave,</line>
            <line>On their departure most of all show evil:</line>
            <line>What have you lost by losing of this day?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEWIS</speaker>
            <line>All days of glory, joy and happiness.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL PANDULPH</speaker>
            <line>If you had won it, certainly you had.</line>
            <line>No, no; when Fortune means to men most good,</line>
            <line>She looks upon them with a threatening eye.</line>
            <line>'Tis strange to think how much King John hath lost</line>
            <line>In this which he accounts so clearly won:</line>
            <line>Are not you grieved that Arthur is his prisoner?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEWIS</speaker>
            <line>As heartily as he is glad he hath him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL PANDULPH</speaker>
            <line>Your mind is all as youthful as your blood.</line>
            <line>Now hear me speak with a prophetic spirit;</line>
            <line>For even the breath of what I mean to speak</line>
            <line>Shall blow each dust, each straw, each little rub,</line>
            <line>Out of the path which shall directly lead</line>
            <line>Thy foot to England's throne; and therefore mark.</line>
            <line>John hath seized Arthur; and it cannot be</line>
            <line>That, whiles warm life plays in that infant's veins,</line>
            <line>The misplaced John should entertain an hour,</line>
            <line>One minute, nay, one quiet breath of rest.</line>
            <line>A sceptre snatch'd with an unruly hand</line>
            <line>Must be as boisterously maintain'd as gain'd;</line>
            <line>And he that stands upon a slippery place</line>
            <line>Makes nice of no vile hold to stay him up:</line>
            <line>That John may stand, then Arthur needs must fall;</line>
            <line>So be it, for it cannot be but so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEWIS</speaker>
            <line>But what shall I gain by young Arthur's fall?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL PANDULPH</speaker>
            <line>You, in the right of Lady Blanch your wife,</line>
            <line>May then make all the claim that Arthur did.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEWIS</speaker>
            <line>And lose it, life and all, as Arthur did.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL PANDULPH</speaker>
            <line>How green you are and fresh in this old world!</line>
            <line>John lays you plots; the times conspire with you;</line>
            <line>For he that steeps his safety in true blood</line>
            <line>Shall find but bloody safety and untrue.</line>
            <line>This act so evilly born shall cool the hearts</line>
            <line>Of all his people and freeze up their zeal,</line>
            <line>That none so small advantage shall step forth</line>
            <line>To cheque his reign, but they will cherish it;</line>
            <line>No natural exhalation in the sky,</line>
            <line>No scope of nature, no distemper'd day,</line>
            <line>No common wind, no customed event,</line>
            <line>But they will pluck away his natural cause</line>
            <line>And call them meteors, prodigies and signs,</line>
            <line>Abortives, presages and tongues of heaven,</line>
            <line>Plainly denouncing vengeance upon John.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEWIS</speaker>
            <line>May be he will not touch young Arthur's life,</line>
            <line>But hold himself safe in his prisonment.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL PANDULPH</speaker>
            <line>O, sir, when he shall hear of your approach,</line>
            <line>If that young Arthur be not gone already,</line>
            <line>Even at that news he dies; and then the hearts</line>
            <line>Of all his people shall revolt from him</line>
            <line>And kiss the lips of unacquainted change</line>
            <line>And pick strong matter of revolt and wrath</line>
            <line>Out of the bloody fingers' ends of John.</line>
            <line>Methinks I see this hurly all on foot:</line>
            <line>And, O, what better matter breeds for you</line>
            <line>Than I have named! The bastard Faulconbridge</line>
            <line>Is now in England, ransacking the church,</line>
            <line>Offending charity: if but a dozen French</line>
            <line>Were there in arms, they would be as a call</line>
            <line>To train ten thousand English to their side,</line>
            <line>Or as a little snow, tumbled about,</line>
            <line>Anon becomes a mountain. O noble Dauphin,</line>
            <line>Go with me to the king: 'tis wonderful</line>
            <line>What may be wrought out of their discontent,</line>
            <line>Now that their souls are topful of offence.</line>
            <line>For England go: I will whet on the king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEWIS</speaker>
            <line>Strong reasons make strong actions: let us go:</line>
            <line>If you say ay, the king will not say no.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>