<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net/doctypes/dita/shakespear/dtd/act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-2">
   <title>ACT II</title>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  France. Before Angiers.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter AUSTRIA and forces, drums, etc. on one side:
on the other KING PHILIP and his power; LEWIS,
ARTHUR, CONSTANCE and attendants</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEWIS</speaker>
            <line>Before Angiers well met, brave Austria.</line>
            <line>Arthur, that great forerunner of thy blood,</line>
            <line>Richard, that robb'd the lion of his heart</line>
            <line>And fought the holy wars in Palestine,</line>
            <line>By this brave duke came early to his grave:</line>
            <line>And for amends to his posterity,</line>
            <line>At our importance hither is he come,</line>
            <line>To spread his colours, boy, in thy behalf,</line>
            <line>And to rebuke the usurpation</line>
            <line>Of thy unnatural uncle, English John:</line>
            <line>Embrace him, love him, give him welcome hither.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARTHUR</speaker>
            <line>God shall forgive you Coeur-de-lion's death</line>
            <line>The rather that you give his offspring life,</line>
            <line>Shadowing their right under your wings of war:</line>
            <line>I give you welcome with a powerless hand,</line>
            <line>But with a heart full of unstained love:</line>
            <line>Welcome before the gates of Angiers, duke.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEWIS</speaker>
            <line>A noble boy! Who would not do thee right?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUSTRIA</speaker>
            <line>Upon thy cheek lay I this zealous kiss,</line>
            <line>As seal to this indenture of my love,</line>
            <line>That to my home I will no more return,</line>
            <line>Till Angiers and the right thou hast in France,</line>
            <line>Together with that pale, that white-faced shore,</line>
            <line>Whose foot spurns back the ocean's roaring tides</line>
            <line>And coops from other lands her islanders,</line>
            <line>Even till that England, hedged in with the main,</line>
            <line>That water-walled bulwark, still secure</line>
            <line>And confident from foreign purposes,</line>
            <line>Even till that utmost corner of the west</line>
            <line>Salute thee for her king: till then, fair boy,</line>
            <line>Will I not think of home, but follow arms.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CONSTANCE</speaker>
            <line>O, take his mother's thanks, a widow's thanks,</line>
            <line>Till your strong hand shall help to give him strength</line>
            <line>To make a more requital to your love!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUSTRIA</speaker>
            <line>The peace of heaven is theirs that lift their swords</line>
            <line>In such a just and charitable war.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING PHILIP</speaker>
            <line>Well then, to work: our cannon shall be bent</line>
            <line>Against the brows of this resisting town.</line>
            <line>Call for our chiefest men of discipline,</line>
            <line>To cull the plots of best advantages:</line>
            <line>We'll lay before this town our royal bones,</line>
            <line>Wade to the market-place in Frenchmen's blood,</line>
            <line>But we will make it subject to this boy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CONSTANCE</speaker>
            <line>Stay for an answer to your embassy,</line>
            <line>Lest unadvised you stain your swords with blood:</line>
            <line>My Lord Chatillon may from England bring,</line>
            <line>That right in peace which here we urge in war,</line>
            <line>And then we shall repent each drop of blood</line>
            <line>That hot rash haste so indirectly shed.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter CHATILLON</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING PHILIP</speaker>
            <line>A wonder, lady! lo, upon thy wish,</line>
            <line>Our messenger Chatillon is arrived!</line>
            <line>What England says, say briefly, gentle lord;</line>
            <line>We coldly pause for thee; Chatillon, speak.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHATILLON</speaker>
            <line>Then turn your forces from this paltry siege</line>
            <line>And stir them up against a mightier task.</line>
            <line>England, impatient of your just demands,</line>
            <line>Hath put himself in arms: the adverse winds,</line>
            <line>Whose leisure I have stay'd, have given him time</line>
            <line>To land his legions all as soon as I;</line>
            <line>His marches are expedient to this town,</line>
            <line>His forces strong, his soldiers confident.</line>
            <line>With him along is come the mother-queen,</line>
            <line>An Ate, stirring him to blood and strife;</line>
            <line>With her her niece, the Lady Blanch of Spain;</line>
            <line>With them a bastard of the king's deceased,</line>
            <line>And all the unsettled humours of the land,</line>
            <line>Rash, inconsiderate, fiery voluntaries,</line>
            <line>With ladies' faces and fierce dragons' spleens,</line>
            <line>Have sold their fortunes at their native homes,</line>
            <line>Bearing their birthrights proudly on their backs,</line>
            <line>To make hazard of new fortunes here:</line>
            <line>In brief, a braver choice of dauntless spirits</line>
            <line>Than now the English bottoms have waft o'er</line>
            <line>Did nearer float upon the swelling tide,</line>
            <line>To do offence and scath in Christendom.</line>
            <stagedir>Drum beats</stagedir>
            <line>The interruption of their churlish drums</line>
            <line>Cuts off more circumstance: they are at hand,</line>
            <line>To parley or to fight; therefore prepare.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING PHILIP</speaker>
            <line>How much unlook'd for is this expedition!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUSTRIA</speaker>
            <line>By how much unexpected, by so much</line>
            <line>We must awake endavour for defence;</line>
            <line>For courage mounteth with occasion:</line>
            <line>Let them be welcome then: we are prepared.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter KING JOHN, QUEEN ELINOR, BLANCH, the BASTARD,
Lords, and forces</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>Peace be to France, if France in peace permit</line>
            <line>Our just and lineal entrance to our own;</line>
            <line>If not, bleed France, and peace ascend to heaven,</line>
            <line>Whiles we, God's wrathful agent, do correct</line>
            <line>Their proud contempt that beats His peace to heaven.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING PHILIP</speaker>
            <line>Peace be to England, if that war return</line>
            <line>From France to England, there to live in peace.</line>
            <line>England we love; and for that England's sake</line>
            <line>With burden of our armour here we sweat.</line>
            <line>This toil of ours should be a work of thine;</line>
            <line>But thou from loving England art so far,</line>
            <line>That thou hast under-wrought his lawful king</line>
            <line>Cut off the sequence of posterity,</line>
            <line>Out-faced infant state and done a rape</line>
            <line>Upon the maiden virtue of the crown.</line>
            <line>Look here upon thy brother Geffrey's face;</line>
            <line>These eyes, these brows, were moulded out of his:</line>
            <line>This little abstract doth contain that large</line>
            <line>Which died in Geffrey, and the hand of time</line>
            <line>Shall draw this brief into as huge a volume.</line>
            <line>That Geffrey was thy elder brother born,</line>
            <line>And this his son; England was Geffrey's right</line>
            <line>And this is Geffrey's: in the name of God</line>
            <line>How comes it then that thou art call'd a king,</line>
            <line>When living blood doth in these temples beat,</line>
            <line>Which owe the crown that thou o'ermasterest?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>From whom hast thou this great commission, France,</line>
            <line>To draw my answer from thy articles?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING PHILIP</speaker>
            <line>From that supernal judge, that stirs good thoughts</line>
            <line>In any breast of strong authority,</line>
            <line>To look into the blots and stains of right:</line>
            <line>That judge hath made me guardian to this boy:</line>
            <line>Under whose warrant I impeach thy wrong</line>
            <line>And by whose help I mean to chastise it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>Alack, thou dost usurp authority.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING PHILIP</speaker>
            <line>Excuse; it is to beat usurping down.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELINOR</speaker>
            <line>Who is it thou dost call usurper, France?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CONSTANCE</speaker>
            <line>Let me make answer; thy usurping son.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELINOR</speaker>
            <line>Out, insolent! thy bastard shall be king,</line>
            <line>That thou mayst be a queen, and cheque the world!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CONSTANCE</speaker>
            <line>My bed was ever to thy son as true</line>
            <line>As thine was to thy husband; and this boy</line>
            <line>Liker in feature to his father Geffrey</line>
            <line>Than thou and John in manners; being as like</line>
            <line>As rain to water, or devil to his dam.</line>
            <line>My boy a bastard! By my soul, I think</line>
            <line>His father never was so true begot:</line>
            <line>It cannot be, an if thou wert his mother.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELINOR</speaker>
            <line>There's a good mother, boy, that blots thy father.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CONSTANCE</speaker>
            <line>There's a good grandam, boy, that would blot thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUSTRIA</speaker>
            <line>Peace!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>Hear the crier.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUSTRIA</speaker>
            <line>What the devil art thou?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>One that will play the devil, sir, with you,</line>
            <line>An a' may catch your hide and you alone:</line>
            <line>You are the hare of whom the proverb goes,</line>
            <line>Whose valour plucks dead lions by the beard;</line>
            <line>I'll smoke your skin-coat, an I catch you right;</line>
            <line>Sirrah, look to't; i' faith, I will, i' faith.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BLANCH</speaker>
            <line>O, well did he become that lion's robe</line>
            <line>That did disrobe the lion of that robe!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>It lies as sightly on the back of him</line>
            <line>As great Alcides' shows upon an ass:</line>
            <line>But, ass, I'll take that burthen from your back,</line>
            <line>Or lay on that shall make your shoulders crack.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUSTRIA</speaker>
            <line>What craker is this same that deafs our ears</line>
            <line>With this abundance of superfluous breath?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING PHILIP</speaker>
            <line>Lewis, determine what we shall do straight.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEWIS</speaker>
            <line>Women and fools, break off your conference.</line>
            <line>King John, this is the very sum of all;</line>
            <line>England and Ireland, Anjou, Touraine, Maine,</line>
            <line>In right of Arthur do I claim of thee:</line>
            <line>Wilt thou resign them and lay down thy arms?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>My life as soon: I do defy thee, France.</line>
            <line>Arthur of Bretagne, yield thee to my hand;</line>
            <line>And out of my dear love I'll give thee more</line>
            <line>Than e'er the coward hand of France can win:</line>
            <line>Submit thee, boy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELINOR</speaker>
            <line>Come to thy grandam, child.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CONSTANCE</speaker>
            <line>Do, child, go to it grandam, child:</line>
            <line>Give grandam kingdom, and it grandam will</line>
            <line>Give it a plum, a cherry, and a fig:</line>
            <line>There's a good grandam.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARTHUR</speaker>
            <line>Good my mother, peace!</line>
            <line>I would that I were low laid in my grave:</line>
            <line>I am not worth this coil that's made for me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELINOR</speaker>
            <line>His mother shames him so, poor boy, he weeps.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CONSTANCE</speaker>
            <line>Now shame upon you, whether she does or no!</line>
            <line>His grandam's wrongs, and not his mother's shames,</line>
            <line>Draws those heaven-moving pearls from his poor eyes,</line>
            <line>Which heaven shall take in nature of a fee;</line>
            <line>Ay, with these crystal beads heaven shall be bribed</line>
            <line>To do him justice and revenge on you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELINOR</speaker>
            <line>Thou monstrous slanderer of heaven and earth!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CONSTANCE</speaker>
            <line>Thou monstrous injurer of heaven and earth!</line>
            <line>Call not me slanderer; thou and thine usurp</line>
            <line>The dominations, royalties and rights</line>
            <line>Of this oppressed boy: this is thy eld'st son's son,</line>
            <line>Infortunate in nothing but in thee:</line>
            <line>Thy sins are visited in this poor child;</line>
            <line>The canon of the law is laid on him,</line>
            <line>Being but the second generation</line>
            <line>Removed from thy sin-conceiving womb.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>Bedlam, have done.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CONSTANCE</speaker>
            <line>I have but this to say,</line>
            <line>That he is not only plagued for her sin,</line>
            <line>But God hath made her sin and her the plague</line>
            <line>On this removed issue, plague for her</line>
            <line>And with her plague; her sin his injury,</line>
            <line>Her injury the beadle to her sin,</line>
            <line>All punish'd in the person of this child,</line>
            <line>And all for her; a plague upon her!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELINOR</speaker>
            <line>Thou unadvised scold, I can produce</line>
            <line>A will that bars the title of thy son.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CONSTANCE</speaker>
            <line>Ay, who doubts that? a will! a wicked will:</line>
            <line>A woman's will; a canker'd grandam's will!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING PHILIP</speaker>
            <line>Peace, lady! pause, or be more temperate:</line>
            <line>It ill beseems this presence to cry aim</line>
            <line>To these ill-tuned repetitions.</line>
            <line>Some trumpet summon hither to the walls</line>
            <line>These men of Angiers: let us hear them speak</line>
            <line>Whose title they admit, Arthur's or John's.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Trumpet sounds. Enter certain Citizens upon the walls</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Who is it that hath warn'd us to the walls?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING PHILIP</speaker>
            <line>'Tis France, for England.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>England, for itself.</line>
            <line>You men of Angiers, and my loving subjects--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING PHILIP</speaker>
            <line>You loving men of Angiers, Arthur's subjects,</line>
            <line>Our trumpet call'd you to this gentle parle--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>For our advantage; therefore hear us first.</line>
            <line>These flags of France, that are advanced here</line>
            <line>Before the eye and prospect of your town,</line>
            <line>Have hither march'd to your endamagement:</line>
            <line>The cannons have their bowels full of wrath,</line>
            <line>And ready mounted are they to spit forth</line>
            <line>Their iron indignation 'gainst your walls:</line>
            <line>All preparation for a bloody siege</line>
            <line>All merciless proceeding by these French</line>
            <line>Confronts your city's eyes, your winking gates;</line>
            <line>And but for our approach those sleeping stones,</line>
            <line>That as a waist doth girdle you about,</line>
            <line>By the compulsion of their ordinance</line>
            <line>By this time from their fixed beds of lime</line>
            <line>Had been dishabited, and wide havoc made</line>
            <line>For bloody power to rush upon your peace.</line>
            <line>But on the sight of us your lawful king,</line>
            <line>Who painfully with much expedient march</line>
            <line>Have brought a countercheque before your gates,</line>
            <line>To save unscratch'd your city's threatened cheeks,</line>
            <line>Behold, the French amazed vouchsafe a parle;</line>
            <line>And now, instead of bullets wrapp'd in fire,</line>
            <line>To make a shaking fever in your walls,</line>
            <line>They shoot but calm words folded up in smoke,</line>
            <line>To make a faithless error in your ears:</line>
            <line>Which trust accordingly, kind citizens,</line>
            <line>And let us in, your king, whose labour'd spirits,</line>
            <line>Forwearied in this action of swift speed,</line>
            <line>Crave harbourage within your city walls.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING PHILIP</speaker>
            <line>When I have said, make answer to us both.</line>
            <line>Lo, in this right hand, whose protection</line>
            <line>Is most divinely vow'd upon the right</line>
            <line>Of him it holds, stands young Plantagenet,</line>
            <line>Son to the elder brother of this man,</line>
            <line>And king o'er him and all that he enjoys:</line>
            <line>For this down-trodden equity, we tread</line>
            <line>In warlike march these greens before your town,</line>
            <line>Being no further enemy to you</line>
            <line>Than the constraint of hospitable zeal</line>
            <line>In the relief of this oppressed child</line>
            <line>Religiously provokes. Be pleased then</line>
            <line>To pay that duty which you truly owe</line>
            <line>To that owes it, namely this young prince:</line>
            <line>And then our arms, like to a muzzled bear,</line>
            <line>Save in aspect, hath all offence seal'd up;</line>
            <line>Our cannons' malice vainly shall be spent</line>
            <line>Against the invulnerable clouds of heaven;</line>
            <line>And with a blessed and unvex'd retire,</line>
            <line>With unhack'd swords and helmets all unbruised,</line>
            <line>We will bear home that lusty blood again</line>
            <line>Which here we came to spout against your town,</line>
            <line>And leave your children, wives and you in peace.</line>
            <line>But if you fondly pass our proffer'd offer,</line>
            <line>'Tis not the roundure of your old-faced walls</line>
            <line>Can hide you from our messengers of war,</line>
            <line>Though all these English and their discipline</line>
            <line>Were harbour'd in their rude circumference.</line>
            <line>Then tell us, shall your city call us lord,</line>
            <line>In that behalf which we have challenged it?</line>
            <line>Or shall we give the signal to our rage</line>
            <line>And stalk in blood to our possession?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>In brief, we are the king of England's subjects:</line>
            <line>For him, and in his right, we hold this town.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>Acknowledge then the king, and let me in.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>That can we not; but he that proves the king,</line>
            <line>To him will we prove loyal: till that time</line>
            <line>Have we ramm'd up our gates against the world.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>Doth not the crown of England prove the king?</line>
            <line>And if not that, I bring you witnesses,</line>
            <line>Twice fifteen thousand hearts of England's breed,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>Bastards, and else.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>To verify our title with their lives.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING PHILIP</speaker>
            <line>As many and as well-born bloods as those,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>Some bastards too.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING PHILIP</speaker>
            <line>Stand in his face to contradict his claim.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Till you compound whose right is worthiest,</line>
            <line>We for the worthiest hold the right from both.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>Then God forgive the sin of all those souls</line>
            <line>That to their everlasting residence,</line>
            <line>Before the dew of evening fall, shall fleet,</line>
            <line>In dreadful trial of our kingdom's king!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING PHILIP</speaker>
            <line>Amen, amen! Mount, chevaliers! to arms!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>Saint George, that swinged the dragon, and e'er since</line>
            <line>Sits on his horseback at mine hostess' door,</line>
            <line>Teach us some fence!</line>
            <stagedir>To AUSTRIA</stagedir>
            <line>Sirrah, were I at home,</line>
            <line>At your den, sirrah, with your lioness</line>
            <line>I would set an ox-head to your lion's hide,</line>
            <line>And make a monster of you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUSTRIA</speaker>
            <line>Peace! no more.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>O tremble, for you hear the lion roar.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>Up higher to the plain; where we'll set forth</line>
            <line>In best appointment all our regiments.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>Speed then, to take advantage of the field.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING PHILIP</speaker>
            <line>It shall be so; and at the other hill</line>
            <line>Command the rest to stand. God and our right!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Here after excursions, enter the Herald of France,
with trumpets, to the gates</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>French Herald</speaker>
            <line>You men of Angiers, open wide your gates,</line>
            <line>And let young Arthur, Duke of Bretagne, in,</line>
            <line>Who by the hand of France this day hath made</line>
            <line>Much work for tears in many an English mother,</line>
            <line>Whose sons lie scattered on the bleeding ground;</line>
            <line>Many a widow's husband grovelling lies,</line>
            <line>Coldly embracing the discolour'd earth;</line>
            <line>And victory, with little loss, doth play</line>
            <line>Upon the dancing banners of the French,</line>
            <line>Who are at hand, triumphantly display'd,</line>
            <line>To enter conquerors and to proclaim</line>
            <line>Arthur of Bretagne England's king and yours.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter English Herald, with trumpet</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>English Herald</speaker>
            <line>Rejoice, you men of Angiers, ring your bells:</line>
            <line>King John, your king and England's doth approach,</line>
            <line>Commander of this hot malicious day:</line>
            <line>Their armours, that march'd hence so silver-bright,</line>
            <line>Hither return all gilt with Frenchmen's blood;</line>
            <line>There stuck no plume in any English crest</line>
            <line>That is removed by a staff of France;</line>
            <line>Our colours do return in those same hands</line>
            <line>That did display them when we first march'd forth;</line>
            <line>And, like a troop of jolly huntsmen, come</line>
            <line>Our lusty English, all with purpled hands,</line>
            <line>Dyed in the dying slaughter of their foes:</line>
            <line>Open your gates and gives the victors way.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Heralds, from off our towers we might behold,</line>
            <line>From first to last, the onset and retire</line>
            <line>Of both your armies; whose equality</line>
            <line>By our best eyes cannot be censured:</line>
            <line>Blood hath bought blood and blows have answered blows;</line>
            <line>Strength match'd with strength, and power confronted power:</line>
            <line>Both are alike; and both alike we like.</line>
            <line>One must prove greatest: while they weigh so even,</line>
            <line>We hold our town for neither, yet for both.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter KING JOHN and KING PHILIP, with their
powers, severally</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>France, hast thou yet more blood to cast away?</line>
            <line>Say, shall the current of our right run on?</line>
            <line>Whose passage, vex'd with thy impediment,</line>
            <line>Shall leave his native channel and o'erswell</line>
            <line>With course disturb'd even thy confining shores,</line>
            <line>Unless thou let his silver water keep</line>
            <line>A peaceful progress to the ocean.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING PHILIP</speaker>
            <line>England, thou hast not saved one drop of blood,</line>
            <line>In this hot trial, more than we of France;</line>
            <line>Rather, lost more. And by this hand I swear,</line>
            <line>That sways the earth this climate overlooks,</line>
            <line>Before we will lay down our just-borne arms,</line>
            <line>We'll put thee down, 'gainst whom these arms we bear,</line>
            <line>Or add a royal number to the dead,</line>
            <line>Gracing the scroll that tells of this war's loss</line>
            <line>With slaughter coupled to the name of kings.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>Ha, majesty! how high thy glory towers,</line>
            <line>When the rich blood of kings is set on fire!</line>
            <line>O, now doth Death line his dead chaps with steel;</line>
            <line>The swords of soldiers are his teeth, his fangs;</line>
            <line>And now he feasts, mousing the flesh of men,</line>
            <line>In undetermined differences of kings.</line>
            <line>Why stand these royal fronts amazed thus?</line>
            <line>Cry, 'havoc!' kings; back to the stained field,</line>
            <line>You equal potents, fiery kindled spirits!</line>
            <line>Then let confusion of one part confirm</line>
            <line>The other's peace: till then, blows, blood and death!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>Whose party do the townsmen yet admit?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING PHILIP</speaker>
            <line>Speak, citizens, for England; who's your king?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>The king of England; when we know the king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING PHILIP</speaker>
            <line>Know him in us, that here hold up his right.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>In us, that are our own great deputy</line>
            <line>And bear possession of our person here,</line>
            <line>Lord of our presence, Angiers, and of you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>A greater power then we denies all this;</line>
            <line>And till it be undoubted, we do lock</line>
            <line>Our former scruple in our strong-barr'd gates;</line>
            <line>King'd of our fears, until our fears, resolved,</line>
            <line>Be by some certain king purged and deposed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>By heaven, these scroyles of Angiers flout you, kings,</line>
            <line>And stand securely on their battlements,</line>
            <line>As in a theatre, whence they gape and point</line>
            <line>At your industrious scenes and acts of death.</line>
            <line>Your royal presences be ruled by me:</line>
            <line>Do like the mutines of Jerusalem,</line>
            <line>Be friends awhile and both conjointly bend</line>
            <line>Your sharpest deeds of malice on this town:</line>
            <line>By east and west let France and England mount</line>
            <line>Their battering cannon charged to the mouths,</line>
            <line>Till their soul-fearing clamours have brawl'd down</line>
            <line>The flinty ribs of this contemptuous city:</line>
            <line>I'ld play incessantly upon these jades,</line>
            <line>Even till unfenced desolation</line>
            <line>Leave them as naked as the vulgar air.</line>
            <line>That done, dissever your united strengths,</line>
            <line>And part your mingled colours once again;</line>
            <line>Turn face to face and bloody point to point;</line>
            <line>Then, in a moment, Fortune shall cull forth</line>
            <line>Out of one side her happy minion,</line>
            <line>To whom in favour she shall give the day,</line>
            <line>And kiss him with a glorious victory.</line>
            <line>How like you this wild counsel, mighty states?</line>
            <line>Smacks it not something of the policy?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>Now, by the sky that hangs above our heads,</line>
            <line>I like it well. France, shall we knit our powers</line>
            <line>And lay this Angiers even to the ground;</line>
            <line>Then after fight who shall be king of it?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>An if thou hast the mettle of a king,</line>
            <line>Being wronged as we are by this peevish town,</line>
            <line>Turn thou the mouth of thy artillery,</line>
            <line>As we will ours, against these saucy walls;</line>
            <line>And when that we have dash'd them to the ground,</line>
            <line>Why then defy each other and pell-mell</line>
            <line>Make work upon ourselves, for heaven or hell.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING PHILIP</speaker>
            <line>Let it be so. Say, where will you assault?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>We from the west will send destruction</line>
            <line>Into this city's bosom.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUSTRIA</speaker>
            <line>I from the north.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING PHILIP</speaker>
            <line>Our thunder from the south</line>
            <line>Shall rain their drift of bullets on this town.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>O prudent discipline! From north to south:</line>
            <line>Austria and France shoot in each other's mouth:</line>
            <line>I'll stir them to it. Come, away, away!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Hear us, great kings: vouchsafe awhile to stay,</line>
            <line>And I shall show you peace and fair-faced league;</line>
            <line>Win you this city without stroke or wound;</line>
            <line>Rescue those breathing lives to die in beds,</line>
            <line>That here come sacrifices for the field:</line>
            <line>Persever not, but hear me, mighty kings.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>Speak on with favour; we are bent to hear.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>That daughter there of Spain, the Lady Blanch,</line>
            <line>Is niece to England: look upon the years</line>
            <line>Of Lewis the Dauphin and that lovely maid:</line>
            <line>If lusty love should go in quest of beauty,</line>
            <line>Where should he find it fairer than in Blanch?</line>
            <line>If zealous love should go in search of virtue,</line>
            <line>Where should he find it purer than in Blanch?</line>
            <line>If love ambitious sought a match of birth,</line>
            <line>Whose veins bound richer blood than Lady Blanch?</line>
            <line>Such as she is, in beauty, virtue, birth,</line>
            <line>Is the young Dauphin every way complete:</line>
            <line>If not complete of, say he is not she;</line>
            <line>And she again wants nothing, to name want,</line>
            <line>If want it be not that she is not he:</line>
            <line>He is the half part of a blessed man,</line>
            <line>Left to be finished by such as she;</line>
            <line>And she a fair divided excellence,</line>
            <line>Whose fulness of perfection lies in him.</line>
            <line>O, two such silver currents, when they join,</line>
            <line>Do glorify the banks that bound them in;</line>
            <line>And two such shores to two such streams made one,</line>
            <line>Two such controlling bounds shall you be, kings,</line>
            <line>To these two princes, if you marry them.</line>
            <line>This union shall do more than battery can</line>
            <line>To our fast-closed gates; for at this match,</line>
            <line>With swifter spleen than powder can enforce,</line>
            <line>The mouth of passage shall we fling wide ope,</line>
            <line>And give you entrance: but without this match,</line>
            <line>The sea enraged is not half so deaf,</line>
            <line>Lions more confident, mountains and rocks</line>
            <line>More free from motion, no, not Death himself</line>
            <line>In moral fury half so peremptory,</line>
            <line>As we to keep this city.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>Here's a stay</line>
            <line>That shakes the rotten carcass of old Death</line>
            <line>Out of his rags! Here's a large mouth, indeed,</line>
            <line>That spits forth death and mountains, rocks and seas,</line>
            <line>Talks as familiarly of roaring lions</line>
            <line>As maids of thirteen do of puppy-dogs!</line>
            <line>What cannoneer begot this lusty blood?</line>
            <line>He speaks plain cannon fire, and smoke and bounce;</line>
            <line>He gives the bastinado with his tongue:</line>
            <line>Our ears are cudgell'd; not a word of his</line>
            <line>But buffets better than a fist of France:</line>
            <line>Zounds! I was never so bethump'd with words</line>
            <line>Since I first call'd my brother's father dad.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELINOR</speaker>
            <line>Son, list to this conjunction, make this match;</line>
            <line>Give with our niece a dowry large enough:</line>
            <line>For by this knot thou shalt so surely tie</line>
            <line>Thy now unsured assurance to the crown,</line>
            <line>That yon green boy shall have no sun to ripe</line>
            <line>The bloom that promiseth a mighty fruit.</line>
            <line>I see a yielding in the looks of France;</line>
            <line>Mark, how they whisper: urge them while their souls</line>
            <line>Are capable of this ambition,</line>
            <line>Lest zeal, now melted by the windy breath</line>
            <line>Of soft petitions, pity and remorse,</line>
            <line>Cool and congeal again to what it was.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Why answer not the double majesties</line>
            <line>This friendly treaty of our threaten'd town?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING PHILIP</speaker>
            <line>Speak England first, that hath been forward first</line>
            <line>To speak unto this city: what say you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>If that the Dauphin there, thy princely son,</line>
            <line>Can in this book of beauty read 'I love,'</line>
            <line>Her dowry shall weigh equal with a queen:</line>
            <line>For Anjou and fair Touraine, Maine, Poictiers,</line>
            <line>And all that we upon this side the sea,</line>
            <line>Except this city now by us besieged,</line>
            <line>Find liable to our crown and dignity,</line>
            <line>Shall gild her bridal bed and make her rich</line>
            <line>In titles, honours and promotions,</line>
            <line>As she in beauty, education, blood,</line>
            <line>Holds hand with any princess of the world.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING PHILIP</speaker>
            <line>What say'st thou, boy? look in the lady's face.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEWIS</speaker>
            <line>I do, my lord; and in her eye I find</line>
            <line>A wonder, or a wondrous miracle,</line>
            <line>The shadow of myself form'd in her eye:</line>
            <line>Which being but the shadow of your son,</line>
            <line>Becomes a sun and makes your son a shadow:</line>
            <line>I do protest I never loved myself</line>
            <line>Till now infixed I beheld myself</line>
            <line>Drawn in the flattering table of her eye.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Whispers with BLANCH</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>Drawn in the flattering table of her eye!</line>
            <line>Hang'd in the frowning wrinkle of her brow!</line>
            <line>And quarter'd in her heart! he doth espy</line>
            <line>Himself love's traitor: this is pity now,</line>
            <line>That hang'd and drawn and quartered, there should be</line>
            <line>In such a love so vile a lout as he.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BLANCH</speaker>
            <line>My uncle's will in this respect is mine:</line>
            <line>If he see aught in you that makes him like,</line>
            <line>That any thing he sees, which moves his liking,</line>
            <line>I can with ease translate it to my will;</line>
            <line>Or if you will, to speak more properly,</line>
            <line>I will enforce it easily to my love.</line>
            <line>Further I will not flatter you, my lord,</line>
            <line>That all I see in you is worthy love,</line>
            <line>Than this; that nothing do I see in you,</line>
            <line>Though churlish thoughts themselves should be your judge,</line>
            <line>That I can find should merit any hate.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>What say these young ones? What say you my niece?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BLANCH</speaker>
            <line>That she is bound in honour still to do</line>
            <line>What you in wisdom still vouchsafe to say.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>Speak then, prince Dauphin; can you love this lady?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEWIS</speaker>
            <line>Nay, ask me if I can refrain from love;</line>
            <line>For I do love her most unfeignedly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>Then do I give Volquessen, Touraine, Maine,</line>
            <line>Poictiers and Anjou, these five provinces,</line>
            <line>With her to thee; and this addition more,</line>
            <line>Full thirty thousand marks of English coin.</line>
            <line>Philip of France, if thou be pleased withal,</line>
            <line>Command thy son and daughter to join hands.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING PHILIP</speaker>
            <line>It likes us well; young princes, close your hands.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUSTRIA</speaker>
            <line>And your lips too; for I am well assured</line>
            <line>That I did so when I was first assured.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING PHILIP</speaker>
            <line>Now, citizens of Angiers, ope your gates,</line>
            <line>Let in that amity which you have made;</line>
            <line>For at Saint Mary's chapel presently</line>
            <line>The rites of marriage shall be solemnized.</line>
            <line>Is not the Lady Constance in this troop?</line>
            <line>I know she is not, for this match made up</line>
            <line>Her presence would have interrupted much:</line>
            <line>Where is she and her son? tell me, who knows.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEWIS</speaker>
            <line>She is sad and passionate at your highness' tent.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING PHILIP</speaker>
            <line>And, by my faith, this league that we have made</line>
            <line>Will give her sadness very little cure.</line>
            <line>Brother of England, how may we content</line>
            <line>This widow lady? In her right we came;</line>
            <line>Which we, God knows, have turn'd another way,</line>
            <line>To our own vantage.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>We will heal up all;</line>
            <line>For we'll create young Arthur Duke of Bretagne</line>
            <line>And Earl of Richmond; and this rich fair town</line>
            <line>We make him lord of. Call the Lady Constance;</line>
            <line>Some speedy messenger bid her repair</line>
            <line>To our solemnity: I trust we shall,</line>
            <line>If not fill up the measure of her will,</line>
            <line>Yet in some measure satisfy her so</line>
            <line>That we shall stop her exclamation.</line>
            <line>Go we, as well as haste will suffer us,</line>
            <line>To this unlook'd for, unprepared pomp.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt all but the BASTARD</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>Mad world! mad kings! mad composition!</line>
            <line>John, to stop Arthur's title in the whole,</line>
            <line>Hath willingly departed with a part,</line>
            <line>And France, whose armour conscience buckled on,</line>
            <line>Whom zeal and charity brought to the field</line>
            <line>As God's own soldier, rounded in the ear</line>
            <line>With that same purpose-changer, that sly devil,</line>
            <line>That broker, that still breaks the pate of faith,</line>
            <line>That daily break-vow, he that wins of all,</line>
            <line>Of kings, of beggars, old men, young men, maids,</line>
            <line>Who, having no external thing to lose</line>
            <line>But the word 'maid,' cheats the poor maid of that,</line>
            <line>That smooth-faced gentleman, tickling Commodity,</line>
            <line>Commodity, the bias of the world,</line>
            <line>The world, who of itself is peised well,</line>
            <line>Made to run even upon even ground,</line>
            <line>Till this advantage, this vile-drawing bias,</line>
            <line>This sway of motion, this Commodity,</line>
            <line>Makes it take head from all indifferency,</line>
            <line>From all direction, purpose, course, intent:</line>
            <line>And this same bias, this Commodity,</line>
            <line>This bawd, this broker, this all-changing word,</line>
            <line>Clapp'd on the outward eye of fickle France,</line>
            <line>Hath drawn him from his own determined aid,</line>
            <line>From a resolved and honourable war,</line>
            <line>To a most base and vile-concluded peace.</line>
            <line>And why rail I on this Commodity?</line>
            <line>But for because he hath not woo'd me yet:</line>
            <line>Not that I have the power to clutch my hand,</line>
            <line>When his fair angels would salute my palm;</line>
            <line>But for my hand, as unattempted yet,</line>
            <line>Like a poor beggar, raileth on the rich.</line>
            <line>Well, whiles I am a beggar, I will rail</line>
            <line>And say there is no sin but to be rich;</line>
            <line>And being rich, my virtue then shall be</line>
            <line>To say there is no vice but beggary.</line>
            <line>Since kings break faith upon commodity,</line>
            <line>Gain, be my lord, for I will worship thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>