<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net/doctypes/dita/shakespear/dtd/act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-4">
   <title>ACT IV</title>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  A room in a castle.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter HUBERT and Executioners</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HUBERT</speaker>
            <line>Heat me these irons hot; and look thou stand</line>
            <line>Within the arras: when I strike my foot</line>
            <line>Upon the bosom of the ground, rush forth,</line>
            <line>And bind the boy which you shall find with me</line>
            <line>Fast to the chair: be heedful: hence, and watch.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Executioner</speaker>
            <line>I hope your warrant will bear out the deed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HUBERT</speaker>
            <line>Uncleanly scruples! fear not you: look to't.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt Executioners</stagedir>
            <line>Young lad, come forth; I have to say with you.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter ARTHUR</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARTHUR</speaker>
            <line>Good morrow, Hubert.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HUBERT</speaker>
            <line>Good morrow, little prince.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARTHUR</speaker>
            <line>As little prince, having so great a title</line>
            <line>To be more prince, as may be. You are sad.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HUBERT</speaker>
            <line>Indeed, I have been merrier.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARTHUR</speaker>
            <line>Mercy on me!</line>
            <line>Methinks no body should be sad but I:</line>
            <line>Yet, I remember, when I was in France,</line>
            <line>Young gentlemen would be as sad as night,</line>
            <line>Only for wantonness. By my christendom,</line>
            <line>So I were out of prison and kept sheep,</line>
            <line>I should be as merry as the day is long;</line>
            <line>And so I would be here, but that I doubt</line>
            <line>My uncle practises more harm to me:</line>
            <line>He is afraid of me and I of him:</line>
            <line>Is it my fault that I was Geffrey's son?</line>
            <line>No, indeed, is't not; and I would to heaven</line>
            <line>I were your son, so you would love me, Hubert.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HUBERT</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  If I talk to him, with his innocent prate</line>
            <line>He will awake my mercy which lies dead:</line>
            <line>Therefore I will be sudden and dispatch.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARTHUR</speaker>
            <line>Are you sick, Hubert? you look pale to-day:</line>
            <line>In sooth, I would you were a little sick,</line>
            <line>That I might sit all night and watch with you:</line>
            <line>I warrant I love you more than you do me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HUBERT</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  His words do take possession of my bosom.</line>
            <line>Read here, young Arthur.</line>
            <stagedir>Showing a paper</stagedir>
            <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>
            <line>How now, foolish rheum!</line>
            <line>Turning dispiteous torture out of door!</line>
            <line>I must be brief, lest resolution drop</line>
            <line>Out at mine eyes in tender womanish tears.</line>
            <line>Can you not read it? Is it not fair writ?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARTHUR</speaker>
            <line>Too fairly, Hubert, for so foul effect:</line>
            <line>Must you with hot irons burn out both mine eyes?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HUBERT</speaker>
            <line>Young boy, I must.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARTHUR</speaker>
            <line>And will you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HUBERT</speaker>
            <line>And I will.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARTHUR</speaker>
            <line>Have you the heart? When your head did but ache,</line>
            <line>I knit my handercher about your brows,</line>
            <line>The best I had, a princess wrought it me,</line>
            <line>And I did never ask it you again;</line>
            <line>And with my hand at midnight held your head,</line>
            <line>And like the watchful minutes to the hour,</line>
            <line>Still and anon cheer'd up the heavy time,</line>
            <line>Saying, 'What lack you?' and 'Where lies your grief?'</line>
            <line>Or 'What good love may I perform for you?'</line>
            <line>Many a poor man's son would have lien still</line>
            <line>And ne'er have spoke a loving word to you;</line>
            <line>But you at your sick service had a prince.</line>
            <line>Nay, you may think my love was crafty love</line>
            <line>And call it cunning: do, an if you will:</line>
            <line>If heaven be pleased that you must use me ill,</line>
            <line>Why then you must. Will you put out mine eyes?</line>
            <line>These eyes that never did nor never shall</line>
            <line>So much as frown on you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HUBERT</speaker>
            <line>I have sworn to do it;</line>
            <line>And with hot irons must I burn them out.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARTHUR</speaker>
            <line>Ah, none but in this iron age would do it!</line>
            <line>The iron of itself, though heat red-hot,</line>
            <line>Approaching near these eyes, would drink my tears</line>
            <line>And quench his fiery indignation</line>
            <line>Even in the matter of mine innocence;</line>
            <line>Nay, after that, consume away in rust</line>
            <line>But for containing fire to harm mine eye.</line>
            <line>Are you more stubborn-hard than hammer'd iron?</line>
            <line>An if an angel should have come to me</line>
            <line>And told me Hubert should put out mine eyes,</line>
            <line>I would not have believed him,--no tongue but Hubert's.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HUBERT</speaker>
            <line>Come forth.</line>
            <stagedir>Stamps</stagedir>
            <stagedir>Re-enter Executioners, with a cord, irons, &amp;c</stagedir>
            <line>Do as I bid you do.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARTHUR</speaker>
            <line>O, save me, Hubert, save me! my eyes are out</line>
            <line>Even with the fierce looks of these bloody men.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HUBERT</speaker>
            <line>Give me the iron, I say, and bind him here.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARTHUR</speaker>
            <line>Alas, what need you be so boisterous-rough?</line>
            <line>I will not struggle, I will stand stone-still.</line>
            <line>For heaven sake, Hubert, let me not be bound!</line>
            <line>Nay, hear me, Hubert, drive these men away,</line>
            <line>And I will sit as quiet as a lamb;</line>
            <line>I will not stir, nor wince, nor speak a word,</line>
            <line>Nor look upon the iron angerly:</line>
            <line>Thrust but these men away, and I'll forgive you,</line>
            <line>Whatever torment you do put me to.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HUBERT</speaker>
            <line>Go, stand within; let me alone with him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Executioner</speaker>
            <line>I am best pleased to be from such a deed.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt Executioners</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARTHUR</speaker>
            <line>Alas, I then have chid away my friend!</line>
            <line>He hath a stern look, but a gentle heart:</line>
            <line>Let him come back, that his compassion may</line>
            <line>Give life to yours.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HUBERT</speaker>
            <line>Come, boy, prepare yourself.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARTHUR</speaker>
            <line>Is there no remedy?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HUBERT</speaker>
            <line>None, but to lose your eyes.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARTHUR</speaker>
            <line>O heaven, that there were but a mote in yours,</line>
            <line>A grain, a dust, a gnat, a wandering hair,</line>
            <line>Any annoyance in that precious sense!</line>
            <line>Then feeling what small things are boisterous there,</line>
            <line>Your vile intent must needs seem horrible.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HUBERT</speaker>
            <line>Is this your promise? go to, hold your tongue.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARTHUR</speaker>
            <line>Hubert, the utterance of a brace of tongues</line>
            <line>Must needs want pleading for a pair of eyes:</line>
            <line>Let me not hold my tongue, let me not, Hubert;</line>
            <line>Or, Hubert, if you will, cut out my tongue,</line>
            <line>So I may keep mine eyes: O, spare mine eyes.</line>
            <line>Though to no use but still to look on you!</line>
            <line>Lo, by my truth, the instrument is cold</line>
            <line>And would not harm me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HUBERT</speaker>
            <line>I can heat it, boy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARTHUR</speaker>
            <line>No, in good sooth: the fire is dead with grief,</line>
            <line>Being create for comfort, to be used</line>
            <line>In undeserved extremes: see else yourself;</line>
            <line>There is no malice in this burning coal;</line>
            <line>The breath of heaven has blown his spirit out</line>
            <line>And strew'd repentent ashes on his head.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HUBERT</speaker>
            <line>But with my breath I can revive it, boy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARTHUR</speaker>
            <line>An if you do, you will but make it blush</line>
            <line>And glow with shame of your proceedings, Hubert:</line>
            <line>Nay, it perchance will sparkle in your eyes;</line>
            <line>And like a dog that is compell'd to fight,</line>
            <line>Snatch at his master that doth tarre him on.</line>
            <line>All things that you should use to do me wrong</line>
            <line>Deny their office: only you do lack</line>
            <line>That mercy which fierce fire and iron extends,</line>
            <line>Creatures of note for mercy-lacking uses.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HUBERT</speaker>
            <line>Well, see to live; I will not touch thine eye</line>
            <line>For all the treasure that thine uncle owes:</line>
            <line>Yet am I sworn and I did purpose, boy,</line>
            <line>With this same very iron to burn them out.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARTHUR</speaker>
            <line>O, now you look like Hubert! all this while</line>
            <line>You were disguised.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HUBERT</speaker>
            <line>Peace; no more. Adieu.</line>
            <line>Your uncle must not know but you are dead;</line>
            <line>I'll fill these dogged spies with false reports:</line>
            <line>And, pretty child, sleep doubtless and secure,</line>
            <line>That Hubert, for the wealth of all the world,</line>
            <line>Will not offend thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARTHUR</speaker>
            <line>O heaven! I thank you, Hubert.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HUBERT</speaker>
            <line>Silence; no more: go closely in with me:</line>
            <line>Much danger do I undergo for thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  KING JOHN'S palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter KING JOHN, PEMBROKE, SALISBURY, and other Lords</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>Here once again we sit, once again crown'd,</line>
            <line>And looked upon, I hope, with cheerful eyes.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PEMBROKE</speaker>
            <line>This 'once again,' but that your highness pleased,</line>
            <line>Was once superfluous: you were crown'd before,</line>
            <line>And that high royalty was ne'er pluck'd off,</line>
            <line>The faiths of men ne'er stained with revolt;</line>
            <line>Fresh expectation troubled not the land</line>
            <line>With any long'd-for change or better state.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALISBURY</speaker>
            <line>Therefore, to be possess'd with double pomp,</line>
            <line>To guard a title that was rich before,</line>
            <line>To gild refined gold, to paint the lily,</line>
            <line>To throw a perfume on the violet,</line>
            <line>To smooth the ice, or add another hue</line>
            <line>Unto the rainbow, or with taper-light</line>
            <line>To seek the beauteous eye of heaven to garnish,</line>
            <line>Is wasteful and ridiculous excess.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PEMBROKE</speaker>
            <line>But that your royal pleasure must be done,</line>
            <line>This act is as an ancient tale new told,</line>
            <line>And in the last repeating troublesome,</line>
            <line>Being urged at a time unseasonable.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALISBURY</speaker>
            <line>In this the antique and well noted face</line>
            <line>Of plain old form is much disfigured;</line>
            <line>And, like a shifted wind unto a sail,</line>
            <line>It makes the course of thoughts to fetch about,</line>
            <line>Startles and frights consideration,</line>
            <line>Makes sound opinion sick and truth suspected,</line>
            <line>For putting on so new a fashion'd robe.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PEMBROKE</speaker>
            <line>When workmen strive to do better than well,</line>
            <line>They do confound their skill in covetousness;</line>
            <line>And oftentimes excusing of a fault</line>
            <line>Doth make the fault the worse by the excuse,</line>
            <line>As patches set upon a little breach</line>
            <line>Discredit more in hiding of the fault</line>
            <line>Than did the fault before it was so patch'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALISBURY</speaker>
            <line>To this effect, before you were new crown'd,</line>
            <line>We breathed our counsel: but it pleased your highness</line>
            <line>To overbear it, and we are all well pleased,</line>
            <line>Since all and every part of what we would</line>
            <line>Doth make a stand at what your highness will.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>Some reasons of this double coronation</line>
            <line>I have possess'd you with and think them strong;</line>
            <line>And more, more strong, then lesser is my fear,</line>
            <line>I shall indue you with: meantime but ask</line>
            <line>What you would have reform'd that is not well,</line>
            <line>And well shall you perceive how willingly</line>
            <line>I will both hear and grant you your requests.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PEMBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Then I, as one that am the tongue of these,</line>
            <line>To sound the purpose of all their hearts,</line>
            <line>Both for myself and them, but, chief of all,</line>
            <line>Your safety, for the which myself and them</line>
            <line>Bend their best studies, heartily request</line>
            <line>The enfranchisement of Arthur; whose restraint</line>
            <line>Doth move the murmuring lips of discontent</line>
            <line>To break into this dangerous argument,--</line>
            <line>If what in rest you have in right you hold,</line>
            <line>Why then your fears, which, as they say, attend</line>
            <line>The steps of wrong, should move you to mew up</line>
            <line>Your tender kinsman and to choke his days</line>
            <line>With barbarous ignorance and deny his youth</line>
            <line>The rich advantage of good exercise?</line>
            <line>That the time's enemies may not have this</line>
            <line>To grace occasions, let it be our suit</line>
            <line>That you have bid us ask his liberty;</line>
            <line>Which for our goods we do no further ask</line>
            <line>Than whereupon our weal, on you depending,</line>
            <line>Counts it your weal he have his liberty.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter HUBERT</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>Let it be so: I do commit his youth</line>
            <line>To your direction. Hubert, what news with you?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Taking him apart</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PEMBROKE</speaker>
            <line>This is the man should do the bloody deed;</line>
            <line>He show'd his warrant to a friend of mine:</line>
            <line>The image of a wicked heinous fault</line>
            <line>Lives in his eye; that close aspect of his</line>
            <line>Does show the mood of a much troubled breast;</line>
            <line>And I do fearfully believe 'tis done,</line>
            <line>What we so fear'd he had a charge to do.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALISBURY</speaker>
            <line>The colour of the king doth come and go</line>
            <line>Between his purpose and his conscience,</line>
            <line>Like heralds 'twixt two dreadful battles set:</line>
            <line>His passion is so ripe, it needs must break.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PEMBROKE</speaker>
            <line>And when it breaks, I fear will issue thence</line>
            <line>The foul corruption of a sweet child's death.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>We cannot hold mortality's strong hand:</line>
            <line>Good lords, although my will to give is living,</line>
            <line>The suit which you demand is gone and dead:</line>
            <line>He tells us Arthur is deceased to-night.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALISBURY</speaker>
            <line>Indeed we fear'd his sickness was past cure.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PEMBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Indeed we heard how near his death he was</line>
            <line>Before the child himself felt he was sick:</line>
            <line>This must be answer'd either here or hence.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>Why do you bend such solemn brows on me?</line>
            <line>Think you I bear the shears of destiny?</line>
            <line>Have I commandment on the pulse of life?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALISBURY</speaker>
            <line>It is apparent foul play; and 'tis shame</line>
            <line>That greatness should so grossly offer it:</line>
            <line>So thrive it in your game! and so, farewell.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PEMBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Stay yet, Lord Salisbury; I'll go with thee,</line>
            <line>And find the inheritance of this poor child,</line>
            <line>His little kingdom of a forced grave.</line>
            <line>That blood which owed the breadth of all this isle,</line>
            <line>Three foot of it doth hold: bad world the while!</line>
            <line>This must not be thus borne: this will break out</line>
            <line>To all our sorrows, and ere long I doubt.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt Lords</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>They burn in indignation. I repent:</line>
            <line>There is no sure foundation set on blood,</line>
            <line>No certain life achieved by others' death.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter a Messenger</stagedir>
            <line>A fearful eye thou hast: where is that blood</line>
            <line>That I have seen inhabit in those cheeks?</line>
            <line>So foul a sky clears not without a storm:</line>
            <line>Pour down thy weather: how goes all in France?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>From France to England. Never such a power</line>
            <line>For any foreign preparation</line>
            <line>Was levied in the body of a land.</line>
            <line>The copy of your speed is learn'd by them;</line>
            <line>For when you should be told they do prepare,</line>
            <line>The tidings come that they are all arrived.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>O, where hath our intelligence been drunk?</line>
            <line>Where hath it slept? Where is my mother's care,</line>
            <line>That such an army could be drawn in France,</line>
            <line>And she not hear of it?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>My liege, her ear</line>
            <line>Is stopp'd with dust; the first of April died</line>
            <line>Your noble mother: and, as I hear, my lord,</line>
            <line>The Lady Constance in a frenzy died</line>
            <line>Three days before: but this from rumour's tongue</line>
            <line>I idly heard; if true or false I know not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>Withhold thy speed, dreadful occasion!</line>
            <line>O, make a league with me, till I have pleased</line>
            <line>My discontented peers! What! mother dead!</line>
            <line>How wildly then walks my estate in France!</line>
            <line>Under whose conduct came those powers of France</line>
            <line>That thou for truth givest out are landed here?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>Under the Dauphin.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>Thou hast made me giddy</line>
            <line>With these ill tidings.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter the BASTARD and PETER of Pomfret</stagedir>
            <line>Now, what says the world</line>
            <line>To your proceedings? do not seek to stuff</line>
            <line>My head with more ill news, for it is full.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>But if you be afeard to hear the worst,</line>
            <line>Then let the worst unheard fall on your bead.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>Bear with me cousin, for I was amazed</line>
            <line>Under the tide: but now I breathe again</line>
            <line>Aloft the flood, and can give audience</line>
            <line>To any tongue, speak it of what it will.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>How I have sped among the clergymen,</line>
            <line>The sums I have collected shall express.</line>
            <line>But as I travell'd hither through the land,</line>
            <line>I find the people strangely fantasied;</line>
            <line>Possess'd with rumours, full of idle dreams,</line>
            <line>Not knowing what they fear, but full of fear:</line>
            <line>And here a prophet, that I brought with me</line>
            <line>From forth the streets of Pomfret, whom I found</line>
            <line>With many hundreds treading on his heels;</line>
            <line>To whom he sung, in rude harsh-sounding rhymes,</line>
            <line>That, ere the next Ascension-day at noon,</line>
            <line>Your highness should deliver up your crown.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>Thou idle dreamer, wherefore didst thou so?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETER</speaker>
            <line>Foreknowing that the truth will fall out so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>Hubert, away with him; imprison him;</line>
            <line>And on that day at noon whereon he says</line>
            <line>I shall yield up my crown, let him be hang'd.</line>
            <line>Deliver him to safety; and return,</line>
            <line>For I must use thee.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt HUBERT with PETER</stagedir>
            <line>O my gentle cousin,</line>
            <line>Hear'st thou the news abroad, who are arrived?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>The French, my lord; men's mouths are full of it:</line>
            <line>Besides, I met Lord Bigot and Lord Salisbury,</line>
            <line>With eyes as red as new-enkindled fire,</line>
            <line>And others more, going to seek the grave</line>
            <line>Of Arthur, who they say is kill'd to-night</line>
            <line>On your suggestion.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>Gentle kinsman, go,</line>
            <line>And thrust thyself into their companies:</line>
            <line>I have a way to win their loves again;</line>
            <line>Bring them before me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>I will seek them out.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>Nay, but make haste; the better foot before.</line>
            <line>O, let me have no subject enemies,</line>
            <line>When adverse foreigners affright my towns</line>
            <line>With dreadful pomp of stout invasion!</line>
            <line>Be Mercury, set feathers to thy heels,</line>
            <line>And fly like thought from them to me again.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>The spirit of the time shall teach me speed.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>Spoke like a sprightful noble gentleman.</line>
            <line>Go after him; for he perhaps shall need</line>
            <line>Some messenger betwixt me and the peers;</line>
            <line>And be thou he.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>With all my heart, my liege.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>My mother dead!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter HUBERT</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HUBERT</speaker>
            <line>My lord, they say five moons were seen to-night;</line>
            <line>Four fixed, and the fifth did whirl about</line>
            <line>The other four in wondrous motion.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>Five moons!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HUBERT</speaker>
            <line>Old men and beldams in the streets</line>
            <line>Do prophesy upon it dangerously:</line>
            <line>Young Arthur's death is common in their mouths:</line>
            <line>And when they talk of him, they shake their heads</line>
            <line>And whisper one another in the ear;</line>
            <line>And he that speaks doth gripe the hearer's wrist,</line>
            <line>Whilst he that hears makes fearful action,</line>
            <line>With wrinkled brows, with nods, with rolling eyes.</line>
            <line>I saw a smith stand with his hammer, thus,</line>
            <line>The whilst his iron did on the anvil cool,</line>
            <line>With open mouth swallowing a tailor's news;</line>
            <line>Who, with his shears and measure in his hand,</line>
            <line>Standing on slippers, which his nimble haste</line>
            <line>Had falsely thrust upon contrary feet,</line>
            <line>Told of a many thousand warlike French</line>
            <line>That were embattailed and rank'd in Kent:</line>
            <line>Another lean unwash'd artificer</line>
            <line>Cuts off his tale and talks of Arthur's death.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>Why seek'st thou to possess me with these fears?</line>
            <line>Why urgest thou so oft young Arthur's death?</line>
            <line>Thy hand hath murder'd him: I had a mighty cause</line>
            <line>To wish him dead, but thou hadst none to kill him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HUBERT</speaker>
            <line>No had, my lord! why, did you not provoke me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>It is the curse of kings to be attended</line>
            <line>By slaves that take their humours for a warrant</line>
            <line>To break within the bloody house of life,</line>
            <line>And on the winking of authority</line>
            <line>To understand a law, to know the meaning</line>
            <line>Of dangerous majesty, when perchance it frowns</line>
            <line>More upon humour than advised respect.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HUBERT</speaker>
            <line>Here is your hand and seal for what I did.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>O, when the last account 'twixt heaven and earth</line>
            <line>Is to be made, then shall this hand and seal</line>
            <line>Witness against us to damnation!</line>
            <line>How oft the sight of means to do ill deeds</line>
            <line>Make deeds ill done! Hadst not thou been by,</line>
            <line>A fellow by the hand of nature mark'd,</line>
            <line>Quoted and sign'd to do a deed of shame,</line>
            <line>This murder had not come into my mind:</line>
            <line>But taking note of thy abhorr'd aspect,</line>
            <line>Finding thee fit for bloody villany,</line>
            <line>Apt, liable to be employ'd in danger,</line>
            <line>I faintly broke with thee of Arthur's death;</line>
            <line>And thou, to be endeared to a king,</line>
            <line>Made it no conscience to destroy a prince.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HUBERT</speaker>
            <line>My lord--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>Hadst thou but shook thy head or made a pause</line>
            <line>When I spake darkly what I purposed,</line>
            <line>Or turn'd an eye of doubt upon my face,</line>
            <line>As bid me tell my tale in express words,</line>
            <line>Deep shame had struck me dumb, made me break off,</line>
            <line>And those thy fears might have wrought fears in me:</line>
            <line>But thou didst understand me by my signs</line>
            <line>And didst in signs again parley with sin;</line>
            <line>Yea, without stop, didst let thy heart consent,</line>
            <line>And consequently thy rude hand to act</line>
            <line>The deed, which both our tongues held vile to name.</line>
            <line>Out of my sight, and never see me more!</line>
            <line>My nobles leave me; and my state is braved,</line>
            <line>Even at my gates, with ranks of foreign powers:</line>
            <line>Nay, in the body of this fleshly land,</line>
            <line>This kingdom, this confine of blood and breath,</line>
            <line>Hostility and civil tumult reigns</line>
            <line>Between my conscience and my cousin's death.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HUBERT</speaker>
            <line>Arm you against your other enemies,</line>
            <line>I'll make a peace between your soul and you.</line>
            <line>Young Arthur is alive: this hand of mine</line>
            <line>Is yet a maiden and an innocent hand,</line>
            <line>Not painted with the crimson spots of blood.</line>
            <line>Within this bosom never enter'd yet</line>
            <line>The dreadful motion of a murderous thought;</line>
            <line>And you have slander'd nature in my form,</line>
            <line>Which, howsoever rude exteriorly,</line>
            <line>Is yet the cover of a fairer mind</line>
            <line>Than to be butcher of an innocent child.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING JOHN</speaker>
            <line>Doth Arthur live? O, haste thee to the peers,</line>
            <line>Throw this report on their incensed rage,</line>
            <line>And make them tame to their obedience!</line>
            <line>Forgive the comment that my passion made</line>
            <line>Upon thy feature; for my rage was blind,</line>
            <line>And foul imaginary eyes of blood</line>
            <line>Presented thee more hideous than thou art.</line>
            <line>O, answer not, but to my closet bring</line>
            <line>The angry lords with all expedient haste.</line>
            <line>I conjure thee but slowly; run more fast.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  Before the castle.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter ARTHUR, on the walls</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARTHUR</speaker>
            <line>The wall is high, and yet will I leap down:</line>
            <line>Good ground, be pitiful and hurt me not!</line>
            <line>There's few or none do know me: if they did,</line>
            <line>This ship-boy's semblance hath disguised me quite.</line>
            <line>I am afraid; and yet I'll venture it.</line>
            <line>If I get down, and do not break my limbs,</line>
            <line>I'll find a thousand shifts to get away:</line>
            <line>As good to die and go, as die and stay.</line>
            <stagedir>Leaps down</stagedir>
            <line>O me! my uncle's spirit is in these stones:</line>
            <line>Heaven take my soul, and England keep my bones!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Dies</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Enter PEMBROKE, SALISBURY, and BIGOT</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALISBURY</speaker>
            <line>Lords, I will meet him at Saint Edmundsbury:</line>
            <line>It is our safety, and we must embrace</line>
            <line>This gentle offer of the perilous time.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PEMBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Who brought that letter from the cardinal?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALISBURY</speaker>
            <line>The Count Melun, a noble lord of France,</line>
            <line>Whose private with me of the Dauphin's love</line>
            <line>Is much more general than these lines import.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIGOT</speaker>
            <line>To-morrow morning let us meet him then.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALISBURY</speaker>
            <line>Or rather then set forward; for 'twill be</line>
            <line>Two long days' journey, lords, or ere we meet.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter the BASTARD</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>Once more to-day well met, distemper'd lords!</line>
            <line>The king by me requests your presence straight.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALISBURY</speaker>
            <line>The king hath dispossess'd himself of us:</line>
            <line>We will not line his thin bestained cloak</line>
            <line>With our pure honours, nor attend the foot</line>
            <line>That leaves the print of blood where'er it walks.</line>
            <line>Return and tell him so: we know the worst.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>Whate'er you think, good words, I think, were best.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALISBURY</speaker>
            <line>Our griefs, and not our manners, reason now.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>But there is little reason in your grief;</line>
            <line>Therefore 'twere reason you had manners now.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PEMBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Sir, sir, impatience hath his privilege.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>'Tis true, to hurt his master, no man else.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALISBURY</speaker>
            <line>This is the prison. What is he lies here?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Seeing ARTHUR</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PEMBROKE</speaker>
            <line>O death, made proud with pure and princely beauty!</line>
            <line>The earth had not a hole to hide this deed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALISBURY</speaker>
            <line>Murder, as hating what himself hath done,</line>
            <line>Doth lay it open to urge on revenge.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIGOT</speaker>
            <line>Or, when he doom'd this beauty to a grave,</line>
            <line>Found it too precious-princely for a grave.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALISBURY</speaker>
            <line>Sir Richard, what think you? have you beheld,</line>
            <line>Or have you read or heard? or could you think?</line>
            <line>Or do you almost think, although you see,</line>
            <line>That you do see? could thought, without this object,</line>
            <line>Form such another? This is the very top,</line>
            <line>The height, the crest, or crest unto the crest,</line>
            <line>Of murder's arms: this is the bloodiest shame,</line>
            <line>The wildest savagery, the vilest stroke,</line>
            <line>That ever wall-eyed wrath or staring rage</line>
            <line>Presented to the tears of soft remorse.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PEMBROKE</speaker>
            <line>All murders past do stand excused in this:</line>
            <line>And this, so sole and so unmatchable,</line>
            <line>Shall give a holiness, a purity,</line>
            <line>To the yet unbegotten sin of times;</line>
            <line>And prove a deadly bloodshed but a jest,</line>
            <line>Exampled by this heinous spectacle.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>It is a damned and a bloody work;</line>
            <line>The graceless action of a heavy hand,</line>
            <line>If that it be the work of any hand.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALISBURY</speaker>
            <line>If that it be the work of any hand!</line>
            <line>We had a kind of light what would ensue:</line>
            <line>It is the shameful work of Hubert's hand;</line>
            <line>The practise and the purpose of the king:</line>
            <line>From whose obedience I forbid my soul,</line>
            <line>Kneeling before this ruin of sweet life,</line>
            <line>And breathing to his breathless excellence</line>
            <line>The incense of a vow, a holy vow,</line>
            <line>Never to taste the pleasures of the world,</line>
            <line>Never to be infected with delight,</line>
            <line>Nor conversant with ease and idleness,</line>
            <line>Till I have set a glory to this hand,</line>
            <line>By giving it the worship of revenge.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PEMBROKE</speaker>
            <speaker>BIGOT</speaker>
            <line>Our souls religiously confirm thy words.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter HUBERT</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HUBERT</speaker>
            <line>Lords, I am hot with haste in seeking you:</line>
            <line>Arthur doth live; the king hath sent for you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALISBURY</speaker>
            <line>O, he is old and blushes not at death.</line>
            <line>Avaunt, thou hateful villain, get thee gone!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HUBERT</speaker>
            <line>I am no villain.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALISBURY</speaker>
            <line>Must I rob the law?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Drawing his sword</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>Your sword is bright, sir; put it up again.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALISBURY</speaker>
            <line>Not till I sheathe it in a murderer's skin.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HUBERT</speaker>
            <line>Stand back, Lord Salisbury, stand back, I say;</line>
            <line>By heaven, I think my sword's as sharp as yours:</line>
            <line>I would not have you, lord, forget yourself,</line>
            <line>Nor tempt the danger of my true defence;</line>
            <line>Lest I, by marking of your rage, forget</line>
            <line>Your worth, your greatness and nobility.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIGOT</speaker>
            <line>Out, dunghill! darest thou brave a nobleman?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HUBERT</speaker>
            <line>Not for my life: but yet I dare defend</line>
            <line>My innocent life against an emperor.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALISBURY</speaker>
            <line>Thou art a murderer.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HUBERT</speaker>
            <line>Do not prove me so;</line>
            <line>Yet I am none: whose tongue soe'er speaks false,</line>
            <line>Not truly speaks; who speaks not truly, lies.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PEMBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Cut him to pieces.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>Keep the peace, I say.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALISBURY</speaker>
            <line>Stand by, or I shall gall you, Faulconbridge.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>Thou wert better gall the devil, Salisbury:</line>
            <line>If thou but frown on me, or stir thy foot,</line>
            <line>Or teach thy hasty spleen to do me shame,</line>
            <line>I'll strike thee dead. Put up thy sword betime;</line>
            <line>Or I'll so maul you and your toasting-iron,</line>
            <line>That you shall think the devil is come from hell.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIGOT</speaker>
            <line>What wilt thou do, renowned Faulconbridge?</line>
            <line>Second a villain and a murderer?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HUBERT</speaker>
            <line>Lord Bigot, I am none.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIGOT</speaker>
            <line>Who kill'd this prince?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HUBERT</speaker>
            <line>'Tis not an hour since I left him well:</line>
            <line>I honour'd him, I loved him, and will weep</line>
            <line>My date of life out for his sweet life's loss.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALISBURY</speaker>
            <line>Trust not those cunning waters of his eyes,</line>
            <line>For villany is not without such rheum;</line>
            <line>And he, long traded in it, makes it seem</line>
            <line>Like rivers of remorse and innocency.</line>
            <line>Away with me, all you whose souls abhor</line>
            <line>The uncleanly savours of a slaughter-house;</line>
            <line>For I am stifled with this smell of sin.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIGOT</speaker>
            <line>Away toward Bury, to the Dauphin there!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PEMBROKE</speaker>
            <line>There tell the king he may inquire us out.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt Lords</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>Here's a good world! Knew you of this fair work?</line>
            <line>Beyond the infinite and boundless reach</line>
            <line>Of mercy, if thou didst this deed of death,</line>
            <line>Art thou damn'd, Hubert.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HUBERT</speaker>
            <line>Do but hear me, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>Ha! I'll tell thee what;</line>
            <line>Thou'rt damn'd as black--nay, nothing is so black;</line>
            <line>Thou art more deep damn'd than Prince Lucifer:</line>
            <line>There is not yet so ugly a fiend of hell</line>
            <line>As thou shalt be, if thou didst kill this child.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HUBERT</speaker>
            <line>Upon my soul--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>If thou didst but consent</line>
            <line>To this most cruel act, do but despair;</line>
            <line>And if thou want'st a cord, the smallest thread</line>
            <line>That ever spider twisted from her womb</line>
            <line>Will serve to strangle thee, a rush will be a beam</line>
            <line>To hang thee on; or wouldst thou drown thyself,</line>
            <line>Put but a little water in a spoon,</line>
            <line>And it shall be as all the ocean,</line>
            <line>Enough to stifle such a villain up.</line>
            <line>I do suspect thee very grievously.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HUBERT</speaker>
            <line>If I in act, consent, or sin of thought,</line>
            <line>Be guilty of the stealing that sweet breath</line>
            <line>Which was embounded in this beauteous clay,</line>
            <line>Let hell want pains enough to torture me.</line>
            <line>I left him well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD</speaker>
            <line>Go, bear him in thine arms.</line>
            <line>I am amazed, methinks, and lose my way</line>
            <line>Among the thorns and dangers of this world.</line>
            <line>How easy dost thou take all England up!</line>
            <line>From forth this morsel of dead royalty,</line>
            <line>The life, the right and truth of all this realm</line>
            <line>Is fled to heaven; and England now is left</line>
            <line>To tug and scamble and to part by the teeth</line>
            <line>The unowed interest of proud-swelling state.</line>
            <line>Now for the bare-pick'd bone of majesty</line>
            <line>Doth dogged war bristle his angry crest</line>
            <line>And snarleth in the gentle eyes of peace:</line>
            <line>Now powers from home and discontents at home</line>
            <line>Meet in one line; and vast confusion waits,</line>
            <line>As doth a raven on a sick-fall'n beast,</line>
            <line>The imminent decay of wrested pomp.</line>
            <line>Now happy he whose cloak and cincture can</line>
            <line>Hold out this tempest. Bear away that child</line>
            <line>And follow me with speed: I'll to the king:</line>
            <line>A thousand businesses are brief in hand,</line>
            <line>And heaven itself doth frown upon the land.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>