<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net/doctypes/dita/shakespear/dtd/act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-3">
   <title>ACT III</title>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  A room in the palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter DUKE FREDERICK, Lords, and OLIVER</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE FREDERICK</speaker>
            <line>Not see him since? Sir, sir, that cannot be:</line>
            <line>But were I not the better part made mercy,</line>
            <line>I should not seek an absent argument</line>
            <line>Of my revenge, thou present. But look to it:</line>
            <line>Find out thy brother, wheresoe'er he is;</line>
            <line>Seek him with candle; bring him dead or living</line>
            <line>Within this twelvemonth, or turn thou no more</line>
            <line>To seek a living in our territory.</line>
            <line>Thy lands and all things that thou dost call thine</line>
            <line>Worth seizure do we seize into our hands,</line>
            <line>Till thou canst quit thee by thy brothers mouth</line>
            <line>Of what we think against thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVER</speaker>
            <line>O that your highness knew my heart in this!</line>
            <line>I never loved my brother in my life.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE FREDERICK</speaker>
            <line>More villain thou. Well, push him out of doors;</line>
            <line>And let my officers of such a nature</line>
            <line>Make an extent upon his house and lands:</line>
            <line>Do this expediently and turn him going.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  The forest.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter ORLANDO, with a paper</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>Hang there, my verse, in witness of my love:</line>
            <line>And thou, thrice-crowned queen of night, survey</line>
            <line>With thy chaste eye, from thy pale sphere above,</line>
            <line>Thy huntress' name that my full life doth sway.</line>
            <line>O Rosalind! these trees shall be my books</line>
            <line>And in their barks my thoughts I'll character;</line>
            <line>That every eye which in this forest looks</line>
            <line>Shall see thy virtue witness'd every where.</line>
            <line>Run, run, Orlando; carve on every tree</line>
            <line>The fair, the chaste and unexpressive she.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Enter CORIN and TOUCHSTONE</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIN</speaker>
            <line>And how like you this shepherd's life, Master Touchstone?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>Truly, shepherd, in respect of itself, it is a good</line>
            <line>life, but in respect that it is a shepherd's life,</line>
            <line>it is naught. In respect that it is solitary, I</line>
            <line>like it very well; but in respect that it is</line>
            <line>private, it is a very vile life. Now, in respect it</line>
            <line>is in the fields, it pleaseth me well; but in</line>
            <line>respect it is not in the court, it is tedious. As</line>
            <line>is it a spare life, look you, it fits my humour well;</line>
            <line>but as there is no more plenty in it, it goes much</line>
            <line>against my stomach. Hast any philosophy in thee, shepherd?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIN</speaker>
            <line>No more but that I know the more one sickens the</line>
            <line>worse at ease he is; and that he that wants money,</line>
            <line>means and content is without three good friends;</line>
            <line>that the property of rain is to wet and fire to</line>
            <line>burn; that good pasture makes fat sheep, and that a</line>
            <line>great cause of the night is lack of the sun; that</line>
            <line>he that hath learned no wit by nature nor art may</line>
            <line>complain of good breeding or comes of a very dull kindred.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>Such a one is a natural philosopher. Wast ever in</line>
            <line>court, shepherd?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIN</speaker>
            <line>No, truly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>Then thou art damned.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIN</speaker>
            <line>Nay, I hope.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>Truly, thou art damned like an ill-roasted egg, all</line>
            <line>on one side.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIN</speaker>
            <line>For not being at court? Your reason.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>Why, if thou never wast at court, thou never sawest</line>
            <line>good manners; if thou never sawest good manners,</line>
            <line>then thy manners must be wicked; and wickedness is</line>
            <line>sin, and sin is damnation. Thou art in a parlous</line>
            <line>state, shepherd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIN</speaker>
            <line>Not a whit, Touchstone: those that are good manners</line>
            <line>at the court are as ridiculous in the country as the</line>
            <line>behavior of the country is most mockable at the</line>
            <line>court. You told me you salute not at the court, but</line>
            <line>you kiss your hands: that courtesy would be</line>
            <line>uncleanly, if courtiers were shepherds.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>Instance, briefly; come, instance.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIN</speaker>
            <line>Why, we are still handling our ewes, and their</line>
            <line>fells, you know, are greasy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>Why, do not your courtier's hands sweat? and is not</line>
            <line>the grease of a mutton as wholesome as the sweat of</line>
            <line>a man? Shallow, shallow. A better instance, I say; come.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIN</speaker>
            <line>Besides, our hands are hard.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>Your lips will feel them the sooner. Shallow again.</line>
            <line>A more sounder instance, come.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIN</speaker>
            <line>And they are often tarred over with the surgery of</line>
            <line>our sheep: and would you have us kiss tar? The</line>
            <line>courtier's hands are perfumed with civet.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>Most shallow man! thou worms-meat, in respect of a</line>
            <line>good piece of flesh indeed! Learn of the wise, and</line>
            <line>perpend: civet is of a baser birth than tar, the</line>
            <line>very uncleanly flux of a cat. Mend the instance, shepherd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIN</speaker>
            <line>You have too courtly a wit for me: I'll rest.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>Wilt thou rest damned? God help thee, shallow man!</line>
            <line>God make incision in thee! thou art raw.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIN</speaker>
            <line>Sir, I am a true labourer: I earn that I eat, get</line>
            <line>that I wear, owe no man hate, envy no man's</line>
            <line>happiness, glad of other men's good, content with my</line>
            <line>harm, and the greatest of my pride is to see my ewes</line>
            <line>graze and my lambs suck.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>That is another simple sin in you, to bring the ewes</line>
            <line>and the rams together and to offer to get your</line>
            <line>living by the copulation of cattle; to be bawd to a</line>
            <line>bell-wether, and to betray a she-lamb of a</line>
            <line>twelvemonth to a crooked-pated, old, cuckoldly ram,</line>
            <line>out of all reasonable match. If thou beest not</line>
            <line>damned for this, the devil himself will have no</line>
            <line>shepherds; I cannot see else how thou shouldst</line>
            <line>'scape.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIN</speaker>
            <line>Here comes young Master Ganymede, my new mistress's brother.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter ROSALIND, with a paper, reading</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>From the east to western Ind,</line>
            <line>No jewel is like Rosalind.</line>
            <line>Her worth, being mounted on the wind,</line>
            <line>Through all the world bears Rosalind.</line>
            <line>All the pictures fairest lined</line>
            <line>Are but black to Rosalind.</line>
            <line>Let no fair be kept in mind</line>
            <line>But the fair of Rosalind.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>I'll rhyme you so eight years together, dinners and</line>
            <line>suppers and sleeping-hours excepted: it is the</line>
            <line>right butter-women's rank to market.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>Out, fool!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>For a taste:</line>
            <line>If a hart do lack a hind,</line>
            <line>Let him seek out Rosalind.</line>
            <line>If the cat will after kind,</line>
            <line>So be sure will Rosalind.</line>
            <line>Winter garments must be lined,</line>
            <line>So must slender Rosalind.</line>
            <line>They that reap must sheaf and bind;</line>
            <line>Then to cart with Rosalind.</line>
            <line>Sweetest nut hath sourest rind,</line>
            <line>Such a nut is Rosalind.</line>
            <line>He that sweetest rose will find</line>
            <line>Must find love's prick and Rosalind.</line>
            <line>This is the very false gallop of verses: why do you</line>
            <line>infect yourself with them?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>Peace, you dull fool! I found them on a tree.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>Truly, the tree yields bad fruit.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>I'll graff it with you, and then I shall graff it</line>
            <line>with a medlar: then it will be the earliest fruit</line>
            <line>i' the country; for you'll be rotten ere you be half</line>
            <line>ripe, and that's the right virtue of the medlar.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>You have said; but whether wisely or no, let the</line>
            <line>forest judge.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter CELIA, with a writing</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>Peace! Here comes my sister, reading: stand aside.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>
            </line>
            <line>Why should this a desert be?</line>
            <line>For it is unpeopled? No:</line>
            <line>Tongues I'll hang on every tree,</line>
            <line>That shall civil sayings show:</line>
            <line>Some, how brief the life of man</line>
            <line>Runs his erring pilgrimage,</line>
            <line>That the stretching of a span</line>
            <line>Buckles in his sum of age;</line>
            <line>Some, of violated vows</line>
            <line>'Twixt the souls of friend and friend:</line>
            <line>But upon the fairest boughs,</line>
            <line>Or at every sentence end,</line>
            <line>Will I Rosalinda write,</line>
            <line>Teaching all that read to know</line>
            <line>The quintessence of every sprite</line>
            <line>Heaven would in little show.</line>
            <line>Therefore Heaven Nature charged</line>
            <line>That one body should be fill'd</line>
            <line>With all graces wide-enlarged:</line>
            <line>Nature presently distill'd</line>
            <line>Helen's cheek, but not her heart,</line>
            <line>Cleopatra's majesty,</line>
            <line>Atalanta's better part,</line>
            <line>Sad Lucretia's modesty.</line>
            <line>Thus Rosalind of many parts</line>
            <line>By heavenly synod was devised,</line>
            <line>Of many faces, eyes and hearts,</line>
            <line>To have the touches dearest prized.</line>
            <line>Heaven would that she these gifts should have,</line>
            <line>And I to live and die her slave.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>O most gentle pulpiter! what tedious homily of love</line>
            <line>have you wearied your parishioners withal, and never</line>
            <line>cried 'Have patience, good people!'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>How now! back, friends! Shepherd, go off a little.</line>
            <line>Go with him, sirrah.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>Come, shepherd, let us make an honourable retreat;</line>
            <line>though not with bag and baggage, yet with scrip and scrippage.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt CORIN and TOUCHSTONE</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>Didst thou hear these verses?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>O, yes, I heard them all, and more too; for some of</line>
            <line>them had in them more feet than the verses would bear.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>That's no matter: the feet might bear the verses.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>Ay, but the feet were lame and could not bear</line>
            <line>themselves without the verse and therefore stood</line>
            <line>lamely in the verse.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>But didst thou hear without wondering how thy name</line>
            <line>should be hanged and carved upon these trees?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>I was seven of the nine days out of the wonder</line>
            <line>before you came; for look here what I found on a</line>
            <line>palm-tree. I was never so be-rhymed since</line>
            <line>Pythagoras' time, that I was an Irish rat, which I</line>
            <line>can hardly remember.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>Trow you who hath done this?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>Is it a man?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>And a chain, that you once wore, about his neck.</line>
            <line>Change you colour?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>I prithee, who?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>O Lord, Lord! it is a hard matter for friends to</line>
            <line>meet; but mountains may be removed with earthquakes</line>
            <line>and so encounter.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>Nay, but who is it?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>Is it possible?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>Nay, I prithee now with most petitionary vehemence,</line>
            <line>tell me who it is.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>O wonderful, wonderful, and most wonderful</line>
            <line>wonderful! and yet again wonderful, and after that,</line>
            <line>out of all hooping!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>Good my complexion! dost thou think, though I am</line>
            <line>caparisoned like a man, I have a doublet and hose in</line>
            <line>my disposition? One inch of delay more is a</line>
            <line>South-sea of discovery; I prithee, tell me who is it</line>
            <line>quickly, and speak apace. I would thou couldst</line>
            <line>stammer, that thou mightst pour this concealed man</line>
            <line>out of thy mouth, as wine comes out of a narrow-</line>
            <line>mouthed bottle, either too much at once, or none at</line>
            <line>all. I prithee, take the cork out of thy mouth that</line>
            <line>may drink thy tidings.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>So you may put a man in your belly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>Is he of God's making? What manner of man? Is his</line>
            <line>head worth a hat, or his chin worth a beard?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>Nay, he hath but a little beard.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>Why, God will send more, if the man will be</line>
            <line>thankful: let me stay the growth of his beard, if</line>
            <line>thou delay me not the knowledge of his chin.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>It is young Orlando, that tripped up the wrestler's</line>
            <line>heels and your heart both in an instant.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>Nay, but the devil take mocking: speak, sad brow and</line>
            <line>true maid.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>I' faith, coz, 'tis he.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>Orlando?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>Orlando.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>Alas the day! what shall I do with my doublet and</line>
            <line>hose? What did he when thou sawest him? What said</line>
            <line>he? How looked he? Wherein went he? What makes</line>
            <line>him here? Did he ask for me? Where remains he?</line>
            <line>How parted he with thee? and when shalt thou see</line>
            <line>him again? Answer me in one word.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>You must borrow me Gargantua's mouth first: 'tis a</line>
            <line>word too great for any mouth of this age's size. To</line>
            <line>say ay and no to these particulars is more than to</line>
            <line>answer in a catechism.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>But doth he know that I am in this forest and in</line>
            <line>man's apparel? Looks he as freshly as he did the</line>
            <line>day he wrestled?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>It is as easy to count atomies as to resolve the</line>
            <line>propositions of a lover; but take a taste of my</line>
            <line>finding him, and relish it with good observance.</line>
            <line>I found him under a tree, like a dropped acorn.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>It may well be called Jove's tree, when it drops</line>
            <line>forth such fruit.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>Give me audience, good madam.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>Proceed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>There lay he, stretched along, like a wounded knight.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>Though it be pity to see such a sight, it well</line>
            <line>becomes the ground.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>Cry 'holla' to thy tongue, I prithee; it curvets</line>
            <line>unseasonably. He was furnished like a hunter.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>O, ominous! he comes to kill my heart.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>I would sing my song without a burden: thou bringest</line>
            <line>me out of tune.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>Do you not know I am a woman? when I think, I must</line>
            <line>speak. Sweet, say on.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>You bring me out. Soft! comes he not here?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter ORLANDO and JAQUES</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>'Tis he: slink by, and note him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JAQUES</speaker>
            <line>I thank you for your company; but, good faith, I had</line>
            <line>as lief have been myself alone.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>And so had I; but yet, for fashion sake, I thank you</line>
            <line>too for your society.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JAQUES</speaker>
            <line>God be wi' you: let's meet as little as we can.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>I do desire we may be better strangers.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JAQUES</speaker>
            <line>I pray you, mar no more trees with writing</line>
            <line>love-songs in their barks.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>I pray you, mar no more of my verses with reading</line>
            <line>them ill-favouredly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JAQUES</speaker>
            <line>Rosalind is your love's name?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>Yes, just.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JAQUES</speaker>
            <line>I do not like her name.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>There was no thought of pleasing you when she was</line>
            <line>christened.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JAQUES</speaker>
            <line>What stature is she of?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>Just as high as my heart.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JAQUES</speaker>
            <line>You are full of pretty answers. Have you not been</line>
            <line>acquainted with goldsmiths' wives, and conned them</line>
            <line>out of rings?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>Not so; but I answer you right painted cloth, from</line>
            <line>whence you have studied your questions.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JAQUES</speaker>
            <line>You have a nimble wit: I think 'twas made of</line>
            <line>Atalanta's heels. Will you sit down with me? and</line>
            <line>we two will rail against our mistress the world and</line>
            <line>all our misery.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>I will chide no breather in the world but myself,</line>
            <line>against whom I know most faults.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JAQUES</speaker>
            <line>The worst fault you have is to be in love.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>'Tis a fault I will not change for your best virtue.</line>
            <line>I am weary of you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JAQUES</speaker>
            <line>By my troth, I was seeking for a fool when I found</line>
            <line>you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>He is drowned in the brook: look but in, and you</line>
            <line>shall see him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JAQUES</speaker>
            <line>There I shall see mine own figure.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>Which I take to be either a fool or a cipher.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JAQUES</speaker>
            <line>I'll tarry no longer with you: farewell, good</line>
            <line>Signior Love.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>I am glad of your departure: adieu, good Monsieur</line>
            <line>Melancholy.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit JAQUES</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside to CELIA</stagedir>  I will speak to him, like a saucy</line>
            <line>lackey and under that habit play the knave with him.</line>
            <line>Do you hear, forester?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>Very well: what would you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>I pray you, what is't o'clock?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>You should ask me what time o' day: there's no clock</line>
            <line>in the forest.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>Then there is no true lover in the forest; else</line>
            <line>sighing every minute and groaning every hour would</line>
            <line>detect the lazy foot of Time as well as a clock.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>And why not the swift foot of Time? had not that</line>
            <line>been as proper?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>By no means, sir: Time travels in divers paces with</line>
            <line>divers persons. I'll tell you who Time ambles</line>
            <line>withal, who Time trots withal, who Time gallops</line>
            <line>withal and who he stands still withal.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>I prithee, who doth he trot withal?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>Marry, he trots hard with a young maid between the</line>
            <line>contract of her marriage and the day it is</line>
            <line>solemnized: if the interim be but a se'nnight,</line>
            <line>Time's pace is so hard that it seems the length of</line>
            <line>seven year.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>Who ambles Time withal?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>With a priest that lacks Latin and a rich man that</line>
            <line>hath not the gout, for the one sleeps easily because</line>
            <line>he cannot study, and the other lives merrily because</line>
            <line>he feels no pain, the one lacking the burden of lean</line>
            <line>and wasteful learning, the other knowing no burden</line>
            <line>of heavy tedious penury; these Time ambles withal.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>Who doth he gallop withal?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>With a thief to the gallows, for though he go as</line>
            <line>softly as foot can fall, he thinks himself too soon there.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>Who stays it still withal?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>With lawyers in the vacation, for they sleep between</line>
            <line>term and term and then they perceive not how Time moves.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>Where dwell you, pretty youth?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>With this shepherdess, my sister; here in the</line>
            <line>skirts of the forest, like fringe upon a petticoat.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>Are you native of this place?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>As the cony that you see dwell where she is kindled.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>Your accent is something finer than you could</line>
            <line>purchase in so removed a dwelling.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>I have been told so of many: but indeed an old</line>
            <line>religious uncle of mine taught me to speak, who was</line>
            <line>in his youth an inland man; one that knew courtship</line>
            <line>too well, for there he fell in love. I have heard</line>
            <line>him read many lectures against it, and I thank God</line>
            <line>I am not a woman, to be touched with so many</line>
            <line>giddy offences as he hath generally taxed their</line>
            <line>whole sex withal.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>Can you remember any of the principal evils that he</line>
            <line>laid to the charge of women?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>There were none principal; they were all like one</line>
            <line>another as half-pence are, every one fault seeming</line>
            <line>monstrous till his fellow fault came to match it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>I prithee, recount some of them.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>No, I will not cast away my physic but on those that</line>
            <line>are sick. There is a man haunts the forest, that</line>
            <line>abuses our young plants with carving 'Rosalind' on</line>
            <line>their barks; hangs odes upon hawthorns and elegies</line>
            <line>on brambles, all, forsooth, deifying the name of</line>
            <line>Rosalind: if I could meet that fancy-monger I would</line>
            <line>give him some good counsel, for he seems to have the</line>
            <line>quotidian of love upon him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>I am he that is so love-shaked: I pray you tell me</line>
            <line>your remedy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>There is none of my uncle's marks upon you: he</line>
            <line>taught me how to know a man in love; in which cage</line>
            <line>of rushes I am sure you are not prisoner.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>What were his marks?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>A lean cheek, which you have not, a blue eye and</line>
            <line>sunken, which you have not, an unquestionable</line>
            <line>spirit, which you have not, a beard neglected,</line>
            <line>which you have not; but I pardon you for that, for</line>
            <line>simply your having in beard is a younger brother's</line>
            <line>revenue: then your hose should be ungartered, your</line>
            <line>bonnet unbanded, your sleeve unbuttoned, your shoe</line>
            <line>untied and every thing about you demonstrating a</line>
            <line>careless desolation; but you are no such man; you</line>
            <line>are rather point-device in your accoutrements as</line>
            <line>loving yourself than seeming the lover of any other.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>Fair youth, I would I could make thee believe I love.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>Me believe it! you may as soon make her that you</line>
            <line>love believe it; which, I warrant, she is apter to</line>
            <line>do than to confess she does: that is one of the</line>
            <line>points in the which women still give the lie to</line>
            <line>their consciences. But, in good sooth, are you he</line>
            <line>that hangs the verses on the trees, wherein Rosalind</line>
            <line>is so admired?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>I swear to thee, youth, by the white hand of</line>
            <line>Rosalind, I am that he, that unfortunate he.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>But are you so much in love as your rhymes speak?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>Neither rhyme nor reason can express how much.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>Love is merely a madness, and, I tell you, deserves</line>
            <line>as well a dark house and a whip as madmen do: and</line>
            <line>the reason why they are not so punished and cured</line>
            <line>is, that the lunacy is so ordinary that the whippers</line>
            <line>are in love too. Yet I profess curing it by counsel.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>Did you ever cure any so?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>Yes, one, and in this manner. He was to imagine me</line>
            <line>his love, his mistress; and I set him every day to</line>
            <line>woo me: at which time would I, being but a moonish</line>
            <line>youth, grieve, be effeminate, changeable, longing</line>
            <line>and liking, proud, fantastical, apish, shallow,</line>
            <line>inconstant, full of tears, full of smiles, for every</line>
            <line>passion something and for no passion truly any</line>
            <line>thing, as boys and women are for the most part</line>
            <line>cattle of this colour; would now like him, now loathe</line>
            <line>him; then entertain him, then forswear him; now weep</line>
            <line>for him, then spit at him; that I drave my suitor</line>
            <line>from his mad humour of love to a living humour of</line>
            <line>madness; which was, to forswear the full stream of</line>
            <line>the world, and to live in a nook merely monastic.</line>
            <line>And thus I cured him; and this way will I take upon</line>
            <line>me to wash your liver as clean as a sound sheep's</line>
            <line>heart, that there shall not be one spot of love in't.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>I would not be cured, youth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>I would cure you, if you would but call me Rosalind</line>
            <line>and come every day to my cote and woo me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>Now, by the faith of my love, I will: tell me</line>
            <line>where it is.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>Go with me to it and I'll show it you and by the way</line>
            <line>you shall tell me where in the forest you live.</line>
            <line>Will you go?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>With all my heart, good youth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>Nay you must call me Rosalind. Come, sister, will you go?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  The forest.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter TOUCHSTONE and AUDREY; JAQUES behind</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>Come apace, good Audrey: I will fetch up your</line>
            <line>goats, Audrey. And how, Audrey? am I the man yet?</line>
            <line>doth my simple feature content you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUDREY</speaker>
            <line>Your features! Lord warrant us! what features!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>I am here with thee and thy goats, as the most</line>
            <line>capricious poet, honest Ovid, was among the Goths.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JAQUES</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  O knowledge ill-inhabited, worse than Jove</line>
            <line>in a thatched house!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>When a man's verses cannot be understood, nor a</line>
            <line>man's good wit seconded with the forward child</line>
            <line>Understanding, it strikes a man more dead than a</line>
            <line>great reckoning in a little room. Truly, I would</line>
            <line>the gods had made thee poetical.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUDREY</speaker>
            <line>I do not know what 'poetical' is: is it honest in</line>
            <line>deed and word? is it a true thing?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>No, truly; for the truest poetry is the most</line>
            <line>feigning; and lovers are given to poetry, and what</line>
            <line>they swear in poetry may be said as lovers they do feign.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUDREY</speaker>
            <line>Do you wish then that the gods had made me poetical?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>I do, truly; for thou swearest to me thou art</line>
            <line>honest: now, if thou wert a poet, I might have some</line>
            <line>hope thou didst feign.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUDREY</speaker>
            <line>Would you not have me honest?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>No, truly, unless thou wert hard-favoured; for</line>
            <line>honesty coupled to beauty is to have honey a sauce to sugar.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JAQUES</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  A material fool!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUDREY</speaker>
            <line>Well, I am not fair; and therefore I pray the gods</line>
            <line>make me honest.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>Truly, and to cast away honesty upon a foul slut</line>
            <line>were to put good meat into an unclean dish.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUDREY</speaker>
            <line>I am not a slut, though I thank the gods I am foul.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>Well, praised be the gods for thy foulness!</line>
            <line>sluttishness may come hereafter. But be it as it may</line>
            <line>be, I will marry thee, and to that end I have been</line>
            <line>with Sir Oliver Martext, the vicar of the next</line>
            <line>village, who hath promised to meet me in this place</line>
            <line>of the forest and to couple us.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JAQUES</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  I would fain see this meeting.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUDREY</speaker>
            <line>Well, the gods give us joy!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>Amen. A man may, if he were of a fearful heart,</line>
            <line>stagger in this attempt; for here we have no temple</line>
            <line>but the wood, no assembly but horn-beasts. But what</line>
            <line>though? Courage! As horns are odious, they are</line>
            <line>necessary. It is said, 'many a man knows no end of</line>
            <line>his goods:' right; many a man has good horns, and</line>
            <line>knows no end of them. Well, that is the dowry of</line>
            <line>his wife; 'tis none of his own getting. Horns?</line>
            <line>Even so. Poor men alone? No, no; the noblest deer</line>
            <line>hath them as huge as the rascal. Is the single man</line>
            <line>therefore blessed? No: as a walled town is more</line>
            <line>worthier than a village, so is the forehead of a</line>
            <line>married man more honourable than the bare brow of a</line>
            <line>bachelor; and by how much defence is better than no</line>
            <line>skill, by so much is a horn more precious than to</line>
            <line>want. Here comes Sir Oliver.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter SIR OLIVER MARTEXT</stagedir>
            <line>Sir Oliver Martext, you are well met: will you</line>
            <line>dispatch us here under this tree, or shall we go</line>
            <line>with you to your chapel?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR OLIVER MARTEXT</speaker>
            <line>Is there none here to give the woman?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>I will not take her on gift of any man.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR OLIVER MARTEXT</speaker>
            <line>Truly, she must be given, or the marriage is not lawful.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JAQUES</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Advancing</stagedir>
            </line>
            <line>Proceed, proceed I'll give her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>Good even, good Master What-ye-call't: how do you,</line>
            <line>sir? You are very well met: God 'ild you for your</line>
            <line>last company: I am very glad to see you: even a</line>
            <line>toy in hand here, sir: nay, pray be covered.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JAQUES</speaker>
            <line>Will you be married, motley?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>As the ox hath his bow, sir, the horse his curb and</line>
            <line>the falcon her bells, so man hath his desires; and</line>
            <line>as pigeons bill, so wedlock would be nibbling.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JAQUES</speaker>
            <line>And will you, being a man of your breeding, be</line>
            <line>married under a bush like a beggar? Get you to</line>
            <line>church, and have a good priest that can tell you</line>
            <line>what marriage is: this fellow will but join you</line>
            <line>together as they join wainscot; then one of you will</line>
            <line>prove a shrunk panel and, like green timber, warp, warp.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  I am not in the mind but I were better to be</line>
            <line>married of him than of another: for he is not like</line>
            <line>to marry me well; and not being well married, it</line>
            <line>will be a good excuse for me hereafter to leave my wife.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JAQUES</speaker>
            <line>Go thou with me, and let me counsel thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>'Come, sweet Audrey:</line>
            <line>We must be married, or we must live in bawdry.</line>
            <line>Farewell, good Master Oliver: not,--</line>
            <line>O sweet Oliver,</line>
            <line>O brave Oliver,</line>
            <line>Leave me not behind thee: but,--</line>
            <line>Wind away,</line>
            <line>Begone, I say,</line>
            <line>I will not to wedding with thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt JAQUES, TOUCHSTONE and AUDREY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR OLIVER MARTEXT</speaker>
            <line>'Tis no matter: ne'er a fantastical knave of them</line>
            <line>all shall flout me out of my calling.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-4">
      <title>SCENE IV.  The forest.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter ROSALIND and CELIA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>Never talk to me; I will weep.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>Do, I prithee; but yet have the grace to consider</line>
            <line>that tears do not become a man.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>But have I not cause to weep?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>As good cause as one would desire; therefore weep.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>His very hair is of the dissembling colour.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>Something browner than Judas's marry, his kisses are</line>
            <line>Judas's own children.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>I' faith, his hair is of a good colour.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>An excellent colour: your chestnut was ever the only colour.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>And his kissing is as full of sanctity as the touch</line>
            <line>of holy bread.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>He hath bought a pair of cast lips of Diana: a nun</line>
            <line>of winter's sisterhood kisses not more religiously;</line>
            <line>the very ice of chastity is in them.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>But why did he swear he would come this morning, and</line>
            <line>comes not?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>Nay, certainly, there is no truth in him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>Do you think so?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>Yes; I think he is not a pick-purse nor a</line>
            <line>horse-stealer, but for his verity in love, I do</line>
            <line>think him as concave as a covered goblet or a</line>
            <line>worm-eaten nut.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>Not true in love?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>Yes, when he is in; but I think he is not in.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>You have heard him swear downright he was.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>'Was' is not 'is:' besides, the oath of a lover is</line>
            <line>no stronger than the word of a tapster; they are</line>
            <line>both the confirmer of false reckonings. He attends</line>
            <line>here in the forest on the duke your father.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>I met the duke yesterday and had much question with</line>
            <line>him: he asked me of what parentage I was; I told</line>
            <line>him, of as good as he; so he laughed and let me go.</line>
            <line>But what talk we of fathers, when there is such a</line>
            <line>man as Orlando?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>O, that's a brave man! he writes brave verses,</line>
            <line>speaks brave words, swears brave oaths and breaks</line>
            <line>them bravely, quite traverse, athwart the heart of</line>
            <line>his lover; as a puisny tilter, that spurs his horse</line>
            <line>but on one side, breaks his staff like a noble</line>
            <line>goose: but all's brave that youth mounts and folly</line>
            <line>guides. Who comes here?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter CORIN</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIN</speaker>
            <line>Mistress and master, you have oft inquired</line>
            <line>After the shepherd that complain'd of love,</line>
            <line>Who you saw sitting by me on the turf,</line>
            <line>Praising the proud disdainful shepherdess</line>
            <line>That was his mistress.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>Well, and what of him?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIN</speaker>
            <line>If you will see a pageant truly play'd,</line>
            <line>Between the pale complexion of true love</line>
            <line>And the red glow of scorn and proud disdain,</line>
            <line>Go hence a little and I shall conduct you,</line>
            <line>If you will mark it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>O, come, let us remove:</line>
            <line>The sight of lovers feedeth those in love.</line>
            <line>Bring us to this sight, and you shall say</line>
            <line>I'll prove a busy actor in their play.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-5">
      <title>SCENE V.  Another part of the forest.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter SILVIUS and PHEBE</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SILVIUS</speaker>
            <line>Sweet Phebe, do not scorn me; do not, Phebe;</line>
            <line>Say that you love me not, but say not so</line>
            <line>In bitterness. The common executioner,</line>
            <line>Whose heart the accustom'd sight of death makes hard,</line>
            <line>Falls not the axe upon the humbled neck</line>
            <line>But first begs pardon: will you sterner be</line>
            <line>Than he that dies and lives by bloody drops?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter ROSALIND, CELIA, and CORIN, behind</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PHEBE</speaker>
            <line>I would not be thy executioner:</line>
            <line>I fly thee, for I would not injure thee.</line>
            <line>Thou tell'st me there is murder in mine eye:</line>
            <line>'Tis pretty, sure, and very probable,</line>
            <line>That eyes, that are the frail'st and softest things,</line>
            <line>Who shut their coward gates on atomies,</line>
            <line>Should be call'd tyrants, butchers, murderers!</line>
            <line>Now I do frown on thee with all my heart;</line>
            <line>And if mine eyes can wound, now let them kill thee:</line>
            <line>Now counterfeit to swoon; why now fall down;</line>
            <line>Or if thou canst not, O, for shame, for shame,</line>
            <line>Lie not, to say mine eyes are murderers!</line>
            <line>Now show the wound mine eye hath made in thee:</line>
            <line>Scratch thee but with a pin, and there remains</line>
            <line>Some scar of it; lean but upon a rush,</line>
            <line>The cicatrice and capable impressure</line>
            <line>Thy palm some moment keeps; but now mine eyes,</line>
            <line>Which I have darted at thee, hurt thee not,</line>
            <line>Nor, I am sure, there is no force in eyes</line>
            <line>That can do hurt.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SILVIUS</speaker>
            <line>O dear Phebe,</line>
            <line>If ever,--as that ever may be near,--</line>
            <line>You meet in some fresh cheek the power of fancy,</line>
            <line>Then shall you know the wounds invisible</line>
            <line>That love's keen arrows make.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PHEBE</speaker>
            <line>But till that time</line>
            <line>Come not thou near me: and when that time comes,</line>
            <line>Afflict me with thy mocks, pity me not;</line>
            <line>As till that time I shall not pity thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>And why, I pray you? Who might be your mother,</line>
            <line>That you insult, exult, and all at once,</line>
            <line>Over the wretched? What though you have no beauty,--</line>
            <line>As, by my faith, I see no more in you</line>
            <line>Than without candle may go dark to bed--</line>
            <line>Must you be therefore proud and pitiless?</line>
            <line>Why, what means this? Why do you look on me?</line>
            <line>I see no more in you than in the ordinary</line>
            <line>Of nature's sale-work. 'Od's my little life,</line>
            <line>I think she means to tangle my eyes too!</line>
            <line>No, faith, proud mistress, hope not after it:</line>
            <line>'Tis not your inky brows, your black silk hair,</line>
            <line>Your bugle eyeballs, nor your cheek of cream,</line>
            <line>That can entame my spirits to your worship.</line>
            <line>You foolish shepherd, wherefore do you follow her,</line>
            <line>Like foggy south puffing with wind and rain?</line>
            <line>You are a thousand times a properer man</line>
            <line>Than she a woman: 'tis such fools as you</line>
            <line>That makes the world full of ill-favour'd children:</line>
            <line>'Tis not her glass, but you, that flatters her;</line>
            <line>And out of you she sees herself more proper</line>
            <line>Than any of her lineaments can show her.</line>
            <line>But, mistress, know yourself: down on your knees,</line>
            <line>And thank heaven, fasting, for a good man's love:</line>
            <line>For I must tell you friendly in your ear,</line>
            <line>Sell when you can: you are not for all markets:</line>
            <line>Cry the man mercy; love him; take his offer:</line>
            <line>Foul is most foul, being foul to be a scoffer.</line>
            <line>So take her to thee, shepherd: fare you well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PHEBE</speaker>
            <line>Sweet youth, I pray you, chide a year together:</line>
            <line>I had rather hear you chide than this man woo.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>He's fallen in love with your foulness and she'll</line>
            <line>fall in love with my anger. If it be so, as fast as</line>
            <line>she answers thee with frowning looks, I'll sauce her</line>
            <line>with bitter words. Why look you so upon me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PHEBE</speaker>
            <line>For no ill will I bear you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>I pray you, do not fall in love with me,</line>
            <line>For I am falser than vows made in wine:</line>
            <line>Besides, I like you not. If you will know my house,</line>
            <line>'Tis at the tuft of olives here hard by.</line>
            <line>Will you go, sister? Shepherd, ply her hard.</line>
            <line>Come, sister. Shepherdess, look on him better,</line>
            <line>And be not proud: though all the world could see,</line>
            <line>None could be so abused in sight as he.</line>
            <line>Come, to our flock.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt ROSALIND, CELIA and CORIN</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PHEBE</speaker>
            <line>Dead Shepherd, now I find thy saw of might,</line>
            <line>'Who ever loved that loved not at first sight?'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SILVIUS</speaker>
            <line>Sweet Phebe,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PHEBE</speaker>
            <line>Ha, what say'st thou, Silvius?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SILVIUS</speaker>
            <line>Sweet Phebe, pity me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PHEBE</speaker>
            <line>Why, I am sorry for thee, gentle Silvius.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SILVIUS</speaker>
            <line>Wherever sorrow is, relief would be:</line>
            <line>If you do sorrow at my grief in love,</line>
            <line>By giving love your sorrow and my grief</line>
            <line>Were both extermined.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PHEBE</speaker>
            <line>Thou hast my love: is not that neighbourly?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SILVIUS</speaker>
            <line>I would have you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PHEBE</speaker>
            <line>Why, that were covetousness.</line>
            <line>Silvius, the time was that I hated thee,</line>
            <line>And yet it is not that I bear thee love;</line>
            <line>But since that thou canst talk of love so well,</line>
            <line>Thy company, which erst was irksome to me,</line>
            <line>I will endure, and I'll employ thee too:</line>
            <line>But do not look for further recompense</line>
            <line>Than thine own gladness that thou art employ'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SILVIUS</speaker>
            <line>So holy and so perfect is my love,</line>
            <line>And I in such a poverty of grace,</line>
            <line>That I shall think it a most plenteous crop</line>
            <line>To glean the broken ears after the man</line>
            <line>That the main harvest reaps: loose now and then</line>
            <line>A scatter'd smile, and that I'll live upon.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PHEBE</speaker>
            <line>Know'st now the youth that spoke to me erewhile?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SILVIUS</speaker>
            <line>Not very well, but I have met him oft;</line>
            <line>And he hath bought the cottage and the bounds</line>
            <line>That the old carlot once was master of.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PHEBE</speaker>
            <line>Think not I love him, though I ask for him:</line>
            <line>'Tis but a peevish boy; yet he talks well;</line>
            <line>But what care I for words? yet words do well</line>
            <line>When he that speaks them pleases those that hear.</line>
            <line>It is a pretty youth: not very pretty:</line>
            <line>But, sure, he's proud, and yet his pride becomes him:</line>
            <line>He'll make a proper man: the best thing in him</line>
            <line>Is his complexion; and faster than his tongue</line>
            <line>Did make offence his eye did heal it up.</line>
            <line>He is not very tall; yet for his years he's tall:</line>
            <line>His leg is but so so; and yet 'tis well:</line>
            <line>There was a pretty redness in his lip,</line>
            <line>A little riper and more lusty red</line>
            <line>Than that mix'd in his cheek; 'twas just the difference</line>
            <line>Between the constant red and mingled damask.</line>
            <line>There be some women, Silvius, had they mark'd him</line>
            <line>In parcels as I did, would have gone near</line>
            <line>To fall in love with him; but, for my part,</line>
            <line>I love him not nor hate him not; and yet</line>
            <line>I have more cause to hate him than to love him:</line>
            <line>For what had he to do to chide at me?</line>
            <line>He said mine eyes were black and my hair black:</line>
            <line>And, now I am remember'd, scorn'd at me:</line>
            <line>I marvel why I answer'd not again:</line>
            <line>But that's all one; omittance is no quittance.</line>
            <line>I'll write to him a very taunting letter,</line>
            <line>And thou shalt bear it: wilt thou, Silvius?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SILVIUS</speaker>
            <line>Phebe, with all my heart.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PHEBE</speaker>
            <line>I'll write it straight;</line>
            <line>The matter's in my head and in my heart:</line>
            <line>I will be bitter with him and passing short.</line>
            <line>Go with me, Silvius.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>