<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net/doctypes/dita/shakespear/dtd/act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-1">
   <title>ACT I</title>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  Orchard of Oliver's house.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter ORLANDO and ADAM</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>As I remember, Adam, it was upon this fashion</line>
            <line>bequeathed me by will but poor a thousand crowns,</line>
            <line>and, as thou sayest, charged my brother, on his</line>
            <line>blessing, to breed me well: and there begins my</line>
            <line>sadness. My brother Jaques he keeps at school, and</line>
            <line>report speaks goldenly of his profit: for my part,</line>
            <line>he keeps me rustically at home, or, to speak more</line>
            <line>properly, stays me here at home unkept; for call you</line>
            <line>that keeping for a gentleman of my birth, that</line>
            <line>differs not from the stalling of an ox? His horses</line>
            <line>are bred better; for, besides that they are fair</line>
            <line>with their feeding, they are taught their manage,</line>
            <line>and to that end riders dearly hired: but I, his</line>
            <line>brother, gain nothing under him but growth; for the</line>
            <line>which his animals on his dunghills are as much</line>
            <line>bound to him as I. Besides this nothing that he so</line>
            <line>plentifully gives me, the something that nature gave</line>
            <line>me his countenance seems to take from me: he lets</line>
            <line>me feed with his hinds, bars me the place of a</line>
            <line>brother, and, as much as in him lies, mines my</line>
            <line>gentility with my education. This is it, Adam, that</line>
            <line>grieves me; and the spirit of my father, which I</line>
            <line>think is within me, begins to mutiny against this</line>
            <line>servitude: I will no longer endure it, though yet I</line>
            <line>know no wise remedy how to avoid it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ADAM</speaker>
            <line>Yonder comes my master, your brother.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>Go apart, Adam, and thou shalt hear how he will</line>
            <line>shake me up.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter OLIVER</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVER</speaker>
            <line>Now, sir! what make you here?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>Nothing: I am not taught to make any thing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVER</speaker>
            <line>What mar you then, sir?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>Marry, sir, I am helping you to mar that which God</line>
            <line>made, a poor unworthy brother of yours, with idleness.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVER</speaker>
            <line>Marry, sir, be better employed, and be naught awhile.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>Shall I keep your hogs and eat husks with them?</line>
            <line>What prodigal portion have I spent, that I should</line>
            <line>come to such penury?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVER</speaker>
            <line>Know you where your are, sir?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>O, sir, very well; here in your orchard.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVER</speaker>
            <line>Know you before whom, sir?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>Ay, better than him I am before knows me. I know</line>
            <line>you are my eldest brother; and, in the gentle</line>
            <line>condition of blood, you should so know me. The</line>
            <line>courtesy of nations allows you my better, in that</line>
            <line>you are the first-born; but the same tradition</line>
            <line>takes not away my blood, were there twenty brothers</line>
            <line>betwixt us: I have as much of my father in me as</line>
            <line>you; albeit, I confess, your coming before me is</line>
            <line>nearer to his reverence.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVER</speaker>
            <line>What, boy!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>Come, come, elder brother, you are too young in this.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVER</speaker>
            <line>Wilt thou lay hands on me, villain?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>I am no villain; I am the youngest son of Sir</line>
            <line>Rowland de Boys; he was my father, and he is thrice</line>
            <line>a villain that says such a father begot villains.</line>
            <line>Wert thou not my brother, I would not take this hand</line>
            <line>from thy throat till this other had pulled out thy</line>
            <line>tongue for saying so: thou hast railed on thyself.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ADAM</speaker>
            <line>Sweet masters, be patient: for your father's</line>
            <line>remembrance, be at accord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVER</speaker>
            <line>Let me go, I say.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>I will not, till I please: you shall hear me. My</line>
            <line>father charged you in his will to give me good</line>
            <line>education: you have trained me like a peasant,</line>
            <line>obscuring and hiding from me all gentleman-like</line>
            <line>qualities. The spirit of my father grows strong in</line>
            <line>me, and I will no longer endure it: therefore allow</line>
            <line>me such exercises as may become a gentleman, or</line>
            <line>give me the poor allottery my father left me by</line>
            <line>testament; with that I will go buy my fortunes.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVER</speaker>
            <line>And what wilt thou do? beg, when that is spent?</line>
            <line>Well, sir, get you in: I will not long be troubled</line>
            <line>with you; you shall have some part of your will: I</line>
            <line>pray you, leave me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>I will no further offend you than becomes me for my good.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVER</speaker>
            <line>Get you with him, you old dog.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ADAM</speaker>
            <line>Is 'old dog' my reward? Most true, I have lost my</line>
            <line>teeth in your service. God be with my old master!</line>
            <line>he would not have spoke such a word.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt ORLANDO and ADAM</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVER</speaker>
            <line>Is it even so? begin you to grow upon me? I will</line>
            <line>physic your rankness, and yet give no thousand</line>
            <line>crowns neither. Holla, Dennis!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter DENNIS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DENNIS</speaker>
            <line>Calls your worship?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVER</speaker>
            <line>Was not Charles, the duke's wrestler, here to speak with me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DENNIS</speaker>
            <line>So please you, he is here at the door and importunes</line>
            <line>access to you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVER</speaker>
            <line>Call him in.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit DENNIS</stagedir>
            <line>'Twill be a good way; and to-morrow the wrestling is.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter CHARLES</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHARLES</speaker>
            <line>Good morrow to your worship.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVER</speaker>
            <line>Good Monsieur Charles, what's the new news at the</line>
            <line>new court?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHARLES</speaker>
            <line>There's no news at the court, sir, but the old news:</line>
            <line>that is, the old duke is banished by his younger</line>
            <line>brother the new duke; and three or four loving lords</line>
            <line>have put themselves into voluntary exile with him,</line>
            <line>whose lands and revenues enrich the new duke;</line>
            <line>therefore he gives them good leave to wander.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVER</speaker>
            <line>Can you tell if Rosalind, the duke's daughter, be</line>
            <line>banished with her father?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHARLES</speaker>
            <line>O, no; for the duke's daughter, her cousin, so loves</line>
            <line>her, being ever from their cradles bred together,</line>
            <line>that she would have followed her exile, or have died</line>
            <line>to stay behind her. She is at the court, and no</line>
            <line>less beloved of her uncle than his own daughter; and</line>
            <line>never two ladies loved as they do.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVER</speaker>
            <line>Where will the old duke live?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHARLES</speaker>
            <line>They say he is already in the forest of Arden, and</line>
            <line>a many merry men with him; and there they live like</line>
            <line>the old Robin Hood of England: they say many young</line>
            <line>gentlemen flock to him every day, and fleet the time</line>
            <line>carelessly, as they did in the golden world.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVER</speaker>
            <line>What, you wrestle to-morrow before the new duke?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHARLES</speaker>
            <line>Marry, do I, sir; and I came to acquaint you with a</line>
            <line>matter. I am given, sir, secretly to understand</line>
            <line>that your younger brother Orlando hath a disposition</line>
            <line>to come in disguised against me to try a fall.</line>
            <line>To-morrow, sir, I wrestle for my credit; and he that</line>
            <line>escapes me without some broken limb shall acquit him</line>
            <line>well. Your brother is but young and tender; and,</line>
            <line>for your love, I would be loath to foil him, as I</line>
            <line>must, for my own honour, if he come in: therefore,</line>
            <line>out of my love to you, I came hither to acquaint you</line>
            <line>withal, that either you might stay him from his</line>
            <line>intendment or brook such disgrace well as he shall</line>
            <line>run into, in that it is a thing of his own search</line>
            <line>and altogether against my will.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVER</speaker>
            <line>Charles, I thank thee for thy love to me, which</line>
            <line>thou shalt find I will most kindly requite. I had</line>
            <line>myself notice of my brother's purpose herein and</line>
            <line>have by underhand means laboured to dissuade him from</line>
            <line>it, but he is resolute. I'll tell thee, Charles:</line>
            <line>it is the stubbornest young fellow of France, full</line>
            <line>of ambition, an envious emulator of every man's</line>
            <line>good parts, a secret and villanous contriver against</line>
            <line>me his natural brother: therefore use thy</line>
            <line>discretion; I had as lief thou didst break his neck</line>
            <line>as his finger. And thou wert best look to't; for if</line>
            <line>thou dost him any slight disgrace or if he do not</line>
            <line>mightily grace himself on thee, he will practise</line>
            <line>against thee by poison, entrap thee by some</line>
            <line>treacherous device and never leave thee till he</line>
            <line>hath ta'en thy life by some indirect means or other;</line>
            <line>for, I assure thee, and almost with tears I speak</line>
            <line>it, there is not one so young and so villanous this</line>
            <line>day living. I speak but brotherly of him; but</line>
            <line>should I anatomize him to thee as he is, I must</line>
            <line>blush and weep and thou must look pale and wonder.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHARLES</speaker>
            <line>I am heartily glad I came hither to you. If he come</line>
            <line>to-morrow, I'll give him his payment: if ever he go</line>
            <line>alone again, I'll never wrestle for prize more: and</line>
            <line>so God keep your worship!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVER</speaker>
            <line>Farewell, good Charles.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit CHARLES</stagedir>
            <line>Now will I stir this gamester: I hope I shall see</line>
            <line>an end of him; for my soul, yet I know not why,</line>
            <line>hates nothing more than he. Yet he's gentle, never</line>
            <line>schooled and yet learned, full of noble device, of</line>
            <line>all sorts enchantingly beloved, and indeed so much</line>
            <line>in the heart of the world, and especially of my own</line>
            <line>people, who best know him, that I am altogether</line>
            <line>misprised: but it shall not be so long; this</line>
            <line>wrestler shall clear all: nothing remains but that</line>
            <line>I kindle the boy thither; which now I'll go about.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  Lawn before the Duke's palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter CELIA and ROSALIND</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>I pray thee, Rosalind, sweet my coz, be merry.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>Dear Celia, I show more mirth than I am mistress of;</line>
            <line>and would you yet I were merrier? Unless you could</line>
            <line>teach me to forget a banished father, you must not</line>
            <line>learn me how to remember any extraordinary pleasure.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>Herein I see thou lovest me not with the full weight</line>
            <line>that I love thee. If my uncle, thy banished father,</line>
            <line>had banished thy uncle, the duke my father, so thou</line>
            <line>hadst been still with me, I could have taught my</line>
            <line>love to take thy father for mine: so wouldst thou,</line>
            <line>if the truth of thy love to me were so righteously</line>
            <line>tempered as mine is to thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>Well, I will forget the condition of my estate, to</line>
            <line>rejoice in yours.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>You know my father hath no child but I, nor none is</line>
            <line>like to have: and, truly, when he dies, thou shalt</line>
            <line>be his heir, for what he hath taken away from thy</line>
            <line>father perforce, I will render thee again in</line>
            <line>affection; by mine honour, I will; and when I break</line>
            <line>that oath, let me turn monster: therefore, my</line>
            <line>sweet Rose, my dear Rose, be merry.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>From henceforth I will, coz, and devise sports. Let</line>
            <line>me see; what think you of falling in love?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>Marry, I prithee, do, to make sport withal: but</line>
            <line>love no man in good earnest; nor no further in sport</line>
            <line>neither than with safety of a pure blush thou mayst</line>
            <line>in honour come off again.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>What shall be our sport, then?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>Let us sit and mock the good housewife Fortune from</line>
            <line>her wheel, that her gifts may henceforth be bestowed equally.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>I would we could do so, for her benefits are</line>
            <line>mightily misplaced, and the bountiful blind woman</line>
            <line>doth most mistake in her gifts to women.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>'Tis true; for those that she makes fair she scarce</line>
            <line>makes honest, and those that she makes honest she</line>
            <line>makes very ill-favouredly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>Nay, now thou goest from Fortune's office to</line>
            <line>Nature's: Fortune reigns in gifts of the world,</line>
            <line>not in the lineaments of Nature.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter TOUCHSTONE</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>No? when Nature hath made a fair creature, may she</line>
            <line>not by Fortune fall into the fire? Though Nature</line>
            <line>hath given us wit to flout at Fortune, hath not</line>
            <line>Fortune sent in this fool to cut off the argument?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>Indeed, there is Fortune too hard for Nature, when</line>
            <line>Fortune makes Nature's natural the cutter-off of</line>
            <line>Nature's wit.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>Peradventure this is not Fortune's work neither, but</line>
            <line>Nature's; who perceiveth our natural wits too dull</line>
            <line>to reason of such goddesses and hath sent this</line>
            <line>natural for our whetstone; for always the dulness of</line>
            <line>the fool is the whetstone of the wits. How now,</line>
            <line>wit! whither wander you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>Mistress, you must come away to your father.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>Were you made the messenger?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>No, by mine honour, but I was bid to come for you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>Where learned you that oath, fool?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>Of a certain knight that swore by his honour they</line>
            <line>were good pancakes and swore by his honour the</line>
            <line>mustard was naught: now I'll stand to it, the</line>
            <line>pancakes were naught and the mustard was good, and</line>
            <line>yet was not the knight forsworn.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>How prove you that, in the great heap of your</line>
            <line>knowledge?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>Ay, marry, now unmuzzle your wisdom.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>Stand you both forth now: stroke your chins, and</line>
            <line>swear by your beards that I am a knave.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>By our beards, if we had them, thou art.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>By my knavery, if I had it, then I were; but if you</line>
            <line>swear by that that is not, you are not forsworn: no</line>
            <line>more was this knight swearing by his honour, for he</line>
            <line>never had any; or if he had, he had sworn it away</line>
            <line>before ever he saw those pancakes or that mustard.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>Prithee, who is't that thou meanest?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>One that old Frederick, your father, loves.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>My father's love is enough to honour him: enough!</line>
            <line>speak no more of him; you'll be whipped for taxation</line>
            <line>one of these days.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>The more pity, that fools may not speak wisely what</line>
            <line>wise men do foolishly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>By my troth, thou sayest true; for since the little</line>
            <line>wit that fools have was silenced, the little foolery</line>
            <line>that wise men have makes a great show. Here comes</line>
            <line>Monsieur Le Beau.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>With his mouth full of news.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>Which he will put on us, as pigeons feed their young.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>Then shall we be news-crammed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>All the better; we shall be the more marketable.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter LE BEAU</stagedir>
            <line>Bon jour, Monsieur Le Beau: what's the news?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LE BEAU</speaker>
            <line>Fair princess, you have lost much good sport.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>Sport! of what colour?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LE BEAU</speaker>
            <line>What colour, madam! how shall I answer you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>As wit and fortune will.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>Or as the Destinies decree.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>Well said: that was laid on with a trowel.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>Nay, if I keep not my rank,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>Thou losest thy old smell.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LE BEAU</speaker>
            <line>You amaze me, ladies: I would have told you of good</line>
            <line>wrestling, which you have lost the sight of.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>You tell us the manner of the wrestling.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LE BEAU</speaker>
            <line>I will tell you the beginning; and, if it please</line>
            <line>your ladyships, you may see the end; for the best is</line>
            <line>yet to do; and here, where you are, they are coming</line>
            <line>to perform it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>Well, the beginning, that is dead and buried.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LE BEAU</speaker>
            <line>There comes an old man and his three sons,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>I could match this beginning with an old tale.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LE BEAU</speaker>
            <line>Three proper young men, of excellent growth and presence.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>With bills on their necks, 'Be it known unto all men</line>
            <line>by these presents.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LE BEAU</speaker>
            <line>The eldest of the three wrestled with Charles, the</line>
            <line>duke's wrestler; which Charles in a moment threw him</line>
            <line>and broke three of his ribs, that there is little</line>
            <line>hope of life in him: so he served the second, and</line>
            <line>so the third. Yonder they lie; the poor old man,</line>
            <line>their father, making such pitiful dole over them</line>
            <line>that all the beholders take his part with weeping.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>Alas!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>But what is the sport, monsieur, that the ladies</line>
            <line>have lost?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LE BEAU</speaker>
            <line>Why, this that I speak of.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>Thus men may grow wiser every day: it is the first</line>
            <line>time that ever I heard breaking of ribs was sport</line>
            <line>for ladies.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>Or I, I promise thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>But is there any else longs to see this broken music</line>
            <line>in his sides? is there yet another dotes upon</line>
            <line>rib-breaking? Shall we see this wrestling, cousin?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LE BEAU</speaker>
            <line>You must, if you stay here; for here is the place</line>
            <line>appointed for the wrestling, and they are ready to</line>
            <line>perform it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>Yonder, sure, they are coming: let us now stay and see it.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Flourish. Enter DUKE FREDERICK, Lords, ORLANDO,
CHARLES, and Attendants</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE FREDERICK</speaker>
            <line>Come on: since the youth will not be entreated, his</line>
            <line>own peril on his forwardness.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>Is yonder the man?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LE BEAU</speaker>
            <line>Even he, madam.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>Alas, he is too young! yet he looks successfully.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE FREDERICK</speaker>
            <line>How now, daughter and cousin! are you crept hither</line>
            <line>to see the wrestling?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>Ay, my liege, so please you give us leave.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE FREDERICK</speaker>
            <line>You will take little delight in it, I can tell you;</line>
            <line>there is such odds in the man. In pity of the</line>
            <line>challenger's youth I would fain dissuade him, but he</line>
            <line>will not be entreated. Speak to him, ladies; see if</line>
            <line>you can move him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>Call him hither, good Monsieur Le Beau.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE FREDERICK</speaker>
            <line>Do so: I'll not be by.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LE BEAU</speaker>
            <line>Monsieur the challenger, the princesses call for you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>I attend them with all respect and duty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>Young man, have you challenged Charles the wrestler?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>No, fair princess; he is the general challenger: I</line>
            <line>come but in, as others do, to try with him the</line>
            <line>strength of my youth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>Young gentleman, your spirits are too bold for your</line>
            <line>years. You have seen cruel proof of this man's</line>
            <line>strength: if you saw yourself with your eyes or</line>
            <line>knew yourself with your judgment, the fear of your</line>
            <line>adventure would counsel you to a more equal</line>
            <line>enterprise. We pray you, for your own sake, to</line>
            <line>embrace your own safety and give over this attempt.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>Do, young sir; your reputation shall not therefore</line>
            <line>be misprised: we will make it our suit to the duke</line>
            <line>that the wrestling might not go forward.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>I beseech you, punish me not with your hard</line>
            <line>thoughts; wherein I confess me much guilty, to deny</line>
            <line>so fair and excellent ladies any thing. But let</line>
            <line>your fair eyes and gentle wishes go with me to my</line>
            <line>trial: wherein if I be foiled, there is but one</line>
            <line>shamed that was never gracious; if killed, but one</line>
            <line>dead that was willing to be so: I shall do my</line>
            <line>friends no wrong, for I have none to lament me, the</line>
            <line>world no injury, for in it I have nothing; only in</line>
            <line>the world I fill up a place, which may be better</line>
            <line>supplied when I have made it empty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>The little strength that I have, I would it were with you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>And mine, to eke out hers.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>Fare you well: pray heaven I be deceived in you!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>Your heart's desires be with you!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHARLES</speaker>
            <line>Come, where is this young gallant that is so</line>
            <line>desirous to lie with his mother earth?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>Ready, sir; but his will hath in it a more modest working.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE FREDERICK</speaker>
            <line>You shall try but one fall.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHARLES</speaker>
            <line>No, I warrant your grace, you shall not entreat him</line>
            <line>to a second, that have so mightily persuaded him</line>
            <line>from a first.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>An you mean to mock me after, you should not have</line>
            <line>mocked me before: but come your ways.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>Now Hercules be thy speed, young man!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>I would I were invisible, to catch the strong</line>
            <line>fellow by the leg.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>They wrestle</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>O excellent young man!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>If I had a thunderbolt in mine eye, I can tell who</line>
            <line>should down.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Shout. CHARLES is thrown</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE FREDERICK</speaker>
            <line>No more, no more.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>Yes, I beseech your grace: I am not yet well breathed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE FREDERICK</speaker>
            <line>How dost thou, Charles?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LE BEAU</speaker>
            <line>He cannot speak, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE FREDERICK</speaker>
            <line>Bear him away. What is thy name, young man?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>Orlando, my liege; the youngest son of Sir Rowland de Boys.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE FREDERICK</speaker>
            <line>I would thou hadst been son to some man else:</line>
            <line>The world esteem'd thy father honourable,</line>
            <line>But I did find him still mine enemy:</line>
            <line>Thou shouldst have better pleased me with this deed,</line>
            <line>Hadst thou descended from another house.</line>
            <line>But fare thee well; thou art a gallant youth:</line>
            <line>I would thou hadst told me of another father.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt DUKE FREDERICK, train, and LE BEAU</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>Were I my father, coz, would I do this?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>I am more proud to be Sir Rowland's son,</line>
            <line>His youngest son; and would not change that calling,</line>
            <line>To be adopted heir to Frederick.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>My father loved Sir Rowland as his soul,</line>
            <line>And all the world was of my father's mind:</line>
            <line>Had I before known this young man his son,</line>
            <line>I should have given him tears unto entreaties,</line>
            <line>Ere he should thus have ventured.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>Gentle cousin,</line>
            <line>Let us go thank him and encourage him:</line>
            <line>My father's rough and envious disposition</line>
            <line>Sticks me at heart. Sir, you have well deserved:</line>
            <line>If you do keep your promises in love</line>
            <line>But justly, as you have exceeded all promise,</line>
            <line>Your mistress shall be happy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>Gentleman,</line>
            <stagedir>Giving him a chain from her neck</stagedir>
            <line>Wear this for me, one out of suits with fortune,</line>
            <line>That could give more, but that her hand lacks means.</line>
            <line>Shall we go, coz?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>Ay. Fare you well, fair gentleman.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>Can I not say, I thank you? My better parts</line>
            <line>Are all thrown down, and that which here stands up</line>
            <line>Is but a quintain, a mere lifeless block.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>He calls us back: my pride fell with my fortunes;</line>
            <line>I'll ask him what he would. Did you call, sir?</line>
            <line>Sir, you have wrestled well and overthrown</line>
            <line>More than your enemies.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>Will you go, coz?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>Have with you. Fare you well.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt ROSALIND and CELIA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>What passion hangs these weights upon my tongue?</line>
            <line>I cannot speak to her, yet she urged conference.</line>
            <line>O poor Orlando, thou art overthrown!</line>
            <line>Or Charles or something weaker masters thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter LE BEAU</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LE BEAU</speaker>
            <line>Good sir, I do in friendship counsel you</line>
            <line>To leave this place. Albeit you have deserved</line>
            <line>High commendation, true applause and love,</line>
            <line>Yet such is now the duke's condition</line>
            <line>That he misconstrues all that you have done.</line>
            <line>The duke is humorous; what he is indeed,</line>
            <line>More suits you to conceive than I to speak of.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>I thank you, sir: and, pray you, tell me this:</line>
            <line>Which of the two was daughter of the duke</line>
            <line>That here was at the wrestling?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LE BEAU</speaker>
            <line>Neither his daughter, if we judge by manners;</line>
            <line>But yet indeed the lesser is his daughter</line>
            <line>The other is daughter to the banish'd duke,</line>
            <line>And here detain'd by her usurping uncle,</line>
            <line>To keep his daughter company; whose loves</line>
            <line>Are dearer than the natural bond of sisters.</line>
            <line>But I can tell you that of late this duke</line>
            <line>Hath ta'en displeasure 'gainst his gentle niece,</line>
            <line>Grounded upon no other argument</line>
            <line>But that the people praise her for her virtues</line>
            <line>And pity her for her good father's sake;</line>
            <line>And, on my life, his malice 'gainst the lady</line>
            <line>Will suddenly break forth. Sir, fare you well:</line>
            <line>Hereafter, in a better world than this,</line>
            <line>I shall desire more love and knowledge of you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>I rest much bounden to you: fare you well.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit LE BEAU</stagedir>
            <line>Thus must I from the smoke into the smother;</line>
            <line>From tyrant duke unto a tyrant brother:</line>
            <line>But heavenly Rosalind!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  A room in the palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter CELIA and ROSALIND</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>Why, cousin! why, Rosalind! Cupid have mercy! not a word?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>Not one to throw at a dog.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>No, thy words are too precious to be cast away upon</line>
            <line>curs; throw some of them at me; come, lame me with reasons.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>Then there were two cousins laid up; when the one</line>
            <line>should be lamed with reasons and the other mad</line>
            <line>without any.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>But is all this for your father?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>No, some of it is for my child's father. O, how</line>
            <line>full of briers is this working-day world!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>They are but burs, cousin, thrown upon thee in</line>
            <line>holiday foolery: if we walk not in the trodden</line>
            <line>paths our very petticoats will catch them.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>I could shake them off my coat: these burs are in my heart.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>Hem them away.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>I would try, if I could cry 'hem' and have him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>Come, come, wrestle with thy affections.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>O, they take the part of a better wrestler than myself!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>O, a good wish upon you! you will try in time, in</line>
            <line>despite of a fall. But, turning these jests out of</line>
            <line>service, let us talk in good earnest: is it</line>
            <line>possible, on such a sudden, you should fall into so</line>
            <line>strong a liking with old Sir Rowland's youngest son?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>The duke my father loved his father dearly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>Doth it therefore ensue that you should love his son</line>
            <line>dearly? By this kind of chase, I should hate him,</line>
            <line>for my father hated his father dearly; yet I hate</line>
            <line>not Orlando.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>No, faith, hate him not, for my sake.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>Why should I not? doth he not deserve well?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>Let me love him for that, and do you love him</line>
            <line>because I do. Look, here comes the duke.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>With his eyes full of anger.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter DUKE FREDERICK, with Lords</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE FREDERICK</speaker>
            <line>Mistress, dispatch you with your safest haste</line>
            <line>And get you from our court.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>Me, uncle?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE FREDERICK</speaker>
            <line>You, cousin</line>
            <line>Within these ten days if that thou be'st found</line>
            <line>So near our public court as twenty miles,</line>
            <line>Thou diest for it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>I do beseech your grace,</line>
            <line>Let me the knowledge of my fault bear with me:</line>
            <line>If with myself I hold intelligence</line>
            <line>Or have acquaintance with mine own desires,</line>
            <line>If that I do not dream or be not frantic,--</line>
            <line>As I do trust I am not--then, dear uncle,</line>
            <line>Never so much as in a thought unborn</line>
            <line>Did I offend your highness.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE FREDERICK</speaker>
            <line>Thus do all traitors:</line>
            <line>If their purgation did consist in words,</line>
            <line>They are as innocent as grace itself:</line>
            <line>Let it suffice thee that I trust thee not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>Yet your mistrust cannot make me a traitor:</line>
            <line>Tell me whereon the likelihood depends.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE FREDERICK</speaker>
            <line>Thou art thy father's daughter; there's enough.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>So was I when your highness took his dukedom;</line>
            <line>So was I when your highness banish'd him:</line>
            <line>Treason is not inherited, my lord;</line>
            <line>Or, if we did derive it from our friends,</line>
            <line>What's that to me? my father was no traitor:</line>
            <line>Then, good my liege, mistake me not so much</line>
            <line>To think my poverty is treacherous.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>Dear sovereign, hear me speak.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE FREDERICK</speaker>
            <line>Ay, Celia; we stay'd her for your sake,</line>
            <line>Else had she with her father ranged along.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>I did not then entreat to have her stay;</line>
            <line>It was your pleasure and your own remorse:</line>
            <line>I was too young that time to value her;</line>
            <line>But now I know her: if she be a traitor,</line>
            <line>Why so am I; we still have slept together,</line>
            <line>Rose at an instant, learn'd, play'd, eat together,</line>
            <line>And wheresoever we went, like Juno's swans,</line>
            <line>Still we went coupled and inseparable.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE FREDERICK</speaker>
            <line>She is too subtle for thee; and her smoothness,</line>
            <line>Her very silence and her patience</line>
            <line>Speak to the people, and they pity her.</line>
            <line>Thou art a fool: she robs thee of thy name;</line>
            <line>And thou wilt show more bright and seem more virtuous</line>
            <line>When she is gone. Then open not thy lips:</line>
            <line>Firm and irrevocable is my doom</line>
            <line>Which I have pass'd upon her; she is banish'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>Pronounce that sentence then on me, my liege:</line>
            <line>I cannot live out of her company.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE FREDERICK</speaker>
            <line>You are a fool. You, niece, provide yourself:</line>
            <line>If you outstay the time, upon mine honour,</line>
            <line>And in the greatness of my word, you die.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt DUKE FREDERICK and Lords</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>O my poor Rosalind, whither wilt thou go?</line>
            <line>Wilt thou change fathers? I will give thee mine.</line>
            <line>I charge thee, be not thou more grieved than I am.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>I have more cause.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>Thou hast not, cousin;</line>
            <line>Prithee be cheerful: know'st thou not, the duke</line>
            <line>Hath banish'd me, his daughter?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>That he hath not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>No, hath not? Rosalind lacks then the love</line>
            <line>Which teacheth thee that thou and I am one:</line>
            <line>Shall we be sunder'd? shall we part, sweet girl?</line>
            <line>No: let my father seek another heir.</line>
            <line>Therefore devise with me how we may fly,</line>
            <line>Whither to go and what to bear with us;</line>
            <line>And do not seek to take your change upon you,</line>
            <line>To bear your griefs yourself and leave me out;</line>
            <line>For, by this heaven, now at our sorrows pale,</line>
            <line>Say what thou canst, I'll go along with thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>Why, whither shall we go?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>To seek my uncle in the forest of Arden.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>Alas, what danger will it be to us,</line>
            <line>Maids as we are, to travel forth so far!</line>
            <line>Beauty provoketh thieves sooner than gold.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>I'll put myself in poor and mean attire</line>
            <line>And with a kind of umber smirch my face;</line>
            <line>The like do you: so shall we pass along</line>
            <line>And never stir assailants.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>Were it not better,</line>
            <line>Because that I am more than common tall,</line>
            <line>That I did suit me all points like a man?</line>
            <line>A gallant curtle-axe upon my thigh,</line>
            <line>A boar-spear in my hand; and--in my heart</line>
            <line>Lie there what hidden woman's fear there will--</line>
            <line>We'll have a swashing and a martial outside,</line>
            <line>As many other mannish cowards have</line>
            <line>That do outface it with their semblances.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>What shall I call thee when thou art a man?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>I'll have no worse a name than Jove's own page;</line>
            <line>And therefore look you call me Ganymede.</line>
            <line>But what will you be call'd?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>Something that hath a reference to my state</line>
            <line>No longer Celia, but Aliena.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>But, cousin, what if we assay'd to steal</line>
            <line>The clownish fool out of your father's court?</line>
            <line>Would he not be a comfort to our travel?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CELIA</speaker>
            <line>He'll go along o'er the wide world with me;</line>
            <line>Leave me alone to woo him. Let's away,</line>
            <line>And get our jewels and our wealth together,</line>
            <line>Devise the fittest time and safest way</line>
            <line>To hide us from pursuit that will be made</line>
            <line>After my flight. Now go we in content</line>
            <line>To liberty and not to banishment.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>