<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net/doctypes/dita/shakespear/dtd/act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-5">
   <title>ACT V</title>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  The forest.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter TOUCHSTONE and AUDREY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>We shall find a time, Audrey; patience, gentle Audrey.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUDREY</speaker>
            <line>Faith, the priest was good enough, for all the old</line>
            <line>gentleman's saying.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>A most wicked Sir Oliver, Audrey, a most vile</line>
            <line>Martext. But, Audrey, there is a youth here in the</line>
            <line>forest lays claim to you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUDREY</speaker>
            <line>Ay, I know who 'tis; he hath no interest in me in</line>
            <line>the world: here comes the man you mean.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>It is meat and drink to me to see a clown: by my</line>
            <line>troth, we that have good wits have much to answer</line>
            <line>for; we shall be flouting; we cannot hold.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter WILLIAM</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WILLIAM</speaker>
            <line>Good even, Audrey.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUDREY</speaker>
            <line>God ye good even, William.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WILLIAM</speaker>
            <line>And good even to you, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>Good even, gentle friend. Cover thy head, cover thy</line>
            <line>head; nay, prithee, be covered. How old are you, friend?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WILLIAM</speaker>
            <line>Five and twenty, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>A ripe age. Is thy name William?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WILLIAM</speaker>
            <line>William, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>A fair name. Wast born i' the forest here?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WILLIAM</speaker>
            <line>Ay, sir, I thank God.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>'Thank God;' a good answer. Art rich?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WILLIAM</speaker>
            <line>Faith, sir, so so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>'So so' is good, very good, very excellent good; and</line>
            <line>yet it is not; it is but so so. Art thou wise?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WILLIAM</speaker>
            <line>Ay, sir, I have a pretty wit.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>Why, thou sayest well. I do now remember a saying,</line>
            <line>'The fool doth think he is wise, but the wise man</line>
            <line>knows himself to be a fool.' The heathen</line>
            <line>philosopher, when he had a desire to eat a grape,</line>
            <line>would open his lips when he put it into his mouth;</line>
            <line>meaning thereby that grapes were made to eat and</line>
            <line>lips to open. You do love this maid?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WILLIAM</speaker>
            <line>I do, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>Give me your hand. Art thou learned?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WILLIAM</speaker>
            <line>No, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>Then learn this of me: to have, is to have; for it</line>
            <line>is a figure in rhetoric that drink, being poured out</line>
            <line>of a cup into a glass, by filling the one doth empty</line>
            <line>the other; for all your writers do consent that ipse</line>
            <line>is he: now, you are not ipse, for I am he.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WILLIAM</speaker>
            <line>Which he, sir?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>He, sir, that must marry this woman. Therefore, you</line>
            <line>clown, abandon,--which is in the vulgar leave,--the</line>
            <line>society,--which in the boorish is company,--of this</line>
            <line>female,--which in the common is woman; which</line>
            <line>together is, abandon the society of this female, or,</line>
            <line>clown, thou perishest; or, to thy better</line>
            <line>understanding, diest; or, to wit I kill thee, make</line>
            <line>thee away, translate thy life into death, thy</line>
            <line>liberty into bondage: I will deal in poison with</line>
            <line>thee, or in bastinado, or in steel; I will bandy</line>
            <line>with thee in faction; I will o'errun thee with</line>
            <line>policy; I will kill thee a hundred and fifty ways:</line>
            <line>therefore tremble and depart.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUDREY</speaker>
            <line>Do, good William.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WILLIAM</speaker>
            <line>God rest you merry, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Enter CORIN</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIN</speaker>
            <line>Our master and mistress seeks you; come, away, away!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>Trip, Audrey! trip, Audrey! I attend, I attend.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  The forest.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter ORLANDO and OLIVER</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>Is't possible that on so little acquaintance you</line>
            <line>should like her? that but seeing you should love</line>
            <line>her? and loving woo? and, wooing, she should</line>
            <line>grant? and will you persever to enjoy her?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVER</speaker>
            <line>Neither call the giddiness of it in question, the</line>
            <line>poverty of her, the small acquaintance, my sudden</line>
            <line>wooing, nor her sudden consenting; but say with me,</line>
            <line>I love Aliena; say with her that she loves me;</line>
            <line>consent with both that we may enjoy each other: it</line>
            <line>shall be to your good; for my father's house and all</line>
            <line>the revenue that was old Sir Rowland's will I</line>
            <line>estate upon you, and here live and die a shepherd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>You have my consent. Let your wedding be to-morrow:</line>
            <line>thither will I invite the duke and all's contented</line>
            <line>followers. Go you and prepare Aliena; for look</line>
            <line>you, here comes my Rosalind.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter ROSALIND</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>God save you, brother.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVER</speaker>
            <line>And you, fair sister.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>O, my dear Orlando, how it grieves me to see thee</line>
            <line>wear thy heart in a scarf!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>It is my arm.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>I thought thy heart had been wounded with the claws</line>
            <line>of a lion.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>Wounded it is, but with the eyes of a lady.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>Did your brother tell you how I counterfeited to</line>
            <line>swoon when he showed me your handkerchief?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>Ay, and greater wonders than that.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>O, I know where you are: nay, 'tis true: there was</line>
            <line>never any thing so sudden but the fight of two rams</line>
            <line>and Caesar's thrasonical brag of 'I came, saw, and</line>
            <line>overcame:' for your brother and my sister no sooner</line>
            <line>met but they looked, no sooner looked but they</line>
            <line>loved, no sooner loved but they sighed, no sooner</line>
            <line>sighed but they asked one another the reason, no</line>
            <line>sooner knew the reason but they sought the remedy;</line>
            <line>and in these degrees have they made a pair of stairs</line>
            <line>to marriage which they will climb incontinent, or</line>
            <line>else be incontinent before marriage: they are in</line>
            <line>the very wrath of love and they will together; clubs</line>
            <line>cannot part them.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>They shall be married to-morrow, and I will bid the</line>
            <line>duke to the nuptial. But, O, how bitter a thing it</line>
            <line>is to look into happiness through another man's</line>
            <line>eyes! By so much the more shall I to-morrow be at</line>
            <line>the height of heart-heaviness, by how much I shall</line>
            <line>think my brother happy in having what he wishes for.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>Why then, to-morrow I cannot serve your turn for Rosalind?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>I can live no longer by thinking.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>I will weary you then no longer with idle talking.</line>
            <line>Know of me then, for now I speak to some purpose,</line>
            <line>that I know you are a gentleman of good conceit: I</line>
            <line>speak not this that you should bear a good opinion</line>
            <line>of my knowledge, insomuch I say I know you are;</line>
            <line>neither do I labour for a greater esteem than may in</line>
            <line>some little measure draw a belief from you, to do</line>
            <line>yourself good and not to grace me. Believe then, if</line>
            <line>you please, that I can do strange things: I have,</line>
            <line>since I was three year old, conversed with a</line>
            <line>magician, most profound in his art and yet not</line>
            <line>damnable. If you do love Rosalind so near the heart</line>
            <line>as your gesture cries it out, when your brother</line>
            <line>marries Aliena, shall you marry her: I know into</line>
            <line>what straits of fortune she is driven; and it is</line>
            <line>not impossible to me, if it appear not inconvenient</line>
            <line>to you, to set her before your eyes tomorrow human</line>
            <line>as she is and without any danger.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>Speakest thou in sober meanings?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>By my life, I do; which I tender dearly, though I</line>
            <line>say I am a magician. Therefore, put you in your</line>
            <line>best array: bid your friends; for if you will be</line>
            <line>married to-morrow, you shall, and to Rosalind, if you will.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter SILVIUS and PHEBE</stagedir>
            <line>Look, here comes a lover of mine and a lover of hers.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PHEBE</speaker>
            <line>Youth, you have done me much ungentleness,</line>
            <line>To show the letter that I writ to you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>I care not if I have: it is my study</line>
            <line>To seem despiteful and ungentle to you:</line>
            <line>You are there followed by a faithful shepherd;</line>
            <line>Look upon him, love him; he worships you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PHEBE</speaker>
            <line>Good shepherd, tell this youth what 'tis to love.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SILVIUS</speaker>
            <line>It is to be all made of sighs and tears;</line>
            <line>And so am I for Phebe.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PHEBE</speaker>
            <line>And I for Ganymede.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>And I for Rosalind.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>And I for no woman.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SILVIUS</speaker>
            <line>It is to be all made of faith and service;</line>
            <line>And so am I for Phebe.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PHEBE</speaker>
            <line>And I for Ganymede.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>And I for Rosalind.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>And I for no woman.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SILVIUS</speaker>
            <line>It is to be all made of fantasy,</line>
            <line>All made of passion and all made of wishes,</line>
            <line>All adoration, duty, and observance,</line>
            <line>All humbleness, all patience and impatience,</line>
            <line>All purity, all trial, all observance;</line>
            <line>And so am I for Phebe.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PHEBE</speaker>
            <line>And so am I for Ganymede.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>And so am I for Rosalind.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>And so am I for no woman.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PHEBE</speaker>
            <line>If this be so, why blame you me to love you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SILVIUS</speaker>
            <line>If this be so, why blame you me to love you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>If this be so, why blame you me to love you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>Who do you speak to, 'Why blame you me to love you?'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>To her that is not here, nor doth not hear.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>Pray you, no more of this; 'tis like the howling</line>
            <line>of Irish wolves against the moon.</line>
            <stagedir>To SILVIUS</stagedir>
            <line>I will help you, if I can:</line>
            <stagedir>To PHEBE</stagedir>
            <line>I would love you, if I could. To-morrow meet me all together.</line>
            <stagedir>To PHEBE</stagedir>
            <line>I will marry you, if ever I marry woman, and I'll be</line>
            <line>married to-morrow:</line>
            <stagedir>To ORLANDO</stagedir>
            <line>I will satisfy you, if ever I satisfied man, and you</line>
            <line>shall be married to-morrow:</line>
            <stagedir>To SILVIUS</stagedir>
            <line>I will content you, if what pleases you contents</line>
            <line>you, and you shall be married to-morrow.</line>
            <stagedir>To ORLANDO</stagedir>
            <line>As you love Rosalind, meet:</line>
            <stagedir>To SILVIUS</stagedir>
            <line>as you love Phebe, meet: and as I love no woman,</line>
            <line>I'll meet. So fare you well: I have left you commands.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SILVIUS</speaker>
            <line>I'll not fail, if I live.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PHEBE</speaker>
            <line>Nor I.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>Nor I.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  The forest.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter TOUCHSTONE and AUDREY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>To-morrow is the joyful day, Audrey; to-morrow will</line>
            <line>we be married.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUDREY</speaker>
            <line>I do desire it with all my heart; and I hope it is</line>
            <line>no dishonest desire to desire to be a woman of the</line>
            <line>world. Here comes two of the banished duke's pages.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter two Pages</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Page</speaker>
            <line>Well met, honest gentleman.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>By my troth, well met. Come, sit, sit, and a song.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Page</speaker>
            <line>We are for you: sit i' the middle.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Page</speaker>
            <line>Shall we clap into't roundly, without hawking or</line>
            <line>spitting or saying we are hoarse, which are the only</line>
            <line>prologues to a bad voice?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Page</speaker>
            <line>I'faith, i'faith; and both in a tune, like two</line>
            <line>gipsies on a horse.</line>
            <subhead>SONG.</subhead>
            <line>It was a lover and his lass,</line>
            <line>With a hey, and a ho, and a hey nonino,</line>
            <line>That o'er the green corn-field did pass</line>
            <line>In the spring time, the only pretty ring time,</line>
            <line>When birds do sing, hey ding a ding, ding:</line>
            <line>Sweet lovers love the spring.</line>
            <line>Between the acres of the rye,</line>
            <line>With a hey, and a ho, and a hey nonino</line>
            <line>These pretty country folks would lie,</line>
            <line>In spring time, &amp;c.</line>
            <line>This carol they began that hour,</line>
            <line>With a hey, and a ho, and a hey nonino,</line>
            <line>How that a life was but a flower</line>
            <line>In spring time, &amp;c.</line>
            <line>And therefore take the present time,</line>
            <line>With a hey, and a ho, and a hey nonino;</line>
            <line>For love is crowned with the prime</line>
            <line>In spring time, &amp;c.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>Truly, young gentlemen, though there was no great</line>
            <line>matter in the ditty, yet the note was very</line>
            <line>untuneable.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Page</speaker>
            <line>You are deceived, sir: we kept time, we lost not our time.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>By my troth, yes; I count it but time lost to hear</line>
            <line>such a foolish song. God be wi' you; and God mend</line>
            <line>your voices! Come, Audrey.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-4">
      <title>SCENE IV.  The forest.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter DUKE SENIOR, AMIENS, JAQUES, ORLANDO, OLIVER,
and CELIA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE SENIOR</speaker>
            <line>Dost thou believe, Orlando, that the boy</line>
            <line>Can do all this that he hath promised?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>I sometimes do believe, and sometimes do not;</line>
            <line>As those that fear they hope, and know they fear.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter ROSALIND, SILVIUS, and PHEBE</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>Patience once more, whiles our compact is urged:</line>
            <line>You say, if I bring in your Rosalind,</line>
            <line>You will bestow her on Orlando here?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE SENIOR</speaker>
            <line>That would I, had I kingdoms to give with her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>And you say, you will have her, when I bring her?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>That would I, were I of all kingdoms king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>You say, you'll marry me, if I be willing?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PHEBE</speaker>
            <line>That will I, should I die the hour after.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>But if you do refuse to marry me,</line>
            <line>You'll give yourself to this most faithful shepherd?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PHEBE</speaker>
            <line>So is the bargain.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>You say, that you'll have Phebe, if she will?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SILVIUS</speaker>
            <line>Though to have her and death were both one thing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>I have promised to make all this matter even.</line>
            <line>Keep you your word, O duke, to give your daughter;</line>
            <line>You yours, Orlando, to receive his daughter:</line>
            <line>Keep your word, Phebe, that you'll marry me,</line>
            <line>Or else refusing me, to wed this shepherd:</line>
            <line>Keep your word, Silvius, that you'll marry her.</line>
            <line>If she refuse me: and from hence I go,</line>
            <line>To make these doubts all even.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt ROSALIND and CELIA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE SENIOR</speaker>
            <line>I do remember in this shepherd boy</line>
            <line>Some lively touches of my daughter's favour.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>My lord, the first time that I ever saw him</line>
            <line>Methought he was a brother to your daughter:</line>
            <line>But, my good lord, this boy is forest-born,</line>
            <line>And hath been tutor'd in the rudiments</line>
            <line>Of many desperate studies by his uncle,</line>
            <line>Whom he reports to be a great magician,</line>
            <line>Obscured in the circle of this forest.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter TOUCHSTONE and AUDREY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JAQUES</speaker>
            <line>There is, sure, another flood toward, and these</line>
            <line>couples are coming to the ark. Here comes a pair of</line>
            <line>very strange beasts, which in all tongues are called fools.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>Salutation and greeting to you all!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JAQUES</speaker>
            <line>Good my lord, bid him welcome: this is the</line>
            <line>motley-minded gentleman that I have so often met in</line>
            <line>the forest: he hath been a courtier, he swears.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>If any man doubt that, let him put me to my</line>
            <line>purgation. I have trod a measure; I have flattered</line>
            <line>a lady; I have been politic with my friend, smooth</line>
            <line>with mine enemy; I have undone three tailors; I have</line>
            <line>had four quarrels, and like to have fought one.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JAQUES</speaker>
            <line>And how was that ta'en up?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>Faith, we met, and found the quarrel was upon the</line>
            <line>seventh cause.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JAQUES</speaker>
            <line>How seventh cause? Good my lord, like this fellow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE SENIOR</speaker>
            <line>I like him very well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>God 'ild you, sir; I desire you of the like. I</line>
            <line>press in here, sir, amongst the rest of the country</line>
            <line>copulatives, to swear and to forswear: according as</line>
            <line>marriage binds and blood breaks: a poor virgin,</line>
            <line>sir, an ill-favoured thing, sir, but mine own; a poor</line>
            <line>humour of mine, sir, to take that that no man else</line>
            <line>will: rich honesty dwells like a miser, sir, in a</line>
            <line>poor house; as your pearl in your foul oyster.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE SENIOR</speaker>
            <line>By my faith, he is very swift and sententious.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>According to the fool's bolt, sir, and such dulcet diseases.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JAQUES</speaker>
            <line>But, for the seventh cause; how did you find the</line>
            <line>quarrel on the seventh cause?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>Upon a lie seven times removed:--bear your body more</line>
            <line>seeming, Audrey:--as thus, sir. I did dislike the</line>
            <line>cut of a certain courtier's beard: he sent me word,</line>
            <line>if I said his beard was not cut well, he was in the</line>
            <line>mind it was: this is called the Retort Courteous.</line>
            <line>If I sent him word again 'it was not well cut,' he</line>
            <line>would send me word, he cut it to please himself:</line>
            <line>this is called the Quip Modest. If again 'it was</line>
            <line>not well cut,' he disabled my judgment: this is</line>
            <line>called the Reply Churlish. If again 'it was not</line>
            <line>well cut,' he would answer, I spake not true: this</line>
            <line>is called the Reproof Valiant. If again 'it was not</line>
            <line>well cut,' he would say I lied: this is called the</line>
            <line>Counter-cheque Quarrelsome: and so to the Lie</line>
            <line>Circumstantial and the Lie Direct.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JAQUES</speaker>
            <line>And how oft did you say his beard was not well cut?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>I durst go no further than the Lie Circumstantial,</line>
            <line>nor he durst not give me the Lie Direct; and so we</line>
            <line>measured swords and parted.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JAQUES</speaker>
            <line>Can you nominate in order now the degrees of the lie?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TOUCHSTONE</speaker>
            <line>O sir, we quarrel in print, by the book; as you have</line>
            <line>books for good manners: I will name you the degrees.</line>
            <line>The first, the Retort Courteous; the second, the</line>
            <line>Quip Modest; the third, the Reply Churlish; the</line>
            <line>fourth, the Reproof Valiant; the fifth, the</line>
            <line>Countercheque Quarrelsome; the sixth, the Lie with</line>
            <line>Circumstance; the seventh, the Lie Direct. All</line>
            <line>these you may avoid but the Lie Direct; and you may</line>
            <line>avoid that too, with an If. I knew when seven</line>
            <line>justices could not take up a quarrel, but when the</line>
            <line>parties were met themselves, one of them thought but</line>
            <line>of an If, as, 'If you said so, then I said so;' and</line>
            <line>they shook hands and swore brothers. Your If is the</line>
            <line>only peacemaker; much virtue in If.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JAQUES</speaker>
            <line>Is not this a rare fellow, my lord? he's as good at</line>
            <line>any thing and yet a fool.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE SENIOR</speaker>
            <line>He uses his folly like a stalking-horse and under</line>
            <line>the presentation of that he shoots his wit.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter HYMEN, ROSALIND, and CELIA</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Still Music</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HYMEN</speaker>
            <line>Then is there mirth in heaven,</line>
            <line>When earthly things made even</line>
            <line>Atone together.</line>
            <line>Good duke, receive thy daughter</line>
            <line>Hymen from heaven brought her,</line>
            <line>Yea, brought her hither,</line>
            <line>That thou mightst join her hand with his</line>
            <line>Whose heart within his bosom is.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>To DUKE SENIOR</stagedir>  To you I give myself, for I am yours.</line>
            <stagedir>To ORLANDO</stagedir>
            <line>To you I give myself, for I am yours.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE SENIOR</speaker>
            <line>If there be truth in sight, you are my daughter.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLANDO</speaker>
            <line>If there be truth in sight, you are my Rosalind.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PHEBE</speaker>
            <line>If sight and shape be true,</line>
            <line>Why then, my love adieu!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>I'll have no father, if you be not he:</line>
            <line>I'll have no husband, if you be not he:</line>
            <line>Nor ne'er wed woman, if you be not she.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HYMEN</speaker>
            <line>Peace, ho! I bar confusion:</line>
            <line>'Tis I must make conclusion</line>
            <line>Of these most strange events:</line>
            <line>Here's eight that must take hands</line>
            <line>To join in Hymen's bands,</line>
            <line>If truth holds true contents.</line>
            <line>You and you no cross shall part:</line>
            <line>You and you are heart in heart</line>
            <line>You to his love must accord,</line>
            <line>Or have a woman to your lord:</line>
            <line>You and you are sure together,</line>
            <line>As the winter to foul weather.</line>
            <line>Whiles a wedlock-hymn we sing,</line>
            <line>Feed yourselves with questioning;</line>
            <line>That reason wonder may diminish,</line>
            <line>How thus we met, and these things finish.</line>
            <subhead>SONG.</subhead>
            <line>Wedding is great Juno's crown:</line>
            <line>O blessed bond of board and bed!</line>
            <line>'Tis Hymen peoples every town;</line>
            <line>High wedlock then be honoured:</line>
            <line>Honour, high honour and renown,</line>
            <line>To Hymen, god of every town!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE SENIOR</speaker>
            <line>O my dear niece, welcome thou art to me!</line>
            <line>Even daughter, welcome, in no less degree.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PHEBE</speaker>
            <line>I will not eat my word, now thou art mine;</line>
            <line>Thy faith my fancy to thee doth combine.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter JAQUES DE BOYS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JAQUES DE BOYS</speaker>
            <line>Let me have audience for a word or two:</line>
            <line>I am the second son of old Sir Rowland,</line>
            <line>That bring these tidings to this fair assembly.</line>
            <line>Duke Frederick, hearing how that every day</line>
            <line>Men of great worth resorted to this forest,</line>
            <line>Address'd a mighty power; which were on foot,</line>
            <line>In his own conduct, purposely to take</line>
            <line>His brother here and put him to the sword:</line>
            <line>And to the skirts of this wild wood he came;</line>
            <line>Where meeting with an old religious man,</line>
            <line>After some question with him, was converted</line>
            <line>Both from his enterprise and from the world,</line>
            <line>His crown bequeathing to his banish'd brother,</line>
            <line>And all their lands restored to them again</line>
            <line>That were with him exiled. This to be true,</line>
            <line>I do engage my life.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE SENIOR</speaker>
            <line>Welcome, young man;</line>
            <line>Thou offer'st fairly to thy brothers' wedding:</line>
            <line>To one his lands withheld, and to the other</line>
            <line>A land itself at large, a potent dukedom.</line>
            <line>First, in this forest, let us do those ends</line>
            <line>That here were well begun and well begot:</line>
            <line>And after, every of this happy number</line>
            <line>That have endured shrewd days and nights with us</line>
            <line>Shall share the good of our returned fortune,</line>
            <line>According to the measure of their states.</line>
            <line>Meantime, forget this new-fall'n dignity</line>
            <line>And fall into our rustic revelry.</line>
            <line>Play, music! And you, brides and bridegrooms all,</line>
            <line>With measure heap'd in joy, to the measures fall.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JAQUES</speaker>
            <line>Sir, by your patience. If I heard you rightly,</line>
            <line>The duke hath put on a religious life</line>
            <line>And thrown into neglect the pompous court?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JAQUES DE BOYS</speaker>
            <line>He hath.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JAQUES</speaker>
            <line>To him will I : out of these convertites</line>
            <line>There is much matter to be heard and learn'd.</line>
            <stagedir>To DUKE SENIOR</stagedir>
            <line>You to your former honour I bequeath;</line>
            <line>Your patience and your virtue well deserves it:</line>
            <stagedir>To ORLANDO</stagedir>
            <line>You to a love that your true faith doth merit:</line>
            <stagedir>To OLIVER</stagedir>
            <line>You to your land and love and great allies:</line>
            <stagedir>To SILVIUS</stagedir>
            <line>You to a long and well-deserved bed:</line>
            <stagedir>To TOUCHSTONE</stagedir>
            <line>And you to wrangling; for thy loving voyage</line>
            <line>Is but for two months victuall'd. So, to your pleasures:</line>
            <line>I am for other than for dancing measures.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE SENIOR</speaker>
            <line>Stay, Jaques, stay.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JAQUES</speaker>
            <line>To see no pastime I what you would have</line>
            <line>I'll stay to know at your abandon'd cave.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE SENIOR</speaker>
            <line>Proceed, proceed: we will begin these rites,</line>
            <line>As we do trust they'll end, in true delights.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>A dance</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <epilogue id="act-5-epilog">
      <title>EPILOGUE</title>
      <epilogue-body>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALIND</speaker>
            <line>It is not the fashion to see the lady the epilogue;</line>
            <line>but it is no more unhandsome than to see the lord</line>
            <line>the prologue. If it be true that good wine needs</line>
            <line>no bush, 'tis true that a good play needs no</line>
            <line>epilogue; yet to good wine they do use good bushes,</line>
            <line>and good plays prove the better by the help of good</line>
            <line>epilogues. What a case am I in then, that am</line>
            <line>neither a good epilogue nor cannot insinuate with</line>
            <line>you in the behalf of a good play! I am not</line>
            <line>furnished like a beggar, therefore to beg will not</line>
            <line>become me: my way is to conjure you; and I'll begin</line>
            <line>with the women. I charge you, O women, for the love</line>
            <line>you bear to men, to like as much of this play as</line>
            <line>please you: and I charge you, O men, for the love</line>
            <line>you bear to women--as I perceive by your simpering,</line>
            <line>none of you hates them--that between you and the</line>
            <line>women the play may please. If I were a woman I</line>
            <line>would kiss as many of you as had beards that pleased</line>
            <line>me, complexions that liked me and breaths that I</line>
            <line>defied not: and, I am sure, as many as have good</line>
            <line>beards or good faces or sweet breaths will, for my</line>
            <line>kind offer, when I make curtsy, bid me farewell.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </epilogue-body>
   </epilogue>
</act>