<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:shakespear:dtd:act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-5">
   <title>ACT V</title>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  A room in the Garter Inn.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter FALSTAFF and MISTRESS QUICKLY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Prithee, no more prattling; go. I'll hold. This is</line>
            <line>the third time; I hope good luck lies in odd</line>
            <line>numbers. Away I go. They say there is divinity in</line>
            <line>odd numbers, either in nativity, chance, or death. Away!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS QUICKLY</speaker>
            <line>I'll provide you a chain; and I'll do what I can to</line>
            <line>get you a pair of horns.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Away, I say; time wears: hold up your head, and mince.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit MISTRESS QUICKLY</stagedir>
            <stagedir>Enter FORD</stagedir>
            <line>How now, Master Brook! Master Brook, the matter</line>
            <line>will be known to-night, or never. Be you in the</line>
            <line>Park about midnight, at Herne's oak, and you shall</line>
            <line>see wonders.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>Went you not to her yesterday, sir, as you told me</line>
            <line>you had appointed?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>I went to her, Master Brook, as you see, like a poor</line>
            <line>old man: but I came from her, Master Brook, like a</line>
            <line>poor old woman. That same knave Ford, her husband,</line>
            <line>hath the finest mad devil of jealousy in him,</line>
            <line>Master Brook, that ever governed frenzy. I will tell</line>
            <line>you: he beat me grievously, in the shape of a</line>
            <line>woman; for in the shape of man, Master Brook, I fear</line>
            <line>not Goliath with a weaver's beam; because I know</line>
            <line>also life is a shuttle. I am in haste; go along</line>
            <line>with me: I'll tell you all, Master Brook. Since I</line>
            <line>plucked geese, played truant and whipped top, I knew</line>
            <line>not what 'twas to be beaten till lately. Follow</line>
            <line>me: I'll tell you strange things of this knave</line>
            <line>Ford, on whom to-night I will be revenged, and I</line>
            <line>will deliver his wife into your hand. Follow.</line>
            <line>Strange things in hand, Master Brook! Follow.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  Windsor Park.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter PAGE, SHALLOW, and SLENDER</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Come, come; we'll couch i' the castle-ditch till we</line>
            <line>see the light of our fairies. Remember, son Slender,</line>
            <line>my daughter.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SLENDER</speaker>
            <line>Ay, forsooth; I have spoke with her and we have a</line>
            <line>nay-word how to know one another: I come to her in</line>
            <line>white, and cry 'mum;' she cries 'budget;' and by</line>
            <line>that we know one another.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>That's good too: but what needs either your 'mum'</line>
            <line>or her 'budget?' the white will decipher her well</line>
            <line>enough. It hath struck ten o'clock.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAGE</speaker>
            <line>The night is dark; light and spirits will become it</line>
            <line>well. Heaven prosper our sport! No man means evil</line>
            <line>but the devil, and we shall know him by his horns.</line>
            <line>Let's away; follow me.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  A street leading to the Park.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter MISTRESS PAGE, MISTRESS FORD, and
DOCTOR CAIUS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Master doctor, my daughter is in green: when you</line>
            <line>see your time, take her by the band, away with her</line>
            <line>to the deanery, and dispatch it quickly. Go before</line>
            <line>into the Park: we two must go together.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOCTOR CAIUS</speaker>
            <line>I know vat I have to do. Adieu.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Fare you well, sir.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit DOCTOR CAIUS</stagedir>
            <line>My husband will not rejoice so much at the abuse of</line>
            <line>Falstaff as he will chafe at the doctor's marrying</line>
            <line>my daughter: but 'tis no matter; better a little</line>
            <line>chiding than a great deal of heart-break.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS FORD</speaker>
            <line>Where is Nan now and her troop of fairies, and the</line>
            <line>Welsh devil Hugh?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>They are all couched in a pit hard by Herne's oak,</line>
            <line>with obscured lights; which, at the very instant of</line>
            <line>Falstaff's and our meeting, they will at once</line>
            <line>display to the night.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS FORD</speaker>
            <line>That cannot choose but amaze him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>If he be not amazed, he will be mocked; if he be</line>
            <line>amazed, he will every way be mocked.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS FORD</speaker>
            <line>We'll betray him finely.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Against such lewdsters and their lechery</line>
            <line>Those that betray them do no treachery.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS FORD</speaker>
            <line>The hour draws on. To the oak, to the oak!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-4">
      <title>SCENE IV.  Windsor Park.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter SIR HUGH EVANS, disguised, with others as Fairies</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR HUGH EVANS</speaker>
            <line>Trib, trib, fairies; come; and remember your parts:</line>
            <line>be pold, I pray you; follow me into the pit; and</line>
            <line>when I give the watch-'ords, do as I pid you:</line>
            <line>come, come; trib, trib.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-5">
      <title>SCENE V.  Another part of the Park.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter FALSTAFF disguised as Herne</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>The Windsor bell hath struck twelve; the minute</line>
            <line>draws on. Now, the hot-blooded gods assist me!</line>
            <line>Remember, Jove, thou wast a bull for thy Europa; love</line>
            <line>set on thy horns. O powerful love! that, in some</line>
            <line>respects, makes a beast a man, in some other, a man</line>
            <line>a beast. You were also, Jupiter, a swan for the love</line>
            <line>of Leda. O omnipotent Love! how near the god drew</line>
            <line>to the complexion of a goose! A fault done first in</line>
            <line>the form of a beast. O Jove, a beastly fault! And</line>
            <line>then another fault in the semblance of a fowl; think</line>
            <line>on 't, Jove; a foul fault! When gods have hot</line>
            <line>backs, what shall poor men do? For me, I am here a</line>
            <line>Windsor stag; and the fattest, I think, i' the</line>
            <line>forest. Send me a cool rut-time, Jove, or who can</line>
            <line>blame me to piss my tallow? Who comes here? my</line>
            <line>doe?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter MISTRESS FORD and MISTRESS PAGE</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS FORD</speaker>
            <line>Sir John! art thou there, my deer? my male deer?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>My doe with the black scut! Let the sky rain</line>
            <line>potatoes; let it thunder to the tune of Green</line>
            <line>Sleeves, hail kissing-comfits and snow eringoes; let</line>
            <line>there come a tempest of provocation, I will shelter me here.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS FORD</speaker>
            <line>Mistress Page is come with me, sweetheart.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Divide me like a bribe buck, each a haunch: I will</line>
            <line>keep my sides to myself, my shoulders for the fellow</line>
            <line>of this walk, and my horns I bequeath your husbands.</line>
            <line>Am I a woodman, ha? Speak I like Herne the hunter?</line>
            <line>Why, now is Cupid a child of conscience; he makes</line>
            <line>restitution. As I am a true spirit, welcome!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Noise within</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Alas, what noise?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS FORD</speaker>
            <line>Heaven forgive our sins</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>What should this be?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS FORD</speaker>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Away, away!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>They run off</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>I think the devil will not have me damned, lest the</line>
            <line>oil that's in me should set hell on fire; he would</line>
            <line>never else cross me thus.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter SIR HUGH EVANS, disguised as before; PISTOL,
as Hobgoblin; MISTRESS QUICKLY, ANNE PAGE, and
others, as Fairies, with tapers</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS QUICKLY</speaker>
            <line>Fairies, black, grey, green, and white,</line>
            <line>You moonshine revellers and shades of night,</line>
            <line>You orphan heirs of fixed destiny,</line>
            <line>Attend your office and your quality.</line>
            <line>Crier Hobgoblin, make the fairy oyes.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>Elves, list your names; silence, you airy toys.</line>
            <line>Cricket, to Windsor chimneys shalt thou leap:</line>
            <line>Where fires thou find'st unraked and hearths unswept,</line>
            <line>There pinch the maids as blue as bilberry:</line>
            <line>Our radiant queen hates sluts and sluttery.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>They are fairies; he that speaks to them shall die:</line>
            <line>I'll wink and couch: no man their works must eye.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Lies down upon his face</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR HUGH EVANS</speaker>
            <line>Where's Bede? Go you, and where you find a maid</line>
            <line>That, ere she sleep, has thrice her prayers said,</line>
            <line>Raise up the organs of her fantasy;</line>
            <line>Sleep she as sound as careless infancy:</line>
            <line>But those as sleep and think not on their sins,</line>
            <line>Pinch them, arms, legs, backs, shoulders, sides and shins.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS QUICKLY</speaker>
            <line>About, about;</line>
            <line>Search Windsor Castle, elves, within and out:</line>
            <line>Strew good luck, ouphes, on every sacred room:</line>
            <line>That it may stand till the perpetual doom,</line>
            <line>In state as wholesome as in state 'tis fit,</line>
            <line>Worthy the owner, and the owner it.</line>
            <line>The several chairs of order look you scour</line>
            <line>With juice of balm and every precious flower:</line>
            <line>Each fair instalment, coat, and several crest,</line>
            <line>With loyal blazon, evermore be blest!</line>
            <line>And nightly, meadow-fairies, look you sing,</line>
            <line>Like to the Garter's compass, in a ring:</line>
            <line>The expressure that it bears, green let it be,</line>
            <line>More fertile-fresh than all the field to see;</line>
            <line>And 'Honi soit qui mal y pense' write</line>
            <line>In emerald tufts, flowers purple, blue and white;</line>
            <line>Let sapphire, pearl and rich embroidery,</line>
            <line>Buckled below fair knighthood's bending knee:</line>
            <line>Fairies use flowers for their charactery.</line>
            <line>Away; disperse: but till 'tis one o'clock,</line>
            <line>Our dance of custom round about the oak</line>
            <line>Of Herne the hunter, let us not forget.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR HUGH EVANS</speaker>
            <line>Pray you, lock hand in hand; yourselves in order set</line>
            <line>And twenty glow-worms shall our lanterns be,</line>
            <line>To guide our measure round about the tree.</line>
            <line>But, stay; I smell a man of middle-earth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Heavens defend me from that Welsh fairy, lest he</line>
            <line>transform me to a piece of cheese!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>Vile worm, thou wast o'erlook'd even in thy birth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS QUICKLY</speaker>
            <line>With trial-fire touch me his finger-end:</line>
            <line>If he be chaste, the flame will back descend</line>
            <line>And turn him to no pain; but if he start,</line>
            <line>It is the flesh of a corrupted heart.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>A trial, come.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR HUGH EVANS</speaker>
            <line>Come, will this wood take fire?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>They burn him with their tapers</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Oh, Oh, Oh!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS QUICKLY</speaker>
            <line>Corrupt, corrupt, and tainted in desire!</line>
            <line>About him, fairies; sing a scornful rhyme;</line>
            <line>And, as you trip, still pinch him to your time.</line>
            <subhead>SONG.</subhead>
            <line>Fie on sinful fantasy!</line>
            <line>Fie on lust and luxury!</line>
            <line>Lust is but a bloody fire,</line>
            <line>Kindled with unchaste desire,</line>
            <line>Fed in heart, whose flames aspire</line>
            <line>As thoughts do blow them, higher and higher.</line>
            <line>Pinch him, fairies, mutually;</line>
            <line>Pinch him for his villany;</line>
            <line>Pinch him, and burn him, and turn him about,</line>
            <line>Till candles and starlight and moonshine be out.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>During this song they pinch FALSTAFF. DOCTOR CAIUS
comes one way, and steals away a boy in green;
SLENDER another way, and takes off a boy in white;
and FENTON comes and steals away ANN PAGE.
A noise of hunting is heard within. All the
Fairies run away. FALSTAFF pulls off his buck's
head, and rises</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Enter PAGE, FORD, MISTRESS PAGE, and MISTRESS FORD</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Nay, do not fly; I think we have watch'd you now</line>
            <line>Will none but Herne the hunter serve your turn?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>I pray you, come, hold up the jest no higher</line>
            <line>Now, good Sir John, how like you Windsor wives?</line>
            <line>See you these, husband? do not these fair yokes</line>
            <line>Become the forest better than the town?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>Now, sir, who's a cuckold now? Master Brook,</line>
            <line>Falstaff's a knave, a cuckoldly knave; here are his</line>
            <line>horns, Master Brook: and, Master Brook, he hath</line>
            <line>enjoyed nothing of Ford's but his buck-basket, his</line>
            <line>cudgel, and twenty pounds of money, which must be</line>
            <line>paid to Master Brook; his horses are arrested for</line>
            <line>it, Master Brook.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS FORD</speaker>
            <line>Sir John, we have had ill luck; we could never meet.</line>
            <line>I will never take you for my love again; but I will</line>
            <line>always count you my deer.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>I do begin to perceive that I am made an ass.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>Ay, and an ox too: both the proofs are extant.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>And these are not fairies? I was three or four</line>
            <line>times in the thought they were not fairies: and yet</line>
            <line>the guiltiness of my mind, the sudden surprise of my</line>
            <line>powers, drove the grossness of the foppery into a</line>
            <line>received belief, in despite of the teeth of all</line>
            <line>rhyme and reason, that they were fairies. See now</line>
            <line>how wit may be made a Jack-a-Lent, when 'tis upon</line>
            <line>ill employment!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR HUGH EVANS</speaker>
            <line>Sir John Falstaff, serve Got, and leave your</line>
            <line>desires, and fairies will not pinse you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>Well said, fairy Hugh.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR HUGH EVANS</speaker>
            <line>And leave your jealousies too, I pray you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>I will never mistrust my wife again till thou art</line>
            <line>able to woo her in good English.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Have I laid my brain in the sun and dried it, that</line>
            <line>it wants matter to prevent so gross o'erreaching as</line>
            <line>this? Am I ridden with a Welsh goat too? shall I</line>
            <line>have a coxcomb of frize? 'Tis time I were choked</line>
            <line>with a piece of toasted cheese.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR HUGH EVANS</speaker>
            <line>Seese is not good to give putter; your belly is all putter.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>'Seese' and 'putter'! have I lived to stand at the</line>
            <line>taunt of one that makes fritters of English? This</line>
            <line>is enough to be the decay of lust and late-walking</line>
            <line>through the realm.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Why Sir John, do you think, though we would have the</line>
            <line>virtue out of our hearts by the head and shoulders</line>
            <line>and have given ourselves without scruple to hell,</line>
            <line>that ever the devil could have made you our delight?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>What, a hodge-pudding? a bag of flax?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>A puffed man?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Old, cold, withered and of intolerable entrails?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>And one that is as slanderous as Satan?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAGE</speaker>
            <line>And as poor as Job?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>And as wicked as his wife?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR HUGH EVANS</speaker>
            <line>And given to fornications, and to taverns and sack</line>
            <line>and wine and metheglins, and to drinkings and</line>
            <line>swearings and starings, pribbles and prabbles?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Well, I am your theme: you have the start of me; I</line>
            <line>am dejected; I am not able to answer the Welsh</line>
            <line>flannel; ignorance itself is a plummet o'er me: use</line>
            <line>me as you will.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>Marry, sir, we'll bring you to Windsor, to one</line>
            <line>Master Brook, that you have cozened of money, to</line>
            <line>whom you should have been a pander: over and above</line>
            <line>that you have suffered, I think to repay that money</line>
            <line>will be a biting affliction.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Yet be cheerful, knight: thou shalt eat a posset</line>
            <line>to-night at my house; where I will desire thee to</line>
            <line>laugh at my wife, that now laughs at thee: tell her</line>
            <line>Master Slender hath married her daughter.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  Doctors doubt that: if Anne Page be my</line>
            <line>daughter, she is, by this, Doctor Caius' wife.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter SLENDER</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SLENDER</speaker>
            <line>Whoa ho! ho, father Page!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Son, how now! how now, son! have you dispatched?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SLENDER</speaker>
            <line>Dispatched! I'll make the best in Gloucestershire</line>
            <line>know on't; would I were hanged, la, else.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Of what, son?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SLENDER</speaker>
            <line>I came yonder at Eton to marry Mistress Anne Page,</line>
            <line>and she's a great lubberly boy. If it had not been</line>
            <line>i' the church, I would have swinged him, or he</line>
            <line>should have swinged me. If I did not think it had</line>
            <line>been Anne Page, would I might never stir!--and 'tis</line>
            <line>a postmaster's boy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Upon my life, then, you took the wrong.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SLENDER</speaker>
            <line>What need you tell me that? I think so, when I took</line>
            <line>a boy for a girl. If I had been married to him, for</line>
            <line>all he was in woman's apparel, I would not have had</line>
            <line>him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Why, this is your own folly. Did not I tell you how</line>
            <line>you should know my daughter by her garments?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SLENDER</speaker>
            <line>I went to her in white, and cried 'mum,' and she</line>
            <line>cried 'budget,' as Anne and I had appointed; and yet</line>
            <line>it was not Anne, but a postmaster's boy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Good George, be not angry: I knew of your purpose;</line>
            <line>turned my daughter into green; and, indeed, she is</line>
            <line>now with the doctor at the deanery, and there married.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter DOCTOR CAIUS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOCTOR CAIUS</speaker>
            <line>Vere is Mistress Page? By gar, I am cozened: I ha'</line>
            <line>married un garcon, a boy; un paysan, by gar, a boy;</line>
            <line>it is not Anne Page: by gar, I am cozened.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Why, did you take her in green?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOCTOR CAIUS</speaker>
            <line>Ay, by gar, and 'tis a boy: by gar, I'll raise all Windsor.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>This is strange. Who hath got the right Anne?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAGE</speaker>
            <line>My heart misgives me: here comes Master Fenton.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter FENTON and ANNE PAGE</stagedir>
            <line>How now, Master Fenton!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANNE PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Pardon, good father! good my mother, pardon!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Now, mistress, how chance you went not with Master Slender?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Why went you not with master doctor, maid?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FENTON</speaker>
            <line>You do amaze her: hear the truth of it.</line>
            <line>You would have married her most shamefully,</line>
            <line>Where there was no proportion held in love.</line>
            <line>The truth is, she and I, long since contracted,</line>
            <line>Are now so sure that nothing can dissolve us.</line>
            <line>The offence is holy that she hath committed;</line>
            <line>And this deceit loses the name of craft,</line>
            <line>Of disobedience, or unduteous title,</line>
            <line>Since therein she doth evitate and shun</line>
            <line>A thousand irreligious cursed hours,</line>
            <line>Which forced marriage would have brought upon her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>Stand not amazed; here is no remedy:</line>
            <line>In love the heavens themselves do guide the state;</line>
            <line>Money buys lands, and wives are sold by fate.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>I am glad, though you have ta'en a special stand to</line>
            <line>strike at me, that your arrow hath glanced.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Well, what remedy? Fenton, heaven give thee joy!</line>
            <line>What cannot be eschew'd must be embraced.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>When night-dogs run, all sorts of deer are chased.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Well, I will muse no further. Master Fenton,</line>
            <line>Heaven give you many, many merry days!</line>
            <line>Good husband, let us every one go home,</line>
            <line>And laugh this sport o'er by a country fire;</line>
            <line>Sir John and all.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>Let it be so. Sir John,</line>
            <line>To Master Brook you yet shall hold your word</line>
            <line>For he tonight shall lie with Mistress Ford.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>