<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:shakespear:dtd:act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-3">
   <title>ACT III</title>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  A field near Frogmore.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter SIR HUGH EVANS and SIMPLE</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR HUGH EVANS</speaker>
            <line>I pray you now, good master Slender's serving-man,</line>
            <line>and friend Simple by your name, which way have you</line>
            <line>looked for Master Caius, that calls himself doctor of physic?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIMPLE</speaker>
            <line>Marry, sir, the pittie-ward, the park-ward, every</line>
            <line>way; old Windsor way, and every way but the town</line>
            <line>way.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR HUGH EVANS</speaker>
            <line>I most fehemently desire you you will also look that</line>
            <line>way.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIMPLE</speaker>
            <line>I will, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR HUGH EVANS</speaker>
            <line>'Pless my soul, how full of chollors I am, and</line>
            <line>trempling of mind! I shall be glad if he have</line>
            <line>deceived me. How melancholies I am! I will knog</line>
            <line>his urinals about his knave's costard when I have</line>
            <line>good opportunities for the ork. 'Pless my soul!</line>
            <stagedir>Sings</stagedir>
            <line>To shallow rivers, to whose falls</line>
            <line>Melodious birds sings madrigals;</line>
            <line>There will we make our peds of roses,</line>
            <line>And a thousand fragrant posies.</line>
            <line>To shallow--</line>
            <line>Mercy on me! I have a great dispositions to cry.</line>
            <stagedir>Sings</stagedir>
            <line>Melodious birds sing madrigals--</line>
            <line>When as I sat in Pabylon--</line>
            <line>And a thousand vagram posies.</line>
            <line>To shallow &amp;c.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter SIMPLE</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIMPLE</speaker>
            <line>Yonder he is coming, this way, Sir Hugh.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR HUGH EVANS</speaker>
            <line>He's welcome.</line>
            <stagedir>Sings</stagedir>
            <line>To shallow rivers, to whose falls-</line>
            <line>Heaven prosper the right! What weapons is he?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIMPLE</speaker>
            <line>No weapons, sir. There comes my master, Master</line>
            <line>Shallow, and another gentleman, from Frogmore, over</line>
            <line>the stile, this way.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR HUGH EVANS</speaker>
            <line>Pray you, give me my gown; or else keep it in your arms.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter PAGE, SHALLOW, and SLENDER</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>How now, master Parson! Good morrow, good Sir Hugh.</line>
            <line>Keep a gamester from the dice, and a good student</line>
            <line>from his book, and it is wonderful.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SLENDER</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  Ah, sweet Anne Page!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAGE</speaker>
            <line>'Save you, good Sir Hugh!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR HUGH EVANS</speaker>
            <line>'Pless you from his mercy sake, all of you!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>What, the sword and the word! do you study them</line>
            <line>both, master parson?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAGE</speaker>
            <line>And youthful still! in your doublet and hose this</line>
            <line>raw rheumatic day!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR HUGH EVANS</speaker>
            <line>There is reasons and causes for it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAGE</speaker>
            <line>We are come to you to do a good office, master parson.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR HUGH EVANS</speaker>
            <line>Fery well: what is it?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Yonder is a most reverend gentleman, who, belike</line>
            <line>having received wrong by some person, is at most</line>
            <line>odds with his own gravity and patience that ever you</line>
            <line>saw.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>I have lived fourscore years and upward; I never</line>
            <line>heard a man of his place, gravity and learning, so</line>
            <line>wide of his own respect.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR HUGH EVANS</speaker>
            <line>What is he?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAGE</speaker>
            <line>I think you know him; Master Doctor Caius, the</line>
            <line>renowned French physician.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR HUGH EVANS</speaker>
            <line>Got's will, and his passion of my heart! I had as</line>
            <line>lief you would tell me of a mess of porridge.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Why?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR HUGH EVANS</speaker>
            <line>He has no more knowledge in Hibocrates and Galen,</line>
            <line>--and he is a knave besides; a cowardly knave as you</line>
            <line>would desires to be acquainted withal.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAGE</speaker>
            <line>I warrant you, he's the man should fight with him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  O sweet Anne Page!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>It appears so by his weapons. Keep them asunder:</line>
            <line>here comes Doctor Caius.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter Host, DOCTOR CAIUS, and RUGBY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Nay, good master parson, keep in your weapon.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>So do you, good master doctor.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Host</speaker>
            <line>Disarm them, and let them question: let them keep</line>
            <line>their limbs whole and hack our English.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOCTOR CAIUS</speaker>
            <line>I pray you, let-a me speak a word with your ear.</line>
            <line>Vherefore vill you not meet-a me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR HUGH EVANS</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside to DOCTOR CAIUS</stagedir>  Pray you, use your patience:</line>
            <line>in good time.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOCTOR CAIUS</speaker>
            <line>By gar, you are de coward, de Jack dog, John ape.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR HUGH EVANS</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside to DOCTOR CAIUS</stagedir>  Pray you let us not be</line>
            <line>laughing-stocks to other men's humours; I desire you</line>
            <line>in friendship, and I will one way or other make you amends.</line>
            <stagedir>Aloud</stagedir>
            <line>I will knog your urinals about your knave's cockscomb</line>
            <line>for missing your meetings and appointments.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOCTOR CAIUS</speaker>
            <line>Diable! Jack Rugby,--mine host de Jarteer,--have I</line>
            <line>not stay for him to kill him? have I not, at de place</line>
            <line>I did appoint?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR HUGH EVANS</speaker>
            <line>As I am a Christians soul now, look you, this is the</line>
            <line>place appointed: I'll be judgement by mine host of</line>
            <line>the Garter.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Host</speaker>
            <line>Peace, I say, Gallia and Gaul, French and Welsh,</line>
            <line>soul-curer and body-curer!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOCTOR CAIUS</speaker>
            <line>Ay, dat is very good; excellent.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Host</speaker>
            <line>Peace, I say! hear mine host of the Garter. Am I</line>
            <line>politic? am I subtle? am I a Machiavel? Shall I</line>
            <line>lose my doctor? no; he gives me the potions and the</line>
            <line>motions. Shall I lose my parson, my priest, my Sir</line>
            <line>Hugh? no; he gives me the proverbs and the</line>
            <line>no-verbs. Give me thy hand, terrestrial; so. Give me</line>
            <line>thy hand, celestial; so. Boys of art, I have</line>
            <line>deceived you both; I have directed you to wrong</line>
            <line>places: your hearts are mighty, your skins are</line>
            <line>whole, and let burnt sack be the issue. Come, lay</line>
            <line>their swords to pawn. Follow me, lads of peace;</line>
            <line>follow, follow, follow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>Trust me, a mad host. Follow, gentlemen, follow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SLENDER</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  O sweet Anne Page!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt SHALLOW, SLENDER, PAGE, and Host</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOCTOR CAIUS</speaker>
            <line>Ha, do I perceive dat? have you make-a de sot of</line>
            <line>us, ha, ha?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR HUGH EVANS</speaker>
            <line>This is well; he has made us his vlouting-stog. I</line>
            <line>desire you that we may be friends; and let us knog</line>
            <line>our prains together to be revenge on this same</line>
            <line>scall, scurvy cogging companion, the host of the Garter.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOCTOR CAIUS</speaker>
            <line>By gar, with all my heart. He promise to bring me</line>
            <line>where is Anne Page; by gar, he deceive me too.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR HUGH EVANS</speaker>
            <line>Well, I will smite his noddles. Pray you, follow.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  A street.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter MISTRESS PAGE and ROBIN</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Nay, keep your way, little gallant; you were wont to</line>
            <line>be a follower, but now you are a leader. Whether</line>
            <line>had you rather lead mine eyes, or eye your master's heels?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROBIN</speaker>
            <line>I had rather, forsooth, go before you like a man</line>
            <line>than follow him like a dwarf.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>O, you are a flattering boy: now I see you'll be a courtier.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter FORD</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>Well met, Mistress Page. Whither go you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Truly, sir, to see your wife. Is she at home?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>Ay; and as idle as she may hang together, for want</line>
            <line>of company. I think, if your husbands were dead,</line>
            <line>you two would marry.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Be sure of that,--two other husbands.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>Where had you this pretty weather-cock?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>I cannot tell what the dickens his name is my</line>
            <line>husband had him of. What do you call your knight's</line>
            <line>name, sirrah?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROBIN</speaker>
            <line>Sir John Falstaff.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>Sir John Falstaff!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>He, he; I can never hit on's name. There is such a</line>
            <line>league between my good man and he! Is your wife at</line>
            <line>home indeed?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>Indeed she is.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>By your leave, sir: I am sick till I see her.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt MISTRESS PAGE and ROBIN</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>Has Page any brains? hath he any eyes? hath he any</line>
            <line>thinking? Sure, they sleep; he hath no use of them.</line>
            <line>Why, this boy will carry a letter twenty mile, as</line>
            <line>easy as a cannon will shoot point-blank twelve</line>
            <line>score. He pieces out his wife's inclination; he</line>
            <line>gives her folly motion and advantage: and now she's</line>
            <line>going to my wife, and Falstaff's boy with her. A</line>
            <line>man may hear this shower sing in the wind. And</line>
            <line>Falstaff's boy with her! Good plots, they are laid;</line>
            <line>and our revolted wives share damnation together.</line>
            <line>Well; I will take him, then torture my wife, pluck</line>
            <line>the borrowed veil of modesty from the so seeming</line>
            <line>Mistress Page, divulge Page himself for a secure and</line>
            <line>wilful Actaeon; and to these violent proceedings all</line>
            <line>my neighbours shall cry aim.</line>
            <stagedir>Clock heard</stagedir>
            <line>The clock gives me my cue, and my assurance bids me</line>
            <line>search: there I shall find Falstaff: I shall be</line>
            <line>rather praised for this than mocked; for it is as</line>
            <line>positive as the earth is firm that Falstaff is</line>
            <line>there: I will go.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter PAGE, SHALLOW, SLENDER, Host,
SIR HUGH EVANS, DOCTOR CAIUS, and RUGBY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <speaker>PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Well met, Master Ford.</line>
            <line>&amp;c.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>Trust me, a good knot: I have good cheer at home;</line>
            <line>and I pray you all go with me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>I must excuse myself, Master Ford.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SLENDER</speaker>
            <line>And so must I, sir: we have appointed to dine with</line>
            <line>Mistress Anne, and I would not break with her for</line>
            <line>more money than I'll speak of.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>We have lingered about a match between Anne Page and</line>
            <line>my cousin Slender, and this day we shall have our answer.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SLENDER</speaker>
            <line>I hope I have your good will, father Page.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAGE</speaker>
            <line>You have, Master Slender; I stand wholly for you:</line>
            <line>but my wife, master doctor, is for you altogether.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOCTOR CAIUS</speaker>
            <line>Ay, be-gar; and de maid is love-a me: my nursh-a</line>
            <line>Quickly tell me so mush.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Host</speaker>
            <line>What say you to young Master Fenton? he capers, he</line>
            <line>dances, he has eyes of youth, he writes verses, he</line>
            <line>speaks holiday, he smells April and May: he will</line>
            <line>carry't, he will carry't; 'tis in his buttons; he</line>
            <line>will carry't.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Not by my consent, I promise you. The gentleman is</line>
            <line>of no having: he kept company with the wild prince</line>
            <line>and Poins; he is of too high a region; he knows too</line>
            <line>much. No, he shall not knit a knot in his fortunes</line>
            <line>with the finger of my substance: if he take her,</line>
            <line>let him take her simply; the wealth I have waits on</line>
            <line>my consent, and my consent goes not that way.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>I beseech you heartily, some of you go home with me</line>
            <line>to dinner: besides your cheer, you shall have</line>
            <line>sport; I will show you a monster. Master doctor,</line>
            <line>you shall go; so shall you, Master Page; and you, Sir Hugh.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>Well, fare you well: we shall have the freer wooing</line>
            <line>at Master Page's.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt SHALLOW, and SLENDER</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOCTOR CAIUS</speaker>
            <line>Go home, John Rugby; I come anon.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit RUGBY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Host</speaker>
            <line>Farewell, my hearts: I will to my honest knight</line>
            <line>Falstaff, and drink canary with him.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  I think I shall drink in pipe wine first</line>
            <line>with him; I'll make him dance. Will you go, gentles?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>All</speaker>
            <line>Have with you to see this monster.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  A room in FORD'S house.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter MISTRESS FORD and MISTRESS PAGE</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS FORD</speaker>
            <line>What, John! What, Robert!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Quickly, quickly! is the buck-basket--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS FORD</speaker>
            <line>I warrant. What, Robin, I say!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter Servants with a basket</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Come, come, come.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS FORD</speaker>
            <line>Here, set it down.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Give your men the charge; we must be brief.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS FORD</speaker>
            <line>Marry, as I told you before, John and Robert, be</line>
            <line>ready here hard by in the brew-house: and when I</line>
            <line>suddenly call you, come forth, and without any pause</line>
            <line>or staggering take this basket on your shoulders:</line>
            <line>that done, trudge with it in all haste, and carry</line>
            <line>it among the whitsters in Datchet-mead, and there</line>
            <line>empty it in the muddy ditch close by the Thames side.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>You will do it?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS FORD</speaker>
            <line>I ha' told them over and over; they lack no</line>
            <line>direction. Be gone, and come when you are called.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt Servants</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Here comes little Robin.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter ROBIN</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS FORD</speaker>
            <line>How now, my eyas-musket! what news with you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROBIN</speaker>
            <line>My master, Sir John, is come in at your back-door,</line>
            <line>Mistress Ford, and requests your company.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>You little Jack-a-Lent, have you been true to us?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROBIN</speaker>
            <line>Ay, I'll be sworn. My master knows not of your</line>
            <line>being here and hath threatened to put me into</line>
            <line>everlasting liberty if I tell you of it; for he</line>
            <line>swears he'll turn me away.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Thou'rt a good boy: this secrecy of thine shall be</line>
            <line>a tailor to thee and shall make thee a new doublet</line>
            <line>and hose. I'll go hide me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS FORD</speaker>
            <line>Do so. Go tell thy master I am alone.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit ROBIN</stagedir>
            <line>Mistress Page, remember you your cue.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>I warrant thee; if I do not act it, hiss me.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS FORD</speaker>
            <line>Go to, then: we'll use this unwholesome humidity,</line>
            <line>this gross watery pumpion; we'll teach him to know</line>
            <line>turtles from jays.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter FALSTAFF</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Have I caught thee, my heavenly jewel? Why, now let</line>
            <line>me die, for I have lived long enough: this is the</line>
            <line>period of my ambition: O this blessed hour!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS FORD</speaker>
            <line>O sweet Sir John!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Mistress Ford, I cannot cog, I cannot prate,</line>
            <line>Mistress Ford. Now shall I sin in my wish: I would</line>
            <line>thy husband were dead: I'll speak it before the</line>
            <line>best lord; I would make thee my lady.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS FORD</speaker>
            <line>I your lady, Sir John! alas, I should be a pitiful lady!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Let the court of France show me such another. I see</line>
            <line>how thine eye would emulate the diamond: thou hast</line>
            <line>the right arched beauty of the brow that becomes the</line>
            <line>ship-tire, the tire-valiant, or any tire of</line>
            <line>Venetian admittance.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS FORD</speaker>
            <line>A plain kerchief, Sir John: my brows become nothing</line>
            <line>else; nor that well neither.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>By the Lord, thou art a traitor to say so: thou</line>
            <line>wouldst make an absolute courtier; and the firm</line>
            <line>fixture of thy foot would give an excellent motion</line>
            <line>to thy gait in a semi-circled farthingale. I see</line>
            <line>what thou wert, if Fortune thy foe were not, Nature</line>
            <line>thy friend. Come, thou canst not hide it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS FORD</speaker>
            <line>Believe me, there is no such thing in me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>What made me love thee? let that persuade thee</line>
            <line>there's something extraordinary in thee. Come, I</line>
            <line>cannot cog and say thou art this and that, like a</line>
            <line>many of these lisping hawthorn-buds, that come like</line>
            <line>women in men's apparel, and smell like Bucklersbury</line>
            <line>in simple time; I cannot: but I love thee; none</line>
            <line>but thee; and thou deservest it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS FORD</speaker>
            <line>Do not betray me, sir. I fear you love Mistress Page.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Thou mightst as well say I love to walk by the</line>
            <line>Counter-gate, which is as hateful to me as the reek</line>
            <line>of a lime-kiln.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS FORD</speaker>
            <line>Well, heaven knows how I love you; and you shall one</line>
            <line>day find it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Keep in that mind; I'll deserve it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS FORD</speaker>
            <line>Nay, I must tell you, so you do; or else I could not</line>
            <line>be in that mind.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROBIN</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Within</stagedir>  Mistress Ford, Mistress Ford! here's</line>
            <line>Mistress Page at the door, sweating and blowing and</line>
            <line>looking wildly, and would needs speak with you presently.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>She shall not see me: I will ensconce me behind the arras.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS FORD</speaker>
            <line>Pray you, do so: she's a very tattling woman.</line>
            <stagedir>FALSTAFF hides himself</stagedir>
            <stagedir>Re-enter MISTRESS PAGE and ROBIN</stagedir>
            <line>What's the matter? how now!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>O Mistress Ford, what have you done? You're shamed,</line>
            <line>you're overthrown, you're undone for ever!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS FORD</speaker>
            <line>What's the matter, good Mistress Page?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>O well-a-day, Mistress Ford! having an honest man</line>
            <line>to your husband, to give him such cause of suspicion!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS FORD</speaker>
            <line>What cause of suspicion?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>What cause of suspicion! Out pon you! how am I</line>
            <line>mistook in you!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS FORD</speaker>
            <line>Why, alas, what's the matter?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Your husband's coming hither, woman, with all the</line>
            <line>officers in Windsor, to search for a gentleman that</line>
            <line>he says is here now in the house by your consent, to</line>
            <line>take an ill advantage of his assence: you are undone.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS FORD</speaker>
            <line>'Tis not so, I hope.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Pray heaven it be not so, that you have such a man</line>
            <line>here! but 'tis most certain your husband's coming,</line>
            <line>with half Windsor at his heels, to search for such a</line>
            <line>one. I come before to tell you. If you know</line>
            <line>yourself clear, why, I am glad of it; but if you</line>
            <line>have a friend here convey, convey him out. Be not</line>
            <line>amazed; call all your senses to you; defend your</line>
            <line>reputation, or bid farewell to your good life for ever.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS FORD</speaker>
            <line>What shall I do? There is a gentleman my dear</line>
            <line>friend; and I fear not mine own shame so much as his</line>
            <line>peril: I had rather than a thousand pound he were</line>
            <line>out of the house.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>For shame! never stand 'you had rather' and 'you</line>
            <line>had rather:' your husband's here at hand, bethink</line>
            <line>you of some conveyance: in the house you cannot</line>
            <line>hide him. O, how have you deceived me! Look, here</line>
            <line>is a basket: if he be of any reasonable stature, he</line>
            <line>may creep in here; and throw foul linen upon him, as</line>
            <line>if it were going to bucking: or--it is whiting-time</line>
            <line>--send him by your two men to Datchet-mead.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS FORD</speaker>
            <line>He's too big to go in there. What shall I do?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Coming forward</stagedir>  Let me see't, let me see't, O, let</line>
            <line>me see't! I'll in, I'll in. Follow your friend's</line>
            <line>counsel. I'll in.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>What, Sir John Falstaff! Are these your letters, knight?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>I love thee. Help me away. Let me creep in here.</line>
            <line>I'll never--</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Gets into the basket; they cover him with foul linen</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Help to cover your master, boy. Call your men,</line>
            <line>Mistress Ford. You dissembling knight!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS FORD</speaker>
            <line>What, John! Robert! John!</line>
            <stagedir>Exit ROBIN</stagedir>
            <stagedir>Re-enter Servants</stagedir>
            <line>Go take up these clothes here quickly. Where's the</line>
            <line>cowl-staff? look, how you drumble! Carry them to</line>
            <line>the laundress in Datchet-meat; quickly, come.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter FORD, PAGE, DOCTOR CAIUS, and SIR HUGH EVANS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>Pray you, come near: if I suspect without cause,</line>
            <line>why then make sport at me; then let me be your jest;</line>
            <line>I deserve it. How now! whither bear you this?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>To the laundress, forsooth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS FORD</speaker>
            <line>Why, what have you to do whither they bear it? You</line>
            <line>were best meddle with buck-washing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>Buck! I would I could wash myself of the buck!</line>
            <line>Buck, buck, buck! Ay, buck; I warrant you, buck;</line>
            <line>and of the season too, it shall appear.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt Servants with the basket</stagedir>
            <line>Gentlemen, I have dreamed to-night; I'll tell you my</line>
            <line>dream. Here, here, here be my keys: ascend my</line>
            <line>chambers; search, seek, find out: I'll warrant</line>
            <line>we'll unkennel the fox. Let me stop this way first.</line>
            <stagedir>Locking the door</stagedir>
            <line>So, now uncape.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Good Master Ford, be contented: you wrong yourself too much.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>True, Master Page. Up, gentlemen: you shall see</line>
            <line>sport anon: follow me, gentlemen.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR HUGH EVANS</speaker>
            <line>This is fery fantastical humours and jealousies.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOCTOR CAIUS</speaker>
            <line>By gar, 'tis no the fashion of France; it is not</line>
            <line>jealous in France.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Nay, follow him, gentlemen; see the issue of his search.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt PAGE, DOCTOR CAIUS, and SIR HUGH EVANS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Is there not a double excellency in this?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS FORD</speaker>
            <line>I know not which pleases me better, that my husband</line>
            <line>is deceived, or Sir John.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>What a taking was he in when your husband asked who</line>
            <line>was in the basket!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS FORD</speaker>
            <line>I am half afraid he will have need of washing; so</line>
            <line>throwing him into the water will do him a benefit.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Hang him, dishonest rascal! I would all of the same</line>
            <line>strain were in the same distress.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS FORD</speaker>
            <line>I think my husband hath some special suspicion of</line>
            <line>Falstaff's being here; for I never saw him so gross</line>
            <line>in his jealousy till now.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>I will lay a plot to try that; and we will yet have</line>
            <line>more tricks with Falstaff: his dissolute disease will</line>
            <line>scarce obey this medicine.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS FORD</speaker>
            <line>Shall we send that foolish carrion, Mistress</line>
            <line>Quickly, to him, and excuse his throwing into the</line>
            <line>water; and give him another hope, to betray him to</line>
            <line>another punishment?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>We will do it: let him be sent for to-morrow,</line>
            <line>eight o'clock, to have amends.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter FORD, PAGE, DOCTOR CAIUS, and
SIR HUGH EVANS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>I cannot find him: may be the knave bragged of that</line>
            <line>he could not compass.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside to MISTRESS FORD</stagedir>  Heard you that?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS FORD</speaker>
            <line>You use me well, Master Ford, do you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>Ay, I do so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS FORD</speaker>
            <line>Heaven make you better than your thoughts!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>Amen!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>You do yourself mighty wrong, Master Ford.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>Ay, ay; I must bear it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR HUGH EVANS</speaker>
            <line>If there be any pody in the house, and in the</line>
            <line>chambers, and in the coffers, and in the presses,</line>
            <line>heaven forgive my sins at the day of judgment!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOCTOR CAIUS</speaker>
            <line>By gar, nor I too: there is no bodies.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Fie, fie, Master Ford! are you not ashamed? What</line>
            <line>spirit, what devil suggests this imagination? I</line>
            <line>would not ha' your distemper in this kind for the</line>
            <line>wealth of Windsor Castle.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>'Tis my fault, Master Page: I suffer for it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR HUGH EVANS</speaker>
            <line>You suffer for a pad conscience: your wife is as</line>
            <line>honest a 'omans as I will desires among five</line>
            <line>thousand, and five hundred too.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOCTOR CAIUS</speaker>
            <line>By gar, I see 'tis an honest woman.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>Well, I promised you a dinner. Come, come, walk in</line>
            <line>the Park: I pray you, pardon me; I will hereafter</line>
            <line>make known to you why I have done this. Come,</line>
            <line>wife; come, Mistress Page. I pray you, pardon me;</line>
            <line>pray heartily, pardon me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Let's go in, gentlemen; but, trust me, we'll mock</line>
            <line>him. I do invite you to-morrow morning to my house</line>
            <line>to breakfast: after, we'll a-birding together; I</line>
            <line>have a fine hawk for the bush. Shall it be so?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>Any thing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR HUGH EVANS</speaker>
            <line>If there is one, I shall make two in the company.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOCTOR CAIUS</speaker>
            <line>If dere be one or two, I shall make-a the turd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>Pray you, go, Master Page.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR HUGH EVANS</speaker>
            <line>I pray you now, remembrance tomorrow on the lousy</line>
            <line>knave, mine host.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOCTOR CAIUS</speaker>
            <line>Dat is good; by gar, with all my heart!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR HUGH EVANS</speaker>
            <line>A lousy knave, to have his gibes and his mockeries!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-4">
      <title>SCENE IV.  A room in PAGE'S house.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter FENTON and ANNE PAGE</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FENTON</speaker>
            <line>I see I cannot get thy father's love;</line>
            <line>Therefore no more turn me to him, sweet Nan.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANNE PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Alas, how then?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FENTON</speaker>
            <line>Why, thou must be thyself.</line>
            <line>He doth object I am too great of birth--,</line>
            <line>And that, my state being gall'd with my expense,</line>
            <line>I seek to heal it only by his wealth:</line>
            <line>Besides these, other bars he lays before me,</line>
            <line>My riots past, my wild societies;</line>
            <line>And tells me 'tis a thing impossible</line>
            <line>I should love thee but as a property.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANNE PAGE</speaker>
            <line>May be he tells you true.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FENTON</speaker>
            <line>No, heaven so speed me in my time to come!</line>
            <line>Albeit I will confess thy father's wealth</line>
            <line>Was the first motive that I woo'd thee, Anne:</line>
            <line>Yet, wooing thee, I found thee of more value</line>
            <line>Than stamps in gold or sums in sealed bags;</line>
            <line>And 'tis the very riches of thyself</line>
            <line>That now I aim at.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANNE PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Gentle Master Fenton,</line>
            <line>Yet seek my father's love; still seek it, sir:</line>
            <line>If opportunity and humblest suit</line>
            <line>Cannot attain it, why, then,--hark you hither!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>They converse apart</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Enter SHALLOW, SLENDER, and MISTRESS QUICKLY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>Break their talk, Mistress Quickly: my kinsman shall</line>
            <line>speak for himself.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SLENDER</speaker>
            <line>I'll make a shaft or a bolt on't: 'slid, 'tis but</line>
            <line>venturing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>Be not dismayed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SLENDER</speaker>
            <line>No, she shall not dismay me: I care not for that,</line>
            <line>but that I am afeard.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS QUICKLY</speaker>
            <line>Hark ye; Master Slender would speak a word with you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANNE PAGE</speaker>
            <line>I come to him.</line>
            <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>
            <line>This is my father's choice.</line>
            <line>O, what a world of vile ill-favor'd faults</line>
            <line>Looks handsome in three hundred pounds a-year!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS QUICKLY</speaker>
            <line>And how does good Master Fenton? Pray you, a word with you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>She's coming; to her, coz. O boy, thou hadst a father!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SLENDER</speaker>
            <line>I had a father, Mistress Anne; my uncle can tell you</line>
            <line>good jests of him. Pray you, uncle, tell Mistress</line>
            <line>Anne the jest, how my father stole two geese out of</line>
            <line>a pen, good uncle.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>Mistress Anne, my cousin loves you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SLENDER</speaker>
            <line>Ay, that I do; as well as I love any woman in</line>
            <line>Gloucestershire.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>He will maintain you like a gentlewoman.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SLENDER</speaker>
            <line>Ay, that I will, come cut and long-tail, under the</line>
            <line>degree of a squire.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>He will make you a hundred and fifty pounds jointure.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANNE PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Good Master Shallow, let him woo for himself.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>Marry, I thank you for it; I thank you for that good</line>
            <line>comfort. She calls you, coz: I'll leave you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANNE PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Now, Master Slender,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SLENDER</speaker>
            <line>Now, good Mistress Anne,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANNE PAGE</speaker>
            <line>What is your will?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SLENDER</speaker>
            <line>My will! 'od's heartlings, that's a pretty jest</line>
            <line>indeed! I ne'er made my will yet, I thank heaven; I</line>
            <line>am not such a sickly creature, I give heaven praise.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANNE PAGE</speaker>
            <line>I mean, Master Slender, what would you with me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SLENDER</speaker>
            <line>Truly, for mine own part, I would little or nothing</line>
            <line>with you. Your father and my uncle hath made</line>
            <line>motions: if it be my luck, so; if not, happy man be</line>
            <line>his dole! They can tell you how things go better</line>
            <line>than I can: you may ask your father; here he comes.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter PAGE and MISTRESS PAGE</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Now, Master Slender: love him, daughter Anne.</line>
            <line>Why, how now! what does Master Fenton here?</line>
            <line>You wrong me, sir, thus still to haunt my house:</line>
            <line>I told you, sir, my daughter is disposed of.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FENTON</speaker>
            <line>Nay, Master Page, be not impatient.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Good Master Fenton, come not to my child.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAGE</speaker>
            <line>She is no match for you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FENTON</speaker>
            <line>Sir, will you hear me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAGE</speaker>
            <line>No, good Master Fenton.</line>
            <line>Come, Master Shallow; come, son Slender, in.</line>
            <line>Knowing my mind, you wrong me, Master Fenton.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt PAGE, SHALLOW, and SLENDER</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS QUICKLY</speaker>
            <line>Speak to Mistress Page.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FENTON</speaker>
            <line>Good Mistress Page, for that I love your daughter</line>
            <line>In such a righteous fashion as I do,</line>
            <line>Perforce, against all cheques, rebukes and manners,</line>
            <line>I must advance the colours of my love</line>
            <line>And not retire: let me have your good will.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANNE PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Good mother, do not marry me to yond fool.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>I mean it not; I seek you a better husband.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS QUICKLY</speaker>
            <line>That's my master, master doctor.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANNE PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Alas, I had rather be set quick i' the earth</line>
            <line>And bowl'd to death with turnips!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Come, trouble not yourself. Good Master Fenton,</line>
            <line>I will not be your friend nor enemy:</line>
            <line>My daughter will I question how she loves you,</line>
            <line>And as I find her, so am I affected.</line>
            <line>Till then farewell, sir: she must needs go in;</line>
            <line>Her father will be angry.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FENTON</speaker>
            <line>Farewell, gentle mistress: farewell, Nan.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt MISTRESS PAGE and ANNE PAGE</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS QUICKLY</speaker>
            <line>This is my doing, now: 'Nay,' said I, 'will you cast</line>
            <line>away your child on a fool, and a physician? Look on</line>
            <line>Master Fenton:' this is my doing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FENTON</speaker>
            <line>I thank thee; and I pray thee, once to-night</line>
            <line>Give my sweet Nan this ring: there's for thy pains.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS QUICKLY</speaker>
            <line>Now heaven send thee good fortune!</line>
            <stagedir>Exit FENTON</stagedir>
            <line>A kind heart he hath: a woman would run through</line>
            <line>fire and water for such a kind heart. But yet I</line>
            <line>would my master had Mistress Anne; or I would</line>
            <line>Master Slender had her; or, in sooth, I would Master</line>
            <line>Fenton had her; I will do what I can for them all</line>
            <line>three; for so I have promised, and I'll be as good</line>
            <line>as my word; but speciously for Master Fenton. Well,</line>
            <line>I must of another errand to Sir John Falstaff from</line>
            <line>my two mistresses: what a beast am I to slack it!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-5">
      <title>SCENE V.  A room in the Garter Inn.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter FALSTAFF and BARDOLPH</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Bardolph, I say,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BARDOLPH</speaker>
            <line>Here, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Go fetch me a quart of sack; put a toast in't.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit BARDOLPH</stagedir>
            <line>Have I lived to be carried in a basket, like a</line>
            <line>barrow of butcher's offal, and to be thrown in the</line>
            <line>Thames? Well, if I be served such another trick,</line>
            <line>I'll have my brains ta'en out and buttered, and give</line>
            <line>them to a dog for a new-year's gift. The rogues</line>
            <line>slighted me into the river with as little remorse as</line>
            <line>they would have drowned a blind bitch's puppies,</line>
            <line>fifteen i' the litter: and you may know by my size</line>
            <line>that I have a kind of alacrity in sinking; if the</line>
            <line>bottom were as deep as hell, I should down. I had</line>
            <line>been drowned, but that the shore was shelvy and</line>
            <line>shallow,--a death that I abhor; for the water swells</line>
            <line>a man; and what a thing should I have been when I</line>
            <line>had been swelled! I should have been a mountain of mummy.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter BARDOLPH with sack</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BARDOLPH</speaker>
            <line>Here's Mistress Quickly, sir, to speak with you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Let me pour in some sack to the Thames water; for my</line>
            <line>belly's as cold as if I had swallowed snowballs for</line>
            <line>pills to cool the reins. Call her in.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BARDOLPH</speaker>
            <line>Come in, woman!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter MISTRESS QUICKLY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS QUICKLY</speaker>
            <line>By your leave; I cry you mercy: give your worship</line>
            <line>good morrow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Take away these chalices. Go brew me a pottle of</line>
            <line>sack finely.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BARDOLPH</speaker>
            <line>With eggs, sir?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Simple of itself; I'll no pullet-sperm in my brewage.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit BARDOLPH</stagedir>
            <line>How now!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS QUICKLY</speaker>
            <line>Marry, sir, I come to your worship from Mistress Ford.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Mistress Ford! I have had ford enough; I was thrown</line>
            <line>into the ford; I have my belly full of ford.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS QUICKLY</speaker>
            <line>Alas the day! good heart, that was not her fault:</line>
            <line>she does so take on with her men; they mistook their erection.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>So did I mine, to build upon a foolish woman's promise.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS QUICKLY</speaker>
            <line>Well, she laments, sir, for it, that it would yearn</line>
            <line>your heart to see it. Her husband goes this morning</line>
            <line>a-birding; she desires you once more to come to her</line>
            <line>between eight and nine: I must carry her word</line>
            <line>quickly: she'll make you amends, I warrant you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Well, I will visit her: tell her so; and bid her</line>
            <line>think what a man is: let her consider his frailty,</line>
            <line>and then judge of my merit.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS QUICKLY</speaker>
            <line>I will tell her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Do so. Between nine and ten, sayest thou?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS QUICKLY</speaker>
            <line>Eight and nine, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Well, be gone: I will not miss her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS QUICKLY</speaker>
            <line>Peace be with you, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>I marvel I hear not of Master Brook; he sent me word</line>
            <line>to stay within: I like his money well. O, here he comes.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter FORD</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>Bless you, sir!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Now, master Brook, you come to know what hath passed</line>
            <line>between me and Ford's wife?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>That, indeed, Sir John, is my business.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Master Brook, I will not lie to you: I was at her</line>
            <line>house the hour she appointed me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>And sped you, sir?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Very ill-favoredly, Master Brook.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>How so, sir? Did she change her determination?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>No, Master Brook; but the peaking Cornuto her</line>
            <line>husband, Master Brook, dwelling in a continual</line>
            <line>'larum of jealousy, comes me in the instant of our</line>
            <line>encounter, after we had embraced, kissed, protested,</line>
            <line>and, as it were, spoke the prologue of our comedy;</line>
            <line>and at his heels a rabble of his companions, thither</line>
            <line>provoked and instigated by his distemper, and,</line>
            <line>forsooth, to search his house for his wife's love.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>What, while you were there?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>While I was there.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>And did he search for you, and could not find you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>You shall hear. As good luck would have it, comes</line>
            <line>in one Mistress Page; gives intelligence of Ford's</line>
            <line>approach; and, in her invention and Ford's wife's</line>
            <line>distraction, they conveyed me into a buck-basket.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>A buck-basket!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>By the Lord, a buck-basket! rammed me in with foul</line>
            <line>shirts and smocks, socks, foul stockings, greasy</line>
            <line>napkins; that, Master Brook, there was the rankest</line>
            <line>compound of villanous smell that ever offended nostril.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>And how long lay you there?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Nay, you shall hear, Master Brook, what I have</line>
            <line>suffered to bring this woman to evil for your good.</line>
            <line>Being thus crammed in the basket, a couple of Ford's</line>
            <line>knaves, his hinds, were called forth by their</line>
            <line>mistress to carry me in the name of foul clothes to</line>
            <line>Datchet-lane: they took me on their shoulders; met</line>
            <line>the jealous knave their master in the door, who</line>
            <line>asked them once or twice what they had in their</line>
            <line>basket: I quaked for fear, lest the lunatic knave</line>
            <line>would have searched it; but fate, ordaining he</line>
            <line>should be a cuckold, held his hand. Well: on went he</line>
            <line>for a search, and away went I for foul clothes. But</line>
            <line>mark the sequel, Master Brook: I suffered the pangs</line>
            <line>of three several deaths; first, an intolerable</line>
            <line>fright, to be detected with a jealous rotten</line>
            <line>bell-wether; next, to be compassed, like a good</line>
            <line>bilbo, in the circumference of a peck, hilt to</line>
            <line>point, heel to head; and then, to be stopped in,</line>
            <line>like a strong distillation, with stinking clothes</line>
            <line>that fretted in their own grease: think of that,--a</line>
            <line>man of my kidney,--think of that,--that am as subject</line>
            <line>to heat as butter; a man of continual dissolution</line>
            <line>and thaw: it was a miracle to scape suffocation.</line>
            <line>And in the height of this bath, when I was more than</line>
            <line>half stewed in grease, like a Dutch dish, to be</line>
            <line>thrown into the Thames, and cooled, glowing hot,</line>
            <line>in that surge, like a horse-shoe; think of</line>
            <line>that,--hissing hot,--think of that, Master Brook.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>In good sadness, I am sorry that for my sake you</line>
            <line>have sufferd all this. My suit then is desperate;</line>
            <line>you'll undertake her no more?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Master Brook, I will be thrown into Etna, as I have</line>
            <line>been into Thames, ere I will leave her thus. Her</line>
            <line>husband is this morning gone a-birding: I have</line>
            <line>received from her another embassy of meeting; 'twixt</line>
            <line>eight and nine is the hour, Master Brook.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>'Tis past eight already, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Is it? I will then address me to my appointment.</line>
            <line>Come to me at your convenient leisure, and you shall</line>
            <line>know how I speed; and the conclusion shall be</line>
            <line>crowned with your enjoying her. Adieu. You shall</line>
            <line>have her, Master Brook; Master Brook, you shall</line>
            <line>cuckold Ford.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>Hum! ha! is this a vision? is this a dream? do I</line>
            <line>sleep? Master Ford awake! awake, Master Ford!</line>
            <line>there's a hole made in your best coat, Master Ford.</line>
            <line>This 'tis to be married! this 'tis to have linen</line>
            <line>and buck-baskets! Well, I will proclaim myself</line>
            <line>what I am: I will now take the lecher; he is at my</line>
            <line>house; he cannot 'scape me; 'tis impossible he</line>
            <line>should; he cannot creep into a halfpenny purse,</line>
            <line>nor into a pepper-box: but, lest the devil that</line>
            <line>guides him should aid him, I will search</line>
            <line>impossible places. Though what I am I cannot avoid,</line>
            <line>yet to be what I would not shall not make me tame:</line>
            <line>if I have horns to make one mad, let the proverb go</line>
            <line>with me: I'll be horn-mad.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>