<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net/doctypes/dita/shakespear/dtd/act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-2">
   <title>ACT II</title>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  Before PAGE'S house.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter MISTRESS PAGE, with a letter</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>What, have I scaped love-letters in the holiday-</line>
            <line>time of my beauty, and am I now a subject for them?</line>
            <line>Let me see.</line>
            <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>
            <line>'Ask me no reason why I love you; for though</line>
            <line>Love use Reason for his physician, he admits him</line>
            <line>not for his counsellor. You are not young, no more</line>
            <line>am I; go to then, there's sympathy: you are merry,</line>
            <line>so am I; ha, ha! then there's more sympathy: you</line>
            <line>love sack, and so do I; would you desire better</line>
            <line>sympathy? Let it suffice thee, Mistress Page,--at</line>
            <line>the least, if the love of soldier can suffice,--</line>
            <line>that I love thee. I will not say, pity me; 'tis</line>
            <line>not a soldier-like phrase: but I say, love me. By me,</line>
            <line>Thine own true knight,</line>
            <line>By day or night,</line>
            <line>Or any kind of light,</line>
            <line>With all his might</line>
            <line>For thee to fight,    JOHN FALSTAFF'</line>
            <line>What a Herod of Jewry is this! O wicked</line>
            <line>world! One that is well-nigh worn to pieces with</line>
            <line>age to show himself a young gallant! What an</line>
            <line>unweighed behavior hath this Flemish drunkard</line>
            <line>picked--with the devil's name!--out of my</line>
            <line>conversation, that he dares in this manner assay me?</line>
            <line>Why, he hath not been thrice in my company! What</line>
            <line>should I say to him? I was then frugal of my</line>
            <line>mirth: Heaven forgive me! Why, I'll exhibit a bill</line>
            <line>in the parliament for the putting down of men. How</line>
            <line>shall I be revenged on him? for revenged I will be,</line>
            <line>as sure as his guts are made of puddings.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter MISTRESS FORD</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS FORD</speaker>
            <line>Mistress Page! trust me, I was going to your house.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>And, trust me, I was coming to you. You look very</line>
            <line>ill.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS FORD</speaker>
            <line>Nay, I'll ne'er believe that; I have to show to the contrary.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Faith, but you do, in my mind.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS FORD</speaker>
            <line>Well, I do then; yet I say I could show you to the</line>
            <line>contrary. O Mistress Page, give me some counsel!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>What's the matter, woman?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS FORD</speaker>
            <line>O woman, if it were not for one trifling respect, I</line>
            <line>could come to such honour!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Hang the trifle, woman! take the honour. What is</line>
            <line>it? dispense with trifles; what is it?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS FORD</speaker>
            <line>If I would but go to hell for an eternal moment or so,</line>
            <line>I could be knighted.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>What? thou liest! Sir Alice Ford! These knights</line>
            <line>will hack; and so thou shouldst not alter the</line>
            <line>article of thy gentry.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS FORD</speaker>
            <line>We burn daylight: here, read, read; perceive how I</line>
            <line>might be knighted. I shall think the worse of fat</line>
            <line>men, as long as I have an eye to make difference of</line>
            <line>men's liking: and yet he would not swear; praised</line>
            <line>women's modesty; and gave such orderly and</line>
            <line>well-behaved reproof to all uncomeliness, that I</line>
            <line>would have sworn his disposition would have gone to</line>
            <line>the truth of his words; but they do no more adhere</line>
            <line>and keep place together than the Hundredth Psalm to</line>
            <line>the tune of 'Green Sleeves.' What tempest, I trow,</line>
            <line>threw this whale, with so many tuns of oil in his</line>
            <line>belly, ashore at Windsor? How shall I be revenged</line>
            <line>on him? I think the best way were to entertain him</line>
            <line>with hope, till the wicked fire of lust have melted</line>
            <line>him in his own grease. Did you ever hear the like?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Letter for letter, but that the name of Page and</line>
            <line>Ford differs! To thy great comfort in this mystery</line>
            <line>of ill opinions, here's the twin-brother of thy</line>
            <line>letter: but let thine inherit first; for, I</line>
            <line>protest, mine never shall. I warrant he hath a</line>
            <line>thousand of these letters, writ with blank space for</line>
            <line>different names--sure, more,--and these are of the</line>
            <line>second edition: he will print them, out of doubt;</line>
            <line>for he cares not what he puts into the press, when</line>
            <line>he would put us two. I had rather be a giantess,</line>
            <line>and lie under Mount Pelion. Well, I will find you</line>
            <line>twenty lascivious turtles ere one chaste man.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS FORD</speaker>
            <line>Why, this is the very same; the very hand, the very</line>
            <line>words. What doth he think of us?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Nay, I know not: it makes me almost ready to</line>
            <line>wrangle with mine own honesty. I'll entertain</line>
            <line>myself like one that I am not acquainted withal;</line>
            <line>for, sure, unless he know some strain in me, that I</line>
            <line>know not myself, he would never have boarded me in this fury.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS FORD</speaker>
            <line>'Boarding,' call you it? I'll be sure to keep him</line>
            <line>above deck.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>So will I if he come under my hatches, I'll never</line>
            <line>to sea again. Let's be revenged on him: let's</line>
            <line>appoint him a meeting; give him a show of comfort in</line>
            <line>his suit and lead him on with a fine-baited delay,</line>
            <line>till he hath pawned his horses to mine host of the Garter.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS FORD</speaker>
            <line>Nay, I will consent to act any villany against him,</line>
            <line>that may not sully the chariness of our honesty. O,</line>
            <line>that my husband saw this letter! it would give</line>
            <line>eternal food to his jealousy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Why, look where he comes; and my good man too: he's</line>
            <line>as far from jealousy as I am from giving him cause;</line>
            <line>and that I hope is an unmeasurable distance.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS FORD</speaker>
            <line>You are the happier woman.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Let's consult together against this greasy knight.</line>
            <line>Come hither.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>They retire</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Enter FORD with PISTOL, and PAGE with NYM</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>Well, I hope it be not so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>Hope is a curtal dog in some affairs:</line>
            <line>Sir John affects thy wife.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>Why, sir, my wife is not young.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>He wooes both high and low, both rich and poor,</line>
            <line>Both young and old, one with another, Ford;</line>
            <line>He loves the gallimaufry: Ford, perpend.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>Love my wife!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>With liver burning hot. Prevent, or go thou,</line>
            <line>Like Sir Actaeon he, with Ringwood at thy heels:</line>
            <line>O, odious is the name!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>What name, sir?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>The horn, I say. Farewell.</line>
            <line>Take heed, have open eye, for thieves do foot by night:</line>
            <line>Take heed, ere summer comes or cuckoo-birds do sing.</line>
            <line>Away, Sir Corporal Nym!</line>
            <line>Believe it, Page; he speaks sense.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  I will be patient; I will find out this.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NYM</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>To PAGE</stagedir>  And this is true; I like not the humour</line>
            <line>of lying. He hath wronged me in some humours: I</line>
            <line>should have borne the humoured letter to her; but I</line>
            <line>have a sword and it shall bite upon my necessity.</line>
            <line>He loves your wife; there's the short and the long.</line>
            <line>My name is Corporal Nym; I speak and I avouch; 'tis</line>
            <line>true: my name is Nym and Falstaff loves your wife.</line>
            <line>Adieu. I love not the humour of bread and cheese,</line>
            <line>and there's the humour of it. Adieu.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAGE</speaker>
            <line>'The humour of it,' quoth a'! here's a fellow</line>
            <line>frights English out of his wits.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>I will seek out Falstaff.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAGE</speaker>
            <line>I never heard such a drawling, affecting rogue.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>If I do find it: well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAGE</speaker>
            <line>I will not believe such a Cataian, though the priest</line>
            <line>o' the town commended him for a true man.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>'Twas a good sensible fellow: well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAGE</speaker>
            <line>How now, Meg!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>MISTRESS PAGE and MISTRESS FORD come forward</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Whither go you, George? Hark you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS FORD</speaker>
            <line>How now, sweet Frank! why art thou melancholy?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>I melancholy! I am not melancholy. Get you home, go.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS FORD</speaker>
            <line>Faith, thou hast some crotchets in thy head. Now,</line>
            <line>will you go, Mistress Page?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Have with you. You'll come to dinner, George.</line>
            <stagedir>Aside to MISTRESS FORD</stagedir>
            <line>Look who comes yonder: she shall be our messenger</line>
            <line>to this paltry knight.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS FORD</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside to MISTRESS PAGE</stagedir>  Trust me, I thought on her:</line>
            <line>she'll fit it.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter MISTRESS QUICKLY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>You are come to see my daughter Anne?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS QUICKLY</speaker>
            <line>Ay, forsooth; and, I pray, how does good Mistress Anne?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Go in with us and see: we have an hour's talk with</line>
            <line>you.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt MISTRESS PAGE, MISTRESS FORD, and MISTRESS QUICKLY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAGE</speaker>
            <line>How now, Master Ford!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>You heard what this knave told me, did you not?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Yes: and you heard what the other told me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>Do you think there is truth in them?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Hang 'em, slaves! I do not think the knight would</line>
            <line>offer it: but these that accuse him in his intent</line>
            <line>towards our wives are a yoke of his discarded men;</line>
            <line>very rogues, now they be out of service.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>Were they his men?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Marry, were they.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>I like it never the better for that. Does he lie at</line>
            <line>the Garter?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Ay, marry, does he. If he should intend this voyage</line>
            <line>towards my wife, I would turn her loose to him; and</line>
            <line>what he gets more of her than sharp words, let it</line>
            <line>lie on my head.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>I do not misdoubt my wife; but I would be loath to</line>
            <line>turn them together. A man may be too confident: I</line>
            <line>would have nothing lie on my head: I cannot be thus satisfied.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Look where my ranting host of the Garter comes:</line>
            <line>there is either liquor in his pate or money in his</line>
            <line>purse when he looks so merrily.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter Host</stagedir>
            <line>How now, mine host!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Host</speaker>
            <line>How now, bully-rook! thou'rt a gentleman.</line>
            <line>Cavaleiro-justice, I say!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter SHALLOW</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>I follow, mine host, I follow. Good even and</line>
            <line>twenty, good Master Page! Master Page, will you go</line>
            <line>with us? we have sport in hand.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Host</speaker>
            <line>Tell him, cavaleiro-justice; tell him, bully-rook.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>Sir, there is a fray to be fought between Sir Hugh</line>
            <line>the Welsh priest and Caius the French doctor.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>Good mine host o' the Garter, a word with you.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Drawing him aside</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Host</speaker>
            <line>What sayest thou, my bully-rook?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>To PAGE</stagedir>  Will you go with us to behold it? My</line>
            <line>merry host hath had the measuring of their weapons;</line>
            <line>and, I think, hath appointed them contrary places;</line>
            <line>for, believe me, I hear the parson is no jester.</line>
            <line>Hark, I will tell you what our sport shall be.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>They converse apart</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Host</speaker>
            <line>Hast thou no suit against my knight, my</line>
            <line>guest-cavaleire?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>None, I protest: but I'll give you a pottle of</line>
            <line>burnt sack to give me recourse to him and tell him</line>
            <line>my name is Brook; only for a jest.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Host</speaker>
            <line>My hand, bully; thou shalt have egress and regress;</line>
            <line>--said I well?--and thy name shall be Brook. It is</line>
            <line>a merry knight. Will you go, An-heires?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>Have with you, mine host.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAGE</speaker>
            <line>I have heard the Frenchman hath good skill in</line>
            <line>his rapier.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>Tut, sir, I could have told you more. In these times</line>
            <line>you stand on distance, your passes, stoccadoes, and</line>
            <line>I know not what: 'tis the heart, Master Page; 'tis</line>
            <line>here, 'tis here. I have seen the time, with my long</line>
            <line>sword I would have made you four tall fellows skip like rats.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Host</speaker>
            <line>Here, boys, here, here! shall we wag?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Have with you. I would rather hear them scold than fight.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt Host, SHALLOW, and PAGE</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>Though Page be a secure fool, an stands so firmly</line>
            <line>on his wife's frailty, yet I cannot put off my</line>
            <line>opinion so easily: she was in his company at Page's</line>
            <line>house; and what they made there, I know not. Well,</line>
            <line>I will look further into't: and I have a disguise</line>
            <line>to sound Falstaff. If I find her honest, I lose not</line>
            <line>my labour; if she be otherwise, 'tis labour well bestowed.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  A room in the Garter Inn.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter FALSTAFF and PISTOL</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>I will not lend thee a penny.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>Why, then the world's mine oyster.</line>
            <line>Which I with sword will open.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Not a penny. I have been content, sir, you should</line>
            <line>lay my countenance to pawn; I have grated upon my</line>
            <line>good friends for three reprieves for you and your</line>
            <line>coach-fellow Nym; or else you had looked through</line>
            <line>the grate, like a geminy of baboons. I am damned in</line>
            <line>hell for swearing to gentlemen my friends, you were</line>
            <line>good soldiers and tall fellows; and when Mistress</line>
            <line>Bridget lost the handle of her fan, I took't upon</line>
            <line>mine honour thou hadst it not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>Didst not thou share? hadst thou not fifteen pence?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Reason, you rogue, reason: thinkest thou I'll</line>
            <line>endanger my soul gratis? At a word, hang no more</line>
            <line>about me, I am no gibbet for you. Go. A short knife</line>
            <line>and a throng! To your manor of Pickt-hatch! Go.</line>
            <line>You'll not bear a letter for me, you rogue! you</line>
            <line>stand upon your honour! Why, thou unconfinable</line>
            <line>baseness, it is as much as I can do to keep the</line>
            <line>terms of my honour precise: I, I, I myself</line>
            <line>sometimes, leaving the fear of God on the left hand</line>
            <line>and hiding mine honour in my necessity, am fain to</line>
            <line>shuffle, to hedge and to lurch; and yet you, rogue,</line>
            <line>will ensconce your rags, your cat-a-mountain</line>
            <line>looks, your red-lattice phrases, and your</line>
            <line>bold-beating oaths, under the shelter of your</line>
            <line>honour! You will not do it, you!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>I do relent: what would thou more of man?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter ROBIN</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROBIN</speaker>
            <line>Sir, here's a woman would speak with you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Let her approach.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter MISTRESS QUICKLY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS QUICKLY</speaker>
            <line>Give your worship good morrow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Good morrow, good wife.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS QUICKLY</speaker>
            <line>Not so, an't please your worship.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Good maid, then.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS QUICKLY</speaker>
            <line>I'll be sworn,</line>
            <line>As my mother was, the first hour I was born.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>I do believe the swearer. What with me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS QUICKLY</speaker>
            <line>Shall I vouchsafe your worship a word or two?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Two thousand, fair woman: and I'll vouchsafe thee</line>
            <line>the hearing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS QUICKLY</speaker>
            <line>There is one Mistress Ford, sir:--I pray, come a</line>
            <line>little nearer this ways:--I myself dwell with master</line>
            <line>Doctor Caius,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Well, on: Mistress Ford, you say,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS QUICKLY</speaker>
            <line>Your worship says very true: I pray your worship,</line>
            <line>come a little nearer this ways.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>I warrant thee, nobody hears; mine own people, mine</line>
            <line>own people.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS QUICKLY</speaker>
            <line>Are they so? God bless them and make them his servants!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Well, Mistress Ford; what of her?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS QUICKLY</speaker>
            <line>Why, sir, she's a good creature. Lord Lord! your</line>
            <line>worship's a wanton! Well, heaven forgive you and all</line>
            <line>of us, I pray!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Mistress Ford; come, Mistress Ford,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS QUICKLY</speaker>
            <line>Marry, this is the short and the long of it; you</line>
            <line>have brought her into such a canaries as 'tis</line>
            <line>wonderful. The best courtier of them all, when the</line>
            <line>court lay at Windsor, could never have brought her</line>
            <line>to such a canary. Yet there has been knights, and</line>
            <line>lords, and gentlemen, with their coaches, I warrant</line>
            <line>you, coach after coach, letter after letter, gift</line>
            <line>after gift; smelling so sweetly, all musk, and so</line>
            <line>rushling, I warrant you, in silk and gold; and in</line>
            <line>such alligant terms; and in such wine and sugar of</line>
            <line>the best and the fairest, that would have won any</line>
            <line>woman's heart; and, I warrant you, they could never</line>
            <line>get an eye-wink of her: I had myself twenty angels</line>
            <line>given me this morning; but I defy all angels, in</line>
            <line>any such sort, as they say, but in the way of</line>
            <line>honesty: and, I warrant you, they could never get</line>
            <line>her so much as sip on a cup with the proudest of</line>
            <line>them all: and yet there has been earls, nay, which</line>
            <line>is more, pensioners; but, I warrant you, all is one with her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>But what says she to me? be brief, my good</line>
            <line>she-Mercury.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS QUICKLY</speaker>
            <line>Marry, she hath received your letter, for the which</line>
            <line>she thanks you a thousand times; and she gives you</line>
            <line>to notify that her husband will be absence from his</line>
            <line>house between ten and eleven.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Ten and eleven?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS QUICKLY</speaker>
            <line>Ay, forsooth; and then you may come and see the</line>
            <line>picture, she says, that you wot of: Master Ford,</line>
            <line>her husband, will be from home. Alas! the sweet</line>
            <line>woman leads an ill life with him: he's a very</line>
            <line>jealousy man: she leads a very frampold life with</line>
            <line>him, good heart.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Ten and eleven. Woman, commend me to her; I will</line>
            <line>not fail her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS QUICKLY</speaker>
            <line>Why, you say well. But I have another messenger to</line>
            <line>your worship. Mistress Page hath her hearty</line>
            <line>commendations to you too: and let me tell you in</line>
            <line>your ear, she's as fartuous a civil modest wife, and</line>
            <line>one, I tell you, that will not miss you morning nor</line>
            <line>evening prayer, as any is in Windsor, whoe'er be the</line>
            <line>other: and she bade me tell your worship that her</line>
            <line>husband is seldom from home; but she hopes there</line>
            <line>will come a time. I never knew a woman so dote upon</line>
            <line>a man: surely I think you have charms, la; yes, in truth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Not I, I assure thee: setting the attractions of my</line>
            <line>good parts aside I have no other charms.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS QUICKLY</speaker>
            <line>Blessing on your heart for't!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>But, I pray thee, tell me this: has Ford's wife and</line>
            <line>Page's wife acquainted each other how they love me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS QUICKLY</speaker>
            <line>That were a jest indeed! they have not so little</line>
            <line>grace, I hope: that were a trick indeed! but</line>
            <line>Mistress Page would desire you to send her your</line>
            <line>little page, of all loves: her husband has a</line>
            <line>marvellous infection to the little page; and truly</line>
            <line>Master Page is an honest man. Never a wife in</line>
            <line>Windsor leads a better life than she does: do what</line>
            <line>she will, say what she will, take all, pay all, go</line>
            <line>to bed when she list, rise when she list, all is as</line>
            <line>she will: and truly she deserves it; for if there</line>
            <line>be a kind woman in Windsor, she is one. You must</line>
            <line>send her your page; no remedy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Why, I will.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS QUICKLY</speaker>
            <line>Nay, but do so, then: and, look you, he may come and</line>
            <line>go between you both; and in any case have a</line>
            <line>nay-word, that you may know one another's mind, and</line>
            <line>the boy never need to understand any thing; for</line>
            <line>'tis not good that children should know any</line>
            <line>wickedness: old folks, you know, have discretion,</line>
            <line>as they say, and know the world.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Fare thee well: commend me to them both: there's</line>
            <line>my purse; I am yet thy debtor. Boy, go along with</line>
            <line>this woman.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt MISTRESS QUICKLY and ROBIN</stagedir>
            <line>This news distracts me!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>This punk is one of Cupid's carriers:</line>
            <line>Clap on more sails; pursue; up with your fights:</line>
            <line>Give fire: she is my prize, or ocean whelm them all!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Sayest thou so, old Jack? go thy ways; I'll make</line>
            <line>more of thy old body than I have done. Will they</line>
            <line>yet look after thee? Wilt thou, after the expense</line>
            <line>of so much money, be now a gainer? Good body, I</line>
            <line>thank thee. Let them say 'tis grossly done; so it be</line>
            <line>fairly done, no matter.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter BARDOLPH</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BARDOLPH</speaker>
            <line>Sir John, there's one Master Brook below would fain</line>
            <line>speak with you, and be acquainted with you; and hath</line>
            <line>sent your worship a morning's draught of sack.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Brook is his name?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BARDOLPH</speaker>
            <line>Ay, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Call him in.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit BARDOLPH</stagedir>
            <line>Such Brooks are welcome to me, that o'erflow such</line>
            <line>liquor. Ah, ha! Mistress Ford and Mistress Page</line>
            <line>have I encompassed you? go to; via!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter BARDOLPH, with FORD disguised</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>Bless you, sir!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>And you, sir! Would you speak with me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>I make bold to press with so little preparation upon</line>
            <line>you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>You're welcome. What's your will? Give us leave, drawer.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit BARDOLPH</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>Sir, I am a gentleman that have spent much; my name is Brook.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Good Master Brook, I desire more acquaintance of you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>Good Sir John, I sue for yours: not to charge you;</line>
            <line>for I must let you understand I think myself in</line>
            <line>better plight for a lender than you are: the which</line>
            <line>hath something embolden'd me to this unseasoned</line>
            <line>intrusion; for they say, if money go before, all</line>
            <line>ways do lie open.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Money is a good soldier, sir, and will on.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>Troth, and I have a bag of money here troubles me:</line>
            <line>if you will help to bear it, Sir John, take all, or</line>
            <line>half, for easing me of the carriage.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Sir, I know not how I may deserve to be your porter.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>I will tell you, sir, if you will give me the hearing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Speak, good Master Brook: I shall be glad to be</line>
            <line>your servant.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>Sir, I hear you are a scholar,--I will be brief</line>
            <line>with you,--and you have been a man long known to me,</line>
            <line>though I had never so good means, as desire, to make</line>
            <line>myself acquainted with you. I shall discover a</line>
            <line>thing to you, wherein I must very much lay open mine</line>
            <line>own imperfection: but, good Sir John, as you have</line>
            <line>one eye upon my follies, as you hear them unfolded,</line>
            <line>turn another into the register of your own; that I</line>
            <line>may pass with a reproof the easier, sith you</line>
            <line>yourself know how easy it is to be such an offender.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Very well, sir; proceed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>There is a gentlewoman in this town; her husband's</line>
            <line>name is Ford.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Well, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>I have long loved her, and, I protest to you,</line>
            <line>bestowed much on her; followed her with a doting</line>
            <line>observance; engrossed opportunities to meet her;</line>
            <line>fee'd every slight occasion that could but niggardly</line>
            <line>give me sight of her; not only bought many presents</line>
            <line>to give her, but have given largely to many to know</line>
            <line>what she would have given; briefly, I have pursued</line>
            <line>her as love hath pursued me; which hath been on the</line>
            <line>wing of all occasions. But whatsoever I have</line>
            <line>merited, either in my mind or, in my means, meed,</line>
            <line>I am sure, I have received none; unless experience</line>
            <line>be a jewel that I have purchased at an infinite</line>
            <line>rate, and that hath taught me to say this:</line>
            <line>'Love like a shadow flies when substance love pursues;</line>
            <line>Pursuing that that flies, and flying what pursues.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Have you received no promise of satisfaction at her hands?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>Never.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Have you importuned her to such a purpose?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>Never.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Of what quality was your love, then?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>Like a fair house built on another man's ground; so</line>
            <line>that I have lost my edifice by mistaking the place</line>
            <line>where I erected it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>To what purpose have you unfolded this to me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>When I have told you that, I have told you all.</line>
            <line>Some say, that though she appear honest to me, yet in</line>
            <line>other places she enlargeth her mirth so far that</line>
            <line>there is shrewd construction made of her. Now, Sir</line>
            <line>John, here is the heart of my purpose: you are a</line>
            <line>gentleman of excellent breeding, admirable</line>
            <line>discourse, of great admittance, authentic in your</line>
            <line>place and person, generally allowed for your many</line>
            <line>war-like, court-like, and learned preparations.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>O, sir!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>Believe it, for you know it. There is money; spend</line>
            <line>it, spend it; spend more; spend all I have; only</line>
            <line>give me so much of your time in exchange of it, as</line>
            <line>to lay an amiable siege to the honesty of this</line>
            <line>Ford's wife: use your art of wooing; win her to</line>
            <line>consent to you: if any man may, you may as soon as</line>
            <line>any.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Would it apply well to the vehemency of your</line>
            <line>affection, that I should win what you would enjoy?</line>
            <line>Methinks you prescribe to yourself very preposterously.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>O, understand my drift. She dwells so securely on</line>
            <line>the excellency of her honour, that the folly of my</line>
            <line>soul dares not present itself: she is too bright to</line>
            <line>be looked against. Now, could I could come to her</line>
            <line>with any detection in my hand, my desires had</line>
            <line>instance and argument to commend themselves: I</line>
            <line>could drive her then from the ward of her purity,</line>
            <line>her reputation, her marriage-vow, and a thousand</line>
            <line>other her defences, which now are too too strongly</line>
            <line>embattled against me. What say you to't, Sir John?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Master Brook, I will first make bold with your</line>
            <line>money; next, give me your hand; and last, as I am a</line>
            <line>gentleman, you shall, if you will, enjoy Ford's wife.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>O good sir!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>I say you shall.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>Want no money, Sir John; you shall want none.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Want no Mistress Ford, Master Brook; you shall want</line>
            <line>none. I shall be with her, I may tell you, by her</line>
            <line>own appointment; even as you came in to me, her</line>
            <line>assistant or go-between parted from me: I say I</line>
            <line>shall be with her between ten and eleven; for at</line>
            <line>that time the jealous rascally knave her husband</line>
            <line>will be forth. Come you to me at night; you shall</line>
            <line>know how I speed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>I am blest in your acquaintance. Do you know Ford,</line>
            <line>sir?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Hang him, poor cuckoldly knave! I know him not:</line>
            <line>yet I wrong him to call him poor; they say the</line>
            <line>jealous wittolly knave hath masses of money; for the</line>
            <line>which his wife seems to me well-favored. I will</line>
            <line>use her as the key of the cuckoldly rogue's coffer;</line>
            <line>and there's my harvest-home.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>I would you knew Ford, sir, that you might avoid him</line>
            <line>if you saw him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Hang him, mechanical salt-butter rogue! I will</line>
            <line>stare him out of his wits; I will awe him with my</line>
            <line>cudgel: it shall hang like a meteor o'er the</line>
            <line>cuckold's horns. Master Brook, thou shalt know I</line>
            <line>will predominate over the peasant, and thou shalt</line>
            <line>lie with his wife. Come to me soon at night.</line>
            <line>Ford's a knave, and I will aggravate his style;</line>
            <line>thou, Master Brook, shalt know him for knave and</line>
            <line>cuckold. Come to me soon at night.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FORD</speaker>
            <line>What a damned Epicurean rascal is this! My heart is</line>
            <line>ready to crack with impatience. Who says this is</line>
            <line>improvident jealousy? my wife hath sent to him; the</line>
            <line>hour is fixed; the match is made. Would any man</line>
            <line>have thought this? See the hell of having a false</line>
            <line>woman! My bed shall be abused, my coffers</line>
            <line>ransacked, my reputation gnawn at; and I shall not</line>
            <line>only receive this villanous wrong, but stand under</line>
            <line>the adoption of abominable terms, and by him that</line>
            <line>does me this wrong. Terms! names! Amaimon sounds</line>
            <line>well; Lucifer, well; Barbason, well; yet they are</line>
            <line>devils' additions, the names of fiends: but</line>
            <line>Cuckold! Wittol!--Cuckold! the devil himself hath</line>
            <line>not such a name. Page is an ass, a secure ass: he</line>
            <line>will trust his wife; he will not be jealous. I will</line>
            <line>rather trust a Fleming with my butter, Parson Hugh</line>
            <line>the Welshman with my cheese, an Irishman with my</line>
            <line>aqua-vitae bottle, or a thief to walk my ambling</line>
            <line>gelding, than my wife with herself; then she plots,</line>
            <line>then she ruminates, then she devises; and what they</line>
            <line>think in their hearts they may effect, they will</line>
            <line>break their hearts but they will effect. God be</line>
            <line>praised for my jealousy! Eleven o'clock the hour.</line>
            <line>I will prevent this, detect my wife, be revenged on</line>
            <line>Falstaff, and laugh at Page. I will about it;</line>
            <line>better three hours too soon than a minute too late.</line>
            <line>Fie, fie, fie! cuckold! cuckold! cuckold!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  A field near Windsor.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter DOCTOR CAIUS and RUGBY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOCTOR CAIUS</speaker>
            <line>Jack Rugby!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RUGBY</speaker>
            <line>Sir?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOCTOR CAIUS</speaker>
            <line>Vat is de clock, Jack?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RUGBY</speaker>
            <line>'Tis past the hour, sir, that Sir Hugh promised to meet.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOCTOR CAIUS</speaker>
            <line>By gar, he has save his soul, dat he is no come; he</line>
            <line>has pray his Pible well, dat he is no come: by gar,</line>
            <line>Jack Rugby, he is dead already, if he be come.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RUGBY</speaker>
            <line>He is wise, sir; he knew your worship would kill</line>
            <line>him, if he came.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOCTOR CAIUS</speaker>
            <line>By gar, de herring is no dead so as I vill kill him.</line>
            <line>Take your rapier, Jack; I vill tell you how I vill kill him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RUGBY</speaker>
            <line>Alas, sir, I cannot fence.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOCTOR CAIUS</speaker>
            <line>Villany, take your rapier.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RUGBY</speaker>
            <line>Forbear; here's company.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter Host, SHALLOW, SLENDER, and PAGE</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Host</speaker>
            <line>Bless thee, bully doctor!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>Save you, Master Doctor Caius!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Now, good master doctor!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SLENDER</speaker>
            <line>Give you good morrow, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOCTOR CAIUS</speaker>
            <line>Vat be all you, one, two, tree, four, come for?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Host</speaker>
            <line>To see thee fight, to see thee foin, to see thee</line>
            <line>traverse; to see thee here, to see thee there; to</line>
            <line>see thee pass thy punto, thy stock, thy reverse, thy</line>
            <line>distance, thy montant. Is he dead, my Ethiopian? is</line>
            <line>he dead, my Francisco? ha, bully! What says my</line>
            <line>AEsculapius? my Galen? my heart of elder? ha! is</line>
            <line>he dead, bully stale? is he dead?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOCTOR CAIUS</speaker>
            <line>By gar, he is de coward Jack priest of de vorld; he</line>
            <line>is not show his face.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Host</speaker>
            <line>Thou art a Castalion-King-Urinal. Hector of Greece, my boy!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOCTOR CAIUS</speaker>
            <line>I pray you, bear vitness that me have stay six or</line>
            <line>seven, two, tree hours for him, and he is no come.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>He is the wiser man, master doctor: he is a curer of</line>
            <line>souls, and you a curer of bodies; if you should</line>
            <line>fight, you go against the hair of your professions.</line>
            <line>Is it not true, Master Page?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Master Shallow, you have yourself been a great</line>
            <line>fighter, though now a man of peace.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>Bodykins, Master Page, though I now be old and of</line>
            <line>the peace, if I see a sword out, my finger itches to</line>
            <line>make one. Though we are justices and doctors and</line>
            <line>churchmen, Master Page, we have some salt of our</line>
            <line>youth in us; we are the sons of women, Master Page.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAGE</speaker>
            <line>'Tis true, Master Shallow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>It will be found so, Master Page. Master Doctor</line>
            <line>Caius, I am come to fetch you home. I am sworn of</line>
            <line>the peace: you have showed yourself a wise</line>
            <line>physician, and Sir Hugh hath shown himself a wise</line>
            <line>and patient churchman. You must go with me, master doctor.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Host</speaker>
            <line>Pardon, guest-justice. A word, Mounseur Mockwater.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOCTOR CAIUS</speaker>
            <line>Mock-vater! vat is dat?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Host</speaker>
            <line>Mock-water, in our English tongue, is valour, bully.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOCTOR CAIUS</speaker>
            <line>By gar, den, I have as mush mock-vater as de</line>
            <line>Englishman. Scurvy jack-dog priest! by gar, me</line>
            <line>vill cut his ears.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Host</speaker>
            <line>He will clapper-claw thee tightly, bully.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOCTOR CAIUS</speaker>
            <line>Clapper-de-claw! vat is dat?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Host</speaker>
            <line>That is, he will make thee amends.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOCTOR CAIUS</speaker>
            <line>By gar, me do look he shall clapper-de-claw me;</line>
            <line>for, by gar, me vill have it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Host</speaker>
            <line>And I will provoke him to't, or let him wag.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOCTOR CAIUS</speaker>
            <line>Me tank you for dat.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Host</speaker>
            <line>And, moreover, bully,--but first, master guest, and</line>
            <line>Master Page, and eke Cavaleiro Slender, go you</line>
            <line>through the town to Frogmore.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Aside to them</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAGE</speaker>
            <line>Sir Hugh is there, is he?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Host</speaker>
            <line>He is there: see what humour he is in; and I will</line>
            <line>bring the doctor about by the fields. Will it do well?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>We will do it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAGE</speaker>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <speaker>SLENDER</speaker>
            <line>Adieu, good master doctor.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt PAGE, SHALLOW, and SLENDER</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOCTOR CAIUS</speaker>
            <line>By gar, me vill kill de priest; for he speak for a</line>
            <line>jack-an-ape to Anne Page.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Host</speaker>
            <line>Let him die: sheathe thy impatience, throw cold</line>
            <line>water on thy choler: go about the fields with me</line>
            <line>through Frogmore: I will bring thee where Mistress</line>
            <line>Anne Page is, at a farm-house a-feasting; and thou</line>
            <line>shalt woo her. Cried I aim? said I well?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOCTOR CAIUS</speaker>
            <line>By gar, me dank you for dat: by gar, I love you;</line>
            <line>and I shall procure-a you de good guest, de earl,</line>
            <line>de knight, de lords, de gentlemen, my patients.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Host</speaker>
            <line>For the which I will be thy adversary toward Anne</line>
            <line>Page. Said I well?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOCTOR CAIUS</speaker>
            <line>By gar, 'tis good; vell said.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Host</speaker>
            <line>Let us wag, then.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOCTOR CAIUS</speaker>
            <line>Come at my heels, Jack Rugby.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>