<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:shakespear:dtd:act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-1">
   <title>ACT I</title>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  The king of Navarre's park.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter FERDINAND king of Navarre, BIRON, LONGAVILLE
and DUMAIN</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>Let fame, that all hunt after in their lives,</line>
            <line>Live register'd upon our brazen tombs</line>
            <line>And then grace us in the disgrace of death;</line>
            <line>When, spite of cormorant devouring Time,</line>
            <line>The endeavor of this present breath may buy</line>
            <line>That honour which shall bate his scythe's keen edge</line>
            <line>And make us heirs of all eternity.</line>
            <line>Therefore, brave conquerors,--for so you are,</line>
            <line>That war against your own affections</line>
            <line>And the huge army of the world's desires,--</line>
            <line>Our late edict shall strongly stand in force:</line>
            <line>Navarre shall be the wonder of the world;</line>
            <line>Our court shall be a little Academe,</line>
            <line>Still and contemplative in living art.</line>
            <line>You three, Biron, Dumain, and Longaville,</line>
            <line>Have sworn for three years' term to live with me</line>
            <line>My fellow-scholars, and to keep those statutes</line>
            <line>That are recorded in this schedule here:</line>
            <line>Your oaths are pass'd; and now subscribe your names,</line>
            <line>That his own hand may strike his honour down</line>
            <line>That violates the smallest branch herein:</line>
            <line>If you are arm'd to do as sworn to do,</line>
            <line>Subscribe to your deep oaths, and keep it too.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LONGAVILLE</speaker>
            <line>I am resolved; 'tis but a three years' fast:</line>
            <line>The mind shall banquet, though the body pine:</line>
            <line>Fat paunches have lean pates, and dainty bits</line>
            <line>Make rich the ribs, but bankrupt quite the wits.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUMAIN</speaker>
            <line>My loving lord, Dumain is mortified:</line>
            <line>The grosser manner of these world's delights</line>
            <line>He throws upon the gross world's baser slaves:</line>
            <line>To love, to wealth, to pomp, I pine and die;</line>
            <line>With all these living in philosophy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>I can but say their protestation over;</line>
            <line>So much, dear liege, I have already sworn,</line>
            <line>That is, to live and study here three years.</line>
            <line>But there are other strict observances;</line>
            <line>As, not to see a woman in that term,</line>
            <line>Which I hope well is not enrolled there;</line>
            <line>And one day in a week to touch no food</line>
            <line>And but one meal on every day beside,</line>
            <line>The which I hope is not enrolled there;</line>
            <line>And then, to sleep but three hours in the night,</line>
            <line>And not be seen to wink of all the day--</line>
            <line>When I was wont to think no harm all night</line>
            <line>And make a dark night too of half the day--</line>
            <line>Which I hope well is not enrolled there:</line>
            <line>O, these are barren tasks, too hard to keep,</line>
            <line>Not to see ladies, study, fast, not sleep!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>Your oath is pass'd to pass away from these.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>Let me say no, my liege, an if you please:</line>
            <line>I only swore to study with your grace</line>
            <line>And stay here in your court for three years' space.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LONGAVILLE</speaker>
            <line>You swore to that, Biron, and to the rest.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>By yea and nay, sir, then I swore in jest.</line>
            <line>What is the end of study? let me know.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>Why, that to know, which else we should not know.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>Things hid and barr'd, you mean, from common sense?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>Ay, that is study's godlike recompense.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>Come on, then; I will swear to study so,</line>
            <line>To know the thing I am forbid to know:</line>
            <line>As thus,--to study where I well may dine,</line>
            <line>When I to feast expressly am forbid;</line>
            <line>Or study where to meet some mistress fine,</line>
            <line>When mistresses from common sense are hid;</line>
            <line>Or, having sworn too hard a keeping oath,</line>
            <line>Study to break it and not break my troth.</line>
            <line>If study's gain be thus and this be so,</line>
            <line>Study knows that which yet it doth not know:</line>
            <line>Swear me to this, and I will ne'er say no.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>These be the stops that hinder study quite</line>
            <line>And train our intellects to vain delight.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>Why, all delights are vain; but that most vain,</line>
            <line>Which with pain purchased doth inherit pain:</line>
            <line>As, painfully to pore upon a book</line>
            <line>To seek the light of truth; while truth the while</line>
            <line>Doth falsely blind the eyesight of his look:</line>
            <line>Light seeking light doth light of light beguile:</line>
            <line>So, ere you find where light in darkness lies,</line>
            <line>Your light grows dark by losing of your eyes.</line>
            <line>Study me how to please the eye indeed</line>
            <line>By fixing it upon a fairer eye,</line>
            <line>Who dazzling so, that eye shall be his heed</line>
            <line>And give him light that it was blinded by.</line>
            <line>Study is like the heaven's glorious sun</line>
            <line>That will not be deep-search'd with saucy looks:</line>
            <line>Small have continual plodders ever won</line>
            <line>Save base authority from others' books</line>
            <line>These earthly godfathers of heaven's lights</line>
            <line>That give a name to every fixed star</line>
            <line>Have no more profit of their shining nights</line>
            <line>Than those that walk and wot not what they are.</line>
            <line>Too much to know is to know nought but fame;</line>
            <line>And every godfather can give a name.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>How well he's read, to reason against reading!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUMAIN</speaker>
            <line>Proceeded well, to stop all good proceeding!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LONGAVILLE</speaker>
            <line>He weeds the corn and still lets grow the weeding.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>The spring is near when green geese are a-breeding.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUMAIN</speaker>
            <line>How follows that?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>Fit in his place and time.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUMAIN</speaker>
            <line>In reason nothing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>Something then in rhyme.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>Biron is like an envious sneaping frost,</line>
            <line>That bites the first-born infants of the spring.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>Well, say I am; why should proud summer boast</line>
            <line>Before the birds have any cause to sing?</line>
            <line>Why should I joy in any abortive birth?</line>
            <line>At Christmas I no more desire a rose</line>
            <line>Than wish a snow in May's new-fangled mirth;</line>
            <line>But like of each thing that in season grows.</line>
            <line>So you, to study now it is too late,</line>
            <line>Climb o'er the house to unlock the little gate.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>Well, sit you out: go home, Biron: adieu.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>No, my good lord; I have sworn to stay with you:</line>
            <line>And though I have for barbarism spoke more</line>
            <line>Than for that angel knowledge you can say,</line>
            <line>Yet confident I'll keep what I have swore</line>
            <line>And bide the penance of each three years' day.</line>
            <line>Give me the paper; let me read the same;</line>
            <line>And to the strict'st decrees I'll write my name.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>How well this yielding rescues thee from shame!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>  'Item, That no woman shall come within a</line>
            <line>mile of my court:' Hath this been proclaimed?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LONGAVILLE</speaker>
            <line>Four days ago.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>Let's see the penalty.</line>
            <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>
            <line>'On pain of losing her tongue.' Who devised this penalty?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LONGAVILLE</speaker>
            <line>Marry, that did I.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>Sweet lord, and why?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LONGAVILLE</speaker>
            <line>To fright them hence with that dread penalty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>A dangerous law against gentility!</line>
            <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>
            <line>'Item, If any man be seen to talk with a woman</line>
            <line>within the term of three years, he shall endure such</line>
            <line>public shame as the rest of the court can possibly devise.'</line>
            <line>This article, my liege, yourself must break;</line>
            <line>For well you know here comes in embassy</line>
            <line>The French king's daughter with yourself to speak--</line>
            <line>A maid of grace and complete majesty--</line>
            <line>About surrender up of Aquitaine</line>
            <line>To her decrepit, sick and bedrid father:</line>
            <line>Therefore this article is made in vain,</line>
            <line>Or vainly comes the admired princess hither.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>What say you, lords? Why, this was quite forgot.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>So study evermore is overshot:</line>
            <line>While it doth study to have what it would</line>
            <line>It doth forget to do the thing it should,</line>
            <line>And when it hath the thing it hunteth most,</line>
            <line>'Tis won as towns with fire, so won, so lost.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>We must of force dispense with this decree;</line>
            <line>She must lie here on mere necessity.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>Necessity will make us all forsworn</line>
            <line>Three thousand times within this three years' space;</line>
            <line>For every man with his affects is born,</line>
            <line>Not by might master'd but by special grace:</line>
            <line>If I break faith, this word shall speak for me;</line>
            <line>I am forsworn on 'mere necessity.'</line>
            <line>So to the laws at large I write my name:</line>
            <stagedir>Subscribes</stagedir>
            <line>And he that breaks them in the least degree</line>
            <line>Stands in attainder of eternal shame:</line>
            <line>Suggestions are to other as to me;</line>
            <line>But I believe, although I seem so loath,</line>
            <line>I am the last that will last keep his oath.</line>
            <line>But is there no quick recreation granted?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>Ay, that there is. Our court, you know, is haunted</line>
            <line>With a refined traveller of Spain;</line>
            <line>A man in all the world's new fashion planted,</line>
            <line>That hath a mint of phrases in his brain;</line>
            <line>One whom the music of his own vain tongue</line>
            <line>Doth ravish like enchanting harmony;</line>
            <line>A man of complements, whom right and wrong</line>
            <line>Have chose as umpire of their mutiny:</line>
            <line>This child of fancy, that Armado hight,</line>
            <line>For interim to our studies shall relate</line>
            <line>In high-born words the worth of many a knight</line>
            <line>From tawny Spain lost in the world's debate.</line>
            <line>How you delight, my lords, I know not, I;</line>
            <line>But, I protest, I love to hear him lie</line>
            <line>And I will use him for my minstrelsy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>Armado is a most illustrious wight,</line>
            <line>A man of fire-new words, fashion's own knight.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LONGAVILLE</speaker>
            <line>Costard the swain and he shall be our sport;</line>
            <line>And so to study, three years is but short.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter DULL with a letter, and COSTARD</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DULL</speaker>
            <line>Which is the duke's own person?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>This, fellow: what wouldst?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DULL</speaker>
            <line>I myself reprehend his own person, for I am his</line>
            <line>grace's tharborough: but I would see his own person</line>
            <line>in flesh and blood.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>This is he.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DULL</speaker>
            <line>Signior Arme--Arme--commends you. There's villany</line>
            <line>abroad: this letter will tell you more.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COSTARD</speaker>
            <line>Sir, the contempts thereof are as touching me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>A letter from the magnificent Armado.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>How low soever the matter, I hope in God for high words.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LONGAVILLE</speaker>
            <line>A high hope for a low heaven: God grant us patience!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>To hear? or forbear laughing?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LONGAVILLE</speaker>
            <line>To hear meekly, sir, and to laugh moderately; or to</line>
            <line>forbear both.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>Well, sir, be it as the style shall give us cause to</line>
            <line>climb in the merriness.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COSTARD</speaker>
            <line>The matter is to me, sir, as concerning Jaquenetta.</line>
            <line>The manner of it is, I was taken with the manner.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>In what manner?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COSTARD</speaker>
            <line>In manner and form following, sir; all those three:</line>
            <line>I was seen with her in the manor-house, sitting with</line>
            <line>her upon the form, and taken following her into the</line>
            <line>park; which, put together, is in manner and form</line>
            <line>following. Now, sir, for the manner,--it is the</line>
            <line>manner of a man to speak to a woman: for the form,--</line>
            <line>in some form.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>For the following, sir?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COSTARD</speaker>
            <line>As it shall follow in my correction: and God defend</line>
            <line>the right!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>Will you hear this letter with attention?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>As we would hear an oracle.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COSTARD</speaker>
            <line>Such is the simplicity of man to hearken after the flesh.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>  'Great deputy, the welkin's vicegerent and</line>
            <line>sole dominator of Navarre, my soul's earth's god,</line>
            <line>and body's fostering patron.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COSTARD</speaker>
            <line>Not a word of Costard yet.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>  'So it is,'--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COSTARD</speaker>
            <line>It may be so: but if he say it is so, he is, in</line>
            <line>telling true, but so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>Peace!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COSTARD</speaker>
            <line>Be to me and every man that dares not fight!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>No words!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COSTARD</speaker>
            <line>Of other men's secrets, I beseech you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>  'So it is, besieged with sable-coloured</line>
            <line>melancholy, I did commend the black-oppressing humour</line>
            <line>to the most wholesome physic of thy health-giving</line>
            <line>air; and, as I am a gentleman, betook myself to</line>
            <line>walk. The time when. About the sixth hour; when</line>
            <line>beasts most graze, birds best peck, and men sit down</line>
            <line>to that nourishment which is called supper: so much</line>
            <line>for the time when. Now for the ground which; which,</line>
            <line>I mean, I walked upon: it is y-cleped thy park. Then</line>
            <line>for the place where; where, I mean, I did encounter</line>
            <line>that obscene and preposterous event, that draweth</line>
            <line>from my snow-white pen the ebon-coloured ink, which</line>
            <line>here thou viewest, beholdest, surveyest, or seest;</line>
            <line>but to the place where; it standeth north-north-east</line>
            <line>and by east from the west corner of thy curious-</line>
            <line>knotted garden: there did I see that low-spirited</line>
            <line>swain, that base minnow of thy mirth,'--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COSTARD</speaker>
            <line>Me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>  'that unlettered small-knowing soul,'--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COSTARD</speaker>
            <line>Me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>  'that shallow vassal,'--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COSTARD</speaker>
            <line>Still me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>  'which, as I remember, hight Costard,'--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COSTARD</speaker>
            <line>O, me!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>  'sorted and consorted, contrary to thy</line>
            <line>established proclaimed edict and continent canon,</line>
            <line>which with,--O, with--but with this I passion to say</line>
            <line>wherewith,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COSTARD</speaker>
            <line>With a wench.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>  'with a child of our grandmother Eve, a</line>
            <line>female; or, for thy more sweet understanding, a</line>
            <line>woman. Him I, as my ever-esteemed duty pricks me on,</line>
            <line>have sent to thee, to receive the meed of</line>
            <line>punishment, by thy sweet grace's officer, Anthony</line>
            <line>Dull; a man of good repute, carriage, bearing, and</line>
            <line>estimation.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DULL</speaker>
            <line>'Me, an't shall please you; I am Anthony Dull.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>  'For Jaquenetta,--so is the weaker vessel</line>
            <line>called which I apprehended with the aforesaid</line>
            <line>swain,--I keep her as a vessel of the law's fury;</line>
            <line>and shall, at the least of thy sweet notice, bring</line>
            <line>her to trial. Thine, in all compliments of devoted</line>
            <line>and heart-burning heat of duty.</line>
            <line>DON ADRIANO DE ARMADO.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>This is not so well as I looked for, but the best</line>
            <line>that ever I heard.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>Ay, the best for the worst. But, sirrah, what say</line>
            <line>you to this?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COSTARD</speaker>
            <line>Sir, I confess the wench.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>Did you hear the proclamation?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COSTARD</speaker>
            <line>I do confess much of the hearing it but little of</line>
            <line>the marking of it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>It was proclaimed a year's imprisonment, to be taken</line>
            <line>with a wench.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COSTARD</speaker>
            <line>I was taken with none, sir: I was taken with a damsel.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>Well, it was proclaimed 'damsel.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COSTARD</speaker>
            <line>This was no damsel, neither, sir; she was a virgin.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>It is so varied, too; for it was proclaimed 'virgin.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COSTARD</speaker>
            <line>If it were, I deny her virginity: I was taken with a maid.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>This maid will not serve your turn, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COSTARD</speaker>
            <line>This maid will serve my turn, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>Sir, I will pronounce your sentence: you shall fast</line>
            <line>a week with bran and water.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COSTARD</speaker>
            <line>I had rather pray a month with mutton and porridge.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>And Don Armado shall be your keeper.</line>
            <line>My Lord Biron, see him deliver'd o'er:</line>
            <line>And go we, lords, to put in practise that</line>
            <line>Which each to other hath so strongly sworn.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt FERDINAND, LONGAVILLE, and DUMAIN</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>I'll lay my head to any good man's hat,</line>
            <line>These oaths and laws will prove an idle scorn.</line>
            <line>Sirrah, come on.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COSTARD</speaker>
            <line>I suffer for the truth, sir; for true it is, I was</line>
            <line>taken with Jaquenetta, and Jaquenetta is a true</line>
            <line>girl; and therefore welcome the sour cup of</line>
            <line>prosperity! Affliction may one day smile again; and</line>
            <line>till then, sit thee down, sorrow!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  The same.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter DON ADRIANO DE ARMADO and MOTH</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON ADRIANO DE ARMADO</speaker>
            <line>Boy, what sign is it when a man of great spirit</line>
            <line>grows melancholy?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOTH</speaker>
            <line>A great sign, sir, that he will look sad.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON ADRIANO DE ARMADO</speaker>
            <line>Why, sadness is one and the self-same thing, dear imp.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOTH</speaker>
            <line>No, no; O Lord, sir, no.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON ADRIANO DE ARMADO</speaker>
            <line>How canst thou part sadness and melancholy, my</line>
            <line>tender juvenal?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOTH</speaker>
            <line>By a familiar demonstration of the working, my tough senior.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON ADRIANO DE ARMADO</speaker>
            <line>Why tough senior? why tough senior?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOTH</speaker>
            <line>Why tender juvenal? why tender juvenal?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON ADRIANO DE ARMADO</speaker>
            <line>I spoke it, tender juvenal, as a congruent epitheton</line>
            <line>appertaining to thy young days, which we may</line>
            <line>nominate tender.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOTH</speaker>
            <line>And I, tough senior, as an appertinent title to your</line>
            <line>old time, which we may name tough.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON ADRIANO DE ARMADO</speaker>
            <line>Pretty and apt.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOTH</speaker>
            <line>How mean you, sir? I pretty, and my saying apt? or</line>
            <line>I apt, and my saying pretty?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON ADRIANO DE ARMADO</speaker>
            <line>Thou pretty, because little.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOTH</speaker>
            <line>Little pretty, because little. Wherefore apt?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON ADRIANO DE ARMADO</speaker>
            <line>And therefore apt, because quick.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOTH</speaker>
            <line>Speak you this in my praise, master?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON ADRIANO DE ARMADO</speaker>
            <line>In thy condign praise.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOTH</speaker>
            <line>I will praise an eel with the same praise.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON ADRIANO DE ARMADO</speaker>
            <line>What, that an eel is ingenious?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOTH</speaker>
            <line>That an eel is quick.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON ADRIANO DE ARMADO</speaker>
            <line>I do say thou art quick in answers: thou heatest my blood.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOTH</speaker>
            <line>I am answered, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON ADRIANO DE ARMADO</speaker>
            <line>I love not to be crossed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOTH</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  He speaks the mere contrary; crosses love not him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON ADRIANO DE ARMADO</speaker>
            <line>I have promised to study three years with the duke.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOTH</speaker>
            <line>You may do it in an hour, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON ADRIANO DE ARMADO</speaker>
            <line>Impossible.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOTH</speaker>
            <line>How many is one thrice told?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON ADRIANO DE ARMADO</speaker>
            <line>I am ill at reckoning; it fitteth the spirit of a tapster.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOTH</speaker>
            <line>You are a gentleman and a gamester, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON ADRIANO DE ARMADO</speaker>
            <line>I confess both: they are both the varnish of a</line>
            <line>complete man.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOTH</speaker>
            <line>Then, I am sure, you know how much the gross sum of</line>
            <line>deuce-ace amounts to.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON ADRIANO DE ARMADO</speaker>
            <line>It doth amount to one more than two.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOTH</speaker>
            <line>Which the base vulgar do call three.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON ADRIANO DE ARMADO</speaker>
            <line>True.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOTH</speaker>
            <line>Why, sir, is this such a piece of study? Now here</line>
            <line>is three studied, ere ye'll thrice wink: and how</line>
            <line>easy it is to put 'years' to the word 'three,' and</line>
            <line>study three years in two words, the dancing horse</line>
            <line>will tell you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON ADRIANO DE ARMADO</speaker>
            <line>A most fine figure!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOTH</speaker>
            <line>To prove you a cipher.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON ADRIANO DE ARMADO</speaker>
            <line>I will hereupon confess I am in love: and as it is</line>
            <line>base for a soldier to love, so am I in love with a</line>
            <line>base wench. If drawing my sword against the humour</line>
            <line>of affection would deliver me from the reprobate</line>
            <line>thought of it, I would take Desire prisoner, and</line>
            <line>ransom him to any French courtier for a new-devised</line>
            <line>courtesy. I think scorn to sigh: methinks I should</line>
            <line>outswear Cupid. Comfort, me, boy: what great men</line>
            <line>have been in love?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOTH</speaker>
            <line>Hercules, master.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON ADRIANO DE ARMADO</speaker>
            <line>Most sweet Hercules! More authority, dear boy, name</line>
            <line>more; and, sweet my child, let them be men of good</line>
            <line>repute and carriage.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOTH</speaker>
            <line>Samson, master: he was a man of good carriage, great</line>
            <line>carriage, for he carried the town-gates on his back</line>
            <line>like a porter: and he was in love.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON ADRIANO DE ARMADO</speaker>
            <line>O well-knit Samson! strong-jointed Samson! I do</line>
            <line>excel thee in my rapier as much as thou didst me in</line>
            <line>carrying gates. I am in love too. Who was Samson's</line>
            <line>love, my dear Moth?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOTH</speaker>
            <line>A woman, master.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON ADRIANO DE ARMADO</speaker>
            <line>Of what complexion?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOTH</speaker>
            <line>Of all the four, or the three, or the two, or one of the four.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON ADRIANO DE ARMADO</speaker>
            <line>Tell me precisely of what complexion.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOTH</speaker>
            <line>Of the sea-water green, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON ADRIANO DE ARMADO</speaker>
            <line>Is that one of the four complexions?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOTH</speaker>
            <line>As I have read, sir; and the best of them too.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON ADRIANO DE ARMADO</speaker>
            <line>Green indeed is the colour of lovers; but to have a</line>
            <line>love of that colour, methinks Samson had small reason</line>
            <line>for it. He surely affected her for her wit.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOTH</speaker>
            <line>It was so, sir; for she had a green wit.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON ADRIANO DE ARMADO</speaker>
            <line>My love is most immaculate white and red.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOTH</speaker>
            <line>Most maculate thoughts, master, are masked under</line>
            <line>such colours.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON ADRIANO DE ARMADO</speaker>
            <line>Define, define, well-educated infant.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOTH</speaker>
            <line>My father's wit and my mother's tongue, assist me!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON ADRIANO DE ARMADO</speaker>
            <line>Sweet invocation of a child; most pretty and</line>
            <line>pathetical!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOTH</speaker>
            <line>If she be made of white and red,</line>
            <line>Her faults will ne'er be known,</line>
            <line>For blushing cheeks by faults are bred</line>
            <line>And fears by pale white shown:</line>
            <line>Then if she fear, or be to blame,</line>
            <line>By this you shall not know,</line>
            <line>For still her cheeks possess the same</line>
            <line>Which native she doth owe.</line>
            <line>A dangerous rhyme, master, against the reason of</line>
            <line>white and red.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON ADRIANO DE ARMADO</speaker>
            <line>Is there not a ballad, boy, of the King and the Beggar?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOTH</speaker>
            <line>The world was very guilty of such a ballad some</line>
            <line>three ages since: but I think now 'tis not to be</line>
            <line>found; or, if it were, it would neither serve for</line>
            <line>the writing nor the tune.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON ADRIANO DE ARMADO</speaker>
            <line>I will have that subject newly writ o'er, that I may</line>
            <line>example my digression by some mighty precedent.</line>
            <line>Boy, I do love that country girl that I took in the</line>
            <line>park with the rational hind Costard: she deserves well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOTH</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  To be whipped; and yet a better love than</line>
            <line>my master.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON ADRIANO DE ARMADO</speaker>
            <line>Sing, boy; my spirit grows heavy in love.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOTH</speaker>
            <line>And that's great marvel, loving a light wench.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON ADRIANO DE ARMADO</speaker>
            <line>I say, sing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOTH</speaker>
            <line>Forbear till this company be past.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter DULL, COSTARD, and JAQUENETTA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DULL</speaker>
            <line>Sir, the duke's pleasure is, that you keep Costard</line>
            <line>safe: and you must suffer him to take no delight</line>
            <line>nor no penance; but a' must fast three days a week.</line>
            <line>For this damsel, I must keep her at the park: she</line>
            <line>is allowed for the day-woman. Fare you well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON ADRIANO DE ARMADO</speaker>
            <line>I do betray myself with blushing. Maid!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JAQUENETTA</speaker>
            <line>Man?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON ADRIANO DE ARMADO</speaker>
            <line>I will visit thee at the lodge.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JAQUENETTA</speaker>
            <line>That's hereby.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON ADRIANO DE ARMADO</speaker>
            <line>I know where it is situate.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JAQUENETTA</speaker>
            <line>Lord, how wise you are!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON ADRIANO DE ARMADO</speaker>
            <line>I will tell thee wonders.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JAQUENETTA</speaker>
            <line>With that face?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON ADRIANO DE ARMADO</speaker>
            <line>I love thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JAQUENETTA</speaker>
            <line>So I heard you say.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON ADRIANO DE ARMADO</speaker>
            <line>And so, farewell.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JAQUENETTA</speaker>
            <line>Fair weather after you!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DULL</speaker>
            <line>Come, Jaquenetta, away!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt DULL and JAQUENETTA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON ADRIANO DE ARMADO</speaker>
            <line>Villain, thou shalt fast for thy offences ere thou</line>
            <line>be pardoned.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COSTARD</speaker>
            <line>Well, sir, I hope, when I do it, I shall do it on a</line>
            <line>full stomach.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON ADRIANO DE ARMADO</speaker>
            <line>Thou shalt be heavily punished.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COSTARD</speaker>
            <line>I am more bound to you than your fellows, for they</line>
            <line>are but lightly rewarded.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON ADRIANO DE ARMADO</speaker>
            <line>Take away this villain; shut him up.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOTH</speaker>
            <line>Come, you transgressing slave; away!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COSTARD</speaker>
            <line>Let me not be pent up, sir: I will fast, being loose.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOTH</speaker>
            <line>No, sir; that were fast and loose: thou shalt to prison.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COSTARD</speaker>
            <line>Well, if ever I do see the merry days of desolation</line>
            <line>that I have seen, some shall see.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOTH</speaker>
            <line>What shall some see?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COSTARD</speaker>
            <line>Nay, nothing, Master Moth, but what they look upon.</line>
            <line>It is not for prisoners to be too silent in their</line>
            <line>words; and therefore I will say nothing: I thank</line>
            <line>God I have as little patience as another man; and</line>
            <line>therefore I can be quiet.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt MOTH and COSTARD</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON ADRIANO DE ARMADO</speaker>
            <line>I do affect the very ground, which is base, where</line>
            <line>her shoe, which is baser, guided by her foot, which</line>
            <line>is basest, doth tread. I shall be forsworn, which</line>
            <line>is a great argument of falsehood, if I love. And</line>
            <line>how can that be true love which is falsely</line>
            <line>attempted? Love is a familiar; Love is a devil:</line>
            <line>there is no evil angel but Love. Yet was Samson so</line>
            <line>tempted, and he had an excellent strength; yet was</line>
            <line>Solomon so seduced, and he had a very good wit.</line>
            <line>Cupid's butt-shaft is too hard for Hercules' club;</line>
            <line>and therefore too much odds for a Spaniard's rapier.</line>
            <line>The first and second cause will not serve my turn;</line>
            <line>the passado he respects not, the duello he regards</line>
            <line>not: his disgrace is to be called boy; but his</line>
            <line>glory is to subdue men. Adieu, valour! rust rapier!</line>
            <line>be still, drum! for your manager is in love; yea,</line>
            <line>he loveth. Assist me, some extemporal god of rhyme,</line>
            <line>for I am sure I shall turn sonnet. Devise, wit;</line>
            <line>write, pen; for I am for whole volumes in folio.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>