<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:shakespear:dtd:act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-4">
   <title>ACT IV</title>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  The same.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter the PRINCESS, and her train, a Forester,
BOYET, ROSALINE, MARIA, and KATHARINE</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCESS</speaker>
            <line>Was that the king, that spurred his horse so hard</line>
            <line>Against the steep uprising of the hill?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOYET</speaker>
            <line>I know not; but I think it was not he.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCESS</speaker>
            <line>Whoe'er a' was, a' show'd a mounting mind.</line>
            <line>Well, lords, to-day we shall have our dispatch:</line>
            <line>On Saturday we will return to France.</line>
            <line>Then, forester, my friend, where is the bush</line>
            <line>That we must stand and play the murderer in?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Forester</speaker>
            <line>Hereby, upon the edge of yonder coppice;</line>
            <line>A stand where you may make the fairest shoot.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCESS</speaker>
            <line>I thank my beauty, I am fair that shoot,</line>
            <line>And thereupon thou speak'st the fairest shoot.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Forester</speaker>
            <line>Pardon me, madam, for I meant not so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCESS</speaker>
            <line>What, what? first praise me and again say no?</line>
            <line>O short-lived pride! Not fair? alack for woe!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Forester</speaker>
            <line>Yes, madam, fair.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCESS</speaker>
            <line>Nay, never paint me now:</line>
            <line>Where fair is not, praise cannot mend the brow.</line>
            <line>Here, good my glass, take this for telling true:</line>
            <line>Fair payment for foul words is more than due.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Forester</speaker>
            <line>Nothing but fair is that which you inherit.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCESS</speaker>
            <line>See see, my beauty will be saved by merit!</line>
            <line>O heresy in fair, fit for these days!</line>
            <line>A giving hand, though foul, shall have fair praise.</line>
            <line>But come, the bow: now mercy goes to kill,</line>
            <line>And shooting well is then accounted ill.</line>
            <line>Thus will I save my credit in the shoot:</line>
            <line>Not wounding, pity would not let me do't;</line>
            <line>If wounding, then it was to show my skill,</line>
            <line>That more for praise than purpose meant to kill.</line>
            <line>And out of question so it is sometimes,</line>
            <line>Glory grows guilty of detested crimes,</line>
            <line>When, for fame's sake, for praise, an outward part,</line>
            <line>We bend to that the working of the heart;</line>
            <line>As I for praise alone now seek to spill</line>
            <line>The poor deer's blood, that my heart means no ill.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOYET</speaker>
            <line>Do not curst wives hold that self-sovereignty</line>
            <line>Only for praise sake, when they strive to be</line>
            <line>Lords o'er their lords?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCESS</speaker>
            <line>Only for praise: and praise we may afford</line>
            <line>To any lady that subdues a lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOYET</speaker>
            <line>Here comes a member of the commonwealth.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter COSTARD</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COSTARD</speaker>
            <line>God dig-you-den all! Pray you, which is the head lady?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCESS</speaker>
            <line>Thou shalt know her, fellow, by the rest that have no heads.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COSTARD</speaker>
            <line>Which is the greatest lady, the highest?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCESS</speaker>
            <line>The thickest and the tallest.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COSTARD</speaker>
            <line>The thickest and the tallest! it is so; truth is truth.</line>
            <line>An your waist, mistress, were as slender as my wit,</line>
            <line>One o' these maids' girdles for your waist should be fit.</line>
            <line>Are not you the chief woman? you are the thickest here.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCESS</speaker>
            <line>What's your will, sir? what's your will?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COSTARD</speaker>
            <line>I have a letter from Monsieur Biron to one Lady Rosaline.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCESS</speaker>
            <line>O, thy letter, thy letter! he's a good friend of mine:</line>
            <line>Stand aside, good bearer. Boyet, you can carve;</line>
            <line>Break up this capon.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOYET</speaker>
            <line>I am bound to serve.</line>
            <line>This letter is mistook, it importeth none here;</line>
            <line>It is writ to Jaquenetta.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCESS</speaker>
            <line>We will read it, I swear.</line>
            <line>Break the neck of the wax, and every one give ear.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOYET</speaker>
            <line>'By heaven, that thou art fair, is most infallible;</line>
            <line>true, that thou art beauteous; truth itself, that</line>
            <line>thou art lovely. More fairer than fair, beautiful</line>
            <line>than beauteous, truer than truth itself, have</line>
            <line>commiseration on thy heroical vassal! The</line>
            <line>magnanimous and most illustrate king Cophetua set</line>
            <line>eye upon the pernicious and indubitate beggar</line>
            <line>Zenelophon; and he it was that might rightly say,</line>
            <line>Veni, vidi, vici; which to annothanize in the</line>
            <line>vulgar,--O base and obscure vulgar!--videlicet, He</line>
            <line>came, saw, and overcame: he came, one; saw two;</line>
            <line>overcame, three. Who came? the king: why did he</line>
            <line>come? to see: why did he see? to overcome: to</line>
            <line>whom came he? to the beggar: what saw he? the</line>
            <line>beggar: who overcame he? the beggar. The</line>
            <line>conclusion is victory: on whose side? the king's.</line>
            <line>The captive is enriched: on whose side? the</line>
            <line>beggar's. The catastrophe is a nuptial: on whose</line>
            <line>side? the king's: no, on both in one, or one in</line>
            <line>both. I am the king; for so stands the comparison:</line>
            <line>thou the beggar; for so witnesseth thy lowliness.</line>
            <line>Shall I command thy love? I may: shall I enforce</line>
            <line>thy love? I could: shall I entreat thy love? I</line>
            <line>will. What shalt thou exchange for rags? robes;</line>
            <line>for tittles? titles; for thyself? me. Thus,</line>
            <line>expecting thy reply, I profane my lips on thy foot,</line>
            <line>my eyes on thy picture. and my heart on thy every</line>
            <line>part. Thine, in the dearest design of industry,</line>
            <line>DON ADRIANO DE ARMADO.'</line>
            <line>Thus dost thou hear the Nemean lion roar</line>
            <line>'Gainst thee, thou lamb, that standest as his prey.</line>
            <line>Submissive fall his princely feet before,</line>
            <line>And he from forage will incline to play:</line>
            <line>But if thou strive, poor soul, what art thou then?</line>
            <line>Food for his rage, repasture for his den.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCESS</speaker>
            <line>What plume of feathers is he that indited this letter?</line>
            <line>What vane? what weathercock? did you ever hear better?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOYET</speaker>
            <line>I am much deceived but I remember the style.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCESS</speaker>
            <line>Else your memory is bad, going o'er it erewhile.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOYET</speaker>
            <line>This Armado is a Spaniard, that keeps here in court;</line>
            <line>A phantasime, a Monarcho, and one that makes sport</line>
            <line>To the prince and his bookmates.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCESS</speaker>
            <line>Thou fellow, a word:</line>
            <line>Who gave thee this letter?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COSTARD</speaker>
            <line>I told you; my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCESS</speaker>
            <line>To whom shouldst thou give it?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COSTARD</speaker>
            <line>From my lord to my lady.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCESS</speaker>
            <line>From which lord to which lady?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COSTARD</speaker>
            <line>From my lord Biron, a good master of mine,</line>
            <line>To a lady of France that he call'd Rosaline.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCESS</speaker>
            <line>Thou hast mistaken his letter. Come, lords, away.</line>
            <stagedir>To ROSALINE</stagedir>
            <line>Here, sweet, put up this: 'twill be thine another day.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt PRINCESS and train</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOYET</speaker>
            <line>Who is the suitor? who is the suitor?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALINE</speaker>
            <line>Shall I teach you to know?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOYET</speaker>
            <line>Ay, my continent of beauty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALINE</speaker>
            <line>Why, she that bears the bow.</line>
            <line>Finely put off!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOYET</speaker>
            <line>My lady goes to kill horns; but, if thou marry,</line>
            <line>Hang me by the neck, if horns that year miscarry.</line>
            <line>Finely put on!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALINE</speaker>
            <line>Well, then, I am the shooter.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOYET</speaker>
            <line>And who is your deer?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALINE</speaker>
            <line>If we choose by the horns, yourself come not near.</line>
            <line>Finely put on, indeed!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>You still wrangle with her, Boyet, and she strikes</line>
            <line>at the brow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOYET</speaker>
            <line>But she herself is hit lower: have I hit her now?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALINE</speaker>
            <line>Shall I come upon thee with an old saying, that was</line>
            <line>a man when King Pepin of France was a little boy, as</line>
            <line>touching the hit it?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOYET</speaker>
            <line>So I may answer thee with one as old, that was a</line>
            <line>woman when Queen Guinover of Britain was a little</line>
            <line>wench, as touching the hit it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSALINE</speaker>
            <line>Thou canst not hit it, hit it, hit it,</line>
            <line>Thou canst not hit it, my good man.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOYET</speaker>
            <line>An I cannot, cannot, cannot,</line>
            <line>An I cannot, another can.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt ROSALINE and KATHARINE</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COSTARD</speaker>
            <line>By my troth, most pleasant: how both did fit it!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>A mark marvellous well shot, for they both did hit it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOYET</speaker>
            <line>A mark! O, mark but that mark! A mark, says my lady!</line>
            <line>Let the mark have a prick in't, to mete at, if it may be.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>Wide o' the bow hand! i' faith, your hand is out.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COSTARD</speaker>
            <line>Indeed, a' must shoot nearer, or he'll ne'er hit the clout.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOYET</speaker>
            <line>An if my hand be out, then belike your hand is in.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COSTARD</speaker>
            <line>Then will she get the upshoot by cleaving the pin.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>Come, come, you talk greasily; your lips grow foul.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COSTARD</speaker>
            <line>She's too hard for you at pricks, sir: challenge her to bowl.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOYET</speaker>
            <line>I fear too much rubbing. Good night, my good owl.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt BOYET and MARIA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COSTARD</speaker>
            <line>By my soul, a swain! a most simple clown!</line>
            <line>Lord, Lord, how the ladies and I have put him down!</line>
            <line>O' my troth, most sweet jests! most incony</line>
            <line>vulgar wit!</line>
            <line>When it comes so smoothly off, so obscenely, as it</line>
            <line>were, so fit.</line>
            <line>Armado o' th' one side,--O, a most dainty man!</line>
            <line>To see him walk before a lady and to bear her fan!</line>
            <line>To see him kiss his hand! and how most sweetly a'</line>
            <line>will swear!</line>
            <line>And his page o' t' other side, that handful of wit!</line>
            <line>Ah, heavens, it is a most pathetical nit!</line>
            <line>Sola, sola!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Shout within</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Exit COSTARD, running</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  The same.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter HOLOFERNES, SIR NATHANIEL, and DULL</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR NATHANIEL</speaker>
            <line>Very reverend sport, truly; and done in the testimony</line>
            <line>of a good conscience.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOLOFERNES</speaker>
            <line>The deer was, as you know, sanguis, in blood; ripe</line>
            <line>as the pomewater, who now hangeth like a jewel in</line>
            <line>the ear of caelo, the sky, the welkin, the heaven;</line>
            <line>and anon falleth like a crab on the face of terra,</line>
            <line>the soil, the land, the earth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR NATHANIEL</speaker>
            <line>Truly, Master Holofernes, the epithets are sweetly</line>
            <line>varied, like a scholar at the least: but, sir, I</line>
            <line>assure ye, it was a buck of the first head.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOLOFERNES</speaker>
            <line>Sir Nathaniel, haud credo.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DULL</speaker>
            <line>'Twas not a haud credo; 'twas a pricket.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOLOFERNES</speaker>
            <line>Most barbarous intimation! yet a kind of</line>
            <line>insinuation, as it were, in via, in way, of</line>
            <line>explication; facere, as it were, replication, or</line>
            <line>rather, ostentare, to show, as it were, his</line>
            <line>inclination, after his undressed, unpolished,</line>
            <line>uneducated, unpruned, untrained, or rather,</line>
            <line>unlettered, or ratherest, unconfirmed fashion, to</line>
            <line>insert again my haud credo for a deer.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DULL</speaker>
            <line>I said the deer was not a haud credo; twas a pricket.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOLOFERNES</speaker>
            <line>Twice-sod simplicity, his coctus!</line>
            <line>O thou monster Ignorance, how deformed dost thou look!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR NATHANIEL</speaker>
            <line>Sir, he hath never fed of the dainties that are bred</line>
            <line>in a book; he hath not eat paper, as it were; he</line>
            <line>hath not drunk ink: his intellect is not</line>
            <line>replenished; he is only an animal, only sensible in</line>
            <line>the duller parts:</line>
            <line>And such barren plants are set before us, that we</line>
            <line>thankful should be,</line>
            <line>Which we of taste and feeling are, for those parts that</line>
            <line>do fructify in us more than he.</line>
            <line>For as it would ill become me to be vain, indiscreet, or a fool,</line>
            <line>So were there a patch set on learning, to see him in a school:</line>
            <line>But omne bene, say I; being of an old father's mind,</line>
            <line>Many can brook the weather that love not the wind.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DULL</speaker>
            <line>You two are book-men: can you tell me by your wit</line>
            <line>What was a month old at Cain's birth, that's not five</line>
            <line>weeks old as yet?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOLOFERNES</speaker>
            <line>Dictynna, goodman Dull; Dictynna, goodman Dull.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DULL</speaker>
            <line>What is Dictynna?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR NATHANIEL</speaker>
            <line>A title to Phoebe, to Luna, to the moon.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOLOFERNES</speaker>
            <line>The moon was a month old when Adam was no more,</line>
            <line>And raught not to five weeks when he came to</line>
            <line>five-score.</line>
            <line>The allusion holds in the exchange.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DULL</speaker>
            <line>'Tis true indeed; the collusion holds in the exchange.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOLOFERNES</speaker>
            <line>God comfort thy capacity! I say, the allusion holds</line>
            <line>in the exchange.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DULL</speaker>
            <line>And I say, the pollusion holds in the exchange; for</line>
            <line>the moon is never but a month old: and I say beside</line>
            <line>that, 'twas a pricket that the princess killed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOLOFERNES</speaker>
            <line>Sir Nathaniel, will you hear an extemporal epitaph</line>
            <line>on the death of the deer? And, to humour the</line>
            <line>ignorant, call I the deer the princess killed a pricket.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR NATHANIEL</speaker>
            <line>Perge, good Master Holofernes, perge; so it shall</line>
            <line>please you to abrogate scurrility.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOLOFERNES</speaker>
            <line>I will something affect the letter, for it argues facility.</line>
            <line>The preyful princess pierced and prick'd a pretty</line>
            <line>pleasing pricket;</line>
            <line>Some say a sore; but not a sore, till now made</line>
            <line>sore with shooting.</line>
            <line>The dogs did yell: put L to sore, then sorel jumps</line>
            <line>from thicket;</line>
            <line>Or pricket sore, or else sorel; the people fall a-hooting.</line>
            <line>If sore be sore, then L to sore makes fifty sores</line>
            <line>one sorel.</line>
            <line>Of one sore I an hundred make by adding but one more L.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR NATHANIEL</speaker>
            <line>A rare talent!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DULL</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  If a talent be a claw, look how he claws</line>
            <line>him with a talent.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOLOFERNES</speaker>
            <line>This is a gift that I have, simple, simple; a</line>
            <line>foolish extravagant spirit, full of forms, figures,</line>
            <line>shapes, objects, ideas, apprehensions, motions,</line>
            <line>revolutions: these are begot in the ventricle of</line>
            <line>memory, nourished in the womb of pia mater, and</line>
            <line>delivered upon the mellowing of occasion. But the</line>
            <line>gift is good in those in whom it is acute, and I am</line>
            <line>thankful for it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR NATHANIEL</speaker>
            <line>Sir, I praise the Lord for you; and so may my</line>
            <line>parishioners; for their sons are well tutored by</line>
            <line>you, and their daughters profit very greatly under</line>
            <line>you: you are a good member of the commonwealth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOLOFERNES</speaker>
            <line>Mehercle, if their sons be ingenuous, they shall</line>
            <line>want no instruction; if their daughters be capable,</line>
            <line>I will put it to them: but vir sapit qui pauca</line>
            <line>loquitur; a soul feminine saluteth us.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter JAQUENETTA and COSTARD</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JAQUENETTA</speaker>
            <line>God give you good morrow, master Parson.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOLOFERNES</speaker>
            <line>Master Parson, quasi pers-on. An if one should be</line>
            <line>pierced, which is the one?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COSTARD</speaker>
            <line>Marry, master schoolmaster, he that is likest to a hogshead.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOLOFERNES</speaker>
            <line>Piercing a hogshead! a good lustre of conceit in a</line>
            <line>tuft of earth; fire enough for a flint, pearl enough</line>
            <line>for a swine: 'tis pretty; it is well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JAQUENETTA</speaker>
            <line>Good master Parson, be so good as read me this</line>
            <line>letter: it was given me by Costard, and sent me</line>
            <line>from Don Armado: I beseech you, read it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOLOFERNES</speaker>
            <line>Fauste, precor gelida quando pecus omne sub umbra</line>
            <line>Ruminat,--and so forth. Ah, good old Mantuan! I</line>
            <line>may speak of thee as the traveller doth of Venice;</line>
            <line>Venetia, Venetia,</line>
            <line>Chi non ti vede non ti pretia.</line>
            <line>Old Mantuan, old Mantuan! who understandeth thee</line>
            <line>not, loves thee not. Ut, re, sol, la, mi, fa.</line>
            <line>Under pardon, sir, what are the contents? or rather,</line>
            <line>as Horace says in his--What, my soul, verses?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR NATHANIEL</speaker>
            <line>Ay, sir, and very learned.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOLOFERNES</speaker>
            <line>Let me hear a staff, a stanze, a verse; lege, domine.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR NATHANIEL</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>
            </line>
            <line>If love make me forsworn, how shall I swear to love?</line>
            <line>Ah, never faith could hold, if not to beauty vow'd!</line>
            <line>Though to myself forsworn, to thee I'll faithful prove:</line>
            <line>Those thoughts to me were oaks, to thee like</line>
            <line>osiers bow'd.</line>
            <line>Study his bias leaves and makes his book thine eyes,</line>
            <line>Where all those pleasures live that art would</line>
            <line>comprehend:</line>
            <line>If knowledge be the mark, to know thee shall suffice;</line>
            <line>Well learned is that tongue that well can thee commend,</line>
            <line>All ignorant that soul that sees thee without wonder;</line>
            <line>Which is to me some praise that I thy parts admire:</line>
            <line>Thy eye Jove's lightning bears, thy voice his dreadful thunder,</line>
            <line>Which not to anger bent, is music and sweet fire.</line>
            <line>Celestial as thou art, O, pardon, love, this wrong,</line>
            <line>That sings heaven's praise with such an earthly tongue.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOLOFERNES</speaker>
            <line>You find not the apostraphas, and so miss the</line>
            <line>accent: let me supervise the canzonet. Here are</line>
            <line>only numbers ratified; but, for the elegancy,</line>
            <line>facility, and golden cadence of poesy, caret.</line>
            <line>Ovidius Naso was the man: and why, indeed, Naso,</line>
            <line>but for smelling out the odouriferous flowers of</line>
            <line>fancy, the jerks of invention? Imitari is nothing:</line>
            <line>so doth the hound his master, the ape his keeper,</line>
            <line>the tired horse his rider. But, damosella virgin,</line>
            <line>was this directed to you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JAQUENETTA</speaker>
            <line>Ay, sir, from one Monsieur Biron, one of the strange</line>
            <line>queen's lords.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOLOFERNES</speaker>
            <line>I will overglance the superscript: 'To the</line>
            <line>snow-white hand of the most beauteous Lady</line>
            <line>Rosaline.' I will look again on the intellect of</line>
            <line>the letter, for the nomination of the party writing</line>
            <line>to the person written unto: 'Your ladyship's in all</line>
            <line>desired employment, BIRON.' Sir Nathaniel, this</line>
            <line>Biron is one of the votaries with the king; and here</line>
            <line>he hath framed a letter to a sequent of the stranger</line>
            <line>queen's, which accidentally, or by the way of</line>
            <line>progression, hath miscarried. Trip and go, my</line>
            <line>sweet; deliver this paper into the royal hand of the</line>
            <line>king: it may concern much. Stay not thy</line>
            <line>compliment; I forgive thy duty; adieu.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JAQUENETTA</speaker>
            <line>Good Costard, go with me. Sir, God save your life!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COSTARD</speaker>
            <line>Have with thee, my girl.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt COSTARD and JAQUENETTA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR NATHANIEL</speaker>
            <line>Sir, you have done this in the fear of God, very</line>
            <line>religiously; and, as a certain father saith,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOLOFERNES</speaker>
            <line>Sir tell me not of the father; I do fear colourable</line>
            <line>colours. But to return to the verses: did they</line>
            <line>please you, Sir Nathaniel?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR NATHANIEL</speaker>
            <line>Marvellous well for the pen.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOLOFERNES</speaker>
            <line>I do dine to-day at the father's of a certain pupil</line>
            <line>of mine; where, if, before repast, it shall please</line>
            <line>you to gratify the table with a grace, I will, on my</line>
            <line>privilege I have with the parents of the foresaid</line>
            <line>child or pupil, undertake your ben venuto; where I</line>
            <line>will prove those verses to be very unlearned,</line>
            <line>neither savouring of poetry, wit, nor invention: I</line>
            <line>beseech your society.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR NATHANIEL</speaker>
            <line>And thank you too; for society, saith the text, is</line>
            <line>the happiness of life.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOLOFERNES</speaker>
            <line>And, certes, the text most infallibly concludes it.</line>
            <stagedir>To DULL</stagedir>
            <line>Sir, I do invite you too; you shall not</line>
            <line>say me nay: pauca verba. Away! the gentles are at</line>
            <line>their game, and we will to our recreation.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  The same.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter BIRON, with a paper</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>The king he is hunting the deer; I am coursing</line>
            <line>myself: they have pitched a toil; I am toiling in</line>
            <line>a pitch,--pitch that defiles: defile! a foul</line>
            <line>word. Well, set thee down, sorrow! for so they say</line>
            <line>the fool said, and so say I, and I the fool: well</line>
            <line>proved, wit! By the Lord, this love is as mad as</line>
            <line>Ajax: it kills sheep; it kills me, I a sheep:</line>
            <line>well proved again o' my side! I will not love: if</line>
            <line>I do, hang me; i' faith, I will not. O, but her</line>
            <line>eye,--by this light, but for her eye, I would not</line>
            <line>love her; yes, for her two eyes. Well, I do nothing</line>
            <line>in the world but lie, and lie in my throat. By</line>
            <line>heaven, I do love: and it hath taught me to rhyme</line>
            <line>and to be melancholy; and here is part of my rhyme,</line>
            <line>and here my melancholy. Well, she hath one o' my</line>
            <line>sonnets already: the clown bore it, the fool sent</line>
            <line>it, and the lady hath it: sweet clown, sweeter</line>
            <line>fool, sweetest lady! By the world, I would not care</line>
            <line>a pin, if the other three were in. Here comes one</line>
            <line>with a paper: God give him grace to groan!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Stands aside</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Enter FERDINAND, with a paper</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>Ay me!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  Shot, by heaven! Proceed, sweet Cupid:</line>
            <line>thou hast thumped him with thy bird-bolt under the</line>
            <line>left pap. In faith, secrets!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>
            </line>
            <line>So sweet a kiss the golden sun gives not</line>
            <line>To those fresh morning drops upon the rose,</line>
            <line>As thy eye-beams, when their fresh rays have smote</line>
            <line>The night of dew that on my cheeks down flows:</line>
            <line>Nor shines the silver moon one half so bright</line>
            <line>Through the transparent bosom of the deep,</line>
            <line>As doth thy face through tears of mine give light;</line>
            <line>Thou shinest in every tear that I do weep:</line>
            <line>No drop but as a coach doth carry thee;</line>
            <line>So ridest thou triumphing in my woe.</line>
            <line>Do but behold the tears that swell in me,</line>
            <line>And they thy glory through my grief will show:</line>
            <line>But do not love thyself; then thou wilt keep</line>
            <line>My tears for glasses, and still make me weep.</line>
            <line>O queen of queens! how far dost thou excel,</line>
            <line>No thought can think, nor tongue of mortal tell.</line>
            <line>How shall she know my griefs? I'll drop the paper:</line>
            <line>Sweet leaves, shade folly. Who is he comes here?</line>
            <stagedir>Steps aside</stagedir>
            <line>What, Longaville! and reading! listen, ear.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>Now, in thy likeness, one more fool appear!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter LONGAVILLE, with a paper</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LONGAVILLE</speaker>
            <line>Ay me, I am forsworn!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>Why, he comes in like a perjure, wearing papers.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>In love, I hope: sweet fellowship in shame!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>One drunkard loves another of the name.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LONGAVILLE</speaker>
            <line>Am I the first that have been perjured so?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>I could put thee in comfort. Not by two that I know:</line>
            <line>Thou makest the triumviry, the corner-cap of society,</line>
            <line>The shape of Love's Tyburn that hangs up simplicity.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LONGAVILLE</speaker>
            <line>I fear these stubborn lines lack power to move:</line>
            <line>O sweet Maria, empress of my love!</line>
            <line>These numbers will I tear, and write in prose.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>O, rhymes are guards on wanton Cupid's hose:</line>
            <line>Disfigure not his slop.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LONGAVILLE</speaker>
            <line>This same shall go.</line>
            <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>
            <line>Did not the heavenly rhetoric of thine eye,</line>
            <line>'Gainst whom the world cannot hold argument,</line>
            <line>Persuade my heart to this false perjury?</line>
            <line>Vows for thee broke deserve not punishment.</line>
            <line>A woman I forswore; but I will prove,</line>
            <line>Thou being a goddess, I forswore not thee:</line>
            <line>My vow was earthly, thou a heavenly love;</line>
            <line>Thy grace being gain'd cures all disgrace in me.</line>
            <line>Vows are but breath, and breath a vapour is:</line>
            <line>Then thou, fair sun, which on my earth dost shine,</line>
            <line>Exhalest this vapour-vow; in thee it is:</line>
            <line>If broken then, it is no fault of mine:</line>
            <line>If by me broke, what fool is not so wise</line>
            <line>To lose an oath to win a paradise?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>This is the liver-vein, which makes flesh a deity,</line>
            <line>A green goose a goddess: pure, pure idolatry.</line>
            <line>God amend us, God amend! we are much out o' the way.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LONGAVILLE</speaker>
            <line>By whom shall I send this?--Company! stay.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Steps aside</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>All hid, all hid; an old infant play.</line>
            <line>Like a demigod here sit I in the sky.</line>
            <line>And wretched fools' secrets heedfully o'ereye.</line>
            <line>More sacks to the mill! O heavens, I have my wish!</line>
            <stagedir>Enter DUMAIN, with a paper</stagedir>
            <line>Dumain transform'd! four woodcocks in a dish!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUMAIN</speaker>
            <line>O most divine Kate!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>O most profane coxcomb!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUMAIN</speaker>
            <line>By heaven, the wonder in a mortal eye!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>By earth, she is not, corporal, there you lie.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUMAIN</speaker>
            <line>Her amber hair for foul hath amber quoted.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>An amber-colour'd raven was well noted.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUMAIN</speaker>
            <line>As upright as the cedar.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>Stoop, I say;</line>
            <line>Her shoulder is with child.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUMAIN</speaker>
            <line>As fair as day.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>Ay, as some days; but then no sun must shine.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUMAIN</speaker>
            <line>O that I had my wish!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LONGAVILLE</speaker>
            <line>And I had mine!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>And I mine too, good Lord!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>Amen, so I had mine: is not that a good word?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUMAIN</speaker>
            <line>I would forget her; but a fever she</line>
            <line>Reigns in my blood and will remember'd be.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>A fever in your blood! why, then incision</line>
            <line>Would let her out in saucers: sweet misprision!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUMAIN</speaker>
            <line>Once more I'll read the ode that I have writ.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>Once more I'll mark how love can vary wit.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUMAIN</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>
            </line>
            <line>On a day--alack the day!--</line>
            <line>Love, whose month is ever May,</line>
            <line>Spied a blossom passing fair</line>
            <line>Playing in the wanton air:</line>
            <line>Through the velvet leaves the wind,</line>
            <line>All unseen, can passage find;</line>
            <line>That the lover, sick to death,</line>
            <line>Wish himself the heaven's breath.</line>
            <line>Air, quoth he, thy cheeks may blow;</line>
            <line>Air, would I might triumph so!</line>
            <line>But, alack, my hand is sworn</line>
            <line>Ne'er to pluck thee from thy thorn;</line>
            <line>Vow, alack, for youth unmeet,</line>
            <line>Youth so apt to pluck a sweet!</line>
            <line>Do not call it sin in me,</line>
            <line>That I am forsworn for thee;</line>
            <line>Thou for whom Jove would swear</line>
            <line>Juno but an Ethiope were;</line>
            <line>And deny himself for Jove,</line>
            <line>Turning mortal for thy love.</line>
            <line>This will I send, and something else more plain,</line>
            <line>That shall express my true love's fasting pain.</line>
            <line>O, would the king, Biron, and Longaville,</line>
            <line>Were lovers too! Ill, to example ill,</line>
            <line>Would from my forehead wipe a perjured note;</line>
            <line>For none offend where all alike do dote.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LONGAVILLE</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Advancing</stagedir>  Dumain, thy love is far from charity.</line>
            <line>You may look pale, but I should blush, I know,</line>
            <line>To be o'erheard and taken napping so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Advancing</stagedir>  Come, sir, you blush; as his your case is such;</line>
            <line>You chide at him, offending twice as much;</line>
            <line>You do not love Maria; Longaville</line>
            <line>Did never sonnet for her sake compile,</line>
            <line>Nor never lay his wreathed arms athwart</line>
            <line>His loving bosom to keep down his heart.</line>
            <line>I have been closely shrouded in this bush</line>
            <line>And mark'd you both and for you both did blush:</line>
            <line>I heard your guilty rhymes, observed your fashion,</line>
            <line>Saw sighs reek from you, noted well your passion:</line>
            <line>Ay me! says one; O Jove! the other cries;</line>
            <line>One, her hairs were gold, crystal the other's eyes:</line>
            <stagedir>To LONGAVILLE</stagedir>
            <line>You would for paradise break faith, and troth;</line>
            <stagedir>To DUMAIN</stagedir>
            <line>And Jove, for your love, would infringe an oath.</line>
            <line>What will Biron say when that he shall hear</line>
            <line>Faith so infringed, which such zeal did swear?</line>
            <line>How will he scorn! how will he spend his wit!</line>
            <line>How will he triumph, leap and laugh at it!</line>
            <line>For all the wealth that ever I did see,</line>
            <line>I would not have him know so much by me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>Now step I forth to whip hypocrisy.</line>
            <stagedir>Advancing</stagedir>
            <line>Ah, good my liege, I pray thee, pardon me!</line>
            <line>Good heart, what grace hast thou, thus to reprove</line>
            <line>These worms for loving, that art most in love?</line>
            <line>Your eyes do make no coaches; in your tears</line>
            <line>There is no certain princess that appears;</line>
            <line>You'll not be perjured, 'tis a hateful thing;</line>
            <line>Tush, none but minstrels like of sonneting!</line>
            <line>But are you not ashamed? nay, are you not,</line>
            <line>All three of you, to be thus much o'ershot?</line>
            <line>You found his mote; the king your mote did see;</line>
            <line>But I a beam do find in each of three.</line>
            <line>O, what a scene of foolery have I seen,</line>
            <line>Of sighs, of groans, of sorrow and of teen!</line>
            <line>O me, with what strict patience have I sat,</line>
            <line>To see a king transformed to a gnat!</line>
            <line>To see great Hercules whipping a gig,</line>
            <line>And profound Solomon to tune a jig,</line>
            <line>And Nestor play at push-pin with the boys,</line>
            <line>And critic Timon laugh at idle toys!</line>
            <line>Where lies thy grief, O, tell me, good Dumain?</line>
            <line>And gentle Longaville, where lies thy pain?</line>
            <line>And where my liege's? all about the breast:</line>
            <line>A caudle, ho!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>Too bitter is thy jest.</line>
            <line>Are we betray'd thus to thy over-view?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>Not you to me, but I betray'd by you:</line>
            <line>I, that am honest; I, that hold it sin</line>
            <line>To break the vow I am engaged in;</line>
            <line>I am betray'd, by keeping company</line>
            <line>With men like men of inconstancy.</line>
            <line>When shall you see me write a thing in rhyme?</line>
            <line>Or groan for love? or spend a minute's time</line>
            <line>In pruning me? When shall you hear that I</line>
            <line>Will praise a hand, a foot, a face, an eye,</line>
            <line>A gait, a state, a brow, a breast, a waist,</line>
            <line>A leg, a limb?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>Soft! whither away so fast?</line>
            <line>A true man or a thief that gallops so?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>I post from love: good lover, let me go.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter JAQUENETTA and COSTARD</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JAQUENETTA</speaker>
            <line>God bless the king!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>What present hast thou there?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COSTARD</speaker>
            <line>Some certain treason.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>What makes treason here?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COSTARD</speaker>
            <line>Nay, it makes nothing, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>If it mar nothing neither,</line>
            <line>The treason and you go in peace away together.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JAQUENETTA</speaker>
            <line>I beseech your grace, let this letter be read:</line>
            <line>Our parson misdoubts it; 'twas treason, he said.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>Biron, read it over.</line>
            <stagedir>Giving him the paper</stagedir>
            <line>Where hadst thou it?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JAQUENETTA</speaker>
            <line>Of Costard.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>Where hadst thou it?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COSTARD</speaker>
            <line>Of Dun Adramadio, Dun Adramadio.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>BIRON tears the letter</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>How now! what is in you? why dost thou tear it?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>A toy, my liege, a toy: your grace needs not fear it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LONGAVILLE</speaker>
            <line>It did move him to passion, and therefore let's hear it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUMAIN</speaker>
            <line>It is Biron's writing, and here is his name.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Gathering up the pieces</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>To COSTARD</stagedir>  Ah, you whoreson loggerhead! you were</line>
            <line>born to do me shame.</line>
            <line>Guilty, my lord, guilty! I confess, I confess.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>What?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>That you three fools lack'd me fool to make up the mess:</line>
            <line>He, he, and you, and you, my liege, and I,</line>
            <line>Are pick-purses in love, and we deserve to die.</line>
            <line>O, dismiss this audience, and I shall tell you more.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUMAIN</speaker>
            <line>Now the number is even.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>True, true; we are four.</line>
            <line>Will these turtles be gone?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>Hence, sirs; away!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COSTARD</speaker>
            <line>Walk aside the true folk, and let the traitors stay.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt COSTARD and JAQUENETTA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>Sweet lords, sweet lovers, O, let us embrace!</line>
            <line>As true we are as flesh and blood can be:</line>
            <line>The sea will ebb and flow, heaven show his face;</line>
            <line>Young blood doth not obey an old decree:</line>
            <line>We cannot cross the cause why we were born;</line>
            <line>Therefore of all hands must we be forsworn.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>What, did these rent lines show some love of thine?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>Did they, quoth you? Who sees the heavenly Rosaline,</line>
            <line>That, like a rude and savage man of Inde,</line>
            <line>At the first opening of the gorgeous east,</line>
            <line>Bows not his vassal head and strucken blind</line>
            <line>Kisses the base ground with obedient breast?</line>
            <line>What peremptory eagle-sighted eye</line>
            <line>Dares look upon the heaven of her brow,</line>
            <line>That is not blinded by her majesty?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>What zeal, what fury hath inspired thee now?</line>
            <line>My love, her mistress, is a gracious moon;</line>
            <line>She an attending star, scarce seen a light.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>My eyes are then no eyes, nor I Biron:</line>
            <line>O, but for my love, day would turn to night!</line>
            <line>Of all complexions the cull'd sovereignty</line>
            <line>Do meet, as at a fair, in her fair cheek,</line>
            <line>Where several worthies make one dignity,</line>
            <line>Where nothing wants that want itself doth seek.</line>
            <line>Lend me the flourish of all gentle tongues,--</line>
            <line>Fie, painted rhetoric! O, she needs it not:</line>
            <line>To things of sale a seller's praise belongs,</line>
            <line>She passes praise; then praise too short doth blot.</line>
            <line>A wither'd hermit, five-score winters worn,</line>
            <line>Might shake off fifty, looking in her eye:</line>
            <line>Beauty doth varnish age, as if new-born,</line>
            <line>And gives the crutch the cradle's infancy:</line>
            <line>O, 'tis the sun that maketh all things shine.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>By heaven, thy love is black as ebony.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>Is ebony like her? O wood divine!</line>
            <line>A wife of such wood were felicity.</line>
            <line>O, who can give an oath? where is a book?</line>
            <line>That I may swear beauty doth beauty lack,</line>
            <line>If that she learn not of her eye to look:</line>
            <line>No face is fair that is not full so black.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>O paradox! Black is the badge of hell,</line>
            <line>The hue of dungeons and the suit of night;</line>
            <line>And beauty's crest becomes the heavens well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>Devils soonest tempt, resembling spirits of light.</line>
            <line>O, if in black my lady's brows be deck'd,</line>
            <line>It mourns that painting and usurping hair</line>
            <line>Should ravish doters with a false aspect;</line>
            <line>And therefore is she born to make black fair.</line>
            <line>Her favour turns the fashion of the days,</line>
            <line>For native blood is counted painting now;</line>
            <line>And therefore red, that would avoid dispraise,</line>
            <line>Paints itself black, to imitate her brow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUMAIN</speaker>
            <line>To look like her are chimney-sweepers black.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LONGAVILLE</speaker>
            <line>And since her time are colliers counted bright.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>And Ethiopes of their sweet complexion crack.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUMAIN</speaker>
            <line>Dark needs no candles now, for dark is light.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>Your mistresses dare never come in rain,</line>
            <line>For fear their colours should be wash'd away.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>'Twere good, yours did; for, sir, to tell you plain,</line>
            <line>I'll find a fairer face not wash'd to-day.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>I'll prove her fair, or talk till doomsday here.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>No devil will fright thee then so much as she.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUMAIN</speaker>
            <line>I never knew man hold vile stuff so dear.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LONGAVILLE</speaker>
            <line>Look, here's thy love: my foot and her face see.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>O, if the streets were paved with thine eyes,</line>
            <line>Her feet were much too dainty for such tread!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUMAIN</speaker>
            <line>O, vile! then, as she goes, what upward lies</line>
            <line>The street should see as she walk'd overhead.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>But what of this? are we not all in love?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>Nothing so sure; and thereby all forsworn.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>Then leave this chat; and, good Biron, now prove</line>
            <line>Our loving lawful, and our faith not torn.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUMAIN</speaker>
            <line>Ay, marry, there; some flattery for this evil.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LONGAVILLE</speaker>
            <line>O, some authority how to proceed;</line>
            <line>Some tricks, some quillets, how to cheat the devil.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUMAIN</speaker>
            <line>Some salve for perjury.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>'Tis more than need.</line>
            <line>Have at you, then, affection's men at arms.</line>
            <line>Consider what you first did swear unto,</line>
            <line>To fast, to study, and to see no woman;</line>
            <line>Flat treason 'gainst the kingly state of youth.</line>
            <line>Say, can you fast? your stomachs are too young;</line>
            <line>And abstinence engenders maladies.</line>
            <line>And where that you have vow'd to study, lords,</line>
            <line>In that each of you have forsworn his book,</line>
            <line>Can you still dream and pore and thereon look?</line>
            <line>For when would you, my lord, or you, or you,</line>
            <line>Have found the ground of study's excellence</line>
            <line>Without the beauty of a woman's face?</line>
            <stagedir>From women's eyes this doctrine I derive;
They are the ground, the books, the academes
From whence doth spring the true Promethean fire</stagedir>
            <line>Why, universal plodding poisons up</line>
            <line>The nimble spirits in the arteries,</line>
            <line>As motion and long-during action tires</line>
            <line>The sinewy vigour of the traveller.</line>
            <line>Now, for not looking on a woman's face,</line>
            <line>You have in that forsworn the use of eyes</line>
            <line>And study too, the causer of your vow;</line>
            <line>For where is any author in the world</line>
            <line>Teaches such beauty as a woman's eye?</line>
            <line>Learning is but an adjunct to ourself</line>
            <line>And where we are our learning likewise is:</line>
            <line>Then when ourselves we see in ladies' eyes,</line>
            <line>Do we not likewise see our learning there?</line>
            <line>O, we have made a vow to study, lords,</line>
            <line>And in that vow we have forsworn our books.</line>
            <line>For when would you, my liege, or you, or you,</line>
            <line>In leaden contemplation have found out</line>
            <line>Such fiery numbers as the prompting eyes</line>
            <line>Of beauty's tutors have enrich'd you with?</line>
            <line>Other slow arts entirely keep the brain;</line>
            <line>And therefore, finding barren practisers,</line>
            <line>Scarce show a harvest of their heavy toil:</line>
            <line>But love, first learned in a lady's eyes,</line>
            <line>Lives not alone immured in the brain;</line>
            <line>But, with the motion of all elements,</line>
            <line>Courses as swift as thought in every power,</line>
            <line>And gives to every power a double power,</line>
            <line>Above their functions and their offices.</line>
            <line>It adds a precious seeing to the eye;</line>
            <line>A lover's eyes will gaze an eagle blind;</line>
            <line>A lover's ear will hear the lowest sound,</line>
            <line>When the suspicious head of theft is stopp'd:</line>
            <line>Love's feeling is more soft and sensible</line>
            <line>Than are the tender horns of cockl'd snails;</line>
            <line>Love's tongue proves dainty Bacchus gross in taste:</line>
            <line>For valour, is not Love a Hercules,</line>
            <line>Still climbing trees in the Hesperides?</line>
            <line>Subtle as Sphinx; as sweet and musical</line>
            <line>As bright Apollo's lute, strung with his hair:</line>
            <line>And when Love speaks, the voice of all the gods</line>
            <line>Makes heaven drowsy with the harmony.</line>
            <line>Never durst poet touch a pen to write</line>
            <line>Until his ink were temper'd with Love's sighs;</line>
            <line>O, then his lines would ravish savage ears</line>
            <line>And plant in tyrants mild humility.</line>
            <line>From women's eyes this doctrine I derive:</line>
            <line>They sparkle still the right Promethean fire;</line>
            <line>They are the books, the arts, the academes,</line>
            <line>That show, contain and nourish all the world:</line>
            <line>Else none at all in ought proves excellent.</line>
            <line>Then fools you were these women to forswear,</line>
            <line>Or keeping what is sworn, you will prove fools.</line>
            <line>For wisdom's sake, a word that all men love,</line>
            <line>Or for love's sake, a word that loves all men,</line>
            <line>Or for men's sake, the authors of these women,</line>
            <line>Or women's sake, by whom we men are men,</line>
            <line>Let us once lose our oaths to find ourselves,</line>
            <line>Or else we lose ourselves to keep our oaths.</line>
            <line>It is religion to be thus forsworn,</line>
            <line>For charity itself fulfills the law,</line>
            <line>And who can sever love from charity?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>Saint Cupid, then! and, soldiers, to the field!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>Advance your standards, and upon them, lords;</line>
            <line>Pell-mell, down with them! but be first advised,</line>
            <line>In conflict that you get the sun of them.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LONGAVILLE</speaker>
            <line>Now to plain-dealing; lay these glozes by:</line>
            <line>Shall we resolve to woo these girls of France?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>And win them too: therefore let us devise</line>
            <line>Some entertainment for them in their tents.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>First, from the park let us conduct them thither;</line>
            <line>Then homeward every man attach the hand</line>
            <line>Of his fair mistress: in the afternoon</line>
            <line>We will with some strange pastime solace them,</line>
            <line>Such as the shortness of the time can shape;</line>
            <line>For revels, dances, masks and merry hours</line>
            <line>Forerun fair Love, strewing her way with flowers.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>Away, away! no time shall be omitted</line>
            <line>That will betime, and may by us be fitted.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIRON</speaker>
            <line>Allons! allons! Sow'd cockle reap'd no corn;</line>
            <line>And justice always whirls in equal measure:</line>
            <line>Light wenches may prove plagues to men forsworn;</line>
            <line>If so, our copper buys no better treasure.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>