<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:shakespear:dtd:act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-5">
   <title>ACT V</title>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  Rome. A public place.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter MENENIUS, COMINIUS, SICINIUS, BRUTUS,
and others</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>No, I'll not go: you hear what he hath said</line>
            <line>Which was sometime his general; who loved him</line>
            <line>In a most dear particular. He call'd me father:</line>
            <line>But what o' that? Go, you that banish'd him;</line>
            <line>A mile before his tent fall down, and knee</line>
            <line>The way into his mercy: nay, if he coy'd</line>
            <line>To hear Cominius speak, I'll keep at home.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COMINIUS</speaker>
            <line>He would not seem to know me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>Do you hear?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COMINIUS</speaker>
            <line>Yet one time he did call me by my name:</line>
            <line>I urged our old acquaintance, and the drops</line>
            <line>That we have bled together. Coriolanus</line>
            <line>He would not answer to: forbad all names;</line>
            <line>He was a kind of nothing, titleless,</line>
            <line>Till he had forged himself a name o' the fire</line>
            <line>Of burning Rome.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>Why, so: you have made good work!</line>
            <line>A pair of tribunes that have rack'd for Rome,</line>
            <line>To make coals cheap,--a noble memory!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COMINIUS</speaker>
            <line>I minded him how royal 'twas to pardon</line>
            <line>When it was less expected: he replied,</line>
            <line>It was a bare petition of a state</line>
            <line>To one whom they had punish'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>Very well:</line>
            <line>Could he say less?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COMINIUS</speaker>
            <line>I offer'd to awaken his regard</line>
            <line>For's private friends: his answer to me was,</line>
            <line>He could not stay to pick them in a pile</line>
            <line>Of noisome musty chaff: he said 'twas folly,</line>
            <line>For one poor grain or two, to leave unburnt,</line>
            <line>And still to nose the offence.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>For one poor grain or two!</line>
            <line>I am one of those; his mother, wife, his child,</line>
            <line>And this brave fellow too, we are the grains:</line>
            <line>You are the musty chaff; and you are smelt</line>
            <line>Above the moon: we must be burnt for you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SICINIUS</speaker>
            <line>Nay, pray, be patient: if you refuse your aid</line>
            <line>In this so never-needed help, yet do not</line>
            <line>Upbraid's with our distress. But, sure, if you</line>
            <line>Would be your country's pleader, your good tongue,</line>
            <line>More than the instant army we can make,</line>
            <line>Might stop our countryman.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>No, I'll not meddle.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SICINIUS</speaker>
            <line>Pray you, go to him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>What should I do?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>Only make trial what your love can do</line>
            <line>For Rome, towards Marcius.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>Well, and say that Marcius</line>
            <line>Return me, as Cominius is return'd,</line>
            <line>Unheard; what then?</line>
            <line>But as a discontented friend, grief-shot</line>
            <line>With his unkindness? say't be so?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SICINIUS</speaker>
            <line>Yet your good will</line>
            <line>must have that thanks from Rome, after the measure</line>
            <line>As you intended well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>I'll undertake 't:</line>
            <line>I think he'll hear me. Yet, to bite his lip</line>
            <line>And hum at good Cominius, much unhearts me.</line>
            <line>He was not taken well; he had not dined:</line>
            <line>The veins unfill'd, our blood is cold, and then</line>
            <line>We pout upon the morning, are unapt</line>
            <line>To give or to forgive; but when we have stuff'd</line>
            <line>These and these conveyances of our blood</line>
            <line>With wine and feeding, we have suppler souls</line>
            <line>Than in our priest-like fasts: therefore I'll watch him</line>
            <line>Till he be dieted to my request,</line>
            <line>And then I'll set upon him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>You know the very road into his kindness,</line>
            <line>And cannot lose your way.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>Good faith, I'll prove him,</line>
            <line>Speed how it will. I shall ere long have knowledge</line>
            <line>Of my success.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COMINIUS</speaker>
            <line>He'll never hear him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SICINIUS</speaker>
            <line>Not?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COMINIUS</speaker>
            <line>I tell you, he does sit in gold, his eye</line>
            <line>Red as 'twould burn Rome; and his injury</line>
            <line>The gaoler to his pity. I kneel'd before him;</line>
            <line>'Twas very faintly he said 'Rise;' dismiss'd me</line>
            <line>Thus, with his speechless hand: what he would do,</line>
            <line>He sent in writing after me; what he would not,</line>
            <line>Bound with an oath to yield to his conditions:</line>
            <line>So that all hope is vain.</line>
            <line>Unless his noble mother, and his wife;</line>
            <line>Who, as I hear, mean to solicit him</line>
            <line>For mercy to his country. Therefore, let's hence,</line>
            <line>And with our fair entreaties haste them on.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  Entrance of the Volscian camp before Rome. Two Sentinels on guard.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter to them, MENENIUS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>Stay: whence are you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Senator</speaker>
            <line>Stand, and go back.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>You guard like men; 'tis well: but, by your leave,</line>
            <line>I am an officer of state, and come</line>
            <line>To speak with Coriolanus.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>From whence?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>From Rome.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>You may not pass, you must return: our general</line>
            <line>Will no more hear from thence.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Senator</speaker>
            <line>You'll see your Rome embraced with fire before</line>
            <line>You'll speak with Coriolanus.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>Good my friends,</line>
            <line>If you have heard your general talk of Rome,</line>
            <line>And of his friends there, it is lots to blanks,</line>
            <line>My name hath touch'd your ears it is Menenius.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>Be it so; go back: the virtue of your name</line>
            <line>Is not here passable.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>I tell thee, fellow,</line>
            <line>The general is my lover: I have been</line>
            <line>The book of his good acts, whence men have read</line>
            <line>His name unparallel'd, haply amplified;</line>
            <line>For I have ever verified my friends,</line>
            <line>Of whom he's chief, with all the size that verity</line>
            <line>Would without lapsing suffer: nay, sometimes,</line>
            <line>Like to a bowl upon a subtle ground,</line>
            <line>I have tumbled past the throw; and in his praise</line>
            <line>Have almost stamp'd the leasing: therefore, fellow,</line>
            <line>I must have leave to pass.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>Faith, sir, if you had told as many lies in his</line>
            <line>behalf as you have uttered words in your own, you</line>
            <line>should not pass here; no, though it were as virtuous</line>
            <line>to lie as to live chastely. Therefore, go back.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>Prithee, fellow, remember my name is Menenius,</line>
            <line>always factionary on the party of your general.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Senator</speaker>
            <line>Howsoever you have been his liar, as you say you</line>
            <line>have, I am one that, telling true under him, must</line>
            <line>say, you cannot pass. Therefore, go back.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>Has he dined, canst thou tell? for I would not</line>
            <line>speak with him till after dinner.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>You are a Roman, are you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>I am, as thy general is.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>Then you should hate Rome, as he does. Can you,</line>
            <line>when you have pushed out your gates the very</line>
            <line>defender of them, and, in a violent popular</line>
            <line>ignorance, given your enemy your shield, think to</line>
            <line>front his revenges with the easy groans of old</line>
            <line>women, the virginal palms of your daughters, or with</line>
            <line>the palsied intercession of such a decayed dotant as</line>
            <line>you seem to be? Can you think to blow out the</line>
            <line>intended fire your city is ready to flame in, with</line>
            <line>such weak breath as this? No, you are deceived;</line>
            <line>therefore, back to Rome, and prepare for your</line>
            <line>execution: you are condemned, our general has sworn</line>
            <line>you out of reprieve and pardon.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>Sirrah, if thy captain knew I were here, he would</line>
            <line>use me with estimation.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Senator</speaker>
            <line>Come, my captain knows you not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>I mean, thy general.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>My general cares not for you. Back, I say, go; lest</line>
            <line>I let forth your half-pint of blood; back,--that's</line>
            <line>the utmost of your having: back.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>Nay, but, fellow, fellow,--</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter CORIOLANUS and AUFIDIUS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>What's the matter?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>Now, you companion, I'll say an errand for you:</line>
            <line>You shall know now that I am in estimation; you shall</line>
            <line>perceive that a Jack guardant cannot office me from</line>
            <line>my son Coriolanus: guess, but by my entertainment</line>
            <line>with him, if thou standest not i' the state of</line>
            <line>hanging, or of some death more long in</line>
            <line>spectatorship, and crueller in suffering; behold now</line>
            <line>presently, and swoon for what's to come upon thee.</line>
            <stagedir>To CORIOLANUS</stagedir>
            <line>The glorious gods sit in hourly synod about thy</line>
            <line>particular prosperity, and love thee no worse than</line>
            <line>thy old father Menenius does! O my son, my son!</line>
            <line>thou art preparing fire for us; look thee, here's</line>
            <line>water to quench it. I was hardly moved to come to</line>
            <line>thee; but being assured none but myself could move</line>
            <line>thee, I have been blown out of your gates with</line>
            <line>sighs; and conjure thee to pardon Rome, and thy</line>
            <line>petitionary countrymen. The good gods assuage thy</line>
            <line>wrath, and turn the dregs of it upon this varlet</line>
            <line>here,--this, who, like a block, hath denied my</line>
            <line>access to thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>Away!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>How! away!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>Wife, mother, child, I know not. My affairs</line>
            <line>Are servanted to others: though I owe</line>
            <line>My revenge properly, my remission lies</line>
            <line>In Volscian breasts. That we have been familiar,</line>
            <line>Ingrate forgetfulness shall poison, rather</line>
            <line>Than pity note how much. Therefore, be gone.</line>
            <line>Mine ears against your suits are stronger than</line>
            <line>Your gates against my force. Yet, for I loved thee,</line>
            <line>Take this along; I writ it for thy sake</line>
            <stagedir>Gives a letter</stagedir>
            <line>And would have rent it. Another word, Menenius,</line>
            <line>I will not hear thee speak. This man, Aufidius,</line>
            <line>Was my beloved in Rome: yet thou behold'st!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUFIDIUS</speaker>
            <line>You keep a constant temper.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt CORIOLANUS and AUFIDIUS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>Now, sir, is your name Menenius?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Senator</speaker>
            <line>'Tis a spell, you see, of much power: you know the</line>
            <line>way home again.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>Do you hear how we are shent for keeping your</line>
            <line>greatness back?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Senator</speaker>
            <line>What cause, do you think, I have to swoon?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>I neither care for the world nor your general: for</line>
            <line>such things as you, I can scarce think there's any,</line>
            <line>ye're so slight. He that hath a will to die by</line>
            <line>himself fears it not from another: let your general</line>
            <line>do his worst. For you, be that you are, long; and</line>
            <line>your misery increase with your age! I say to you,</line>
            <line>as I was said to, Away!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>A noble fellow, I warrant him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Senator</speaker>
            <line>The worthy fellow is our general: he's the rock, the</line>
            <line>oak not to be wind-shaken.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  The tent of Coriolanus.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter CORIOLANUS, AUFIDIUS, and others</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>We will before the walls of Rome tomorrow</line>
            <line>Set down our host. My partner in this action,</line>
            <line>You must report to the Volscian lords, how plainly</line>
            <line>I have borne this business.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUFIDIUS</speaker>
            <line>Only their ends</line>
            <line>You have respected; stopp'd your ears against</line>
            <line>The general suit of Rome; never admitted</line>
            <line>A private whisper, no, not with such friends</line>
            <line>That thought them sure of you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>This last old man,</line>
            <line>Whom with a crack'd heart I have sent to Rome,</line>
            <line>Loved me above the measure of a father;</line>
            <line>Nay, godded me, indeed. Their latest refuge</line>
            <line>Was to send him; for whose old love I have,</line>
            <line>Though I show'd sourly to him, once more offer'd</line>
            <line>The first conditions, which they did refuse</line>
            <line>And cannot now accept; to grace him only</line>
            <line>That thought he could do more, a very little</line>
            <line>I have yielded to: fresh embassies and suits,</line>
            <line>Nor from the state nor private friends, hereafter</line>
            <line>Will I lend ear to. Ha! what shout is this?</line>
            <stagedir>Shout within</stagedir>
            <line>Shall I be tempted to infringe my vow</line>
            <line>In the same time 'tis made? I will not.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter in mourning habits, VIRGILIA, VOLUMNIA,
leading young MARCIUS, VALERIA, and Attendants</stagedir>
            <line>My wife comes foremost; then the honour'd mould</line>
            <line>Wherein this trunk was framed, and in her hand</line>
            <line>The grandchild to her blood. But, out, affection!</line>
            <line>All bond and privilege of nature, break!</line>
            <line>Let it be virtuous to be obstinate.</line>
            <line>What is that curt'sy worth? or those doves' eyes,</line>
            <line>Which can make gods forsworn? I melt, and am not</line>
            <line>Of stronger earth than others. My mother bows;</line>
            <line>As if Olympus to a molehill should</line>
            <line>In supplication nod: and my young boy</line>
            <line>Hath an aspect of intercession, which</line>
            <line>Great nature cries 'Deny not.' let the Volsces</line>
            <line>Plough Rome and harrow Italy: I'll never</line>
            <line>Be such a gosling to obey instinct, but stand,</line>
            <line>As if a man were author of himself</line>
            <line>And knew no other kin.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIRGILIA</speaker>
            <line>My lord and husband!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>These eyes are not the same I wore in Rome.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIRGILIA</speaker>
            <line>The sorrow that delivers us thus changed</line>
            <line>Makes you think so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>Like a dull actor now,</line>
            <line>I have forgot my part, and I am out,</line>
            <line>Even to a full disgrace. Best of my flesh,</line>
            <line>Forgive my tyranny; but do not say</line>
            <line>For that 'Forgive our Romans.' O, a kiss</line>
            <line>Long as my exile, sweet as my revenge!</line>
            <line>Now, by the jealous queen of heaven, that kiss</line>
            <line>I carried from thee, dear; and my true lip</line>
            <line>Hath virgin'd it e'er since. You gods! I prate,</line>
            <line>And the most noble mother of the world</line>
            <line>Leave unsaluted: sink, my knee, i' the earth;</line>
            <stagedir>Kneels</stagedir>
            <line>Of thy deep duty more impression show</line>
            <line>Than that of common sons.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VOLUMNIA</speaker>
            <line>O, stand up blest!</line>
            <line>Whilst, with no softer cushion than the flint,</line>
            <line>I kneel before thee; and unproperly</line>
            <line>Show duty, as mistaken all this while</line>
            <line>Between the child and parent.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Kneels</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>What is this?</line>
            <line>Your knees to me? to your corrected son?</line>
            <line>Then let the pebbles on the hungry beach</line>
            <line>Fillip the stars; then let the mutinous winds</line>
            <line>Strike the proud cedars 'gainst the fiery sun;</line>
            <line>Murdering impossibility, to make</line>
            <line>What cannot be, slight work.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VOLUMNIA</speaker>
            <line>Thou art my warrior;</line>
            <line>I holp to frame thee. Do you know this lady?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>The noble sister of Publicola,</line>
            <line>The moon of Rome, chaste as the icicle</line>
            <line>That's curdied by the frost from purest snow</line>
            <line>And hangs on Dian's temple: dear Valeria!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VOLUMNIA</speaker>
            <line>This is a poor epitome of yours,</line>
            <line>Which by the interpretation of full time</line>
            <line>May show like all yourself.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>The god of soldiers,</line>
            <line>With the consent of supreme Jove, inform</line>
            <line>Thy thoughts with nobleness; that thou mayst prove</line>
            <line>To shame unvulnerable, and stick i' the wars</line>
            <line>Like a great sea-mark, standing every flaw,</line>
            <line>And saving those that eye thee!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VOLUMNIA</speaker>
            <line>Your knee, sirrah.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>That's my brave boy!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VOLUMNIA</speaker>
            <line>Even he, your wife, this lady, and myself,</line>
            <line>Are suitors to you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>I beseech you, peace:</line>
            <line>Or, if you'ld ask, remember this before:</line>
            <line>The thing I have forsworn to grant may never</line>
            <line>Be held by you denials. Do not bid me</line>
            <line>Dismiss my soldiers, or capitulate</line>
            <line>Again with Rome's mechanics: tell me not</line>
            <line>Wherein I seem unnatural: desire not</line>
            <line>To ally my rages and revenges with</line>
            <line>Your colder reasons.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VOLUMNIA</speaker>
            <line>O, no more, no more!</line>
            <line>You have said you will not grant us any thing;</line>
            <line>For we have nothing else to ask, but that</line>
            <line>Which you deny already: yet we will ask;</line>
            <line>That, if you fail in our request, the blame</line>
            <line>May hang upon your hardness: therefore hear us.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>Aufidius, and you Volsces, mark; for we'll</line>
            <line>Hear nought from Rome in private. Your request?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VOLUMNIA</speaker>
            <line>Should we be silent and not speak, our raiment</line>
            <line>And state of bodies would bewray what life</line>
            <line>We have led since thy exile. Think with thyself</line>
            <line>How more unfortunate than all living women</line>
            <line>Are we come hither: since that thy sight,</line>
            <line>which should</line>
            <line>Make our eyes flow with joy, hearts dance</line>
            <line>with comforts,</line>
            <line>Constrains them weep and shake with fear and sorrow;</line>
            <line>Making the mother, wife and child to see</line>
            <line>The son, the husband and the father tearing</line>
            <line>His country's bowels out. And to poor we</line>
            <line>Thine enmity's most capital: thou barr'st us</line>
            <line>Our prayers to the gods, which is a comfort</line>
            <line>That all but we enjoy; for how can we,</line>
            <line>Alas, how can we for our country pray.</line>
            <line>Whereto we are bound, together with thy victory,</line>
            <line>Whereto we are bound? alack, or we must lose</line>
            <line>The country, our dear nurse, or else thy person,</line>
            <line>Our comfort in the country. We must find</line>
            <line>An evident calamity, though we had</line>
            <line>Our wish, which side should win: for either thou</line>
            <line>Must, as a foreign recreant, be led</line>
            <line>With manacles thorough our streets, or else</line>
            <line>triumphantly tread on thy country's ruin,</line>
            <line>And bear the palm for having bravely shed</line>
            <line>Thy wife and children's blood. For myself, son,</line>
            <line>I purpose not to wait on fortune till</line>
            <line>These wars determine: if I cannot persuade thee</line>
            <line>Rather to show a noble grace to both parts</line>
            <line>Than seek the end of one, thou shalt no sooner</line>
            <line>March to assault thy country than to tread--</line>
            <line>Trust to't, thou shalt not--on thy mother's womb,</line>
            <line>That brought thee to this world.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIRGILIA</speaker>
            <line>Ay, and mine,</line>
            <line>That brought you forth this boy, to keep your name</line>
            <line>Living to time.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Young MARCIUS</speaker>
            <line>A' shall not tread on me;</line>
            <line>I'll run away till I am bigger, but then I'll fight.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>Not of a woman's tenderness to be,</line>
            <line>Requires nor child nor woman's face to see.</line>
            <line>I have sat too long.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Rising</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VOLUMNIA</speaker>
            <line>Nay, go not from us thus.</line>
            <line>If it were so that our request did tend</line>
            <line>To save the Romans, thereby to destroy</line>
            <line>The Volsces whom you serve, you might condemn us,</line>
            <line>As poisonous of your honour: no; our suit</line>
            <line>Is that you reconcile them: while the Volsces</line>
            <line>May say 'This mercy we have show'd;' the Romans,</line>
            <line>'This we received;' and each in either side</line>
            <line>Give the all-hail to thee and cry 'Be blest</line>
            <line>For making up this peace!' Thou know'st, great son,</line>
            <line>The end of war's uncertain, but this certain,</line>
            <line>That, if thou conquer Rome, the benefit</line>
            <line>Which thou shalt thereby reap is such a name,</line>
            <line>Whose repetition will be dogg'd with curses;</line>
            <line>Whose chronicle thus writ: 'The man was noble,</line>
            <line>But with his last attempt he wiped it out;</line>
            <line>Destroy'd his country, and his name remains</line>
            <line>To the ensuing age abhorr'd.' Speak to me, son:</line>
            <line>Thou hast affected the fine strains of honour,</line>
            <line>To imitate the graces of the gods;</line>
            <line>To tear with thunder the wide cheeks o' the air,</line>
            <line>And yet to charge thy sulphur with a bolt</line>
            <line>That should but rive an oak. Why dost not speak?</line>
            <line>Think'st thou it honourable for a noble man</line>
            <line>Still to remember wrongs? Daughter, speak you:</line>
            <line>He cares not for your weeping. Speak thou, boy:</line>
            <line>Perhaps thy childishness will move him more</line>
            <line>Than can our reasons. There's no man in the world</line>
            <line>More bound to 's mother; yet here he lets me prate</line>
            <line>Like one i' the stocks. Thou hast never in thy life</line>
            <line>Show'd thy dear mother any courtesy,</line>
            <line>When she, poor hen, fond of no second brood,</line>
            <line>Has cluck'd thee to the wars and safely home,</line>
            <line>Loaden with honour. Say my request's unjust,</line>
            <line>And spurn me back: but if it be not so,</line>
            <line>Thou art not honest; and the gods will plague thee,</line>
            <line>That thou restrain'st from me the duty which</line>
            <line>To a mother's part belongs. He turns away:</line>
            <line>Down, ladies; let us shame him with our knees.</line>
            <line>To his surname Coriolanus 'longs more pride</line>
            <line>Than pity to our prayers. Down: an end;</line>
            <line>This is the last: so we will home to Rome,</line>
            <line>And die among our neighbours. Nay, behold 's:</line>
            <line>This boy, that cannot tell what he would have</line>
            <line>But kneels and holds up bands for fellowship,</line>
            <line>Does reason our petition with more strength</line>
            <line>Than thou hast to deny 't. Come, let us go:</line>
            <line>This fellow had a Volscian to his mother;</line>
            <line>His wife is in Corioli and his child</line>
            <line>Like him by chance. Yet give us our dispatch:</line>
            <line>I am hush'd until our city be a-fire,</line>
            <line>And then I'll speak a little.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>He holds her by the hand, silent</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>O mother, mother!</line>
            <line>What have you done? Behold, the heavens do ope,</line>
            <line>The gods look down, and this unnatural scene</line>
            <line>They laugh at. O my mother, mother! O!</line>
            <line>You have won a happy victory to Rome;</line>
            <line>But, for your son,--believe it, O, believe it,</line>
            <line>Most dangerously you have with him prevail'd,</line>
            <line>If not most mortal to him. But, let it come.</line>
            <line>Aufidius, though I cannot make true wars,</line>
            <line>I'll frame convenient peace. Now, good Aufidius,</line>
            <line>Were you in my stead, would you have heard</line>
            <line>A mother less? or granted less, Aufidius?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUFIDIUS</speaker>
            <line>I was moved withal.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>I dare be sworn you were:</line>
            <line>And, sir, it is no little thing to make</line>
            <line>Mine eyes to sweat compassion. But, good sir,</line>
            <line>What peace you'll make, advise me: for my part,</line>
            <line>I'll not to Rome, I'll back with you; and pray you,</line>
            <line>Stand to me in this cause. O mother! wife!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUFIDIUS</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  I am glad thou hast set thy mercy and</line>
            <line>thy honour</line>
            <line>At difference in thee: out of that I'll work</line>
            <line>Myself a former fortune.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>The Ladies make signs to CORIOLANUS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>Ay, by and by;</line>
            <stagedir>To VOLUMNIA, VIRGILIA, &amp;c</stagedir>
            <line>But we will drink together; and you shall bear</line>
            <line>A better witness back than words, which we,</line>
            <line>On like conditions, will have counter-seal'd.</line>
            <line>Come, enter with us. Ladies, you deserve</line>
            <line>To have a temple built you: all the swords</line>
            <line>In Italy, and her confederate arms,</line>
            <line>Could not have made this peace.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-4">
      <title>SCENE IV.  Rome. A public place.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter MENENIUS and SICINIUS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>See you yond coign o' the Capitol, yond</line>
            <line>corner-stone?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SICINIUS</speaker>
            <line>Why, what of that?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>If it be possible for you to displace it with your</line>
            <line>little finger, there is some hope the ladies of</line>
            <line>Rome, especially his mother, may prevail with him.</line>
            <line>But I say there is no hope in't: our throats are</line>
            <line>sentenced and stay upon execution.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SICINIUS</speaker>
            <line>Is't possible that so short a time can alter the</line>
            <line>condition of a man!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>There is differency between a grub and a butterfly;</line>
            <line>yet your butterfly was a grub. This Marcius is grown</line>
            <line>from man to dragon: he has wings; he's more than a</line>
            <line>creeping thing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SICINIUS</speaker>
            <line>He loved his mother dearly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>So did he me: and he no more remembers his mother</line>
            <line>now than an eight-year-old horse. The tartness</line>
            <line>of his face sours ripe grapes: when he walks, he</line>
            <line>moves like an engine, and the ground shrinks before</line>
            <line>his treading: he is able to pierce a corslet with</line>
            <line>his eye; talks like a knell, and his hum is a</line>
            <line>battery. He sits in his state, as a thing made for</line>
            <line>Alexander. What he bids be done is finished with</line>
            <line>his bidding. He wants nothing of a god but eternity</line>
            <line>and a heaven to throne in.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SICINIUS</speaker>
            <line>Yes, mercy, if you report him truly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>I paint him in the character. Mark what mercy his</line>
            <line>mother shall bring from him: there is no more mercy</line>
            <line>in him than there is milk in a male tiger; that</line>
            <line>shall our poor city find: and all this is long of</line>
            <line>you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SICINIUS</speaker>
            <line>The gods be good unto us!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>No, in such a case the gods will not be good unto</line>
            <line>us. When we banished him, we respected not them;</line>
            <line>and, he returning to break our necks, they respect not us.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter a Messenger</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>Sir, if you'ld save your life, fly to your house:</line>
            <line>The plebeians have got your fellow-tribune</line>
            <line>And hale him up and down, all swearing, if</line>
            <line>The Roman ladies bring not comfort home,</line>
            <line>They'll give him death by inches.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter a second Messenger</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SICINIUS</speaker>
            <line>What's the news?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Messenger</speaker>
            <line>Good news, good news; the ladies have prevail'd,</line>
            <line>The Volscians are dislodged, and Marcius gone:</line>
            <line>A merrier day did never yet greet Rome,</line>
            <line>No, not the expulsion of the Tarquins.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SICINIUS</speaker>
            <line>Friend,</line>
            <line>Art thou certain this is true? is it most certain?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Messenger</speaker>
            <line>As certain as I know the sun is fire:</line>
            <line>Where have you lurk'd, that you make doubt of it?</line>
            <line>Ne'er through an arch so hurried the blown tide,</line>
            <line>As the recomforted through the gates. Why, hark you!</line>
            <stagedir>Trumpets; hautboys; drums beat; all together</stagedir>
            <line>The trumpets, sackbuts, psalteries and fifes,</line>
            <line>Tabours and cymbals and the shouting Romans,</line>
            <line>Make the sun dance. Hark you!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>A shout within</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>This is good news:</line>
            <line>I will go meet the ladies. This Volumnia</line>
            <line>Is worth of consuls, senators, patricians,</line>
            <line>A city full; of tribunes, such as you,</line>
            <line>A sea and land full. You have pray'd well to-day:</line>
            <line>This morning for ten thousand of your throats</line>
            <line>I'd not have given a doit. Hark, how they joy!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Music still, with shouts</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SICINIUS</speaker>
            <line>First, the gods bless you for your tidings; next,</line>
            <line>Accept my thankfulness.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Messenger</speaker>
            <line>Sir, we have all</line>
            <line>Great cause to give great thanks.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SICINIUS</speaker>
            <line>They are near the city?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Messenger</speaker>
            <line>Almost at point to enter.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SICINIUS</speaker>
            <line>We will meet them,</line>
            <line>And help the joy.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-5">
      <title>SCENE V.  The same. A street near the gate.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter two Senators with VOLUMNIA, VIRGILIA,
VALERIA, &amp;c. passing over the stage,
followed by Patricians and others</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>Behold our patroness, the life of Rome!</line>
            <line>Call all your tribes together, praise the gods,</line>
            <line>And make triumphant fires; strew flowers before them:</line>
            <line>Unshout the noise that banish'd Marcius,</line>
            <line>Repeal him with the welcome of his mother;</line>
            <line>Cry 'Welcome, ladies, welcome!'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>All</speaker>
            <line>Welcome, ladies, Welcome!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>A flourish with drums and trumpets. Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-6">
      <title>SCENE VI.  Antium. A public place.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter TULLUS AUFIDIUS, with Attendants</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUFIDIUS</speaker>
            <line>Go tell the lords o' the city I am here:</line>
            <line>Deliver them this paper: having read it,</line>
            <line>Bid them repair to the market place; where I,</line>
            <line>Even in theirs and in the commons' ears,</line>
            <line>Will vouch the truth of it. Him I accuse</line>
            <line>The city ports by this hath enter'd and</line>
            <line>Intends to appear before the people, hoping</line>
            <line>To purge herself with words: dispatch.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt Attendants</stagedir>
            <stagedir>Enter three or four Conspirators of AUFIDIUS' faction</stagedir>
            <line>Most welcome!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Conspirator</speaker>
            <line>How is it with our general?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUFIDIUS</speaker>
            <line>Even so</line>
            <line>As with a man by his own alms empoison'd,</line>
            <line>And with his charity slain.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Conspirator</speaker>
            <line>Most noble sir,</line>
            <line>If you do hold the same intent wherein</line>
            <line>You wish'd us parties, we'll deliver you</line>
            <line>Of your great danger.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUFIDIUS</speaker>
            <line>Sir, I cannot tell:</line>
            <line>We must proceed as we do find the people.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Conspirator</speaker>
            <line>The people will remain uncertain whilst</line>
            <line>'Twixt you there's difference; but the fall of either</line>
            <line>Makes the survivor heir of all.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUFIDIUS</speaker>
            <line>I know it;</line>
            <line>And my pretext to strike at him admits</line>
            <line>A good construction. I raised him, and I pawn'd</line>
            <line>Mine honour for his truth: who being so heighten'd,</line>
            <line>He water'd his new plants with dews of flattery,</line>
            <line>Seducing so my friends; and, to this end,</line>
            <line>He bow'd his nature, never known before</line>
            <line>But to be rough, unswayable and free.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Conspirator</speaker>
            <line>Sir, his stoutness</line>
            <line>When he did stand for consul, which he lost</line>
            <line>By lack of stooping,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUFIDIUS</speaker>
            <line>That I would have spoke of:</line>
            <line>Being banish'd for't, he came unto my hearth;</line>
            <line>Presented to my knife his throat: I took him;</line>
            <line>Made him joint-servant with me; gave him way</line>
            <line>In all his own desires; nay, let him choose</line>
            <line>Out of my files, his projects to accomplish,</line>
            <line>My best and freshest men; served his designments</line>
            <line>In mine own person; holp to reap the fame</line>
            <line>Which he did end all his; and took some pride</line>
            <line>To do myself this wrong: till, at the last,</line>
            <line>I seem'd his follower, not partner, and</line>
            <line>He waged me with his countenance, as if</line>
            <line>I had been mercenary.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Conspirator</speaker>
            <line>So he did, my lord:</line>
            <line>The army marvell'd at it, and, in the last,</line>
            <line>When he had carried Rome and that we look'd</line>
            <line>For no less spoil than glory,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUFIDIUS</speaker>
            <line>There was it:</line>
            <line>For which my sinews shall be stretch'd upon him.</line>
            <line>At a few drops of women's rheum, which are</line>
            <line>As cheap as lies, he sold the blood and labour</line>
            <line>Of our great action: therefore shall he die,</line>
            <line>And I'll renew me in his fall. But, hark!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Drums and trumpets sound, with great shouts of
the People</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Conspirator</speaker>
            <line>Your native town you enter'd like a post,</line>
            <line>And had no welcomes home: but he returns,</line>
            <line>Splitting the air with noise.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Conspirator</speaker>
            <line>And patient fools,</line>
            <line>Whose children he hath slain, their base throats tear</line>
            <line>With giving him glory.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Conspirator</speaker>
            <line>Therefore, at your vantage,</line>
            <line>Ere he express himself, or move the people</line>
            <line>With what he would say, let him feel your sword,</line>
            <line>Which we will second. When he lies along,</line>
            <line>After your way his tale pronounced shall bury</line>
            <line>His reasons with his body.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUFIDIUS</speaker>
            <line>Say no more:</line>
            <line>Here come the lords.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter the Lords of the city</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>All The Lords</speaker>
            <line>You are most welcome home.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUFIDIUS</speaker>
            <line>I have not deserved it.</line>
            <line>But, worthy lords, have you with heed perused</line>
            <line>What I have written to you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lords</speaker>
            <line>We have.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>And grieve to hear't.</line>
            <line>What faults he made before the last, I think</line>
            <line>Might have found easy fines: but there to end</line>
            <line>Where he was to begin and give away</line>
            <line>The benefit of our levies, answering us</line>
            <line>With our own charge, making a treaty where</line>
            <line>There was a yielding,--this admits no excuse.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUFIDIUS</speaker>
            <line>He approaches: you shall hear him.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter CORIOLANUS, marching with drum and
colours; commoners being with him</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>Hail, lords! I am return'd your soldier,</line>
            <line>No more infected with my country's love</line>
            <line>Than when I parted hence, but still subsisting</line>
            <line>Under your great command. You are to know</line>
            <line>That prosperously I have attempted and</line>
            <line>With bloody passage led your wars even to</line>
            <line>The gates of Rome. Our spoils we have brought home</line>
            <line>Do more than counterpoise a full third part</line>
            <line>The charges of the action. We have made peace</line>
            <line>With no less honour to the Antiates</line>
            <line>Than shame to the Romans: and we here deliver,</line>
            <line>Subscribed by the consuls and patricians,</line>
            <line>Together with the seal o' the senate, what</line>
            <line>We have compounded on.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUFIDIUS</speaker>
            <line>Read it not, noble lords;</line>
            <line>But tell the traitor, in the high'st degree</line>
            <line>He hath abused your powers.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>Traitor! how now!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUFIDIUS</speaker>
            <line>Ay, traitor, Marcius!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>Marcius!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUFIDIUS</speaker>
            <line>Ay, Marcius, Caius Marcius: dost thou think</line>
            <line>I'll grace thee with that robbery, thy stol'n name</line>
            <line>Coriolanus in Corioli?</line>
            <line>You lords and heads o' the state, perfidiously</line>
            <line>He has betray'd your business, and given up,</line>
            <line>For certain drops of salt, your city Rome,</line>
            <line>I say 'your city,' to his wife and mother;</line>
            <line>Breaking his oath and resolution like</line>
            <line>A twist of rotten silk, never admitting</line>
            <line>Counsel o' the war, but at his nurse's tears</line>
            <line>He whined and roar'd away your victory,</line>
            <line>That pages blush'd at him and men of heart</line>
            <line>Look'd wondering each at other.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>Hear'st thou, Mars?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUFIDIUS</speaker>
            <line>Name not the god, thou boy of tears!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>Ha!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUFIDIUS</speaker>
            <line>No more.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>Measureless liar, thou hast made my heart</line>
            <line>Too great for what contains it. Boy! O slave!</line>
            <line>Pardon me, lords, 'tis the first time that ever</line>
            <line>I was forced to scold. Your judgments, my grave lords,</line>
            <line>Must give this cur the lie: and his own notion--</line>
            <line>Who wears my stripes impress'd upon him; that</line>
            <line>Must bear my beating to his grave--shall join</line>
            <line>To thrust the lie unto him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>Peace, both, and hear me speak.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>Cut me to pieces, Volsces; men and lads,</line>
            <line>Stain all your edges on me. Boy! false hound!</line>
            <line>If you have writ your annals true, 'tis there,</line>
            <line>That, like an eagle in a dove-cote, I</line>
            <line>Flutter'd your Volscians in Corioli:</line>
            <line>Alone I did it. Boy!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUFIDIUS</speaker>
            <line>Why, noble lords,</line>
            <line>Will you be put in mind of his blind fortune,</line>
            <line>Which was your shame, by this unholy braggart,</line>
            <line>'Fore your own eyes and ears?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>All Conspirators</speaker>
            <line>Let him die for't.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>All The People</speaker>
            <line>'Tear him to pieces.' 'Do it presently.' 'He kill'd</line>
            <line>my son.' 'My daughter.' 'He killed my cousin</line>
            <line>Marcus.' 'He killed my father.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>Peace, ho! no outrage: peace!</line>
            <line>The man is noble and his fame folds-in</line>
            <line>This orb o' the earth. His last offences to us</line>
            <line>Shall have judicious hearing. Stand, Aufidius,</line>
            <line>And trouble not the peace.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>O that I had him,</line>
            <line>With six Aufidiuses, or more, his tribe,</line>
            <line>To use my lawful sword!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUFIDIUS</speaker>
            <line>Insolent villain!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>All Conspirators</speaker>
            <line>Kill, kill, kill, kill, kill him!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>The Conspirators draw, and kill CORIOLANUS:
AUFIDIUS stands on his body</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lords</speaker>
            <line>Hold, hold, hold, hold!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUFIDIUS</speaker>
            <line>My noble masters, hear me speak.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>O Tullus,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>Thou hast done a deed whereat valour will weep.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Lord</speaker>
            <line>Tread not upon him. Masters all, be quiet;</line>
            <line>Put up your swords.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUFIDIUS</speaker>
            <line>My lords, when you shall know--as in this rage,</line>
            <line>Provoked by him, you cannot--the great danger</line>
            <line>Which this man's life did owe you, you'll rejoice</line>
            <line>That he is thus cut off. Please it your honours</line>
            <line>To call me to your senate, I'll deliver</line>
            <line>Myself your loyal servant, or endure</line>
            <line>Your heaviest censure.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>Bear from hence his body;</line>
            <line>And mourn you for him: let him be regarded</line>
            <line>As the most noble corse that ever herald</line>
            <line>Did follow to his urn.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>His own impatience</line>
            <line>Takes from Aufidius a great part of blame.</line>
            <line>Let's make the best of it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUFIDIUS</speaker>
            <line>My rage is gone;</line>
            <line>And I am struck with sorrow. Take him up.</line>
            <line>Help, three o' the chiefest soldiers; I'll be one.</line>
            <line>Beat thou the drum, that it speak mournfully:</line>
            <line>Trail your steel pikes. Though in this city he</line>
            <line>Hath widow'd and unchilded many a one,</line>
            <line>Which to this hour bewail the injury,</line>
            <line>Yet he shall have a noble memory. Assist.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt, bearing the body of CORIOLANUS. A dead
march sounded</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>