<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net/doctypes/dita/shakespear/dtd/act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-1">
   <title>ACT I</title>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  Rome. A street.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter a company of mutinous Citizens, with staves,
clubs, and other weapons</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Before we proceed any further, hear me speak.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>All</speaker>
            <line>Speak, speak.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>You are all resolved rather to die than to famish?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>All</speaker>
            <line>Resolved. resolved.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>First, you know Caius Marcius is chief enemy to the people.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>All</speaker>
            <line>We know't, we know't.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Let us kill him, and we'll have corn at our own price.</line>
            <line>Is't a verdict?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>All</speaker>
            <line>No more talking on't; let it be done: away, away!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Citizen</speaker>
            <line>One word, good citizens.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>We are accounted poor citizens, the patricians good.</line>
            <line>What authority surfeits on would relieve us: if they</line>
            <line>would yield us but the superfluity, while it were</line>
            <line>wholesome, we might guess they relieved us humanely;</line>
            <line>but they think we are too dear: the leanness that</line>
            <line>afflicts us, the object of our misery, is as an</line>
            <line>inventory to particularise their abundance; our</line>
            <line>sufferance is a gain to them Let us revenge this with</line>
            <line>our pikes, ere we become rakes: for the gods know I</line>
            <line>speak this in hunger for bread, not in thirst for revenge.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Would you proceed especially against Caius Marcius?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>All</speaker>
            <line>Against him first: he's a very dog to the commonalty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Consider you what services he has done for his country?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Very well; and could be content to give him good</line>
            <line>report fort, but that he pays himself with being proud.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Nay, but speak not maliciously.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>I say unto you, what he hath done famously, he did</line>
            <line>it to that end: though soft-conscienced men can be</line>
            <line>content to say it was for his country he did it to</line>
            <line>please his mother and to be partly proud; which he</line>
            <line>is, even till the altitude of his virtue.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Citizen</speaker>
            <line>What he cannot help in his nature, you account a</line>
            <line>vice in him. You must in no way say he is covetous.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>If I must not, I need not be barren of accusations;</line>
            <line>he hath faults, with surplus, to tire in repetition.</line>
            <stagedir>Shouts within</stagedir>
            <line>What shouts are these? The other side o' the city</line>
            <line>is risen: why stay we prating here? to the Capitol!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>All</speaker>
            <line>Come, come.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Soft! who comes here?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter MENENIUS AGRIPPA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Worthy Menenius Agrippa; one that hath always loved</line>
            <line>the people.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>He's one honest enough: would all the rest were so!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>What work's, my countrymen, in hand? where go you</line>
            <line>With bats and clubs? The matter? speak, I pray you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Our business is not unknown to the senate; they have</line>
            <line>had inkling this fortnight what we intend to do,</line>
            <line>which now we'll show 'em in deeds. They say poor</line>
            <line>suitors have strong breaths: they shall know we</line>
            <line>have strong arms too.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>Why, masters, my good friends, mine honest neighbours,</line>
            <line>Will you undo yourselves?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>We cannot, sir, we are undone already.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>I tell you, friends, most charitable care</line>
            <line>Have the patricians of you. For your wants,</line>
            <line>Your suffering in this dearth, you may as well</line>
            <line>Strike at the heaven with your staves as lift them</line>
            <line>Against the Roman state, whose course will on</line>
            <line>The way it takes, cracking ten thousand curbs</line>
            <line>Of more strong link asunder than can ever</line>
            <line>Appear in your impediment. For the dearth,</line>
            <line>The gods, not the patricians, make it, and</line>
            <line>Your knees to them, not arms, must help. Alack,</line>
            <line>You are transported by calamity</line>
            <line>Thither where more attends you, and you slander</line>
            <line>The helms o' the state, who care for you like fathers,</line>
            <line>When you curse them as enemies.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Care for us! True, indeed! They ne'er cared for us</line>
            <line>yet: suffer us to famish, and their store-houses</line>
            <line>crammed with grain; make edicts for usury, to</line>
            <line>support usurers; repeal daily any wholesome act</line>
            <line>established against the rich, and provide more</line>
            <line>piercing statutes daily, to chain up and restrain</line>
            <line>the poor. If the wars eat us not up, they will; and</line>
            <line>there's all the love they bear us.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>Either you must</line>
            <line>Confess yourselves wondrous malicious,</line>
            <line>Or be accused of folly. I shall tell you</line>
            <line>A pretty tale: it may be you have heard it;</line>
            <line>But, since it serves my purpose, I will venture</line>
            <line>To stale 't a little more.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Well, I'll hear it, sir: yet you must not think to</line>
            <line>fob off our disgrace with a tale: but, an 't please</line>
            <line>you, deliver.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>There was a time when all the body's members</line>
            <line>Rebell'd against the belly, thus accused it:</line>
            <line>That only like a gulf it did remain</line>
            <line>I' the midst o' the body, idle and unactive,</line>
            <line>Still cupboarding the viand, never bearing</line>
            <line>Like labour with the rest, where the other instruments</line>
            <line>Did see and hear, devise, instruct, walk, feel,</line>
            <line>And, mutually participate, did minister</line>
            <line>Unto the appetite and affection common</line>
            <line>Of the whole body. The belly answer'd--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Well, sir, what answer made the belly?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>Sir, I shall tell you. With a kind of smile,</line>
            <line>Which ne'er came from the lungs, but even thus--</line>
            <line>For, look you, I may make the belly smile</line>
            <line>As well as speak--it tauntingly replied</line>
            <line>To the discontented members, the mutinous parts</line>
            <line>That envied his receipt; even so most fitly</line>
            <line>As you malign our senators for that</line>
            <line>They are not such as you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Your belly's answer? What!</line>
            <line>The kingly-crowned head, the vigilant eye,</line>
            <line>The counsellor heart, the arm our soldier,</line>
            <line>Our steed the leg, the tongue our trumpeter.</line>
            <line>With other muniments and petty helps</line>
            <line>In this our fabric, if that they--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>What then?</line>
            <line>'Fore me, this fellow speaks! What then? what then?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Should by the cormorant belly be restrain'd,</line>
            <line>Who is the sink o' the body,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>Well, what then?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>The former agents, if they did complain,</line>
            <line>What could the belly answer?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>I will tell you</line>
            <line>If you'll bestow a small--of what you have little--</line>
            <line>Patience awhile, you'll hear the belly's answer.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Ye're long about it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>Note me this, good friend;</line>
            <line>Your most grave belly was deliberate,</line>
            <line>Not rash like his accusers, and thus answer'd:</line>
            <line>'True is it, my incorporate friends,' quoth he,</line>
            <line>'That I receive the general food at first,</line>
            <line>Which you do live upon; and fit it is,</line>
            <line>Because I am the store-house and the shop</line>
            <line>Of the whole body: but, if you do remember,</line>
            <line>I send it through the rivers of your blood,</line>
            <line>Even to the court, the heart, to the seat o' the brain;</line>
            <line>And, through the cranks and offices of man,</line>
            <line>The strongest nerves and small inferior veins</line>
            <line>From me receive that natural competency</line>
            <line>Whereby they live: and though that all at once,</line>
            <line>You, my good friends,'--this says the belly, mark me,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Ay, sir; well, well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>'Though all at once cannot</line>
            <line>See what I do deliver out to each,</line>
            <line>Yet I can make my audit up, that all</line>
            <line>From me do back receive the flour of all,</line>
            <line>And leave me but the bran.' What say you to't?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>It was an answer: how apply you this?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>The senators of Rome are this good belly,</line>
            <line>And you the mutinous members; for examine</line>
            <line>Their counsels and their cares, digest things rightly</line>
            <line>Touching the weal o' the common, you shall find</line>
            <line>No public benefit which you receive</line>
            <line>But it proceeds or comes from them to you</line>
            <line>And no way from yourselves. What do you think,</line>
            <line>You, the great toe of this assembly?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>I the great toe! why the great toe?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>For that, being one o' the lowest, basest, poorest,</line>
            <line>Of this most wise rebellion, thou go'st foremost:</line>
            <line>Thou rascal, that art worst in blood to run,</line>
            <line>Lead'st first to win some vantage.</line>
            <line>But make you ready your stiff bats and clubs:</line>
            <line>Rome and her rats are at the point of battle;</line>
            <line>The one side must have bale.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter CAIUS MARCIUS</stagedir>
            <line>Hail, noble Marcius!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCIUS</speaker>
            <line>Thanks. What's the matter, you dissentious rogues,</line>
            <line>That, rubbing the poor itch of your opinion,</line>
            <line>Make yourselves scabs?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>We have ever your good word.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCIUS</speaker>
            <line>He that will give good words to thee will flatter</line>
            <line>Beneath abhorring. What would you have, you curs,</line>
            <line>That like nor peace nor war? the one affrights you,</line>
            <line>The other makes you proud. He that trusts to you,</line>
            <line>Where he should find you lions, finds you hares;</line>
            <line>Where foxes, geese: you are no surer, no,</line>
            <line>Than is the coal of fire upon the ice,</line>
            <line>Or hailstone in the sun. Your virtue is</line>
            <line>To make him worthy whose offence subdues him</line>
            <line>And curse that justice did it.</line>
            <line>Who deserves greatness</line>
            <line>Deserves your hate; and your affections are</line>
            <line>A sick man's appetite, who desires most that</line>
            <line>Which would increase his evil. He that depends</line>
            <line>Upon your favours swims with fins of lead</line>
            <line>And hews down oaks with rushes. Hang ye! Trust Ye?</line>
            <line>With every minute you do change a mind,</line>
            <line>And call him noble that was now your hate,</line>
            <line>Him vile that was your garland. What's the matter,</line>
            <line>That in these several places of the city</line>
            <line>You cry against the noble senate, who,</line>
            <line>Under the gods, keep you in awe, which else</line>
            <line>Would feed on one another? What's their seeking?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>For corn at their own rates; whereof, they say,</line>
            <line>The city is well stored.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCIUS</speaker>
            <line>Hang 'em! They say!</line>
            <line>They'll sit by the fire, and presume to know</line>
            <line>What's done i' the Capitol; who's like to rise,</line>
            <line>Who thrives and who declines; side factions</line>
            <line>and give out</line>
            <line>Conjectural marriages; making parties strong</line>
            <line>And feebling such as stand not in their liking</line>
            <line>Below their cobbled shoes. They say there's</line>
            <line>grain enough!</line>
            <line>Would the nobility lay aside their ruth,</line>
            <line>And let me use my sword, I'll make a quarry</line>
            <line>With thousands of these quarter'd slaves, as high</line>
            <line>As I could pick my lance.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>Nay, these are almost thoroughly persuaded;</line>
            <line>For though abundantly they lack discretion,</line>
            <line>Yet are they passing cowardly. But, I beseech you,</line>
            <line>What says the other troop?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCIUS</speaker>
            <line>They are dissolved: hang 'em!</line>
            <line>They said they were an-hungry; sigh'd forth proverbs,</line>
            <line>That hunger broke stone walls, that dogs must eat,</line>
            <line>That meat was made for mouths, that the gods sent not</line>
            <line>Corn for the rich men only: with these shreds</line>
            <line>They vented their complainings; which being answer'd,</line>
            <line>And a petition granted them, a strange one--</line>
            <line>To break the heart of generosity,</line>
            <line>And make bold power look pale--they threw their caps</line>
            <line>As they would hang them on the horns o' the moon,</line>
            <line>Shouting their emulation.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>What is granted them?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCIUS</speaker>
            <line>Five tribunes to defend their vulgar wisdoms,</line>
            <line>Of their own choice: one's Junius Brutus,</line>
            <line>Sicinius Velutus, and I know not--'Sdeath!</line>
            <line>The rabble should have first unroof'd the city,</line>
            <line>Ere so prevail'd with me: it will in time</line>
            <line>Win upon power and throw forth greater themes</line>
            <line>For insurrection's arguing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>This is strange.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCIUS</speaker>
            <line>Go, get you home, you fragments!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter a Messenger, hastily</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>Where's Caius Marcius?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCIUS</speaker>
            <line>Here: what's the matter?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>The news is, sir, the Volsces are in arms.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCIUS</speaker>
            <line>I am glad on 't: then we shall ha' means to vent</line>
            <line>Our musty superfluity. See, our best elders.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter COMINIUS, TITUS LARTIUS, and other Senators;
JUNIUS BRUTUS and SICINIUS VELUTUS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>Marcius, 'tis true that you have lately told us;</line>
            <line>The Volsces are in arms.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCIUS</speaker>
            <line>They have a leader,</line>
            <line>Tullus Aufidius, that will put you to 't.</line>
            <line>I sin in envying his nobility,</line>
            <line>And were I any thing but what I am,</line>
            <line>I would wish me only he.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COMINIUS</speaker>
            <line>You have fought together.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCIUS</speaker>
            <line>Were half to half the world by the ears and he.</line>
            <line>Upon my party, I'ld revolt to make</line>
            <line>Only my wars with him: he is a lion</line>
            <line>That I am proud to hunt.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>Then, worthy Marcius,</line>
            <line>Attend upon Cominius to these wars.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COMINIUS</speaker>
            <line>It is your former promise.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCIUS</speaker>
            <line>Sir, it is;</line>
            <line>And I am constant. Titus Lartius, thou</line>
            <line>Shalt see me once more strike at Tullus' face.</line>
            <line>What, art thou stiff? stand'st out?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS</speaker>
            <line>No, Caius Marcius;</line>
            <line>I'll lean upon one crutch and fight with t'other,</line>
            <line>Ere stay behind this business.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>O, true-bred!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>Your company to the Capitol; where, I know,</line>
            <line>Our greatest friends attend us.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>To COMINIUS</stagedir>                Lead you on.</line>
            <line>
               <stagedir>To MARCIUS</stagedir>  Follow Cominius; we must follow you;</line>
            <line>Right worthy you priority.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COMINIUS</speaker>
            <line>Noble Marcius!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>To the Citizens</stagedir>  Hence to your homes; be gone!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCIUS</speaker>
            <line>Nay, let them follow:</line>
            <line>The Volsces have much corn; take these rats thither</line>
            <line>To gnaw their garners. Worshipful mutiners,</line>
            <line>Your valour puts well forth: pray, follow.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Citizens steal away. Exeunt all but SICINIUS
and BRUTUS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SICINIUS</speaker>
            <line>Was ever man so proud as is this Marcius?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>He has no equal.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SICINIUS</speaker>
            <line>When we were chosen tribunes for the people,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>Mark'd you his lip and eyes?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SICINIUS</speaker>
            <line>Nay. but his taunts.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>Being moved, he will not spare to gird the gods.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SICINIUS</speaker>
            <line>Be-mock the modest moon.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>The present wars devour him: he is grown</line>
            <line>Too proud to be so valiant.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SICINIUS</speaker>
            <line>Such a nature,</line>
            <line>Tickled with good success, disdains the shadow</line>
            <line>Which he treads on at noon: but I do wonder</line>
            <line>His insolence can brook to be commanded</line>
            <line>Under Cominius.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>Fame, at the which he aims,</line>
            <line>In whom already he's well graced, can not</line>
            <line>Better be held nor more attain'd than by</line>
            <line>A place below the first: for what miscarries</line>
            <line>Shall be the general's fault, though he perform</line>
            <line>To the utmost of a man, and giddy censure</line>
            <line>Will then cry out of Marcius 'O if he</line>
            <line>Had borne the business!'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SICINIUS</speaker>
            <line>Besides, if things go well,</line>
            <line>Opinion that so sticks on Marcius shall</line>
            <line>Of his demerits rob Cominius.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>Come:</line>
            <line>Half all Cominius' honours are to Marcius.</line>
            <line>Though Marcius earned them not, and all his faults</line>
            <line>To Marcius shall be honours, though indeed</line>
            <line>In aught he merit not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SICINIUS</speaker>
            <line>Let's hence, and hear</line>
            <line>How the dispatch is made, and in what fashion,</line>
            <line>More than his singularity, he goes</line>
            <line>Upon this present action.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>Lets along.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  Corioli. The Senate-house.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter TULLUS AUFIDIUS and certain Senators</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>So, your opinion is, Aufidius,</line>
            <line>That they of Rome are entered in our counsels</line>
            <line>And know how we proceed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUFIDIUS</speaker>
            <line>Is it not yours?</line>
            <line>What ever have been thought on in this state,</line>
            <line>That could be brought to bodily act ere Rome</line>
            <line>Had circumvention? 'Tis not four days gone</line>
            <line>Since I heard thence; these are the words: I think</line>
            <line>I have the letter here; yes, here it is.</line>
            <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>
            <line>'They have press'd a power, but it is not known</line>
            <line>Whether for east or west: the dearth is great;</line>
            <line>The people mutinous; and it is rumour'd,</line>
            <line>Cominius, Marcius your old enemy,</line>
            <line>Who is of Rome worse hated than of you,</line>
            <line>And Titus Lartius, a most valiant Roman,</line>
            <line>These three lead on this preparation</line>
            <line>Whither 'tis bent: most likely 'tis for you:</line>
            <line>Consider of it.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>Our army's in the field</line>
            <line>We never yet made doubt but Rome was ready</line>
            <line>To answer us.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUFIDIUS</speaker>
            <line>Nor did you think it folly</line>
            <line>To keep your great pretences veil'd till when</line>
            <line>They needs must show themselves; which</line>
            <line>in the hatching,</line>
            <line>It seem'd, appear'd to Rome. By the discovery.</line>
            <line>We shall be shorten'd in our aim, which was</line>
            <line>To take in many towns ere almost Rome</line>
            <line>Should know we were afoot.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Senator</speaker>
            <line>Noble Aufidius,</line>
            <line>Take your commission; hie you to your bands:</line>
            <line>Let us alone to guard Corioli:</line>
            <line>If they set down before 's, for the remove</line>
            <line>Bring your army; but, I think, you'll find</line>
            <line>They've not prepared for us.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUFIDIUS</speaker>
            <line>O, doubt not that;</line>
            <line>I speak from certainties. Nay, more,</line>
            <line>Some parcels of their power are forth already,</line>
            <line>And only hitherward. I leave your honours.</line>
            <line>If we and Caius Marcius chance to meet,</line>
            <line>'Tis sworn between us we shall ever strike</line>
            <line>Till one can do no more.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>All</speaker>
            <line>The gods assist you!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUFIDIUS</speaker>
            <line>And keep your honours safe!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>Farewell.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Senator</speaker>
            <line>Farewell.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>All</speaker>
            <line>Farewell.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  Rome. A room in Marcius' house.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter VOLUMNIA and VIRGILIA they set them down
on two low stools, and sew</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VOLUMNIA</speaker>
            <line>I pray you, daughter, sing; or express yourself in a</line>
            <line>more comfortable sort: if my son were my husband, I</line>
            <line>should freelier rejoice in that absence wherein he</line>
            <line>won honour than in the embracements of his bed where</line>
            <line>he would show most love. When yet he was but</line>
            <line>tender-bodied and the only son of my womb, when</line>
            <line>youth with comeliness plucked all gaze his way, when</line>
            <line>for a day of kings' entreaties a mother should not</line>
            <line>sell him an hour from her beholding, I, considering</line>
            <line>how honour would become such a person. that it was</line>
            <line>no better than picture-like to hang by the wall, if</line>
            <line>renown made it not stir, was pleased to let him seek</line>
            <line>danger where he was like to find fame. To a cruel</line>
            <line>war I sent him; from whence he returned, his brows</line>
            <line>bound with oak. I tell thee, daughter, I sprang not</line>
            <line>more in joy at first hearing he was a man-child</line>
            <line>than now in first seeing he had proved himself a</line>
            <line>man.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIRGILIA</speaker>
            <line>But had he died in the business, madam; how then?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VOLUMNIA</speaker>
            <line>Then his good report should have been my son; I</line>
            <line>therein would have found issue. Hear me profess</line>
            <line>sincerely: had I a dozen sons, each in my love</line>
            <line>alike and none less dear than thine and my good</line>
            <line>Marcius, I had rather had eleven die nobly for their</line>
            <line>country than one voluptuously surfeit out of action.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter a Gentlewoman</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Gentlewoman</speaker>
            <line>Madam, the Lady Valeria is come to visit you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIRGILIA</speaker>
            <line>Beseech you, give me leave to retire myself.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VOLUMNIA</speaker>
            <line>Indeed, you shall not.</line>
            <line>Methinks I hear hither your husband's drum,</line>
            <line>See him pluck Aufidius down by the hair,</line>
            <line>As children from a bear, the Volsces shunning him:</line>
            <line>Methinks I see him stamp thus, and call thus:</line>
            <line>'Come on, you cowards! you were got in fear,</line>
            <line>Though you were born in Rome:' his bloody brow</line>
            <line>With his mail'd hand then wiping, forth he goes,</line>
            <line>Like to a harvest-man that's task'd to mow</line>
            <line>Or all or lose his hire.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIRGILIA</speaker>
            <line>His bloody brow! O Jupiter, no blood!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VOLUMNIA</speaker>
            <line>Away, you fool! it more becomes a man</line>
            <line>Than gilt his trophy: the breasts of Hecuba,</line>
            <line>When she did suckle Hector, look'd not lovelier</line>
            <line>Than Hector's forehead when it spit forth blood</line>
            <line>At Grecian sword, contemning. Tell Valeria,</line>
            <line>We are fit to bid her welcome.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit Gentlewoman</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIRGILIA</speaker>
            <line>Heavens bless my lord from fell Aufidius!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VOLUMNIA</speaker>
            <line>He'll beat Aufidius 'head below his knee</line>
            <line>And tread upon his neck.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter VALERIA, with an Usher and Gentlewoman</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VALERIA</speaker>
            <line>My ladies both, good day to you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VOLUMNIA</speaker>
            <line>Sweet madam.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIRGILIA</speaker>
            <line>I am glad to see your ladyship.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VALERIA</speaker>
            <line>How do you both? you are manifest house-keepers.</line>
            <line>What are you sewing here? A fine spot, in good</line>
            <line>faith. How does your little son?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIRGILIA</speaker>
            <line>I thank your ladyship; well, good madam.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VOLUMNIA</speaker>
            <line>He had rather see the swords, and hear a drum, than</line>
            <line>look upon his school-master.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VALERIA</speaker>
            <line>O' my word, the father's son: I'll swear,'tis a</line>
            <line>very pretty boy. O' my troth, I looked upon him o'</line>
            <line>Wednesday half an hour together: has such a</line>
            <line>confirmed countenance. I saw him run after a gilded</line>
            <line>butterfly: and when he caught it, he let it go</line>
            <line>again; and after it again; and over and over he</line>
            <line>comes, and again; catched it again; or whether his</line>
            <line>fall enraged him, or how 'twas, he did so set his</line>
            <line>teeth and tear it; O, I warrant it, how he mammocked</line>
            <line>it!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VOLUMNIA</speaker>
            <line>One on 's father's moods.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VALERIA</speaker>
            <line>Indeed, la, 'tis a noble child.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIRGILIA</speaker>
            <line>A crack, madam.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VALERIA</speaker>
            <line>Come, lay aside your stitchery; I must have you play</line>
            <line>the idle husewife with me this afternoon.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIRGILIA</speaker>
            <line>No, good madam; I will not out of doors.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VALERIA</speaker>
            <line>Not out of doors!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VOLUMNIA</speaker>
            <line>She shall, she shall.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIRGILIA</speaker>
            <line>Indeed, no, by your patience; I'll not over the</line>
            <line>threshold till my lord return from the wars.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VALERIA</speaker>
            <line>Fie, you confine yourself most unreasonably: come,</line>
            <line>you must go visit the good lady that lies in.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIRGILIA</speaker>
            <line>I will wish her speedy strength, and visit her with</line>
            <line>my prayers; but I cannot go thither.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VOLUMNIA</speaker>
            <line>Why, I pray you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIRGILIA</speaker>
            <line>'Tis not to save labour, nor that I want love.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VALERIA</speaker>
            <line>You would be another Penelope: yet, they say, all</line>
            <line>the yarn she spun in Ulysses' absence did but fill</line>
            <line>Ithaca full of moths. Come; I would your cambric</line>
            <line>were sensible as your finger, that you might leave</line>
            <line>pricking it for pity. Come, you shall go with us.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIRGILIA</speaker>
            <line>No, good madam, pardon me; indeed, I will not forth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VALERIA</speaker>
            <line>In truth, la, go with me; and I'll tell you</line>
            <line>excellent news of your husband.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIRGILIA</speaker>
            <line>O, good madam, there can be none yet.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VALERIA</speaker>
            <line>Verily, I do not jest with you; there came news from</line>
            <line>him last night.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIRGILIA</speaker>
            <line>Indeed, madam?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VALERIA</speaker>
            <line>In earnest, it's true; I heard a senator speak it.</line>
            <line>Thus it is: the Volsces have an army forth; against</line>
            <line>whom Cominius the general is gone, with one part of</line>
            <line>our Roman power: your lord and Titus Lartius are set</line>
            <line>down before their city Corioli; they nothing doubt</line>
            <line>prevailing and to make it brief wars. This is true,</line>
            <line>on mine honour; and so, I pray, go with us.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIRGILIA</speaker>
            <line>Give me excuse, good madam; I will obey you in every</line>
            <line>thing hereafter.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VOLUMNIA</speaker>
            <line>Let her alone, lady: as she is now, she will but</line>
            <line>disease our better mirth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VALERIA</speaker>
            <line>In troth, I think she would. Fare you well, then.</line>
            <line>Come, good sweet lady. Prithee, Virgilia, turn thy</line>
            <line>solemness out o' door. and go along with us.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIRGILIA</speaker>
            <line>No, at a word, madam; indeed, I must not. I wish</line>
            <line>you much mirth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VALERIA</speaker>
            <line>Well, then, farewell.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-4">
      <title>SCENE IV.  Before Corioli.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter, with drum and colours, MARCIUS, TITUS
LARTIUS, Captains and Soldiers. To them a
Messenger</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCIUS</speaker>
            <line>Yonder comes news. A wager they have met.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LARTIUS</speaker>
            <line>My horse to yours, no.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCIUS</speaker>
            <line>'Tis done.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LARTIUS</speaker>
            <line>Agreed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCIUS</speaker>
            <line>Say, has our general met the enemy?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>They lie in view; but have not spoke as yet.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LARTIUS</speaker>
            <line>So, the good horse is mine.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCIUS</speaker>
            <line>I'll buy him of you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LARTIUS</speaker>
            <line>No, I'll nor sell nor give him: lend you him I will</line>
            <line>For half a hundred years. Summon the town.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCIUS</speaker>
            <line>How far off lie these armies?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>Within this mile and half.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCIUS</speaker>
            <line>Then shall we hear their 'larum, and they ours.</line>
            <line>Now, Mars, I prithee, make us quick in work,</line>
            <line>That we with smoking swords may march from hence,</line>
            <line>To help our fielded friends! Come, blow thy blast.</line>
            <stagedir>They sound a parley. Enter two Senators with others
on the walls</stagedir>
            <line>Tutus Aufidius, is he within your walls?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>No, nor a man that fears you less than he,</line>
            <line>That's lesser than a little.</line>
            <stagedir>Drums afar off</stagedir>
            <line>Hark! our drums</line>
            <line>Are bringing forth our youth. We'll break our walls,</line>
            <line>Rather than they shall pound us up: our gates,</line>
            <line>Which yet seem shut, we, have but pinn'd with rushes;</line>
            <line>They'll open of themselves.</line>
            <stagedir>Alarum afar off</stagedir>
            <line>Hark you. far off!</line>
            <line>There is Aufidius; list, what work he makes</line>
            <line>Amongst your cloven army.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCIUS</speaker>
            <line>O, they are at it!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LARTIUS</speaker>
            <line>Their noise be our instruction. Ladders, ho!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter the army of the Volsces</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCIUS</speaker>
            <line>They fear us not, but issue forth their city.</line>
            <line>Now put your shields before your hearts, and fight</line>
            <line>With hearts more proof than shields. Advance,</line>
            <line>brave Titus:</line>
            <line>They do disdain us much beyond our thoughts,</line>
            <line>Which makes me sweat with wrath. Come on, my fellows:</line>
            <line>He that retires I'll take him for a Volsce,</line>
            <line>And he shall feel mine edge.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Alarum. The Romans are beat back to their
trenches. Re-enter MARCIUS cursing</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCIUS</speaker>
            <line>All the contagion of the south light on you,</line>
            <line>You shames of Rome! you herd of--Boils and plagues</line>
            <line>Plaster you o'er, that you may be abhorr'd</line>
            <line>Further than seen and one infect another</line>
            <line>Against the wind a mile! You souls of geese,</line>
            <line>That bear the shapes of men, how have you run</line>
            <line>From slaves that apes would beat! Pluto and hell!</line>
            <line>All hurt behind; backs red, and faces pale</line>
            <line>With flight and agued fear! Mend and charge home,</line>
            <line>Or, by the fires of heaven, I'll leave the foe</line>
            <line>And make my wars on you: look to't: come on;</line>
            <line>If you'll stand fast, we'll beat them to their wives,</line>
            <line>As they us to our trenches followed.</line>
            <stagedir>Another alarum. The Volsces fly, and MARCIUS
follows them to the gates</stagedir>
            <line>So, now the gates are ope: now prove good seconds:</line>
            <line>'Tis for the followers fortune widens them,</line>
            <line>Not for the fliers: mark me, and do the like.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enters the gates</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Soldier</speaker>
            <line>Fool-hardiness; not I.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Soldier</speaker>
            <line>Nor I.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>MARCIUS is shut in</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Soldier</speaker>
            <line>See, they have shut him in.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>All</speaker>
            <line>To the pot, I warrant him.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Alarum continues</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Re-enter TITUS LARTIUS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LARTIUS</speaker>
            <line>What is become of Marcius?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>All</speaker>
            <line>Slain, sir, doubtless.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Soldier</speaker>
            <line>Following the fliers at the very heels,</line>
            <line>With them he enters; who, upon the sudden,</line>
            <line>Clapp'd to their gates: he is himself alone,</line>
            <line>To answer all the city.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LARTIUS</speaker>
            <line>O noble fellow!</line>
            <line>Who sensibly outdares his senseless sword,</line>
            <line>And, when it bows, stands up. Thou art left, Marcius:</line>
            <line>A carbuncle entire, as big as thou art,</line>
            <line>Were not so rich a jewel. Thou wast a soldier</line>
            <line>Even to Cato's wish, not fierce and terrible</line>
            <line>Only in strokes; but, with thy grim looks and</line>
            <line>The thunder-like percussion of thy sounds,</line>
            <line>Thou madst thine enemies shake, as if the world</line>
            <line>Were feverous and did tremble.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter MARCIUS, bleeding, assaulted by the enemy</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Soldier</speaker>
            <line>Look, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LARTIUS</speaker>
            <line>O,'tis Marcius!</line>
            <line>Let's fetch him off, or make remain alike.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>They fight, and all enter the city</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-5">
      <title>SCENE V.  Corioli. A street.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter certain Romans, with spoils</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Roman</speaker>
            <line>This will I carry to Rome.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Roman</speaker>
            <line>And I this.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Roman</speaker>
            <line>A murrain on't! I took this for silver.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Alarum continues still afar off</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Enter MARCIUS and TITUS LARTIUS with a trumpet</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCIUS</speaker>
            <line>See here these movers that do prize their hours</line>
            <line>At a crack'd drachm! Cushions, leaden spoons,</line>
            <line>Irons of a doit, doublets that hangmen would</line>
            <line>Bury with those that wore them, these base slaves,</line>
            <line>Ere yet the fight be done, pack up: down with them!</line>
            <line>And hark, what noise the general makes! To him!</line>
            <line>There is the man of my soul's hate, Aufidius,</line>
            <line>Piercing our Romans: then, valiant Titus, take</line>
            <line>Convenient numbers to make good the city;</line>
            <line>Whilst I, with those that have the spirit, will haste</line>
            <line>To help Cominius.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LARTIUS</speaker>
            <line>Worthy sir, thou bleed'st;</line>
            <line>Thy exercise hath been too violent for</line>
            <line>A second course of fight.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCIUS</speaker>
            <line>Sir, praise me not;</line>
            <line>My work hath yet not warm'd me: fare you well:</line>
            <line>The blood I drop is rather physical</line>
            <line>Than dangerous to me: to Aufidius thus</line>
            <line>I will appear, and fight.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LARTIUS</speaker>
            <line>Now the fair goddess, Fortune,</line>
            <line>Fall deep in love with thee; and her great charms</line>
            <line>Misguide thy opposers' swords! Bold gentleman,</line>
            <line>Prosperity be thy page!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCIUS</speaker>
            <line>Thy friend no less</line>
            <line>Than those she placeth highest! So, farewell.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LARTIUS</speaker>
            <line>Thou worthiest Marcius!</line>
            <stagedir>Exit MARCIUS</stagedir>
            <line>Go, sound thy trumpet in the market-place;</line>
            <line>Call thither all the officers o' the town,</line>
            <line>Where they shall know our mind: away!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-6">
      <title>SCENE VI.  Near the camp of Cominius.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter COMINIUS, as it were in retire,
with soldiers</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COMINIUS</speaker>
            <line>Breathe you, my friends: well fought;</line>
            <line>we are come off</line>
            <line>Like Romans, neither foolish in our stands,</line>
            <line>Nor cowardly in retire: believe me, sirs,</line>
            <line>We shall be charged again. Whiles we have struck,</line>
            <line>By interims and conveying gusts we have heard</line>
            <line>The charges of our friends. Ye Roman gods!</line>
            <line>Lead their successes as we wish our own,</line>
            <line>That both our powers, with smiling</line>
            <line>fronts encountering,</line>
            <line>May give you thankful sacrifice.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter a Messenger</stagedir>
            <line>Thy news?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>The citizens of Corioli have issued,</line>
            <line>And given to Lartius and to Marcius battle:</line>
            <line>I saw our party to their trenches driven,</line>
            <line>And then I came away.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COMINIUS</speaker>
            <line>Though thou speak'st truth,</line>
            <line>Methinks thou speak'st not well.</line>
            <line>How long is't since?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>Above an hour, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COMINIUS</speaker>
            <line>'Tis not a mile; briefly we heard their drums:</line>
            <line>How couldst thou in a mile confound an hour,</line>
            <line>And bring thy news so late?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>Spies of the Volsces</line>
            <line>Held me in chase, that I was forced to wheel</line>
            <line>Three or four miles about, else had I, sir,</line>
            <line>Half an hour since brought my report.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COMINIUS</speaker>
            <line>Who's yonder,</line>
            <line>That does appear as he were flay'd? O gods</line>
            <line>He has the stamp of Marcius; and I have</line>
            <line>Before-time seen him thus.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCIUS</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Within</stagedir>                 Come I too late?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COMINIUS</speaker>
            <line>The shepherd knows not thunder from a tabour</line>
            <line>More than I know the sound of Marcius' tongue</line>
            <line>From every meaner man.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter MARCIUS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCIUS</speaker>
            <line>Come I too late?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COMINIUS</speaker>
            <line>Ay, if you come not in the blood of others,</line>
            <line>But mantled in your own.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCIUS</speaker>
            <line>O, let me clip ye</line>
            <line>In arms as sound as when I woo'd, in heart</line>
            <line>As merry as when our nuptial day was done,</line>
            <line>And tapers burn'd to bedward!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COMINIUS</speaker>
            <line>Flower of warriors,</line>
            <line>How is it with Titus Lartius?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCIUS</speaker>
            <line>As with a man busied about decrees:</line>
            <line>Condemning some to death, and some to exile;</line>
            <line>Ransoming him, or pitying, threatening the other;</line>
            <line>Holding Corioli in the name of Rome,</line>
            <line>Even like a fawning greyhound in the leash,</line>
            <line>To let him slip at will.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COMINIUS</speaker>
            <line>Where is that slave</line>
            <line>Which told me they had beat you to your trenches?</line>
            <line>Where is he? call him hither.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCIUS</speaker>
            <line>Let him alone;</line>
            <line>He did inform the truth: but for our gentlemen,</line>
            <line>The common file--a plague! tribunes for them!--</line>
            <line>The mouse ne'er shunn'd the cat as they did budge</line>
            <line>From rascals worse than they.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COMINIUS</speaker>
            <line>But how prevail'd you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCIUS</speaker>
            <line>Will the time serve to tell? I do not think.</line>
            <line>Where is the enemy? are you lords o' the field?</line>
            <line>If not, why cease you till you are so?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COMINIUS</speaker>
            <line>Marcius,</line>
            <line>We have at disadvantage fought and did</line>
            <line>Retire to win our purpose.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCIUS</speaker>
            <line>How lies their battle? know you on which side</line>
            <line>They have placed their men of trust?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COMINIUS</speaker>
            <line>As I guess, Marcius,</line>
            <line>Their bands i' the vaward are the Antiates,</line>
            <line>Of their best trust; o'er them Aufidius,</line>
            <line>Their very heart of hope.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCIUS</speaker>
            <line>I do beseech you,</line>
            <line>By all the battles wherein we have fought,</line>
            <line>By the blood we have shed together, by the vows</line>
            <line>We have made to endure friends, that you directly</line>
            <line>Set me against Aufidius and his Antiates;</line>
            <line>And that you not delay the present, but,</line>
            <line>Filling the air with swords advanced and darts,</line>
            <line>We prove this very hour.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COMINIUS</speaker>
            <line>Though I could wish</line>
            <line>You were conducted to a gentle bath</line>
            <line>And balms applied to, you, yet dare I never</line>
            <line>Deny your asking: take your choice of those</line>
            <line>That best can aid your action.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCIUS</speaker>
            <line>Those are they</line>
            <line>That most are willing. If any such be here--</line>
            <line>As it were sin to doubt--that love this painting</line>
            <line>Wherein you see me smear'd; if any fear</line>
            <line>Lesser his person than an ill report;</line>
            <line>If any think brave death outweighs bad life</line>
            <line>And that his country's dearer than himself;</line>
            <line>Let him alone, or so many so minded,</line>
            <line>Wave thus, to express his disposition,</line>
            <line>And follow Marcius.</line>
            <stagedir>They all shout and wave their swords, take him up in
their arms, and cast up their caps</stagedir>
            <line>O, me alone! make you a sword of me?</line>
            <line>If these shows be not outward, which of you</line>
            <line>But is four Volsces? none of you but is</line>
            <line>Able to bear against the great Aufidius</line>
            <line>A shield as hard as his. A certain number,</line>
            <line>Though thanks to all, must I select</line>
            <line>from all: the rest</line>
            <line>Shall bear the business in some other fight,</line>
            <line>As cause will be obey'd. Please you to march;</line>
            <line>And four shall quickly draw out my command,</line>
            <line>Which men are best inclined.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COMINIUS</speaker>
            <line>March on, my fellows:</line>
            <line>Make good this ostentation, and you shall</line>
            <line>Divide in all with us.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-7">
      <title>SCENE VII.  The gates of Corioli.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>TITUS LARTIUS, having set a guard upon
Corioli, going with drum and trumpet toward
COMINIUS and CAIUS MARCIUS, enters with
Lieutenant, other Soldiers, and a Scout</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LARTIUS</speaker>
            <line>So, let the ports be guarded: keep your duties,</line>
            <line>As I have set them down. If I do send, dispatch</line>
            <line>Those centuries to our aid: the rest will serve</line>
            <line>For a short holding: if we lose the field,</line>
            <line>We cannot keep the town.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lieutenant</speaker>
            <line>Fear not our care, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LARTIUS</speaker>
            <line>Hence, and shut your gates upon's.</line>
            <line>Our guider, come; to the Roman camp conduct us.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-8">
      <title>SCENE VIII.  A field of battle.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Alarum as in battle. Enter, from opposite sides,
MARCIUS and AUFIDIUS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCIUS</speaker>
            <line>I'll fight with none but thee; for I do hate thee</line>
            <line>Worse than a promise-breaker.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUFIDIUS</speaker>
            <line>We hate alike:</line>
            <line>Not Afric owns a serpent I abhor</line>
            <line>More than thy fame and envy. Fix thy foot.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCIUS</speaker>
            <line>Let the first budger die the other's slave,</line>
            <line>And the gods doom him after!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUFIDIUS</speaker>
            <line>If I fly, Marcius,</line>
            <line>Holloa me like a hare.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCIUS</speaker>
            <line>Within these three hours, Tullus,</line>
            <line>Alone I fought in your Corioli walls,</line>
            <line>And made what work I pleased: 'tis not my blood</line>
            <line>Wherein thou seest me mask'd; for thy revenge</line>
            <line>Wrench up thy power to the highest.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUFIDIUS</speaker>
            <line>Wert thou the Hector</line>
            <line>That was the whip of your bragg'd progeny,</line>
            <line>Thou shouldst not scape me here.</line>
            <stagedir>They fight, and certain Volsces come to the aid of
AUFIDIUS. MARCIUS fights till they be driven in
breathless</stagedir>
            <line>Officious, and not valiant, you have shamed me</line>
            <line>In your condemned seconds.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-9">
      <title>SCENE IX.  The Roman camp.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Flourish. Alarum. A retreat is sounded. Flourish.
Enter, from one side, COMINIUS with the Romans; from
the other side, MARCIUS, with his arm in a scarf</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COMINIUS</speaker>
            <line>If I should tell thee o'er this thy day's work,</line>
            <line>Thou'ldst not believe thy deeds: but I'll report it</line>
            <line>Where senators shall mingle tears with smiles,</line>
            <line>Where great patricians shall attend and shrug,</line>
            <line>I' the end admire, where ladies shall be frighted,</line>
            <line>And, gladly quaked, hear more; where the</line>
            <line>dull tribunes,</line>
            <line>That, with the fusty plebeians, hate thine honours,</line>
            <line>Shall say against their hearts 'We thank the gods</line>
            <line>Our Rome hath such a soldier.'</line>
            <line>Yet camest thou to a morsel of this feast,</line>
            <line>Having fully dined before.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter TITUS LARTIUS, with his power,
from the pursuit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LARTIUS</speaker>
            <line>O general,</line>
            <line>Here is the steed, we the caparison:</line>
            <line>Hadst thou beheld--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCIUS</speaker>
            <line>Pray now, no more: my mother,</line>
            <line>Who has a charter to extol her blood,</line>
            <line>When she does praise me grieves me. I have done</line>
            <line>As you have done; that's what I can; induced</line>
            <line>As you have been; that's for my country:</line>
            <line>He that has but effected his good will</line>
            <line>Hath overta'en mine act.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COMINIUS</speaker>
            <line>You shall not be</line>
            <line>The grave of your deserving; Rome must know</line>
            <line>The value of her own: 'twere a concealment</line>
            <line>Worse than a theft, no less than a traducement,</line>
            <line>To hide your doings; and to silence that,</line>
            <line>Which, to the spire and top of praises vouch'd,</line>
            <line>Would seem but modest: therefore, I beseech you</line>
            <line>In sign of what you are, not to reward</line>
            <line>What you have done--before our army hear me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCIUS</speaker>
            <line>I have some wounds upon me, and they smart</line>
            <line>To hear themselves remember'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COMINIUS</speaker>
            <line>Should they not,</line>
            <line>Well might they fester 'gainst ingratitude,</line>
            <line>And tent themselves with death. Of all the horses,</line>
            <line>Whereof we have ta'en good and good store, of all</line>
            <line>The treasure in this field achieved and city,</line>
            <line>We render you the tenth, to be ta'en forth,</line>
            <line>Before the common distribution, at</line>
            <line>Your only choice.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCIUS</speaker>
            <line>I thank you, general;</line>
            <line>But cannot make my heart consent to take</line>
            <line>A bribe to pay my sword: I do refuse it;</line>
            <line>And stand upon my common part with those</line>
            <line>That have beheld the doing.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>A long flourish. They all cry 'Marcius! Marcius!'
cast up their caps and lances: COMINIUS and LARTIUS
stand bare</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCIUS</speaker>
            <line>May these same instruments, which you profane,</line>
            <line>Never sound more! when drums and trumpets shall</line>
            <line>I' the field prove flatterers, let courts and cities be</line>
            <line>Made all of false-faced soothing!</line>
            <line>When steel grows soft as the parasite's silk,</line>
            <line>Let him be made a coverture for the wars!</line>
            <line>No more, I say! For that I have not wash'd</line>
            <line>My nose that bled, or foil'd some debile wretch.--</line>
            <line>Which, without note, here's many else have done,--</line>
            <line>You shout me forth</line>
            <line>In acclamations hyperbolical;</line>
            <line>As if I loved my little should be dieted</line>
            <line>In praises sauced with lies.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COMINIUS</speaker>
            <line>Too modest are you;</line>
            <line>More cruel to your good report than grateful</line>
            <line>To us that give you truly: by your patience,</line>
            <line>If 'gainst yourself you be incensed, we'll put you,</line>
            <line>Like one that means his proper harm, in manacles,</line>
            <line>Then reason safely with you. Therefore, be it known,</line>
            <line>As to us, to all the world, that Caius Marcius</line>
            <line>Wears this war's garland: in token of the which,</line>
            <line>My noble steed, known to the camp, I give him,</line>
            <line>With all his trim belonging; and from this time,</line>
            <line>For what he did before Corioli, call him,</line>
            <line>With all the applause and clamour of the host,</line>
            <line>CAIUS MARCIUS CORIOLANUS! Bear</line>
            <line>The addition nobly ever!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Flourish. Trumpets sound, and drums</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>All</speaker>
            <line>Caius Marcius Coriolanus!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>I will go wash;</line>
            <line>And when my face is fair, you shall perceive</line>
            <line>Whether I blush or no: howbeit, I thank you.</line>
            <line>I mean to stride your steed, and at all times</line>
            <line>To undercrest your good addition</line>
            <line>To the fairness of my power.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COMINIUS</speaker>
            <line>So, to our tent;</line>
            <line>Where, ere we do repose us, we will write</line>
            <line>To Rome of our success. You, Titus Lartius,</line>
            <line>Must to Corioli back: send us to Rome</line>
            <line>The best, with whom we may articulate,</line>
            <line>For their own good and ours.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LARTIUS</speaker>
            <line>I shall, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>The gods begin to mock me. I, that now</line>
            <line>Refused most princely gifts, am bound to beg</line>
            <line>Of my lord general.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COMINIUS</speaker>
            <line>Take't; 'tis yours. What is't?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>I sometime lay here in Corioli</line>
            <line>At a poor man's house; he used me kindly:</line>
            <line>He cried to me; I saw him prisoner;</line>
            <line>But then Aufidius was within my view,</line>
            <line>And wrath o'erwhelm'd my pity: I request you</line>
            <line>To give my poor host freedom.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COMINIUS</speaker>
            <line>O, well begg'd!</line>
            <line>Were he the butcher of my son, he should</line>
            <line>Be free as is the wind. Deliver him, Titus.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LARTIUS</speaker>
            <line>Marcius, his name?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>By Jupiter! forgot.</line>
            <line>I am weary; yea, my memory is tired.</line>
            <line>Have we no wine here?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COMINIUS</speaker>
            <line>Go we to our tent:</line>
            <line>The blood upon your visage dries; 'tis time</line>
            <line>It should be look'd to: come.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-10">
      <title>SCENE X.  The camp of the Volsces.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>A flourish. Cornets. Enter TULLUS AUFIDIUS,
bloody, with two or three Soldiers</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUFIDIUS</speaker>
            <line>The town is ta'en!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Soldier</speaker>
            <line>'Twill be deliver'd back on good condition.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUFIDIUS</speaker>
            <line>Condition!</line>
            <line>I would I were a Roman; for I cannot,</line>
            <line>Being a Volsce, be that I am. Condition!</line>
            <line>What good condition can a treaty find</line>
            <line>I' the part that is at mercy? Five times, Marcius,</line>
            <line>I have fought with thee: so often hast thou beat me,</line>
            <line>And wouldst do so, I think, should we encounter</line>
            <line>As often as we eat. By the elements,</line>
            <line>If e'er again I meet him beard to beard,</line>
            <line>He's mine, or I am his: mine emulation</line>
            <line>Hath not that honour in't it had; for where</line>
            <line>I thought to crush him in an equal force,</line>
            <line>True sword to sword, I'll potch at him some way</line>
            <line>Or wrath or craft may get him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Soldier</speaker>
            <line>He's the devil.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUFIDIUS</speaker>
            <line>Bolder, though not so subtle. My valour's poison'd</line>
            <line>With only suffering stain by him; for him</line>
            <line>Shall fly out of itself: nor sleep nor sanctuary,</line>
            <line>Being naked, sick, nor fane nor Capitol,</line>
            <line>The prayers of priests nor times of sacrifice,</line>
            <line>Embarquements all of fury, shall lift up</line>
            <line>Their rotten privilege and custom 'gainst</line>
            <line>My hate to Marcius: where I find him, were it</line>
            <line>At home, upon my brother's guard, even there,</line>
            <line>Against the hospitable canon, would I</line>
            <line>Wash my fierce hand in's heart. Go you to the city;</line>
            <line>Learn how 'tis held; and what they are that must</line>
            <line>Be hostages for Rome.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Soldier</speaker>
            <line>Will not you go?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUFIDIUS</speaker>
            <line>I am attended at the cypress grove: I pray you--</line>
            <line>'Tis south the city mills--bring me word thither</line>
            <line>How the world goes, that to the pace of it</line>
            <line>I may spur on my journey.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Soldier</speaker>
            <line>I shall, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>