<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:shakespear:dtd:act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-2">
   <title>ACT II</title>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  Rome. A public place.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter MENENIUS with the two Tribunes of the people,
SICINIUS and BRUTUS.</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>The augurer tells me we shall have news to-night.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>Good or bad?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>Not according to the prayer of the people, for they</line>
            <line>love not Marcius.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SICINIUS</speaker>
            <line>Nature teaches beasts to know their friends.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>Pray you, who does the wolf love?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SICINIUS</speaker>
            <line>The lamb.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>Ay, to devour him; as the hungry plebeians would the</line>
            <line>noble Marcius.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>He's a lamb indeed, that baes like a bear.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>He's a bear indeed, that lives like a lamb. You two</line>
            <line>are old men: tell me one thing that I shall ask you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Both</speaker>
            <line>Well, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>In what enormity is Marcius poor in, that you two</line>
            <line>have not in abundance?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>He's poor in no one fault, but stored with all.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SICINIUS</speaker>
            <line>Especially in pride.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>And topping all others in boasting.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>This is strange now: do you two know how you are</line>
            <line>censured here in the city, I mean of us o' the</line>
            <line>right-hand file? do you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Both</speaker>
            <line>Why, how are we censured?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>Because you talk of pride now,--will you not be angry?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Both</speaker>
            <line>Well, well, sir, well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>Why, 'tis no great matter; for a very little thief of</line>
            <line>occasion will rob you of a great deal of patience:</line>
            <line>give your dispositions the reins, and be angry at</line>
            <line>your pleasures; at the least if you take it as a</line>
            <line>pleasure to you in being so. You blame Marcius for</line>
            <line>being proud?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>We do it not alone, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>I know you can do very little alone; for your helps</line>
            <line>are many, or else your actions would grow wondrous</line>
            <line>single: your abilities are too infant-like for</line>
            <line>doing much alone. You talk of pride: O that you</line>
            <line>could turn your eyes toward the napes of your necks,</line>
            <line>and make but an interior survey of your good selves!</line>
            <line>O that you could!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>What then, sir?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>Why, then you should discover a brace of unmeriting,</line>
            <line>proud, violent, testy magistrates, alias fools, as</line>
            <line>any in Rome.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SICINIUS</speaker>
            <line>Menenius, you are known well enough too.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>I am known to be a humorous patrician, and one that</line>
            <line>loves a cup of hot wine with not a drop of allaying</line>
            <line>Tiber in't; said to be something imperfect in</line>
            <line>favouring the first complaint; hasty and tinder-like</line>
            <line>upon too trivial motion; one that converses more</line>
            <line>with the buttock of the night than with the forehead</line>
            <line>of the morning: what I think I utter, and spend my</line>
            <line>malice in my breath. Meeting two such wealsmen as</line>
            <line>you are--I cannot call you Lycurguses--if the drink</line>
            <line>you give me touch my palate adversely, I make a</line>
            <line>crooked face at it. I can't say your worships have</line>
            <line>delivered the matter well, when I find the ass in</line>
            <line>compound with the major part of your syllables: and</line>
            <line>though I must be content to bear with those that say</line>
            <line>you are reverend grave men, yet they lie deadly that</line>
            <line>tell you you have good faces. If you see this in</line>
            <line>the map of my microcosm, follows it that I am known</line>
            <line>well enough too? what barm can your bisson</line>
            <line>conspectuities glean out of this character, if I be</line>
            <line>known well enough too?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>Come, sir, come, we know you well enough.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>You know neither me, yourselves nor any thing. You</line>
            <line>are ambitious for poor knaves' caps and legs: you</line>
            <line>wear out a good wholesome forenoon in hearing a</line>
            <line>cause between an orange wife and a fosset-seller;</line>
            <line>and then rejourn the controversy of three pence to a</line>
            <line>second day of audience. When you are hearing a</line>
            <line>matter between party and party, if you chance to be</line>
            <line>pinched with the colic, you make faces like</line>
            <line>mummers; set up the bloody flag against all</line>
            <line>patience; and, in roaring for a chamber-pot,</line>
            <line>dismiss the controversy bleeding the more entangled</line>
            <line>by your hearing: all the peace you make in their</line>
            <line>cause is, calling both the parties knaves. You are</line>
            <line>a pair of strange ones.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>Come, come, you are well understood to be a</line>
            <line>perfecter giber for the table than a necessary</line>
            <line>bencher in the Capitol.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>Our very priests must become mockers, if they shall</line>
            <line>encounter such ridiculous subjects as you are. When</line>
            <line>you speak best unto the purpose, it is not worth the</line>
            <line>wagging of your beards; and your beards deserve not</line>
            <line>so honourable a grave as to stuff a botcher's</line>
            <line>cushion, or to be entombed in an ass's pack-</line>
            <line>saddle. Yet you must be saying, Marcius is proud;</line>
            <line>who in a cheap estimation, is worth predecessors</line>
            <line>since Deucalion, though peradventure some of the</line>
            <line>best of 'em were hereditary hangmen. God-den to</line>
            <line>your worships: more of your conversation would</line>
            <line>infect my brain, being the herdsmen of the beastly</line>
            <line>plebeians: I will be bold to take my leave of you.</line>
            <stagedir>BRUTUS and SICINIUS go aside</stagedir>
            <stagedir>Enter VOLUMNIA, VIRGILIA, and VALERIA</stagedir>
            <line>How now, my as fair as noble ladies,--and the moon,</line>
            <line>were she earthly, no nobler,--whither do you follow</line>
            <line>your eyes so fast?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VOLUMNIA</speaker>
            <line>Honourable Menenius, my boy Marcius approaches; for</line>
            <line>the love of Juno, let's go.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>Ha! Marcius coming home!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VOLUMNIA</speaker>
            <line>Ay, worthy Menenius; and with most prosperous</line>
            <line>approbation.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>Take my cap, Jupiter, and I thank thee. Hoo!</line>
            <line>Marcius coming home!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VOLUMNIA</speaker>
            <speaker>VIRGILIA</speaker>
            <line>Nay,'tis true.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VOLUMNIA</speaker>
            <line>Look, here's a letter from him: the state hath</line>
            <line>another, his wife another; and, I think, there's one</line>
            <line>at home for you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>I will make my very house reel tonight: a letter for</line>
            <line>me!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIRGILIA</speaker>
            <line>Yes, certain, there's a letter for you; I saw't.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>A letter for me! it gives me an estate of seven</line>
            <line>years' health; in which time I will make a lip at</line>
            <line>the physician: the most sovereign prescription in</line>
            <line>Galen is but empiricutic, and, to this preservative,</line>
            <line>of no better report than a horse-drench. Is he</line>
            <line>not wounded? he was wont to come home wounded.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIRGILIA</speaker>
            <line>O, no, no, no.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VOLUMNIA</speaker>
            <line>O, he is wounded; I thank the gods for't.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>So do I too, if it be not too much: brings a'</line>
            <line>victory in his pocket? the wounds become him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VOLUMNIA</speaker>
            <line>On's brows: Menenius, he comes the third time home</line>
            <line>with the oaken garland.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>Has he disciplined Aufidius soundly?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VOLUMNIA</speaker>
            <line>Titus Lartius writes, they fought together, but</line>
            <line>Aufidius got off.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>And 'twas time for him too, I'll warrant him that:</line>
            <line>an he had stayed by him, I would not have been so</line>
            <line>fidiused for all the chests in Corioli, and the gold</line>
            <line>that's in them. Is the senate possessed of this?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VOLUMNIA</speaker>
            <line>Good ladies, let's go. Yes, yes, yes; the senate</line>
            <line>has letters from the general, wherein he gives my</line>
            <line>son the whole name of the war: he hath in this</line>
            <line>action outdone his former deeds doubly</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VALERIA</speaker>
            <line>In troth, there's wondrous things spoke of him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>Wondrous! ay, I warrant you, and not without his</line>
            <line>true purchasing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIRGILIA</speaker>
            <line>The gods grant them true!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VOLUMNIA</speaker>
            <line>True! pow, wow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>True! I'll be sworn they are true.</line>
            <line>Where is he wounded?</line>
            <stagedir>To the Tribunes</stagedir>
            <line>God save your good worships! Marcius is coming</line>
            <line>home: he has more cause to be proud. Where is he wounded?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VOLUMNIA</speaker>
            <line>I' the shoulder and i' the left arm there will be</line>
            <line>large cicatrices to show the people, when he shall</line>
            <line>stand for his place. He received in the repulse of</line>
            <line>Tarquin seven hurts i' the body.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>One i' the neck, and two i' the thigh,--there's</line>
            <line>nine that I know.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VOLUMNIA</speaker>
            <line>He had, before this last expedition, twenty-five</line>
            <line>wounds upon him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>Now it's twenty-seven: every gash was an enemy's grave.</line>
            <stagedir>A shout and flourish</stagedir>
            <line>Hark! the trumpets.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VOLUMNIA</speaker>
            <line>These are the ushers of Marcius: before him he</line>
            <line>carries noise, and behind him he leaves tears:</line>
            <line>Death, that dark spirit, in 's nervy arm doth lie;</line>
            <line>Which, being advanced, declines, and then men die.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>A sennet. Trumpets sound. Enter COMINIUS the
general, and TITUS LARTIUS; between them, CORIOLANUS,
crowned with an oaken garland; with Captains and
Soldiers, and a Herald</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Herald</speaker>
            <line>Know, Rome, that all alone Marcius did fight</line>
            <line>Within Corioli gates: where he hath won,</line>
            <line>With fame, a name to Caius Marcius; these</line>
            <line>In honour follows Coriolanus.</line>
            <line>Welcome to Rome, renowned Coriolanus!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Flourish</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>All</speaker>
            <line>Welcome to Rome, renowned Coriolanus!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>No more of this; it does offend my heart:</line>
            <line>Pray now, no more.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COMINIUS</speaker>
            <line>Look, sir, your mother!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>O,</line>
            <line>You have, I know, petition'd all the gods</line>
            <line>For my prosperity!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Kneels</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VOLUMNIA</speaker>
            <line>Nay, my good soldier, up;</line>
            <line>My gentle Marcius, worthy Caius, and</line>
            <line>By deed-achieving honour newly named,--</line>
            <line>What is it?--Coriolanus must I call thee?--</line>
            <line>But O, thy wife!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>My gracious silence, hail!</line>
            <line>Wouldst thou have laugh'd had I come coffin'd home,</line>
            <line>That weep'st to see me triumph? Ay, my dear,</line>
            <line>Such eyes the widows in Corioli wear,</line>
            <line>And mothers that lack sons.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>Now, the gods crown thee!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>And live you yet?</line>
            <stagedir>To VALERIA</stagedir>
            <line>O my sweet lady, pardon.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VOLUMNIA</speaker>
            <line>I know not where to turn: O, welcome home:</line>
            <line>And welcome, general: and ye're welcome all.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>A hundred thousand welcomes. I could weep</line>
            <line>And I could laugh, I am light and heavy. Welcome.</line>
            <line>A curse begin at very root on's heart,</line>
            <line>That is not glad to see thee! You are three</line>
            <line>That Rome should dote on: yet, by the faith of men,</line>
            <line>We have some old crab-trees here</line>
            <line>at home that will not</line>
            <line>Be grafted to your relish. Yet welcome, warriors:</line>
            <line>We call a nettle but a nettle and</line>
            <line>The faults of fools but folly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COMINIUS</speaker>
            <line>Ever right.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>Menenius ever, ever.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Herald</speaker>
            <line>Give way there, and go on!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>To VOLUMNIA and VIRGILIA</stagedir>  Your hand, and yours:</line>
            <line>Ere in our own house I do shade my head,</line>
            <line>The good patricians must be visited;</line>
            <line>From whom I have received not only greetings,</line>
            <line>But with them change of honours.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VOLUMNIA</speaker>
            <line>I have lived</line>
            <line>To see inherited my very wishes</line>
            <line>And the buildings of my fancy: only</line>
            <line>There's one thing wanting, which I doubt not but</line>
            <line>Our Rome will cast upon thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>Know, good mother,</line>
            <line>I had rather be their servant in my way,</line>
            <line>Than sway with them in theirs.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COMINIUS</speaker>
            <line>On, to the Capitol!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Flourish. Cornets. Exeunt in state, as before.
BRUTUS and SICINIUS come forward</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>All tongues speak of him, and the bleared sights</line>
            <line>Are spectacled to see him: your prattling nurse</line>
            <line>Into a rapture lets her baby cry</line>
            <line>While she chats him: the kitchen malkin pins</line>
            <line>Her richest lockram 'bout her reechy neck,</line>
            <line>Clambering the walls to eye him: stalls, bulks, windows,</line>
            <line>Are smother'd up, leads fill'd, and ridges horsed</line>
            <line>With variable complexions, all agreeing</line>
            <line>In earnestness to see him: seld-shown flamens</line>
            <line>Do press among the popular throngs and puff</line>
            <line>To win a vulgar station: or veil'd dames</line>
            <line>Commit the war of white and damask in</line>
            <line>Their nicely-gawded cheeks to the wanton spoil</line>
            <line>Of Phoebus' burning kisses: such a pother</line>
            <line>As if that whatsoever god who leads him</line>
            <line>Were slily crept into his human powers</line>
            <line>And gave him graceful posture.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SICINIUS</speaker>
            <line>On the sudden,</line>
            <line>I warrant him consul.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>Then our office may,</line>
            <line>During his power, go sleep.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SICINIUS</speaker>
            <line>He cannot temperately transport his honours</line>
            <line>From where he should begin and end, but will</line>
            <line>Lose those he hath won.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>In that there's comfort.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SICINIUS</speaker>
            <line>Doubt not</line>
            <line>The commoners, for whom we stand, but they</line>
            <line>Upon their ancient malice will forget</line>
            <line>With the least cause these his new honours, which</line>
            <line>That he will give them make I as little question</line>
            <line>As he is proud to do't.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>I heard him swear,</line>
            <line>Were he to stand for consul, never would he</line>
            <line>Appear i' the market-place nor on him put</line>
            <line>The napless vesture of humility;</line>
            <line>Nor showing, as the manner is, his wounds</line>
            <line>To the people, beg their stinking breaths.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SICINIUS</speaker>
            <line>'Tis right.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>It was his word: O, he would miss it rather</line>
            <line>Than carry it but by the suit of the gentry to him,</line>
            <line>And the desire of the nobles.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SICINIUS</speaker>
            <line>I wish no better</line>
            <line>Than have him hold that purpose and to put it</line>
            <line>In execution.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>'Tis most like he will.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SICINIUS</speaker>
            <line>It shall be to him then as our good wills,</line>
            <line>A sure destruction.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>So it must fall out</line>
            <line>To him or our authorities. For an end,</line>
            <line>We must suggest the people in what hatred</line>
            <line>He still hath held them; that to's power he would</line>
            <line>Have made them mules, silenced their pleaders and</line>
            <line>Dispropertied their freedoms, holding them,</line>
            <line>In human action and capacity,</line>
            <line>Of no more soul nor fitness for the world</line>
            <line>Than camels in the war, who have their provand</line>
            <line>Only for bearing burdens, and sore blows</line>
            <line>For sinking under them.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SICINIUS</speaker>
            <line>This, as you say, suggested</line>
            <line>At some time when his soaring insolence</line>
            <line>Shall touch the people--which time shall not want,</line>
            <line>If he be put upon 't; and that's as easy</line>
            <line>As to set dogs on sheep--will be his fire</line>
            <line>To kindle their dry stubble; and their blaze</line>
            <line>Shall darken him for ever.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter a Messenger</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>What's the matter?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>You are sent for to the Capitol. 'Tis thought</line>
            <line>That Marcius shall be consul:</line>
            <line>I have seen the dumb men throng to see him and</line>
            <line>The blind to bear him speak: matrons flung gloves,</line>
            <line>Ladies and maids their scarfs and handkerchers,</line>
            <line>Upon him as he pass'd: the nobles bended,</line>
            <line>As to Jove's statue, and the commons made</line>
            <line>A shower and thunder with their caps and shouts:</line>
            <line>I never saw the like.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>Let's to the Capitol;</line>
            <line>And carry with us ears and eyes for the time,</line>
            <line>But hearts for the event.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SICINIUS</speaker>
            <line>Have with you.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE  II.  The same. The Capitol.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter two Officers, to lay cushions</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Officer</speaker>
            <line>Come, come, they are almost here. How many stand</line>
            <line>for consulships?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Officer</speaker>
            <line>Three, they say: but 'tis thought of every one</line>
            <line>Coriolanus will carry it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Officer</speaker>
            <line>That's a brave fellow; but he's vengeance proud, and</line>
            <line>loves not the common people.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Officer</speaker>
            <line>Faith, there had been many great men that have</line>
            <line>flattered the people, who ne'er loved them; and there</line>
            <line>be many that they have loved, they know not</line>
            <line>wherefore: so that, if they love they know not why,</line>
            <line>they hate upon no better a ground: therefore, for</line>
            <line>Coriolanus neither to care whether they love or hate</line>
            <line>him manifests the true knowledge he has in their</line>
            <line>disposition; and out of his noble carelessness lets</line>
            <line>them plainly see't.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Officer</speaker>
            <line>If he did not care whether he had their love or no,</line>
            <line>he waved indifferently 'twixt doing them neither</line>
            <line>good nor harm: but he seeks their hate with greater</line>
            <line>devotion than can render it him; and leaves</line>
            <line>nothing undone that may fully discover him their</line>
            <line>opposite. Now, to seem to affect the malice and</line>
            <line>displeasure of the people is as bad as that which he</line>
            <line>dislikes, to flatter them for their love.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Officer</speaker>
            <line>He hath deserved worthily of his country: and his</line>
            <line>ascent is not by such easy degrees as those who,</line>
            <line>having been supple and courteous to the people,</line>
            <line>bonneted, without any further deed to have them at</line>
            <line>an into their estimation and report: but he hath so</line>
            <line>planted his honours in their eyes, and his actions</line>
            <line>in their hearts, that for their tongues to be</line>
            <line>silent, and not confess so much, were a kind of</line>
            <line>ingrateful injury; to report otherwise, were a</line>
            <line>malice, that, giving itself the lie, would pluck</line>
            <line>reproof and rebuke from every ear that heard it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Officer</speaker>
            <line>No more of him; he is a worthy man: make way, they</line>
            <line>are coming.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>A sennet. Enter, with actors before them, COMINIUS
the consul, MENENIUS, CORIOLANUS, Senators,
SICINIUS and BRUTUS. The Senators take their
places; the Tribunes take their Places by
themselves. CORIOLANUS stands</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>Having determined of the Volsces and</line>
            <line>To send for Titus Lartius, it remains,</line>
            <line>As the main point of this our after-meeting,</line>
            <line>To gratify his noble service that</line>
            <line>Hath thus stood for his country: therefore,</line>
            <line>please you,</line>
            <line>Most reverend and grave elders, to desire</line>
            <line>The present consul, and last general</line>
            <line>In our well-found successes, to report</line>
            <line>A little of that worthy work perform'd</line>
            <line>By Caius Marcius Coriolanus, whom</line>
            <line>We met here both to thank and to remember</line>
            <line>With honours like himself.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>Speak, good Cominius:</line>
            <line>Leave nothing out for length, and make us think</line>
            <line>Rather our state's defective for requital</line>
            <line>Than we to stretch it out.</line>
            <stagedir>To the Tribunes</stagedir>
            <line>Masters o' the people,</line>
            <line>We do request your kindest ears, and after,</line>
            <line>Your loving motion toward the common body,</line>
            <line>To yield what passes here.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SICINIUS</speaker>
            <line>We are convented</line>
            <line>Upon a pleasing treaty, and have hearts</line>
            <line>Inclinable to honour and advance</line>
            <line>The theme of our assembly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>Which the rather</line>
            <line>We shall be blest to do, if he remember</line>
            <line>A kinder value of the people than</line>
            <line>He hath hereto prized them at.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>That's off, that's off;</line>
            <line>I would you rather had been silent. Please you</line>
            <line>To hear Cominius speak?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>Most willingly;</line>
            <line>But yet my caution was more pertinent</line>
            <line>Than the rebuke you give it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>He loves your people</line>
            <line>But tie him not to be their bedfellow.</line>
            <line>Worthy Cominius, speak.</line>
            <stagedir>CORIOLANUS offers to go away</stagedir>
            <line>Nay, keep your place.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>Sit, Coriolanus; never shame to hear</line>
            <line>What you have nobly done.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>Your horror's pardon:</line>
            <line>I had rather have my wounds to heal again</line>
            <line>Than hear say how I got them.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>Sir, I hope</line>
            <line>My words disbench'd you not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>No, sir: yet oft,</line>
            <line>When blows have made me stay, I fled from words.</line>
            <line>You soothed not, therefore hurt not: but</line>
            <line>your people,</line>
            <line>I love them as they weigh.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>Pray now, sit down.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>I had rather have one scratch my head i' the sun</line>
            <line>When the alarum were struck than idly sit</line>
            <line>To hear my nothings monster'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>Masters of the people,</line>
            <line>Your multiplying spawn how can he flatter--</line>
            <line>That's thousand to one good one--when you now see</line>
            <line>He had rather venture all his limbs for honour</line>
            <line>Than one on's ears to hear it? Proceed, Cominius.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COMINIUS</speaker>
            <line>I shall lack voice: the deeds of Coriolanus</line>
            <line>Should not be utter'd feebly. It is held</line>
            <line>That valour is the chiefest virtue, and</line>
            <line>Most dignifies the haver: if it be,</line>
            <line>The man I speak of cannot in the world</line>
            <line>Be singly counterpoised. At sixteen years,</line>
            <line>When Tarquin made a head for Rome, he fought</line>
            <line>Beyond the mark of others: our then dictator,</line>
            <line>Whom with all praise I point at, saw him fight,</line>
            <line>When with his Amazonian chin he drove</line>
            <line>The bristled lips before him: be bestrid</line>
            <line>An o'er-press'd Roman and i' the consul's view</line>
            <line>Slew three opposers: Tarquin's self he met,</line>
            <line>And struck him on his knee: in that day's feats,</line>
            <line>When he might act the woman in the scene,</line>
            <line>He proved best man i' the field, and for his meed</line>
            <line>Was brow-bound with the oak. His pupil age</line>
            <line>Man-enter'd thus, he waxed like a sea,</line>
            <line>And in the brunt of seventeen battles since</line>
            <line>He lurch'd all swords of the garland. For this last,</line>
            <line>Before and in Corioli, let me say,</line>
            <line>I cannot speak him home: he stopp'd the fliers;</line>
            <line>And by his rare example made the coward</line>
            <line>Turn terror into sport: as weeds before</line>
            <line>A vessel under sail, so men obey'd</line>
            <line>And fell below his stem: his sword, death's stamp,</line>
            <line>Where it did mark, it took; from face to foot</line>
            <line>He was a thing of blood, whose every motion</line>
            <line>Was timed with dying cries: alone he enter'd</line>
            <line>The mortal gate of the city, which he painted</line>
            <line>With shunless destiny; aidless came off,</line>
            <line>And with a sudden reinforcement struck</line>
            <line>Corioli like a planet: now all's his:</line>
            <line>When, by and by, the din of war gan pierce</line>
            <line>His ready sense; then straight his doubled spirit</line>
            <line>Re-quicken'd what in flesh was fatigate,</line>
            <line>And to the battle came he; where he did</line>
            <line>Run reeking o'er the lives of men, as if</line>
            <line>'Twere a perpetual spoil: and till we call'd</line>
            <line>Both field and city ours, he never stood</line>
            <line>To ease his breast with panting.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>Worthy man!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>He cannot but with measure fit the honours</line>
            <line>Which we devise him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COMINIUS</speaker>
            <line>Our spoils he kick'd at,</line>
            <line>And look'd upon things precious as they were</line>
            <line>The common muck of the world: he covets less</line>
            <line>Than misery itself would give; rewards</line>
            <line>His deeds with doing them, and is content</line>
            <line>To spend the time to end it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>He's right noble:</line>
            <line>Let him be call'd for.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>Call Coriolanus.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Officer</speaker>
            <line>He doth appear.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter CORIOLANUS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>The senate, Coriolanus, are well pleased</line>
            <line>To make thee consul.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>I do owe them still</line>
            <line>My life and services.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>It then remains</line>
            <line>That you do speak to the people.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>I do beseech you,</line>
            <line>Let me o'erleap that custom, for I cannot</line>
            <line>Put on the gown, stand naked and entreat them,</line>
            <line>For my wounds' sake, to give their suffrage: please you</line>
            <line>That I may pass this doing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SICINIUS</speaker>
            <line>Sir, the people</line>
            <line>Must have their voices; neither will they bate</line>
            <line>One jot of ceremony.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>Put them not to't:</line>
            <line>Pray you, go fit you to the custom and</line>
            <line>Take to you, as your predecessors have,</line>
            <line>Your honour with your form.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>It is apart</line>
            <line>That I shall blush in acting, and might well</line>
            <line>Be taken from the people.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>Mark you that?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>To brag unto them, thus I did, and thus;</line>
            <line>Show them the unaching scars which I should hide,</line>
            <line>As if I had received them for the hire</line>
            <line>Of their breath only!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>Do not stand upon't.</line>
            <line>We recommend to you, tribunes of the people,</line>
            <line>Our purpose to them: and to our noble consul</line>
            <line>Wish we all joy and honour.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Senators</speaker>
            <line>To Coriolanus come all joy and honour!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Flourish of cornets. Exeunt all but SICINIUS
and BRUTUS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>You see how he intends to use the people.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SICINIUS</speaker>
            <line>May they perceive's intent! He will require them,</line>
            <line>As if he did contemn what he requested</line>
            <line>Should be in them to give.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>Come, we'll inform them</line>
            <line>Of our proceedings here: on the marketplace,</line>
            <line>I know, they do attend us.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  The same. The Forum.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter seven or eight Citizens</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Once, if he do require our voices, we ought not to deny him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Citizen</speaker>
            <line>We may, sir, if we will.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Citizen</speaker>
            <line>We have power in ourselves to do it, but it is a</line>
            <line>power that we have no power to do; for if he show us</line>
            <line>his wounds and tell us his deeds, we are to put our</line>
            <line>tongues into those wounds and speak for them; so, if</line>
            <line>he tell us his noble deeds, we must also tell him</line>
            <line>our noble acceptance of them. Ingratitude is</line>
            <line>monstrous, and for the multitude to be ingrateful,</line>
            <line>were to make a monster of the multitude: of the</line>
            <line>which we being members, should bring ourselves to be</line>
            <line>monstrous members.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>And to make us no better thought of, a little help</line>
            <line>will serve; for once we stood up about the corn, he</line>
            <line>himself stuck not to call us the many-headed multitude.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Citizen</speaker>
            <line>We have been called so of many; not that our heads</line>
            <line>are some brown, some black, some auburn, some bald,</line>
            <line>but that our wits are so diversely coloured: and</line>
            <line>truly I think if all our wits were to issue out of</line>
            <line>one skull, they would fly east, west, north, south,</line>
            <line>and their consent of one direct way should be at</line>
            <line>once to all the points o' the compass.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Think you so? Which way do you judge my wit would</line>
            <line>fly?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Nay, your wit will not so soon out as another man's</line>
            <line>will;'tis strongly wedged up in a block-head, but</line>
            <line>if it were at liberty, 'twould, sure, southward.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Why that way?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Citizen</speaker>
            <line>To lose itself in a fog, where being three parts</line>
            <line>melted away with rotten dews, the fourth would return</line>
            <line>for conscience sake, to help to get thee a wife.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Citizen</speaker>
            <line>You are never without your tricks: you may, you may.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Are you all resolved to give your voices? But</line>
            <line>that's no matter, the greater part carries it. I</line>
            <line>say, if he would incline to the people, there was</line>
            <line>never a worthier man.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter CORIOLANUS in a gown of humility, with MENENIUS</stagedir>
            <line>Here he comes, and in the gown of humility: mark his</line>
            <line>behavior. We are not to stay all together, but to</line>
            <line>come by him where he stands, by ones, by twos, and</line>
            <line>by threes. He's to make his requests by</line>
            <line>particulars; wherein every one of us has a single</line>
            <line>honour, in giving him our own voices with our own</line>
            <line>tongues: therefore follow me, and I direct you how</line>
            <line>you shall go by him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>All</speaker>
            <line>Content, content.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt Citizens</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>O sir, you are not right: have you not known</line>
            <line>The worthiest men have done't?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>What must I say?</line>
            <line>'I Pray, sir'--Plague upon't! I cannot bring</line>
            <line>My tongue to such a pace:--'Look, sir, my wounds!</line>
            <line>I got them in my country's service, when</line>
            <line>Some certain of your brethren roar'd and ran</line>
            <line>From the noise of our own drums.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>O me, the gods!</line>
            <line>You must not speak of that: you must desire them</line>
            <line>To think upon you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>Think upon me! hang 'em!</line>
            <line>I would they would forget me, like the virtues</line>
            <line>Which our divines lose by 'em.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>You'll mar all:</line>
            <line>I'll leave you: pray you, speak to 'em, I pray you,</line>
            <line>In wholesome manner.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>Bid them wash their faces</line>
            <line>And keep their teeth clean.</line>
            <stagedir>Re-enter two of the Citizens</stagedir>
            <line>So, here comes a brace.</line>
            <stagedir>Re-enter a third Citizen</stagedir>
            <line>You know the cause, air, of my standing here.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Citizen</speaker>
            <line>We do, sir; tell us what hath brought you to't.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>Mine own desert.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Your own desert!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>Ay, but not mine own desire.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Citizen</speaker>
            <line>How not your own desire?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>No, sir,'twas never my desire yet to trouble the</line>
            <line>poor with begging.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Citizen</speaker>
            <line>You must think, if we give you any thing, we hope to</line>
            <line>gain by you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>Well then, I pray, your price o' the consulship?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>The price is to ask it kindly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>Kindly! Sir, I pray, let me ha't: I have wounds to</line>
            <line>show you, which shall be yours in private. Your</line>
            <line>good voice, sir; what say you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Citizen</speaker>
            <line>You shall ha' it, worthy sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>A match, sir. There's in all two worthy voices</line>
            <line>begged. I have your alms: adieu.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Citizen</speaker>
            <line>But this is something odd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Citizen</speaker>
            <line>An 'twere to give again,--but 'tis no matter.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt the three Citizens</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Re-enter two other Citizens</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>Pray you now, if it may stand with the tune of your</line>
            <line>voices that I may be consul, I have here the</line>
            <line>customary gown.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fourth Citizen</speaker>
            <line>You have deserved nobly of your country, and you</line>
            <line>have not deserved nobly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>Your enigma?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fourth Citizen</speaker>
            <line>You have been a scourge to her enemies, you have</line>
            <line>been a rod to her friends; you have not indeed loved</line>
            <line>the common people.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>You should account me the more virtuous that I have</line>
            <line>not been common in my love. I will, sir, flatter my</line>
            <line>sworn brother, the people, to earn a dearer</line>
            <line>estimation of them; 'tis a condition they account</line>
            <line>gentle: and since the wisdom of their choice is</line>
            <line>rather to have my hat than my heart, I will practise</line>
            <line>the insinuating nod and be off to them most</line>
            <line>counterfeitly; that is, sir, I will counterfeit the</line>
            <line>bewitchment of some popular man and give it</line>
            <line>bountiful to the desirers. Therefore, beseech you,</line>
            <line>I may be consul.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fifth Citizen</speaker>
            <line>We hope to find you our friend; and therefore give</line>
            <line>you our voices heartily.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fourth Citizen</speaker>
            <line>You have received many wounds for your country.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>I will not seal your knowledge with showing them. I</line>
            <line>will make much of your voices, and so trouble you no further.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Both Citizens</speaker>
            <line>The gods give you joy, sir, heartily!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>Most sweet voices!</line>
            <line>Better it is to die, better to starve,</line>
            <line>Than crave the hire which first we do deserve.</line>
            <line>Why in this woolvish toge should I stand here,</line>
            <line>To beg of Hob and Dick, that do appear,</line>
            <line>Their needless vouches? Custom calls me to't:</line>
            <line>What custom wills, in all things should we do't,</line>
            <line>The dust on antique time would lie unswept,</line>
            <line>And mountainous error be too highly heapt</line>
            <line>For truth to o'er-peer. Rather than fool it so,</line>
            <line>Let the high office and the honour go</line>
            <line>To one that would do thus. I am half through;</line>
            <line>The one part suffer'd, the other will I do.</line>
            <stagedir>Re-enter three Citizens more</stagedir>
            <line>Here come more voices.</line>
            <line>Your voices: for your voices I have fought;</line>
            <line>Watch'd for your voices; for Your voices bear</line>
            <line>Of wounds two dozen odd; battles thrice six</line>
            <line>I have seen and heard of; for your voices have</line>
            <line>Done many things, some less, some more your voices:</line>
            <line>Indeed I would be consul.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Sixth Citizen</speaker>
            <line>He has done nobly, and cannot go without any honest</line>
            <line>man's voice.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Seventh Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Therefore let him be consul: the gods give him joy,</line>
            <line>and make him good friend to the people!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>All Citizens</speaker>
            <line>Amen, amen. God save thee, noble consul!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>Worthy voices!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter MENENIUS, with BRUTUS and SICINIUS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>You have stood your limitation; and the tribunes</line>
            <line>Endue you with the people's voice: remains</line>
            <line>That, in the official marks invested, you</line>
            <line>Anon do meet the senate.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>Is this done?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SICINIUS</speaker>
            <line>The custom of request you have discharged:</line>
            <line>The people do admit you, and are summon'd</line>
            <line>To meet anon, upon your approbation.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>Where? at the senate-house?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SICINIUS</speaker>
            <line>There, Coriolanus.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>May I change these garments?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SICINIUS</speaker>
            <line>You may, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORIOLANUS</speaker>
            <line>That I'll straight do; and, knowing myself again,</line>
            <line>Repair to the senate-house.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENENIUS</speaker>
            <line>I'll keep you company. Will you along?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>We stay here for the people.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SICINIUS</speaker>
            <line>Fare you well.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt CORIOLANUS and MENENIUS</stagedir>
            <line>He has it now, and by his looks methink</line>
            <line>'Tis warm at 's heart.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>With a proud heart he wore his humble weeds.</line>
            <line>will you dismiss the people?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter Citizens</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SICINIUS</speaker>
            <line>How now, my masters! have you chose this man?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>He has our voices, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>We pray the gods he may deserve your loves.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Amen, sir: to my poor unworthy notice,</line>
            <line>He mock'd us when he begg'd our voices.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Certainly</line>
            <line>He flouted us downright.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>No,'tis his kind of speech: he did not mock us.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Not one amongst us, save yourself, but says</line>
            <line>He used us scornfully: he should have show'd us</line>
            <line>His marks of merit, wounds received for's country.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SICINIUS</speaker>
            <line>Why, so he did, I am sure.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Citizens</speaker>
            <line>No, no; no man saw 'em.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Citizen</speaker>
            <line>He said he had wounds, which he could show</line>
            <line>in private;</line>
            <line>And with his hat, thus waving it in scorn,</line>
            <line>'I would be consul,' says he: 'aged custom,</line>
            <line>But by your voices, will not so permit me;</line>
            <line>Your voices therefore.' When we granted that,</line>
            <line>Here was 'I thank you for your voices: thank you:</line>
            <line>Your most sweet voices: now you have left</line>
            <line>your voices,</line>
            <line>I have no further with you.' Was not this mockery?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SICINIUS</speaker>
            <line>Why either were you ignorant to see't,</line>
            <line>Or, seeing it, of such childish friendliness</line>
            <line>To yield your voices?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>Could you not have told him</line>
            <line>As you were lesson'd, when he had no power,</line>
            <line>But was a petty servant to the state,</line>
            <line>He was your enemy, ever spake against</line>
            <line>Your liberties and the charters that you bear</line>
            <line>I' the body of the weal; and now, arriving</line>
            <line>A place of potency and sway o' the state,</line>
            <line>If he should still malignantly remain</line>
            <line>Fast foe to the plebeii, your voices might</line>
            <line>Be curses to yourselves? You should have said</line>
            <line>That as his worthy deeds did claim no less</line>
            <line>Than what he stood for, so his gracious nature</line>
            <line>Would think upon you for your voices and</line>
            <line>Translate his malice towards you into love,</line>
            <line>Standing your friendly lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SICINIUS</speaker>
            <line>Thus to have said,</line>
            <line>As you were fore-advised, had touch'd his spirit</line>
            <line>And tried his inclination; from him pluck'd</line>
            <line>Either his gracious promise, which you might,</line>
            <line>As cause had call'd you up, have held him to</line>
            <line>Or else it would have gall'd his surly nature,</line>
            <line>Which easily endures not article</line>
            <line>Tying him to aught; so putting him to rage,</line>
            <line>You should have ta'en the advantage of his choler</line>
            <line>And pass'd him unelected.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>Did you perceive</line>
            <line>He did solicit you in free contempt</line>
            <line>When he did need your loves, and do you think</line>
            <line>That his contempt shall not be bruising to you,</line>
            <line>When he hath power to crush? Why, had your bodies</line>
            <line>No heart among you? or had you tongues to cry</line>
            <line>Against the rectorship of judgment?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SICINIUS</speaker>
            <line>Have you</line>
            <line>Ere now denied the asker? and now again</line>
            <line>Of him that did not ask, but mock, bestow</line>
            <line>Your sued-for tongues?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Citizen</speaker>
            <line>He's not confirm'd; we may deny him yet.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Citizen</speaker>
            <line>And will deny him:</line>
            <line>I'll have five hundred voices of that sound.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>I twice five hundred and their friends to piece 'em.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>Get you hence instantly, and tell those friends,</line>
            <line>They have chose a consul that will from them take</line>
            <line>Their liberties; make them of no more voice</line>
            <line>Than dogs that are as often beat for barking</line>
            <line>As therefore kept to do so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SICINIUS</speaker>
            <line>Let them assemble,</line>
            <line>And on a safer judgment all revoke</line>
            <line>Your ignorant election; enforce his pride,</line>
            <line>And his old hate unto you; besides, forget not</line>
            <line>With what contempt he wore the humble weed,</line>
            <line>How in his suit he scorn'd you; but your loves,</line>
            <line>Thinking upon his services, took from you</line>
            <line>The apprehension of his present portance,</line>
            <line>Which most gibingly, ungravely, he did fashion</line>
            <line>After the inveterate hate he bears you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>Lay</line>
            <line>A fault on us, your tribunes; that we laboured,</line>
            <line>No impediment between, but that you must</line>
            <line>Cast your election on him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SICINIUS</speaker>
            <line>Say, you chose him</line>
            <line>More after our commandment than as guided</line>
            <line>By your own true affections, and that your minds,</line>
            <line>Preoccupied with what you rather must do</line>
            <line>Than what you should, made you against the grain</line>
            <line>To voice him consul: lay the fault on us.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>Ay, spare us not. Say we read lectures to you.</line>
            <line>How youngly he began to serve his country,</line>
            <line>How long continued, and what stock he springs of,</line>
            <line>The noble house o' the Marcians, from whence came</line>
            <line>That Ancus Marcius, Numa's daughter's son,</line>
            <line>Who, after great Hostilius, here was king;</line>
            <line>Of the same house Publius and Quintus were,</line>
            <line>That our beat water brought by conduits hither;</line>
            <line>And  <stagedir>Censorinus,</stagedir>  nobly named so,</line>
            <line>Twice being  <stagedir>by the people chosen</stagedir>  censor,</line>
            <line>Was his great ancestor.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SICINIUS</speaker>
            <line>One thus descended,</line>
            <line>That hath beside well in his person wrought</line>
            <line>To be set high in place, we did commend</line>
            <line>To your remembrances: but you have found,</line>
            <line>Scaling his present bearing with his past,</line>
            <line>That he's your fixed enemy, and revoke</line>
            <line>Your sudden approbation.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>Say, you ne'er had done't--</line>
            <line>Harp on that still--but by our putting on;</line>
            <line>And presently, when you have drawn your number,</line>
            <line>Repair to the Capitol.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>All</speaker>
            <line>We will so: almost all</line>
            <line>Repent in their election.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt Citizens</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>Let them go on;</line>
            <line>This mutiny were better put in hazard,</line>
            <line>Than stay, past doubt, for greater:</line>
            <line>If, as his nature is, he fall in rage</line>
            <line>With their refusal, both observe and answer</line>
            <line>The vantage of his anger.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SICINIUS</speaker>
            <line>To the Capitol, come:</line>
            <line>We will be there before the stream o' the people;</line>
            <line>And this shall seem, as partly 'tis, their own,</line>
            <line>Which we have goaded onward.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>