<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net/doctypes/dita/shakespear/dtd/act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-1">
   <title>ACT I</title>
   <prologue id="act-1-prologue">
      <title>PROLOGUE</title>
      <prologue-body>
         <stagedir>Enter Chorus</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <line>O for a Muse of fire, that would ascend</line>
            <line>The brightest heaven of invention,</line>
            <line>A kingdom for a stage, princes to act</line>
            <line>And monarchs to behold the swelling scene!</line>
            <line>Then should the warlike Harry, like himself,</line>
            <line>Assume the port of Mars; and at his heels,</line>
            <line>Leash'd in like hounds, should famine, sword and fire</line>
            <line>Crouch for employment. But pardon, and gentles all,</line>
            <line>The flat unraised spirits that have dared</line>
            <line>On this unworthy scaffold to bring forth</line>
            <line>So great an object: can this cockpit hold</line>
            <line>The vasty fields of France? or may we cram</line>
            <line>Within this wooden O the very casques</line>
            <line>That did affright the air at Agincourt?</line>
            <line>O, pardon! since a crooked figure may</line>
            <line>Attest in little place a million;</line>
            <line>And let us, ciphers to this great accompt,</line>
            <line>On your imaginary forces work.</line>
            <line>Suppose within the girdle of these walls</line>
            <line>Are now confined two mighty monarchies,</line>
            <line>Whose high upreared and abutting fronts</line>
            <line>The perilous narrow ocean parts asunder:</line>
            <line>Piece out our imperfections with your thoughts;</line>
            <line>Into a thousand parts divide on man,</line>
            <line>And make imaginary puissance;</line>
            <line>Think when we talk of horses, that you see them</line>
            <line>Printing their proud hoofs i' the receiving earth;</line>
            <line>For 'tis your thoughts that now must deck our kings,</line>
            <line>Carry them here and there; jumping o'er times,</line>
            <line>Turning the accomplishment of many years</line>
            <line>Into an hour-glass: for the which supply,</line>
            <line>Admit me Chorus to this history;</line>
            <line>Who prologue-like your humble patience pray,</line>
            <line>Gently to hear, kindly to judge, our play.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </prologue-body>
   </prologue>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  London. An ante-chamber in the KING'S palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter the ARCHBISHOP OF CANTERBURY, and the BISHOP OF ELY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CANTERBURY</speaker>
            <line>My lord, I'll tell you; that self bill is urged,</line>
            <line>Which in the eleventh year of the last king's reign</line>
            <line>Was like, and had indeed against us pass'd,</line>
            <line>But that the scambling and unquiet time</line>
            <line>Did push it out of farther question.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ELY</speaker>
            <line>But how, my lord, shall we resist it now?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CANTERBURY</speaker>
            <line>It must be thought on. If it pass against us,</line>
            <line>We lose the better half of our possession:</line>
            <line>For all the temporal lands which men devout</line>
            <line>By testament have given to the church</line>
            <line>Would they strip from us; being valued thus:</line>
            <line>As much as would maintain, to the king's honour,</line>
            <line>Full fifteen earls and fifteen hundred knights,</line>
            <line>Six thousand and two hundred good esquires;</line>
            <line>And, to relief of lazars and weak age,</line>
            <line>Of indigent faint souls past corporal toil.</line>
            <line>A hundred almshouses right well supplied;</line>
            <line>And to the coffers of the king beside,</line>
            <line>A thousand pounds by the year: thus runs the bill.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ELY</speaker>
            <line>This would drink deep.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CANTERBURY</speaker>
            <line>'Twould drink the cup and all.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ELY</speaker>
            <line>But what prevention?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CANTERBURY</speaker>
            <line>The king is full of grace and fair regard.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ELY</speaker>
            <line>And a true lover of the holy church.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CANTERBURY</speaker>
            <line>The courses of his youth promised it not.</line>
            <line>The breath no sooner left his father's body,</line>
            <line>But that his wildness, mortified in him,</line>
            <line>Seem'd to die too; yea, at that very moment</line>
            <line>Consideration, like an angel, came</line>
            <line>And whipp'd the offending Adam out of him,</line>
            <line>Leaving his body as a paradise,</line>
            <line>To envelop and contain celestial spirits.</line>
            <line>Never was such a sudden scholar made;</line>
            <line>Never came reformation in a flood,</line>
            <line>With such a heady currance, scouring faults</line>
            <line>Nor never Hydra-headed wilfulness</line>
            <line>So soon did lose his seat and all at once</line>
            <line>As in this king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ELY</speaker>
            <line>We are blessed in the change.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CANTERBURY</speaker>
            <line>Hear him but reason in divinity,</line>
            <line>And all-admiring with an inward wish</line>
            <line>You would desire the king were made a prelate:</line>
            <line>Hear him debate of commonwealth affairs,</line>
            <line>You would say it hath been all in all his study:</line>
            <line>List his discourse of war, and you shall hear</line>
            <line>A fearful battle render'd you in music:</line>
            <line>Turn him to any cause of policy,</line>
            <line>The Gordian knot of it he will unloose,</line>
            <line>Familiar as his garter: that, when he speaks,</line>
            <line>The air, a charter'd libertine, is still,</line>
            <line>And the mute wonder lurketh in men's ears,</line>
            <line>To steal his sweet and honey'd sentences;</line>
            <line>So that the art and practic part of life</line>
            <line>Must be the mistress to this theoric:</line>
            <line>Which is a wonder how his grace should glean it,</line>
            <line>Since his addiction was to courses vain,</line>
            <line>His companies unletter'd, rude and shallow,</line>
            <line>His hours fill'd up with riots, banquets, sports,</line>
            <line>And never noted in him any study,</line>
            <line>Any retirement, any sequestration</line>
            <line>From open haunts and popularity.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ELY</speaker>
            <line>The strawberry grows underneath the nettle</line>
            <line>And wholesome berries thrive and ripen best</line>
            <line>Neighbour'd by fruit of baser quality:</line>
            <line>And so the prince obscured his contemplation</line>
            <line>Under the veil of wildness; which, no doubt,</line>
            <line>Grew like the summer grass, fastest by night,</line>
            <line>Unseen, yet crescive in his faculty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CANTERBURY</speaker>
            <line>It must be so; for miracles are ceased;</line>
            <line>And therefore we must needs admit the means</line>
            <line>How things are perfected.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ELY</speaker>
            <line>But, my good lord,</line>
            <line>How now for mitigation of this bill</line>
            <line>Urged by the commons? Doth his majesty</line>
            <line>Incline to it, or no?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CANTERBURY</speaker>
            <line>He seems indifferent,</line>
            <line>Or rather swaying more upon our part</line>
            <line>Than cherishing the exhibiters against us;</line>
            <line>For I have made an offer to his majesty,</line>
            <line>Upon our spiritual convocation</line>
            <line>And in regard of causes now in hand,</line>
            <line>Which I have open'd to his grace at large,</line>
            <line>As touching France, to give a greater sum</line>
            <line>Than ever at one time the clergy yet</line>
            <line>Did to his predecessors part withal.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ELY</speaker>
            <line>How did this offer seem received, my lord?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CANTERBURY</speaker>
            <line>With good acceptance of his majesty;</line>
            <line>Save that there was not time enough to hear,</line>
            <line>As I perceived his grace would fain have done,</line>
            <line>The severals and unhidden passages</line>
            <line>Of his true titles to some certain dukedoms</line>
            <line>And generally to the crown and seat of France</line>
            <line>Derived from Edward, his great-grandfather.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ELY</speaker>
            <line>What was the impediment that broke this off?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CANTERBURY</speaker>
            <line>The French ambassador upon that instant</line>
            <line>Craved audience; and the hour, I think, is come</line>
            <line>To give him hearing: is it four o'clock?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ELY</speaker>
            <line>It is.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CANTERBURY</speaker>
            <line>Then go we in, to know his embassy;</line>
            <line>Which I could with a ready guess declare,</line>
            <line>Before the Frenchman speak a word of it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ELY</speaker>
            <line>I'll wait upon you, and I long to hear it.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  The same. The Presence chamber.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter KING HENRY V, GLOUCESTER, BEDFORD, EXETER, WARWICK, WESTMORELAND, and Attendants</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>Where is my gracious Lord of Canterbury?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EXETER</speaker>
            <line>Not here in presence.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>Send for him, good uncle.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WESTMORELAND</speaker>
            <line>Shall we call in the ambassador, my liege?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>Not yet, my cousin: we would be resolved,</line>
            <line>Before we hear him, of some things of weight</line>
            <line>That task our thoughts, concerning us and France.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter the ARCHBISHOP OF CANTERBURY, and the BISHOP of ELY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CANTERBURY</speaker>
            <line>God and his angels guard your sacred throne</line>
            <line>And make you long become it!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>Sure, we thank you.</line>
            <line>My learned lord, we pray you to proceed</line>
            <line>And justly and religiously unfold</line>
            <line>Why the law Salique that they have in France</line>
            <line>Or should, or should not, bar us in our claim:</line>
            <line>And God forbid, my dear and faithful lord,</line>
            <line>That you should fashion, wrest, or bow your reading,</line>
            <line>Or nicely charge your understanding soul</line>
            <line>With opening titles miscreate, whose right</line>
            <line>Suits not in native colours with the truth;</line>
            <line>For God doth know how many now in health</line>
            <line>Shall drop their blood in approbation</line>
            <line>Of what your reverence shall incite us to.</line>
            <line>Therefore take heed how you impawn our person,</line>
            <line>How you awake our sleeping sword of war:</line>
            <line>We charge you, in the name of God, take heed;</line>
            <line>For never two such kingdoms did contend</line>
            <line>Without much fall of blood; whose guiltless drops</line>
            <line>Are every one a woe, a sore complaint</line>
            <line>'Gainst him whose wrong gives edge unto the swords</line>
            <line>That make such waste in brief mortality.</line>
            <line>Under this conjuration, speak, my lord;</line>
            <line>For we will hear, note and believe in heart</line>
            <line>That what you speak is in your conscience wash'd</line>
            <line>As pure as sin with baptism.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CANTERBURY</speaker>
            <line>Then hear me, gracious sovereign, and you peers,</line>
            <line>That owe yourselves, your lives and services</line>
            <line>To this imperial throne. There is no bar</line>
            <line>To make against your highness' claim to France</line>
            <line>But this, which they produce from Pharamond,</line>
            <line>'In terram Salicam mulieres ne succedant:'</line>
            <line>'No woman shall succeed in Salique land:'</line>
            <line>Which Salique land the French unjustly gloze</line>
            <line>To be the realm of France, and Pharamond</line>
            <line>The founder of this law and female bar.</line>
            <line>Yet their own authors faithfully affirm</line>
            <line>That the land Salique is in Germany,</line>
            <line>Between the floods of Sala and of Elbe;</line>
            <line>Where Charles the Great, having subdued the Saxons,</line>
            <line>There left behind and settled certain French;</line>
            <line>Who, holding in disdain the German women</line>
            <line>For some dishonest manners of their life,</line>
            <line>Establish'd then this law; to wit, no female</line>
            <line>Should be inheritrix in Salique land:</line>
            <line>Which Salique, as I said, 'twixt Elbe and Sala,</line>
            <line>Is at this day in Germany call'd Meisen.</line>
            <line>Then doth it well appear that Salique law</line>
            <line>Was not devised for the realm of France:</line>
            <line>Nor did the French possess the Salique land</line>
            <line>Until four hundred one and twenty years</line>
            <line>After defunction of King Pharamond,</line>
            <line>Idly supposed the founder of this law;</line>
            <line>Who died within the year of our redemption</line>
            <line>Four hundred twenty-six; and Charles the Great</line>
            <line>Subdued the Saxons, and did seat the French</line>
            <line>Beyond the river Sala, in the year</line>
            <line>Eight hundred five. Besides, their writers say,</line>
            <line>King Pepin, which deposed Childeric,</line>
            <line>Did, as heir general, being descended</line>
            <line>Of Blithild, which was daughter to King Clothair,</line>
            <line>Make claim and title to the crown of France.</line>
            <line>Hugh Capet also, who usurped the crown</line>
            <line>Of Charles the duke of Lorraine, sole heir male</line>
            <line>Of the true line and stock of Charles the Great,</line>
            <line>To find his title with some shows of truth,</line>
            <line>'Through, in pure truth, it was corrupt and naught,</line>
            <line>Convey'd himself as heir to the Lady Lingare,</line>
            <line>Daughter to Charlemain, who was the son</line>
            <line>To Lewis the emperor, and Lewis the son</line>
            <line>Of Charles the Great. Also King Lewis the Tenth,</line>
            <line>Who was sole heir to the usurper Capet,</line>
            <line>Could not keep quiet in his conscience,</line>
            <line>Wearing the crown of France, till satisfied</line>
            <line>That fair Queen Isabel, his grandmother,</line>
            <line>Was lineal of the Lady Ermengare,</line>
            <line>Daughter to Charles the foresaid duke of Lorraine:</line>
            <line>By the which marriage the line of Charles the Great</line>
            <line>Was re-united to the crown of France.</line>
            <line>So that, as clear as is the summer's sun.</line>
            <line>King Pepin's title and Hugh Capet's claim,</line>
            <line>King Lewis his satisfaction, all appear</line>
            <line>To hold in right and title of the female:</line>
            <line>So do the kings of France unto this day;</line>
            <line>Howbeit they would hold up this Salique law</line>
            <line>To bar your highness claiming from the female,</line>
            <line>And rather choose to hide them in a net</line>
            <line>Than amply to imbar their crooked titles</line>
            <line>Usurp'd from you and your progenitors.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>May I with right and conscience make this claim?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CANTERBURY</speaker>
            <line>The sin upon my head, dread sovereign!</line>
            <line>For in the book of Numbers is it writ,</line>
            <line>When the man dies, let the inheritance</line>
            <line>Descend unto the daughter. Gracious lord,</line>
            <line>Stand for your own; unwind your bloody flag;</line>
            <line>Look back into your mighty ancestors:</line>
            <line>Go, my dread lord, to your great-grandsire's tomb,</line>
            <line>From whom you claim; invoke his warlike spirit,</line>
            <line>And your great-uncle's, Edward the Black Prince,</line>
            <line>Who on the French ground play'd a tragedy,</line>
            <line>Making defeat on the full power of France,</line>
            <line>Whiles his most mighty father on a hill</line>
            <line>Stood smiling to behold his lion's whelp</line>
            <line>Forage in blood of French nobility.</line>
            <line>O noble English. that could entertain</line>
            <line>With half their forces the full Pride of France</line>
            <line>And let another half stand laughing by,</line>
            <line>All out of work and cold for action!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ELY</speaker>
            <line>Awake remembrance of these valiant dead</line>
            <line>And with your puissant arm renew their feats:</line>
            <line>You are their heir; you sit upon their throne;</line>
            <line>The blood and courage that renowned them</line>
            <line>Runs in your veins; and my thrice-puissant liege</line>
            <line>Is in the very May-morn of his youth,</line>
            <line>Ripe for exploits and mighty enterprises.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EXETER</speaker>
            <line>Your brother kings and monarchs of the earth</line>
            <line>Do all expect that you should rouse yourself,</line>
            <line>As did the former lions of your blood.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WESTMORELAND</speaker>
            <line>They know your grace hath cause and means and might;</line>
            <line>So hath your highness; never king of England</line>
            <line>Had nobles richer and more loyal subjects,</line>
            <line>Whose hearts have left their bodies here in England</line>
            <line>And lie pavilion'd in the fields of France.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CANTERBURY</speaker>
            <line>O, let their bodies follow, my dear liege,</line>
            <line>With blood and sword and fire to win your right;</line>
            <line>In aid whereof we of the spiritualty</line>
            <line>Will raise your highness such a mighty sum</line>
            <line>As never did the clergy at one time</line>
            <line>Bring in to any of your ancestors.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>We must not only arm to invade the French,</line>
            <line>But lay down our proportions to defend</line>
            <line>Against the Scot, who will make road upon us</line>
            <line>With all advantages.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CANTERBURY</speaker>
            <line>They of those marches, gracious sovereign,</line>
            <line>Shall be a wall sufficient to defend</line>
            <line>Our inland from the pilfering borderers.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>We do not mean the coursing snatchers only,</line>
            <line>But fear the main intendment of the Scot,</line>
            <line>Who hath been still a giddy neighbour to us;</line>
            <line>For you shall read that my great-grandfather</line>
            <line>Never went with his forces into France</line>
            <line>But that the Scot on his unfurnish'd kingdom</line>
            <line>Came pouring, like the tide into a breach,</line>
            <line>With ample and brim fulness of his force,</line>
            <line>Galling the gleaned land with hot assays,</line>
            <line>Girding with grievous siege castles and towns;</line>
            <line>That England, being empty of defence,</line>
            <line>Hath shook and trembled at the ill neighbourhood.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CANTERBURY</speaker>
            <line>She hath been then more fear'd than harm'd, my liege;</line>
            <line>For hear her but exampled by herself:</line>
            <line>When all her chivalry hath been in France</line>
            <line>And she a mourning widow of her nobles,</line>
            <line>She hath herself not only well defended</line>
            <line>But taken and impounded as a stray</line>
            <line>The King of Scots; whom she did send to France,</line>
            <line>To fill King Edward's fame with prisoner kings</line>
            <line>And make her chronicle as rich with praise</line>
            <line>As is the ooze and bottom of the sea</line>
            <line>With sunken wreck and sunless treasuries.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WESTMORELAND</speaker>
            <line>But there's a saying very old and true,</line>
            <line>'If that you will France win,</line>
            <line>Then with Scotland first begin:'</line>
            <line>For once the eagle England being in prey,</line>
            <line>To her unguarded nest the weasel Scot</line>
            <line>Comes sneaking and so sucks her princely eggs,</line>
            <line>Playing the mouse in absence of the cat,</line>
            <line>To tear and havoc more than she can eat.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EXETER</speaker>
            <line>It follows then the cat must stay at home:</line>
            <line>Yet that is but a crush'd necessity,</line>
            <line>Since we have locks to safeguard necessaries,</line>
            <line>And pretty traps to catch the petty thieves.</line>
            <line>While that the armed hand doth fight abroad,</line>
            <line>The advised head defends itself at home;</line>
            <line>For government, though high and low and lower,</line>
            <line>Put into parts, doth keep in one consent,</line>
            <line>Congreeing in a full and natural close,</line>
            <line>Like music.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CANTERBURY</speaker>
            <line>Therefore doth heaven divide</line>
            <line>The state of man in divers functions,</line>
            <line>Setting endeavour in continual motion;</line>
            <line>To which is fixed, as an aim or butt,</line>
            <line>Obedience: for so work the honey-bees,</line>
            <line>Creatures that by a rule in nature teach</line>
            <line>The act of order to a peopled kingdom.</line>
            <line>They have a king and officers of sorts;</line>
            <line>Where some, like magistrates, correct at home,</line>
            <line>Others, like merchants, venture trade abroad,</line>
            <line>Others, like soldiers, armed in their stings,</line>
            <line>Make boot upon the summer's velvet buds,</line>
            <line>Which pillage they with merry march bring home</line>
            <line>To the tent-royal of their emperor;</line>
            <line>Who, busied in his majesty, surveys</line>
            <line>The singing masons building roofs of gold,</line>
            <line>The civil citizens kneading up the honey,</line>
            <line>The poor mechanic porters crowding in</line>
            <line>Their heavy burdens at his narrow gate,</line>
            <line>The sad-eyed justice, with his surly hum,</line>
            <line>Delivering o'er to executors pale</line>
            <line>The lazy yawning drone. I this infer,</line>
            <line>That many things, having full reference</line>
            <line>To one consent, may work contrariously:</line>
            <line>As many arrows, loosed several ways,</line>
            <line>Come to one mark; as many ways meet in one town;</line>
            <line>As many fresh streams meet in one salt sea;</line>
            <line>As many lines close in the dial's centre;</line>
            <line>So may a thousand actions, once afoot.</line>
            <line>End in one purpose, and be all well borne</line>
            <line>Without defeat. Therefore to France, my liege.</line>
            <line>Divide your happy England into four;</line>
            <line>Whereof take you one quarter into France,</line>
            <line>And you withal shall make all Gallia shake.</line>
            <line>If we, with thrice such powers left at home,</line>
            <line>Cannot defend our own doors from the dog,</line>
            <line>Let us be worried and our nation lose</line>
            <line>The name of hardiness and policy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>Call in the messengers sent from the Dauphin.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt some Attendants</stagedir>
            <line>Now are we well resolved; and, by God's help,</line>
            <line>And yours, the noble sinews of our power,</line>
            <line>France being ours, we'll bend it to our awe,</line>
            <line>Or break it all to pieces: or there we'll sit,</line>
            <line>Ruling in large and ample empery</line>
            <line>O'er France and all her almost kingly dukedoms,</line>
            <line>Or lay these bones in an unworthy urn,</line>
            <line>Tombless, with no remembrance over them:</line>
            <line>Either our history shall with full mouth</line>
            <line>Speak freely of our acts, or else our grave,</line>
            <line>Like Turkish mute, shall have a tongueless mouth,</line>
            <line>Not worshipp'd with a waxen epitaph.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter Ambassadors of France</stagedir>
            <line>Now are we well prepared to know the pleasure</line>
            <line>Of our fair cousin Dauphin; for we hear</line>
            <line>Your greeting is from him, not from the king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Ambassador</speaker>
            <line>May't please your majesty to give us leave</line>
            <line>Freely to render what we have in charge;</line>
            <line>Or shall we sparingly show you far off</line>
            <line>The Dauphin's meaning and our embassy?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>We are no tyrant, but a Christian king;</line>
            <line>Unto whose grace our passion is as subject</line>
            <line>As are our wretches fetter'd in our prisons:</line>
            <line>Therefore with frank and with uncurbed plainness</line>
            <line>Tell us the Dauphin's mind.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Ambassador</speaker>
            <line>Thus, then, in few.</line>
            <line>Your highness, lately sending into France,</line>
            <line>Did claim some certain dukedoms, in the right</line>
            <line>Of your great predecessor, King Edward the Third.</line>
            <line>In answer of which claim, the prince our master</line>
            <line>Says that you savour too much of your youth,</line>
            <line>And bids you be advised there's nought in France</line>
            <line>That can be with a nimble galliard won;</line>
            <line>You cannot revel into dukedoms there.</line>
            <line>He therefore sends you, meeter for your spirit,</line>
            <line>This tun of treasure; and, in lieu of this,</line>
            <line>Desires you let the dukedoms that you claim</line>
            <line>Hear no more of you. This the Dauphin speaks.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>What treasure, uncle?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EXETER</speaker>
            <line>Tennis-balls, my liege.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>We are glad the Dauphin is so pleasant with us;</line>
            <line>His present and your pains we thank you for:</line>
            <line>When we have march'd our rackets to these balls,</line>
            <line>We will, in France, by God's grace, play a set</line>
            <line>Shall strike his father's crown into the hazard.</line>
            <line>Tell him he hath made a match with such a wrangler</line>
            <line>That all the courts of France will be disturb'd</line>
            <line>With chaces. And we understand him well,</line>
            <line>How he comes o'er us with our wilder days,</line>
            <line>Not measuring what use we made of them.</line>
            <line>We never valued this poor seat of England;</line>
            <line>And therefore, living hence, did give ourself</line>
            <line>To barbarous licence; as 'tis ever common</line>
            <line>That men are merriest when they are from home.</line>
            <line>But tell the Dauphin I will keep my state,</line>
            <line>Be like a king and show my sail of greatness</line>
            <line>When I do rouse me in my throne of France:</line>
            <line>For that I have laid by my majesty</line>
            <line>And plodded like a man for working-days,</line>
            <line>But I will rise there with so full a glory</line>
            <line>That I will dazzle all the eyes of France,</line>
            <line>Yea, strike the Dauphin blind to look on us.</line>
            <line>And tell the pleasant prince this mock of his</line>
            <line>Hath turn'd his balls to gun-stones; and his soul</line>
            <line>Shall stand sore charged for the wasteful vengeance</line>
            <line>That shall fly with them: for many a thousand widows</line>
            <line>Shall this his mock mock out of their dear husbands;</line>
            <line>Mock mothers from their sons, mock castles down;</line>
            <line>And some are yet ungotten and unborn</line>
            <line>That shall have cause to curse the Dauphin's scorn.</line>
            <line>But this lies all within the will of God,</line>
            <line>To whom I do appeal; and in whose name</line>
            <line>Tell you the Dauphin I am coming on,</line>
            <line>To venge me as I may and to put forth</line>
            <line>My rightful hand in a well-hallow'd cause.</line>
            <line>So get you hence in peace; and tell the Dauphin</line>
            <line>His jest will savour but of shallow wit,</line>
            <line>When thousands weep more than did laugh at it.</line>
            <line>Convey them with safe conduct. Fare you well.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt Ambassadors</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EXETER</speaker>
            <line>This was a merry message.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>We hope to make the sender blush at it.</line>
            <line>Therefore, my lords, omit no happy hour</line>
            <line>That may give furtherance to our expedition;</line>
            <line>For we have now no thought in us but France,</line>
            <line>Save those to God, that run before our business.</line>
            <line>Therefore let our proportions for these wars</line>
            <line>Be soon collected and all things thought upon</line>
            <line>That may with reasonable swiftness add</line>
            <line>More feathers to our wings; for, God before,</line>
            <line>We'll chide this Dauphin at his father's door.</line>
            <line>Therefore let every man now task his thought,</line>
            <line>That this fair action may on foot be brought.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt. Flourish</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>