<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:shakespear:dtd:act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-2">
   <title>ACT II</title>
   <prologue id="act-2-prologue">
      <title>PROLOGUE</title>
      <prologue-body>
         <stagedir>Enter Chorus</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <line>Now all the youth of England are on fire,</line>
            <line>And silken dalliance in the wardrobe lies:</line>
            <line>Now thrive the armourers, and honour's thought</line>
            <line>Reigns solely in the breast of every man:</line>
            <line>They sell the pasture now to buy the horse,</line>
            <line>Following the mirror of all Christian kings,</line>
            <line>With winged heels, as English Mercuries.</line>
            <line>For now sits Expectation in the air,</line>
            <line>And hides a sword from hilts unto the point</line>
            <line>With crowns imperial, crowns and coronets,</line>
            <line>Promised to Harry and his followers.</line>
            <line>The French, advised by good intelligence</line>
            <line>Of this most dreadful preparation,</line>
            <line>Shake in their fear and with pale policy</line>
            <line>Seek to divert the English purposes.</line>
            <line>O England! model to thy inward greatness,</line>
            <line>Like little body with a mighty heart,</line>
            <line>What mightst thou do, that honour would thee do,</line>
            <line>Were all thy children kind and natural!</line>
            <line>But see thy fault! France hath in thee found out</line>
            <line>A nest of hollow bosoms, which he fills</line>
            <line>With treacherous crowns; and three corrupted men,</line>
            <line>One, Richard Earl of Cambridge, and the second,</line>
            <line>Henry Lord Scroop of Masham, and the third,</line>
            <line>Sir Thomas Grey, knight, of Northumberland,</line>
            <line>Have, for the gilt of France,--O guilt indeed!</line>
            <line>Confirm'd conspiracy with fearful France;</line>
            <line>And by their hands this grace of kings must die,</line>
            <line>If hell and treason hold their promises,</line>
            <line>Ere he take ship for France, and in Southampton.</line>
            <line>Linger your patience on; and we'll digest</line>
            <line>The abuse of distance; force a play:</line>
            <line>The sum is paid; the traitors are agreed;</line>
            <line>The king is set from London; and the scene</line>
            <line>Is now transported, gentles, to Southampton;</line>
            <line>There is the playhouse now, there must you sit:</line>
            <line>And thence to France shall we convey you safe,</line>
            <line>And bring you back, charming the narrow seas</line>
            <line>To give you gentle pass; for, if we may,</line>
            <line>We'll not offend one stomach with our play.</line>
            <line>But, till the king come forth, and not till then,</line>
            <line>Unto Southampton do we shift our scene.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </prologue-body>
   </prologue>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  London. A street.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter Corporal NYM and Lieutenant BARDOLPH</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BARDOLPH</speaker>
            <line>Well met, Corporal Nym.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NYM</speaker>
            <line>Good morrow, Lieutenant Bardolph.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BARDOLPH</speaker>
            <line>What, are Ancient Pistol and you friends yet?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NYM</speaker>
            <line>For my part, I care not: I say little; but when</line>
            <line>time shall serve, there shall be smiles; but that</line>
            <line>shall be as it may. I dare not fight; but I will</line>
            <line>wink and hold out mine iron: it is a simple one; but</line>
            <line>what though? it will toast cheese, and it will</line>
            <line>endure cold as another man's sword will: and</line>
            <line>there's an end.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BARDOLPH</speaker>
            <line>I will bestow a breakfast to make you friends; and</line>
            <line>we'll be all three sworn brothers to France: let it</line>
            <line>be so, good Corporal Nym.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NYM</speaker>
            <line>Faith, I will live so long as I may, that's the</line>
            <line>certain of it; and when I cannot live any longer, I</line>
            <line>will do as I may: that is my rest, that is the</line>
            <line>rendezvous of it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BARDOLPH</speaker>
            <line>It is certain, corporal, that he is married to Nell</line>
            <line>Quickly: and certainly she did you wrong; for you</line>
            <line>were troth-plight to her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NYM</speaker>
            <line>I cannot tell: things must be as they may: men may</line>
            <line>sleep, and they may have their throats about them at</line>
            <line>that time; and some say knives have edges. It must</line>
            <line>be as it may: though patience be a tired mare, yet</line>
            <line>she will plod. There must be conclusions. Well, I</line>
            <line>cannot tell.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter PISTOL and Hostess</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BARDOLPH</speaker>
            <line>Here comes Ancient Pistol and his wife: good</line>
            <line>corporal, be patient here. How now, mine host Pistol!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>Base tike, call'st thou me host? Now, by this hand,</line>
            <line>I swear, I scorn the term; Nor shall my Nell keep lodgers.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Hostess</speaker>
            <line>No, by my troth, not long; for we cannot lodge and</line>
            <line>board a dozen or fourteen gentlewomen that live</line>
            <line>honestly by the prick of their needles, but it will</line>
            <line>be thought we keep a bawdy house straight.</line>
            <stagedir>NYM and PISTOL draw</stagedir>
            <line>O well a day, Lady, if he be not drawn now! we</line>
            <line>shall see wilful adultery and murder committed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BARDOLPH</speaker>
            <line>Good lieutenant! good corporal! offer nothing here.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NYM</speaker>
            <line>Pish!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>Pish for thee, Iceland dog! thou prick-ear'd cur of Iceland!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Hostess</speaker>
            <line>Good Corporal Nym, show thy valour, and put up your sword.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NYM</speaker>
            <line>Will you shog off? I would have you solus.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>'Solus,' egregious dog? O viper vile!</line>
            <line>The 'solus' in thy most mervailous face;</line>
            <line>The 'solus' in thy teeth, and in thy throat,</line>
            <line>And in thy hateful lungs, yea, in thy maw, perdy,</line>
            <line>And, which is worse, within thy nasty mouth!</line>
            <line>I do retort the 'solus' in thy bowels;</line>
            <line>For I can take, and Pistol's cock is up,</line>
            <line>And flashing fire will follow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NYM</speaker>
            <line>I am not Barbason; you cannot conjure me. I have an</line>
            <line>humour to knock you indifferently well. If you grow</line>
            <line>foul with me, Pistol, I will scour you with my</line>
            <line>rapier, as I may, in fair terms: if you would walk</line>
            <line>off, I would prick your guts a little, in good</line>
            <line>terms, as I may: and that's the humour of it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>O braggart vile and damned furious wight!</line>
            <line>The grave doth gape, and doting death is near;</line>
            <line>Therefore exhale.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BARDOLPH</speaker>
            <line>Hear me, hear me what I say: he that strikes the</line>
            <line>first stroke, I'll run him up to the hilts, as I am a soldier.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Draws</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>An oath of mickle might; and fury shall abate.</line>
            <line>Give me thy fist, thy fore-foot to me give:</line>
            <line>Thy spirits are most tall.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NYM</speaker>
            <line>I will cut thy throat, one time or other, in fair</line>
            <line>terms: that is the humour of it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>'Couple a gorge!'</line>
            <line>That is the word. I thee defy again.</line>
            <line>O hound of Crete, think'st thou my spouse to get?</line>
            <line>No; to the spital go,</line>
            <line>And from the powdering tub of infamy</line>
            <line>Fetch forth the lazar kite of Cressid's kind,</line>
            <line>Doll Tearsheet she by name, and her espouse:</line>
            <line>I have, and I will hold, the quondam Quickly</line>
            <line>For the only she; and--pauca, there's enough. Go to.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter the Boy</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Boy</speaker>
            <line>Mine host Pistol, you must come to my master, and</line>
            <line>you, hostess: he is very sick, and would to bed.</line>
            <line>Good Bardolph, put thy face between his sheets, and</line>
            <line>do the office of a warming-pan. Faith, he's very ill.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BARDOLPH</speaker>
            <line>Away, you rogue!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Hostess</speaker>
            <line>By my troth, he'll yield the crow a pudding one of</line>
            <line>these days. The king has killed his heart. Good</line>
            <line>husband, come home presently.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt Hostess and Boy</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BARDOLPH</speaker>
            <line>Come, shall I make you two friends? We must to</line>
            <line>France together: why the devil should we keep</line>
            <line>knives to cut one another's throats?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>Let floods o'erswell, and fiends for food howl on!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NYM</speaker>
            <line>You'll pay me the eight shillings I won of you at betting?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>Base is the slave that pays.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NYM</speaker>
            <line>That now I will have: that's the humour of it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>As manhood shall compound: push home.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>They draw</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BARDOLPH</speaker>
            <line>By this sword, he that makes the first thrust, I'll</line>
            <line>kill him; by this sword, I will.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>Sword is an oath, and oaths must have their course.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BARDOLPH</speaker>
            <line>Corporal Nym, an thou wilt be friends, be friends:</line>
            <line>an thou wilt not, why, then, be enemies with me too.</line>
            <line>Prithee, put up.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NYM</speaker>
            <line>I shall have my eight shillings I won of you at betting?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>A noble shalt thou have, and present pay;</line>
            <line>And liquor likewise will I give to thee,</line>
            <line>And friendship shall combine, and brotherhood:</line>
            <line>I'll live by Nym, and Nym shall live by me;</line>
            <line>Is not this just? for I shall sutler be</line>
            <line>Unto the camp, and profits will accrue.</line>
            <line>Give me thy hand.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NYM</speaker>
            <line>I shall have my noble?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>In cash most justly paid.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NYM</speaker>
            <line>Well, then, that's the humour of't.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter Hostess</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Hostess</speaker>
            <line>As ever you came of women, come in quickly to Sir</line>
            <line>John. Ah, poor heart! he is so shaked of a burning</line>
            <line>quotidian tertian, that it is most lamentable to</line>
            <line>behold. Sweet men, come to him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NYM</speaker>
            <line>The king hath run bad humours on the knight; that's</line>
            <line>the even of it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>Nym, thou hast spoke the right;</line>
            <line>His heart is fracted and corroborate.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NYM</speaker>
            <line>The king is a good king: but it must be as it may;</line>
            <line>he passes some humours and careers.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>Let us condole the knight; for, lambkins we will live.</line>
         </speech>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  Southampton. A council-chamber.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter EXETER, BEDFORD, and WESTMORELAND</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEDFORD</speaker>
            <line>'Fore God, his grace is bold, to trust these traitors.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EXETER</speaker>
            <line>They shall be apprehended by and by.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WESTMORELAND</speaker>
            <line>How smooth and even they do bear themselves!</line>
            <line>As if allegiance in their bosoms sat,</line>
            <line>Crowned with faith and constant loyalty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEDFORD</speaker>
            <line>The king hath note of all that they intend,</line>
            <line>By interception which they dream not of.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EXETER</speaker>
            <line>Nay, but the man that was his bedfellow,</line>
            <line>Whom he hath dull'd and cloy'd with gracious favours,</line>
            <line>That he should, for a foreign purse, so sell</line>
            <line>His sovereign's life to death and treachery.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Trumpets sound. Enter KING HENRY V, SCROOP,
CAMBRIDGE, GREY, and Attendants</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>Now sits the wind fair, and we will aboard.</line>
            <line>My Lord of Cambridge, and my kind Lord of Masham,</line>
            <line>And you, my gentle knight, give me your thoughts:</line>
            <line>Think you not that the powers we bear with us</line>
            <line>Will cut their passage through the force of France,</line>
            <line>Doing the execution and the act</line>
            <line>For which we have in head assembled them?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SCROOP</speaker>
            <line>No doubt, my liege, if each man do his best.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>I doubt not that; since we are well persuaded</line>
            <line>We carry not a heart with us from hence</line>
            <line>That grows not in a fair consent with ours,</line>
            <line>Nor leave not one behind that doth not wish</line>
            <line>Success and conquest to attend on us.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMBRIDGE</speaker>
            <line>Never was monarch better fear'd and loved</line>
            <line>Than is your majesty: there's not, I think, a subject</line>
            <line>That sits in heart-grief and uneasiness</line>
            <line>Under the sweet shade of your government.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GREY</speaker>
            <line>True: those that were your father's enemies</line>
            <line>Have steep'd their galls in honey and do serve you</line>
            <line>With hearts create of duty and of zeal.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>We therefore have great cause of thankfulness;</line>
            <line>And shall forget the office of our hand,</line>
            <line>Sooner than quittance of desert and merit</line>
            <line>According to the weight and worthiness.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SCROOP</speaker>
            <line>So service shall with steeled sinews toil,</line>
            <line>And labour shall refresh itself with hope,</line>
            <line>To do your grace incessant services.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>We judge no less. Uncle of Exeter,</line>
            <line>Enlarge the man committed yesterday,</line>
            <line>That rail'd against our person: we consider</line>
            <line>it was excess of wine that set him on;</line>
            <line>And on his more advice we pardon him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SCROOP</speaker>
            <line>That's mercy, but too much security:</line>
            <line>Let him be punish'd, sovereign, lest example</line>
            <line>Breed, by his sufferance, more of such a kind.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>O, let us yet be merciful.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMBRIDGE</speaker>
            <line>So may your highness, and yet punish too.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GREY</speaker>
            <line>Sir,</line>
            <line>You show great mercy, if you give him life,</line>
            <line>After the taste of much correction.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>Alas, your too much love and care of me</line>
            <line>Are heavy orisons 'gainst this poor wretch!</line>
            <line>If little faults, proceeding on distemper,</line>
            <line>Shall not be wink'd at, how shall we stretch our eye</line>
            <line>When capital crimes, chew'd, swallow'd and digested,</line>
            <line>Appear before us? We'll yet enlarge that man,</line>
            <line>Though Cambridge, Scroop and Grey, in their dear care</line>
            <line>And tender preservation of our person,</line>
            <line>Would have him punished. And now to our French causes:</line>
            <line>Who are the late commissioners?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMBRIDGE</speaker>
            <line>I one, my lord:</line>
            <line>Your highness bade me ask for it to-day.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SCROOP</speaker>
            <line>So did you me, my liege.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GREY</speaker>
            <line>And I, my royal sovereign.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>Then, Richard Earl of Cambridge, there is yours;</line>
            <line>There yours, Lord Scroop of Masham; and, sir knight,</line>
            <line>Grey of Northumberland, this same is yours:</line>
            <line>Read them; and know, I know your worthiness.</line>
            <line>My Lord of Westmoreland, and uncle Exeter,</line>
            <line>We will aboard to night. Why, how now, gentlemen!</line>
            <line>What see you in those papers that you lose</line>
            <line>So much complexion? Look ye, how they change!</line>
            <line>Their cheeks are paper. Why, what read you there</line>
            <line>That hath so cowarded and chased your blood</line>
            <line>Out of appearance?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMBRIDGE</speaker>
            <line>I do confess my fault;</line>
            <line>And do submit me to your highness' mercy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GREY</speaker>
            <speaker>SCROOP</speaker>
            <line>To which we all appeal.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>The mercy that was quick in us but late,</line>
            <line>By your own counsel is suppress'd and kill'd:</line>
            <line>You must not dare, for shame, to talk of mercy;</line>
            <line>For your own reasons turn into your bosoms,</line>
            <line>As dogs upon their masters, worrying you.</line>
            <line>See you, my princes, and my noble peers,</line>
            <line>These English monsters! My Lord of Cambridge here,</line>
            <line>You know how apt our love was to accord</line>
            <line>To furnish him with all appertinents</line>
            <line>Belonging to his honour; and this man</line>
            <line>Hath, for a few light crowns, lightly conspired,</line>
            <line>And sworn unto the practises of France,</line>
            <line>To kill us here in Hampton: to the which</line>
            <line>This knight, no less for bounty bound to us</line>
            <line>Than Cambridge is, hath likewise sworn. But, O,</line>
            <line>What shall I say to thee, Lord Scroop? thou cruel,</line>
            <line>Ingrateful, savage and inhuman creature!</line>
            <line>Thou that didst bear the key of all my counsels,</line>
            <line>That knew'st the very bottom of my soul,</line>
            <line>That almost mightst have coin'd me into gold,</line>
            <line>Wouldst thou have practised on me for thy use,</line>
            <line>May it be possible, that foreign hire</line>
            <line>Could out of thee extract one spark of evil</line>
            <line>That might annoy my finger? 'tis so strange,</line>
            <line>That, though the truth of it stands off as gross</line>
            <line>As black and white, my eye will scarcely see it.</line>
            <line>Treason and murder ever kept together,</line>
            <line>As two yoke-devils sworn to either's purpose,</line>
            <line>Working so grossly in a natural cause,</line>
            <line>That admiration did not whoop at them:</line>
            <line>But thou, 'gainst all proportion, didst bring in</line>
            <line>Wonder to wait on treason and on murder:</line>
            <line>And whatsoever cunning fiend it was</line>
            <line>That wrought upon thee so preposterously</line>
            <line>Hath got the voice in hell for excellence:</line>
            <line>All other devils that suggest by treasons</line>
            <line>Do botch and bungle up damnation</line>
            <line>With patches, colours, and with forms being fetch'd</line>
            <line>From glistering semblances of piety;</line>
            <line>But he that temper'd thee bade thee stand up,</line>
            <line>Gave thee no instance why thou shouldst do treason,</line>
            <line>Unless to dub thee with the name of traitor.</line>
            <line>If that same demon that hath gull'd thee thus</line>
            <line>Should with his lion gait walk the whole world,</line>
            <line>He might return to vasty Tartar back,</line>
            <line>And tell the legions 'I can never win</line>
            <line>A soul so easy as that Englishman's.'</line>
            <line>O, how hast thou with 'jealousy infected</line>
            <line>The sweetness of affiance! Show men dutiful?</line>
            <line>Why, so didst thou: seem they grave and learned?</line>
            <line>Why, so didst thou: come they of noble family?</line>
            <line>Why, so didst thou: seem they religious?</line>
            <line>Why, so didst thou: or are they spare in diet,</line>
            <line>Free from gross passion or of mirth or anger,</line>
            <line>Constant in spirit, not swerving with the blood,</line>
            <line>Garnish'd and deck'd in modest complement,</line>
            <line>Not working with the eye without the ear,</line>
            <line>And but in purged judgment trusting neither?</line>
            <line>Such and so finely bolted didst thou seem:</line>
            <line>And thus thy fall hath left a kind of blot,</line>
            <line>To mark the full-fraught man and best indued</line>
            <line>With some suspicion. I will weep for thee;</line>
            <line>For this revolt of thine, methinks, is like</line>
            <line>Another fall of man. Their faults are open:</line>
            <line>Arrest them to the answer of the law;</line>
            <line>And God acquit them of their practises!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EXETER</speaker>
            <line>I arrest thee of high treason, by the name of</line>
            <line>Richard Earl of Cambridge.</line>
            <line>I arrest thee of high treason, by the name of</line>
            <line>Henry Lord Scroop of Masham.</line>
            <line>I arrest thee of high treason, by the name of</line>
            <line>Thomas Grey, knight, of Northumberland.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SCROOP</speaker>
            <line>Our purposes God justly hath discover'd;</line>
            <line>And I repent my fault more than my death;</line>
            <line>Which I beseech your highness to forgive,</line>
            <line>Although my body pay the price of it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMBRIDGE</speaker>
            <line>For me, the gold of France did not seduce;</line>
            <line>Although I did admit it as a motive</line>
            <line>The sooner to effect what I intended:</line>
            <line>But God be thanked for prevention;</line>
            <line>Which I in sufferance heartily will rejoice,</line>
            <line>Beseeching God and you to pardon me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GREY</speaker>
            <line>Never did faithful subject more rejoice</line>
            <line>At the discovery of most dangerous treason</line>
            <line>Than I do at this hour joy o'er myself.</line>
            <line>Prevented from a damned enterprise:</line>
            <line>My fault, but not my body, pardon, sovereign.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>God quit you in his mercy! Hear your sentence.</line>
            <line>You have conspired against our royal person,</line>
            <line>Join'd with an enemy proclaim'd and from his coffers</line>
            <line>Received the golden earnest of our death;</line>
            <line>Wherein you would have sold your king to slaughter,</line>
            <line>His princes and his peers to servitude,</line>
            <line>His subjects to oppression and contempt</line>
            <line>And his whole kingdom into desolation.</line>
            <line>Touching our person seek we no revenge;</line>
            <line>But we our kingdom's safety must so tender,</line>
            <line>Whose ruin you have sought, that to her laws</line>
            <line>We do deliver you. Get you therefore hence,</line>
            <line>Poor miserable wretches, to your death:</line>
            <line>The taste whereof, God of his mercy give</line>
            <line>You patience to endure, and true repentance</line>
            <line>Of all your dear offences! Bear them hence.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt CAMBRIDGE, SCROOP and GREY, guarded</stagedir>
            <line>Now, lords, for France; the enterprise whereof</line>
            <line>Shall be to you, as us, like glorious.</line>
            <line>We doubt not of a fair and lucky war,</line>
            <line>Since God so graciously hath brought to light</line>
            <line>This dangerous treason lurking in our way</line>
            <line>To hinder our beginnings. We doubt not now</line>
            <line>But every rub is smoothed on our way.</line>
            <line>Then forth, dear countrymen: let us deliver</line>
            <line>Our puissance into the hand of God,</line>
            <line>Putting it straight in expedition.</line>
            <line>Cheerly to sea; the signs of war advance:</line>
            <line>No king of England, if not king of France.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  London. Before a tavern.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter PISTOL, Hostess, NYM, BARDOLPH, and Boy</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Hostess</speaker>
            <line>Prithee, honey-sweet husband, let me bring thee to Staines.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>No; for my manly heart doth yearn.</line>
            <line>Bardolph, be blithe: Nym, rouse thy vaunting veins:</line>
            <line>Boy, bristle thy courage up; for Falstaff he is dead,</line>
            <line>And we must yearn therefore.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BARDOLPH</speaker>
            <line>Would I were with him, wheresome'er he is, either in</line>
            <line>heaven or in hell!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Hostess</speaker>
            <line>Nay, sure, he's not in hell: he's in Arthur's</line>
            <line>bosom, if ever man went to Arthur's bosom. A' made</line>
            <line>a finer end and went away an it had been any</line>
            <line>christom child; a' parted even just between twelve</line>
            <line>and one, even at the turning o' the tide: for after</line>
            <line>I saw him fumble with the sheets and play with</line>
            <line>flowers and smile upon his fingers' ends, I knew</line>
            <line>there was but one way; for his nose was as sharp as</line>
            <line>a pen, and a' babbled of green fields. 'How now,</line>
            <line>sir John!' quoth I 'what, man! be o' good</line>
            <line>cheer.' So a' cried out 'God, God, God!' three or</line>
            <line>four times. Now I, to comfort him, bid him a'</line>
            <line>should not think of God; I hoped there was no need</line>
            <line>to trouble himself with any such thoughts yet. So</line>
            <line>a' bade me lay more clothes on his feet: I put my</line>
            <line>hand into the bed and felt them, and they were as</line>
            <line>cold as any stone; then I felt to his knees, and</line>
            <line>they were as cold as any stone, and so upward and</line>
            <line>upward, and all was as cold as any stone.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NYM</speaker>
            <line>They say he cried out of sack.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Hostess</speaker>
            <line>Ay, that a' did.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BARDOLPH</speaker>
            <line>And of women.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Hostess</speaker>
            <line>Nay, that a' did not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Boy</speaker>
            <line>Yes, that a' did; and said they were devils</line>
            <line>incarnate.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Hostess</speaker>
            <line>A' could never abide carnation; 'twas a colour he</line>
            <line>never liked.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Boy</speaker>
            <line>A' said once, the devil would have him about women.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Hostess</speaker>
            <line>A' did in some sort, indeed, handle women; but then</line>
            <line>he was rheumatic, and talked of the whore of Babylon.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Boy</speaker>
            <line>Do you not remember, a' saw a flea stick upon</line>
            <line>Bardolph's nose, and a' said it was a black soul</line>
            <line>burning in hell-fire?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BARDOLPH</speaker>
            <line>Well, the fuel is gone that maintained that fire:</line>
            <line>that's all the riches I got in his service.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NYM</speaker>
            <line>Shall we shog? the king will be gone from</line>
            <line>Southampton.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>Come, let's away. My love, give me thy lips.</line>
            <line>Look to my chattels and my movables:</line>
            <line>Let senses rule; the word is 'Pitch and Pay:'</line>
            <line>Trust none;</line>
            <line>For oaths are straws, men's faiths are wafer-cakes,</line>
            <line>And hold-fast is the only dog, my duck:</line>
            <line>Therefore, Caveto be thy counsellor.</line>
            <line>Go, clear thy crystals. Yoke-fellows in arms,</line>
            <line>Let us to France; like horse-leeches, my boys,</line>
            <line>To suck, to suck, the very blood to suck!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Boy</speaker>
            <line>And that's but unwholesome food they say.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>Touch her soft mouth, and march.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BARDOLPH</speaker>
            <line>Farewell, hostess.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Kissing her</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NYM</speaker>
            <line>I cannot kiss, that is the humour of it; but, adieu.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>Let housewifery appear: keep close, I thee command.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Hostess</speaker>
            <line>Farewell; adieu.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-4">
      <title>SCENE IV.  France. The KING'S palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Flourish. Enter the FRENCH KING, the DAUPHIN, the
DUKES of BERRI and BRETAGNE, the Constable, and others</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING OF FRANCE</speaker>
            <line>Thus comes the English with full power upon us;</line>
            <line>And more than carefully it us concerns</line>
            <line>To answer royally in our defences.</line>
            <line>Therefore the Dukes of Berri and of Bretagne,</line>
            <line>Of Brabant and of Orleans, shall make forth,</line>
            <line>And you, Prince Dauphin, with all swift dispatch,</line>
            <line>To line and new repair our towns of war</line>
            <line>With men of courage and with means defendant;</line>
            <line>For England his approaches makes as fierce</line>
            <line>As waters to the sucking of a gulf.</line>
            <line>It fits us then to be as provident</line>
            <line>As fear may teach us out of late examples</line>
            <line>Left by the fatal and neglected English</line>
            <line>Upon our fields.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DAUPHIN</speaker>
            <line>My most redoubted father,</line>
            <line>It is most meet we arm us 'gainst the foe;</line>
            <line>For peace itself should not so dull a kingdom,</line>
            <line>Though war nor no known quarrel were in question,</line>
            <line>But that defences, musters, preparations,</line>
            <line>Should be maintain'd, assembled and collected,</line>
            <line>As were a war in expectation.</line>
            <line>Therefore, I say 'tis meet we all go forth</line>
            <line>To view the sick and feeble parts of France:</line>
            <line>And let us do it with no show of fear;</line>
            <line>No, with no more than if we heard that England</line>
            <line>Were busied with a Whitsun morris-dance:</line>
            <line>For, my good liege, she is so idly king'd,</line>
            <line>Her sceptre so fantastically borne</line>
            <line>By a vain, giddy, shallow, humorous youth,</line>
            <line>That fear attends her not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Constable</speaker>
            <line>O peace, Prince Dauphin!</line>
            <line>You are too much mistaken in this king:</line>
            <line>Question your grace the late ambassadors,</line>
            <line>With what great state he heard their embassy,</line>
            <line>How well supplied with noble counsellors,</line>
            <line>How modest in exception, and withal</line>
            <line>How terrible in constant resolution,</line>
            <line>And you shall find his vanities forespent</line>
            <line>Were but the outside of the Roman Brutus,</line>
            <line>Covering discretion with a coat of folly;</line>
            <line>As gardeners do with ordure hide those roots</line>
            <line>That shall first spring and be most delicate.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DAUPHIN</speaker>
            <line>Well, 'tis not so, my lord high constable;</line>
            <line>But though we think it so, it is no matter:</line>
            <line>In cases of defence 'tis best to weigh</line>
            <line>The enemy more mighty than he seems:</line>
            <line>So the proportions of defence are fill'd;</line>
            <line>Which of a weak or niggardly projection</line>
            <line>Doth, like a miser, spoil his coat with scanting</line>
            <line>A little cloth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING OF FRANCE</speaker>
            <line>Think we King Harry strong;</line>
            <line>And, princes, look you strongly arm to meet him.</line>
            <line>The kindred of him hath been flesh'd upon us;</line>
            <line>And he is bred out of that bloody strain</line>
            <line>That haunted us in our familiar paths:</line>
            <line>Witness our too much memorable shame</line>
            <line>When Cressy battle fatally was struck,</line>
            <line>And all our princes captiv'd by the hand</line>
            <line>Of that black name, Edward, Black Prince of Wales;</line>
            <line>Whiles that his mountain sire, on mountain standing,</line>
            <line>Up in the air, crown'd with the golden sun,</line>
            <line>Saw his heroical seed, and smiled to see him,</line>
            <line>Mangle the work of nature and deface</line>
            <line>The patterns that by God and by French fathers</line>
            <line>Had twenty years been made. This is a stem</line>
            <line>Of that victorious stock; and let us fear</line>
            <line>The native mightiness and fate of him.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter a Messenger</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>Ambassadors from Harry King of England</line>
            <line>Do crave admittance to your majesty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING OF FRANCE</speaker>
            <line>We'll give them present audience. Go, and bring them.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt Messenger and certain Lords</stagedir>
            <line>You see this chase is hotly follow'd, friends.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DAUPHIN</speaker>
            <line>Turn head, and stop pursuit; for coward dogs</line>
            <line>Most spend their mouths when what they seem to threaten</line>
            <line>Runs far before them. Good my sovereign,</line>
            <line>Take up the English short, and let them know</line>
            <line>Of what a monarchy you are the head:</line>
            <line>Self-love, my liege, is not so vile a sin</line>
            <line>As self-neglecting.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter Lords, with EXETER and train</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING OF FRANCE</speaker>
            <line>From our brother England?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EXETER</speaker>
            <line>From him; and thus he greets your majesty.</line>
            <line>He wills you, in the name of God Almighty,</line>
            <line>That you divest yourself, and lay apart</line>
            <line>The borrow'd glories that by gift of heaven,</line>
            <line>By law of nature and of nations, 'long</line>
            <line>To him and to his heirs; namely, the crown</line>
            <line>And all wide-stretched honours that pertain</line>
            <line>By custom and the ordinance of times</line>
            <line>Unto the crown of France. That you may know</line>
            <line>'Tis no sinister nor no awkward claim,</line>
            <line>Pick'd from the worm-holes of long-vanish'd days,</line>
            <line>Nor from the dust of old oblivion raked,</line>
            <line>He sends you this most memorable line,</line>
            <line>In every branch truly demonstrative;</line>
            <line>Willing to overlook this pedigree:</line>
            <line>And when you find him evenly derived</line>
            <line>From his most famed of famous ancestors,</line>
            <line>Edward the Third, he bids you then resign</line>
            <line>Your crown and kingdom, indirectly held</line>
            <line>From him the native and true challenger.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING OF FRANCE</speaker>
            <line>Or else what follows?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EXETER</speaker>
            <line>Bloody constraint; for if you hide the crown</line>
            <line>Even in your hearts, there will he rake for it:</line>
            <line>Therefore in fierce tempest is he coming,</line>
            <line>In thunder and in earthquake, like a Jove,</line>
            <line>That, if requiring fail, he will compel;</line>
            <line>And bids you, in the bowels of the Lord,</line>
            <line>Deliver up the crown, and to take mercy</line>
            <line>On the poor souls for whom this hungry war</line>
            <line>Opens his vasty jaws; and on your head</line>
            <line>Turning the widows' tears, the orphans' cries</line>
            <line>The dead men's blood, the pining maidens groans,</line>
            <line>For husbands, fathers and betrothed lovers,</line>
            <line>That shall be swallow'd in this controversy.</line>
            <line>This is his claim, his threatening and my message;</line>
            <line>Unless the Dauphin be in presence here,</line>
            <line>To whom expressly I bring greeting too.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING OF FRANCE</speaker>
            <line>For us, we will consider of this further:</line>
            <line>To-morrow shall you bear our full intent</line>
            <line>Back to our brother England.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DAUPHIN</speaker>
            <line>For the Dauphin,</line>
            <line>I stand here for him: what to him from England?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EXETER</speaker>
            <line>Scorn and defiance; slight regard, contempt,</line>
            <line>And any thing that may not misbecome</line>
            <line>The mighty sender, doth he prize you at.</line>
            <line>Thus says my king; an' if your father's highness</line>
            <line>Do not, in grant of all demands at large,</line>
            <line>Sweeten the bitter mock you sent his majesty,</line>
            <line>He'll call you to so hot an answer of it,</line>
            <line>That caves and womby vaultages of France</line>
            <line>Shall chide your trespass and return your mock</line>
            <line>In second accent of his ordnance.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DAUPHIN</speaker>
            <line>Say, if my father render fair return,</line>
            <line>It is against my will; for I desire</line>
            <line>Nothing but odds with England: to that end,</line>
            <line>As matching to his youth and vanity,</line>
            <line>I did present him with the Paris balls.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EXETER</speaker>
            <line>He'll make your Paris Louvre shake for it,</line>
            <line>Were it the mistress-court of mighty Europe:</line>
            <line>And, be assured, you'll find a difference,</line>
            <line>As we his subjects have in wonder found,</line>
            <line>Between the promise of his greener days</line>
            <line>And these he masters now: now he weighs time</line>
            <line>Even to the utmost grain: that you shall read</line>
            <line>In your own losses, if he stay in France.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING OF FRANCE</speaker>
            <line>To-morrow shall you know our mind at full.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EXETER</speaker>
            <line>Dispatch us with all speed, lest that our king</line>
            <line>Come here himself to question our delay;</line>
            <line>For he is footed in this land already.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING OF FRANCE</speaker>
            <line>You shall be soon dispatch's with fair conditions:</line>
            <line>A night is but small breath and little pause</line>
            <line>To answer matters of this consequence.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Flourish. Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>