<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:shakespear:dtd:act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-4">
   <title>ACT IV</title>
   <prologue id="act-4-prologue">
      <title>PROLOGUE.</title>
      <prologue-body>
         <stagedir>Enter Chorus</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
            <line>Now entertain conjecture of a time</line>
            <line>When creeping murmur and the poring dark</line>
            <line>Fills the wide vessel of the universe.</line>
            <line>From camp to camp through the foul womb of night</line>
            <line>The hum of either army stilly sounds,</line>
            <line>That the fixed sentinels almost receive</line>
            <line>The secret whispers of each other's watch:</line>
            <line>Fire answers fire, and through their paly flames</line>
            <line>Each battle sees the other's umber'd face;</line>
            <line>Steed threatens steed, in high and boastful neighs</line>
            <line>Piercing the night's dull ear, and from the tents</line>
            <line>The armourers, accomplishing the knights,</line>
            <line>With busy hammers closing rivets up,</line>
            <line>Give dreadful note of preparation:</line>
            <line>The country cocks do crow, the clocks do toll,</line>
            <line>And the third hour of drowsy morning name.</line>
            <line>Proud of their numbers and secure in soul,</line>
            <line>The confident and over-lusty French</line>
            <line>Do the low-rated English play at dice;</line>
            <line>And chide the cripple tardy-gaited night</line>
            <line>Who, like a foul and ugly witch, doth limp</line>
            <line>So tediously away. The poor condemned English,</line>
            <line>Like sacrifices, by their watchful fires</line>
            <line>Sit patiently and inly ruminate</line>
            <line>The morning's danger, and their gesture sad</line>
            <line>Investing lank-lean; cheeks and war-worn coats</line>
            <line>Presenteth them unto the gazing moon</line>
            <line>So many horrid ghosts. O now, who will behold</line>
            <line>The royal captain of this ruin'd band</line>
            <line>Walking from watch to watch, from tent to tent,</line>
            <line>Let him cry 'Praise and glory on his head!'</line>
            <line>For forth he goes and visits all his host.</line>
            <line>Bids them good morrow with a modest smile</line>
            <line>And calls them brothers, friends and countrymen.</line>
            <line>Upon his royal face there is no note</line>
            <line>How dread an army hath enrounded him;</line>
            <line>Nor doth he dedicate one jot of colour</line>
            <line>Unto the weary and all-watched night,</line>
            <line>But freshly looks and over-bears attaint</line>
            <line>With cheerful semblance and sweet majesty;</line>
            <line>That every wretch, pining and pale before,</line>
            <line>Beholding him, plucks comfort from his looks:</line>
            <line>A largess universal like the sun</line>
            <line>His liberal eye doth give to every one,</line>
            <line>Thawing cold fear, that mean and gentle all,</line>
            <line>Behold, as may unworthiness define,</line>
            <line>A little touch of Harry in the night.</line>
            <line>And so our scene must to the battle fly;</line>
            <line>Where--O for pity!--we shall much disgrace</line>
            <line>With four or five most vile and ragged foils,</line>
            <line>Right ill-disposed in brawl ridiculous,</line>
            <line>The name of Agincourt. Yet sit and see,</line>
            <line>Minding true things by what their mockeries be.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </prologue-body>
   </prologue>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  The English camp at Agincourt.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter KING HENRY, BEDFORD, and GLOUCESTER</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>Gloucester, 'tis true that we are in great danger;</line>
            <line>The greater therefore should our courage be.</line>
            <line>Good morrow, brother Bedford. God Almighty!</line>
            <line>There is some soul of goodness in things evil,</line>
            <line>Would men observingly distil it out.</line>
            <line>For our bad neighbour makes us early stirrers,</line>
            <line>Which is both healthful and good husbandry:</line>
            <line>Besides, they are our outward consciences,</line>
            <line>And preachers to us all, admonishing</line>
            <line>That we should dress us fairly for our end.</line>
            <line>Thus may we gather honey from the weed,</line>
            <line>And make a moral of the devil himself.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter ERPINGHAM</stagedir>
            <line>Good morrow, old Sir Thomas Erpingham:</line>
            <line>A good soft pillow for that good white head</line>
            <line>Were better than a churlish turf of France.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ERPINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Not so, my liege: this lodging likes me better,</line>
            <line>Since I may say 'Now lie I like a king.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>'Tis good for men to love their present pains</line>
            <line>Upon example; so the spirit is eased:</line>
            <line>And when the mind is quicken'd, out of doubt,</line>
            <line>The organs, though defunct and dead before,</line>
            <line>Break up their drowsy grave and newly move,</line>
            <line>With casted slough and fresh legerity.</line>
            <line>Lend me thy cloak, Sir Thomas. Brothers both,</line>
            <line>Commend me to the princes in our camp;</line>
            <line>Do my good morrow to them, and anon</line>
            <line>Desire them an to my pavilion.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>We shall, my liege.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ERPINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Shall I attend your grace?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>No, my good knight;</line>
            <line>Go with my brothers to my lords of England:</line>
            <line>I and my bosom must debate awhile,</line>
            <line>And then I would no other company.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ERPINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>The Lord in heaven bless thee, noble Harry!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt all but KING HENRY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>God-a-mercy, old heart! thou speak'st cheerfully.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter PISTOL</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>Qui va la?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>A friend.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>Discuss unto me; art thou officer?</line>
            <line>Or art thou base, common and popular?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>I am a gentleman of a company.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>Trail'st thou the puissant pike?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>Even so. What are you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>As good a gentleman as the emperor.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>Then you are a better than the king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>The king's a bawcock, and a heart of gold,</line>
            <line>A lad of life, an imp of fame;</line>
            <line>Of parents good, of fist most valiant.</line>
            <line>I kiss his dirty shoe, and from heart-string</line>
            <line>I love the lovely bully. What is thy name?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>Harry le Roy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>Le Roy! a Cornish name: art thou of Cornish crew?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>No, I am a Welshman.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>Know'st thou Fluellen?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>Yes.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>Tell him, I'll knock his leek about his pate</line>
            <line>Upon Saint Davy's day.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>Do not you wear your dagger in your cap that day,</line>
            <line>lest he knock that about yours.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>Art thou his friend?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>And his kinsman too.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>The figo for thee, then!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>I thank you: God be with you!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>My name is Pistol call'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>It sorts well with your fierceness.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter FLUELLEN and GOWER</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GOWER</speaker>
            <line>Captain Fluellen!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLUELLEN</speaker>
            <line>So! in the name of Jesu Christ, speak lower. It is</line>
            <line>the greatest admiration of the universal world, when</line>
            <line>the true and aunchient prerogatifes and laws of the</line>
            <line>wars is not kept: if you would take the pains but to</line>
            <line>examine the wars of Pompey the Great, you shall</line>
            <line>find, I warrant you, that there is no tiddle toddle</line>
            <line>nor pibble pabble in Pompey's camp; I warrant you,</line>
            <line>you shall find the ceremonies of the wars, and the</line>
            <line>cares of it, and the forms of it, and the sobriety</line>
            <line>of it, and the modesty of it, to be otherwise.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GOWER</speaker>
            <line>Why, the enemy is loud; you hear him all night.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLUELLEN</speaker>
            <line>If the enemy is an ass and a fool and a prating</line>
            <line>coxcomb, is it meet, think you, that we should also,</line>
            <line>look you, be an ass and a fool and a prating</line>
            <line>coxcomb? in your own conscience, now?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GOWER</speaker>
            <line>I will speak lower.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLUELLEN</speaker>
            <line>I pray you and beseech you that you will.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt GOWER and FLUELLEN</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>Though it appear a little out of fashion,</line>
            <line>There is much care and valour in this Welshman.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter three soldiers, JOHN BATES, ALEXANDER COURT,
and MICHAEL WILLIAMS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COURT</speaker>
            <line>Brother John Bates, is not that the morning which</line>
            <line>breaks yonder?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BATES</speaker>
            <line>I think it be: but we have no great cause to desire</line>
            <line>the approach of day.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WILLIAMS</speaker>
            <line>We see yonder the beginning of the day, but I think</line>
            <line>we shall never see the end of it. Who goes there?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>A friend.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WILLIAMS</speaker>
            <line>Under what captain serve you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>Under Sir Thomas Erpingham.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WILLIAMS</speaker>
            <line>A good old commander and a most kind gentleman: I</line>
            <line>pray you, what thinks he of our estate?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>Even as men wrecked upon a sand, that look to be</line>
            <line>washed off the next tide.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BATES</speaker>
            <line>He hath not told his thought to the king?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>No; nor it is not meet he should. For, though I</line>
            <line>speak it to you, I think the king is but a man, as I</line>
            <line>am: the violet smells to him as it doth to me: the</line>
            <line>element shows to him as it doth to me; all his</line>
            <line>senses have but human conditions: his ceremonies</line>
            <line>laid by, in his nakedness he appears but a man; and</line>
            <line>though his affections are higher mounted than ours,</line>
            <line>yet, when they stoop, they stoop with the like</line>
            <line>wing. Therefore when he sees reason of fears, as we</line>
            <line>do, his fears, out of doubt, be of the same relish</line>
            <line>as ours are: yet, in reason, no man should possess</line>
            <line>him with any appearance of fear, lest he, by showing</line>
            <line>it, should dishearten his army.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BATES</speaker>
            <line>He may show what outward courage he will; but I</line>
            <line>believe, as cold a night as 'tis, he could wish</line>
            <line>himself in Thames up to the neck; and so I would he</line>
            <line>were, and I by him, at all adventures, so we were quit here.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>By my troth, I will speak my conscience of the king:</line>
            <line>I think he would not wish himself any where but</line>
            <line>where he is.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BATES</speaker>
            <line>Then I would he were here alone; so should he be</line>
            <line>sure to be ransomed, and a many poor men's lives saved.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>I dare say you love him not so ill, to wish him here</line>
            <line>alone, howsoever you speak this to feel other men's</line>
            <line>minds: methinks I could not die any where so</line>
            <line>contented as in the king's company; his cause being</line>
            <line>just and his quarrel honourable.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WILLIAMS</speaker>
            <line>That's more than we know.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BATES</speaker>
            <line>Ay, or more than we should seek after; for we know</line>
            <line>enough, if we know we are the kings subjects: if</line>
            <line>his cause be wrong, our obedience to the king wipes</line>
            <line>the crime of it out of us.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WILLIAMS</speaker>
            <line>But if the cause be not good, the king himself hath</line>
            <line>a heavy reckoning to make, when all those legs and</line>
            <line>arms and heads, chopped off in battle, shall join</line>
            <line>together at the latter day and cry all 'We died at</line>
            <line>such a place;' some swearing, some crying for a</line>
            <line>surgeon, some upon their wives left poor behind</line>
            <line>them, some upon the debts they owe, some upon their</line>
            <line>children rawly left. I am afeard there are few die</line>
            <line>well that die in a battle; for how can they</line>
            <line>charitably dispose of any thing, when blood is their</line>
            <line>argument? Now, if these men do not die well, it</line>
            <line>will be a black matter for the king that led them to</line>
            <line>it; whom to disobey were against all proportion of</line>
            <line>subjection.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>So, if a son that is by his father sent about</line>
            <line>merchandise do sinfully miscarry upon the sea, the</line>
            <line>imputation of his wickedness by your rule, should be</line>
            <line>imposed upon his father that sent him: or if a</line>
            <line>servant, under his master's command transporting a</line>
            <line>sum of money, be assailed by robbers and die in</line>
            <line>many irreconciled iniquities, you may call the</line>
            <line>business of the master the author of the servant's</line>
            <line>damnation: but this is not so: the king is not</line>
            <line>bound to answer the particular endings of his</line>
            <line>soldiers, the father of his son, nor the master of</line>
            <line>his servant; for they purpose not their death, when</line>
            <line>they purpose their services. Besides, there is no</line>
            <line>king, be his cause never so spotless, if it come to</line>
            <line>the arbitrement of swords, can try it out with all</line>
            <line>unspotted soldiers: some peradventure have on them</line>
            <line>the guilt of premeditated and contrived murder;</line>
            <line>some, of beguiling virgins with the broken seals of</line>
            <line>perjury; some, making the wars their bulwark, that</line>
            <line>have before gored the gentle bosom of peace with</line>
            <line>pillage and robbery. Now, if these men have</line>
            <line>defeated the law and outrun native punishment,</line>
            <line>though they can outstrip men, they have no wings to</line>
            <line>fly from God: war is his beadle, war is vengeance;</line>
            <line>so that here men are punished for before-breach of</line>
            <line>the king's laws in now the king's quarrel: where</line>
            <line>they feared the death, they have borne life away;</line>
            <line>and where they would be safe, they perish: then if</line>
            <line>they die unprovided, no more is the king guilty of</line>
            <line>their damnation than he was before guilty of those</line>
            <line>impieties for the which they are now visited. Every</line>
            <line>subject's duty is the king's; but every subject's</line>
            <line>soul is his own. Therefore should every soldier in</line>
            <line>the wars do as every sick man in his bed, wash every</line>
            <line>mote out of his conscience: and dying so, death</line>
            <line>is to him advantage; or not dying, the time was</line>
            <line>blessedly lost wherein such preparation was gained:</line>
            <line>and in him that escapes, it were not sin to think</line>
            <line>that, making God so free an offer, He let him</line>
            <line>outlive that day to see His greatness and to teach</line>
            <line>others how they should prepare.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WILLIAMS</speaker>
            <line>'Tis certain, every man that dies ill, the ill upon</line>
            <line>his own head, the king is not to answer it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BATES</speaker>
            <line>But I do not desire he should answer for me; and</line>
            <line>yet I determine to fight lustily for him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>I myself heard the king say he would not be ransomed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WILLIAMS</speaker>
            <line>Ay, he said so, to make us fight cheerfully: but</line>
            <line>when our throats are cut, he may be ransomed, and we</line>
            <line>ne'er the wiser.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>If I live to see it, I will never trust his word after.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WILLIAMS</speaker>
            <line>You pay him then. That's a perilous shot out of an</line>
            <line>elder-gun, that a poor and private displeasure can</line>
            <line>do against a monarch! you may as well go about to</line>
            <line>turn the sun to ice with fanning in his face with a</line>
            <line>peacock's feather. You'll never trust his word</line>
            <line>after! come, 'tis a foolish saying.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>Your reproof is something too round: I should be</line>
            <line>angry with you, if the time were convenient.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WILLIAMS</speaker>
            <line>Let it be a quarrel between us, if you live.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>I embrace it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WILLIAMS</speaker>
            <line>How shall I know thee again?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>Give me any gage of thine, and I will wear it in my</line>
            <line>bonnet: then, if ever thou darest acknowledge it, I</line>
            <line>will make it my quarrel.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WILLIAMS</speaker>
            <line>Here's my glove: give me another of thine.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>There.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WILLIAMS</speaker>
            <line>This will I also wear in my cap: if ever thou come</line>
            <line>to me and say, after to-morrow, 'This is my glove,'</line>
            <line>by this hand, I will take thee a box on the ear.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>If ever I live to see it, I will challenge it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WILLIAMS</speaker>
            <line>Thou darest as well be hanged.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>Well. I will do it, though I take thee in the</line>
            <line>king's company.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WILLIAMS</speaker>
            <line>Keep thy word: fare thee well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BATES</speaker>
            <line>Be friends, you English fools, be friends: we have</line>
            <line>French quarrels enow, if you could tell how to reckon.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>Indeed, the French may lay twenty French crowns to</line>
            <line>one, they will beat us; for they bear them on their</line>
            <line>shoulders: but it is no English treason to cut</line>
            <line>French crowns, and to-morrow the king himself will</line>
            <line>be a clipper.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt soldiers</stagedir>
            <line>Upon the king! let us our lives, our souls,</line>
            <line>Our debts, our careful wives,</line>
            <line>Our children and our sins lay on the king!</line>
            <line>We must bear all. O hard condition,</line>
            <line>Twin-born with greatness, subject to the breath</line>
            <line>Of every fool, whose sense no more can feel</line>
            <line>But his own wringing! What infinite heart's-ease</line>
            <line>Must kings neglect, that private men enjoy!</line>
            <line>And what have kings, that privates have not too,</line>
            <line>Save ceremony, save general ceremony?</line>
            <line>And what art thou, thou idle ceremony?</line>
            <line>What kind of god art thou, that suffer'st more</line>
            <line>Of mortal griefs than do thy worshippers?</line>
            <line>What are thy rents? what are thy comings in?</line>
            <line>O ceremony, show me but thy worth!</line>
            <line>What is thy soul of adoration?</line>
            <line>Art thou aught else but place, degree and form,</line>
            <line>Creating awe and fear in other men?</line>
            <line>Wherein thou art less happy being fear'd</line>
            <line>Than they in fearing.</line>
            <line>What drink'st thou oft, instead of homage sweet,</line>
            <line>But poison'd flattery? O, be sick, great greatness,</line>
            <line>And bid thy ceremony give thee cure!</line>
            <line>Think'st thou the fiery fever will go out</line>
            <line>With titles blown from adulation?</line>
            <line>Will it give place to flexure and low bending?</line>
            <line>Canst thou, when thou command'st the beggar's knee,</line>
            <line>Command the health of it? No, thou proud dream,</line>
            <line>That play'st so subtly with a king's repose;</line>
            <line>I am a king that find thee, and I know</line>
            <line>'Tis not the balm, the sceptre and the ball,</line>
            <line>The sword, the mace, the crown imperial,</line>
            <line>The intertissued robe of gold and pearl,</line>
            <line>The farced title running 'fore the king,</line>
            <line>The throne he sits on, nor the tide of pomp</line>
            <line>That beats upon the high shore of this world,</line>
            <line>No, not all these, thrice-gorgeous ceremony,</line>
            <line>Not all these, laid in bed majestical,</line>
            <line>Can sleep so soundly as the wretched slave,</line>
            <line>Who with a body fill'd and vacant mind</line>
            <line>Gets him to rest, cramm'd with distressful bread;</line>
            <line>Never sees horrid night, the child of hell,</line>
            <line>But, like a lackey, from the rise to set</line>
            <line>Sweats in the eye of Phoebus and all night</line>
            <line>Sleeps in Elysium; next day after dawn,</line>
            <line>Doth rise and help Hyperion to his horse,</line>
            <line>And follows so the ever-running year,</line>
            <line>With profitable labour, to his grave:</line>
            <line>And, but for ceremony, such a wretch,</line>
            <line>Winding up days with toil and nights with sleep,</line>
            <line>Had the fore-hand and vantage of a king.</line>
            <line>The slave, a member of the country's peace,</line>
            <line>Enjoys it; but in gross brain little wots</line>
            <line>What watch the king keeps to maintain the peace,</line>
            <line>Whose hours the peasant best advantages.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter ERPINGHAM</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ERPINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>My lord, your nobles, jealous of your absence,</line>
            <line>Seek through your camp to find you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>Good old knight,</line>
            <line>Collect them all together at my tent:</line>
            <line>I'll be before thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ERPINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>I shall do't, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>O God of battles! steel my soldiers' hearts;</line>
            <line>Possess them not with fear; take from them now</line>
            <line>The sense of reckoning, if the opposed numbers</line>
            <line>Pluck their hearts from them. Not to-day, O Lord,</line>
            <line>O, not to-day, think not upon the fault</line>
            <line>My father made in compassing the crown!</line>
            <line>I Richard's body have interred anew;</line>
            <line>And on it have bestow'd more contrite tears</line>
            <line>Than from it issued forced drops of blood:</line>
            <line>Five hundred poor I have in yearly pay,</line>
            <line>Who twice a-day their wither'd hands hold up</line>
            <line>Toward heaven, to pardon blood; and I have built</line>
            <line>Two chantries, where the sad and solemn priests</line>
            <line>Sing still for Richard's soul. More will I do;</line>
            <line>Though all that I can do is nothing worth,</line>
            <line>Since that my penitence comes after all,</line>
            <line>Imploring pardon.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter GLOUCESTER</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>My liege!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>My brother Gloucester's voice? Ay;</line>
            <line>I know thy errand, I will go with thee:</line>
            <line>The day, my friends and all things stay for me.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  The French camp.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter the DAUPHIN, ORLEANS, RAMBURES, and others</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLEANS</speaker>
            <line>The sun doth gild our armour; up, my lords!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DAUPHIN</speaker>
            <line>Montez A cheval! My horse! varlet! laquais! ha!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLEANS</speaker>
            <line>O brave spirit!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DAUPHIN</speaker>
            <line>Via! les eaux et la terre.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLEANS</speaker>
            <line>Rien puis? L'air et la feu.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DAUPHIN</speaker>
            <line>Ciel, cousin Orleans.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter Constable</stagedir>
            <line>Now, my lord constable!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Constable</speaker>
            <line>Hark, how our steeds for present service neigh!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DAUPHIN</speaker>
            <line>Mount them, and make incision in their hides,</line>
            <line>That their hot blood may spin in English eyes,</line>
            <line>And dout them with superfluous courage, ha!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RAMBURES</speaker>
            <line>What, will you have them weep our horses' blood?</line>
            <line>How shall we, then, behold their natural tears?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter Messenger</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>The English are embattled, you French peers.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Constable</speaker>
            <line>To horse, you gallant princes! straight to horse!</line>
            <line>Do but behold yon poor and starved band,</line>
            <line>And your fair show shall suck away their souls,</line>
            <line>Leaving them but the shales and husks of men.</line>
            <line>There is not work enough for all our hands;</line>
            <line>Scarce blood enough in all their sickly veins</line>
            <line>To give each naked curtle-axe a stain,</line>
            <line>That our French gallants shall to-day draw out,</line>
            <line>And sheathe for lack of sport: let us but blow on them,</line>
            <line>The vapour of our valour will o'erturn them.</line>
            <line>'Tis positive 'gainst all exceptions, lords,</line>
            <line>That our superfluous lackeys and our peasants,</line>
            <line>Who in unnecessary action swarm</line>
            <line>About our squares of battle, were enow</line>
            <line>To purge this field of such a hilding foe,</line>
            <line>Though we upon this mountain's basis by</line>
            <line>Took stand for idle speculation:</line>
            <line>But that our honours must not. What's to say?</line>
            <line>A very little little let us do.</line>
            <line>And all is done. Then let the trumpets sound</line>
            <line>The tucket sonance and the note to mount;</line>
            <line>For our approach shall so much dare the field</line>
            <line>That England shall couch down in fear and yield.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter GRANDPRE</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRANDPRE</speaker>
            <line>Why do you stay so long, my lords of France?</line>
            <line>Yon island carrions, desperate of their bones,</line>
            <line>Ill-favouredly become the morning field:</line>
            <line>Their ragged curtains poorly are let loose,</line>
            <line>And our air shakes them passing scornfully:</line>
            <line>Big Mars seems bankrupt in their beggar'd host</line>
            <line>And faintly through a rusty beaver peeps:</line>
            <line>The horsemen sit like fixed candlesticks,</line>
            <line>With torch-staves in their hand; and their poor jades</line>
            <line>Lob down their heads, dropping the hides and hips,</line>
            <line>The gum down-roping from their pale-dead eyes</line>
            <line>And in their pale dull mouths the gimmal bit</line>
            <line>Lies foul with chew'd grass, still and motionless;</line>
            <line>And their executors, the knavish crows,</line>
            <line>Fly o'er them, all impatient for their hour.</line>
            <line>Description cannot suit itself in words</line>
            <line>To demonstrate the life of such a battle</line>
            <line>In life so lifeless as it shows itself.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Constable</speaker>
            <line>They have said their prayers, and they stay for death.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DAUPHIN</speaker>
            <line>Shall we go send them dinners and fresh suits</line>
            <line>And give their fasting horses provender,</line>
            <line>And after fight with them?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Constable</speaker>
            <line>I stay but for my guidon: to the field!</line>
            <line>I will the banner from a trumpet take,</line>
            <line>And use it for my haste. Come, come, away!</line>
            <line>The sun is high, and we outwear the day.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  The English camp.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter GLOUCESTER, BEDFORD, EXETER, ERPINGHAM, with
all his host: SALISBURY and WESTMORELAND</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Where is the king?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEDFORD</speaker>
            <line>The king himself is rode to view their battle.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WESTMORELAND</speaker>
            <line>Of fighting men they have full three score thousand.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EXETER</speaker>
            <line>There's five to one; besides, they all are fresh.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALISBURY</speaker>
            <line>God's arm strike with us! 'tis a fearful odds.</line>
            <line>God be wi' you, princes all; I'll to my charge:</line>
            <line>If we no more meet till we meet in heaven,</line>
            <line>Then, joyfully, my noble Lord of Bedford,</line>
            <line>My dear Lord Gloucester, and my good Lord Exeter,</line>
            <line>And my kind kinsman, warriors all, adieu!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEDFORD</speaker>
            <line>Farewell, good Salisbury; and good luck go with thee!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EXETER</speaker>
            <line>Farewell, kind lord; fight valiantly to-day:</line>
            <line>And yet I do thee wrong to mind thee of it,</line>
            <line>For thou art framed of the firm truth of valour.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit SALISBURY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEDFORD</speaker>
            <line>He is full of valour as of kindness;</line>
            <line>Princely in both.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter the KING</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WESTMORELAND</speaker>
            <line>O that we now had here</line>
            <line>But one ten thousand of those men in England</line>
            <line>That do no work to-day!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>What's he that wishes so?</line>
            <line>My cousin Westmoreland? No, my fair cousin:</line>
            <line>If we are mark'd to die, we are enow</line>
            <line>To do our country loss; and if to live,</line>
            <line>The fewer men, the greater share of honour.</line>
            <line>God's will! I pray thee, wish not one man more.</line>
            <line>By Jove, I am not covetous for gold,</line>
            <line>Nor care I who doth feed upon my cost;</line>
            <line>It yearns me not if men my garments wear;</line>
            <line>Such outward things dwell not in my desires:</line>
            <line>But if it be a sin to covet honour,</line>
            <line>I am the most offending soul alive.</line>
            <line>No, faith, my coz, wish not a man from England:</line>
            <line>God's peace! I would not lose so great an honour</line>
            <line>As one man more, methinks, would share from me</line>
            <line>For the best hope I have. O, do not wish one more!</line>
            <line>Rather proclaim it, Westmoreland, through my host,</line>
            <line>That he which hath no stomach to this fight,</line>
            <line>Let him depart; his passport shall be made</line>
            <line>And crowns for convoy put into his purse:</line>
            <line>We would not die in that man's company</line>
            <line>That fears his fellowship to die with us.</line>
            <line>This day is called the feast of Crispian:</line>
            <line>He that outlives this day, and comes safe home,</line>
            <line>Will stand a tip-toe when the day is named,</line>
            <line>And rouse him at the name of Crispian.</line>
            <line>He that shall live this day, and see old age,</line>
            <line>Will yearly on the vigil feast his neighbours,</line>
            <line>And say 'To-morrow is Saint Crispian:'</line>
            <line>Then will he strip his sleeve and show his scars.</line>
            <line>And say 'These wounds I had on Crispin's day.'</line>
            <line>Old men forget: yet all shall be forgot,</line>
            <line>But he'll remember with advantages</line>
            <line>What feats he did that day: then shall our names.</line>
            <line>Familiar in his mouth as household words</line>
            <line>Harry the king, Bedford and Exeter,</line>
            <line>Warwick and Talbot, Salisbury and Gloucester,</line>
            <line>Be in their flowing cups freshly remember'd.</line>
            <line>This story shall the good man teach his son;</line>
            <line>And Crispin Crispian shall ne'er go by,</line>
            <line>From this day to the ending of the world,</line>
            <line>But we in it shall be remember'd;</line>
            <line>We few, we happy few, we band of brothers;</line>
            <line>For he to-day that sheds his blood with me</line>
            <line>Shall be my brother; be he ne'er so vile,</line>
            <line>This day shall gentle his condition:</line>
            <line>And gentlemen in England now a-bed</line>
            <line>Shall think themselves accursed they were not here,</line>
            <line>And hold their manhoods cheap whiles any speaks</line>
            <line>That fought with us upon Saint Crispin's day.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter SALISBURY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALISBURY</speaker>
            <line>My sovereign lord, bestow yourself with speed:</line>
            <line>The French are bravely in their battles set,</line>
            <line>And will with all expedience charge on us.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>All things are ready, if our minds be so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WESTMORELAND</speaker>
            <line>Perish the man whose mind is backward now!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>Thou dost not wish more help from England, coz?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WESTMORELAND</speaker>
            <line>God's will! my liege, would you and I alone,</line>
            <line>Without more help, could fight this royal battle!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>Why, now thou hast unwish'd five thousand men;</line>
            <line>Which likes me better than to wish us one.</line>
            <line>You know your places: God be with you all!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Tucket. Enter MONTJOY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MONTJOY</speaker>
            <line>Once more I come to know of thee, King Harry,</line>
            <line>If for thy ransom thou wilt now compound,</line>
            <line>Before thy most assured overthrow:</line>
            <line>For certainly thou art so near the gulf,</line>
            <line>Thou needs must be englutted. Besides, in mercy,</line>
            <line>The constable desires thee thou wilt mind</line>
            <line>Thy followers of repentance; that their souls</line>
            <line>May make a peaceful and a sweet retire</line>
            <line>From off these fields, where, wretches, their poor bodies</line>
            <line>Must lie and fester.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>Who hath sent thee now?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MONTJOY</speaker>
            <line>The Constable of France.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>I pray thee, bear my former answer back:</line>
            <line>Bid them achieve me and then sell my bones.</line>
            <line>Good God! why should they mock poor fellows thus?</line>
            <line>The man that once did sell the lion's skin</line>
            <line>While the beast lived, was killed with hunting him.</line>
            <line>A many of our bodies shall no doubt</line>
            <line>Find native graves; upon the which, I trust,</line>
            <line>Shall witness live in brass of this day's work:</line>
            <line>And those that leave their valiant bones in France,</line>
            <line>Dying like men, though buried in your dunghills,</line>
            <line>They shall be famed; for there the sun shall greet them,</line>
            <line>And draw their honours reeking up to heaven;</line>
            <line>Leaving their earthly parts to choke your clime,</line>
            <line>The smell whereof shall breed a plague in France.</line>
            <line>Mark then abounding valour in our English,</line>
            <line>That being dead, like to the bullet's grazing,</line>
            <line>Break out into a second course of mischief,</line>
            <line>Killing in relapse of mortality.</line>
            <line>Let me speak proudly: tell the constable</line>
            <line>We are but warriors for the working-day;</line>
            <line>Our gayness and our gilt are all besmirch'd</line>
            <line>With rainy marching in the painful field;</line>
            <line>There's not a piece of feather in our host--</line>
            <line>Good argument, I hope, we will not fly--</line>
            <line>And time hath worn us into slovenry:</line>
            <line>But, by the mass, our hearts are in the trim;</line>
            <line>And my poor soldiers tell me, yet ere night</line>
            <line>They'll be in fresher robes, or they will pluck</line>
            <line>The gay new coats o'er the French soldiers' heads</line>
            <line>And turn them out of service. If they do this,--</line>
            <line>As, if God please, they shall,--my ransom then</line>
            <line>Will soon be levied. Herald, save thou thy labour;</line>
            <line>Come thou no more for ransom, gentle herald:</line>
            <line>They shall have none, I swear, but these my joints;</line>
            <line>Which if they have as I will leave 'em them,</line>
            <line>Shall yield them little, tell the constable.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MONTJOY</speaker>
            <line>I shall, King Harry. And so fare thee well:</line>
            <line>Thou never shalt hear herald any more.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>I fear thou'lt once more come again for ransom.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter YORK</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>My lord, most humbly on my knee I beg</line>
            <line>The leading of the vaward.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>Take it, brave York. Now, soldiers, march away:</line>
            <line>And how thou pleasest, God, dispose the day!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-4">
      <title>SCENE IV.  The field of battle.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Alarum. Excursions. Enter PISTOL, French Soldier, and Boy</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>Yield, cur!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>French Soldier</speaker>
            <line>Je pense que vous etes gentilhomme de bonne qualite.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>Qualtitie calmie custure me! Art thou a gentleman?</line>
            <line>what is thy name? discuss.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>French Soldier</speaker>
            <line>O Seigneur Dieu!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>O, Signieur Dew should be a gentleman:</line>
            <line>Perpend my words, O Signieur Dew, and mark;</line>
            <line>O Signieur Dew, thou diest on point of fox,</line>
            <line>Except, O signieur, thou do give to me</line>
            <line>Egregious ransom.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>French Soldier</speaker>
            <line>O, prenez misericorde! ayez pitie de moi!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>Moy shall not serve; I will have forty moys;</line>
            <line>Or I will fetch thy rim out at thy throat</line>
            <line>In drops of crimson blood.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>French Soldier</speaker>
            <line>Est-il impossible d'echapper la force de ton bras?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>Brass, cur!</line>
            <line>Thou damned and luxurious mountain goat,</line>
            <line>Offer'st me brass?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>French Soldier</speaker>
            <line>O pardonnez moi!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>Say'st thou me so? is that a ton of moys?</line>
            <line>Come hither, boy: ask me this slave in French</line>
            <line>What is his name.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Boy</speaker>
            <line>Ecoutez: comment etes-vous appele?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>French Soldier</speaker>
            <line>Monsieur le Fer.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Boy</speaker>
            <line>He says his name is Master Fer.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>Master Fer! I'll fer him, and firk him, and ferret</line>
            <line>him: discuss the same in French unto him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Boy</speaker>
            <line>I do not know the French for fer, and ferret, and firk.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>Bid him prepare; for I will cut his throat.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>French Soldier</speaker>
            <line>Que dit-il, monsieur?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Boy</speaker>
            <line>Il me commande de vous dire que vous faites vous</line>
            <line>pret; car ce soldat ici est dispose tout a cette</line>
            <line>heure de couper votre gorge.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>Owy, cuppele gorge, permafoy,</line>
            <line>Peasant, unless thou give me crowns, brave crowns;</line>
            <line>Or mangled shalt thou be by this my sword.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>French Soldier</speaker>
            <line>O, je vous supplie, pour l'amour de Dieu, me</line>
            <line>pardonner! Je suis gentilhomme de bonne maison:</line>
            <line>gardez ma vie, et je vous donnerai deux cents ecus.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>What are his words?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Boy</speaker>
            <line>He prays you to save his life: he is a gentleman of</line>
            <line>a good house; and for his ransom he will give you</line>
            <line>two hundred crowns.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>Tell him my fury shall abate, and I the crowns will take.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>French Soldier</speaker>
            <line>Petit monsieur, que dit-il?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Boy</speaker>
            <line>Encore qu'il est contre son jurement de pardonner</line>
            <line>aucun prisonnier, neanmoins, pour les ecus que vous</line>
            <line>l'avez promis, il est content de vous donner la</line>
            <line>liberte, le franchisement.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>French Soldier</speaker>
            <line>Sur mes genoux je vous donne mille remercimens; et</line>
            <line>je m'estime heureux que je suis tombe entre les</line>
            <line>mains d'un chevalier, je pense, le plus brave,</line>
            <line>vaillant, et tres distingue seigneur d'Angleterre.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>Expound unto me, boy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Boy</speaker>
            <line>He gives you, upon his knees, a thousand thanks; and</line>
            <line>he esteems himself happy that he hath fallen into</line>
            <line>the hands of one, as he thinks, the most brave,</line>
            <line>valorous, and thrice-worthy signieur of England.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>As I suck blood, I will some mercy show.</line>
            <line>Follow me!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Boy</speaker>
            <line>Suivez-vous le grand capitaine.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt PISTOL, and French Soldier</stagedir>
            <line>I did never know so full a voice issue from so</line>
            <line>empty a heart: but the saying is true 'The empty</line>
            <line>vessel makes the greatest sound.' Bardolph and Nym</line>
            <line>had ten times more valour than this roaring devil i'</line>
            <line>the old play, that every one may pare his nails with</line>
            <line>a wooden dagger; and they are both hanged; and so</line>
            <line>would this be, if he durst steal any thing</line>
            <line>adventurously. I must stay with the lackeys, with</line>
            <line>the luggage of our camp: the French might have a</line>
            <line>good prey of us, if he knew of it; for there is</line>
            <line>none to guard it but boys.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-5">
      <title>SCENE V.  Another part of the field.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter Constable, ORLEANS, BOURBON, DAUPHIN, and RAMBURES</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Constable</speaker>
            <line>O diable!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLEANS</speaker>
            <line>O seigneur! le jour est perdu, tout est perdu!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DAUPHIN</speaker>
            <line>Mort de ma vie! all is confounded, all!</line>
            <line>Reproach and everlasting shame</line>
            <line>Sits mocking in our plumes. O merchante fortune!</line>
            <line>Do not run away.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>A short alarum</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Constable</speaker>
            <line>Why, all our ranks are broke.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DAUPHIN</speaker>
            <line>O perdurable shame! let's stab ourselves.</line>
            <line>Be these the wretches that we play'd at dice for?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLEANS</speaker>
            <line>Is this the king we sent to for his ransom?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOURBON</speaker>
            <line>Shame and eternal shame, nothing but shame!</line>
            <line>Let us die in honour: once more back again;</line>
            <line>And he that will not follow Bourbon now,</line>
            <line>Let him go hence, and with his cap in hand,</line>
            <line>Like a base pander, hold the chamber-door</line>
            <line>Whilst by a slave, no gentler than my dog,</line>
            <line>His fairest daughter is contaminated.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Constable</speaker>
            <line>Disorder, that hath spoil'd us, friend us now!</line>
            <line>Let us on heaps go offer up our lives.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ORLEANS</speaker>
            <line>We are enow yet living in the field</line>
            <line>To smother up the English in our throngs,</line>
            <line>If any order might be thought upon.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOURBON</speaker>
            <line>The devil take order now! I'll to the throng:</line>
            <line>Let life be short; else shame will be too long.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-6">
      <title>SCENE VI.  Another part of the field.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Alarums. Enter KING HENRY and forces, EXETER, and others</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>Well have we done, thrice valiant countrymen:</line>
            <line>But all's not done; yet keep the French the field.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EXETER</speaker>
            <line>The Duke of York commends him to your majesty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>Lives he, good uncle? thrice within this hour</line>
            <line>I saw him down; thrice up again and fighting;</line>
            <line>From helmet to the spur all blood he was.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EXETER</speaker>
            <line>In which array, brave soldier, doth he lie,</line>
            <line>Larding the plain; and by his bloody side,</line>
            <line>Yoke-fellow to his honour-owing wounds,</line>
            <line>The noble Earl of Suffolk also lies.</line>
            <line>Suffolk first died: and York, all haggled over,</line>
            <line>Comes to him, where in gore he lay insteep'd,</line>
            <line>And takes him by the beard; kisses the gashes</line>
            <line>That bloodily did spawn upon his face;</line>
            <line>And cries aloud 'Tarry, dear cousin Suffolk!</line>
            <line>My soul shall thine keep company to heaven;</line>
            <line>Tarry, sweet soul, for mine, then fly abreast,</line>
            <line>As in this glorious and well-foughten field</line>
            <line>We kept together in our chivalry!'</line>
            <line>Upon these words I came and cheer'd him up:</line>
            <line>He smiled me in the face, raught me his hand,</line>
            <line>And, with a feeble gripe, says 'Dear my lord,</line>
            <line>Commend my service to me sovereign.'</line>
            <line>So did he turn and over Suffolk's neck</line>
            <line>He threw his wounded arm and kiss'd his lips;</line>
            <line>And so espoused to death, with blood he seal'd</line>
            <line>A testament of noble-ending love.</line>
            <line>The pretty and sweet manner of it forced</line>
            <line>Those waters from me which I would have stopp'd;</line>
            <line>But I had not so much of man in me,</line>
            <line>And all my mother came into mine eyes</line>
            <line>And gave me up to tears.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>I blame you not;</line>
            <line>For, hearing this, I must perforce compound</line>
            <line>With mistful eyes, or they will issue too.</line>
            <stagedir>Alarum</stagedir>
            <line>But, hark! what new alarum is this same?</line>
            <line>The French have reinforced their scatter'd men:</line>
            <line>Then every soldier kill his prisoners:</line>
            <line>Give the word through.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-7">
      <title>SCENE VII.  Another part of the field.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter FLUELLEN and GOWER</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLUELLEN</speaker>
            <line>Kill the poys and the luggage! 'tis expressly</line>
            <line>against the law of arms: 'tis as arrant a piece of</line>
            <line>knavery, mark you now, as can be offer't; in your</line>
            <line>conscience, now, is it not?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GOWER</speaker>
            <line>'Tis certain there's not a boy left alive; and the</line>
            <line>cowardly rascals that ran from the battle ha' done</line>
            <line>this slaughter: besides, they have burned and</line>
            <line>carried away all that was in the king's tent;</line>
            <line>wherefore the king, most worthily, hath caused every</line>
            <line>soldier to cut his prisoner's throat. O, 'tis a</line>
            <line>gallant king!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLUELLEN</speaker>
            <line>Ay, he was porn at Monmouth, Captain Gower. What</line>
            <line>call you the town's name where Alexander the Pig was born!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GOWER</speaker>
            <line>Alexander the Great.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLUELLEN</speaker>
            <line>Why, I pray you, is not pig great? the pig, or the</line>
            <line>great, or the mighty, or the huge, or the</line>
            <line>magnanimous, are all one reckonings, save the phrase</line>
            <line>is a little variations.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GOWER</speaker>
            <line>I think Alexander the Great was born in Macedon; his</line>
            <line>father was called Philip of Macedon, as I take it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLUELLEN</speaker>
            <line>I think it is in Macedon where Alexander is porn. I</line>
            <line>tell you, captain, if you look in the maps of the</line>
            <line>'orld, I warrant you sall find, in the comparisons</line>
            <line>between Macedon and Monmouth, that the situations,</line>
            <line>look you, is both alike. There is a river in</line>
            <line>Macedon; and there is also moreover a river at</line>
            <line>Monmouth: it is called Wye at Monmouth; but it is</line>
            <line>out of my prains what is the name of the other</line>
            <line>river; but 'tis all one, 'tis alike as my fingers is</line>
            <line>to my fingers, and there is salmons in both. If you</line>
            <line>mark Alexander's life well, Harry of Monmouth's life</line>
            <line>is come after it indifferent well; for there is</line>
            <line>figures in all things. Alexander, God knows, and</line>
            <line>you know, in his rages, and his furies, and his</line>
            <line>wraths, and his cholers, and his moods, and his</line>
            <line>displeasures, and his indignations, and also being a</line>
            <line>little intoxicates in his prains, did, in his ales and</line>
            <line>his angers, look you, kill his best friend, Cleitus.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GOWER</speaker>
            <line>Our king is not like him in that: he never killed</line>
            <line>any of his friends.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLUELLEN</speaker>
            <line>It is not well done, mark you now take the tales out</line>
            <line>of my mouth, ere it is made and finished. I speak</line>
            <line>but in the figures and comparisons of it: as</line>
            <line>Alexander killed his friend Cleitus, being in his</line>
            <line>ales and his cups; so also Harry Monmouth, being in</line>
            <line>his right wits and his good judgments, turned away</line>
            <line>the fat knight with the great belly-doublet: he</line>
            <line>was full of jests, and gipes, and knaveries, and</line>
            <line>mocks; I have forgot his name.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GOWER</speaker>
            <line>Sir John Falstaff.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLUELLEN</speaker>
            <line>That is he: I'll tell you there is good men porn at Monmouth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GOWER</speaker>
            <line>Here comes his majesty.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Alarum. Enter KING HENRY, and forces; WARWICK,
GLOUCESTER, EXETER, and others</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>I was not angry since I came to France</line>
            <line>Until this instant. Take a trumpet, herald;</line>
            <line>Ride thou unto the horsemen on yon hill:</line>
            <line>If they will fight with us, bid them come down,</line>
            <line>Or void the field; they do offend our sight:</line>
            <line>If they'll do neither, we will come to them,</line>
            <line>And make them skirr away, as swift as stones</line>
            <line>Enforced from the old Assyrian slings:</line>
            <line>Besides, we'll cut the throats of those we have,</line>
            <line>And not a man of them that we shall take</line>
            <line>Shall taste our mercy. Go and tell them so.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter MONTJOY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EXETER</speaker>
            <line>Here comes the herald of the French, my liege.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>His eyes are humbler than they used to be.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>How now! what means this, herald? know'st thou not</line>
            <line>That I have fined these bones of mine for ransom?</line>
            <line>Comest thou again for ransom?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MONTJOY</speaker>
            <line>No, great king:</line>
            <line>I come to thee for charitable licence,</line>
            <line>That we may wander o'er this bloody field</line>
            <line>To look our dead, and then to bury them;</line>
            <line>To sort our nobles from our common men.</line>
            <line>For many of our princes--woe the while!--</line>
            <line>Lie drown'd and soak'd in mercenary blood;</line>
            <line>So do our vulgar drench their peasant limbs</line>
            <line>In blood of princes; and their wounded steeds</line>
            <line>Fret fetlock deep in gore and with wild rage</line>
            <line>Yerk out their armed heels at their dead masters,</line>
            <line>Killing them twice. O, give us leave, great king,</line>
            <line>To view the field in safety and dispose</line>
            <line>Of their dead bodies!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>I tell thee truly, herald,</line>
            <line>I know not if the day be ours or no;</line>
            <line>For yet a many of your horsemen peer</line>
            <line>And gallop o'er the field.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MONTJOY</speaker>
            <line>The day is yours.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>Praised be God, and not our strength, for it!</line>
            <line>What is this castle call'd that stands hard by?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MONTJOY</speaker>
            <line>They call it Agincourt.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>Then call we this the field of Agincourt,</line>
            <line>Fought on the day of Crispin Crispianus.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLUELLEN</speaker>
            <line>Your grandfather of famous memory, an't please your</line>
            <line>majesty, and your great-uncle Edward the Plack</line>
            <line>Prince of Wales, as I have read in the chronicles,</line>
            <line>fought a most prave pattle here in France.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>They did, Fluellen.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLUELLEN</speaker>
            <line>Your majesty says very true: if your majesties is</line>
            <line>remembered of it, the Welshmen did good service in a</line>
            <line>garden where leeks did grow, wearing leeks in their</line>
            <line>Monmouth caps; which, your majesty know, to this</line>
            <line>hour is an honourable badge of the service; and I do</line>
            <line>believe your majesty takes no scorn to wear the leek</line>
            <line>upon Saint Tavy's day.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>I wear it for a memorable honour;</line>
            <line>For I am Welsh, you know, good countryman.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLUELLEN</speaker>
            <line>All the water in Wye cannot wash your majesty's</line>
            <line>Welsh plood out of your pody, I can tell you that:</line>
            <line>God pless it and preserve it, as long as it pleases</line>
            <line>his grace, and his majesty too!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>Thanks, good my countryman.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLUELLEN</speaker>
            <line>By Jeshu, I am your majesty's countryman, I care not</line>
            <line>who know it; I will confess it to all the 'orld: I</line>
            <line>need not to be ashamed of your majesty, praised be</line>
            <line>God, so long as your majesty is an honest man.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>God keep me so! Our heralds go with him:</line>
            <line>Bring me just notice of the numbers dead</line>
            <line>On both our parts. Call yonder fellow hither.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Points to WILLIAMS. Exeunt Heralds with Montjoy</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EXETER</speaker>
            <line>Soldier, you must come to the king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>Soldier, why wearest thou that glove in thy cap?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WILLIAMS</speaker>
            <line>An't please your majesty, 'tis the gage of one that</line>
            <line>I should fight withal, if he be alive.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>An Englishman?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WILLIAMS</speaker>
            <line>An't please your majesty, a rascal that swaggered</line>
            <line>with me last night; who, if alive and ever dare to</line>
            <line>challenge this glove, I have sworn to take him a box</line>
            <line>o' th' ear: or if I can see my glove in his cap,</line>
            <line>which he swore, as he was a soldier, he would wear</line>
            <line>if alive, I will strike it out soundly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>What think you, Captain Fluellen? is it fit this</line>
            <line>soldier keep his oath?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLUELLEN</speaker>
            <line>He is a craven and a villain else, an't please your</line>
            <line>majesty, in my conscience.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>It may be his enemy is a gentleman of great sort,</line>
            <line>quite from the answer of his degree.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLUELLEN</speaker>
            <line>Though he be as good a gentleman as the devil is, as</line>
            <line>Lucifer and Belzebub himself, it is necessary, look</line>
            <line>your grace, that he keep his vow and his oath: if</line>
            <line>he be perjured, see you now, his reputation is as</line>
            <line>arrant a villain and a Jacksauce, as ever his black</line>
            <line>shoe trod upon God's ground and his earth, in my</line>
            <line>conscience, la!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>Then keep thy vow, sirrah, when thou meetest the fellow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WILLIAMS</speaker>
            <line>So I will, my liege, as I live.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>Who servest thou under?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WILLIAMS</speaker>
            <line>Under Captain Gower, my liege.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLUELLEN</speaker>
            <line>Gower is a good captain, and is good knowledge and</line>
            <line>literatured in the wars.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>Call him hither to me, soldier.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WILLIAMS</speaker>
            <line>I will, my liege.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>Here, Fluellen; wear thou this favour for me and</line>
            <line>stick it in thy cap: when Alencon and myself were</line>
            <line>down together, I plucked this glove from his helm:</line>
            <line>if any man challenge this, he is a friend to</line>
            <line>Alencon, and an enemy to our person; if thou</line>
            <line>encounter any such, apprehend him, an thou dost me love.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLUELLEN</speaker>
            <line>Your grace doo's me as great honours as can be</line>
            <line>desired in the hearts of his subjects: I would fain</line>
            <line>see the man, that has but two legs, that shall find</line>
            <line>himself aggrieved at this glove; that is all; but I</line>
            <line>would fain see it once, an please God of his grace</line>
            <line>that I might see.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>Knowest thou Gower?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLUELLEN</speaker>
            <line>He is my dear friend, an please you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>Pray thee, go seek him, and bring him to my tent.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLUELLEN</speaker>
            <line>I will fetch him.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>My Lord of Warwick, and my brother Gloucester,</line>
            <line>Follow Fluellen closely at the heels:</line>
            <line>The glove which I have given him for a favour</line>
            <line>May haply purchase him a box o' th' ear;</line>
            <line>It is the soldier's; I by bargain should</line>
            <line>Wear it myself. Follow, good cousin Warwick:</line>
            <line>If that the soldier strike him, as I judge</line>
            <line>By his blunt bearing he will keep his word,</line>
            <line>Some sudden mischief may arise of it;</line>
            <line>For I do know Fluellen valiant</line>
            <line>And, touched with choler, hot as gunpowder,</line>
            <line>And quickly will return an injury:</line>
            <line>Follow and see there be no harm between them.</line>
            <line>Go you with me, uncle of Exeter.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-8">
      <title>SCENE VIII.  Before KING HENRY'S pavilion.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter GOWER and WILLIAMS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WILLIAMS</speaker>
            <line>I warrant it is to knight you, captain.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter FLUELLEN</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLUELLEN</speaker>
            <line>God's will and his pleasure, captain, I beseech you</line>
            <line>now, come apace to the king: there is more good</line>
            <line>toward you peradventure than is in your knowledge to dream of.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WILLIAMS</speaker>
            <line>Sir, know you this glove?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLUELLEN</speaker>
            <line>Know the glove! I know the glove is glove.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WILLIAMS</speaker>
            <line>I know this; and thus I challenge it.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Strikes him</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLUELLEN</speaker>
            <line>'Sblood! an arrant traitor as any is in the</line>
            <line>universal world, or in France, or in England!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GOWER</speaker>
            <line>How now, sir! you villain!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WILLIAMS</speaker>
            <line>Do you think I'll be forsworn?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLUELLEN</speaker>
            <line>Stand away, Captain Gower; I will give treason his</line>
            <line>payment into ploughs, I warrant you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WILLIAMS</speaker>
            <line>I am no traitor.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLUELLEN</speaker>
            <line>That's a lie in thy throat. I charge you in his</line>
            <line>majesty's name, apprehend him: he's a friend of the</line>
            <line>Duke Alencon's.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter WARWICK and GLOUCESTER</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>How now, how now! what's the matter?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLUELLEN</speaker>
            <line>My Lord of Warwick, here is--praised be God for it!</line>
            <line>--a most contagious treason come to light, look</line>
            <line>you, as you shall desire in a summer's day. Here is</line>
            <line>his majesty.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter KING HENRY and EXETER</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>How now! what's the matter?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLUELLEN</speaker>
            <line>My liege, here is a villain and a traitor, that,</line>
            <line>look your grace, has struck the glove which your</line>
            <line>majesty is take out of the helmet of Alencon.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WILLIAMS</speaker>
            <line>My liege, this was my glove; here is the fellow of</line>
            <line>it; and he that I gave it to in change promised to</line>
            <line>wear it in his cap: I promised to strike him, if he</line>
            <line>did: I met this man with my glove in his cap, and I</line>
            <line>have been as good as my word.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLUELLEN</speaker>
            <line>Your majesty hear now, saving your majesty's</line>
            <line>manhood, what an arrant, rascally, beggarly, lousy</line>
            <line>knave it is: I hope your majesty is pear me</line>
            <line>testimony and witness, and will avouchment, that</line>
            <line>this is the glove of Alencon, that your majesty is</line>
            <line>give me; in your conscience, now?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>Give me thy glove, soldier: look, here is the</line>
            <line>fellow of it.</line>
            <line>'Twas I, indeed, thou promised'st to strike;</line>
            <line>And thou hast given me most bitter terms.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLUELLEN</speaker>
            <line>An please your majesty, let his neck answer for it,</line>
            <line>if there is any martial law in the world.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>How canst thou make me satisfaction?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WILLIAMS</speaker>
            <line>All offences, my lord, come from the heart: never</line>
            <line>came any from mine that might offend your majesty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>It was ourself thou didst abuse.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WILLIAMS</speaker>
            <line>Your majesty came not like yourself: you appeared to</line>
            <line>me but as a common man; witness the night, your</line>
            <line>garments, your lowliness; and what your highness</line>
            <line>suffered under that shape, I beseech you take it for</line>
            <line>your own fault and not mine: for had you been as I</line>
            <line>took you for, I made no offence; therefore, I</line>
            <line>beseech your highness, pardon me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>Here, uncle Exeter, fill this glove with crowns,</line>
            <line>And give it to this fellow. Keep it, fellow;</line>
            <line>And wear it for an honour in thy cap</line>
            <line>Till I do challenge it. Give him the crowns:</line>
            <line>And, captain, you must needs be friends with him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLUELLEN</speaker>
            <line>By this day and this light, the fellow has mettle</line>
            <line>enough in his belly. Hold, there is twelve pence</line>
            <line>for you; and I pray you to serve Got, and keep you</line>
            <line>out of prawls, and prabbles' and quarrels, and</line>
            <line>dissensions, and, I warrant you, it is the better for you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WILLIAMS</speaker>
            <line>I will none of your money.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLUELLEN</speaker>
            <line>It is with a good will; I can tell you, it will</line>
            <line>serve you to mend your shoes: come, wherefore should</line>
            <line>you be so pashful? your shoes is not so good: 'tis</line>
            <line>a good silling, I warrant you, or I will change it.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter an English Herald</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>Now, herald, are the dead number'd?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Herald</speaker>
            <line>Here is the number of the slaughter'd French.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>What prisoners of good sort are taken, uncle?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EXETER</speaker>
            <line>Charles Duke of Orleans, nephew to the king;</line>
            <line>John Duke of Bourbon, and Lord Bouciqualt:</line>
            <line>Of other lords and barons, knights and squires,</line>
            <line>Full fifteen hundred, besides common men.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>This note doth tell me of ten thousand French</line>
            <line>That in the field lie slain: of princes, in this number,</line>
            <line>And nobles bearing banners, there lie dead</line>
            <line>One hundred twenty six: added to these,</line>
            <line>Of knights, esquires, and gallant gentlemen,</line>
            <line>Eight thousand and four hundred; of the which,</line>
            <line>Five hundred were but yesterday dubb'd knights:</line>
            <line>So that, in these ten thousand they have lost,</line>
            <line>There are but sixteen hundred mercenaries;</line>
            <line>The rest are princes, barons, lords, knights, squires,</line>
            <line>And gentlemen of blood and quality.</line>
            <line>The names of those their nobles that lie dead:</line>
            <line>Charles Delabreth, high constable of France;</line>
            <line>Jaques of Chatillon, admiral of France;</line>
            <line>The master of the cross-bows, Lord Rambures;</line>
            <line>Great Master of France, the brave Sir Guichard Dolphin,</line>
            <line>John Duke of Alencon, Anthony Duke of Brabant,</line>
            <line>The brother of the Duke of Burgundy,</line>
            <line>And Edward Duke of Bar: of lusty earls,</line>
            <line>Grandpre and Roussi, Fauconberg and Foix,</line>
            <line>Beaumont and Marle, Vaudemont and Lestrale.</line>
            <line>Here was a royal fellowship of death!</line>
            <line>Where is the number of our English dead?</line>
            <stagedir>Herald shews him another paper</stagedir>
            <line>Edward the Duke of York, the Earl of Suffolk,</line>
            <line>Sir Richard Ketly, Davy Gam, esquire:</line>
            <line>None else of name; and of all other men</line>
            <line>But five and twenty. O God, thy arm was here;</line>
            <line>And not to us, but to thy arm alone,</line>
            <line>Ascribe we all! When, without stratagem,</line>
            <line>But in plain shock and even play of battle,</line>
            <line>Was ever known so great and little loss</line>
            <line>On one part and on the other? Take it, God,</line>
            <line>For it is none but thine!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EXETER</speaker>
            <line>'Tis wonderful!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>Come, go we in procession to the village.</line>
            <line>And be it death proclaimed through our host</line>
            <line>To boast of this or take the praise from God</line>
            <line>Which is his only.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLUELLEN</speaker>
            <line>Is it not lawful, an please your majesty, to tell</line>
            <line>how many is killed?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>Yes, captain; but with this acknowledgement,</line>
            <line>That God fought for us.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLUELLEN</speaker>
            <line>Yes, my conscience, he did us great good.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>Do we all holy rites;</line>
            <line>Let there be sung 'Non nobis' and 'Te Deum;'</line>
            <line>The dead with charity enclosed in clay:</line>
            <line>And then to Calais; and to England then:</line>
            <line>Where ne'er from France arrived more happy men.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>