<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="ou-xml.css" title="OU Authoring" alternate="no"?>
<Item
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="OUGeneric_v1.2.xsd"
  SchemaVersion="1.2">
  <CourseCode>S357</CourseCode>
  <CourseTitle>Space, time and cosmology</CourseTitle>
  <ItemID/>
  <ItemTitle/>
  <FrontMatter>
    <Imprint>
      <Standard>
        <GeneralInfo>
          <Paragraph>For information on Open University courses and study packs write to </Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>This text forms part of an Open University Third Level Course. If you would
            like a copy of Studying with The Open University, please write to the Course Enquiries
            Data Service, PO Box 625, Dane Road, Milton Keynes, MK1 1TY. If you have not already
            enrolled on the Course and would like to buy this or other Open University material,
            please write to Open University Educational Enterprises Ltd, 12 Cofferidge Close, Stony
            Stratford, Milton Keynes, MK11 1BY, United Kingdom.</Paragraph>
        </GeneralInfo>
        <Address>
          <AddressLine>The Open University, Walton Hall, Milton Keynes, MK7 6AA</AddressLine>
        </Address>
        <FirstPublished>
          <Paragraph/>
        </FirstPublished>
        <Copyright>
          <Paragraph>Original Copyright &#xA9; 2005 The Open University. Now made available within
            the Creative Commons framework under the CC Attribution &#x2013; Non-commercial licence
            (see http://creativecommons.org/by-nc-sa/2.0/uk/).</Paragraph>
        </Copyright>
        <Rights>
          <Paragraph><!--All rights reserved; no part of this publication may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system, transmitted or utilized in any form or by any means, electronic, mechanical, photocopying, recording or otherwise, without written permission from the publisher or a licence from the Copyright Licensing Agency Ltd. Details of such licences (for reprographic reproduction) may be obtained from the Copyright Licensing Agency Ltd of 90 Tottenham Court Road, London W1P 0LP.--></Paragraph>
        </Rights>
        <Edited>
          <Paragraph>Designed and edited by The Open University</Paragraph>
        </Edited>
        <Typeset>
          <Paragraph>The Open University</Paragraph>
        </Typeset>
        <Printed>
          <Paragraph><!--Henry Ling Ltd, at the Dorset Press, Dorchester, Dorset, United Kingdom--></Paragraph>
        </Printed>
        <ISBN><!--0 7492 6981 2--></ISBN>
        <Edition/>
      </Standard>
    </Imprint>
    <Preface>
      <Figure
        id="FIG_FRONT">
        <Image
          src="S357_1_front.jpg"/>
        <Description/>
      </Figure>
      <Heading/>
    </Preface>
    <Introduction>
      <Title>Introduction</Title>
      <Paragraph>In this unit, we present the three main lines of experimental evidence pointing to
        the big bang origin of the Universe: (i) the recession of the galaxies; (ii) the microwave
        remnant of the early fireball; and (iii) the comparison between the calculated primordial
        nuclear abundances and the present-day composition of matter in the Universe. </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>A data sheet of useful information is provided as a pdf for your use. You may wish
        to print out a copy to keep handy as you progress through the unit.</Paragraph>
      <MediaContent
        id="PDFdatasheet"
        type="pdf"
        src="S357Datasheets"
        target="new window"><Description>Click 'View document' to open the S357_1 data
          sheet.</Description></MediaContent>
      <!--<Paragraph>General relativity has a very different conceptual basis from Band 1 of AC4 introduces that of
this Unit. that of Newtonian mechanics. Its success in accounting for the precession of
Mercury’s orbit, and the bending of light by massive objects like the Sun,
gives us confidence that our picture of space and time should be Einstein’s
rather than Newton’s. In this and the following units, we turn our
attention to the study of the large-scale structure of spacetime. We see
how spacetime as a whole is curved by the gross distribution of mass and
energy in the Universe. This distribution, together with the question of
cosmology how the Universe has developed over time, is the subject of cosmology.
Astronomy and cosmology are subjects that merge into one another with
the single combined aim of understanding the structure and history of the
Universe. The basis and motivation for the whole subject area comes
ultimately from astronomers’ observations. Since the days of Galileo,
optical telescopes of ever greater size have been made. In the last 60 years,
it has been possible to study an increasing range of the electromagnetic
spectrum as different types of telescope have become available. The first
radio telescopes were made just before World War II. Infrared, ultraviolet,
X-ray and gamma ray telescopes then followed, often operating from
spacecraft above the Earth’s atmosphere. These methods have become so
complicated that we have attempted to outline only certain results; a far
longer course would have been necessary to do anything like justice to the
delicacy and sophistication of the techniques involved.
What have we learned from these new techniques? Firstly, matter has
been detected in a wide variety of forms &#x2013; interstellar gas as well as the
stars themselves, for instance. Secondly, it has become possible to perform
detailed studies of the radiation from the very ancient Universe. These
developments have given cosmologists a more comprehensive list of the
forms of mass and energy that govern the spacetime of the Universe. Next,
matter has been detected at much greater distances &#x2013; the more distant
view providing cosmologists with more telling tests of their models. Then
there has been the increasingly detailed information on spectra, with its
evidence on the compositions of the emitting bodies. This information is of
particular concern to the astrophysicist, who tries to understand the
evolution of stars and other types of matter. Such evolution is governed by
stellar dynamics and the processes of nuclear physics. The latter will be
touched on later, though with reference more to nuclear reactions taking
place in the very early Universe than to those occurring in the stars today.
We hope in this Block to build a bridge between the two extremes &#x2013; the
raw data obtained by the astronomer, and the metric parameters derived
by the cosmologist.
In this first unit, we examine the reasons for believing that the Universe
had its origins in the big bang. We shall find that there are three
independent pieces of evidence all pointing to the same conclusion.
Sections 2 to 4 introduce you to the first of these.</Paragraph>-->
    </Introduction>
    <LearningOutcomes>
      <Paragraph>By the end of this unit you should be able to:</Paragraph>
      <LearningOutcome>describe the characteristics of light emitted by stars, and hence the
        information of cosmological interest that can be deduced from it;</LearningOutcome>
      <LearningOutcome>distinguish between true and false statements relevant to the distribution
        and motion of stars within galaxies, and of galaxies within clusters and
        superclusters;</LearningOutcome>
      <LearningOutcome>outline the methods used for estimating the distances to stars and to
        galaxies;</LearningOutcome>
      <LearningOutcome>explain and apply Hubble&#x2019;s law;</LearningOutcome>
      <LearningOutcome>distinguish between various sources of redshift and estimate their relative
        importance in a given situation;</LearningOutcome>
      <LearningOutcome>describe the cosmic microwave radiation in terms of its origin, its thermal
        nature, and how its temperature has changed with time;</LearningOutcome>
      <LearningOutcome>explain how observations of thermal radiation are affected by the motion of
        the observer with respect to it;</LearningOutcome>
      <LearningOutcome>outline the evidence concerning the isotropy of the
        Universe;</LearningOutcome>
      <LearningOutcome>describe the most important basic nuclear reactions taking place in the early
        stages of the big bang, and how the final mix of elements produced provides evidence today
        for the big bang.</LearningOutcome>
    </LearningOutcomes>
  </FrontMatter>
  <Unit>
    <UnitID>S357_1</UnitID>
    <UnitTitle>The big bang</UnitTitle>
    <ByLine/>
    <Session
      id="SES001">
      <Title/>
      <!--Block 1     Newtonian ideas of space and time
Unit 1       Space and time - the setting for the motion of a particle
Unit 2       Newtonian mechanics
Unit 3       Symmetrical and conservation laws
Block 2    Electromagnetism and Einstein's special theory of relativity
Unit 4       Electromagnetic fields
Unit 5       The need for special relativity
Unit 6       Some consequences of special relativity
Unit 7       Spacetime, momentum and energy
Unit 8       Consolidation and revision I
Block 3    Gravitation, Einstein's general theory of relativity and black holes
Unit 9       First steps to a theory of gravitation
Unit 10 & 11   A metric theory of gravity and the field equations of general relativity
Unit 12     Black holes and other consequences of general relativity
Block 4    Cosmology and the early Universe
Unit 13     The big bang
Unit 14     General relativity and cosmology
Unit 15     The evolution of the Universe
Unit 16     Consolidation and revision II-->
      <!--<Section id="SEC001a">
<Title>Aim</Title>

<Paragraph>In this Unit, we present the three main lines of experimental evidence pointing to the big bang origin of the Universe: &#x0028;i&#x0029; the recession of the galaxies; &#x0028;ii&#x0029; the microwave remnant of the early fireball; and &#x0028;iii&#x0029; the comparison between the calculated primordial nuclear abundances and the present-day composition of matter in the Universe.</Paragraph>
</Section>
<Section id="SEC001b">
<Title>Objectives</Title>

<Paragraph>When you have finished studying this Unit, you should be able to:</Paragraph>

<Paragraph>1 Describe the characteristics of light emitted by stars, and hence the information of cosmological interest that can be deduced from it.</Paragraph>

<Paragraph>2 Distinguish between true and false statements relevant to the distribution and motion of stars within galaxies, and of galaxies within clusters and superclusters.</Paragraph>

<Paragraph>3 Outline the methods used for estimating the distances to stars and to galaxies.</Paragraph>

<Paragraph>4 Explain and apply Hubble&#x0027;s law.</Paragraph>

<Paragraph>5 Distinguish between various sources of redshift and estimate their relative importance in a given situation.</Paragraph>

<Paragraph>6 Describe the cosmic microwave radiation in terms of its origin, its thermal nature, and how its temperature has changed with time.</Paragraph>

<Paragraph>7 Explain how observations of thermal radiation are affected by the motion of the observer with respect to it.</Paragraph>

<Paragraph>8 Outline the evidence concerning the isotropy of the Universe.</Paragraph>

<Paragraph>9 Describe the most important basic nuclear reactions taking place in the early stages of the big bang, and how the final mix of elements produced provides evidence today for the big bang.</Paragraph>
</Section>-->
      <Section
        id="SEC001">
        <Title>1 Introducing cosmology</Title>
        <!--<Paragraph>Band 1 of AC4 introduces this Unit.</Paragraph>-->
        <Paragraph>General relativity has a very different conceptual basis from that of Newtonian
          mechanics. Its success in accounting for the precession of Mercury's orbit, and the
          bending of light by massive objects like the Sun, gives us confidence that our picture of
          space and time should be Einstein's rather than Newton's. In this and the following units,
          we turn our attention to the study of the large-scale structure of spacetime. We see how
          spacetime as a whole is curved by the gross distribution of mass and energy in the
          Universe. This distribution, together with the question of how the Universe has developed
          over time, is the subject of <i>cosmology</i>.</Paragraph>
        <!--<Paragraph>cosmology</Paragraph>-->
        <Paragraph>Astronomy and cosmology are subjects that merge into one another with the single
          combined aim of understanding the structure and history of the Universe. The basis and
          motivation for the whole subject area comes ultimately from astronomers&#x2019;
          observations. Since the days of Galileo, optical telescopes of ever greater size have been
          made. In the last 60 years, it has been possible to study an increasing range of the
          electromagnetic spectrum as different types of telescope have become available. The first
          radio telescopes were made just before World War II. Infrared, ultraviolet, X-ray and
          gamma ray telescopes then followed, often operating from spacecraft above the Earth's
          atmosphere. These methods have become so complicated that we have attempted to outline
          only certain results; a far longer course would have been necessary to do anything like
          justice to the delicacy and sophistication of the techniques involved.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>What have we learned from these new techniques? Firstly, matter has been detected
          in a wide variety of forms &#x2013; interstellar gas as well as the stars themselves, for
          instance. Secondly, it has become possible to perform detailed studies of the radiation
          from the very ancient Universe. These developments have given cosmologists a more
          comprehensive list of the forms of mass and energy that govern the spacetime of the
          Universe. Next, matter has been detected at much greater distances &#x2013; the more
          distant view providing cosmologists with more telling tests of their models. Then there
          has been the increasingly detailed information on spectra, with its evidence on the
          compositions of the emitting bodies. This information is of particular concern to the
          astrophysicist, who tries to understand the evolution of stars and other types of matter.
          Such evolution is governed by stellar dynamics and the processes of nuclear physics. The
          latter will be touched on later, though with reference more to nuclear reactions taking
          place in the very early Universe than to those occurring in the stars today.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>We hope <!--in this Block -->to build a bridge between the two extremes &#x2013;
          the raw data obtained by the astronomer, and the metric parameters derived by the
          cosmologist. Thus, we examine the reasons for believing that the Universe had its origins
          in the big bang. We shall find that there are three independent pieces of evidence all
          pointing to the same conclusion. Sections 2 to 4 introduce you to the first of
          these.</Paragraph>
      </Section>
      <Section
        id="SEC002">
        <Title>2 Radiation from the galaxies</Title>
        <!--<Paragraph>galaxy</Paragraph>-->
        <Paragraph>Stars occur in great collections called <i>galaxies</i>. The distribution and
          motion of galaxies provide us with the first important experimental information on which
          we shall build our understanding of the type of universe we inhabit. So, what do we know
          about galaxies?</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>All the stars that can be distinguished by the naked eye &#x2013; a few thousand
          in number &#x2013; belong to one galaxy: our own Milky Way Galaxy. Sometimes it is just
          written Galaxy, with a capital G, to distinguish it from all the billions of other
          galaxies in the observable Universe.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Our Galaxy has the overall shape of a flattened spiral. As shown in <CrossRef
            idref="FIG001_001">Figure 1</CrossRef>, we are halfway inside the Galaxy so the spiral
          form is not obvious to us as we look at the sky. In fact it has only been revealed by
          detailed radio mapping. This is because there are large sections of the
          <!--<Paragraph>galactic dust</Paragraph>--> Galaxy that are obscured from optical
          observations by the intervening <i>dust</i> and gas which scatter and absorb visible
          light. (However, they are essentially transparent to radio waves.) If there were an
          unobscured view through telescopes, we would be able to see to the far side of the Galaxy,
          and in doing so we would record about 10<sup>11</sup> stars within it.</Paragraph>
        <Figure
          id="FIG001_001"><Image
            id="FIG001_001"
            src="S357_1_001i.jpg"/>
          <Caption>
            <b>Figure 1</b>: The Solar System is about halfway out from the centre of the Milky Way
            galaxy. We have a relatively clear view outwards from the disc to other
            galaxies</Caption>
          <Description/>
        </Figure>
        <Paragraph>Fortunately for astronomers, the stars, though vast in number, display a degree
          of uniformity which makes their classification and study possible. Their masses are
          broadly similar &#x2013; most are contained within a couple of orders of magnitude, with
          our Sun having a typical average mass. They do differ considerably in size and therefore
          in density (since their masses are similar), but these differences are thought principally
          to relate to different <i>stages</i> in the life of a star rather than to different
            <i>types</i> of star. These various stages correspond to different types of nuclei
          taking part in the nuclear reactions that provide the energy output. It is one of the
          features of astrophysics that one is able to take nuclear data obtained in the laboratory
          and use them to understand the various stages of evolution seen in different stars. The
          main process in young stars is a sequence of reactions leading to the fusion of hydrogen
          nuclei to make helium nuclei. Later, helium fuses to form carbon, then carbon undergoes
          reactions which build up heavier nuclei. This can continue up to iron. The different
          reactions take place at different temperatures and pressures, so this progression of
          reactions governs the sequence in which a star changes its size and
          appearance.</Paragraph>
        <!--<Paragraph>evolution of galaxies</Paragraph>-->
        <!--<Paragraph>spectrum</Paragraph>-->
        <Paragraph>Stellar evolution is too slow a process for us to see any particular star undergo
          change in one human lifetime, apart from a few exceptionally young stars, and some very
          old stars undergoing gravitational collapse leading to supernova explosions. But by
          observing different stars at their respective different stages of development, it is
          possible to piece together the whole of a typical stellar life cycle.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>The general idea of an evolutionary sequence &#x2013; one that can be
          reconstructed on a computer &#x2013; is of concern in this unit for the following reason:
          when astronomers look at a very distant galaxy, they are receiving radiation that left its
          source long ago. The galaxy will, therefore, seem <i>younger</i> than it actually is now.
          The travel time for the light may have been hundreds or thousands of millions of years. To
          interpret the observations, one needs to know how the power output of the galaxy evolves
          with time.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>The light from a typical galaxy derives mostly from the stars it contains, with
          only a small amount from interstellar matter. So, to understand the power output of a
          galaxy one has to add together the light from about 10<sup>11</sup> stars at various
          stages of development. We cannot assume that the stars of the distant galaxy will be
          emitting the same amount of light as those of our own Galaxy today; the distant stars will
          be seen at an earlier stage in their development when perhaps their power output was
          different from what it actually is now. Indeed, there is an added complication. The
          evolution of a star depends critically on its <i>mass</i>. A very massive star will shine
          much more brightly than a less massive one, but over a much shorter time period. It could
          be that when we look at a young galaxy, we see many more massive stars living out their
          brief active lives than we observe today in our own Galaxy. So the mass distribution of
          active stars in our Galaxy might not be representative of what we see happening in the
          distant younger galaxy. It is difficult to know how to compensate for this. The mass
          distribution of the stars in a galaxy depends on the way the galaxy was formed, and
          unfortunately, the formation and growth of galaxies remains an unsolved, or at least
          poorly understood, problem.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>In summary, we know little about the way the power output of a galaxy changes
          with time, and this represents a severe limitation on the cosmologist's use and
          interpretation of astronomical data on power output. The frustration this causes will
          become apparent later.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>The light from a galaxy can tell us more than just its overall power output.
          Additional information comes from the analysis of its <i>spectrum</i>. Let us assume that
          light comes mainly from the stars and that we can ignore interstellar matter. The majority
          of galaxies are too far away for it to be possible to resolve individual stars, and
          therefore the best one can do is to take the spectrum of the galaxy as a whole:
            10<sup>11</sup> stars summed together. How can we relate this to a stellar
          spectrum?</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>The light from a star comes from the hot layers of gas near its surface. This
          light filters out through the dilute layers above. As it does so, characteristic patterns
          of absorption lines are imprinted on the spectrum.</Paragraph>
        <!--<Paragraph>absorption spectrum</Paragraph>-->
        <!--<Paragraph>emission spectrum</Paragraph>-->
        <Paragraph><CrossRef
            idref="FIG001_002">Figure 2</CrossRef> shows part of the <i>absorption spectrum</i> of
          the Sun, compared to an <i>emission spectrum</i> produced in the laboratory.</Paragraph>
        <Figure
          id="FIG001_002"><Image
            id="FIG001_002"
            src="S357_1_002i.jpg"/>
          <Caption>
            <b>Figure 2</b>: The absorption spectrum of light from the Sun, for wavelengths between
            390 nm and 450 nm. It is complicated because of the many elements involved. The bright
            lines above and below the absorption spectrum belong to the emission spectrum of a
            laboratory reference source</Caption><SourceReference>Hale Observatories <ItemRights>
              <OwnerRef/>
              <ItemRef/>
              <ItemAcknowledgement>Hale Observatories</ItemAcknowledgement>
            </ItemRights></SourceReference>
          <Description/>
        </Figure>
        <!--<Paragraph>Objective 1</Paragraph>-->
        <SAQ
          id="SAQ001_001">
          <Heading>Question 1</Heading>
          <Question>
            <Paragraph>A beam of white light is passed through a bulb containing calcium vapour.
              Explain, in broad terms, with the aid of diagrams, the nature of the light
              transmitted, (a) in the direction of the beam, and (b) at an angle to it.</Paragraph>
          </Question>
          <Answer>
            <Paragraph><b>(a)</b> At position A (<CrossRef
                idref="FIG001_032">Figure 3</CrossRef>), the spectrum of the observed light consists
              of a flat continuum with absorption lines (corresponding to the transitions between
              the ground state and other states) as in <CrossRef
                idref="FIG001_033">Figure 4</CrossRef>(a).</Paragraph>
            <Paragraph><b>(b)</b> At position B, no direct light is seen. The light that is observed
              comes from calcium atoms that have been excited, and is therefore an emission spectrum
              of lines on a dark background, with the wavelengths of the lines the same as those of
              the absorption lines seen at position A. This is shown in <CrossRef
                idref="FIG001_033">Figure 4</CrossRef>(b).</Paragraph>
            <Figure
              id="FIG001_032"><Image
                id="FIG001_032"
                src="S357_1_032i.jpg"/>
              <Caption>
                <b>Figure 3</b>: White light is passed through a bulb containing calcium vapour and
                observed at A (in the direction of the beam) and at B (at an angle to the
                beam)</Caption>
              <Description/>
            </Figure>
            <Figure
              id="FIG001_033"><Image
                id="FIG001_033"
                src="S357_1_033i.jpg"/>
              <Caption>
                <b>Figure 4</b>: The spectra observed at the points A and B of Figure 3</Caption>
              <SourceReference>
                <ItemRights>
                  <OwnerRef/>
                  <ItemRef/>
                  <ItemAcknowledgement/>
                </ItemRights>
              </SourceReference>
              <Description/>
            </Figure>
          </Answer>
        </SAQ>
        <!--<Figure id="FIG001_002"><Image id="FIG001_002" src="S357_1_002i.jpg"/>
<Caption>
<b>Figure 4</b>: The absorption spectrum of light from the Sun, for wavelengths between 390 nm and 450 nm. It is complicated because of the many elements involved. The bright lines above and below the absorption spectrum belong to the emission spectrum of a laboratory reference source.</Caption>
<Description/>
</Figure>-->
        <!--<Paragraph>Doppler shift</Paragraph>-->
        <!--<Paragraph>Doppler broadening</Paragraph>-->
        <Paragraph>The spectral lines in the light from a galaxy enable the astronomer to identify
          the elements emitting the light. Any of the ninety or so stable elements may be present,
          but the lighter elements, especially hydrogen, are usually the more abundant. Because some
          elements are common to most stars, the absorption lines of these particular elements will
          be visible in the light of the galaxy as a whole. Also, the absorption lines of magnesium,
          sodium, calcium and iron are often easy to distinguish, even though other elements, such
          as hydrogen and helium, are more abundant than these.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>Usually the absorption lines are sharp and identifiable, despite several effects
          which can broaden them. One of these effects is a <i>Doppler shift</i> caused by the
          rotation of the source. For example, the spectral lines of calcium atoms moving towards us
          would have their apparent frequencies systematically increased (blueshifted) according to
          the equation</Paragraph>
        <Equation
          id="UEQN001_000"><Image
            src="S357_1_ue018i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
        <Paragraph>where <i>f</i><sub>0</sub> is the observed frequency, <i>f</i><sub>1</sub> is the
          emitted frequency and <InlineEquation><Image
              src="S357_1_ie00italvi.gif"/><Description/></InlineEquation> is the speed of appoach.
          The spectral lines of atoms moving away from us would be correspondingly redshifted. This
          Doppler shift causes the width of a given spectral line to <i>broaden</i> if we are
          viewing the rotating galaxy along the plane of its disc so that the light-absorbing atoms
          belonging to stars on one side are moving away from us, while those on the opposite side
          are moving towards us (refer back to <CrossRef
            idref="FIG001_001">Figure 1</CrossRef>). In addition, the star itself might be rotating
          so that different parts of the star would have different components of velocity towards or
          away from us, thereby increasing the broadening. Random motions of stars can also cause
          line broadening in a similar way.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>The shifts and broadenings of the lines are not usually bad enough to mask the
          spectrum. Therefore, although a galaxy is a very complicated light source, its light is
          not just a meaningless jumble of fuzzy lines. There are some features, such as the calcium
          lines, which stand out sharply.</Paragraph>
        <!--<Paragraph>Objectives 1 and 5</Paragraph>-->
        <SAQ
          id="SAQ001_002">
          <Heading>Question 2</Heading>
          <Question>
            <!--<NumberedList>
<ListItem>-->
            <Paragraph>(a) It can be shown that when radiation rises a height <i>H</i> near the
              Earth's surface, there is a shift in frequency towards the red end of the spectrum
              given by &#x394;<i>f</i>/<i>f</i>&#xA0;=&#xA0;&#x2212;<i>gH/c</i><sup>2</sup>, where
                <i>g</i> is the acceleration due to gravity. When radiation starting from the
              surface of a body of mass <i>M</i> and radius <i>R</i> escapes to a large distance, it
              suffers a fractional frequency shift
                &#x394;<i>f</i>/<i>f</i>&#xA0;=&#xA0;&#x2212;<i>GM/Rc</i><sup>2</sup>, where
                <i>G</i> is the gravitational constant. Outline the steps you would need to take to
              establish the connection between these two statements <i>without</i> necessarily
              giving the derivation. (<i>Hint:</i> Bear in mind that
                <i>g</i>&#xA0;=&#xA0;<i>GM/R</i><sup>2</sup>.)</Paragraph>
            <!--</ListItem>
<ListItem>-->
            <Paragraph>(b) Imagine a star with a mass
                <i>M</i>&#xA0;=&#xA0;2&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>30</sup> kg, a radius
                <i>R</i>&#xA0;=&#xA0;7&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>8</sup> m and a period of rotation
                <i>T</i>&#xA0;=&#xA0;2&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>6</sup> s (similar to the Sun).
              Suppose also that the typical speed of turbulent motion in the atmosphere of the star
              is 6000 m s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>. How is the frequency of the hydrogen line whose
              wavelength in the laboratory is 656 nm, affected by:</Paragraph>
            <!--<NumberedSubsidiaryList>
<SubListItem>-->
            <Paragraph>(i) gravitational redshift;</Paragraph>
            <!--</SubListItem>
<SubListItem>-->
            <Paragraph>(ii) Doppler shift due to rotation;</Paragraph>
            <!--</SubListItem>
<SubListItem>-->
            <Paragraph>(iii) Doppler shift due to turbulence?</Paragraph>
            <!--</SubListItem>
</NumberedSubsidiaryList>-->
            <Paragraph>(The values of <i>G</i> and <i>c</i> are given in the <a
                href="http://openlearn.open.ac.uk/file.php/3639/S357Datasheets.pdf"
                target="_blank">data sheet</a>, and the formula for the Doppler shift of light is
              given in the equation above.)</Paragraph>
            <!--</NumberedList>-->
          </Question>
          <Answer>
            <Paragraph><b>(a)</b> The result
                  &#x394;<i>f</i>/<i>f</i>&#xA0;=&#xA0;&#x2212;<i>gH/c<sup>2</sup></i><!--, given in Unit 9,-->
              applies only to small changes in height, <i>H</i>. For a large change, one must take
              account of the fact that <i>g</i> changes with height. The value of <i>g</i> is given
              by equating the weight of a body, <i>mg</i>, to the gravitational attraction. Thus at
              the surface of the Earth</Paragraph>
            <Equation
              id="UEQN001_0009"><Image
                src="S357_1_ue009i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
            <Paragraph>where <i>M</i> and <i>R</i> are the mass and radius of the Earth
              respectively. At any distance <i>r</i> (greater than <i>R</i>), we may write more
              generally</Paragraph>
            <Equation
              id="UEQN001_0010"><Image
                src="S357_1_ue010i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
            <Paragraph>At each distance <i>r</i>, the frequency shift caused by rising to <i>r</i> +
                <i>dr</i> is given by the formula <!--of Unit 9-->.</Paragraph>
            <Equation
              id="UEQN001_0011"><Image
                src="S357_1_ue011i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
            <Paragraph>where we write <i>dr</i> in place of <i>H</i>. Thus the total frequency shift
              suffered in escaping to a very large distance (&#x2018;infinity&#x2019;) is determined
              by:</Paragraph>
            <Equation
              id="UEQN001_0012"><Image
                src="S357_1_ue012i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
            <Paragraph>where <i>f</i><sub>1</sub> is the emitted frequency and <i>f</i><sub>0</sub>
              is the observed frequency. This gives the method asked for in the
              Question.</Paragraph>
            <Paragraph>Performing the integration (which the Question did <i>not</i> ask for) gives
              the stated result. In fact,</Paragraph>
            <Equation
              id="UEQN001_0013"><Image
                src="S357_1_ue013i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
            <Paragraph>Provided the magnitude of &#x394;<i>f</i>&#xA0;=&#xA0;<i>f</i><sub>0</sub>
              &#x2212;
              <i>f</i><sub>1</sub> &#x226A;
              <i>f</i><sub>1</sub>, we can approximate the left-hand side of this equation
              by</Paragraph>
            <Equation
              id="UEQN001_0014"><Image
                src="S357_1_ue014i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
            <Paragraph>and conclude that, for any emitted frequency <i>f</i>.</Paragraph>
            <Equation
              id="UEQN001_0015"><Image
                src="S357_1_ue015i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
            <Paragraph><b>(b) (i)</b> Using the result of part (a), we can find the effect of the
              gravitational redshift on light leaving the star as follows:</Paragraph>
            <Equation
              id="UEQN001_0016"><Image
                src="S357_1_ue016i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
            <Paragraph>All the radiation leaving the star has been &#x2018;redshifted&#x2019; by
              this amount by the time it reaches the Earth, which we may certainly regard as at an
              &#x2018;infinite&#x2019; distance from the star.</Paragraph>
            <Paragraph><b>(ii)</b> The speed at the edge of the star is</Paragraph>
            <Equation
              id="UEQN001_0017"><Image
                src="S357_1_ue017i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
            <Paragraph><!--As given in Unit 6, -->The Doppler shift is</Paragraph>
            <Equation
              id="UEQN001_0018"><Image
                src="S357_1_ue018i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
            <Paragraph><i/> when <InlineEquation><Image
                  src="S357_1_ie00italvi.gif"/><Description/></InlineEquation> is a speed of
              approach. Here,</Paragraph>
            <Equation
              id="UEQN001_0019"><Image
                src="S357_1_ue019i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
            <Paragraph>This could be used directly in the formula but since <InlineEquation><Image
                  src="S357_1_ie00italvi.gif"/><Description/></InlineEquation>/<i>c</i> is so small,
              we can use the approximation</Paragraph>
            <Equation
              id="UEQN001_0020"><Image
                src="S357_1_ue020i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
            <Paragraph>so the fractional change in frequency, &#x394;<i>f</i>/<i>f</i>, is
              simply:</Paragraph>
            <Equation
              id="UEQN001_0021"><Image
                src="S357_1_ue021i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
            <Paragraph>Light from the advancing limb is blueshifted by this amount, and from the
              receding limb is redshifted by this amount. The width imparted to lines is thus the
              fraction 14.7 &#xD7;10<sup>&#x2212;6</sup> of their central frequency.</Paragraph>
            <Paragraph><b>(iii)</b> The turbulent motion again produces both blueshifts and
              redshifts, of amount &#xB1;6000 m
                s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>/<i>c</i>&#xA0;=&#xA0;&#xB1;20&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;6</sup>.</Paragraph>
            <Paragraph>The frequency of the 656 nm line is given by</Paragraph>
            <Equation
              id="UEQN001_0022"><Image
                src="S357_1_ue022i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
            <Paragraph>The frequency shifts are therefore as shown in <CrossRef
                idref="TBL003">Table 1</CrossRef>.</Paragraph>
            <Table
              id="TBL003">
              <TableHead>Table 1</TableHead>
              <TableBody><table><tr>
                    <th/>
                    <th/>
                    <th>&#x394;<i>f</i>/<i>f</i></th>
                    <th/>
                    <th>&#x394;<i>f/</i>MHz</th>
                  </tr><tr>
                    <td>gravitation</td>
                    <th/>
                    <td>&#x2212;2.12&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;6</sup></td>
                    <th/>
                    <td>&#x2212;970</td>
                  </tr><tr>
                    <td>rotation</td>
                    <th/>
                    <td>&#xB1;7.33&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;6</sup></td>
                    <th/>
                    <td>&#xB1;3350</td>
                  </tr><tr>
                    <td>turbulence</td>
                    <th/>
                    <td>&#xB1;20&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;6</sup></td>
                    <th/>
                    <td>&#xB1;9150</td></tr>
                </table>
              </TableBody><SourceReference/></Table>
          </Answer>
        </SAQ>
        <Paragraph>&#xA0;</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>In many galaxies, spectral lines have been observed whose <i>relative</i>
          positions correspond exactly with those of a known element (so that the spectrum is
          confidently identified), but whose <i>absolute</i> frequencies are all noticeably shifted.
          This can have nothing to do with the random motions of the stars within the galaxy, or the
          rotations of either the individual stars or of the galaxy as a whole; all these motions
          (being as often towards us as away from us) would merely broaden the line. A net shift of
          all the lines in a spectrum seems to suggest that the galaxy itself has a line-of-sight
          motion (i.e. a component of velocity towards or away from us). The shift is nearly always
          to longer wavelengths, i.e. towards the red end of the visible spectrum, so it is referred
          to as the &#x2018;redshift&#x2019;. If the redshift is interpreted as a Doppler shift (an
          interpretation we shall reconsider later) due to the motion of the galaxies, then it
          follows that most of the galaxies are receding from us. In other words, <i>the Universe is
            expanding</i>.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>The term &#x2018;redshift&#x2019; has a precise definition: it is equal to
          &#x394;&#x3BB;/&#x3BB;, where &#x394;&#x3BB; is the shift in wavelength of a line whose
          emitted wavelength is &#x3BB;. The value of &#x394;&#x3BB;/&#x3BB; is the same for all the
          lines in the spectrum of an object receding at a given speed, and is normally denoted by
            <i>z:</i></Paragraph>
        <Equation
          id="EQN000_001"><Image
            src="S357_1_e001i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
        <Paragraph>where &#x3BB;<sub>0</sub> is the observed wavelength now, and &#x3BB;<sub>1</sub>
          is the wavelength at emission. These redshifts in the spectra of galaxies are generally
            <i>far</i> larger than the stellar effects considered in <CrossRef
            idref="SAQ001_002">Question 2</CrossRef>, as can be judged from <CrossRef
            idref="FIG001_003">Figure 5</CrossRef>.</Paragraph>
        <Figure
          id="FIG001_003"><Image
            id="FIG001_003"
            src="S357_1_003i.jpg"/>
          <Caption>
            <b>Figure 5</b>: The absorption spectra of five different galaxies. Only the most
            strongly absorbed lines, common to the bulk of the stars, are visible, but this is
            enough to give a recognisable pattern</Caption>
          <SourceReference>Hale Observatories <ItemRights>
              <OwnerRef/>
              <ItemRef/>
              <ItemAcknowledgement>Hale Observatories</ItemAcknowledgement>
            </ItemRights>
          </SourceReference>
          <Description/>
        </Figure>
        <!--<Paragraph>Note that it is customary to reserve the suffix, 0, for the values of quantities as they are at the present time, <i>t</i><sub>0</sub>. Values at other times must carry some other suffix. In this way, we end up with the rather counterintuitive situation where &#x03BB;<sub>1</sub> applies to an <i>earlier</i> time, <i>t</i><sub>1</sub>, than &#x03BB;<sub>0</sub></Paragraph>-->
        <Paragraph>In summary then, when dealing with light from stars, there are three ways in
          which the frequency can be shifted:</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>(i) The Doppler shift due to motion &#x2013; whether that arises through the
          rotation of the star, its bodily motion along the line of sight, or turbulence in its
          atmosphere. This type of shift, which can be red or blue, is accounted for by special
          relativity.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>(ii) The gravitational redshift, arising from general relativity.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>(iii) A new type of redshift due to the recession of the galaxies,
          which<!--, as we shall see in Unit 14,--> is also a consequence of general
          relativity.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>(Note that it is customary to reserve the suffix, 0, for the values of quantities
          as they are at the present time, <i>t</i><sub>0</sub>. Values at other times must carry
          some other suffix. In this way, we end up with the rather counterintuitive situation where
            &#x3BB;<sub>1</sub> applies to an <i>earlier</i> time, <i>t</i><sub>1</sub>, than
            &#x3BB;<sub>0</sub>.)</Paragraph>
        <!--<Paragraph>Objective 1</Paragraph>-->
        <SAQ
          id="SAQ001_003">
          <Heading>Question 3</Heading>
          <Question>
            <Paragraph>Hydrogen has emission lines at 434, 486 and 656 nm. A galaxy is observed to
              have these three lines redshifted in wavelength by 2% (i.e.
              <i>z</i>&#xA0;=&#xA0;&#x394;&#x3BB;/&#x3BB;&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.02). What wavelengths will
              be observed? What is the frequency shift &#x394;<i>f</i>/<i>f</i> ?</Paragraph>
          </Question>
          <Answer>
            <Paragraph>If &#x3BB;<sub>1</sub> is the emitted wavelength and &#x3BB;<sub>0</sub> is
              the observed wavelength, then</Paragraph>
            <Equation
              id="UEQN001_0023"><Image
                src="S357_1_ue023i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
            <Paragraph>Therefore</Paragraph>
            <Equation
              id="UEQN001_0024"><Image
                src="S357_1_ue024i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
            <Paragraph>Thus the observed wavelengths are:</Paragraph>
            <Equation
              id="UEQN001_0025"><Image
                src="S357_1_ue025i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
            <Paragraph>The relative frequency shift is given by</Paragraph>
            <Equation
              id="UEQN001_0026"><Image
                src="S357_1_ue026i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
            <Paragraph>But</Paragraph>
            <Equation
              id="UEQN001_0027"><Image
                src="S357_1_ue027i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
            <Paragraph>Therefore</Paragraph>
            <Equation
              id="UEQN001_0028"><Image
                src="S357_1_ue028i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
            <Paragraph>and</Paragraph>
            <Equation
              id="UEQN001_0029"><Image
                src="S357_1_ue029i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
            <Paragraph>Note that the shift in frequency is the same for all lines of the spectrum,
              but differs from the shift in wavelength, which is <i>z</i>.</Paragraph>
          </Answer>
        </SAQ>
        <!--<Figure id="FIG001_003"><Image id="FIG001_003" src="S357_1_003i.jpg"/>
<Caption>
<b>Figure 5</b>: The absorption spectra of five different galaxies. Only the most strongly absorbed lines, common to the bulk of the stars, are visible, but this is enough to give a recognisable pattern.</Caption>
<Description/>
</Figure>-->
        <Paragraph>As we shall see later in this unit, the redshift in galactic light has provided
          one of the main clues to the nature of the large-scale structure of spacetime. But to
          discover how the pattern of the redshifts observed in different galaxies reveals this
          structure, we need further information about the distances of galaxies.</Paragraph>
      </Section>
      <Section
        id="SEC003">
        <Title>3 Distances of galaxies</Title>
        <SubSection
          id="SEC003_001">
          <Title>3.1 First steps towards a distance scale</Title>
          <Paragraph>As you will see from <CrossRef
              idref="TBL001">Table 2</CrossRef>, when it comes to astronomy and cosmology, one is
            called on to deal with a wide range of distances. (Note that a light-year (ly) is the
            distance light travels in one year, i.e. 9.46&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>15</sup> m. The
            distances are also quoted in a very commonly used astronomical unit of distance: the
            megaparsec, Mpc, where a parsec (pc) is 3.26 ly or
            3.09&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>16</sup>m.)</Paragraph>
          <Table
            id="TBL001">
            <TableHead>Table 2</TableHead>
            <TableBody><table><tr>
                  <th/>
                  <th
                    colspan="2">Distance</th>
                </tr><tr>
                  <td>Earth&#x2013;Moon</td>
                  <td>1.28 light-seconds</td>
                  <td>1.25&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;14</sup> Mpc</td>
                </tr><tr>
                  <td>Earth&#x2013;Sun</td>
                  <td>8.3 light-minutes</td>
                  <td>4.8&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;12</sup> Mpc</td>
                </tr><tr>
                  <td>Nearest star</td>
                  <td>&#x2248; 4 ly</td>
                  <td>1.23&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;6</sup> Mpc</td>
                </tr><tr>
                  <td>Diameter of our Galaxy</td>
                  <td>&#x2248; 10<sup>5</sup> ly</td>
                  <td>3&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;2</sup> Mpc</td>
                </tr><tr>
                  <td>Distance to nearest galaxy</td>
                  <td>&#x2248; 2&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>6</sup> ly</td>
                  <td>&#x2248; 1 Mpc</td>
                </tr><tr>
                  <td>Farthest galaxy seen</td>
                  <td>&#x2248; 4&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>9</sup> ly</td>
                  <td>&#x2248; 1.2&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>3</sup> Mpc</td></tr>
              </table>
            </TableBody><SourceReference/></Table>
          <!--<Paragraph>luminosity</Paragraph>-->
          <!--<Paragraph>flux density</Paragraph>-->
          <Paragraph>To measure the distance of a far-off galaxy clearly requires a series of steps.
            The first of these, the Earth&#x2013;Sun distance, is based on our knowledge of the
            orbital period of the Earth about the Sun, and that of some other planet. One can then
            readily obtain an estimate of their <i>relative</i> distances from the Sun by using
            Kepler's third law. To convert this to an <i>absolute</i> measurement, one needs a
            determination of the actual distance between the Earth and the planet at some time. In
            practice, this fix is gained by measuring the distances to Mercury, Venus and Mars,
            using radar. These then allow one to compute the Earth&#x2013;Sun distance. It is
            currently estimated, with obvious high precision, to be 149 597 870.66 km.</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>Knowing this, the diameter of the Earth's orbit can now be used as a baseline
            for measuring the distance to nearby stars, using the surveyor's triangulation method.
            One makes angular measurements on a star from opposite ends of an Earth-orbital
            diameter, i.e. at intervals of 6 months. At the time of writing (2004), data from the
            Hipparcos satellite surpass in precision and scope all previous measurements of nearby
            stellar distances.</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>But no matter how good this satellite-gathered data, there soon comes a stage
            where the angles become too small to measure accurately using the triangulation method.
            Some other method must be employed to extend the distance scale to the more distant
            stars.</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>If a source has a known total light output, i.e. known <i>luminosity</i>, then
            it can be used as a standard source. The distance of the source can be found from the
              <i>received</i> light power. The further away the star is, the fainter it appears. The
            relationship follows an inverse square law (allowing for various corrections, such as
            that due to the absorption of light by interstellar dust). The light power received per
            unit area of detector is called the <i>flux density</i>. It follows, summing over the
            area of a sphere centred on the star and of radius, <i>r</i>, equal to the distance to
            the star, that in the absence of absorption:</Paragraph>
          <Equation
            id="EQN000_002"><Image
              src="S357_1_e002i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
          <Paragraph>Unfortunately stars differ widely in their luminosities, so if we simply look
            up at the sky and pick out a faint star, it may be either an intrinsically dim star, or
            a particularly distant star &#x2013; or partly dim and distant.</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>This ambiguity can be partly overcome by recognising that, while it is
            impossible to directly measure the luminosity of a particular source, one <i>can</i>
            estimate the temperature of the star. This is done from measurements on the overall
            shape of its emitted spectrum &#x2013; stars emitting predominantly in the red part of
            the spectrum being cooler than those that emit more in the blue region. Thus the
            spectrum, and hence temperature, can be determined with a fair degree of confidence.
            Now, it turns out that when observations are made on a compact cluster of stars (the
            cluster being small enough for all its stars to be considered equidistant from us), a
            plot of flux density versus temperature generally gives the <i>same</i> distribution no
            matter which cluster is chosen &#x2013; apart from an overall constant factor depending
            on the distance to the cluster. Thus, the most likely luminosity of a star is related to
            its temperature. But in order to use the temperatures of stars to obtain luminosities,
            and hence distances, from Equation 2, we need to progress beyond a plot of <i>flux
              density</i> versus temperature to one of luminosity versus temperature.</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>In order to achieve this, studies have been made of a group of about 100 stars
            called the &#x2018;Hyades star cluster&#x2019;. This group is close enough to us for its
            distance to be determined by the Hipparcos satellite. Knowing this distance and the flux
            density of the stars, the luminosities could be established, and the plot of luminosity
            versus temperature calibrated. By studying the flux densities and colours of stars more
            distant than the Hyades star cluster, we can use this calibrated plot to infer their
            distances from us.</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>This method applies to stars confined to our own Galaxy. As for stars in other
            galaxies, most of these cannot be distinguished separately. So, the next step is to try
            to find a particularly bright type of star &#x2013; one that <i>can</i> be recognised
            not only in our Galaxy but also in neighbouring galaxies. If this were possible, it
            would give us a method of extending the distance scale out to other galaxies.
            Fortunately there <i>does</i> exist a type of star that can be recognised at least in
            neighbouring galaxies &#x2013; a star known as a
            <!--<Paragraph>Cepheid variable</Paragraph>-->
            <i>Cepheid variable</i>. The important characteristic of a Cepheid is that its light
            output varies in a regular fashion, with a period which is directly related to its mean
            luminosity (see <CrossRef
              idref="FIG001_004">Figure 6</CrossRef>a). The variation is due to cyclical changes in
            diameter. The relationship between mean luminosity and period can be calibrated by
            studying Cepheids that are sufficiently close for their distances to have been measured
            by methods mentioned earlier. So whenever such stars can be distinguished from the other
            types of variable star in the more distant galaxies, their luminosities can be deduced
            (see <CrossRef
              idref="FIG001_004">Figure 6</CrossRef>b). Comparing luminosity with the measured flux
            density then enables the distance of the star to be calculated. Cepheids have been used
            extensively to measure the distances to nearby galaxies -those belonging to a cluster of
            galaxies known as the Local Group (to be described later). Following the advent of the
            Hubble Space Telescope with its superior resolution of individual stars, it became
            possible in 1996 to extend Cepheid-based measurements as far as a galaxy known as M100,
            in the Virgo cluster, yielding a distance of 5.6&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>7</sup>
            ly.</Paragraph>
          <Figure
            id="FIG001_004"><Image
              id="FIG001_004"
              src="S357_1_004i.jpg"/>
            <Caption>
              <b>Figure 6</b>: (a) An 18-day section of the light curve of the typical Cepheid
              variable, Delta Cephei, which has a 5.37-day oscillation.
              <!--&#x0028;<i>Apparent magnitude</i> is a term defined in the Glossary.&#x0029; -->(b)
              The observed relationship between the period and luminosity (in watts) of Cepheid
              variables (1&#xA0;W&#xA0;=&#xA0;1&#xA0;J&#xA0;s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>). Notice that both
              scales are logarithmic, so the straight line implies that period
              <!--replace oc with 'is proportional to' sign-->&#x221D;
                (luminosity)<sup><i>m</i></sup>, where 1/<i>m</i> is the slope of the
              line.<!--&#x0028;<i>Absolute magnitude</i> is a term defined in the Glossary&#x0029;--></Caption>
            <SourceReference>based on H. Arp (1960) in <i>Astronomical J.</i>, 65, 426 <ItemRights>
                <OwnerRef/>
                <ItemRef/>
                <ItemAcknowledgement>based on H. Arp (1960) in <i>Astronomical J.</i>, 65,
                  426</ItemAcknowledgement>
              </ItemRights>
            </SourceReference>
            <Description/>
          </Figure>
          <!--<Paragraph>Type Ia supernova</Paragraph>-->
          <Paragraph>Another type of star that can be recognised in other galaxies is a <i>Type Ia
              supernova</i>. What happens is this: when a medium-sized star, such as the Sun,
            approaches the end of its active life, it shrinks down to a small star called a
            &#x2018;white dwarf&#x2019;. If the white dwarf happens to belong to a binary system of
            two stars, it can, from time to time, capture material from the atmosphere of its
            companion, so increasing its own mass. But this is a process that cannot continue
            indefinitely. The maximum mass for a white dwarf is 1.4 solar masses; anything above
            that limit and its inner forces cannot resist the inward pull of gravity, and the star
            has to collapse down to the next stable form (called a &#x2018;neutron star&#x2019;).
            Thus, the white dwarf in the binary system can capture material only up to this limiting
            mass. Once it exceeds this limit, the collapse occurs with the excess energy emitted as
            an explosion &#x2013; the Type Ia supernova. Because white dwarfs are always of the same
            limiting mass when this happens, the explosions are similar, yielding essentially the
            same spectrum and variation of light intensity over time. (It is these characteristics
            that allow the Type Ia supernovae to be distinguished from other types.) Why they are
            important in the present context is that, to within &#xB1;30%, they have the same
            luminosity. Taking into account that the variation in luminosity with time does show a
            difference in characteristic decay times, and these are correlated to somewhat different
            values of peak luminosity, allowance can be made for this, and the uncertainty spread in
            peak luminosity reduced to &#xB1;20%. This in turn leads to relative distances
            measurable to &#xB1;10%.</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>Type Ia supernovae provide us with standard lamps (or standard
              <i>explosions!</i>), that, at their peak, are 100 000 times brighter than a Cepheid,
            and are visible hundreds of times further away. Having established their luminosity by
            measuring the few that occur in galaxies for which the distance is already known from
            measurements on Cepheids, they can be used to extend the distance scale to very great
            distances.</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>This however still does not go far enough. Since normal stars cannot be
            resolved in the farther galaxies, the additional methods of estimating distance will
            have to be based on the properties of galaxies <i>as a whole</i>. We therefore interrupt
            the distance story to describe some properties of whole galaxies, showing first why they
            are important to cosmology, and then how they have led to new ways of measuring
            distance.</Paragraph>
          <!--<Paragraph>Objectives 1 and 3</Paragraph>-->
          <SAQ
            id="SAQ001_004">
            <Heading>Question 4</Heading>
            <Question>
              <Paragraph>Suppose an astronomer using a telescope of 2 m diameter has a detector
                whose limit of sensitivity is 3.2 &#xD7;10<sup>&#x2212;17</sup> W. Use <CrossRef
                  idref="FIG001_004">Figure 6</CrossRef> to deduce, for this instrument, the period
                of the faintest Cepheid variable that can be observed at a distance of
                  2&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>6</sup> ly [light years].</Paragraph>
              <Paragraph>(<i>Remember:</i> The value of a light-year in SI units is given on the <a
                  href="http://openlearn.open.ac.uk/file.php/3639/S357Datasheets.pdf"
                  target="_blank">data sheet</a>)</Paragraph>
            </Question>
            <Answer>
              <Paragraph>At 2&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>6</sup> ly, the fraction of light intercepted
                is:</Paragraph>
              <Paragraph><InlineEquation><Image
                    src="S357_1_ie002i.gif"/><Description/></InlineEquation></Paragraph>
              <Paragraph>The energy received from the faintest star is
                  3.2&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;17</sup> W.</Paragraph>
              <Paragraph>Therefore the output of the star must be</Paragraph>
              <Equation
                id="UEQN001_0030"><Image
                  src="S357_1_ue030i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
              <Paragraph>From <CrossRef
                  idref="FIG001_004">Figure 6</CrossRef>(b), the corresponding period of the Cepheid
                variable is about 3 days.</Paragraph>
            </Answer>
          </SAQ>
          <!--<Paragraph>cluster of galaxies</Paragraph>-->
        </SubSection>
        <SubSection
          id="SEC003_002">
          <Title>3.2 Some general properties of galaxies</Title>
          <Paragraph>Firstly, we note that galaxies tend to occur in clusters rather than singly.
            The mutual gravitational attraction of galaxies naturally tends to hold them on paths
            that remain close to each other. Typically a cluster contains tens or hundreds of
            galaxies. There are, however, large clusters with thousands of galaxies, and there are
            some solitary galaxies. Our own Galaxy is a member of a smallish cluster of about 36
            galaxies called the Local Group (see <CrossRef
              idref="FIG001_005">Figure 7</CrossRef>). A typical cluster of moderate size is shown
            in <CrossRef
              idref="FIG001_006">Figure 8</CrossRef>.</Paragraph>
          <Figure
            id="FIG001_005"><Image
              id="FIG001_005"
              src="S357_1_005i.jpg"/>
            <Caption>
              <b>Figure 7</b>: Our cluster of galaxies, called the Local Group. M31, the Andromeda
              galaxy, can be seen with binoculars. The Large Magellanic Cloud is one of our nearest
              neighbours, and is visible to the naked eye from the Southern Hemisphere</Caption>
            <SourceReference>from <i>Le Grand Atlas de l&#x2019;Astronomie</i>, Encyclopaedia
              Universalis editeur <ItemRights>
                <OwnerRef/>
                <ItemRef/>
                <ItemAcknowledgement>from <i>Le Grand Atlas de l&#x2019;Astronomie</i>,
                  Encyclopaedia Universalis editeur</ItemAcknowledgement>
              </ItemRights>
            </SourceReference>
            <Description/>
          </Figure>
          <Figure
            id="FIG001_006"><Image
              id="FIG001_006"
              src="S357_1_006i.jpg"/>
            <Caption>
              <b>Figure 8</b>: A cluster of galaxies whose position in the sky is behind the
              constellation of stars in our Galaxy which we call Hercules. This cluster is not
              visible to the naked eye &#x2013; not because it is too small but because it is too
              faint</Caption>
            <SourceReference>Hale Observatories <ItemRights>
                <OwnerRef/>
                <ItemRef/>
                <ItemAcknowledgement>Hale Observatories</ItemAcknowledgement>
              </ItemRights>
            </SourceReference>
            <Description/>
          </Figure>
          <Paragraph>How are the galaxy clusters distributed? Are they close enough to affect each
            other? If they are, then the motion of a given cluster would depend mostly on the
            distortion of spacetime caused by its nearest neighbours. Because the distances between
            clusters vary, this would correspond to a large spread in relative speeds. At the other
            extreme, if the clusters of galaxies were very far apart, then the attraction of
            neighbouring clusters would be negligible, and the motion would be dominated by the
            overall spacetime curvature due to the matter of the <i>whole</i> Universe &#x2013; a
            much simpler situation.</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph><!--As we shall see in Unit 15, -->In fact, galaxy clusters are loosely
            associated in superclusters. However, they are far enough apart for one to regard
            clusters as essentially independent (see <CrossRef
              idref="FIG001_007">Figure 9</CrossRef>). The fact that clusters are, in effect,
            independent of one another is of central importance to cosmology. It means that a
            cluster of galaxies can be taken as the basic &#x2018;particle&#x2019; of cosmological
            dynamics, and the motion of individual galaxies within a cluster can be ignored on the
            grand scale of cosmology. Thus, we conclude:</Paragraph>
          <Box
            id="BOX_GALAXYCLUSTERS">
            <Paragraph>Galaxy clusters are the basic test particles of cosmology, their motion
              following geodesic paths through spacetime.</Paragraph>
          </Box>
          <Figure
            id="FIG001_007"><Image
              id="FIG001_007"
              src="S357_1_007i.jpg"/>
            <Caption>
              <b>Figure 9</b>: A very schematic view of three clusters, showing typical diameters of
              galaxies (single dots) and clusters (groups of dots), and typical distances between
              clusters</Caption>
            <SourceReference>
              <ItemRights>
                <OwnerRef/>
                <ItemRef/>
                <ItemAcknowledgement/>
              </ItemRights>
            </SourceReference>
            <Description/>
          </Figure>
          <Paragraph>In other words, a galaxy cluster plays a similar role on the grand scale to
            that of a planet (e.g. Mercury) mapping out the local region of spacetime in the Solar
            System, or Newton's falling apple doing the same thing closer to the Earth's
            surface.</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>The next important property of galaxies is that there is a statistical
            predictability about their masses and luminosities. <CrossRef
              idref="FIG001_008">Figure 10</CrossRef> shows the proportion of galaxies having a
            given luminosity. It varies over quite a wide range, the distribution falling off
            steeply on the high-luminosity side. (Note that the luminosity is expressed in terms of
            (absolute) &#x2018;magnitudes&#x2019;, this being a parameter such that the <i>smaller
              or more negative</i> the value of the magnitude, the more luminous the object. This
            rather odd choice arises for historical reasons.) There are large numbers of the least
            luminous galaxies (shown by the rising curve on the left-hand side), but in practice
            these tend to be invisible in the more distant clusters which are of greater interest to
            cosmologists. No doubt it would have been easier for cosmology if galaxies had been more
            similar. However, because galaxies occur in clusters, one can at least use statistical
            methods. For instance, the distribution of luminosities is more or less the same for all
            clusters, resulting in the average luminosity of galaxies in a cluster being fairly
            standard even though the individual galaxies vary greatly. This statement assumes, of
            course, that we are dealing with galaxy clusters of the same age. As we have already
            pointed out, this might not be the case when observing galaxies at a great distance, and
            hence as they were some time in the distant past.</Paragraph>
          <Figure
            id="FIG001_008"><Image
              id="FIG001_008"
              src="S357_1_008i.jpg"/>
            <Caption>
              <b>Figure 10</b>: Number of galaxies per magnitude class per cubic megaparsec, as a
              function of absolute magnitude. Different symbols represent the results of different
              observers</Caption>
            <SourceReference>based on Erik Holmberg in E.M. and G.R. Burbidge (1975) <i>Galaxies and
                the Universe</i>, University of Chicago Press <ItemRights>
                <OwnerRef/>
                <ItemRef/>
                <ItemAcknowledgement>based on Erik Holmberg in E.M. and G.R. Burbidge (1975)
                    <i>Galaxies and the Universe</i>, University of Chicago
                  Press</ItemAcknowledgement>
              </ItemRights>
            </SourceReference>
            <Description/>
          </Figure>
        </SubSection>
        <SubSection
          id="SEC003_003">
          <Title>3.3 Extending the distance scale</Title>
          <Paragraph>Having reviewed some of the properties of galaxies, we are now in a position to
            return to the question of how we are to develop further our methods of measuring
            distance.</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>The various steps taken in determining larger distances from known smaller ones
            are often called &#x2018;rungs in the distance ladder&#x2019;. The process of
            constructing a rung has been:</Paragraph>
          <NumberedList>
            <ListItem>
              <Paragraph>Find a measurable quantity associated with a class of objects.</Paragraph>
            </ListItem>
            <ListItem>
              <Paragraph>Observe how the measurable quantity depends on distance for objects close
                enough to have had their distances measured by the method of a previous
                rung.</Paragraph>
            </ListItem>
            <ListItem>
              <Paragraph>Assume the same relationship holds for more distant objects of the same
                class, and hence calculate their distances.</Paragraph>
            </ListItem>
            <ListItem>
              <Paragraph>Return to step 1, with a new measurable quantity.</Paragraph>
            </ListItem>
          </NumberedList>
          <Paragraph>The classes of objects (and distance indicators) for the first four rungs of
            the distance ladder were:</Paragraph>
          <Table
            id="TBL002">
            <TableHead/>
            <TableBody><table><tr>
                  <td>Sun</td>
                  <td>(by radar ranging)</td>
                </tr><tr>
                  <td>Nearby stars in our Galaxy</td>
                  <td>(by triangulation)</td>
                </tr><tr>
                  <td>Our Galaxy and nearby galaxies</td>
                  <td>(using Cepheid variables)</td>
                </tr><tr>
                  <td>Nearby and somewhat further off galaxies</td>
                  <td> (using Type Ia supernovae)</td></tr>
              </table>
            </TableBody><SourceReference/></Table>
          <Paragraph>These distance indicators all depended on recognising a particular type of
              <i>star</i>. But, as was mentioned in <CrossRef
              idref="SEC003_001">Section 3.1</CrossRef>, individual stars can be resolved only in
            galaxies that are not too distant. For most galaxies, a method is needed which depends
            on recognising, or deducing, the luminosity of the galaxy as a whole. Although, as
            already noted, individual galaxies vary considerably in their luminosity, they occur in
            clusters. A simple rule which seems to work in practice is to assume that the
            third-brightest galaxy in all clusters has the same luminosity (a standard
              10<sup>37</sup> W lamp).</Paragraph>
          <!--<Figure id="FIG001_009"><Image id="FIG001_009" src="S357_1_009i.jpg"/>
<Caption>
<b>Figure 11</b>: Spiral galaxy M81 &#x0028;NGC 3031&#x0029;, taken with the 200-inch telescope at the Palomar Observatory in California. This galaxy, like our own, has tightly wound arms and a prominent bulge &#x0028;known as a nuclear bulge&#x0029;.</Caption>
<Description/>
</Figure>-->
          <Paragraph>An alternative method is to separate galaxies into different types, with the
            assumption, or at least the hope, that the types have characteristic luminosities. There
            are certainly generic differences between spiral galaxies (<CrossRef
              idref="FIG001_009">Figure 11</CrossRef>) and elliptical galaxies (<CrossRef
              idref="FIG001_010">Figure 12</CrossRef>). But it is also well established that there
            is a useful correlation between the luminosities of spiral galaxies and their rotation
            speeds, which can be determined from (radio) observations of Doppler
            broadening.</Paragraph>
          <!--<Paragraph>size of radio galaxies</Paragraph>-->
          <Figure
            id="FIG001_009"><Image
              id="FIG001_009"
              src="S357_1_009i.jpg"/>
            <Caption>
              <b>Figure 11</b>: Spiral galaxy M81 (NGC 3031), taken with the 200-inch telescope at
              the Palomar Observatory in California. This galaxy, like our own, has tightly wound
              arms and a prominent bulge (known as a nuclear bulge)</Caption>
            <SourceReference>Hale Observatories <ItemRights>
                <OwnerRef/>
                <ItemRef/>
                <ItemAcknowledgement>Hale Observatories</ItemAcknowledgement>
              </ItemRights>
            </SourceReference>
            <Description/>
          </Figure>
          <Figure
            id="FIG001_010"><Image
              id="FIG001_010"
              src="S357_1_010i.jpg"/>
            <Caption>
              <b>Figure 12</b>: M59 (NGC 4261), an elliptical galaxy about 19 Mly (i.e.
                1.9&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>7</sup> ly) away. Like all elliptical galaxies, M59 has
              no spiral arms</Caption>
            <SourceReference>NASA/IPAC Extragalactic Database (NED), Jet Propulsion Laboratory,
              California Institute of Technology <ItemRights>
                <OwnerRef/>
                <ItemRef/>
                <ItemAcknowledgement>NASA/IPAC Extragalactic Database (NED), Jet Propulsion
                  Laboratory, California Institute of Technology</ItemAcknowledgement>
              </ItemRights>
            </SourceReference>
            <Description/>
          </Figure>
          <Paragraph>Another method exploits the fact that some types of <i>radio galaxy</i>
            (so-called because they are strong emitters at radio frequencies) are fairly uniform in
              <i>size</i>, and radio interferometers can resolve very small angular separations
            &#x2013; a thousand times smaller than those resolved by optical telescopes. The
            apparent size leads to an estimate of the distance of the galaxy. Because some radio
            galaxies are also visible at optical wavelengths, the optical and radio distance scales
            can be intercalibrated.</Paragraph>
          <!--<Paragraph>Type II supernova</Paragraph>-->
          <Paragraph>Yet another method should also be mentioned. It involves the behaviour of a
            single star in a galaxy, though one too distant to be resolved. We have already
            mentioned Type Ia supernovae. These are events that occur when a white dwarf (which
            itself originally resulted from the last stages in the active life of a medium-sized
            star) captures material from a companion star, and undergoes collapse to a neutron star.
            If instead of a medium-sized star one begins with a very massive star, then at the end
            of its active life it catastrophically collapses <i>directly</i> to a neutron star or
            black hole. This leads to a gigantic explosion even more energetic than a Type Ia
            supernova; it is called a <i>Type II supernova</i>. These explosions are bright enough
            to be visible at large distances &#x2013; in some cases briefly shining more brightly
            than all the other stars of the galaxy put together. Unfortunately they are rather rare,
            occurring only once every hundred years or so in a typical galaxy. A Type II supernova
            explosion causes a spherical shell of hot gas to expand out of the star at high speed
            &#x2013; thousands of kilometres per second. The spectral lines in the observed light
            from this shell (mostly from hydrogen and therefore easily identified) are
              <i>blueshifted</i> by its velocity towards us. Knowing this velocity from the amount
            of blueshift, the increase in size of the shell, month by month, can be calculated. Thus
            the shell is a source of known size, even though this cannot be resolved from an
            observed angular width. The temperature can be found from the overall shape of the
            continuous spectrum between the spectral lines. Knowing both the size and temperature of
            the shell, its total light output (that is, its luminosity) can be found. From this and
            the observed flux this and the observed flux density, the distance can be calculated
            using the inverse square law.</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>Remember, luminosity&#xA0;=&#xA0;4<InlineEquation><Image
                src="pi.gif"/><Description/></InlineEquation><i>r</i><sup>2</sup>&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;flux
            density, where <i>r</i> is the distance.</Paragraph>
          <Figure
            id="FIG001_011"><Image
              id="FIG001_011"
              src="S357_1_011i.jpg"/>
            <Caption>
              <b>Figure 13</b>: NGC 5457, a spiral galaxy in our Local Group, having looser arms and
              a far less noticeable nuclear bulge than the galaxy shown in Figure 11</Caption>
            <SourceReference>Hale Observatories <ItemRights>
                <OwnerRef/>
                <ItemRef/>
                <ItemAcknowledgement>Hale Observatories</ItemAcknowledgement>
              </ItemRights>
            </SourceReference>
            <Description/>
          </Figure>
          <SAQ
            id="SAQ001_005">
            <Heading>Question 5</Heading>
            <Question>
              <!--<Paragraph>Objective 3</Paragraph>-->
              <Paragraph>Comment on the truth or otherwise of the following statements:</Paragraph>
              <Paragraph>(i) Averaging statistically over the luminosities of its constituent
                galaxies, each cluster of galaxies can be assumed to have the same overall
                luminosity.</Paragraph>
              <Paragraph>(ii) The distance-measuring method involving Type II supernovae relies on
                the fact that the shell of material thrown out by the explosion greatly exceeds the
                parent star in size, to the extent that it can be optically resolved.</Paragraph>
            </Question>
            <Answer>
              <Paragraph>Both statements are incorrect.</Paragraph>
              <Paragraph><b>(i)</b> The overall luminosity of a cluster cannot be used as a standard
                lamp because, as stated in <CrossRef
                  idref="SEC003_002">Section 3.2</CrossRef>, clusters can vary enormously in size
                from thousands of galaxies to a single galaxy. All one can say is that the
                luminosity of a <i>typical</i> galaxy in that cluster (averaged over a number of the
                galaxies it contains) is the same for each cluster.</Paragraph>
              <Paragraph><b>(ii)</b> The shell thrown out from the supernova cannot be resolved
                optically. Instead, the radius of the fireball at a given moment is
                  <i>calculated</i> from the estimated speed of the ejected material and the time
                that has elapsed since the explosion. The colour (temperature) determines the light
                output per unit area. Hence, knowing the surface area from the radius, one arrives
                at an estimate of the luminosity of the supernova at the given time after the
                explosion. This luminosity is then compared to the measured flux density to obtain
                the distance to the star.</Paragraph>
            </Answer>
          </SAQ>
        </SubSection></Section>
      <Section
        id="SEC004">
        <Title>4 The variation of redshift with distance</Title>
        <SubSection
          id="SEC004_001">
          <Title>4.1 Hubble's discoveries</Title>
          <Paragraph>In this section, we bring together two important features of galaxies &#x2013;
            their redshifts and their distances.</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>This crucial development owes its origins to Edwin Hubble. His pioneering work
            in 1923 first led to the confirmation that certain of the fuzzy patches in the sky,
            loosely called &#x2018;nebulae&#x2019;, were in fact galaxies like our own.</Paragraph>
          <Figure
            id="FIG001_012"><Image
              id="FIG001_012"
              src="S357_1_012i.jpg"/>
            <Caption>
              <b>Figure 14</b>: (a) Nebula NGC 6514, a cloud of gas and dust in our own Galaxy; (b)
              Hubble showed that objects like M31 (NGC 224, now called the Andromeda galaxy) were
              galaxies like our own, and they ceased to be called nebulae. The two large bright
              patches near M31 are satellite galaxies, NGC 205 and NGC 221</Caption>
            <SourceReference>(a) courtesy of Uppsala University; (b) Hale Observatories <ItemRights>
                <OwnerRef/>
                <ItemRef/>
                <ItemAcknowledgement>(a) courtesy of Uppsala University; (b) Hale
                  Observatories</ItemAcknowledgement>
              </ItemRights>
            </SourceReference>
            <Description/>
          </Figure>
          <!--<Paragraph>(b) Hubble showed that objects like M31 (NGC 224, now called the Andromeda galaxy) were galaxies like our own, and they ceased to be called nebulae. The two large bright patches near M31 are satellite galaxies, NGC 205 and NGC 221.</Paragraph>-->
          <Paragraph>It was immediately realised that the Universe was enormously bigger than had
            previously been thought. Also the number of galaxies was large. In fact, it is now known
            that the number of galaxies accessible to our telescopes is comparable with the number
            of stars in our Galaxy &#x2013; about 100 billion (i.e. 10<sup>11</sup>).</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>A second significant discovery made by Hubble concerned the spectra of
            galaxies, nearly all of which are redshifted. This redshift was a systematic shift of
              <i>all</i> the lines to the red end of the spectrum (it was discovered by another US
            astronomer, Vesto Slipher). Using his measurements of distance, Hubble showed that the
              <i>redshift increased with distance</i>. As far as he could tell, the redshift of a
            galaxy was proportional to its distance.</Paragraph>
          <Figure
            id="FIG001_013"><Image
              id="FIG001_013"
              src="S357_1_013i.jpg"/>
            <Caption>
              <b>Figure 15</b>: The redshift&#x2013;distance relationship for galaxies, as plotted
              by Hubble in 1929. The solid line represents the relationship inferred from individual
              galaxies (solid circles), the dashed line the relationship when the galaxies are
              combined into groups (open circles). Hubble's distance scale has been omitted since it
              is now known that it was in error.</Caption>
            <SourceReference>based on E. P. Hubble (1929) in <i>Proc. Nat. Acad. Sci.</i>, 15, 168
                <ItemRights>
                <OwnerRef/>
                <ItemRef/>
                <ItemAcknowledgement>based on E. P. Hubble (1929) in <i>Proc. Nat. Acad. Sci.</i>,
                  15, 168</ItemAcknowledgement>
              </ItemRights>
            </SourceReference>
            <Description/>
          </Figure>
          <Paragraph>Hubble's original measurements, shown in <CrossRef
              idref="FIG001_013">Figure 15</CrossRef>, exhibited a large scatter about a straight
            line. This was partly due to the inevitable observational uncertainties, especially in
            distance measurements. But even if one were able to remove the observational
            uncertainties, there would still have been a considerable scatter about a straight line.
            This comes from the fact that most of the galaxies Hubble looked at were members of
            clusters, and each was moving about within its cluster. Because the galaxies were rather
            close to us, the speeds associated with this random motion were comparable to the
            recessional speed Hubble was trying to measure. Sometimes the motion of the galaxy
            relative to the cluster centre was directed towards us (giving a blueshift component),
            sometimes away from us (adding a further redshift component). If the structure of the
            cluster were well enough known, these effects could, in principle, be estimated and a
            correction applied. Allowance must also be made for small gravitational redshifts (see <CrossRef
              idref="SAQ001_002">Question 2</CrossRef>). Finally, the motion of the Earth with
            respect to our Local Group must be subtracted. (This will be discussed in <CrossRef
              idref="SEC006_002_004">Section 6.2.4</CrossRef>.) Suppose that <i>all</i> these
            corrections could be perfectly made in all cases. Then a redshift (<i>z</i>) against
            distance (<i>r</i>) plot would, as far as we know, appear as in <CrossRef
              idref="FIG001_014">Figure 16</CrossRef>.</Paragraph>
          <!--<Paragraph>cosmological redshift</Paragraph>-->
          <Figure
            id="FIG001_014"><Image
              id="FIG001_014"
              src="S357_1_014i.jpg"/>
            <Caption>
              <b>Figure 16</b>: An idealised Hubble diagram with all sources of scatter
              removed</Caption>
            <Description/>
          </Figure>
          <Paragraph>The straight line in <CrossRef
              idref="FIG001_014">Figure 16</CrossRef> would represent the underlying cosmological
            redshift. Thus, for this <i>cosmological redshift</i>, we have</Paragraph>
          <Equation
            id="EQN000_003"><Image
              src="S357_1_e003i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
          <!--<Paragraph>Recall that the suffix 0 refers to the value at the <i>present</i> time, while the suffix 1 refers to the value at the <i>earlier</i> time.</Paragraph>-->
          <!--<Paragraph>Hubble&#x0027;s law</Paragraph>-->
          <!--<Paragraph>Hubble parameter, <i>H</i></Paragraph>-->
          <Paragraph>Interpreting the observed redshift as a Doppler shift implies that each galaxy
            is receding at a speed proportional to its distance from us. To see this, consider the
            Doppler shift formula
            <!--given in Equation 5 of Unit 6 (setting <i>f</i>&#x00A0;=&#x00A0;<i>f</i><sub>1</sub> and <i>f</i>&#x2032;&#x00A0;=&#x00A0;<i>f</i><sub>0</sub>), -->and
            the relationship between redshift, wavelength change and frequency shift given in the
            answer to <CrossRef
              idref="SAQ001_003">Question 3</CrossRef>
            <!--of this unit-->. It follows that the redshift, <i>z</i>, is given by</Paragraph>
          <Equation
            id="EQN000_004"><Image
              src="S357_1_e004i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
          <Paragraph>Hence, Equations 3 and 4 together imply that</Paragraph>
          <Equation
            id="EQN000_005"><Image
              src="S357_1_e005i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
          <Paragraph>This provides the basis for one of the common ways of writing <i>Hubble's
              law</i>,</Paragraph>
          <Equation
            id="EQN000_006"><Image
              src="S357_1_e006i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
          <Paragraph>The factor of proportionality, <i>H</i>, is sometimes called the <i>Hubble
              constant</i>. But the term <i>parameter</i> is perhaps preferable since the word
            &#x2018;constant&#x2019; might lead one to think that it should remain constant in time
            &#x2013; instead of being a constant of proportionality between two variables <i>as
              those variables are at a particular point in time. H</i> must, we now realise, vary
            slowly with time.</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>If the speed of recession is proportional to distance, this implies <i>all</i>
            distances between galaxies are increasing at the same rate. Not only do all clusters of
            galaxies appear to be receding from us here on Earth, they would appear to be receding
            in exactly the same manner from whatever vantage point an observer adopted.</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>Hubble's work has been continued, refined, and extended to much more distant
            and fainter galaxies.</Paragraph>
          <!--<Paragraph>Objectives 4 and 5</Paragraph>-->
          <SAQ
            id="SAQ001_006">
            <Heading>Question 6</Heading>
            <Question>
              <Paragraph>Taking typical intercluster distances to be approximately
                  2&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>8</sup> ly, and the value of <i>H</i> to be about
                  2&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;18</sup> s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>, estimate the
                minimum <i>z</i> value that can reliably be ascribed to the expansion of the
                Universe. Compare this with the redshifts measured by Hubble in <CrossRef
                  idref="FIG001_013">Figure 15</CrossRef>.</Paragraph>
            </Question>
            <Answer>
              <Paragraph>To get a redshift that can confidently be regarded as due to expansion, we
                must look to another cluster.</Paragraph>
              <Paragraph>Intercluster distances are approximately</Paragraph>
              <Equation
                id="UEQN001_0031"><Image
                  src="S357_1_ue031i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
              <Paragraph>The Hubble constant is about 2&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;18</sup>
                  s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup></Paragraph>
              <Paragraph>Hence the cosmological redshift of a neighbouring cluster is</Paragraph>
              <Equation
                id="UEQN001_0032"><Image
                  src="S357_1_ue032i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
              <Paragraph>Compare this with <CrossRef
                  idref="FIG001_013">Figure 15</CrossRef> &#x2013; Hubble was not able to look far
                enough!</Paragraph>
            </Answer>
          </SAQ>
          <Paragraph>Since it is hard to measure the distance to a far-off galaxy, it is not
            surprising that there has been a good deal of controversy about the reliability of
            distance estimates. The redshift measurements are much easier to make and are more
            direct, so there has been much less uncertainty over them. Nevertheless, it is useful to
            have a check, and this has been provided by radio astronomers measuring the redshift of
            lines in the radio spectrum, such as that due to the emission of hydrogen at a
            wavelength of 21 cm. This confirms that the redshift is the same over a large range of
            frequencies.</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>Based on a range of recent results, the value of <i>H</i> is currently reckoned
            to be 2.3&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;18</sup> s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>, with an
            observational uncertainty of about 10%.</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>Hubble, who interpreted redshifts in terms of recessional velocities, would
            quote this as 23 km s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> for every million light-years of distance of a
            galaxy. Estimates of <i>H</i> are often quoted in terms of km s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>
              Mpc<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>. In these units, <i>H</i> is about 70 km s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>
              Mpc<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>.</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>It has become common usage to write
            <i>H</i>&#xA0;=&#xA0;<i>h</i>&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;100 km s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>
              Mpc<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>, in which case <i>h</i> currently has a best estimate of
            0.7.</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>We end this section with a more up-to-date version of the Hubble diagram (<CrossRef
              idref="FIG001_015">Figure 17</CrossRef>) for some galaxies and clusters of
            galaxies.</Paragraph>
          <Figure
            id="FIG001_015"><Image
              id="FIG001_015"
              src="S357_1_015i.jpg"/>
            <Caption>
              <b>Figure 17</b>: A plot of redshift against distance for a selection of galaxies and
              clusters of galaxies</Caption>
            <SourceReference>adapted from A. Sandage (1970) <i>Physics Today</i>, vol. 34, February
              1970, American Institute of Physics <ItemRights>
                <OwnerRef/>
                <ItemRef/>
                <ItemAcknowledgement>adapted from A. Sandage (1970) <i>Physics Today</i>, vol. 34,
                  February 1970, American Institute of Physics</ItemAcknowledgement>
              </ItemRights>
            </SourceReference>
            <Description/>
          </Figure>
          <!--<Paragraph><i>Objectives 4 and 5</i></Paragraph>-->
          <SAQ
            id="SAQ001_007">
            <Heading>Question 7</Heading>
            <Question>
              <Paragraph>Use the sum of the shifts calculated for the star specified in <CrossRef
                  idref="SAQ001_002">Question 2</CrossRef> to give an estimate of the uncertainty in
                the cosmological redshift <i>z</i> for a star in a galaxy at
                  4&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>6</sup> ly from us. (This may be an overestimate because
                the centre of a line can be estimated quite well even if the line is fuzzy. However,
                in a real galactic spectrum there will be a further component of broadening due to
                galactic rotation.)</Paragraph>
            </Question>
            <Answer>
              <Paragraph>From <CrossRef
                  idref="SAQ001_002">Question 2</CrossRef>(b), parts (ii) and (iii), the minimum
                width of the lines is</Paragraph>
              <Equation
                id="UEQN001_0033"><Image
                  src="S357_1_ue033i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
              <Paragraph>with a systematic fractional shift of about
                  &#x2212;2&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;6</sup> (<CrossRef
                  idref="SAQ001_002">Question 2</CrossRef>(b), (i)). Thus the contributions to
                  &#x394;<i>f</i>/<i>f</i> due to turbulence, rotation and gravitational redshift
                vary between (+20 + 7 &#x2212; 2)&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;6</sup> and
                (&#x2212;20 &#x2013; 7 &#x2013; 2)&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;6</sup>. This
                gives an error of about &#xB1;3&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;5</sup>. For a
                galaxy at 4&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>6</sup> ly
                  (&#x2248;4&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>6</sup>&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>16</sup> m),
                the expected cosmological redshift is</Paragraph>
              <Equation
                id="UEQN001_0034"><Image
                  src="S357_1_ue034i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
              <Paragraph>Thus the line-broadening effects are approximately a fraction</Paragraph>
              <Equation
                id="UEQN001_0035"><Image
                  src="S357_1_ue035i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
              <Paragraph>of the expected cosmological shift.</Paragraph>
              <Paragraph>Notice that a distance of 4&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>6</sup> ly corresponds
                to nearby galaxies in our Local Group and the relative uncertainties in redshift
                will <i>decrease</i> with distance. They are commonly less than 1%. The
                uncertainties in distance, however, will increase with distance, because less
                accurate estimation procedures have to be used. Also note that a distance of
                  4&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>6</sup> ly may be unreasonably small for cosmological
                consideration.</Paragraph>
            </Answer>
          </SAQ>
          <!--<Paragraph><i>Objective 4</i></Paragraph>-->
          <SAQ
            id="SAQ001_008">
            <Heading>Question 8</Heading>
            <Question>
              <Paragraph>By taking appropriate readings off the graph of <CrossRef
                  idref="FIG001_015">Figure 17</CrossRef>, estimate the value of the Hubble
                constant, <i>H</i>, indicated by this set of data.</Paragraph>
            </Question>
            <Answer>
              <Paragraph>One can use any pair of points on the straight line graph that has been
                drawn, but to minimise reading errors we take the extreme points. The difference in
                  <i>z</i> is 1.0000 &#x2212; 0.0025&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.9975. The difference in distance,
                  <i>r</i>, is 4000&#xA0;&#x2212;&#xA0;10&#xA0;=&#xA0;3990&#xA0;Mpc.</Paragraph>
              <Paragraph>Thus</Paragraph>
              <Equation
                id="UEQN001_0036"><Image
                  src="S357_1_ue036i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
              <Paragraph>But</Paragraph>
              <Equation
                id="UEQN001_0037"><Image
                  src="S357_1_ue037i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
              <Paragraph>So</Paragraph>
              <Equation
                id="UEQN001_0038"><Image
                  src="S357_1_ue038i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
            </Answer>
          </SAQ>
        </SubSection>
        <SubSection
          id="SEC004_002">
          <Title>4.2 Evidence for a big bang</Title>
          <Paragraph>Having interpreted the redshift as indicating a recessional speed proportional
            to distance, one may extrapolate into the future to predict how the positions of the
            galaxies will evolve with time. One can also run the sequence backwards, so to speak, to
            discuss what their positions were in the past. Clearly, at former times the galaxies
            were closer to each other.</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>But not only that. Because of the proportional relationship between speed and
            distance (Equation 6), at a certain time in the past, all the matter of the Universe
            must have been together at a point of extraordinarily high density. It was from this
            condition that it subsequently expanded giving the matter of the Universe its
            present-day distribution. This is our first indication that the history of the Universe
            featured an explosive event.</Paragraph>
          <!--<Paragraph>big bang</Paragraph>-->
          <Paragraph>This has become known as the <i>big bang</i>. It is believed to have marked the
            beginning of the Universe. (Actually the phrase &#x2018;big bang&#x2019; is used in two
            ways: (i) to denote the instant at which cosmic expansion begins; and (ii) to refer to
            that instant plus the sequence of events immediately following. It is usually clear from
            the context which of these meanings is intended.)</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>It is possible to deduce much about the nature of the big bang and how long ago
            it took place &#x2013; in other words, how old the Universe is. But we need to be sure
            that there really <i>was</i> a big bang. What we seek is evidence that is independent of
            the observation of moving galaxies. The remainder of this unit is devoted to describing
            just such confirmatory observations. Not only do they add to our confidence that the
            Universe did indeed have a definite beginning, they also inform us that the beginning
            was exceedingly violent &#x2013; the big bang was hot. This indication assumes great
            importance when we seek to get some understanding of the varying types of process that
            must have been taking place during the initial stages of expansion &#x2013; during the
            first years, minutes, even fractions of a second after the instant of the big
            bang.</Paragraph>
        </SubSection></Section>
      <Section
        id="SEC005">
        <Title>5 The microwave background radiation</Title>
        <SubSection
          id="SEC005_001">
          <Title>5.1 A second major discovery</Title>
          <Paragraph>In the introduction to this unit, we said that there were three pillars of
            evidence for the big bang. We now turn to the second. It rests on a discovery that ranks
            in importance with that of Hubble's law. It came about when observations in a new region
            of the electromagnetic spectrum &#x2013; the microwave region &#x2013; became possible.
            This was due to the invention of new detectors, working at frequencies as high as 30 000
            MHz. In 1965, two Bell Telephone scientists, A. Penzias and R. Wilson, were
            investigating the radio noise found at wavelengths between a few millimetres and a few
            centimetres. These wavelengths were, at the time, a relatively untapped field for
            communications. (They are now very useful for satellites because even small antennae
            give narrow beams at these wavelengths. Penzias and Wilson were working on the
            Telstar/Echo satellite project at that time.)</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>They found that, once all known sources of noise had been accounted for, they
            were left with a residual signal which was coming equally from all directions. It was
            soon realised that because of this isotropy, it could not originate on the Earth, or in
            the Solar System. Nor could it be coming even from the Galaxy &#x2013; the Galaxy being
            a thin disc, with us not at its centre.</Paragraph>
          <!--<Paragraph>Objective 8</Paragraph>-->
          <SAQ
            id="SAQ001_009">
            <Heading>Question 9</Heading>
            <Question>
              <Paragraph>Consider our Galaxy to be a uniform disc which is generating radio waves
                uniformly throughout its volume (<CrossRef
                  idref="FIG001_016">Figure 19</CrossRef>). Assume for the purposes of this question
                that all other radio sources are negligible. Also assume that the Earth is in the
                central plane of the disc but off centre (nearer the edge than the centre) and that
                it is at rest in the Galaxy. <i>Sketch</i> graphs showing the way the signal picked
                up by a radio telescope on Earth will vary when the telescope rotates:</Paragraph>
              <!--<NumberedList>
<ListItem>--><Paragraph>(a) in the plane of the
                Galaxy;</Paragraph><!--</ListItem>
<ListItem>--><Paragraph>(b) in a plane
                perpendicular to the Galaxy.</Paragraph><!--</ListItem>
</NumberedList>-->
              <Figure
                id="FIG001_016"><Image
                  id="FIG001_016"
                  src="S357_1_016i.jpg"/>
                <Caption>
                  <b>Figure 19</b>: The Earth inside the Galaxy, shown schematically as a
                  disc</Caption>
                <Description/>
              </Figure>
            </Question>
            <Answer>
              <Paragraph><b>(a)</b> If <i>&#x3C6;</i> is the angle between the direction of the
                telescope and the line from the centre of the Galaxy to the telescope, with
                  <i>&#x3C6;</i>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0 corresponding to looking directly away from the
                centre of the Galaxy, then, if the telescope is swept round in the plane of the
                Galaxy, the variation of intensity <i>W</i> of radio waves with &#x3C6; will be that
                shown in <CrossRef
                  idref="FIG001_034">Figure 18</CrossRef>(a).</Paragraph>
              <Paragraph><b>(b)</b> If <i>&#x3B8;</i> is the angle between the direction of the
                telescope and a line drawn perpendicular to the plane of the Galaxy at the
                telescope, with <i>&#x3B8;</i>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0 corresponding to looking directly
                &#x2018;upwards&#x2019; through the disc, then the variation of intensity <i>W</i>
                of radio waves with <i>&#x3B8;</i> will be as shown in <CrossRef
                  idref="FIG001_034">Figure 18</CrossRef> (b).</Paragraph>
              <Figure
                id="FIG001_034"><Image
                  id="FIG001_034"
                  src="S357_1_034i.jpg"/>
                <Caption>
                  <b>Figure 18</b>: Variation of intensity of radio waves with angle (a) in the
                  plane of the Galaxy, and (b) in a plane perpendicular to the Galaxy</Caption>
                <Description/>
              </Figure>
            </Answer>
          </SAQ>
          <Paragraph>Having separated out these other sources of background noise, it was concluded
            that the isotropic component had to be of cosmic origin. It is called the <i>cosmic
              microwave background radiation</i>.</Paragraph>
          <!--<Paragraph>cosmic microwave background radiation</Paragraph>-->
          <Paragraph><CrossRef
              idref="FIG001_017">Figure 20</CrossRef>(a) shows how complicated the overall microwave
            spectrum is, due largely to a set of lines generated in the Earth's atmosphere. <CrossRef
              idref="FIG001_017">Figure 20</CrossRef>(b) focuses on the region at the left-hand side
            of <CrossRef
              idref="FIG001_017">Figure 20</CrossRef>(a). This region is of interest because it is
            at lower frequencies than most of the atmospheric lines. The atmospheric interference
            varies with the thickness of the atmosphere, and hence with the angle of observation.
            This noise can therefore be separated out from the cosmic signal in which we are
            interested. <CrossRef
              idref="FIG001_017">Figure 20</CrossRef>(b) shows the microwave spectrum after
            correcting for the effects of the atmosphere.</Paragraph>
          <Figure
            id="FIG001_017"><Image
              id="FIG001_017"
              src="S357_1_017i.jpg"/>
            <Caption>
              <b>Figure 20</b>: (a) The overall ground-based microwave spectrum. (b) Ground-based
              measurements by Penzias and Wilson, and by other observers, of the microwave intensity
              at various frequencies; an enlargement of the spectrum shown at the left-hand side of
              (a), corrected to remove the effects of the atmosphere. The shaded area represents the
              limits given by measurements made with a detector that covered a wide band of
              frequencies. (The solid line shows a thermal spectrum corresponding to a temperature
              of 2.8 K. The term &#x2018;thermal spectrum&#x2019; is explained a little later in the
              text.)</Caption>
            <SourceReference>(a) based on D.P. Woody <i>et al.</i> (1975) in <i>Phys. Rev.
              Lett.</i>, 34, 1036&#x2013;9; (b) based on R.A. Muller (1978) in <i>Scientific
                American</i>, 238, 64&#x2013;74 <ItemRights>
                <OwnerRef/>
                <ItemRef/>
                <ItemAcknowledgement>(a) based on D.P. Woody <i>et al.</i> (1975) in <i>Phys. Rev.
                    Lett.</i>, 34, 1036&#x2013;9; (b) based on R.A. Muller (1978) in <i>Scientific
                    American</i>, 238, 64&#x2013;74</ItemAcknowledgement>
              </ItemRights>
            </SourceReference>
            <Description/>
          </Figure>
          <Paragraph>In 1989, the COBE satellite was launched. It was able to make measurements from
            above the Earth's atmosphere and was therefore not subject to some of the problems
            encountered by Penzias and Wilson, and by other ground-based observers. However, a major
            contaminant &#x2013; radiation originating from within the Galaxy &#x2013; remained. The
            COBE results, after correction for this effect, are shown in <CrossRef
              idref="FIG001_018">Figure 21</CrossRef>.</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>The shape revealed by this closer look is identical to that found for the
            spectrum inside a hot cavity &#x2013; for example the spectrum in an oven or furnace (<CrossRef
              idref="FIG001_019">Figure 22</CrossRef>). It is called a &#x2018;black body&#x2019;
            spectrum (because it is that which is given out by an idealised heated black surface),
            or simply a <i>&#x2018;thermal&#x2019; spectrum</i>.</Paragraph>
          <!--<Paragraph>thermal spectrum</Paragraph>-->
          <Figure
            id="FIG001_018"><Image
              id="FIG001_018"
              src="S357_1_018i.jpg"/>
            <Caption>
              <b>Figure 21</b>: Data on the microwave background radiation taken by the COBE
              satellite. The curve through the data points is that of a thermal spectrum of 2.73 K.
              Note that Figure 20(b) had a logarithmic frequency scale, while this one is
              linear</Caption>
            <SourceReference>courtesy of NASA/CSFC and COBE Science Working Group <ItemRights>
                <OwnerRef/>
                <ItemRef/>
                <ItemAcknowledgement>courtesy of NASA/CSFC and COBE Science Working
                  Group</ItemAcknowledgement>
              </ItemRights>
            </SourceReference>
            <Description/>
          </Figure>
          <Figure
            id="FIG001_019"><Image
              id="FIG001_019"
              src="S357_1_019i.jpg"/>
            <Caption>
              <b>Figure 22</b>: Thermal spectra for various temperatures, <i>T</i>, based on
              laboratory measurements of relative intensity, <i>W</i>, of radiation with frequency
                <i>f</i></Caption>
            <Description/>
          </Figure>
          <Paragraph>One of the basic features of thermal radiation is that, regardless of the
            temperature of the surface or enclosure generating it, the <i>shape</i> of the spectrum
            is always the same. The <i>peak</i> of the spectrum moves up to higher frequencies as
            the temperature rises (it might glow red hot or white hot). But the basic shape remains
            the same. What this means is that if the spectra for two different temperatures are
            drawn on two graphs, we can always choose scales &#x2013; linear but different &#x2013;
            so that the graphs can be superimposed (<CrossRef
              idref="FIG001_020">Figures 23</CrossRef> and <CrossRef
              idref="FIG001_021">24</CrossRef>). This single, characteristic shape arises from, and
            is an indicator of, the equilibrium conditions inside the oven. The rescaling in <CrossRef
              idref="FIG001_020">Figure 23</CrossRef> works <i>only</i> for thermal spectra, and so
            is a true indicator of equilibrium.</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>As an example of the opposite extreme, take the line spectra from a hydrogen
            lamp and a sodium lamp. No amount of rescaling would fit these two together; they are
            quite distinct.</Paragraph>
          <Figure
            id="FIG001_020"><Image
              id="FIG001_020"
              src="S357_1_020i.jpg"/>
            <Caption>
              <b>Figure 23</b>: What is meant by the shapes of thermal spectra being independent of
              temperature: (a) is the measured spectrum at 998 K (from Figure 22); (b) is obtained
              from (a) by expanding the vertical scale by a factor of
                (1646&#xFEFF;/&#xFEFF;998)&#xFEFF;<sup>3</sup>; (c) is obtained from (b) by
              expanding the horizontal scale by a factor of (1646/998); (d) is the measured spectrum
              at 1646 K (from Figure 22) plotted using the same scales as those in (a), and is the
              same curve as (c).</Caption>
            <Description/>
          </Figure>
          <Figure
            id="FIG001_021"><Image
              id="FIG001_021"
              src="S357_1_021i.jpg"/>
            <Caption>
              <b>Figure 24</b>: As suggested by Figure 23, a plot of <i>W/T</i><sup>3</sup> as a
              function of <i>f/T</i> is a single curve, for all temperatures; that is, if
                <i>W/T</i><sup>3</sup> is plotted against <i>f</i>/<i>T</i> for a number of
              frequencies and temperatures, the plotted points for all frequencies and temperatures
              lie on one and the same curve</Caption>
            <Description/>
          </Figure>
          <!--<Paragraph>&#x0028;a&#x0029; is the measured spectrum at 998 K &#x0028;from <CrossRef idref="FIG001_019">Figure 22</CrossRef>&#x0029;;</Paragraph>

<Paragraph>&#x0028;b&#x0029; is obtained from &#x0028;a&#x0029; by expanding the vertical scale by a factor of &#x0028;1646&#x002F;998&#x0029;<sup>3</sup>;</Paragraph>

<Paragraph>&#x0028;c&#x0029; is obtained from &#x0028;b&#x0029; by expanding the horizontal scale by a factor of</Paragraph>

<Paragraph>&#x0028;1646&#x002F;998&#x0029;;</Paragraph>

<Paragraph>&#x0028;d&#x0029; is the measured spectrum at 1646 K &#x0028;from <CrossRef idref="FIG001_019">Figure 22</CrossRef>&#x0029; plotted using the same scales as those in &#x0028;a&#x0029;, and is the same curve as &#x0028;c&#x0029;.</Paragraph>-->
          <Paragraph>Since the cosmic microwave spectrum has a thermal shape; the conclusion is that
            it was generated in equilibrium conditions &#x2013; in some sort of cavity. But the
            radiation fills the Universe: the &#x2018;cavity&#x2019; is the Universe itself, a
            cavity with no walls.</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>The word &#x2018;equilibrium&#x2019; is used here with some reservations. The
            Universe has not reached overall equilibrium, and strictly speaking never will. This is
            because of the expansion of the Universe. We saw in <CrossRef
              idref="SEC004_001">Section 4.1</CrossRef> how the wavelength of light from distant
            galaxies is redshifted due to the expansion of the Universe. It turns out that the same
            thing happens to the microwave background radiation; its wavelength is also increased.
            The peak frequency of the spectrum is reduced, and this means the radiation is
            progressively cooling. Hence the radiation has not strictly speaking reached
            equilibrium. However, the processes which transferred energy between radiation and
            matter in the early Universe were so rapid that it is meaningful to think of a
            quasi-equilibrium state having been attained at an early time, with the temperature
            gradually falling subsequently because of the expansion of the Universe.</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>A second feature of the thermal spectrum is that if the detector is situated
            within the &#x2018;oven&#x2019; generating it (as distinct from looking at a distant
            black surface or opening to an oven), the intensity of the radiation at any particular
            frequency uniquely identifies the thermal curve to which it belongs, i.e. what the
            temperature of the &#x2018;oven&#x2019; is. So, if <CrossRef
              idref="FIG001_019">Figure 22</CrossRef> referred to thermal spectra picked up by a
            detector situated <i>inside</i> an oven, the ordinate of the graph could be expressed in
            terms of <i>absolute</i>, rather than <i>relative</i> intensities. Under these
            circumstances, a measurement of intensity at a single frequency, say
              60&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>12</sup> Hz, would be sufficient to identify which curve
            that data point belonged to, and hence what the temperature of the oven was.</Paragraph>
          <!--<Paragraph>3K radiation</Paragraph>-->
          <Paragraph>Inasmuch as the Universe can be regarded as an &#x2018;oven&#x2019;, and we are
            in it, Penzias and Wilson were able to estimate from the intensity of the radiation at
            the single frequency they were detecting that the temperature was about 3 K. For this
            reason, the cosmic microwave background radiation is often called the <i>3 K
              radiation</i>. The spectrum observed by COBE allowed a more precise estimate of the
            temperature, namely 2.73 K. This is based on the results presented in <CrossRef
              idref="FIG001_018">Figure 21</CrossRef>, where it should be noted that the data points
            do not deviate from the thermal curve by more than 0.03%, this being consistent with
            measurement precision.</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>In the 1940s, some theoreticians already had an inkling that this radiation
            should exist, from the predictions of their cosmological models. The Abbe Georges
            Lemaitre, a Belgian cosmologist, was the first to see clearly (around 1927) that the
            expansion of the Universe pointed back to a &#x2018;big bang&#x2019;. But he could not
            get much further because not enough was known about nuclear physics at that time. It was
            George Gamow and his colleagues, in 1948, who first saw that very high temperatures must
            be involved at early times in an expanding Universe. They sketched out some nuclear
            reactions that must therefore have taken place. By 1953, their reconstruction had been
            refined and gave definite predictions for nuclear abundances &#x2013; and radiation
            intensity. It was at this stage they realised that radiation had been a vital component
            in the early Universe and that this same radiation, albeit substantially redshifted and
            cooled, should still be around today (there being no other place for it to go!). In the
            1950s, radio equipment already existed which was sensitive enough to detect this
            radiation. Indeed, radio astronomy was developing fast, based at first on the technology
            of military radar in World War II. So by 1953 the stage was set for this radiation to be
            discovered. But as it so happened, the two groups, theoretical and experimental, did not
            stumble into each other for another 12 years. Despite conferences and journals,
            scientific communication with New Jersey was not as effective as communication over
              10<sup>10</sup> light-years! When theory and observation finally came together, the
            question of priority took some sorting out, as indicated in Gamow's letter, reproduced
            as <CrossRef
              idref="FIG001_022">Figure 25</CrossRef>.</Paragraph>
          <Figure
            id="FIG001_022"><Image
              id="FIG001_022"
              src="S357_1_022i.jpg"/>
            <Caption>
              <b>Figure 25</b>: A letter from George Gamow to Arno Penzias</Caption>
            <SourceReference>courtesy of Dr A.A. Penzias <ItemRights>
                <OwnerRef/>
                <ItemRef/>
                <ItemAcknowledgement>courtesy of Dr A.A. Penzias</ItemAcknowledgement>
              </ItemRights>
            </SourceReference>
            <Description/>
          </Figure>
          <Paragraph>The reference to &#x2018;almighty Dicke&#x2019; at the end of this letter
            concerns R. H. Dicke, the leader of a group at Princeton University (also in New Jersey)
            which was pursuing both theoretical and observational research into the background
            radiation in the 1960s. The paper by Penzias and Wilson announcing their discovery, and
            a paper by Dicke's group providing a possible cosmological interpretation, were
            published back to back in volume 142 of the <i>Astrophysical Journal</i> in
            1965.</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>The spectrum of thermal radiation at a given temperature <i>T</i> can be
            expressed in terms of a function <i>W</i>(<i>f</i>, <i>T</i>) which gives the intensity
            of radiation of frequency <i>f</i>. The energy density of that part of the radiation
            with frequencies lying between <i>f</i> and <i>f</i> + &#x394;<i>f</i> is given by
              <i>W</i>(<i>f</i>, <i>T</i>) &#x394;<i>f</i>. The formula for <i>W</i>(<i>f</i>,
              <i>T</i>) was derived by Max Planck in 1900:</Paragraph>
          <Equation
            id="EQN000_007"><Image
              src="S357_1_e007i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
          <Paragraph>where <i>A</i> and <i>B</i> are constants. At low frequencies (<i>f</i>
            &#x226A;
            <i>T</i>/<i>B</i>), one can use a simpler approximate formula:</Paragraph>
          <Equation
            id="EQN000_008"><Image
              src="S357_1_e008i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
          <Activity
            id="ACT001_001a"><Heading>Study comment</Heading>
            <Question>
              <Paragraph>We suggest that you do not omit<!-- the following SAQ-->
                <CrossRef
                  idref="SAQ001_010">Question 10</CrossRef> as it contains information that will be
                needed later.</Paragraph>
            </Question>
          </Activity>
          <!--<Paragraph>Objective 6</Paragraph>-->
          <SAQ
            id="SAQ001_010">
            <Heading>Question 10</Heading>
            <Question>
              <!--<NumberedList>
<ListItem>-->
              <Paragraph>(a) Verify the result represented by <CrossRef
                  idref="FIG001_021">Figure 24</CrossRef>, that <i>W/T</i><sup>3</sup> is a function
                of <i>f/T</i> only, which applies for all frequencies and temperatures.</Paragraph>
              <!--</ListItem>
<ListItem>-->
              <Paragraph>(b) Use the result of (a) to show that maximum intensity occurs at a
                frequency, <i>f</i><sub>max</sub>, which is proportional to the
                temperature.</Paragraph>
              <!--</ListItem>
<ListItem>-->
              <Paragraph>(c) Imagine that you receive a radio message from a very distant galaxy,
                informing you about measurements of the cosmic background radiation at various
                frequencies (defined in terms of fractions of the frequency of a standard spectral
                line). These results do not agree with your own measurements of the radiation. In
                particular, you find that the quoted value of the maximum intensity is <i>eight</i>
                times your value and occurs at a frequency that is <i>twice</i> your frequency for
                maximum intensity. You find that the quoted intensities at low frequencies are
                  <i>twice</i> your values at the same frequencies. How can you explain these
                discrepancies? (You may assume that the discrepancy is not due to calibration or
                other errors.)</Paragraph>
              <!--</ListItem>
</NumberedList>-->
            </Question>
            <Answer>
              <Paragraph><b>(a)</b> Let <i>y</i>&#xA0;=&#xA0;<i>W</i>/<i>T</i><sup>3</sup> and
                  <i>x</i>&#xA0;=&#xA0;<i>f</i>/<i>T</i>. Then</Paragraph>
              <Equation
                id="UEQN001_0039"><Image
                  src="S357_1_ue039i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
              <Paragraph>which shows that <i>W</i>/<i>T</i><sup>3</sup> is a function of
                  <i>f</i>/<i>T</i> only.</Paragraph>
              <Paragraph><b>(b)</b> From the above expression for <i>y</i>, we see there must be a
                universal value of <i>x</i> which gives a maximum value of <i>y</i>. But a maximum
                value of <i>y</i> implies a maximum value of <i>W</i> at a given temperature. If we
                denote this value of <i>x</i> by the constant <i>x</i><sub>max</sub>, it follows
                that</Paragraph>
              <Equation
                id="UEQN001_0040"><Image
                  src="S357_1_ue040i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
              <Paragraph>and hence that</Paragraph>
              <Equation
                id="UEQN001_0041"><Image
                  src="S357_1_ue041i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
              <Paragraph>Thus the frequency, <i>f</i><sub>max</sub> which gives maximum intensity is
                proportional to the temperature <i>T</i>. (You might have heard of this relation
                referred to as Wien's displacement law.)</Paragraph>
              <Paragraph><b>(c)</b> The explanation is that the cosmic background radiation has
                cooled during the time it took for the radio message to reach you. The discrepancies
                between their results and yours can all be explained by this difference in
                temperature of the radiation.</Paragraph>
              <Paragraph>In part (b), it was shown that the frequency, <i>f</i><sub>max</sub>,
                corresponding to maximum intensity, is proportional to <i>T</i>. Since their value
                of <i>f</i><sub>max</sub> is twice yours, the temperature of the cosmic background
                radiation then must have been twice what it is here and now, i.e. it must have been
                just under 6 K.</Paragraph>
              <Paragraph>In part (a), it was shown that:</Paragraph>
              <Equation
                id="UEQN001_0042"><Image
                  src="S357_1_ue042i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
              <Paragraph>If the maximum intensity is <i>W</i><sub>max</sub>, it follows
                that</Paragraph>
              <Equation
                id="UEQN001_0043"><Image
                  src="S357_1_ue043i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
              <Paragraph>which is independent of <i>T</i> since <i>x</i><sub>max</sub> is a
                universal constant from part (b). Hence</Paragraph>
              <Equation
                id="UEQN001_0044"><Image
                  src="S357_1_ue044i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
              <Paragraph>which is why their value of <i>W</i><sub>max</sub> is
                2<sup>3</sup>&#xA0;=&#xA0;8 times yours.</Paragraph>
              <Paragraph>Finally, Equation 8 shows that the intensity at a given low frequency is
                proportional to the temperature and hence will be twice what you measure now at the
                  <i>same</i> low frequency.</Paragraph>
            </Answer>
          </SAQ>
          <!--<Paragraph>Objective 6</Paragraph>-->
          <SAQ
            id="SAQ001_011">
            <Heading>Question 11</Heading>
            <Question>
              <!--<NumberedList>
<ListItem>-->
              <Paragraph>(a) On the basis of your solutions to parts (a) and (b) of <CrossRef
                  idref="SAQ001_010">Question 10</CrossRef>, which would be hotter, a red star or a
                yellow star?</Paragraph>
              <!--</ListItem>
<ListItem>-->
              <Paragraph>(b) The curves of <CrossRef
                  idref="FIG001_019">Figure 22</CrossRef> can be used to extrapolate results to
                lower temperatures. By taking a measurement off the figure, and using the result of <CrossRef
                  idref="SAQ001_010">Question 10</CrossRef>(b), estimate the frequency of the
                intensity maximum for radiation emitted by a body at room temperature. What is the
                term used to describe electromagnetic radiation in this frequency range?</Paragraph>
              <!--</ListItem>
</NumberedList>-->
            </Question>
            <Answer>
              <Paragraph><b>(a)</b> We have already established (in part (b) of the previous
                question) that the frequency of maximum intensity increases proportionately with
                temperature. As yellow light has a higher frequency than red light we would expect
                the yellow star to be the hotter.</Paragraph>
              <Paragraph><b>(b)</b> From <CrossRef
                  idref="FIG001_019">Figure 22</CrossRef>, we see that the maximum intensity for a
                temperature of, say, 1646 K occurs at a frequency of about
                  92&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>12</sup> Hz. The maximum for room temperature, taken to
                be 300 K, is then given by
                  (300/1646)&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;92&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>12</sup>&#xA0;Hz&#xA0;=&#xA0;16.8&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>12</sup>&#xA0;Hz.</Paragraph>
              <Paragraph>Radiation of this frequency occurs in the infrared part of the
                spectrum.</Paragraph>
            </Answer>
          </SAQ>
        </SubSection>
        <SubSection
          id="SEC005_002">
          <Title>5.2 The origin of the 3 K radiation</Title>
          <Paragraph>In speaking of the radiation as having a cosmic origin, what do we have in
            mind? Essentially this:</Paragraph>
          <!--<Paragraph>thermalisation</Paragraph>-->
          <!--<Paragraph>decoupling</Paragraph>-->
          <Paragraph>In the violent conditions of the early evolution of the Universe, a stage was
            reached where the matter consisted of a plasma of electrons, protons, neutrons, and some
            light nuclei such as helium. There were no atoms as such for the simple reason that
            atoms would have been too fragile to withstand the violence of the collisions that were
            taking place at the temperature that then existed. As electromagnetic radiation passed
            through the plasma, it interacted with the matter, exchanging energy in packets or
            &#x2018;quanta&#x2019; of magnitude</Paragraph>
          <Equation
            id="EQN000_009"><Image
              src="S357_1_e009i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
          <Paragraph>where <i>f</i> is the frequency of the radiation and <i>h</i> is the Planck
            constant.</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>The radiation was mainly affected by its collisions with the <i>electrons</i>.
            This is because such collisions cause much bigger energy changes to the photons than
            collisions with the far more massive nucleons (just as a table tennis ball may lose all
            its energy in a collision with another table tennis ball, but will bounce off a
            relatively massive billiard ball with little change in energy). Thus there is a ready
            exchange of energy between the photons and the electrons, in the process of which, the
            radiation acquires the thermal spectrum characterised by the temperature of the
            electrons. The radiation and the electrons tend to come into thermal equilibrium with
            each other, and the electrons are said to have <i>thermalised</i> the
            radiation.</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>As the expansion of the Universe proceeded, the temperature of the radiation
            progressively fell, and so did that of the matter. This fall led to important changes in
            behaviour. From the earliest times, the Universe had been opaque to radiation, in the
            sense that it could not travel far before it interacted with the electrons. But as the
            temperature declined and photon energies decreased, a stage was reached where electrons
            could be bound to nuclei to form neutral atoms &#x2013; atoms that were no longer likely
            to be disrupted in collisions with the reduced-energy photons. Later, the energy of the
            radiation reduced still further to the point where it could not even excite the atomic
            electrons to higher energy states. At this stage, the radiation could no longer be
            strongly absorbed by matter. This being so, the Universe became transparent. This stage
            we call the <i>decoupling</i> of radiation from matter. (You will find that some books
            refer to this stage in the development of the Universe as the
            &#x2018;recombination&#x2019; era rather than the decoupling epoch.) It occurs when the
            radiation has cooled down to the point where the most probable photon energy corresponds
            to a temperature of 3000 K.
            <!--As you will find in Unit 15, where we take you systematically through the various stages in the development of the Universe, -->This
            occurred some 4&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>5</sup> years after the instant of the big bang.
            Thus the radiation we now observe as 3 K radiation is today's cooled-down remnant of
            that 3000 K big bang radiation.</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>How confident can we be that this was indeed the origin of the 3 K radiation?
            There are essentially four properties that lead to this conclusion:</Paragraph>
          <NumberedList>
            <ListItem>
              <Paragraph>As we have already mentioned, the <i>isotropy</i> of the radiation points
                to some global, cosmic origin.</Paragraph>
            </ListItem>
            <ListItem>
              <Paragraph>The <i>spectrum</i> of the radiation is such that it could only have been
                produced by a sufficiently rapid interaction of the radiation with matter for the
                thermal energy distribution of the particles of matter to be imprinted on the
                radiation. Only in the early dense stages of the Universe were particles and
                radiation interacting fast enough for this to have been achieved within the time
                available.</Paragraph>
            </ListItem>
            <ListItem>
              <Paragraph>The <i>present temperature</i> of the radiation of only 3 K is lower than
                that of most visible matter currently in the Universe. How could it be so low? The
                only reasonable explanation is that it has been strongly redshifted -indicating that
                it has been travelling towards us over an exceedingly long period of time, i.e. it
                was emitted soon after the big bang.</Paragraph>
            </ListItem>
            <ListItem>
              <Paragraph>The <i>density of photons</i> corresponding to the 3 K radiation is
                enormous. In fact there are believed to be about 10<sup>9</sup> times as many 3 K
                photons in any large region of the Universe as there are neutrons and protons.
                Clearly this radiation is no mere by-product of an obscure process; it is a
                ubiquitous feature of the Universe. This prompts us to ask at what stage of the
                Universe is radiation likely to have played a dominant role? The answer has to be:
                the violent <i>early</i> Universe.</Paragraph>
            </ListItem>
          </NumberedList>
          <!--<Paragraph>Quasars are believed to be the highly luminous centres of certain galaxies at an early stage in their life. They can be 1000 times brighter than a typical galaxy and can therefore be seen at great distances.</Paragraph>-->
        </SubSection>
        <SubSection
          id="SEC005_003">
          <Title>5.3 The redshift of the 3 K radiation</Title>
          <Paragraph>The temperature, T, of the radiation is proportional to the most probable
            photon energy, <i>E</i>, which as we have said is proportional to <i>f</i>, and hence
            inversely proportional to the wavelength &#x3BB;. Thus,</Paragraph>
          <Equation
            id="EQN000_010"><Image
              src="S357_1_e010i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
          <Paragraph>According to Equation 1, we have for the redshift, <i>z</i></Paragraph>
          <Equation
            id="UEQN001_0001"><Image
              src="S357_1_ue001i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
          <Paragraph>Thus,</Paragraph>
          <Equation
            id="EQN000_011"><Image
              src="S357_1_e011i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
          <Paragraph>The wavelength we observe now, <i>&#x3BB;</i><sub>0</sub>, is that
            corresponding to <i>T</i> &#x2248; 3 K, whereas the original wavelength,
              <i>&#x3BB;</i><sub>1</sub>, emitted during the decoupling epoch corresponded to
              <i>T</i> &#x2248; 3000 K. Hence</Paragraph>
          <Equation
            id="UEQN001_0002"><Image
              src="S357_1_ue002i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
          <Paragraph>and hence <i>z</i> &#x2248; 1000. This compares with <i>z</i> &#x2248; 6 for
            the furthest optical object so far seen (2004). This was associated with a
            quasar.</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>Quasars are believed to be the highly luminous centres of certain galaxies at
            an early stage in their life. They can be 1000 times brighter than a typical galaxy and
            can therefore be seen at great distances.</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>From these <i>z</i> values, you can appreciate how much further back in time
            and farther away in distance it is possible to look with a microwave detector than with
            an optical telescope. Even so, it is important to recognise that we cannot, and never
            shall be able to, see right back to the instant of the big bang. For the first
              4&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>5</sup> years, the Universe was opaque.</Paragraph>
          <!--<Paragraph>Objective 6</Paragraph>-->
          <SAQ
            id="SAQ001_012">
            <Heading>Question 12</Heading>
            <Question>
              <Paragraph><!--In Unit 15, we shall see that -->The wavelengths associated with
                photons increase as <i>t</i><sup>2/3</sup>, where <i>t</i> is the time they were
                emitted after the big bang. Assuming the time now,
                  <i>t</i><sub>0</sub>&#xA0;=&#xA0;1.4&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>10</sup> years, and
                that decoupling took place when <i>T</i>&#xA0;=&#xA0;3000 K, estimate the time,
                  <i>t</i><sub>d</sub>, at which decoupling occurred.</Paragraph>
            </Question>
            <Answer>
              <Equation
                id="UEQN001_0045"><Image
                  src="S357_1_ue045i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
              <Paragraph>Therefore,</Paragraph>
              <Equation
                id="UEQN001_0046"><Image
                  src="S357_1_ue046i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
            </Answer>
          </SAQ>
        </SubSection></Section>
      <Section
        id="SEC006">
        <Title>6 The angular distribution of the 3 K radiation</Title>
        <!--<Paragraph>angular distribution</Paragraph>-->
        <SubSection
          id="SEC006_001">
          <Title>6.1 Basic isotropy</Title>
          <Paragraph>As we have said, the photons in the 3 K background have been practically free
            from interaction with anything since about 4&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>5</sup> years after
            the instant of the big bang. The present <i>angular distribution</i> of the microwave
            radiation &#x2013; the way in which it is spread across the sky &#x2013; is therefore
            almost the same as it was then. The spectrum we find today depends on the temperatures
            at that time &#x2013; for the intensity of the radiation in a particular region of the
            early Universe depended <i>only</i> on the temperature. If the Universe at that time was
            inhomogeneous (in the sense of being hotter in some regions than others) the 3 K
            radiation observed today would be more intense in some directions than in
            others.</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>In fact, as we have indicated, the radiation is largely isotropic. There are,
            however, some small &#x2013; some <i>very</i> small &#x2013; but significant departures
            from perfect isotropy. But before these can be identified, we have to take into account
            the effect of the Earth's motion. This would in any event impose an apparent asymmetry
            on the radiation. Indeed, as we shall now show, this effect can be turned to our
            advantage and provide us with a means for measuring the speed of the Earth relative to
            the average distribution of matter and energy in the Universe.</Paragraph>
        </SubSection>
        <SubSection
          id="SEC006_002">
          <Title>6.2 The effect of the motion of the Earth</Title>
          <!--</SubSection>-->
          <SubSubSection
            id="SEC006_002_001">
            <Heading>6.2.1 The need for a reference frame for describing the Universe</Heading>
            <Paragraph>The speed of the Earth in its orbit round the Sun is 29.8 km
                s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>, in a heliocentric frame. But to specify the velocity vector,
              it is not sufficient to specify the Sun as the origin of the coordinate system; fixed
              directions must also be identified.</Paragraph>
            <!--<Paragraph>Objective 6</Paragraph>-->
            <SAQ
              id="SAQ001_013">
              <Heading>Question 13</Heading>
              <Question>
                <Paragraph>Here are two possible rules for fixing an
                  <i>x</i><sup>1</sup>-direction:</Paragraph>
                <Paragraph>(i) The <i>x</i><sup>1</sup>-axis is taken as the line from the Sun to
                  the nearest star (Proxima Centauri);</Paragraph>
                <Paragraph>(ii) The <i>x</i><sup>1</sup>-axis is taken as pointing in the direction
                  from the centre of the Galaxy to the nearest large galaxy (the Andromeda
                  galaxy).</Paragraph>
                <Paragraph>Are these two methods equally acceptable? If not, which is preferable,
                  and is it completely satisfactory?</Paragraph>
              </Question>
              <Answer>
                <Paragraph>Proxima Centauri is the nearest star, and so is undoubtedly in our
                  Galaxy. Our Galaxy is rotating, as is suggested independently of all frames of
                  reference by its disc-like
                  shape<!-- &#x0028;recall also the Newton bucket experiment described in the Appendix to Unit 2&#x0029;-->.
                  So the line to Proxima Centauri is <i>not</i> a good x<sup>1</sup>-axis, because
                  of the relative motion of the Sun and Proxima Centauri within the
                  Galaxy.</Paragraph>
                <Paragraph>The Andromeda galaxy is the nearest galaxy to ours (apart from satellite
                  galaxies and the Magellanic Clouds). It is gravitationally bound to our Galaxy and
                  moving relative to us. The period of the mutual &#x2018;orbit&#x2019; of our
                  Galaxy and the Andromeda galaxy is certainly longer than the period of the Sun (or
                  Proxima Centauri) round our Galaxy, because the distance from our Galaxy to the
                  Andromeda galaxy is about a hundred times bigger than the distance of the Sun (or
                  Proxima Centauri) from the centre of our Galaxy. Nevertheless, the line connecting
                  our Galaxy to the Andromeda galaxy cannot be taken as fixed because of their
                  motions within the Local Group.</Paragraph>
                <Paragraph>Thus methods (i) and (ii) are not equally acceptable; (ii) is preferable
                  to (i), but is still not fully satisfactory.</Paragraph>
              </Answer>
            </SAQ>
            <Paragraph>The considerations of <CrossRef
                idref="SAQ001_013">Question 13</CrossRef> force one to look at bigger and bigger
              aggregates of matter in the search for reference bodies with respect to which a system
              of coordinates can be defined independently of the motion caused by the gravitational
              effects of nearby matter in our local region of the Universe. We assume that the
              clusters of galaxies fulfil this role. But clusters may be loosely associated (though
              not bound) in superclusters.</Paragraph>
            <Paragraph>For this reason, we would like to have an alternative way of establishing a
              reference frame. The 3 K radiation provides such a means.</Paragraph>
            <Paragraph>If the 3 K radiation filled the Universe at early times and has not
              interacted appreciably with matter since decoupling, then this radiation defines a
              system in which matter and energy in the early Universe are assumed to have been
              distributed homogeneously. So if we were to find that the 3 K radiation is
                <i>completely</i> isotropic when observed on Earth, we could conclude that we are
                <i>at rest</i> with respect to the average distribution of matter and energy in the
              Universe. In that sense, the radiation can be said to define a &#x2018;rest
              frame&#x2019; of the Universe. But if we find that the radiation is not isotropic, and
              moreover, that it varies in a characteristically systematic fashion according to
              direction, then we can conclude that we are moving in a particular direction with
              respect to the frame in which the radiation is isotropic.</Paragraph>
            <Paragraph>It is a matter of great interest to know the velocities of the Earth, the
              Sun, our Galaxy and our Local Group with respect to the system defined by the 3 K
              radiation. It might, for example, provide support for the idea that gravitational
              effects within a supercluster must be taken into account in mapping out the
              Universe.</Paragraph>
          </SubSubSection>
          <SubSubSection
            id="SEC006_002_002">
            <Heading>6.2.2 The Earth's motion relative to the 3 K radiation</Heading>
            <Paragraph><!--As noted in Unit 4, -->Radiation has energy and momentum, so we can use
              the molecules of a fluid such as air as an analogy for the photons of radiation. A
              detector pointing forwards along the direction of our motion (if any) will encounter a
              greater number of photons than a detector pointing backwards; in other words, it will
              record a higher intensity of 3 K radiation. (If the detector is tuned to a narrow band
              of frequencies one would also have to take account of the change in observed spectrum,
              but the principle remains the same.)</Paragraph>
            <Figure
              id="FIG001_023"><Image
                id="FIG001_023"
                src="S357_1_023i.jpg"/>
              <Caption>
                <b>Figure 26</b>: The radiation detected at an angle <i>&#x3B8;</i> to the direction
                of motion has a thermal spectrum characterised by a temperature <i>T</i>(<i>v</i>,
                  <i>&#x3B8;</i>) which depends on the speed <i>v</i> and the angle
                <i>&#x3B8;</i>.</Caption>
              <Description/>
            </Figure>
            <Paragraph>Not only does the Earth's motion affect the intensity as a function of angle,
              but also the <i>energy</i> of the photons. Suppose the Earth is moving with a velocity <InlineEquation><Image
                  src="S357_1_ie00italvi.gif"/><Description/></InlineEquation> with respect to the
              frame in which the radiation is isotropic and we observe the component of the 3 K
              radiation that arrives in a direction making an angle <i>&#x3B8;</i> with our
              direction of motion (see <CrossRef
                idref="FIG001_023">Figure 26</CrossRef>). What sort of spectrum would we observe?
              One might think that the observed spectrum would be very complicated. After all, the
              photons have been shifted to different frequencies, because of the Doppler effect, and
              our clocks and measuring rods will measure different intervals of time and length,
              compared with clocks and measuring rods in the &#x2018;frame of isotropic 3 K
              radiation&#x2019;. But it turns out that the result is very simple: Cosmic microwave
              radiation observed at an angle <i>&#x3B8;</i> relative to the observer's direction of
              motion will still have a <i>thermal</i> spectrum, though it will be characterised by a
              temperature <i>T</i>(<InlineEquation><Image
                  src="S357_1_ie00italvi.gif"/><Description/></InlineEquation>, <i>&#x3B8;</i>)
              which depends on the observer's speed <InlineEquation><Image
                  src="S357_1_ie00italvi.gif"/><Description/></InlineEquation> and the angle
                <i>&#x3B8;</i>. (This reminds us of how the expansion of the Universe affected the
              cosmic background radiation: in that case too the thermal character of the spectrum
              was maintained; only the temperature was changed.)</Paragraph>
            <Paragraph>It is in fact easy to calculate how <i>T</i>(<InlineEquation><Image
                  src="S357_1_ie00italvi.gif"/><Description/></InlineEquation>, <i>&#x3B8;</i>)
              depends on <InlineEquation><Image
                  src="S357_1_ie00italvi.gif"/><Description/></InlineEquation> and <i>&#x3B8;</i>.
              We shall use the fact that the frequency <i>f</i><sub>max</sub>, corresponding to the
              maximum intensity, is proportional to the temperature (see <CrossRef
                idref="SAQ001_010">Question 10</CrossRef>). That means that in the &#x2018;rest
              frame&#x2019;</Paragraph>
            <Equation
              id="UEQN001_0003"><Image
                src="S357_1_ue003i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
            <Paragraph>where <i>C</i> is a constant and <i>T</i><sub>0</sub> (&#x2248; 3 K) is the
              temperature of the radiation in the frame in which it is isotropic. But when we are
              moving with a speed <InlineEquation><Image
                  src="S357_1_ie00italvi.gif"/><Description/></InlineEquation> and observing at an
              angle <i>&#x3B8;</i>, we find a different frequency, <i>f</i>&#x2032;<sub>max</sub>,
              corresponding to maximum intensity:</Paragraph>
            <Equation
              id="UEQN001_0004"><Image
                src="S357_1_ue004i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
            <Paragraph>The relationship between <i>f</i><sub>max</sub> and
                <i>f</i>&#x2032;<sub>max</sub> is given by the formula for the relativistic Doppler
              shift<!-- &#x0028;see SAQ 20 of Unit 7&#x0029;-->:</Paragraph>
            <Equation
              id="UEQN001_0005"><Image
                src="S357_1_ue005i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
            <Paragraph>Thus we find that</Paragraph>
            <Equation
              id="EQN000_012"><Image
                src="S357_1_e012i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
            <Paragraph>Thus, if we were to measure the apparent temperature of the radiation at
              different angles, we could determine our speed <InlineEquation><Image
                  src="S357_1_ie00italvi.gif"/><Description/></InlineEquation> and the direction in
              which we are moving (which is the direction in which the radiation has the highest
              temperature, corresponding to <i>&#x3B8;</i>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0).</Paragraph>
            <Paragraph>Radio astronomers measure the intensity of radiation at a particular
              frequency or over a particular range of frequencies. The variation of intensity with
              angle is particularly simple if measurements are taken at <i>low</i> frequencies, well
              below the frequency for maximum intensity, <i>f</i><sub>max</sub>. In this region of
              the spectrum, the intensity at a given frequency is proportional to the temperature
              (see Equation 8),</Paragraph>
            <Equation
              id="UEQN001_0006"><Image
                src="S357_1_ue006i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
            <Paragraph>and hence</Paragraph>
            <Equation
              id="EQN000_013"><Image
                src="S357_1_e013i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
            <Paragraph>The prediction of Equation 13 is plotted in <CrossRef
                idref="FIG001_024">Figure 27</CrossRef> for values of <InlineEquation><Image
                  src="S357_1_ie00italvi.gif"/><Description/></InlineEquation>/<i>c</i>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0,
              0.1 and 0.2. The angular distributions (b) and (c) show a <i>dipolar
              anisotropy</i>.</Paragraph>
            <!--<Paragraph>dipolar anisotropy</Paragraph>-->
            <Figure
              id="FIG001_024"><Image
                id="FIG001_024"
                src="S357_1_024i.jpg"/>
              <Caption>
                <b>Figure 27</b>: The radiation intensity at low frequencies,
                  <i>W</i>(<i>&#x3B8;</i>), as a function of <i>&#x3B8;</i>, for <i>v</i>/<i>c</i>
                equal to (a) 0, (b) 0.1 and (c) 0.2, where <i>W</i>(<i>&#x3B8;</i>) is calculated
                from Equation 13. (Note that <i>v</i>/<i>c</i> for the Earth's motion round the Sun
                is only 10<sup>&#x2212;4</sup>)</Caption>
              <Description/>
            </Figure>
            <Paragraph>At higher frequencies, the coefficient of cos <i>&#x3B8;</i> is more
              complicated and must be calculated from Equation 7. The result of such a calculation,
              which applies at all frequencies, is</Paragraph>
            <Equation
              id="EQN000_014"><Image
                src="S357_1_e014i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
            <Paragraph>where</Paragraph>
            <Equation
              id="UEQN001_0007"><Image
                src="S357_1_ue007i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
            <Paragraph>But for <i>f</i> &#x226A;
              <i>T</i>/<i>B</i> &#x2248; 6&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>10</sup> Hz, we have
                <i>F</i>(<i>f</i>) &#x2248; 1 and obtain the simpler result of Equation
              13.</Paragraph>
          </SubSubSection>
          <!--<Paragraph>Looking at the Earth from outside the Solar System, one sees it revolving 366&#x00BC; times a year, not 365&#x00BC;. From our position on the Earth, we see only 365&#x00BC; days, because one turn is taken up in the revolution round the Sun. A sidereal day is &#x0028;1&#x002F;366&#x00BC;&#x0029; of a year and a solar day is &#x0028;1&#x002F;365&#x00BC;&#x0029; of a year.</Paragraph>-->
          <SubSubSection
            id="SEC006_002_003">
            <Heading>6.2.3 Measurement of the angular distribution of the 3 K radiation</Heading>
            <Paragraph>How are such angular distributions to be measured? One way, of course, is to
              take a radio telescope and swing it round the sky, taking readings in different
              directions. But as is clear from <CrossRef
                idref="FIG001_017">Figure 20</CrossRef>(a), the atmosphere itself emits microwaves.
              There is therefore a grave danger, with this method, of picking up different
              contributions of atmospheric emission from different directions &#x2013; more as you
              point your telescope close to the ground, with a long path through the atmosphere,
              less when it is vertical with the minimum path through the atmosphere. A better, and
              indeed simpler, way with a ground-based telescope is to leave the telescope in a fixed
              direction with respect to the Earth, say vertical, and let the Earth's rotation carry
              it round. In 24 hours, the telescope will be carried round a whole circle, allowing
              the measured intensity to be plotted against angle of observation as indicated in <CrossRef
                idref="FIG001_024">Figure 27</CrossRef>.</Paragraph>
            <Paragraph>Thus a practical prescription for looking for the translational motion of the
              Earth, relative to the frame in which the 3 K radiation is isotropic, is to look for a
              variation with a 24-hour period in the radiation detected by a fixed radio telescope.
              Such a search, for a variation of <i>known period</i>, can be carried out very
              sensitively. That is why we have looked at the data in two stages, first asking if the
              data look isotropic, and now asking more specifically for the magnitude of any 24-hour
              variation.</Paragraph>
            <Paragraph>A further nice experimental feature is that the component being sought is of
              period 24 <i>sidereal</i> hours. Human interference, on the other hand, will tend to
              have a period of 24 <i>solar</i> hours. This small distinction (explained below) often
              allows a radio astronomer to sort out the pure astronomical signal from the strong
              terrestrial noise.</Paragraph>
            <Paragraph><b>Sidereal Day</b></Paragraph>
            <Paragraph>Looking at the Earth from outside the Solar System, one sees it revolving
              366&#xBC; times a year, not 365&#xBC;. From our position on the Earth, we see only
              365&#xBC; days, because one turn is taken up in the revolution round the Sun. A
              sidereal day is (1/366&#xBC;) of a year and a solar day is (1/365&#xBC;) of a
              year.</Paragraph>
            <!--<Paragraph>Objective 7</Paragraph>-->
            <SAQ
              id="SAQ001_014">
              <Heading>Question 14</Heading>
              <Question>
                <Paragraph>How large a change in apparent temperature of the 3 K radiation is
                  expected due to the Earth's motion round the Sun? How large is it due to the Solar
                  System's motion of 230 km s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> round the Galaxy? (The <a
                    href="http://openlearn.open.ac.uk/file.php/3639/S357Datasheets.pdf"
                    target="_blank">data sheet</a> gives information you may need to answer this
                  question.)</Paragraph>
              </Question>
              <Answer>
                <Paragraph>The mean speed of the Earth round the Sun can be obtained by taking the
                  orbit as a circle of radius 1.5&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>11</sup> m. The speed <InlineEquation><Image
                      src="S357_1_ie00italvi.gif"/><Description/></InlineEquation> is
                  then</Paragraph>
                <Equation
                  id="UEQN001_0047"><Image
                    src="S357_1_ue047i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
                <Paragraph>(Strictly, the orbit is not quite circular, so the speed varies somewhat
                  above and below this value.)</Paragraph>
                <Paragraph>From Equation 12 in <CrossRef
                    idref="SEC006_002">Section 6.2</CrossRef>, the maximum change in apparent
                  temperature, &#x394;<i>T</i>, which this motion can cause at low frequencies
                  arises when cos<i>&#x3B8;</i>&#xA0;=&#xA0;1. &#x394;<i>T</i>/<i>T</i> is then a
                  fraction</Paragraph>
                <Equation
                  id="UEQN001_0048"><Image
                    src="S357_1_ue048i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
                <Paragraph>The speed of the Solar System round the Galaxy about 230 km
                    s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>, gives a &#x394;<i>T</i>/<i>T</i> of about
                    (2.3&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>5</sup>)/(3&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>8</sup>)
                  &#x2248; 10<sup>&#x2212;3</sup>.</Paragraph>
              </Answer>
            </SAQ>
          </SubSubSection>
          <SubSubSection
            id="SEC006_002_004">
            <Heading>6.2.4 The speed and direction of the Earth's motion</Heading>
            <Paragraph>The first significant claim to have detected the motion of the Earth relative
              to the &#x2018;frame of isotropic 3 K radiation&#x2019; came in 1977 from a group at
              Berkeley, California. They concluded that the Earth is moving at a speed of (390
              &#xB1; 60) km s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>, in a direction towards the constellation Leo,
              relative to a frame in which the 3 K radiation is isotropic. Their conclusion resulted
              from observations of a variation of intensity with angle of the form predicted by
              Equation 14, which we have called a 24-hour variation.</Paragraph>
            <Paragraph>Now this motion of the Earth through the 3 K radiation will be the resultant
              of several component motions:</Paragraph>
            <NumberedList>
              <ListItem>
                <Paragraph>The Earth's velocity about the Sun (of magnitude 30 km
                    s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>):</Paragraph>
              </ListItem>
              <ListItem>
                <Paragraph>The velocity of the Sun itself about the Galactic centre (currently
                  estimated to be of magnitude 230 km s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>):</Paragraph>
              </ListItem>
              <ListItem>
                <Paragraph>The velocity of the Galaxy relative to the Local Group;</Paragraph>
              </ListItem>
              <ListItem>
                <Paragraph>Whatever velocity the Local Group has relative to the &#x2018;frame of
                  isotropic 3 K radiation&#x2019;.</Paragraph>
              </ListItem>
            </NumberedList>
            <Figure
              id="FIG001_025"><Image
                id="FIG001_025"
                src="S357_1_025i.jpg"/>
              <Caption>
                <b>Figure 28</b>: The absolute motion of the Earth. The Earth travels in its orbit
                round the Sun at 30 km s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> and is being swept around the centre of
                the Galaxy at 230 km s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>. Experiment shows that the Earth's net
                speed through the 3 K radiation is about 400 km s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>. The Earth's
                net velocity lies in the same plane as its orbit round the Sun and at an angle
                tilted sharply upwards (northwards) from the plane of the Galaxy. In this diagram,
                the Earth's net velocity is depicted as a heavy arrow centred on the Sun (pointing
                upwards and to the right), since the two bodies travel together. Both are being
                carried by the Galaxy's own motion through the 3 K radiation. In order to account
                for the Earth's motion with respect to the 3 K radiation, the Galaxy must be
                travelling at about 600 km s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> in the direction shown by the
                coloured arrow centred on the disc of the Galaxy.</Caption>
              <SourceReference>based on R.A. Muller (1978) in <i>Scientific American</i>, 238,
                64&#x2013;74 <ItemRights>
                  <OwnerRef/>
                  <ItemRef/>
                  <ItemAcknowledgement>based on R.A. Muller (1978) in <i>Scientific American</i>,
                    238, 64&#x2013;74</ItemAcknowledgement>
                </ItemRights>
              </SourceReference>
              <Description/>
            </Figure>
            <Paragraph>The Earth's speed of about 400 km s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>, relative to this
              frame in which the radiation is isotropic, is comparable to its speed of about 230 km
                s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> relative to the Galactic centre of mass. Nevertheless, the
              Galaxy as a whole must be moving through the 3 K radiation even <i>faster</i> than the
              Earth, because the direction of the Solar System's orbital velocity round the Galaxy
              is almost <i>opposite</i> to the direction of maximum observed intensity of the 3 K
              radiation and hence opposite to the direction of the Earth's velocity through the 3 K
              radiation, as depicted in <CrossRef
                idref="FIG001_025">Figure 28</CrossRef>. Adding the two velocity vectors gives the
              centre of the Galaxy a velocity whose magnitude is about 600 km s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>
              with respect to the 3 K radiation. Now <i>if our Galaxy were isolated</i>, this
              velocity could only be interpreted as a departure (and 600 km s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>
              would be an embarrassingly large departure) from the basic idea of cosmology that the
              expansion of the Universe is shared by all matter and radiation; an isolated galaxy,
              or the centre of mass of a cluster of galaxies, should <i>not</i> be moving with
              respect to the 3 K radiation. But our Galaxy is not isolated, it is a member of our
              Local Group of galaxies. It cannot be stationary with respect to the centre of mass of
              the Local Group but must, to avoid falling in, be travelling around in some quite
              complicated orbit. So the next step towards an understanding of the 600 km
                s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> is to subtract from it the velocity of our Galaxy in its
              movement about the Local Group. Unfortunately this velocity is not very well known,
              because the estimates of the masses of some of the galaxies in the Local Group are
              very rough. But current data give the speed of our Galaxy with respect to the
              Andromeda galaxy (which is the other major member of our Local Group) as 40 km
                s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>. This might be an indication of the kind of velocity we have
              relative to the centre of mass of the Local Group. If so, it still leaves an
              unexplained speed of 500&#x2013;600 km s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>.</Paragraph>
            <Paragraph>Our Local Group is thought to be a member of a cluster of clusters called the
              Local Supercluster. So the next step is to subtract the velocity of our Local Group
              with respect to the centre of mass of the Local Supercluster from the 600 km
                s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>. If this is also the final step, the answer should be
              compatible with zero. Unfortunately, the uncertainties are, at this stage, too great
              to be able to decide whether the velocity of our Local Group can be entirely explained
              in terms of the effects of a Local Supercluster. If not, then the effects of other
              structures such as more distant superclusters and the voids between them, must also be
              taken into account.</Paragraph>
          </SubSubSection>
        </SubSection>
        <SubSection
          id="SEC006_003">
          <Title>6.3 Anisotropies in the Universe itself</Title>
          <Paragraph>Having subtracted the dipolar anisotropy due to the motion of the Earth
            relative to the 3 K radiation, we are left with radiation that is exceedingly isotropic.
            So, we have to ask whether there are any residual variations that would point to a
            departure from isotropy of the radiation <i>itself</i>? This is a crucial question.
            Although it was gratifying to have the radiation so isotropic that there could be little
            doubt of its cosmic origins, nevertheless a <i>completely</i> isotropic distribution
            would bring troubles of its own.</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>The reason for this is that, although the <i>matter</i> distribution is
            isotropic on a large enough scale, it is clearly not so on smaller scales. It is clumped
            together in galaxies, the galaxies are preferentially to be found in clusters of
            galaxies, and even the clusters are loosely associated in superclusters. In fact, the
            matter distribution somewhat resembles a gigantic sponge; it has enormous holes in it,
            with the superclusters arranged around the boundaries of these voids. Presumably this
            distribution came about as a result of inhomogeneities in the original distribution of
            matter coming from the big bang. If a particular region happened to have by chance a
            somewhat greater density of matter than its neighbours, its increased gravity would tend
            to attract matter away from the less densely populated regions and towards itself. This
            would enhance the inhomogeneity, leading to this particular region gaining an even
            stronger pulling power, and attracting yet more material to itself. The initial
            inhomogeneities, which in themselves may have been slight, would over the course of time
            have become magnified.</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>That is thought to be the process whereby we have our present-day distribution.
            Having said that, it is not at all clear yet in what order the hierarchy of structures
            formed. Perhaps the matter first assembled to form superclusters; these then broke down
            into their component clusters, which in their turn later separated out into galaxies.
            Finally, the individual stars condensed. Alternatively it could all have happened the
            opposite way round, with stars forming first, these being attracted into galaxies, which
            later gathered into clusters and superclusters. Or indeed it could have been some other
            mix of aspects drawn from both these scenarios. But whichever was the correct sequence
            of events, one thing is clear: there had to be density inhomogeneities on some scale or
            other.</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>From this we infer that there should also be anisotropies in the 3 K radiation.
            The reason is that when gas collects together and is squashed down by its mutual
            gravity, potential energy is converted into kinetic energy leading to a temperature
            rise. It is such temperature increases that can ignite nuclear reactions and result in
            the birth of a new star (assuming sufficient gas has been collected originally). Gas
            collecting to form a primordial galaxy or a cluster of galaxies will similarly undergo a
            temperature rise, this rise being reflected in the type of radiation it emits. The
            angular distribution of this radiation, as we receive it today, should show a degree of
            anisotropy because it originates in matter that was not itself entirely homogeneous.
            Inhomogeneities must have already been present in matter when it was emitting what is
            now the 3 K radiation. Thus we should expect the 3 K radiation to manifest some degree
            of anisotropy; it should <i>not</i> be wholly uniform.</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>This is not to say that we should necessarily expect to detect &#x2018;hot
            spots&#x2019;. The situation is somewhat more subtle than that. We have to recall that
            when we are dealing with galaxies or with clusters, a great deal of matter is involved.
            The gravitational potential energies are enormous. Radiation emitted from the depths of
            one of these conglomerations of matter has to escape the gravitational field of the
            matter producing it. This<!--, as we would expect from Block 3,--> will lead to a
            gravitational redshift, i.e. a cooling of the radiation. The interesting question then
            becomes whether the hot radiation from the interior is still &#x2018;hot&#x2019; when it
            escapes, or whether it will now have lost so much energy through redshift that it
            emerges <i>cooler</i> than the ambient temperature of the surrounding matter. We might
            therefore observe &#x2018;cold spots&#x2019; rather than &#x2018;hot
            spots&#x2019;.</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>So, although the theoretical analysis is complicated, there have to be
            anisotropies of one kind or another in the 3 K radiation at some level of sensitivity,
            and definite predictions have long been made about the angular scale on which such
            anisotropies ought to appear. The refinement of these predictions and the effort to
            detect the anisotropies observationally have become major themes in the recent
            development of cosmology.</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>There was a great stir, which even the popular press recognised, when in 1992,
            the COBE satellite succeeded in detecting the anisotropies, albeit at the extremely low
            level of 1 part in 100 000. <CrossRef
              idref="FIG001_026">Figure 29</CrossRef> shows a picture of the measured intensity
            distribution across the sky.</Paragraph>
          <Figure
            id="FIG001_026"><Image
              id="FIG001_026"
              src="S357_1_026i.jpg"/>
            <Caption>
              <b>Figure 29</b>: Departures from isotropy in the 3 K radiation (COBE
              satellite)</Caption>
            <SourceReference>courtesy of NASA Goddard Space Flight Center, Greenbelt, Maryland
                <ItemRights>
                <OwnerRef/>
                <ItemRef/>
                <ItemAcknowledgement>courtesy of NASA Goddard Space Flight Center, Greenbelt,
                  Maryland</ItemAcknowledgement>
              </ItemRights>
            </SourceReference>
            <Description/>
          </Figure>
          <Paragraph>This first detection of the intrinsic anisotropies in the cosmic microwave
            background had to be interpreted with great care since the signal being detected was of
            the same order of magnitude as the background noise fluctuations. However, since that
            first detection many other studies have been carried out and the angular distribution of
            the anisotropies has been characterised with greatly increased precision.</Paragraph>
          <!--<Paragraph>angular power spectrum</Paragraph>-->
          <Paragraph>The characterisation of the angular distribution of anisotropies is usually
            expressed through a plot of the <i>angular power spectrum</i> of the observed radiation.
            Such a plot indicates the relative strength of intensity (or temperature) fluctuations
            as a function of the angular scale of those fluctuations. A recent determination of this
            angular power spectrum, based on results obtained by COBE's successor, the Wilkinson
            Microwave Anisotropy Probe (WMAP), is shown in <CrossRef
              idref="FIG001_027">Figure 30</CrossRef>.</Paragraph>
          <Figure
            id="FIG001_027"><Image
              id="FIG001_027"
              src="S357_1_027i.jpg"/>
            <Caption>
              <b>Figure 30</b>: The angular power spectrum of the cosmic microwave background
              radiation as determined by the WMAP satellite (based on Bennett et al.,
              2003)</Caption>
            <SourceReference>based on C.L. Bennett <i>et al.</i>, (2003) <i>The Astrophys. J.
                Supp.</i>, 148(1), 1&#x2013;27 <ItemRights>
                <OwnerRef/>
                <ItemRef/>
                <ItemAcknowledgement>based on C.L. Bennett <i>et al.</i>, (2003) <i>The Astrophys.
                    J. Supp.</i>, 148(1), 1&#x2013;27 </ItemAcknowledgement>
              </ItemRights>
            </SourceReference>
            <Description/>
          </Figure>
          <Paragraph>The details of the angular power spectrum need not concern us here, but the
            following points should be noted.</Paragraph>
          <NumberedList>
            <ListItem>
              <Paragraph>The points and vertical &#x2018;error bars&#x2019; represent the results of
                observation. The smooth line represents a &#x2018;best fit&#x2019; to the data based
                on specific theoretical assumptions.</Paragraph>
            </ListItem>
            <ListItem>
              <Paragraph>The shaded band represents the unavoidable uncertainty (known as <i>cosmic
                  variance</i> in this case) associated with trying to determine a
                &#x2018;cosmic&#x2019; quantity from observations made at one (typical) point in the
                Universe, i.e. from the neighbourhood of the Earth.</Paragraph>
            </ListItem>
            <ListItem>
              <Paragraph>The COBE data were limited to angular scales of 10&#xB0; or more. The WMAP
                data reveal anisotropies on much finer scales and tell us much about the angular
                distribution of those anisotropies.</Paragraph>
            </ListItem>
            <ListItem>
              <Paragraph>The anisotropies are particularly powerful on a scale of about 1&#xB0;.
                This is just the angular scale at which the inhomogeneities associated with the
                formation of superclusters are expected to leave their imprint on the 3 K
                radiation.</Paragraph>
            </ListItem>
            <ListItem>
              <Paragraph>Theoretical explanations for the peaks and troughs seen in the data depend
                on the assumed values of various cosmological parameters such as the current value
                of the Hubble parameter. Thus the process of &#x2018;fitting&#x2019; predictions to
                the data provides a method of determining the values of those cosmological
                parameters. We shall return to this point later.</Paragraph>
            </ListItem>
          </NumberedList>
          <Paragraph>In conclusion, we can say that the extreme degree of isotropy of the 3 K
            radiation points to its cosmic origin in the big bang, and justifies us in regarding it
            as powerful confirmatory evidence that there was indeed a big bang. Nevertheless, it is
            perhaps the exceedingly weak inhomogeneities that will ultimately prove to be of the
            most lasting value for cosmology. These give us what may be a unique snapshot of a stage
            in the early development of galaxies/clusters/superclusters &#x2013; the stage reached
            at the time of decoupling, 4&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>5</sup> years after the big
            bang.</Paragraph>
        </SubSection></Section>
      <Section
        id="SEC007">
        <Title>7 The primordial nuclear abundances</Title>
        <SubSection
          id="SEC007_001">
          <Title>7.1 Introduction</Title>
          <Paragraph>So far we have presented two pieces of evidence pointing to the occurrence of a
            big bang: the redshift of the galaxies (indicating the continuing expansion of the
            Universe), and the 3 K radiation (the remnant of the primordial radiation). But there is
            a third imprint such a big bang ought to have left on our present-day world. We cannot
            at this juncture trace out the full sequence of events following the instant of the big
            bang (that can only be done after we have worked through the next two units). But
            regardless of the exact details of the sequence, <i>any</i> big bang scenario is likely
            to have passed through the stage referred to in <CrossRef
              idref="SEC005_002">Section 5.2</CrossRef> where there was a plasma of electrons,
            protons, and neutrons. As this cooled, nuclei (and later still, atoms) would have formed
            in certain proportions. Whatever these proportions were, they ought to be reflected in
            the relative abundances of the different elements we find in the present-day Universe.
            The idea therefore is to try and calculate the primordial nuclear abundances, and
            compare them with what exists now. If there is agreement, then that will be a third
            piece of evidence for our model of the big bang.</Paragraph>
        </SubSection>
        <!--<Paragraph>temperature of matter</Paragraph>-->
        <SubSection
          id="SEC007_002">
          <Title>7.2 The temperature of matter and radiation</Title>
          <Paragraph>The different reactions by which neutrons and protons came together soon after
            the instant of the big bang to produce heavier nuclei will have proceeded at different
            rates according to the energies of the particles involved. The first step in calculating
            nuclear abundances is therefore to make some assumption about these
            energies.</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>The particles at any instant have a wide range of energies; this obviously
            complicates matters. Fortunately, however, it is possible to make one very important
            simplification. This is based on the concept of <i>equilibrium</i>. We have already
            touched on this topic in the context of our discussion of the origin of the 3 K
            radiation. Let us now look into it in a little more detail:</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>We use an analogy. Suppose that a large number of molecules of an ordinary gas
            are introduced into an insulated container. To all external appearances, the state of
            the gas does not change with time. It is at a fixed pressure and a fixed temperature and
            is said to be in equilibrium. Of course, on a microscopic scale, a great deal is
            happening as the molecules collide with one another. Nevertheless, the measurable
            properties of the gas remain effectively constant. The reason for this is that the
            distribution of energy among the molecules fluctuates to only a very small extent about
            a well-defined average pattern. Thus, although the energy of any given molecule
            continually changes as it collides with others, details like the most probable energy
            for a molecule, or the probability of a molecule having an energy greater than, say,
              10<sup>&#x2212;20</sup> J are preserved. Now it turns out that, once the temperature
            of the gas has been specified, it is possible to predict the average pattern of energy
            distribution in the gas at equilibrium &#x2013; the <i>temperature of matter</i> serves
            as a label for the average mixture of energies of the gas molecules. For example, the
            most probable energy for a molecule is proportional to the temperature, and could, in
            the absence of a thermometer, be used to define the temperature scale.</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>If we now have a mixture of gas and radiation, and these are allowed to come
            into equilibrium with each other, not only will the particles of the gas adopt a
            characteristic energy distribution, but so also will the photons of the radiation. As we
            discussed earlier in connection with the microwave radiation, this distribution of
            photon energies is known as a thermal spectrum, and is rather different from the
            Maxwell-Boltzmann distribution for molecules. Nevertheless, the distribution can again
            be labelled by a single number &#x2013; the <i>temperature of radiation</i>. This is
            defined to be proportional to the most probable energy (or frequency) of a photon. Our
            two temperature scales for matter and for radiation are consistent in that, whenever
            radiation is in equilibrium with matter, the values of the two temperatures
            agree.</Paragraph>
          <!--<Paragraph>temperature of radiation</Paragraph>-->
          <Paragraph>Returning now to the early Universe, it is important to realise that the very
            high density of matter and radiation at that time gave rise to a frequency of collisions
            between protons, neutrons, electrons, and photons sufficiently high to ensure that the
            various components of the Universe were in almost perfect equilibrium. Thus, their
            respective distributions of energies could be labelled by a <i>single</i> common
            temperature. The electrons had the same temperature as the protons and the neutrons and
            the photons, because the collisions were so frequent that no part of the Universe could
            get out of step with the rest. This is very important because it allows us to replace
            the great complexity of the possible energy distributions by a single parameter &#x2013;
            the temperature.</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>Strictly speaking, the various equilibria &#x2013; between particles, and
            between particles and radiation &#x2013; can never have been quite perfect because the
            Universe was expanding all the time, and therefore cooling rapidly. There was therefore
            never a steady approach to a final condition such as we associate with the behaviour of,
            say, a cup of coffee cooling to equilibrium with its surroundings. Indeed, as we have
            pointed out before, the Universe has still not reached equilibrium. Nevertheless, there
            was near-equilibrium in the early Universe because of the high rate of
            collisions.</Paragraph>
        </SubSection>
        <SubSection
          id="SEC007_003">
          <Title>7.3 The formation of light nuclei</Title>
          <Paragraph>It is the very high temperatures that make the early stages of the big bang
            relatively simple to calculate. When it comes to the formation of the first nuclei, we
            are looking at a temperature that has dropped to about 10<sup>9</sup> K, this being
            achieved approximately 3 minutes after the instant of the big bang. For nuclei to form,
            the temperature must still be high enough that charged nuclei can approach each other
            closely &#x2013; despite the electrostatic repulsion between their positive charges
            &#x2013; thus allowing further fusion to take place. On the other hand, if the
            temperature is too high, any nuclei that are formed will immediately be disrupted again
            by a subsequent violent collision with another particle.</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>The only particles taking part (to any significant extent) in the reactions at
            this time were neutrons, protons, electrons, and photons. In addition there were
            neutrinos &#x2013; a very weakly interacting particle. The simplest reaction, and
            perhaps the most important as far as cosmology is concerned, is the fusion of a neutron
            (n) and a proton (p) to give a deuteron, d (i.e. a deuterium nucleus) plus a photon of
            sufficiently high energy to be called a gamma ray (<InlineEquation><Image
                src="gamma.gif"/><Description/></InlineEquation>):</Paragraph>
          <Equation
            id="EQN000_015"><Image
              src="S357_1_e021i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
          <Paragraph>Note that the energy is mostly carried away by the gamma ray. This is essential
            if the neutron and proton are to bind, for otherwise the neutron and proton would simply
            bounce apart again. The probability of this fusion reaction occurring is high, as is
            that of the reverse reaction, in which a gamma ray destroys a deuteron.</Paragraph>
          <!--<Paragraph>baryonic density</Paragraph>
<Paragraph>baryons</Paragraph>-->
          <Paragraph>As we have noted, significant numbers of deuterons could form and remain
            undisturbed only after the temperature had dropped to about 10<sup>9</sup> K. On the
            other hand, by the time the temperature had dropped to about
              5&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>8</sup> K, at 20 minutes after the big bang, the density had
            become so reduced that there were now no longer sufficient collisions taking place to
            produce many deuterons. Deuteron formation was therefore confined to the period during
            which the temperature fell between these two values.</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>More complicated nuclei can be produced by similar reactions. For example,
            helium (<sup>4</sup>He) can be formed through the fusion of two deuterons:</Paragraph>
          <Equation
            id="EQN000_016"><Image
              src="S357_1_e016i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
          <Paragraph>But there are also several other ways in which it can be formed, each involving
            two steps. For example:</Paragraph>
          <Equation
            id="EQN000_017"><Image
              src="S357_1_e017i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
          <Equation
            id="EQN000_018"><Image
              src="S357_1_e018i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
          <Paragraph>and</Paragraph>
          <Equation
            id="EQN000_019"><Image
              src="S357_1_e019i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
          <Equation
            id="EQN000_020"><Image
              src="S357_1_e020i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
          <Paragraph>where <sup>3</sup>H is a tritium nucleus (a triton), i.e. the nuclear isotope
            of hydrogen consisting of a proton and two neutrons.</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>Each of the above reactions can occur in either direction. Thus, for example,
            corresponding to Reaction 20 there will be its reverse:</Paragraph>
          <Equation
            id="EQN001_020a"><Image
              src="S357_1_e020ai.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
          <Paragraph>Given sufficient time, an equilibrium state would arise whereby the particles
            present will yield the same rate for Reaction 20a as for Reaction 20. And the same will
            apply for each of the other reactions. Thus, corresponding to any particular temperature
            (the temperature governing the reaction rates) it is possible to estimate the
            proportions of the various particles that would be present once equilibrium had been
            established. This estimate is independent of whether equilibrium was reached quickly
            (under conditions of high density where the interactions happen frequently) or slowly
            (under low-density conditions).</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>So much for the density-independent equilibrium state achieved over a lengthy
            period of time. But the case of the big bang is different. The matter was rapidly
            dispersed only a short time after the mixture of neutrons and protons had started the
            chain of fusion processes. Under these circumstances, the final abundances of nuclides
            depended on how many collisions were able to take place before the dispersion
            effectively brought the processes to a halt. This in turn means that the final mix of
            particles <i>is</i> expected to depend on the density. More specifically, it is
            encounters with protons and neutrons that are significant, so it is the cosmic density
            of protons, neutrons and matter based on protons and neutrons that is important. This
            particular contribution to the overall density of the Universe is known as the
              <i>baryonic density</i>, since the proton and neutron are the lightest members of a
            family of particles known as <i>baryons</i>.
            <!--In keeping with the convention introduced in Unit 10&#x0026;11, -->We shall
            represent the average mass density of baryonic matter in the Universe as
              <i>&#x3C1;</i><sub>b</sub>/<i>c</i><sup>2</sup>, preserving the symbol
              <i>&#x3C1;</i><sub>b</sub> for the associated energy density
            of<!-- Roughly speaking, you can think of the baryonic density as the density of &#x2018;ordinary&#x2019; matter. You are essentially made of baryonic matter as are the Earth, the Sun and all familiar objects.-->
            baryonic matter. Thus, the baryonic density prevailing at the time of nuclear synthesis
            had an important part to play in governing the relative abundances of the light elements
            formed.</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>Roughly speaking, you can think of the baryonic density as the density of
            &#x2018;ordinary&#x2019; matter. You are essentially made of baryonic matter as are the
            Earth, the Sun and all familiar objects.</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>There is a second reason why the baryonic density was important. It arises from
            the fact that while these fusion reactions were taking place, free neutrons (those that
            had not yet been incorporated into nuclei) were decaying:</Paragraph>
          <Equation
            id="UEQN001_0008"><Image
              src="S357_1_ue008i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
          <Paragraph>where <InlineEquation><Image
                src="S357_1_ie001i.gif"/><Description/></InlineEquation> is an
            antineutrino.</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>Unlike the fusion reactions, the rate for this decay is independent of baryonic
            density. Thus when the baryonic density changes, the balance between the two types of
            reaction changes. At low densities, a neutron travels further before colliding with
            another baryon, so it has a <i>greater</i> chance of decaying before being captured into
            a nucleus. Contrast this with collision reactions which have <i>less</i> probability of
            occurring at low densities. It is these different dependences on density that provide
            the second reason why the final mix of nuclei will depend on the baryonic density during
            the period of nuclear synthesis.</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>Now let us take a look at the result of detailed calculations. The rate of each
            reaction depends on the concentrations of the parent nuclei, on experimentally
            determined relationships between the reaction probability and the energies of the
            particles, and on the relationship between the equilibrium distribution of energies and
            the temperature. To find out the net effect of all the reactions is, mathematically,
            simply a matter of solving simultaneous differential equations; but they must be solved
            numerically, and judgement must be exercised in interpolating the experimental data. It
            is a lengthy computer calculation, even though it is basically straightforward. Several
            groups have made these calculations. We show the results of one particular investigation
            in <CrossRef
              idref="FIG001_028">Figure 31</CrossRef>.</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph><CrossRef
              idref="FIG001_028">Figure 31</CrossRef> is based on a model with an assumed value of
            the baryonic density as it is today, <i>&#x3C1;</i><sub>b,now</sub>, from which one can
            extrapolate back in time to what it would have been at the time of the primordial
            nuclear synthesis (making due allowance for the expansion of the Universe between those
            two times). The <i>mass fractions</i> of the various nuclei were calculated as a
            function of time. Since the temperature at a given time can be calculated, the
            horizontal scales are marked with temperature (at the top) as well as time elapsed since
            the big bang (at the bottom).</Paragraph>
          <Figure
            id="FIG001_028"><Image
              id="FIG001_028"
              src="S357_1_028i.jpg"/>
            <Caption>
              <b>Figure 31</b>: Evolution of nuclear abundances during the expansion of a typical
              model of the big bang. The vertical scale shows what fraction of the total mass the
              various types of nucleus form at different times. Note: H, He, Li and Be stand for the
              nuclei of hydrogen, helium, lithium and beryllium respectively, and the superscript
              indicates the mass of the isotope (e.g. <sup>3</sup>He is the isotope of helium
              containing two protons and one neutron). The deuteron is signified by d, and the
              nucleus of tritium (two neutrons + one proton) by t.</Caption>
            <SourceReference>from M.S. Smith, L.H. Kawano and R.A. Malaney (1993) <i>The Astrophys.
                J. Supp.</i>, 85, 219&#x2013;47 <ItemRights>
                <OwnerRef/>
                <ItemRef/>
                <ItemAcknowledgement>from M.S. Smith, L.H. Kawano and R.A. Malaney (1993) <i>The
                    Astrophys. J. Supp.</i>, 85, 219&#x2013;47</ItemAcknowledgement>
              </ItemRights>
            </SourceReference>
            <Description/>
          </Figure>
          <Paragraph>Look first at the basic particles: neutrons and protons. Initially, at time 1
            second, we have essentially 13% neutrons and 87% protons. This ratio can be calculated
            with confidence as it depends only on the mass difference between neutrons and protons.
            <!--&#x0028;We must postpone to Unit 15 a discussion of the processes occurring at epochs earlier than that of nuclear synthesis, during which this mix of neutrons and protons was established.&#x0029;--></Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>As far as we are concerned, the interesting action starts just above
              10<sup>9</sup> K, the temperature at which the proton and neutron numbers begin to
            drop because they are being used up in thermonuclear reactions (similar numbers of
            neutrons and protons are used up &#x2013; it is only the logarithmic scale that makes
            the drop in the proton curve almost invisible). Some elements, such as helium (both the
            normal <sup>4</sup>He and its isotope <sup>3</sup>He), show no decrease, with the main
            production close to 10<sup>9</sup> K. The deuterium concentration, on the other hand,
            increases rapidly at temperatures around 10<sup>9</sup> K, but later (below
              6&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>8</sup> K) the concentration falls a little, because more
            deuterium is being used in making helium than is being synthesised from raw neutrons and
            protons. The point is that at this stage we are dealing with periods of time comparable
            to the mean lifetime of the neutron (930 s, i.e. about 15 minutes). Neutrons are being
            removed by decay &#x2013; note the steady decline in its curve &#x2013; and are thus no
            longer available for synthesising deuterons. However, there are still collisions going
            on that are destroying the deuterons. From a cosmologist's point of view, this is the
            crucial stage. The <i>greater</i> the baryonic density of the Universe at that time, the
            longer the process of deuteron destruction can continue after the synthesis of deuterons
            has effectively ceased, and therefore, the <i>lower</i> the final concentration of
            deuterium. It is true that this effect is partly offset by the fact that in a denser
            Universe, more deuterium would have been formed in the first place. But the destruction
            of deuterium is more sensitive to density than is its initial formation.</Paragraph>
          <!--<Paragraph>mass fraction</Paragraph>-->
          <Paragraph>Below about 4&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>8</sup> K, all the nuclide mass fractions
            &#x2013; apart from the decaying neutrons and tritons, the latter decaying to
              <sup>3</sup>He &#x2013; are more or less constant because the thermonuclear reactions
            are then so slow. The most important feature of <CrossRef
              idref="FIG001_028">Figure 31</CrossRef> is the set of &#x2018;freeze-out&#x2019;
            values of the elemental mass fractions to be found at the extreme right-hand side. This
            set of values corresponds to the particular assumption made about baryonic density. A
            different assumption for the baryonic density now (and hence at earlier times) would
            have led to a different set of curves, and these in turn would be expected to yield a
            different set of freeze-out values.</Paragraph>
          <!--<Paragraph>Objective 9</Paragraph>-->
          <SAQ
            id="SAQ001_015">
            <Heading>Question 15</Heading>
            <Question>
              <Paragraph>Imagine a universe that differs from ours in that neutrons live twice as
                long, on average, as they do in our Universe, but the Hubble constant and the
                baryonic density have the same values as ours. On the basis of Reactions 15 to 20,
                would inhabitants of that universe expect to find more or less deuterium left over
                from the first 20 minutes of their universe than is left over from the first 20
                minutes of ours?</Paragraph>
            </Question>
            <Answer>
              <Paragraph>Other things being equal, the increase in neutron lifetime will mean that
                more deuterium is formed in the reaction</Paragraph>
              <Equation
                id="EQN000_015a"><Image
                  src="S357_1_e021i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
              <Paragraph>and more is destroyed in the reaction</Paragraph>
              <Equation
                id="EQN000_019a"><Image
                  src="S357_1_e022i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
              <Paragraph>eventually producing <sup>4</sup>He in the reaction</Paragraph>
              <Equation
                id="EQN000_020a"><Image
                  src="S357_1_e023i.gif"/><Description/></Equation>
              <Paragraph>In their universe, the increase of neutron lifetime will mean that at any
                point in time there will be more neutrons in their universe than in ours. Moreover,
                the <i>ratio</i> of neutrons in their universe to neutrons in ours will steadily
                increase with time. Thus although at the time when Reaction 15 is important their
                rate of formation of deuterium will be somewhat faster than ours, by the time the
                later Reaction 19 comes into its own their rate of destroying deuterium will be
                greater still in comparison with ours. Thus, deuterium will be formed more readily,
                but <i>destroyed even more readily</i>. The net result will be that they find
                  <i>less</i> deuterium than we do.</Paragraph>
            </Answer>
          </SAQ>
          <Paragraph><CrossRef
              idref="FIG001_029">Figure 32</CrossRef> shows how the computed freeze-out mass
            fractions of light nuclei depend on the assumed present-day value of the baryonic
            density. As you can see, the freeze-out abundance of <sup>4</sup>He is almost
            independent of the present baryonic density, whereas the freeze-out abundance of
            deuterium <sup>2</sup>H depends very sensitively on <i>&#x3C1;</i><sub>b,now</sub>. The
            most abundant nuclide of hydrogen (<sup>1</sup>H) is not shown, but if it had been
            shown, it too would have been relatively insensitive to the present baryonic density,
            its mass fraction being about 0.75.</Paragraph>
          <Figure
            id="FIG001_029"><Image
              id="FIG001_029"
              src="S357_1_029i.jpg"/>
            <Caption>
              <b>Figure 32</b>: Predicted freeze-out mass fractions (at around 10<sup>4</sup> s
              after the big bang) for various light nuclei plotted against the assumed present-day
              mass density of baryonic matter,
              <i>&#x3C1;</i><sub>b,now</sub>/<i>c</i><sup>2</sup></Caption>
            <SourceReference>adapted from R.V. Wagoner (1973) <i>The Astrophys. J.</i>, 179(2), 349
                <ItemRights>
                <OwnerRef/>
                <ItemRef/>
                <ItemAcknowledgement>adapted from R.V. Wagoner (1973) <i>The Astrophys. J.</i>,
                  179(2), 349</ItemAcknowledgement>
              </ItemRights>
            </SourceReference>
            <Description/>
          </Figure>
        </SubSection>
        <SubSection
          id="SEC007_004">
          <Title>7.4 Nuclear abundances as evidence for the big bang</Title>
          <Paragraph>What we have seen is that a theoretical model based on the assumption that
            there was a big bang, and incorporating an assumption about the present-day value of the
            baryonic density, <i>&#x3C1;</i><sub>b,now</sub>, leads to definite predictions as to
            what the nuclear abundances must have been when the elements froze-out. This, therefore,
            provides us with a third way of checking out the big bang hypothesis: Do the present-day
            cosmic nuclear abundances agree with these predictions for any plausible value of the
            present-day baryonic density?</Paragraph>
          <!--<Paragraph>nuclear synthesis</Paragraph>


<Paragraph>The terms <i>nuclear synthesis</i> and <i>nucleosynthesis</i> can be used interchangeably.</Paragraph>-->
          <Paragraph>Obtaining an answer to this question is not as easy as one might think. The
            trouble is that since the freeze-out abundances were established, about 20 minutes after
            the big bang, further modifications to the nuclear abundances have been going on. The
            story of most matter is that it exists for a few hundred million years as a rarefied
            gas, and then is slowly drawn into a star, where its nuclear composition is altered
            because it is heated up to temperatures at which further nuclear reactions take place.
            Because the temperature and density conditions in a star are very different from those
            encountered during the big bang epoch of <i>nuclear synthesis</i>, the thermonuclear
            reactions in stars are different, and they lead to a different mix of end products.
            Therefore, the freeze-out concentrations of the various elements <i>are not reflected
              directly in the abundances found in stars</i>, or indeed on the Earth which itself
            condensed out of stellar matter thrown out of stars during supernova
            explosions.</Paragraph>
          <!--<Paragraph>Objective 9</Paragraph>-->
          <SAQ
            id="SAQ001_016">
            <Heading>Question 16</Heading>
            <Question>
              <Paragraph><CrossRef
                  idref="FIG001_030">Figure 33</CrossRef> shows in a schematic way the conditions of
                temperature and density under which cosmological nuclear reactions are important
                (region on the left), and the conditions for stellar nuclear reactions (region on
                the right).</Paragraph>
              <Figure
                id="FIG001_030"><Image
                  id="FIG001_030"
                  src="S357_1_030i.jpg"/>
                <Caption>
                  <b>Figure 33</b>: Conditions under which fusion reactions occur</Caption>
                <Description/>
              </Figure>
              <!--<BulletedList>
 <ListItem>--><Paragraph>(a) Why is the area between A and B
                inclined to the axes rather than being
                vertical?</Paragraph><!--</ListItem>
<ListItem>--><Paragraph>(b) Why does the area
                for the nucleosynthesis in the big bang not continue above
                A?</Paragraph><!--</ListItem>
<ListItem>--><Paragraph>(c) Why does it not continue
                to the left of B?</Paragraph><!--</ListItem>
<ListItem>--><Paragraph>(d) Why does
                the area for stars not continue below
              C?</Paragraph><!--</ListItem>
</BulletedList>-->
            </Question>
            <Answer>
              <Paragraph><b>(a)</b> While the Universe was expanding and the density decreasing
                during the big bang, the temperature dropped. (A universe that was perfectly uniform
                at all stages would be shown as a line between A and B. We have chosen to show a
                narrow area instead, corresponding to some non-uniformities of density and
                temperature.)</Paragraph>
              <Paragraph><b>(b)</b> Above A, collision energies were too high for nuclei to hold
                together.</Paragraph>
              <Paragraph><b>(c)</b> Because of the reduced density to the left of B, collisions
                occur too infrequently to have much importance.</Paragraph>
              <Paragraph><b>(d)</b> Below C, because the nuclei are moving slowly they have
                difficulty in overcoming the electrostatic repulsion between their charges, and thus
                getting close enough for fusion to take place. For this reason, fusion reactions
                proceed only slowly and the energy release is not sufficient to make the body glow
                (and by definition, stars give off light). This region would correspond to planets,
                rather than stars. Jupiter, for instance, our largest planet, misses being a star by
                a factor of about 50.</Paragraph>
              <Paragraph>These additional conditions have been included in <CrossRef
                  idref="FIG001_035">Figure
                34</CrossRef><!-- &#x0028;overleaf&#x0029;-->.</Paragraph>
              <Figure
                id="FIG001_035"><Image
                  id="FIG001_035"
                  src="S357_1_035i.jpg"/>
                <Caption>
                  <b>Figure 34</b>: Further limits on fusion reactions</Caption>
                <Description/>
              </Figure>
            </Answer>
          </SAQ>
          <!--<Figure id="FIG001_030"><Image id="FIG001_030" src="S357_1_030i.jpg"/>
<Caption>
<b>Figure 34</b>: Conditions under which fusion reactions occur</Caption>
<Description/>
</Figure>

<BulletedList>
 <ListItem><Paragraph>Why is the area between A and B inclined to the axes rather than being vertical&#x003F;</Paragraph></ListItem>
<ListItem><Paragraph>Why does the area for the nucleosynthesis in the big bang not continue above A&#x003F;</Paragraph></ListItem>
<ListItem><Paragraph>Why does it not continue to the left of B&#x003F;</Paragraph></ListItem>
<ListItem><Paragraph>Why does the area for stars not continue below C&#x003F;</Paragraph></ListItem>
</BulletedList>-->
          <Paragraph>The ways in which present-day observations of abundances can be compared with
            the predicted abundances at freeze-out are best considered by treating each of the
            relevant nuclei in turn.</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>First, we can note that there is good evidence from a wide range of
            astronomical bodies that the <sup>1</sup>H nuclide is the most common. This fits well
            with the freeze-out predictions, but is hardly conclusive. For more detailed insight we
            need to look at how the abundances of other nuclei (as expressed by their mass
            fractions) compare with that of <sup>1</sup>H.</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>Turning to the second most abundant nuclide, <sup>4</sup>He, we must confront
            the problem that much of the helium in the present-day Universe has been produced in
            stars. Fortunately, stars also produce other, heavier elements, and we can use these to
            determine how much of the helium in any region is the result of stellar processing
            rather than the big bang. Most stars are not hot enough to show helium lines in their
            spectra, and those that do are unsuitable for primordial abundance measurements.
            Instead, helium is best measured in the clouds of diffuse glowing gas that astronomers
            call HII regions, and even these clouds are best studied in smaller galaxies where there
            has been less stellar processing than in our own Galaxy.</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>One way of proceeding is to use spectral techniques to measure both the helium
            mass fraction and the relative abundance of oxygen nuclei for a number of extragalactic
            HII regions. Once the measurements have been made (and the uncertainties in those
            observations estimated) a plot such as that shown in <CrossRef
              idref="FIG001_031">Figure 35</CrossRef> can be compiled. By extrapolating the data
            back to zero relative abundance of oxygen, a &#x2018;primordial&#x2019; value for the
            helium mass fraction can be deduced. <CrossRef
              idref="FIG001_031">Figure 35</CrossRef> implies a value of about 0.23 for this
            primordial helium mass fraction, in line with several other attempts to determine this
            quantity.</Paragraph>
          <Figure
            id="FIG001_031"><Image
              id="FIG001_031"
              src="S357_1_031i.jpg"/>
            <Caption>
              <b>Figure 35</b>: A plot of observed helium mass fraction against relative abundance
              of oxygen to hydrogen, expressed as 10<sup>6</sup>&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;(number of oxygen
              nuclei)/(number of hydrogen nuclei), for several extragalactic HII regions. (Based on
              measurements by B. Pagel and colleagues)</Caption>
            <SourceReference>B.E.J.Pagel <i>et al.</i> (1992) <i>Monthly Notices of the RAS</i>,
              255, 325&#x2013;45 <ItemRights>
                <OwnerRef/>
                <ItemRef/>
                <ItemAcknowledgement>B.E.J.Pagel <i>et al.</i> (1992) <i>Monthly Notices of the
                    RAS</i>, 255, 325&#x2013;45</ItemAcknowledgement>
              </ItemRights>
            </SourceReference>
            <Description/>
          </Figure>
          <Paragraph>Comparing this &#x2018;observed&#x2019; primordial helium mass fraction (0.23)
            with the predicted values in <CrossRef
              idref="FIG001_029">Figure 32</CrossRef>, there is a reasonable level of agreement for
            a range of present-day baryonic densities.</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>The abundance of <sup>3</sup>He is less useful. A number of observational
            difficulties make it very hard to deduce anything reliable about the primordial
            abundance. The comparison of prediction and measurement has little to offer in this
            case.</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>The present-day abundance of <sup>7</sup>Li can be deduced from spectral
            studies of metal-poor dwarf stars. The outer layers of these stars are believed to be
            relatively unchanged since they were formed. Most share the same lithium abundance
            despite having different amounts of other elements and different masses. This makes it
            probable that the lithium in these outer stellar layers has not been processed, and thus
            gives a direct indication of the primordial mass fraction of lithium. The observations
            favour a <sup>7</sup>Li mass fraction close to
              8&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;10</sup>. According to <CrossRef
              idref="FIG001_029">Figure 32</CrossRef>, this corresponds to a present-day mass
            density of baryonic matter of around (1 to 5)&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;28</sup>
            kg m<sup>&#x2212;3</sup>.</Paragraph>
          <Paragraph>Finally consider the case of deuterium, <sup>2</sup>H. Deuterium is destroyed
            in stars so its currently observed mass fraction provides a lower limit on its
            primordial mass fraction. This lower limit is about
              3&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;5</sup> to
            7&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;5</sup>, consistent (according to <CrossRef
              idref="FIG001_029">Figure 32</CrossRef>) with present-day baryonic mass densities of
            about 5&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;28</sup>kg m<sup>&#x2212;3</sup> or
            less.</Paragraph>
          <!--<Paragraph>Bringing all of the observed abundances together, it does seem that they are consistent with the predicted p--><Paragraph>Bringing
            all of the observed abundances together, it does seem that they are consistent with the
            predicted primordial abundances (<CrossRef
              idref="FIG001_029">Figure 32</CrossRef>), provided the present-day baryonic mass
            density is around 10<sup>&#x2212;28</sup> kg m<sup>&#x2212;3</sup>.</Paragraph>
          <!--rimordial abundances &#x0028;<CrossRef idref="FIG001_029">Figure 32</CrossRef>&#x0029;, provided the present-day baryonic mass density is around 10<sup>&#x2212;28</sup> kg m<sup>&#x2212;3</sup>.</Paragraph>-->
          <Paragraph>Pleasingly, at least to those who like consistency, a present-day baryonic mass
            density of a few times 10<sup>&#x2212;28</sup> kg m<sup>&#x2212;3</sup> is in excellent
            agreement with the rather precise value of
              <i>&#x3C1;</i><sub>b,now</sub>/<i>c</i><sup>2</sup> deduced by those who attempt to
            deduce cosmological parameters from the observed anisotropies in the cosmic microwave
            background radiation (as described in <CrossRef
              idref="SEC006_003">Section 6.3</CrossRef>). The fact that there is a narrow range of
            values for the present-day baryonic densities in which the predicted and
            &#x2018;observed&#x2019; light nuclear abundances agree, is a significant success for
            big bang cosmology. The fact that this narrow range of baryonic densities includes the
            value deduced by a quite different technique is a truly remarkable
            achievement.</Paragraph>
        </SubSection></Section>
      <Section
        id="SEC008">
        <Title>8 Conclusion</Title>
        <Paragraph>We have seen that there are three independent pieces of evidence, all of which
          point to the occurrence of a big bang: (i) the recession of the galaxies; (ii) the cosmic
          microwave background; and (iii) the comparison between the calculated primordial nuclear
          abundances and the present-day composition of matter in the Universe. For these various
          reasons, the vast majority of cosmologists today accept that there was a big bang. This
          acceptance has been given extra support by the agreement between the value of the
          present-day baryonic mass density indicated by abundance measurements, and the value of
          that same quantity deduced from anisotropies in the cosmic background
          radiation.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>In this unit, we have seen two snapshots of the development of the Universe: the
          period of nuclear synthesis which shaped today's nuclear abundances; and the later period
          of decoupling from which emerged today's 3 K radiation.
          <!--Later in this Block, you will see -->In looking at how these two epochs fit into the
          overall pattern of the Universe's evolution, one of the aims is to try and push our
          description as far back in time as we can towards the very instant of the big bang;
          another is to look as far ahead into the future as we can so as to uncover what might be
          the likely end of the Universe.</Paragraph>
      </Section>
      <Section
        id="SEC009">
        <Title>Summary</Title>
        <Paragraph>1 The visible matter in the Universe, stars and interstellar gas, is concentrated
          into galaxies, which are collections of &#x223C;10<sup>11</sup> stars. The galaxies
          themselves are usually to be found in clusters with typically tens or hundreds of members.
          The clusters, in their turn, are loosely associated in superclusters.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>2 Distances are estimated via a series of intercalibrated techniques, each
          overlapping with and extending further than the previous one. The principal stages
          are:</Paragraph>
        <BulletedList>
          <ListItem>
            <Paragraph>Earth&#x2013;Moon and Earth&#x2013;Sun distances involving radar
              ranging;</Paragraph>
          </ListItem>
          <ListItem>
            <Paragraph>Triangulation to nearer stars, using the diameter of the Earth's orbit as
              baseline;</Paragraph>
          </ListItem>
          <ListItem>
            <Paragraph>Calibration of luminosity against temperature for typical stars, using the
              stars of the Hyades cluster;</Paragraph>
          </ListItem>
          <ListItem>
            <Paragraph>Period-luminosity relationship for Cepheids, first for stars in our Galaxy,
              then in other galaxies;</Paragraph>
          </ListItem>
          <ListItem>
            <Paragraph>Type Ia supernovae, first in nearer, then in further-off galaxies;
              Classification of galaxies into recognisable types, of different
              luminosities.</Paragraph>
          </ListItem>
        </BulletedList>
        <Paragraph>Independent checks are provided by radio galaxies and observations of Type II
          supernovae.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>3 The spectra of light emitted by the stars of distant galaxies is redshifted,
          such that the redshift, <i>z</i>, is proportional to the distance of the
          galaxy.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>4 This cosmological redshift finds a natural explanation in terms of the galaxies
          receding from us (and from each other), in accordance with Hubble's law. This is the first
          indication that the Universe began with a big bang.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>5 Radio astronomers have detected microwave radiation (i.e. radiation with
          wavelengths in the region of 1 cm) coming almost isotropically from all directions, with a
          thermal spectrum which tallies, as far as can be measured, with that expected from
          calculations based on the big bang model. No convincing alternative explanations have so
          far been advanced. This 3 K radiation therefore provides good evidence both for there
          having been a big bang, and for the isotropy of the Universe at the time when the
          radiation decoupled from matter, 4&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>5</sup> years
          later.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>6 If the Earth at present is moving with respect to the 3 K radiation, which we
          assume is the same as the &#x2018;rest frame&#x2019; of the Universe at the time of
          decoupling, the angular distribution of the intensity of the radiation would be slightly
          distorted in a characteristic way. Measurements indicate that the Earth <i>does</i> have
          such a velocity, with a magnitude of about 400 km s<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>7 If galaxies, or clusters of galaxies, had already begun to form at a time
          considerably less than 10<sup>7</sup> years after the big bang, one would have expected
          pre-existent inhomogeneities in the matter distribution to have left a trace of their
          presence by imparting some intensity variation to the angular distribution of the 3 K
          radiation. Such inhomogeneities have now been detected at the level of 1 part in 100
          000.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>8 If there has been a hot big bang, we would expect the material produced to
          consist of 23% by mass of helium, the rest being mostly hydrogen, with traces of other
          light elements.</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>9 Detailed comparisons of predicted primordial nuclear mass fractions with those
          deduced from observations also constrain the value of the present-day baryonic mass
          density. A value of 4 or 5 &#xD7;10<sup>&#x2212;28</sup> kg m<sup>&#x2212;3</sup> fits
          well with both the nuclear abundance data and the data on anisotropies in the cosmic
          microwave background radiation.</Paragraph>
        <Box
          id="BOX00A">
          <Heading>Do this</Heading>
          <Paragraph>Now you have completed this unit, you might like to:</Paragraph>
          <BulletedList>
            <ListItem>
              <Paragraph>Post a message to the unit forum.</Paragraph>
            </ListItem>
            <ListItem>
              <Paragraph>Review or add to your Learning Journal.</Paragraph>
            </ListItem>
            <ListItem>
              <Paragraph>Rate this unit.</Paragraph>
            </ListItem>
          </BulletedList>
        </Box>
        <Box
          id="BOX00B">
          <Heading>Try this</Heading>
          <Paragraph>You might also like to:</Paragraph>
          <BulletedList>
            <ListItem>
              <Paragraph>Find out more about the related <a
                  href="http://www3.open.ac.uk/courses/bin/p12.dll?C01S357"
                  target="_blank">Open University course</a></Paragraph>
            </ListItem>
            <ListItem>
              <Paragraph>Book a FlashMeeting to talk live with other learners</Paragraph>
            </ListItem>
            <ListItem>
              <Paragraph>Create a Knowledge Map to summarise this topic.</Paragraph>
            </ListItem>
          </BulletedList>
        </Box>
      </Section>
    </Session>
    <BackMatter>
      <Acknowledgements>
        <Heading>Acknowledgements</Heading>
        <Paragraph>The material acknowledged below is Proprietary and used under licence and not
          subject to Creative Commons licensing <a
            href="http://openlearn.open.ac.uk/mod/resource/view.php?id=15"
            target="_blank">(see terms and conditions)</a>.</Paragraph>
        <Heading>Figures</Heading>
        <Paragraph>Grateful acknowledgement is made to the following sources for material used in
          this Unit:</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph><b><i>Figures 2, 5, 8, 11, 13 and 14b:</i></b> from Hale Observatories;
        </Paragraph>
        <Paragraph><b><i>Figure 6a,b:</i></b> based on H. Arp (1960) in <i>Astronomical J.</i>, 65,
          426;</Paragraph>
        <Paragraph><b><i>Figure 7:</i></b> from <i>Le Grand Atlas de l'Astronomie</i>, Encyclopaedia
          Universalis editeur; </Paragraph>
        <Paragraph><b><i>Figure 10:</i></b> based on Erik Holmberg in E.M. and G.R. Burbidge (1975)
            <i>Galaxies and the Universe</i>, University of Chicago Press; </Paragraph>
        <Paragraph><b><i>Figure 12:</i></b> NASA/IPAC Extragalactic Database (NED), Jet Propulsion
          Laboratory, California Institute of Technology; </Paragraph>
        <Paragraph><b><i>Figure 14a:</i></b> courtesy of Uppsala University; </Paragraph>
        <Paragraph><b><i>Figure 15:</i>
          </b>based on E.P. Hubble (1929) in <i>Proc. Nat. Acad. Sci.</i>, 15, 168; </Paragraph>
        <Paragraph><b><i>Figure 17:</i></b> adapted from A. Sandage (1970) <i>Physics Today</i>,
          vol. 34, February 1970, American Institute of Physics; </Paragraph>
        <Paragraph><b><i>Figure 20a:</i></b> based on D.P. Woody <i>et al</i>. (1975) in <i>Phys.
            Rev. Lett.</i>, 34, 1036&#x2013;9; </Paragraph>
        <Paragraph><b><i>Figures 20b and 28:</i></b> based on R.A. Muller (1978) in <i>Scientific
            American</i>, 238, 64&#x2013;74; </Paragraph>
        <Paragraph><b><i>Figure 21:</i>
          </b>courtesy of NASA/CSFC and COBE Science Working Group; </Paragraph>
        <Paragraph><b><i>Figure 25:</i></b> courtesy of Dr A.A. Penzias; </Paragraph>
        <Paragraph><b><i>Figure 29:</i></b> courtesy of NASA Goddard Space Flight Center, Greenbelt,
          Maryland; </Paragraph>
        <Paragraph><b><i>Figure 30:</i></b> based on C.L. Bennett <i>et al</i>., (2003) <i>The
            Astrophys. J. Supp.</i>, 148(1), 1&#x2013;27; </Paragraph>
        <Paragraph><b><i>Figure 31:</i></b> from M.S. Smith, L.H. Kawano and R.A. Malaney (1993)
            <i>The Astrophys. J. Supp.</i>, <b>85</b>, 219&#x2013;47; </Paragraph>
        <Paragraph><b><i>Figure 32:</i>
          </b>adapted from R.V. Wagoner (1973) <i>The Astrophys. J.</i>, 179(2), 349; </Paragraph>
        <Paragraph><b><i>Figure 35:</i>
          </b>B.E.J. Pagel <i>et al</i>. (1992) <i>Monthly Notices of the RAS</i>, 255,
          325&#x2013;45.</Paragraph>
        <SubHeading>Unit image</SubHeading>
        <Paragraph>NASA: <a
            href="http://www.nasa.gov/home/index.html"
            target="_blank">http://www.nasa.gov/home/index.html</a> [Details correct as of 15th
          April 2008]</Paragraph>
      </Acknowledgements>
    </BackMatter>
  </Unit>
</Item>
