<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE learningContent
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Learning Content//EN" "learningContent.dtd">
<learningContent id="SEC007_004">
   <title>7.4 Nuclear abundances as evidence for the big bang</title>
   <learningContentbody>
      <section>
          
          <p>What we have seen is that a theoretical model based on the assumption that
            there was a big bang, and incorporating an assumption about the present-day value of the
            baryonic density, <i>ρ</i>
            <sub>b,now</sub>, leads to definite predictions as to
            what the nuclear abundances must have been when the elements froze-out. This, therefore,
            provides us with a third way of checking out the big bang hypothesis: Do the present-day
            cosmic nuclear abundances agree with these predictions for any plausible value of the
            present-day baryonic density?</p>
          
          <p>Obtaining an answer to this question is not as easy as one might think. The
            trouble is that since the freeze-out abundances were established, about 20 minutes after
            the big bang, further modifications to the nuclear abundances have been going on. The
            story of most matter is that it exists for a few hundred million years as a rarefied
            gas, and then is slowly drawn into a star, where its nuclear composition is altered
            because it is heated up to temperatures at which further nuclear reactions take place.
            Because the temperature and density conditions in a star are very different from those
            encountered during the big bang epoch of <i>nuclear synthesis</i>, the thermonuclear
            reactions in stars are different, and they lead to a different mix of end products.
            Therefore, the freeze-out concentrations of the various elements <i>are not reflected
              directly in the abundances found in stars</i>, or indeed on the Earth which itself
            condensed out of stellar matter thrown out of stars during supernova
            explosions.</p>
          
          <sectiondiv outputclass="SAQ">
            <p outputclass="Heading">
               <b>Question 16</b>
            </p>
            <sectiondiv outputclass="saq.question">
              <p>
                  <xref href="#FIG001_030">Figure 33</xref> shows in a schematic way the conditions of
                temperature and density under which cosmological nuclear reactions are important
                (region on the left), and the conditions for stellar nuclear reactions (region on
                the right).</p>
              <fig>
                  <title>
                     <b>Figure 33</b>: Conditions under which fusion reactions occur</title>
                  <image href="../../media/S357_1_030i.jpg"/>
                  <p/>
               </fig>
              <p>(a) Why is the area between A and B
                inclined to the axes rather than being
                vertical?</p>
               <p>(b) Why does the area
                for the nucleosynthesis in the big bang not continue above
                A?</p>
               <p>(c) Why does it not continue
                to the left of B?</p>
               <p>(d) Why does
                the area for stars not continue below
              C?</p>
            </sectiondiv>
            <sectiondiv outputclass="saq.answer">
              <p>
                  <b>(a)</b> While the Universe was expanding and the density decreasing
                during the big bang, the temperature dropped. (A universe that was perfectly uniform
                at all stages would be shown as a line between A and B. We have chosen to show a
                narrow area instead, corresponding to some non-uniformities of density and
                temperature.)</p>
              <p>
                  <b>(b)</b> Above A, collision energies were too high for nuclei to hold
                together.</p>
              <p>
                  <b>(c)</b> Because of the reduced density to the left of B, collisions
                occur too infrequently to have much importance.</p>
              <p>
                  <b>(d)</b> Below C, because the nuclei are moving slowly they have
                difficulty in overcoming the electrostatic repulsion between their charges, and thus
                getting close enough for fusion to take place. For this reason, fusion reactions
                proceed only slowly and the energy release is not sufficient to make the body glow
                (and by definition, stars give off light). This region would correspond to planets,
                rather than stars. Jupiter, for instance, our largest planet, misses being a star by
                a factor of about 50.</p>
              <p>These additional conditions have been included in <xref href="#FIG001_035">Figure
                34</xref>.</p>
              <fig>
                  <title>
                     <b>Figure 34</b>: Further limits on fusion reactions</title>
                  <image href="../../media/S357_1_035i.jpg"/>
                  <p/>
               </fig>
            </sectiondiv>
          </sectiondiv>
          
          <p>The ways in which present-day observations of abundances can be compared with
            the predicted abundances at freeze-out are best considered by treating each of the
            relevant nuclei in turn.</p>
          <p>First, we can note that there is good evidence from a wide range of
            astronomical bodies that the <sup>1</sup>H nuclide is the most common. This fits well
            with the freeze-out predictions, but is hardly conclusive. For more detailed insight we
            need to look at how the abundances of other nuclei (as expressed by their mass
            fractions) compare with that of <sup>1</sup>H.</p>
          <p>Turning to the second most abundant nuclide, <sup>4</sup>He, we must confront
            the problem that much of the helium in the present-day Universe has been produced in
            stars. Fortunately, stars also produce other, heavier elements, and we can use these to
            determine how much of the helium in any region is the result of stellar processing
            rather than the big bang. Most stars are not hot enough to show helium lines in their
            spectra, and those that do are unsuitable for primordial abundance measurements.
            Instead, helium is best measured in the clouds of diffuse glowing gas that astronomers
            call HII regions, and even these clouds are best studied in smaller galaxies where there
            has been less stellar processing than in our own Galaxy.</p>
          <p>One way of proceeding is to use spectral techniques to measure both the helium
            mass fraction and the relative abundance of oxygen nuclei for a number of extragalactic
            HII regions. Once the measurements have been made (and the uncertainties in those
            observations estimated) a plot such as that shown in <xref href="#FIG001_031">Figure 35</xref> can be compiled. By extrapolating the data
            back to zero relative abundance of oxygen, a ‘primordial’ value for the
            helium mass fraction can be deduced. <xref href="#FIG001_031">Figure 35</xref> implies a value of about 0.23 for this
            primordial helium mass fraction, in line with several other attempts to determine this
            quantity.</p>
          <fig>
            <title>
              <b>Figure 35</b>: A plot of observed helium mass fraction against relative abundance
              of oxygen to hydrogen, expressed as 10<sup>6</sup> × (number of oxygen
              nuclei)/(number of hydrogen nuclei), for several extragalactic HII regions. (Based on
              measurements by B. Pagel and colleagues)</title>
            <image href="../../media/S357_1_031i.jpg"/>
            <p outputclass="SourceReference">Source: B.E.J.Pagel <i>et al.</i> (1992) <i>Monthly Notices of the RAS</i>,
              255, 325–45 <data name="ItemRights">
                  <data name="OwnerRef"/>
                  <data name="ItemRef"/>
                  <data name="ItemAcknowledgement">B.E.J.Pagel <i>et al.</i> (1992) <i>Monthly Notices of the
                    RAS</i>, 255, 325–45</data>
              </data>
            </p>
            <p/>
         </fig>
          <p>Comparing this ‘observed’ primordial helium mass fraction (0.23)
            with the predicted values in <xref href="#FIG001_029">Figure 32</xref>, there is a reasonable level of agreement for
            a range of present-day baryonic densities.</p>
          <p>The abundance of <sup>3</sup>He is less useful. A number of observational
            difficulties make it very hard to deduce anything reliable about the primordial
            abundance. The comparison of prediction and measurement has little to offer in this
            case.</p>
          <p>The present-day abundance of <sup>7</sup>Li can be deduced from spectral
            studies of metal-poor dwarf stars. The outer layers of these stars are believed to be
            relatively unchanged since they were formed. Most share the same lithium abundance
            despite having different amounts of other elements and different masses. This makes it
            probable that the lithium in these outer stellar layers has not been processed, and thus
            gives a direct indication of the primordial mass fraction of lithium. The observations
            favour a <sup>7</sup>Li mass fraction close to
              8 × 10<sup>−10</sup>. According to <xref href="#FIG001_029">Figure 32</xref>, this corresponds to a present-day mass
            density of baryonic matter of around (1 to 5) × 10<sup>−28</sup>
            kg m<sup>−3</sup>.</p>
          <p>Finally consider the case of deuterium, <sup>2</sup>H. Deuterium is destroyed
            in stars so its currently observed mass fraction provides a lower limit on its
            primordial mass fraction. This lower limit is about
              3 × 10<sup>−5</sup> to
            7 × 10<sup>−5</sup>, consistent (according to <xref href="#FIG001_029">Figure 32</xref>) with present-day baryonic mass densities of
            about 5 × 10<sup>−28</sup>kg m<sup>−3</sup> or
            less.</p>
          <p>Bringing
            all of the observed abundances together, it does seem that they are consistent with the
            predicted primordial abundances (<xref href="#FIG001_029">Figure 32</xref>), provided the present-day baryonic mass
            density is around 10<sup>−28</sup> kg m<sup>−3</sup>.</p>
          
          <p>Pleasingly, at least to those who like consistency, a present-day baryonic mass
            density of a few times 10<sup>−28</sup> kg m<sup>−3</sup> is in excellent
            agreement with the rather precise value of
              <i>ρ</i>
            <sub>b,now</sub>/<i>c</i>
            <sup>2</sup> deduced by those who attempt to
            deduce cosmological parameters from the observed anisotropies in the cosmic microwave
            background radiation (as described in <xref href="#SEC006_003">Section 6.3</xref>). The fact that there is a narrow range of
            values for the present-day baryonic densities in which the predicted and
            ‘observed’ light nuclear abundances agree, is a significant success for
            big bang cosmology. The fact that this narrow range of baryonic densities includes the
            value deduced by a quite different technique is a truly remarkable
            achievement.</p>
        </section>
   </learningContentbody>
</learningContent>