<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE learningContent
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Learning Content//EN" "learningContent.dtd">
<learningContent id="SEC007_002">
   <title>7.2 The temperature of matter and radiation</title>
   <learningContentbody>
      <section>
          
          <p>The different reactions by which neutrons and protons came together soon after
            the instant of the big bang to produce heavier nuclei will have proceeded at different
            rates according to the energies of the particles involved. The first step in calculating
            nuclear abundances is therefore to make some assumption about these
            energies.</p>
          <p>The particles at any instant have a wide range of energies; this obviously
            complicates matters. Fortunately, however, it is possible to make one very important
            simplification. This is based on the concept of <i>equilibrium</i>. We have already
            touched on this topic in the context of our discussion of the origin of the 3 K
            radiation. Let us now look into it in a little more detail:</p>
          <p>We use an analogy. Suppose that a large number of molecules of an ordinary gas
            are introduced into an insulated container. To all external appearances, the state of
            the gas does not change with time. It is at a fixed pressure and a fixed temperature and
            is said to be in equilibrium. Of course, on a microscopic scale, a great deal is
            happening as the molecules collide with one another. Nevertheless, the measurable
            properties of the gas remain effectively constant. The reason for this is that the
            distribution of energy among the molecules fluctuates to only a very small extent about
            a well-defined average pattern. Thus, although the energy of any given molecule
            continually changes as it collides with others, details like the most probable energy
            for a molecule, or the probability of a molecule having an energy greater than, say,
              10<sup>−20</sup> J are preserved. Now it turns out that, once the temperature
            of the gas has been specified, it is possible to predict the average pattern of energy
            distribution in the gas at equilibrium – the <i>temperature of matter</i> serves
            as a label for the average mixture of energies of the gas molecules. For example, the
            most probable energy for a molecule is proportional to the temperature, and could, in
            the absence of a thermometer, be used to define the temperature scale.</p>
          <p>If we now have a mixture of gas and radiation, and these are allowed to come
            into equilibrium with each other, not only will the particles of the gas adopt a
            characteristic energy distribution, but so also will the photons of the radiation. As we
            discussed earlier in connection with the microwave radiation, this distribution of
            photon energies is known as a thermal spectrum, and is rather different from the
            Maxwell-Boltzmann distribution for molecules. Nevertheless, the distribution can again
            be labelled by a single number – the <i>temperature of radiation</i>. This is
            defined to be proportional to the most probable energy (or frequency) of a photon. Our
            two temperature scales for matter and for radiation are consistent in that, whenever
            radiation is in equilibrium with matter, the values of the two temperatures
            agree.</p>
          
          <p>Returning now to the early Universe, it is important to realise that the very
            high density of matter and radiation at that time gave rise to a frequency of collisions
            between protons, neutrons, electrons, and photons sufficiently high to ensure that the
            various components of the Universe were in almost perfect equilibrium. Thus, their
            respective distributions of energies could be labelled by a <i>single</i> common
            temperature. The electrons had the same temperature as the protons and the neutrons and
            the photons, because the collisions were so frequent that no part of the Universe could
            get out of step with the rest. This is very important because it allows us to replace
            the great complexity of the possible energy distributions by a single parameter –
            the temperature.</p>
          <p>Strictly speaking, the various equilibria – between particles, and
            between particles and radiation – can never have been quite perfect because the
            Universe was expanding all the time, and therefore cooling rapidly. There was therefore
            never a steady approach to a final condition such as we associate with the behaviour of,
            say, a cup of coffee cooling to equilibrium with its surroundings. Indeed, as we have
            pointed out before, the Universe has still not reached equilibrium. Nevertheless, there
            was near-equilibrium in the early Universe because of the high rate of
            collisions.</p>
        </section>
   </learningContentbody>
</learningContent>