<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<topic id="d2e15494">
   <title>
      <d4pSimpleEnumerator><!--2.22-->Chapter 22. </d4pSimpleEnumerator>
      <ph>The Last Words of Captain Nemo</ph>
   </title>
   <body>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="size_plus_2">THE PANELS CLOSED</ph> over this frightful
view, but the lights didn't go on in the lounge. Inside the
<i>Nautilus</i> all was gloom and silence. It left this place of
devastation with prodigious speed, 100 feet beneath the waters.
Where was it going? North or south? Where would the man flee after
this horrible act of revenge?</p>
      <p>I reentered my stateroom, where Ned and Conseil were waiting
silently. Captain Nemo filled me with insurmountable horror.
Whatever he had once suffered at the hands of humanity, he had no
right to mete out such punishment. He had made me, if not an
accomplice, at least an eyewitness to his vengeance! Even this was
intolerable.</p>
      <p>At eleven o'clock the electric lights came back on. I went into
the lounge. It was deserted. I consulted the various instruments.
The <i>Nautilus</i> was fleeing northward at a speed of
twenty–five miles per hour, sometimes on the surface of the
sea, sometimes thirty feet beneath it.</p>
      <p>After our position had been marked on the chart, I saw that we
were passing into the mouth of the English Channel, that our
heading would take us to the northernmost seas with incomparable
speed.</p>
      <p>I could barely glimpse the swift passing of longnose sharks,
hammerhead sharks, spotted dogfish that frequent these waters, big
eagle rays, swarms of seahorse looking like knights on a
chessboard, eels quivering like fireworks serpents, armies of crab
that fled obliquely by crossing their pincers over their carapaces,
finally schools of porpoise that held contests of speed with the
<i>Nautilus</i>. But by this point observing, studying, and
classifying were out of the question.</p>
      <p>By evening we had cleared 200 leagues up the Atlantic. Shadows
gathered and gloom overran the sea until the moon came up.</p>
      <p>I repaired to my stateroom. I couldn't sleep. I was assaulted by
nightmares. That horrible scene of destruction kept repeating in my
mind's eye.</p>
      <p>From that day forward, who knows where the <i>Nautilus</i> took
us in the north Atlantic basin? Always at incalculable speed!
Always amid the High Arctic mists! Did it call at the capes of
Spitzbergen or the shores of Novaya Zemlya? Did it visit such
uncharted seas as the White Sea, the Kara Sea, the Gulf of Ob, the
Lyakhov Islands, or those unknown beaches on the Siberian coast?
I'm unable to say. I lost track of the passing hours. Time was in
abeyance on the ship's clocks. As happens in the polar regions, it
seemed that night and day no longer followed their normal sequence.
I felt myself being drawn into that strange domain where the
overwrought imagination of Edgar Allan Poe was at home. Like his
fabled Arthur Gordon Pym, I expected any moment to see that
"shrouded human figure, very far larger in its proportions than any
dweller among men," thrown across the cataract that protects the
outskirts of the pole!</p>
      <p>I estimate—but perhaps I'm mistaken—that the
<i>Nautilus's</i> haphazard course continued for fifteen or twenty
days, and I'm not sure how long this would have gone on without the
catastrophe that ended our voyage. As for Captain Nemo, he was no
longer in the picture. As for his chief officer, the same applied.
Not one crewman was visible for a single instant. The
<i>Nautilus</i> cruised beneath the waters almost continuously.
When it rose briefly to the surface to renew our air, the hatches
opened and closed as if automated. No more positions were reported
on the world map. I didn't know where we were.</p>
      <p>I'll also mention that the Canadian, at the end of his strength
and patience, made no further appearances. Conseil couldn't coax a
single word out of him and feared that, in a fit of delirium while
under the sway of a ghastly homesickness, Ned would kill himself.
So he kept a devoted watch on his friend every instant.</p>
      <p>You can appreciate that under these conditions, our situation
had become untenable.</p>
      <p>One morning—whose date I'm unable to specify—I was
slumbering near the first hours of daylight, a painful, sickly
slumber. Waking up, I saw Ned Land leaning over me, and I heard him
tell me in a low voice:</p>
      <p>"We're going to escape!"</p>
      <p>I sat up.</p>
      <p>"When?" I asked.</p>
      <p>"Tonight. There doesn't seem to be any supervision left on the
<i>Nautilus</i>. You'd think a total daze was reigning on board.
Will you be ready, sir?"</p>
      <p>"Yes. Where are we?"</p>
      <p>"In sight of land. I saw it through the mists just this morning,
twenty miles to the east."</p>
      <p>"What land is it?"</p>
      <p>"I've no idea, but whatever it is, there we'll take refuge."</p>
      <p>"Yes, Ned! We'll escape tonight even if the sea swallows us
up!"</p>
      <p>"The sea's rough, the wind's blowing hard, but a
twenty–mile run in the <i>Nautilus's</i> nimble longboat
doesn't scare me. Unknown to the crew, I've stowed some food and
flasks of water inside."</p>
      <p>"I'm with you."</p>
      <p>"What's more," the Canadian added, "if they catch me, I'll
defend myself, I'll fight to the death."</p>
      <p>"Then we'll die together, Ned my friend."</p>
      <p>My mind was made up. The Canadian left me. I went out on the
platform, where I could barely stand upright against the jolts of
the billows. The skies were threatening, but land lay inside those
dense mists, and we had to escape. Not a single day, or even a
single hour, could we afford to lose.</p>
      <p>I returned to the lounge, dreading yet desiring an encounter
with Captain Nemo, wanting yet not wanting to see him. What would I
say to him? How could I hide the involuntary horror he inspired in
me? No! It was best not to meet him face to face! Best to try and
forget him! And yet . . . !</p>
      <p>How long that day seemed, the last I would spend aboard the
<i>Nautilus</i>! I was left to myself. Ned Land and Conseil avoided
speaking to me, afraid they would give themselves away.</p>
      <p>At six o'clock I ate supper, but I had no appetite. Despite my
revulsion, I forced it down, wanting to keep my strength up.</p>
      <p>At 6:30 Ned Land entered my stateroom. He told me:</p>
      <lq>
         <p>"We won't see each other again before we go. At ten o'clock the
moon won't be up yet. We'll take advantage of the darkness. Come to
the skiff. Conseil and I will be inside waiting for you."</p>
      </lq>
      <p>The Canadian left without giving me time to answer him.</p>
      <p>I wanted to verify the <i>Nautilus's</i> heading. I made my way
to the lounge. We were racing north–northeast with frightful
speed, fifty meters down.</p>
      <p>I took one last look at the natural wonders and artistic
treasures amassed in the museum, this unrivaled collection doomed
to perish someday in the depths of the seas, together with its
curator. I wanted to establish one supreme impression in my mind. I
stayed there an hour, basking in the aura of the ceiling lights,
passing in review the treasures shining in their glass cases. Then
I returned to my stateroom.</p>
      <p>There I dressed in sturdy seafaring clothes. I gathered my notes
and packed them tenderly about my person. My heart was pounding
mightily. I couldn't curb its pulsations. My anxiety and agitation
would certainly have given me away if Captain Nemo had seen me.</p>
      <p>What was he doing just then? I listened at the door to his
stateroom. I heard the sound of footsteps. Captain Nemo was inside.
He hadn't gone to bed. With his every movement I imagined he would
appear and ask me why I wanted to escape! I felt in a perpetual
state of alarm. My imagination magnified this sensation. The
feeling became so acute, I wondered whether it wouldn't be better
to enter the captain's stateroom, dare him face to face, brave it
out with word and deed!</p>
      <p>It was an insane idea. Fortunately I controlled myself and
stretched out on the bed to soothe my bodily agitation. My nerves
calmed a little, but with my brain so aroused, I did a swift review
of my whole existence aboard the <i>Nautilus</i>, every pleasant or
unpleasant incident that had crossed my path since I went overboard
from the <i>Abraham Lincoln</i>: the underwater hunting trip, the
Torres Strait, our running aground, the savages of Papua, the coral
cemetery, the Suez passageway, the island of Santorini, the Cretan
diver, the Bay of Vigo, Atlantis, the Ice Bank, the South Pole, our
imprisonment in the ice, the battle with the devilfish, the storm
in the Gulf Stream, the <i>Avenger</i>, and that horrible scene of
the vessel sinking with its crew . . . ! All these events passed
before my eyes like backdrops unrolling upstage in a theater. In
this strange setting Captain Nemo then grew fantastically. His
features were accentuated, taking on superhuman proportions. He was
no longer my equal, he was the Man of the Waters, the Spirit of the
Seas.</p>
      <p>By then it was 9:30. I held my head in both hands to keep it
from bursting. I closed my eyes. I no longer wanted to think. A
half hour still to wait! A half hour of nightmares that could drive
me insane!</p>
      <p>Just then I heard indistinct chords from the organ, melancholy
harmonies from some undefinable hymn, actual pleadings from a soul
trying to sever its earthly ties. I listened with all my senses at
once, barely breathing, immersed like Captain Nemo in this musical
trance that was drawing him beyond the bounds of this world.</p>
      <p>Then a sudden thought terrified me. Captain Nemo had left his
stateroom. He was in the same lounge I had to cross in order to
escape. There I would encounter him one last time. He would see me,
perhaps speak to me! One gesture from him could obliterate me, a
single word shackle me to his vessel!</p>
      <p>Even so, ten o'clock was about to strike. It was time to leave
my stateroom and rejoin my companions.</p>
      <p>I dared not hesitate, even if Captain Nemo stood before me. I
opened the door cautiously, but as it swung on its hinges, it
seemed to make a frightful noise. This noise existed, perhaps, only
in my imagination!</p>
      <p>I crept forward through the <i>Nautilus's</i> dark gangways,
pausing after each step to curb the pounding of my heart.</p>
      <p>I arrived at the corner door of the lounge. I opened it gently.
The lounge was plunged in profound darkness. Chords from the organ
were reverberating faintly. Captain Nemo was there. He didn't see
me. Even in broad daylight I doubt that he would have noticed me,
so completely was he immersed in his trance.</p>
      <p>I inched over the carpet, avoiding the tiniest bump whose noise
might give me away. It took me five minutes to reach the door at
the far end, which led into the library.</p>
      <p>I was about to open it when a gasp from Captain Nemo nailed me
to the spot. I realized that he was standing up. I even got a
glimpse of him because some rays of light from the library had
filtered into the lounge. He was coming toward me, arms crossed,
silent, not walking but gliding like a ghost. His chest was
heaving, swelling with sobs. And I heard him murmur these words,
the last of his to reach my ears:</p>
      <p>"O almighty God! Enough! Enough!"</p>
      <p>Was it a vow of repentance that had just escaped from this man's
conscience . . . ?</p>
      <p>Frantic, I rushed into the library. I climbed the central
companionway, and going along the upper gangway, I arrived at the
skiff. I went through the opening that had already given access to
my two companions.</p>
      <p>"Let's go, let's go!" I exclaimed.</p>
      <p>"Right away!" the Canadian replied.</p>
      <p>First, Ned Land closed and bolted the opening cut into the
<i>Nautilus's</i> sheet iron, using the monkey wrench he had with
him. After likewise closing the opening in the skiff, the Canadian
began to unscrew the nuts still bolting us to the underwater
boat.</p>
      <p>Suddenly a noise from the ship's interior became audible. Voices
were answering each other hurriedly. What was it? Had they spotted
our escape? I felt Ned Land sliding a dagger into my hand.</p>
      <p>"Yes," I muttered, "we know how to die!"</p>
      <p>The Canadian paused in his work. But one word twenty times
repeated, one dreadful word, told me the reason for the agitation
spreading aboard the <i>Nautilus</i>. We weren't the cause of the
crew's concern.</p>
      <p>"Maelstrom! Maelstrom!" they were shouting.</p>
      <p>The Maelstrom! Could a more frightening name have rung in our
ears under more frightening circumstances? Were we lying in the
dangerous waterways off the Norwegian coast? Was the
<i>Nautilus</i> being dragged into this whirlpool just as the skiff
was about to detach from its plating?</p>
      <p>As you know, at the turn of the tide, the waters confined
between the Faroe and Lofoten Islands rush out with irresistible
violence. They form a vortex from which no ship has ever been able
to escape. Monstrous waves race together from every point of the
horizon. They form a whirlpool aptly called "the ocean's navel,"
whose attracting power extends a distance of fifteen kilometers. It
can suck down not only ships but whales, and even polar bears from
the northernmost regions.</p>
      <p>This was where the <i>Nautilus</i> had been sent
accidentally—or perhaps deliberately—by its captain. It
was sweeping around in a spiral whose radius kept growing smaller
and smaller. The skiff, still attached to the ship's plating, was
likewise carried around at dizzying speed. I could feel us
whirling. I was experiencing that accompanying nausea that follows
such continuous spinning motions. We were in dread, in the last
stages of sheer horror, our blood frozen in our veins, our nerves
numb, drenched in cold sweat as if from the throes of dying! And
what a noise around our frail skiff! What roars echoing from
several miles away! What crashes from the waters breaking against
sharp rocks on the seafloor, where the hardest objects are smashed,
where tree trunks are worn down and worked into "a shaggy fur," as
Norwegians express it!</p>
      <p>What a predicament! We were rocking frightfully. The
<i>Nautilus</i> defended itself like a human being. Its steel
muscles were cracking. Sometimes it stood on end, the three of us
along with it!</p>
      <p>"We've got to hold on tight," Ned said, "and screw the nuts down
again! If we can stay attached to the <i>Nautilus</i>, we can still
make it . . . !"</p>
      <p>He hadn't finished speaking when a cracking sound occurred. The
nuts gave way, and ripped out of its socket, the skiff was hurled
like a stone from a sling into the midst of the vortex.</p>
      <p>My head struck against an iron timber, and with this violent
shock I lost consciousness.</p>
   </body>
</topic>