<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<topic id="d2e14768">
   <title>
      <d4pSimpleEnumerator><!--2.20-->Chapter 20. </d4pSimpleEnumerator>
      <ph>In Latitude 47° 24' and Longitude 17° 28'</ph>
   </title>
   <body>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="size_plus_2">IN THE AFTERMATH</ph> of this storm, we were
thrown back to the east. Away went any hope of escaping to the
landing places of New York or the St. Lawrence. In despair, poor
Ned went into seclusion like Captain Nemo. Conseil and I no longer
left each other.</p>
      <p>As I said, the <i>Nautilus</i> veered to the east. To be more
accurate, I should have said to the northeast. Sometimes on the
surface of the waves, sometimes beneath them, the ship wandered for
days amid these mists so feared by navigators. These are caused
chiefly by melting ice, which keeps the air extremely damp. How
many ships have perished in these waterways as they tried to get
directions from the hazy lights on the coast! How many casualties
have been caused by these opaque mists! How many collisions have
occurred with these reefs, where the breaking surf is covered by
the noise of the wind! How many vessels have rammed each other,
despite their running lights, despite the warnings given by their
bosun's pipes and alarm bells!</p>
      <p>So the floor of this sea had the appearance of a battlefield
where every ship defeated by the ocean still lay, some already old
and encrusted, others newer and reflecting our beacon light on
their ironwork and copper undersides. Among these vessels, how many
went down with all hands, with their crews and hosts of immigrants,
at these trouble spots so prominent in the statistics: Cape Race,
St. Paul Island, the Strait of Belle Isle, the St. Lawrence
estuary! And in only a few years, how many victims have been
furnished to the obituary notices by the Royal Mail, Inman, and
Montreal lines; by vessels named the <i>Solway</i>, the
<i>Isis</i>, the <i>Paramatta</i>, the <i>Hungarian</i>, the
<i>Canadian</i>, the <i>Anglo–Saxon</i>, the <i>Humboldt</i>,
and the <i>United States</i>, all run aground; by the <i>Arctic</i>
and the <i>Lyonnais</i>, sunk in collisions; by the
<i>President</i>, the <i>Pacific</i>, and the <i>City of
Glasgow</i>, lost for reasons unknown; in the midst of their gloomy
rubble, the <i>Nautilus</i> navigated as if passing the dead in
review!</p>
      <p>By May 15 we were off the southern tip of the Grand Banks of
Newfoundland. These banks are the result of marine sedimentation,
an extensive accumulation of organic waste brought either from the
equator by the Gulf Stream's current, or from the North Pole by the
countercurrent of cold water that skirts the American coast. Here,
too, erratically drifting chunks collect from the ice breakup. Here
a huge boneyard forms from fish, mollusks, and zoophytes dying over
it by the billions.</p>
      <p>The sea is of no great depth at the Grand Banks. A few hundred
fathoms at best. But to the south there is a deep, suddenly
occurring depression, a 3,000–meter pit. Here the Gulf Stream
widens. Its waters come to full bloom. It loses its speed and
temperature, but it turns into a sea.</p>
      <p>Among the fish that the <i>Nautilus</i> startled on its way,
I'll mention a one–meter lumpfish, blackish on top with
orange on the belly and rare among its brethren in that it
practices monogamy, a good–sized eelpout, a type of emerald
moray whose flavor is excellent, wolffish with big eyes in a head
somewhat resembling a canine's, viviparous blennies whose eggs
hatch inside their bodies like those of snakes, bloated gobio (or
black gudgeon) measuring two decimeters, grenadiers with long tails
and gleaming with a silvery glow, speedy fish venturing far from
their High Arctic seas.</p>
      <p>Our nets also hauled in a bold, daring, vigorous, and muscular
fish armed with prickles on its head and stings on its fins, a real
scorpion measuring two to three meters, the ruthless enemy of cod,
blennies, and salmon; it was the bullhead of the northerly seas, a
fish with red fins and a brown body covered with nodules. The
<i>Nautilus's</i> fishermen had some trouble getting a grip on this
animal, which, thanks to the formation of its gill covers, can
protect its respiratory organs from any parching contact with the
air and can live out of water for a good while.</p>
      <p>And I'll mention—for the record—some little banded
blennies that follow ships into the northernmost seas,
sharp–snouted carp exclusive to the north Atlantic,
scorpionfish, and lastly the <i>gadoid</i> family, chiefly the
<i>cod</i> species, which I detected in their waters of choice over
these inexhaustible Grand Banks.</p>
      <p>Because Newfoundland is simply an underwater peak, you could
call these cod mountain fish. While the <i>Nautilus</i> was
clearing a path through their tight ranks, Conseil couldn't refrain
from making this comment:</p>
      <p>"Mercy, look at these cod!" he said. "Why, I thought cod were
flat, like dab or sole!"</p>
      <p>"Innocent boy!" I exclaimed. "Cod are flat only at the grocery
store, where they're cut open and spread out on display. But in the
water they're like mullet, spindle–shaped and perfectly built
for speed."</p>
      <p>"I can easily believe Master," Conseil replied. "But what crowds
of them! What swarms!"</p>
      <p>"Bah! My friend, there'd be many more without their enemies,
scorpionfish and human beings! Do you know how many eggs have been
counted in a single female?"</p>
      <p>"I'll go all out," Conseil replied. "500,000."</p>
      <p>"11,000,000, my friend."</p>
      <p>"11,000,000! I refuse to accept that until I count them
myself."</p>
      <p>"So count them, Conseil. But it would be less work to believe
me. Besides, Frenchmen, Englishmen, Americans, Danes, and
Norwegians catch these cod by the thousands. They're eaten in
prodigious quantities, and without the astonishing fertility of
these fish, the seas would soon be depopulated of them.
Accordingly, in England and America alone, 5,000 ships manned by
75,000 seamen go after cod. Each ship brings back an average catch
of 4,400 fish, making 22,000,000. Off the coast of Norway, the
total is the same."</p>
      <p>"Fine," Conseil replied, "I'll take Master's word for it. I
won't count them."</p>
      <p>"Count what?"</p>
      <p>"Those 11,000,000 eggs. But I'll make one comment."</p>
      <p>"What's that?"</p>
      <p>"If all their eggs hatched, just four codfish could feed
England, America, and Norway."</p>
      <p>As we skimmed the depths of the Grand Banks, I could see
perfectly those long fishing lines, each armed with 200 hooks, that
every boat dangled by the dozens. The lower end of each line
dragged the bottom by means of a small grappling iron, and at the
surface it was secured to the buoy–rope of a cork float. The
<i>Nautilus</i> had to maneuver shrewdly in the midst of this
underwater spiderweb.</p>
      <p>But the ship didn't stay long in these heavily traveled
waterways. It went up to about latitude 42°. This brought it
abreast of St. John's in Newfoundland and Heart's Content, where
the Atlantic Cable reaches its end point.</p>
      <p>Instead of continuing north, the <i>Nautilus</i> took an
easterly heading, as if to go along this plateau on which the
telegraph cable rests, where multiple soundings have given the
contours of the terrain with the utmost accuracy.</p>
      <p>It was on May 17, about 500 miles from Heart's Content and 2,800
meters down, that I spotted this cable lying on the seafloor.
Conseil, whom I hadn't alerted, mistook it at first for a gigantic
sea snake and was gearing up to classify it in his best manner. But
I enlightened the fine lad and let him down gently by giving him
various details on the laying of this cable.</p>
      <p>The first cable was put down during the years 1857–1858;
but after transmitting about 400 telegrams, it went dead. In 1863
engineers built a new cable that measured 3,400 kilometers, weighed
4,500 metric tons, and was shipped aboard the <i>Great Eastern</i>.
This attempt also failed.</p>
      <p>Now then, on May 25 while submerged to a depth of 3,836 meters,
the <i>Nautilus</i> lay in precisely the locality where this second
cable suffered the rupture that ruined the undertaking. It happened
638 miles from the coast of Ireland. At around two o'clock in the
afternoon, all contact with Europe broke off. The electricians on
board decided to cut the cable before fishing it up, and by eleven
o'clock that evening they had retrieved the damaged part. They
repaired the joint and its splice; then the cable was resubmerged.
But a few days later it snapped again and couldn't be recovered
from the ocean depths.</p>
      <p>These Americans refused to give up. The daring Cyrus Field, who
had risked his whole fortune to promote this undertaking, called
for a new bond issue. It sold out immediately. Another cable was
put down under better conditions. Its sheaves of conducting wire
were insulated within a gutta–percha covering, which was
protected by a padding of textile material enclosed in a metal
sheath. The <i>Great Eastern</i> put back to sea on July 13,
1866.</p>
      <p>The operation proceeded apace. Yet there was one hitch. As they
gradually unrolled this third cable, the electricians observed on
several occasions that someone had recently driven nails into it,
trying to damage its core. Captain Anderson, his officers, and the
engineers put their heads together, then posted a warning that if
the culprit were detected, he would be thrown overboard without a
trial. After that, these villainous attempts were not repeated.</p>
      <p>By July 23 the <i>Great Eastern</i> was lying no farther than
800 kilometers from Newfoundland when it received telegraphed news
from Ireland of an armistice signed between Prussia and Austria
after the Battle of Sadova. Through the mists on the 27th, it
sighted the port of Heart's Content. The undertaking had ended
happily, and in its first dispatch, young America addressed old
Europe with these wise words so rarely understood: "Glory to God in
the highest, and peace on earth to men of good will."</p>
      <p>I didn't expect to find this electric cable in mint condition,
as it looked on leaving its place of manufacture. The long snake
was covered with seashell rubble and bristling with
<i>foraminifera</i>; a crust of caked gravel protected it from any
mollusks that might bore into it. It rested serenely, sheltered
from the sea's motions, under a pressure favorable to the
transmission of that electric spark that goes from America to
Europe in 32/100 of a second. This cable will no doubt last
indefinitely because, as observers note, its gutta–percha
casing is improved by a stay in salt water.</p>
      <p>Besides, on this well–chosen plateau, the cable never lies
at depths that could cause a break. The <i>Nautilus</i> followed it
to its lowest reaches, located 4,431 meters down, and even there it
rested without any stress or strain. Then we returned to the
locality where the 1863 accident had taken place.</p>
      <p>There the ocean floor formed a valley 120 kilometers wide, into
which you could fit Mt. Blanc without its summit poking above the
surface of the waves. This valley is closed off to the east by a
sheer wall 2,000 meters high. We arrived there on May 28, and the
<i>Nautilus</i> lay no farther than 150 kilometers from
Ireland.</p>
      <p>Would Captain Nemo head up north and beach us on the British
Isles? No. Much to my surprise, he went back down south and
returned to European seas. As we swung around the Emerald Isle, I
spotted Cape Clear for an instant, plus the lighthouse on Fastnet
Rock that guides all those thousands of ships setting out from
Glasgow or Liverpool.</p>
      <p>An important question then popped into my head. Would the
<i>Nautilus</i> dare to tackle the English Channel? Ned Land (who
promptly reappeared after we hugged shore) never stopped
questioning me. What could I answer him? Captain Nemo remained
invisible. After giving the Canadian a glimpse of American shores,
was he about to show me the coast of France?</p>
      <p>But the <i>Nautilus</i> kept gravitating southward. On May 30,
in sight of Land's End, it passed between the lowermost tip of
England and the Scilly Islands, which it left behind to
starboard.</p>
      <p>If it was going to enter the English Channel, it clearly needed
to head east. It did not.</p>
      <p>All day long on May 31, the <i>Nautilus</i> swept around the sea
in a series of circles that had me deeply puzzled. It seemed to be
searching for a locality that it had some trouble finding. At noon
Captain Nemo himself came to take our bearings. He didn't address a
word to me. He looked gloomier than ever. What was filling him with
such sadness? Was it our proximity to these European shores? Was he
reliving his memories of that country he had left behind? If so,
what did he feel? Remorse or regret? For a good while these
thoughts occupied my mind, and I had a hunch that fate would soon
give away the captain's secrets.</p>
      <p>The next day, June 1, the <i>Nautilus</i> kept to the same tack.
It was obviously trying to locate some precise spot in the ocean.
Just as on the day before, Captain Nemo came to take the altitude
of the sun. The sea was smooth, the skies clear. Eight miles to the
east, a big steamship was visible on the horizon line. No flag was
flapping from the gaff of its fore–and–aft sail, and I
couldn't tell its nationality.</p>
      <p>A few minutes before the sun passed its zenith, Captain Nemo
raised his sextant and took his sights with the utmost precision.
The absolute calm of the waves facilitated this operation. The
<i>Nautilus</i> lay motionless, neither rolling nor pitching.</p>
      <p>I was on the platform just then. After determining our position,
the captain pronounced only these words:</p>
      <p>"It's right here!"</p>
      <p>He went down the hatch. Had he seen that vessel change course
and seemingly head toward us? I'm unable to say.</p>
      <p>I returned to the lounge. The hatch closed, and I heard water
hissing in the ballast tanks. The <i>Nautilus</i> began to sink on
a vertical line, because its propeller was in check and no longer
furnished any forward motion.</p>
      <p>Some minutes later it stopped at a depth of 833 meters and came
to rest on the seafloor.</p>
      <p>The ceiling lights in the lounge then went out, the panels
opened, and through the windows I saw, for a half–mile
radius, the sea brightly lit by the beacon's rays.</p>
      <p>I looked to port and saw nothing but the immenseness of these
tranquil waters.</p>
      <p>To starboard, a prominent bulge on the sea bottom caught my
attention. You would have thought it was some ruin enshrouded in a
crust of whitened seashells, as if under a mantle of snow.
Carefully examining this mass, I could identify the swollen
outlines of a ship shorn of its masts, which must have sunk bow
first. This casualty certainly dated from some far–off time.
To be so caked with the limestone of these waters, this wreckage
must have spent many a year on the ocean floor.</p>
      <p>What ship was this? Why had the <i>Nautilus</i> come to visit
its grave? Was it something other than a maritime accident that had
dragged this craft under the waters?</p>
      <p>I wasn't sure what to think, but next to me I heard Captain
Nemo's voice slowly say:</p>
      <p>"Originally this ship was christened the <i>Marseillais</i>. It
carried seventy–four cannons and was launched in 1762. On
August 13, 1778, commanded by La Poype–Vertrieux, it fought
valiantly against the <i>Preston</i>. On July 4, 1779, as a member
of the squadron under Admiral d'Estaing, it assisted in the capture
of the island of Grenada. On September 5, 1781, under the Count de
Grasse, it took part in the Battle of Chesapeake Bay. In 1794 the
new Republic of France changed the name of this ship. On April 16
of that same year, it joined the squadron at Brest under Rear
Admiral Villaret de Joyeuse, who was entrusted with escorting a
convoy of wheat coming from America under the command of Admiral
Van Stabel. In this second year of the French Revolutionary
Calendar, on the 11th and 12th days in the Month of Pasture, this
squadron fought an encounter with English vessels. Sir, today is
June 1, 1868, or the 13th day in the Month of Pasture.
Seventy–four years ago to the day, at this very spot in
latitude 47° 24' and longitude 17° 28', this ship sank
after a heroic battle; its three masts gone, water in its hold, a
third of its crew out of action, it preferred to go to the bottom
with its 356 seamen rather than surrender; and with its flag nailed
up on the afterdeck, it disappeared beneath the waves to shouts of
'Long live the Republic!'"</p>
      <p>"This is the <i>Avenger</i>!" I exclaimed.</p>
      <p>"Yes, sir! <i>The Avenger</i>! A splendid name!" Captain Nemo
murmured, crossing his arms.</p>
   </body>
</topic>