<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<topic id="d2e13659">
   <title>
      <d4pSimpleEnumerator><!--2.17-->Chapter 17. </d4pSimpleEnumerator>
      <ph>From Cape Horn to the Amazon</ph>
   </title>
   <body>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="size_plus_2">HOW I GOT ONTO</ph> the platform I'm unable to
say. Perhaps the Canadian transferred me there. But I could
breathe, I could inhale the life–giving sea air. Next to me
my two companions were getting tipsy on the fresh oxygen particles.
Poor souls who have suffered from long starvation mustn't pounce
heedlessly on the first food given them. We, on the other hand,
didn't have to practice such moderation: we could suck the atoms
from the air by the lungful, and it was the breeze, the breeze
itself, that poured into us this luxurious intoxication!</p>
      <p>"Ahhh!" Conseil was putting in. "What fine oxygen! Let Master
have no fears about breathing. There's enough for everyone."</p>
      <p>As for Ned Land, he didn't say a word, but his wide–open
jaws would have scared off a shark. And what powerful inhalations!
The Canadian "drew" like a furnace going full blast.</p>
      <p>Our strength returned promptly, and when I looked around, I saw
that we were alone on the platform. No crewmen. Not even Captain
Nemo. Those strange seamen on the <i>Nautilus</i> were content with
the oxygen circulating inside. Not one of them had come up to enjoy
the open air.</p>
      <p>The first words I pronounced were words of appreciation and
gratitude to my two companions. Ned and Conseil had kept me alive
during the final hours of our long death throes. But no expression
of thanks could repay them fully for such devotion.</p>
      <p>"Good lord, Professor," Ned Land answered me, "don't mention it!
What did we do that's so praiseworthy? Not a thing. It was a
question of simple arithmetic. Your life is worth more than ours.
So we had to save it."</p>
      <p>"No, Ned," I replied, "it isn't worth more. Nobody could be
better than a kind and generous man like yourself!"</p>
      <p>"All right, all right!" the Canadian repeated in
embarrassment.</p>
      <p>"And you, my gallant Conseil, you suffered a great deal."</p>
      <p>"Not too much, to be candid with Master. I was lacking a few
throatfuls of air, but I would have gotten by. Besides, when I saw
Master fainting, it left me without the slightest desire to
breathe. It took my breath away, in a manner of . . ."</p>
      <p>Confounded by this lapse into banality, Conseil left his
sentence hanging.</p>
      <p>"My friends," I replied, very moved, "we're bound to each other
forever, and I'm deeply indebted to you—"</p>
      <p>"Which I'll take advantage of," the Canadian shot back.</p>
      <p>"Eh?" Conseil put in.</p>
      <p>"Yes," Ned Land went on. "You can repay your debt by coming with
me when I leave this infernal <i>Nautilus</i>."</p>
      <p>"By the way," Conseil said, "are we going in a favorable
direction?"</p>
      <p>"Yes," I replied, "because we're going in the direction of the
sun, and here the sun is due north."</p>
      <p>"Sure," Ned Land went on, "but it remains to be seen whether
we'll make for the Atlantic or the Pacific, in other words, whether
we'll end up in well–traveled or deserted seas."</p>
      <p>I had no reply to this, and I feared that Captain Nemo wouldn't
take us homeward but rather into that huge ocean washing the shores
of both Asia and America. In this way he would complete his
underwater tour of the world, going back to those seas where the
<i>Nautilus</i> enjoyed the greatest freedom. But if we returned to
the Pacific, far from every populated shore, what would happen to
Ned Land's plans?</p>
      <p>We would soon settle this important point. The <i>Nautilus</i>
traveled swiftly. Soon we had cleared the Antarctic Circle plus the
promontory of Cape Horn. We were abreast of the tip of South
America by March 31 at seven o'clock in the evening.</p>
      <p>By then all our past sufferings were forgotten. The memory of
that imprisonment under the ice faded from our minds. We had
thoughts only of the future. Captain Nemo no longer appeared,
neither in the lounge nor on the platform. The positions reported
each day on the world map were put there by the chief officer, and
they enabled me to determine the <i>Nautilus's</i> exact heading.
Now then, that evening it became obvious, much to my satisfaction,
that we were returning north by the Atlantic route.</p>
      <p>I shared the results of my observations with the Canadian and
Conseil.</p>
      <p>"That's good news," the Canadian replied, "but where's the
<i>Nautilus</i> going?"</p>
      <p>"I'm unable to say, Ned."</p>
      <p>"After the South Pole, does our captain want to tackle the North
Pole, then go back to the Pacific by the notorious Northwest
Passage?"</p>
      <p>"I wouldn't double dare him," Conseil replied.</p>
      <p>"Oh well," the Canadian said, "we'll give him the slip long
before then."</p>
      <p>"In any event," Conseil added, "he's a superman, that Captain
Nemo, and we'll never regret having known him."</p>
      <p>"Especially once we've left him," Ned Land shot back.</p>
      <p>The next day, April 1, when the <i>Nautilus</i> rose to the
surface of the waves a few minutes before noon, we raised land to
the west. It was Tierra del Fuego, the Land of Fire, a name given
it by early navigators after they saw numerous curls of smoke
rising from the natives' huts. This Land of Fire forms a huge
cluster of islands over thirty leagues long and eighty leagues
wide, extending between latitude 53° and 56° south, and
between longitude 67° 50' and 77° 15' west. Its coastline
looked flat, but high mountains rose in the distance. I even
thought I glimpsed Mt. Sarmiento, whose elevation is 2,070 meters
above sea level: a pyramid–shaped block of shale with a very
sharp summit, which, depending on whether it's clear or veiled in
vapor, "predicts fair weather or foul," as Ned Land told me.</p>
      <p>"A first–class barometer, my friend."</p>
      <p>"Yes, sir, a natural barometer that didn't let me down when I
navigated the narrows of the Strait of Magellan."</p>
      <p>Just then its peak appeared before us, standing out distinctly
against the background of the skies. This forecast fair weather.
And so it proved.</p>
      <p>Going back under the waters, the <i>Nautilus</i> drew near the
coast, cruising along it for only a few miles. Through the lounge
windows I could see long creepers and gigantic fucus plants,
bulb–bearing seaweed of which the open sea at the pole had
revealed a few specimens; with their smooth, viscous filaments,
they measured as much as 300 meters long; genuine cables more than
an inch thick and very tough, they're often used as mooring lines
for ships. Another weed, known by the name velp and boasting
four–foot leaves, was crammed into the coral concretions and
carpeted the ocean floor. It served as both nest and nourishment
for myriads of crustaceans and mollusks, for crabs and cuttlefish.
Here seals and otters could indulge in a sumptuous meal, mixing
meat from fish with vegetables from the sea, like the English with
their Irish stews.</p>
      <p>The <i>Nautilus</i> passed over these lush, luxuriant depths
with tremendous speed. Near evening it approached the Falkland
Islands, whose rugged summits I recognized the next day. The sea
was of moderate depth. So not without good reason, I assumed that
these two islands, plus the many islets surrounding them, used to
be part of the Magellan coastline. The Falkland Islands were
probably discovered by the famous navigator John Davis, who gave
them the name Davis Southern Islands. Later Sir Richard Hawkins
called them the Maidenland, after the Blessed Virgin. Subsequently,
at the beginning of the 18th century, they were named the Malouines
by fishermen from Saint–Malo in Brittany, then finally dubbed
the Falklands by the English, to whom they belong today.</p>
      <p>In these waterways our nets brought up fine samples of algae, in
particular certain fucus plants whose roots were laden with the
world's best mussels. Geese and duck alighted by the dozens on the
platform and soon took their places in the ship's pantry. As for
fish, I specifically observed some bony fish belonging to the
<i>goby</i> genus, especially some gudgeon two decimeters long,
sprinkled with whitish and yellow spots.</p>
      <p>I likewise marveled at the numerous <i>medusas</i>, including
the most beautiful of their breed, the compass jellyfish, unique to
the Falkland seas. Some of these jellyfish were shaped like very
smooth, semispheric parasols with russet stripes and fringes of
twelve neat festoons. Others looked like upside–down baskets
from which wide leaves and long red twigs were gracefully trailing.
They swam with quiverings of their four leaflike arms, letting the
opulent tresses of their tentacles dangle in the drift. I wanted to
preserve a few specimens of these delicate zoophytes, but they were
merely clouds, shadows, illusions, melting and evaporating outside
their native element.</p>
      <p>When the last tips of the Falkland Islands had disappeared below
the horizon, the <i>Nautilus</i> submerged to a depth between
twenty and twenty–five meters and went along the South
American coast. Captain Nemo didn't put in an appearance.</p>
      <p>We didn't leave these Patagonian waterways until April 3,
sometimes cruising under the ocean, sometimes on its surface. The
<i>Nautilus</i> passed the wide estuary formed by the mouth of the
Rio de la Plata, and on April 4 we lay abreast of Uruguay, albeit
fifty miles out. Keeping to its northerly heading, it followed the
long windings of South America. By then we had fared 16,000 leagues
since coming on board in the seas of Japan.</p>
      <p>Near eleven o'clock in the morning, we cut the Tropic of
Capricorn on the 37th meridian, passing well out from Cape Frio.
Much to Ned Land's displeasure, Captain Nemo had no liking for the
neighborhood of Brazil's populous shores, because he shot by with
dizzying speed. Not even the swiftest fish or birds could keep up
with us, and the natural curiosities in these seas completely
eluded our observation.</p>
      <p>This speed was maintained for several days, and on the evening
of April 9, we raised South America's easternmost tip, Cape
São Roque. But then the <i>Nautilus</i> veered away again
and went looking for the lowest depths of an underwater valley
gouged between this cape and Sierra Leone on the coast of Africa.
Abreast of the West Indies, this valley forks into two arms, and to
the north it ends in an enormous depression 9,000 meters deep. From
this locality to the Lesser Antilles, the ocean's geologic profile
features a steeply cut cliff six kilometers high, and abreast of
the Cape Verde Islands, there's another wall just as imposing;
together these two barricades confine the whole submerged continent
of Atlantis. The floor of this immense valley is made picturesque
by mountains that furnish these underwater depths with scenic
views. This description is based mostly on certain hand–drawn
charts kept in the <i>Nautilus's</i> library, charts obviously
rendered by Captain Nemo himself from his own personal
observations.</p>
      <p>For two days we visited these deep and deserted waters by means
of our slanting fins. The <i>Nautilus</i> would do long, diagonal
dives that took us to every level. But on April 11 it rose
suddenly, and the shore reappeared at the mouth of the Amazon
River, a huge estuary whose outflow is so considerable, it desalts
the sea over an area of several leagues.</p>
      <p>We cut the Equator. Twenty miles to the west lay Guiana, French
territory where we could easily have taken refuge. But the wind was
blowing a strong gust, and the furious billows would not allow us
to face them in a mere skiff. No doubt Ned Land understood this
because he said nothing to me. For my part, I made no allusion to
his escape plans because I didn't want to push him into an attempt
that was certain to misfire.</p>
      <p>I was readily compensated for this delay by fascinating
research. During those two days of April 11–12, the
<i>Nautilus</i> didn't leave the surface of the sea, and its trawl
brought up a simply miraculous catch of zoophytes, fish, and
reptiles.</p>
      <p>Some zoophytes were dredged up by the chain of our trawl. Most
were lovely sea anemone belonging to the family <i>Actinidia</i>,
including among other species, the <i>Phyctalis protexta</i>,
native to this part of the ocean: a small cylindrical trunk adorned
with vertical lines, mottled with red spots, and crowned by a
wondrous blossoming of tentacles. As for mollusks, they consisted
of exhibits I had already observed: turret snails, olive shells of
the "tent olive" species with neatly intersecting lines and russet
spots standing out sharply against a flesh–colored
background, fanciful spider conchs that looked like petrified
scorpions, transparent glass snails, argonauts, some highly edible
cuttlefish, and certain species of squid that the naturalists of
antiquity classified with the flying fish, which are used chiefly
as bait for catching cod.</p>
      <p>As for the fish in these waterways, I noted various species that
I hadn't yet had the opportunity to study. Among cartilaginous
fish: some brook lamprey, a type of eel fifteen inches long, head
greenish, fins violet, back bluish gray, belly a silvery brown
strewn with bright spots, iris of the eye encircled in gold,
unusual animals that the Amazon's current must have swept out to
sea because their natural habitat is fresh water; sting rays, the
snout pointed, the tail long, slender, and armed with an extensive
jagged sting; small one–meter sharks with gray and whitish
hides, their teeth arranged in several backward–curving rows,
fish commonly known by the name carpet shark; batfish, a sort of
reddish isosceles triangle half a meter long, whose pectoral fins
are attached by fleshy extensions that make these fish look like
bats, although an appendage made of horn, located near the
nostrils, earns them the nickname of sea unicorns; lastly, a couple
species of triggerfish, the cucuyo whose stippled flanks glitter
with a sparkling gold color, and the bright purple leatherjacket
whose hues glisten like a pigeon's throat.</p>
      <p>I'll finish up this catalog, a little dry but quite accurate,
with the series of bony fish I observed: eels belonging to the
genus <i>Apteronotus</i> whose snow–white snout is very
blunt, the body painted a handsome black and armed with a very
long, slender, fleshy whip; long sardines from the genus
<i>Odontognathus</i>, like three–decimeter pike, shining with
a bright silver glow; Guaranian mackerel furnished with two anal
fins; black–tinted rudderfish that you catch by using
torches, fish measuring two meters and boasting white, firm, plump
meat that, when fresh, tastes like eel, when dried, like smoked
salmon; semired wrasse sporting scales only at the bases of their
dorsal and anal fins; grunts on which gold and silver mingle their
luster with that of ruby and topaz; yellow–tailed gilthead
whose flesh is extremely dainty and whose phosphorescent properties
give them away in the midst of the waters; porgies tinted orange,
with slender tongues; croakers with gold caudal fins; black
surgeonfish; four–eyed fish from Surinam, etc.</p>
      <p>This "et cetera" won't keep me from mentioning one more fish
that Conseil, with good reason, will long remember.</p>
      <p>One of our nets had hauled up a type of very flat ray that
weighed some twenty kilograms; with its tail cut off, it would have
formed a perfect disk. It was white underneath and reddish on top,
with big round spots of deep blue encircled in black, its hide
quite smooth and ending in a double–lobed fin. Laid out on
the platform, it kept struggling with convulsive movements, trying
to turn over, making such efforts that its final lunge was about to
flip it into the sea. But Conseil, being very possessive of his
fish, rushed at it, and before I could stop him, he seized it with
both hands.</p>
      <p>Instantly there he was, thrown on his back, legs in the air, his
body half paralyzed, and yelling:</p>
      <p>"Oh, sir, sir! Will you help me!"</p>
      <p>For once in his life, the poor lad didn't address me "in the
third person."</p>
      <p>The Canadian and I sat him up; we massaged his contracted arms,
and when he regained his five senses, that eternal classifier
mumbled in a broken voice:</p>
      <p>"Class of <i>cartilaginous</i> fish, order
<i>Chondropterygia</i> with fixed gills, suborder <i>Selacia</i>,
family <i>Rajiiforma</i>, genus <i>electric ray</i>."</p>
      <p>"Yes, my friend," I answered, "it was an electric ray that put
you in this deplorable state."</p>
      <p>"Oh, Master can trust me on this," Conseil shot back. "I'll be
revenged on that animal!"</p>
      <p>"How?"</p>
      <p>"I'll eat it."</p>
      <p>Which he did that same evening, but strictly as retaliation.
Because, frankly, it tasted like leather.</p>
      <p>Poor Conseil had assaulted an electric ray of the most dangerous
species, the <i>cumana</i>. Living in a conducting medium such as
water, this bizarre animal can electrocute other fish from several
meters away, so great is the power of its electric organ, an organ
whose two chief surfaces measure at least twenty–seven square
feet.</p>
      <p>During the course of the next day, April 12, the <i>Nautilus</i>
drew near the coast of Dutch Guiana, by the mouth of the Maroni
River. There several groups of sea cows were living in family
units. These were manatees, which belong to the order
<i>Sirenia</i>, like the dugong and Steller's sea cow. Harmless and
unaggressive, these fine animals were six to seven meters long and
must have weighed at least 4,000 kilograms each. I told Ned Land
and Conseil that farseeing nature had given these mammals a major
role to play. In essence, manatees, like seals, are designed to
graze the underwater prairies, destroying the clusters of weeds
that obstruct the mouths of tropical rivers.</p>
      <p>"And do you know," I added, "what happened since man has almost
completely wiped out these beneficial races? Rotting weeds have
poisoned the air, and this poisoned air causes the yellow fever
that devastates these wonderful countries. This toxic vegetation
has increased beneath the seas of the Torrid Zone, so the disease
spreads unchecked from the mouth of the Rio de la Plata to
Florida!"</p>
      <p>And if Professor Toussenel is correct, this plague is nothing
compared to the scourge that will strike our descendants once the
seas are depopulated of whales and seals. By then, crowded with
jellyfish, squid, and other devilfish, the oceans will have become
huge centers of infection, because their waves will no longer
possess "these huge stomachs that God has entrusted with scouring
the surface of the sea."</p>
      <p>Meanwhile, without scorning these theories, the
<i>Nautilus's</i> crew captured half a dozen manatees. In essence,
it was an issue of stocking the larder with excellent red meat,
even better than beef or veal. Their hunting was not a fascinating
sport. The manatees let themselves be struck down without offering
any resistance. Several thousand kilos of meat were hauled below,
to be dried and stored.</p>
      <p>The same day an odd fishing practice further increased the
<i>Nautilus's</i> stores, so full of game were these seas. Our
trawl brought up in its meshes a number of fish whose heads were
topped by little oval slabs with fleshy edges. These were
suckerfish from the third family of the <i>subbrachian
Malacopterygia</i>. These flat disks on their heads consist of
crosswise plates of movable cartilage, between which the animals
can create a vacuum, enabling them to stick to objects like suction
cups.</p>
      <p>The <i>remoras</i> I had observed in the Mediterranean were
related to this species. But the creature at issue here was an
<i>Echeneis osteochara</i>, unique to this sea. Right after
catching them, our seamen dropped them in buckets of water.</p>
      <p>Its fishing finished, the <i>Nautilus</i> drew nearer to the
coast. In this locality a number of sea turtles were sleeping on
the surface of the waves. It would have been difficult to capture
these valuable reptiles, because they wake up at the slightest
sound, and their solid carapaces are harpoon–proof. But our
suckerfish would effect their capture with extraordinary certainty
and precision. In truth, this animal is a living fishhook,
promising wealth and happiness to the greenest fisherman in the
business.</p>
      <p>The <i>Nautilus's</i> men attached to each fish's tail a ring
that was big enough not to hamper its movements, and to this ring a
long rope whose other end was moored on board.</p>
      <p>Thrown into the sea, the suckerfish immediately began to play
their roles, going and fastening themselves onto the breastplates
of the turtles. Their tenacity was so great, they would rip apart
rather than let go. They were hauled in, still sticking to the
turtles that came aboard with them.</p>
      <p>In this way we caught several loggerheads, reptiles a meter wide
and weighing 200 kilos. They're extremely valuable because of their
carapaces, which are covered with big slabs of horn, thin, brown,
transparent, with white and yellow markings. Besides, they were
excellent from an edible viewpoint, with an exquisite flavor
comparable to the green turtle.</p>
      <p>This fishing ended our stay in the waterways of the Amazon, and
that evening the <i>Nautilus</i> took to the high seas once
more.</p>
   </body>
</topic>