<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<topic id="d2e10630">
   <title>
      <d4pSimpleEnumerator><!--2.9-->Chapter 9. </d4pSimpleEnumerator>
      <ph>A Lost Continent</ph>
   </title>
   <body>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="size_plus_2">THE NEXT MORNING</ph>, February 19, I beheld
the Canadian entering my stateroom. I was expecting this visit. He
wore an expression of great disappointment.</p>
      <p>"Well, sir?" he said to me.</p>
      <p>"Well, Ned, the fates were against us yesterday."</p>
      <p>"Yes! That damned captain had to call a halt just as we were
going to escape from his boat."</p>
      <p>"Yes, Ned, he had business with his bankers."</p>
      <p>"His bankers?"</p>
      <p>"Or rather his bank vaults. By which I mean this ocean, where
his wealth is safer than in any national treasury."</p>
      <p>I then related the evening's incidents to the Canadian, secretly
hoping he would come around to the idea of not deserting the
captain; but my narrative had no result other than Ned's voicing
deep regret that he hadn't strolled across the Vigo battlefield on
his own behalf.</p>
      <p>"Anyhow," he said, "it's not over yet! My first harpoon missed,
that's all! We'll succeed the next time, and as soon as this
evening, if need be . . ."</p>
      <p>"What's the <i>Nautilus's</i> heading?" I asked.</p>
      <p>"I've no idea," Ned replied.</p>
      <p>"All right, at noon we'll find out what our position is!"</p>
      <p>The Canadian returned to Conseil's side. As soon as I was
dressed, I went into the lounge. The compass wasn't encouraging.
The <i>Nautilus's</i> course was south–southwest. We were
turning our backs on Europe.</p>
      <p>I could hardly wait until our position was reported on the
chart. Near 11:30 the ballast tanks emptied, and the submersible
rose to the surface of the ocean. I leaped onto the platform. Ned
Land was already there.</p>
      <p>No more shore in sight. Nothing but the immenseness of the sea.
A few sails were on the horizon, no doubt ships going as far as
Cape São Roque to find favorable winds for doubling the Cape
of Good Hope. The sky was overcast. A squall was on the way.</p>
      <p>Furious, Ned tried to see through the mists on the horizon. He
still hoped that behind all that fog there lay those shores he
longed for.</p>
      <p>At noon the sun made a momentary appearance. Taking advantage of
this rift in the clouds, the chief officer took the orb's altitude.
Then the sea grew turbulent, we went below again, and the hatch
closed once more.</p>
      <p>When I consulted the chart an hour later, I saw that the
<i>Nautilus's</i> position was marked at longitude 16° 17' and
latitude 33° 22', a good 150 leagues from the nearest coast. It
wouldn't do to even dream of escaping, and I'll let the reader
decide how promptly the Canadian threw a tantrum when I ventured to
tell him our situation.</p>
      <p>As for me, I wasn't exactly grief–stricken. I felt as if a
heavy weight had been lifted from me, and I was able to resume my
regular tasks in a state of comparative calm.</p>
      <p>Near eleven o'clock in the evening, I received a most unexpected
visit from Captain Nemo. He asked me very graciously if I felt
exhausted from our vigil the night before. I said no.</p>
      <p>"Then, Professor Aronnax, I propose an unusual excursion."</p>
      <p>"Propose away, Captain."</p>
      <p>"So far you've visited the ocean depths only by day and under
sunlight. Would you like to see these depths on a dark night?"</p>
      <p>"Very much."</p>
      <p>"I warn you, this will be an exhausting stroll. We'll need to
walk long hours and scale a mountain. The roads aren't terribly
well kept up."</p>
      <p>"Everything you say, Captain, just increases my curiosity. I'm
ready to go with you."</p>
      <p>"Then come along, professor, and we'll go put on our diving
suits."</p>
      <p>Arriving at the wardrobe, I saw that neither my companions nor
any crewmen would be coming with us on this excursion. Captain Nemo
hadn't even suggested my fetching Ned or Conseil.</p>
      <p>In a few moments we had put on our equipment. Air tanks,
abundantly charged, were placed on our backs, but the electric
lamps were not in readiness. I commented on this to the
captain.</p>
      <p>"They'll be useless to us," he replied.</p>
      <p>I thought I hadn't heard him right, but I couldn't repeat my
comment because the captain's head had already disappeared into its
metal covering. I finished harnessing myself, I felt an alpenstock
being placed in my hand, and a few minutes later, after the usual
procedures, we set foot on the floor of the Atlantic, 300 meters
down.</p>
      <p>Midnight was approaching. The waters were profoundly dark, but
Captain Nemo pointed to a reddish spot in the distance, a sort of
wide glow shimmering about two miles from the <i>Nautilus</i>. What
this fire was, what substances fed it, how and why it kept burning
in the liquid mass, I couldn't say. Anyhow it lit our way, although
hazily, but I soon grew accustomed to this unique gloom, and in
these circumstances I understood the uselessness of the Ruhmkorff
device.</p>
      <p>Side by side, Captain Nemo and I walked directly toward this
conspicuous flame. The level seafloor rose imperceptibly. We took
long strides, helped by our alpenstocks; but in general our
progress was slow, because our feet kept sinking into a kind of
slimy mud mixed with seaweed and assorted flat stones.</p>
      <p>As we moved forward, I heard a kind of pitter–patter above
my head. Sometimes this noise increased and became a continuous
crackle. I soon realized the cause. It was a heavy rainfall
rattling on the surface of the waves. Instinctively I worried that
I might get soaked! By water in the midst of water! I couldn't help
smiling at this outlandish notion. But to tell the truth, wearing
these heavy diving suits, you no longer feel the liquid element,
you simply think you're in the midst of air a little denser than
air on land, that's all.</p>
      <p>After half an hour of walking, the seafloor grew rocky.
Jellyfish, microscopic crustaceans, and sea–pen coral lit it
faintly with their phosphorescent glimmers. I glimpsed piles of
stones covered by a couple million zoophytes and tangles of algae.
My feet often slipped on this viscous seaweed carpet, and without
my alpenstock I would have fallen more than once. When I turned
around, I could still see the <i>Nautilus's</i> whitish beacon,
which was starting to grow pale in the distance.</p>
      <p>Those piles of stones just mentioned were laid out on the ocean
floor with a distinct but inexplicable symmetry. I spotted gigantic
furrows trailing off into the distant darkness, their length
incalculable. There also were other peculiarities I couldn't make
sense of. It seemed to me that my heavy lead soles were crushing a
litter of bones that made a dry crackling noise. So what were these
vast plains we were now crossing? I wanted to ask the captain, but
I still didn't grasp that sign language that allowed him to chat
with his companions when they went with him on his underwater
excursions.</p>
      <p>Meanwhile the reddish light guiding us had expanded and inflamed
the horizon. The presence of this furnace under the waters had me
extremely puzzled. Was it some sort of electrical discharge? Was I
approaching some natural phenomenon still unknown to scientists on
shore? Or, rather (and this thought did cross my mind), had the
hand of man intervened in that blaze? Had human beings fanned those
flames? In these deep strata would I meet up with more of Captain
Nemo's companions, friends he was about to visit who led lives as
strange as his own? Would I find a whole colony of exiles down
here, men tired of the world's woes, men who had sought and found
independence in the ocean's lower depths? All these insane,
inadmissible ideas dogged me, and in this frame of mind,
continually excited by the series of wonders passing before my
eyes, I wouldn't have been surprised to find on this sea bottom one
of those underwater towns Captain Nemo dreamed about!</p>
      <p>Our path was getting brighter and brighter. The red glow had
turned white and was radiating from a mountain peak about 800 feet
high. But what I saw was simply a reflection produced by the
crystal waters of these strata. The furnace that was the source of
this inexplicable light occupied the far side of the mountain.</p>
      <p>In the midst of the stone mazes furrowing this Atlantic
seafloor, Captain Nemo moved forward without hesitation. He knew
this dark path. No doubt he had often traveled it and was incapable
of losing his way. I followed him with unshakeable confidence. He
seemed like some Spirit of the Sea, and as he walked ahead of me, I
marveled at his tall figure, which stood out in black against the
glowing background of the horizon.</p>
      <p>It was one o'clock in the morning. We arrived at the mountain's
lower gradients. But in grappling with them, we had to venture up
difficult trails through a huge thicket.</p>
      <p>Yes, a thicket of dead trees! Trees without leaves, without sap,
turned to stone by the action of the waters, and crowned here and
there by gigantic pines. It was like a still–erect coalfield,
its roots clutching broken soil, its boughs clearly outlined
against the ceiling of the waters like thin, black, paper cutouts.
Picture a forest clinging to the sides of a peak in the Harz
Mountains, but a submerged forest. The trails were cluttered with
algae and fucus plants, hosts of crustaceans swarming among them. I
plunged on, scaling rocks, straddling fallen tree trunks, snapping
marine creepers that swayed from one tree to another, startling the
fish that flitted from branch to branch. Carried away, I didn't
feel exhausted any more. I followed a guide who was immune to
exhaustion.</p>
      <p>What a sight! How can I describe it! How can I portray these
woods and rocks in this liquid setting, their lower parts dark and
sullen, their upper parts tinted red in this light whose intensity
was doubled by the reflecting power of the waters! We scaled rocks
that crumbled behind us, collapsing in enormous sections with the
hollow rumble of an avalanche. To our right and left there were
carved gloomy galleries where the eye lost its way. Huge glades
opened up, seemingly cleared by the hand of man, and I sometimes
wondered whether some residents of these underwater regions would
suddenly appear before me.</p>
      <p>But Captain Nemo kept climbing. I didn't want to fall behind. I
followed him boldly. My alpenstock was a great help. One wrong step
would have been disastrous on the narrow paths cut into the sides
of these chasms, but I walked along with a firm tread and without
the slightest feeling of dizziness. Sometimes I leaped over a
crevasse whose depth would have made me recoil had I been in the
midst of glaciers on shore; sometimes I ventured out on a wobbling
tree trunk fallen across a gorge, without looking down, having eyes
only for marveling at the wild scenery of this region. There,
leaning on erratically cut foundations, monumental rocks seemed to
defy the laws of balance. From between their stony knees, trees
sprang up like jets under fearsome pressure, supporting other trees
that supported them in turn. Next, natural towers with wide,
steeply carved battlements leaned at angles that, on dry land, the
laws of gravity would never have authorized.</p>
      <p>And I too could feel the difference created by the water's
powerful density—despite my heavy clothing, copper headpiece,
and metal soles, I climbed the most impossibly steep gradients with
all the nimbleness, I swear it, of a chamois or a Pyrenees mountain
goat!</p>
      <p>As for my account of this excursion under the waters, I'm well
aware that it sounds incredible! I'm the chronicler of deeds
seemingly impossible and yet incontestably real. This was no
fantasy. This was what I saw and felt!</p>
      <p>Two hours after leaving the <i>Nautilus</i>, we had cleared the
timberline, and 100 feet above our heads stood the mountain peak,
forming a dark silhouette against the brilliant glare that came
from its far slope. Petrified shrubs rambled here and there in
sprawling zigzags. Fish rose in a body at our feet like birds
startled in tall grass. The rocky mass was gouged with impenetrable
crevices, deep caves, unfathomable holes at whose far ends I could
hear fearsome things moving around. My blood would curdle as I
watched some enormous antenna bar my path, or saw some frightful
pincer snap shut in the shadow of some cavity! A thousand specks of
light glittered in the midst of the gloom. They were the eyes of
gigantic crustaceans crouching in their lairs, giant lobsters
rearing up like spear carriers and moving their claws with a
scrap–iron clanking, titanic crabs aiming their bodies like
cannons on their carriages, and hideous devilfish intertwining
their tentacles like bushes of writhing snakes.</p>
      <p>What was this astounding world that I didn't yet know? In what
order did these articulates belong, these creatures for which the
rocks provided a second carapace? Where had nature learned the
secret of their vegetating existence, and for how many centuries
had they lived in the ocean's lower strata?</p>
      <p>But I couldn't linger. Captain Nemo, on familiar terms with
these dreadful animals, no longer minded them. We arrived at a
preliminary plateau where still other surprises were waiting for
me. There picturesque ruins took shape, betraying the hand of man,
not our Creator. They were huge stacks of stones in which you could
distinguish the indistinct forms of palaces and temples, now
arrayed in hosts of blossoming zoophytes, and over it all, not ivy
but a heavy mantle of algae and fucus plants.</p>
      <p>But what part of the globe could this be, this land swallowed by
cataclysms? Who had set up these rocks and stones like the dolmens
of prehistoric times? Where was I, where had Captain Nemo's fancies
taken me?</p>
      <p>I wanted to ask him. Unable to, I stopped him. I seized his arm.
But he shook his head, pointed to the mountain's topmost peak, and
seemed to tell me:</p>
      <p>"Come on! Come with me! Come higher!"</p>
      <p>I followed him with one last burst of energy, and in a few
minutes I had scaled the peak, which crowned the whole rocky mass
by some ten meters.</p>
      <p>I looked back down the side we had just cleared. There the
mountain rose only 700 to 800 feet above the plains; but on its far
slope it crowned the receding bottom of this part of the Atlantic
by a height twice that. My eyes scanned the distance and took in a
vast area lit by intense flashes of light. In essence, this
mountain was a volcano. Fifty feet below its peak, amid a shower of
stones and slag, a wide crater vomited torrents of lava that were
dispersed in fiery cascades into the heart of the liquid mass. So
situated, this volcano was an immense torch that lit up the lower
plains all the way to the horizon.</p>
      <p>As I said, this underwater crater spewed lava, but not flames.
Flames need oxygen from the air and are unable to spread
underwater; but a lava flow, which contains in itself the principle
of its incandescence, can rise to a white heat, overpower the
liquid element, and turn it into steam on contact. Swift currents
swept away all this diffuse gas, and torrents of lava slid to the
foot of the mountain, like the disgorgings of a Mt. Vesuvius over
the city limits of a second Torre del Greco.</p>
      <p>In fact, there beneath my eyes was a town in ruins, demolished,
overwhelmed, laid low, its roofs caved in, its temples pulled down,
its arches dislocated, its columns stretching over the earth; in
these ruins you could still detect the solid proportions of a sort
of Tuscan architecture; farther off, the remains of a gigantic
aqueduct; here, the caked heights of an acropolis along with the
fluid forms of a Parthenon; there, the remnants of a wharf, as if
some bygone port had long ago harbored merchant vessels and
triple–tiered war galleys on the shores of some lost ocean;
still farther off, long rows of collapsing walls, deserted
thoroughfares, a whole Pompeii buried under the waters, which
Captain Nemo had resurrected before my eyes!</p>
      <p>Where was I? Where was I? I had to find out at all cost, I
wanted to speak, I wanted to rip off the copper sphere imprisoning
my head.</p>
      <p>But Captain Nemo came over and stopped me with a gesture. Then,
picking up a piece of chalky stone, he advanced to a black basaltic
rock and scrawled this one word:</p>
      <lq>
         <p>ATLANTIS</p>
      </lq>
      <p>What lightning flashed through my mind! Atlantis, that ancient
land of Meropis mentioned by the historian Theopompus; Plato's
Atlantis; the continent whose very existence has been denied by
such philosophers and scientists as Origen, Porphyry, Iamblichus,
d'Anville, Malte–Brun, and Humboldt, who entered its
disappearance in the ledger of myths and folk tales; the country
whose reality has nevertheless been accepted by such other thinkers
as Posidonius, Pliny, Ammianus Marcellinus, Tertullian, Engel,
Scherer, Tournefort, Buffon, and d'Avezac; I had this land right
under my eyes, furnishing its own unimpeachable evidence of the
catastrophe that had overtaken it! So this was the submerged region
that had existed outside Europe, Asia, and Libya, beyond the
Pillars of Hercules, home of those powerful Atlantean people
against whom ancient Greece had waged its earliest wars!</p>
      <p>The writer whose narratives record the lofty deeds of those
heroic times is Plato himself. His dialogues <i>Timæus</i>
and <i>Critias</i> were drafted with the poet and legislator Solon
as their inspiration, as it were.</p>
      <p>One day Solon was conversing with some elderly wise men in the
Egyptian capital of Sais, a town already 8,000 years of age, as
documented by the annals engraved on the sacred walls of its
temples. One of these elders related the history of another town
1,000 years older still. This original city of Athens, ninety
centuries old, had been invaded and partly destroyed by the
Atlanteans. These Atlanteans, he said, resided on an immense
continent greater than Africa and Asia combined, taking in an area
that lay between latitude 12° and 40° north. Their dominion
extended even to Egypt. They tried to enforce their rule as far as
Greece, but they had to retreat before the indomitable resistance
of the Hellenic people. Centuries passed. A cataclysm
occurred—floods, earthquakes. A single night and day were
enough to obliterate this Atlantis, whose highest peaks (Madeira,
the Azores, the Canaries, the Cape Verde Islands) still emerge
above the waves.</p>
      <p>These were the historical memories that Captain Nemo's scrawl
sent rushing through my mind. Thus, led by the strangest of fates,
I was treading underfoot one of the mountains of that continent! My
hands were touching ruins many thousands of years old, contemporary
with prehistoric times! I was walking in the very place where
contemporaries of early man had walked! My heavy soles were
crushing the skeletons of animals from the age of fable, animals
that used to take cover in the shade of these trees now turned to
stone!</p>
      <p>Oh, why was I so short of time! I would have gone down the steep
slopes of this mountain, crossed this entire immense continent,
which surely connects Africa with America, and visited its great
prehistoric cities. Under my eyes there perhaps lay the warlike
town of Makhimos or the pious village of Eusebes, whose gigantic
inhabitants lived for whole centuries and had the strength to raise
blocks of stone that still withstood the action of the waters. One
day perhaps, some volcanic phenomenon will bring these sunken ruins
back to the surface of the waves! Numerous underwater volcanoes
have been sighted in this part of the ocean, and many ships have
felt terrific tremors when passing over these turbulent depths. A
few have heard hollow noises that announced some struggle of the
elements far below, others have hauled in volcanic ash hurled above
the waves. As far as the equator this whole seafloor is still under
construction by plutonic forces. And in some remote epoch, built up
by volcanic disgorgings and successive layers of lava, who knows
whether the peaks of these fire–belching mountains may
reappear above the surface of the Atlantic!</p>
      <p>As I mused in this way, trying to establish in my memory every
detail of this impressive landscape, Captain Nemo was leaning his
elbows on a moss–covered monument, motionless as if petrified
in some mute trance. Was he dreaming of those lost generations,
asking them for the secret of human destiny? Was it here that this
strange man came to revive himself, basking in historical memories,
reliving that bygone life, he who had no desire for our modern one?
I would have given anything to know his thoughts, to share them,
understand them!</p>
      <p>We stayed in this place an entire hour, contemplating its vast
plains in the lava's glow, which sometimes took on a startling
intensity. Inner boilings sent quick shivers running through the
mountain's crust. Noises from deep underneath, clearly transmitted
by the liquid medium, reverberated with majestic amplitude.</p>
      <p>Just then the moon appeared for an instant through the watery
mass, casting a few pale rays over this submerged continent. It was
only a fleeting glimmer, but its effect was indescribable. The
captain stood up and took one last look at these immense plains;
then his hand signaled me to follow him.</p>
      <p>We went swiftly down the mountain. Once past the petrified
forest, I could see the <i>Nautilus's</i> beacon twinkling like a
star. The captain walked straight toward it, and we were back on
board just as the first glimmers of dawn were whitening the surface
of the ocean.</p>
   </body>
</topic>