<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<topic id="d2e12479">
   <title>
      <d4pSimpleEnumerator><!--2.14-->Chapter 14. </d4pSimpleEnumerator>
      <ph>The South Pole</ph>
   </title>
   <body>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="size_plus_2">I RUSHED UP</ph> onto the platform. Yes, open
sea! Barely a few sparse floes, some moving icebergs; a sea
stretching into the distance; hosts of birds in the air and myriads
of fish under the waters, which varied from intense blue to olive
green depending on the depth. The thermometer marked 3°
centigrade. It was as if a comparative springtime had been locked
up behind that Ice Bank, whose distant masses were outlined on the
northern horizon.</p>
      <p>"Are we at the pole?" I asked the captain, my heart
pounding.</p>
      <p>"I've no idea," he answered me. "At noon we'll fix our
position."</p>
      <p>"But will the sun show through this mist?" I said, staring at
the grayish sky.</p>
      <p>"No matter how faintly it shines, it will be enough for me," the
captain replied.</p>
      <p>To the south, ten miles from the <i>Nautilus</i>, a solitary
islet rose to a height of 200 meters. We proceeded toward it, but
cautiously, because this sea could have been strewn with reefs.</p>
      <p>In an hour we had reached the islet. Two hours later we had
completed a full circle around it. It measured four to five miles
in circumference. A narrow channel separated it from a considerable
shore, perhaps a continent whose limits we couldn't see. The
existence of this shore seemed to bear out Commander Maury's
hypotheses. In essence, this ingenious American has noted that
between the South Pole and the 60th parallel, the sea is covered
with floating ice of dimensions much greater than any found in the
north Atlantic. From this fact he drew the conclusion that the
Antarctic Circle must contain considerable shores, since icebergs
can't form on the high seas but only along coastlines. According to
his calculations, this frozen mass enclosing the southernmost pole
forms a vast ice cap whose width must reach 4,000 kilometers.</p>
      <p>Meanwhile, to avoid running aground, the <i>Nautilus</i> halted
three cable lengths from a strand crowned by superb piles of rocks.
The skiff was launched to sea. Two crewmen carrying instruments,
the captain, Conseil, and I were on board. It was ten o'clock in
the morning. I hadn't seen Ned Land. No doubt, in the presence of
the South Pole, the Canadian hated having to eat his words.</p>
      <p>A few strokes of the oar brought the skiff to the sand, where it
ran aground. Just as Conseil was about to jump ashore, I held him
back.</p>
      <p>"Sir," I told Captain Nemo, "to you belongs the honor of first
setting foot on this shore."</p>
      <p>"Yes, sir," the captain replied, "and if I have no hesitation in
treading this polar soil, it's because no human being until now has
left a footprint here."</p>
      <p>So saying, he leaped lightly onto the sand. His heart must have
been throbbing with intense excitement. He scaled an overhanging
rock that ended in a small promontory and there, mute and
motionless, with crossed arms and blazing eyes, he seemed to be
laying claim to these southernmost regions. After spending five
minutes in this trance, he turned to us.</p>
      <p>"Whenever you're ready, sir," he called to me.</p>
      <p>I got out, Conseil at my heels, leaving the two men in the
skiff.</p>
      <p>Over an extensive area, the soil consisted of that igneous
gravel called "tuff," reddish in color as if made from crushed
bricks. The ground was covered with slag, lava flows, and pumice
stones. Its volcanic origin was unmistakable. In certain localities
thin smoke holes gave off a sulfurous odor, showing that the inner
fires still kept their wide–ranging power. Nevertheless, when
I scaled a high escarpment, I could see no volcanoes within a
radius of several miles. In these Antarctic districts, as is well
known, Sir James Clark Ross had found the craters of Mt. Erebus and
Mt. Terror in fully active condition on the 167th meridian at
latitude 77° 32'.</p>
      <p>The vegetation on this desolate continent struck me as quite
limited. A few lichens of the species <i>Usnea melanoxanthra</i>
sprawled over the black rocks. The whole meager flora of this
region consisted of certain microscopic buds, rudimentary diatoms
made up of a type of cell positioned between two quartz–rich
shells, plus long purple and crimson fucus plants, buoyed by small
air bladders and washed up on the coast by the surf.</p>
      <p>The beach was strewn with mollusks: small mussels, limpets,
smooth heart–shaped cockles, and especially some sea
butterflies with oblong, membrane–filled bodies whose heads
are formed from two rounded lobes. I also saw myriads of those
northernmost sea butterflies three centimeters long, which a baleen
whale can swallow by the thousands in one gulp. The open waters at
the shoreline were alive with these delightful pteropods, true
butterflies of the sea.</p>
      <p>Among other zoophytes present in these shallows, there were a
few coral tree forms that, according to Sir James Clark Ross, live
in these Antarctic seas at depths as great as 1,000 meters; then
small alcyon coral belonging to the species <i>Procellaria
pelagica</i>, also a large number of starfish unique to these
climes, plus some feather stars spangling the sand.</p>
      <p>But it was in the air that life was superabundant. There various
species of birds flew and fluttered by the thousands, deafening us
with their calls. Crowding the rocks, other fowl watched without
fear as we passed and pressed familiarly against our feet. These
were auks, as agile and supple in water, where they are sometimes
mistaken for fast bonito, as they are clumsy and heavy on land.
They uttered outlandish calls and participated in numerous public
assemblies that featured much noise but little action.</p>
      <p>Among other fowl I noted some sheathbills from the
wading–bird family, the size of pigeons, white in color, the
beak short and conical, the eyes framed by red circles. Conseil
laid in a supply of them, because when they're properly cooked,
these winged creatures make a pleasant dish. In the air there
passed sooty albatross with four–meter wingspans, birds aptly
dubbed "vultures of the ocean," also gigantic petrels including
several with arching wings, enthusiastic eaters of seal that are
known as quebrantahuesos,<fn callout="*">Spanish: "ospreys."
Ed.</fn> and cape
pigeons, a sort of small duck, the tops of their bodies black and
white—in short, a whole series of petrels, some whitish with
wings trimmed in brown, others blue and exclusive to these
Antarctic seas, the former "so oily," I told Conseil, "that
inhabitants of the Faroe Islands simply fit the bird with a wick,
then light it up."</p>
      <p>"With that minor addition," Conseil replied, "these fowl would
make perfect lamps! After this, we should insist that nature equip
them with wicks in advance!"</p>
      <p>Half a mile farther on, the ground was completely riddled with
penguin nests, egg–laying burrows from which numerous birds
emerged. Later Captain Nemo had hundreds of them hunted because
their black flesh is highly edible. They brayed like donkeys. The
size of a goose with slate–colored bodies, white undersides,
and lemon–colored neck bands, these animals let themselves be
stoned to death without making any effort to get away.</p>
      <p>Meanwhile the mists didn't clear, and by eleven o'clock the sun
still hadn't made an appearance. Its absence disturbed me. Without
it, no sights were possible. Then how could we tell whether we had
reached the pole?</p>
      <p>When I rejoined Captain Nemo, I found him leaning silently
against a piece of rock and staring at the sky. He seemed
impatient, baffled. But what could we do? This daring and powerful
man couldn't control the sun as he did the sea.</p>
      <p>Noon arrived without the orb of day appearing for a single
instant. You couldn't even find its hiding place behind the curtain
of mist. And soon this mist began to condense into snow.</p>
      <p>"Until tomorrow," the captain said simply; and we went back to
the <i>Nautilus</i>, amid flurries in the air.</p>
      <p>During our absence the nets had been spread, and I observed with
fascination the fish just hauled on board. The Antarctic seas serve
as a refuge for an extremely large number of migratory fish that
flee from storms in the subpolar zones, in truth only to slide down
the gullets of porpoises and seals. I noted some
one–decimeter southern bullhead, a species of whitish
cartilaginous fish overrun with bluish gray stripes and armed with
stings, then some Antarctic rabbitfish three feet long, the body
very slender, the skin a smooth silver white, the head rounded, the
topside furnished with three fins, the snout ending in a trunk that
curved back toward the mouth. I sampled its flesh but found it
tasteless, despite Conseil's views, which were largely
approving.</p>
      <p>The blizzard lasted until the next day. It was impossible to
stay on the platform. From the lounge, where I was writing up the
incidents of this excursion to the polar continent, I could hear
the calls of petrel and albatross cavorting in the midst of the
turmoil. The <i>Nautilus</i> didn't stay idle, and cruising along
the coast, it advanced some ten miles farther south amid the half
light left by the sun as it skimmed the edge of the horizon.</p>
      <p>The next day, March 20, it stopped snowing. The cold was a
little more brisk. The thermometer marked –2° centigrade.
The mist had cleared, and on that day I hoped our noon sights could
be accomplished.</p>
      <p>Since Captain Nemo hadn't yet appeared, only Conseil and I were
taken ashore by the skiff. The soil's nature was still the same:
volcanic. Traces of lava, slag, and basaltic rock were everywhere,
but I couldn't find the crater that had vomited them up. There as
yonder, myriads of birds enlivened this part of the polar
continent. But they had to share their dominion with huge herds of
marine mammals that looked at us with gentle eyes. These were seals
of various species, some stretched out on the ground, others lying
on drifting ice floes, several leaving or reentering the sea.
Having never dealt with man, they didn't run off at our approach,
and I counted enough of them thereabouts to provision a couple
hundred ships.</p>
      <p>"Ye gods," Conseil said, "it's fortunate that Ned Land didn't
come with us!"</p>
      <p>"Why so, Conseil?"</p>
      <p>"Because that madcap hunter would kill every animal here."</p>
      <p>"Every animal may be overstating it, but in truth I doubt we
could keep our Canadian friend from harpooning some of these
magnificent <i>cetaceans</i>. Which would be an affront to Captain
Nemo, since he hates to slay harmless beasts needlessly."</p>
      <p>"He's right."</p>
      <p>"Certainly, Conseil. But tell me, haven't you finished
classifying these superb specimens of marine fauna?"</p>
      <p>"Master is well aware," Conseil replied, "that I'm not seasoned
in practical application. When master has told me these animals'
names . . ."</p>
      <p>"They're seals and walruses."</p>
      <p>"Two genera," our scholarly Conseil hastened to say, "that
belong to the family <i>Pinnipedia</i>, order <i>Carnivora</i>,
group <i>Unguiculata</i>, subclass <i>Monodelphia</i>, class
<i>Mammalia</i>, branch <i>Vertebrata</i>."</p>
      <p>"Very nice, Conseil," I replied, "but these two genera of seals
and walruses are each divided into species, and if I'm not
mistaken, we now have a chance to actually look at them.
Let's."</p>
      <p>It was eight o'clock in the morning. We had four hours to
ourselves before the sun could be productively observed. I guided
our steps toward a huge bay that made a crescent–shaped
incision in the granite cliffs along the beach.</p>
      <p>There, all about us, I swear that the shores and ice floes were
crowded with marine mammals as far as the eye could see, and I
involuntarily looked around for old Proteus, that mythological
shepherd who guarded King Neptune's immense flocks. To be specific,
these were seals. They formed distinct male–and–female
groups, the father watching over his family, the mother suckling
her little ones, the stronger youngsters emancipated a few paces
away. When these mammals wanted to relocate, they moved in little
jumps made by contracting their bodies, clumsily helped by their
imperfectly developed flippers, which, as with their manatee
relatives, form actual forearms. In the water, their ideal element,
I must say these animals swim wonderfully thanks to their flexible
backbones, narrow pelvises, close–cropped hair, and webbed
feet. Resting on shore, they assumed extremely graceful positions.
Consequently, their gentle features, their sensitive expressions
equal to those of the loveliest women, their soft, limpid eyes,
their charming poses, led the ancients to glorify them by
metamorphosing the males into sea gods and the females into
mermaids.</p>
      <p>I drew Conseil's attention to the considerable growth of the
cerebral lobes found in these intelligent <i>cetaceans</i>. No
mammal except man has more abundant cerebral matter. Accordingly,
seals are quite capable of being educated; they make good pets, and
together with certain other naturalists, I think these animals can
be properly trained to perform yeoman service as hunting dogs for
fishermen.</p>
      <p>Most of these seals were sleeping on the rocks or the sand.
Among those properly termed seals—which have no external
ears, unlike sea lions whose ears protrude—I observed several
varieties of the species <i>stenorhynchus</i>, three meters long,
with white hair, bulldog heads, and armed with ten teeth in each
jaw: four incisors in both the upper and lower, plus two big
canines shaped like the fleur–de–lis. Among them
slithered some sea elephants, a type of seal with a short, flexible
trunk; these are the giants of the species, with a circumference of
twenty feet and a length of ten meters. They didn't move as we
approached.</p>
      <p>"Are these animals dangerous?" Conseil asked me.</p>
      <p>"Only if they're attacked," I replied. "But when these giant
seals defend their little ones, their fury is dreadful, and it
isn't rare for them to smash a fisherman's longboat to bits."</p>
      <p>"They're within their rights," Conseil answered.</p>
      <p>"I don't say nay."</p>
      <p>Two miles farther on, we were stopped by a promontory that
screened the bay from southerly winds. It dropped straight down to
the sea, and surf foamed against it. From beyond this ridge there
came fearsome bellows, such as a herd of cattle might produce.</p>
      <p>"Gracious," Conseil put in, "a choir of bulls?"</p>
      <p>"No," I said, "a choir of walruses."</p>
      <p>"Are they fighting with each other?"</p>
      <p>"Either fighting or playing."</p>
      <p>"With all due respect to Master, this we must see."</p>
      <p>"Then see it we must, Conseil."</p>
      <p>And there we were, climbing these blackish rocks amid sudden
landslides and over stones slippery with ice. More than once I took
a tumble at the expense of my backside. Conseil, more cautious or
more stable, barely faltered and would help me up, saying:</p>
      <p>"If Master's legs would kindly adopt a wider stance, Master will
keep his balance."</p>
      <p>Arriving at the topmost ridge of this promontory, I could see
vast white plains covered with walruses. These animals were playing
among themselves. They were howling not in anger but in glee.</p>
      <p>Walruses resemble seals in the shape of their bodies and the
arrangement of their limbs. But their lower jaws lack canines and
incisors, and as for their upper canines, they consist of two tusks
eighty centimeters long with a circumference of thirty–three
centimeters at the socket. Made of solid ivory, without striations,
harder than elephant tusks, and less prone to yellowing, these
teeth are in great demand. Accordingly, walruses are the victims of
a mindless hunting that soon will destroy them all, since their
hunters indiscriminately slaughter pregnant females and youngsters,
and over 4,000 individuals are destroyed annually.</p>
      <p>Passing near these unusual animals, I could examine them at my
leisure since they didn't stir. Their hides were rough and heavy, a
tan color leaning toward a reddish brown; their coats were short
and less than abundant. Some were four meters long. More tranquil
and less fearful than their northern relatives, they posted no
sentinels on guard duty at the approaches to their campsite.</p>
      <p>After examining this community of walruses, I decided to return
in my tracks. It was eleven o'clock, and if Captain Nemo found
conditions favorable for taking his sights, I wanted to be present
at the operation. But I held no hopes that the sun would make an
appearance that day. It was hidden from our eyes by clouds squeezed
together on the horizon. Apparently the jealous orb didn't want to
reveal this inaccessible spot on the globe to any human being.</p>
      <p>Yet I decided to return to the <i>Nautilus</i>. We went along a
steep, narrow path that ran over the cliff's summit. By 11:30 we
had arrived at our landing place. The beached skiff had brought the
captain ashore. I spotted him standing on a chunk of basalt. His
instruments were beside him. His eyes were focused on the northern
horizon, along which the sun was sweeping in its extended arc.</p>
      <p>I found a place near him and waited without speaking. Noon
arrived, and just as on the day before, the sun didn't put in an
appearance.</p>
      <p>It was sheer bad luck. Our noon sights were still lacking. If we
couldn't obtain them tomorrow, we would finally have to give up any
hope of fixing our position.</p>
      <p>In essence, it was precisely March 20. Tomorrow, the 21st, was
the day of the equinox; the sun would disappear below the horizon
for six months not counting refraction, and after its disappearance
the long polar night would begin. Following the September equinox,
the sun had emerged above the northerly horizon, rising in long
spirals until December 21. At that time, the summer solstice of
these southernmost districts, the sun had started back down, and
tomorrow it would cast its last rays.</p>
      <p>I shared my thoughts and fears with Captain Nemo.</p>
      <p>"You're right, Professor Aronnax," he told me. "If I can't take
the sun's altitude tomorrow, I won't be able to try again for
another six months. But precisely because sailors' luck has led me
into these seas on March 21, it will be easy to get our bearings if
the noonday sun does appear before our eyes."</p>
      <p>"Why easy, Captain?"</p>
      <p>"Because when the orb of day sweeps in such long spirals, it's
difficult to measure its exact altitude above the horizon, and our
instruments are open to committing serious errors."</p>
      <p>"Then what can you do?"</p>
      <p>"I use only my chronometer," Captain Nemo answered me. "At noon
tomorrow, March 21, if, after accounting for refraction, the sun's
disk is cut exactly in half by the northern horizon, that will mean
I'm at the South Pole."</p>
      <p>"Right," I said. "Nevertheless, it isn't mathematically exact
proof, because the equinox needn't fall precisely at noon."</p>
      <p>"No doubt, sir, but the error will be under 100 meters, and
that's close enough for us. Until tomorrow then."</p>
      <p>Captain Nemo went back on board. Conseil and I stayed behind
until five o'clock, surveying the beach, observing and studying.
The only unusual object I picked up was an auk's egg of remarkable
size, for which a collector would have paid more than ₣1,000.
Its cream–colored tint, plus the streaks and markings that
decorated it like so many hieroglyphics, made it a rare trinket. I
placed it in Conseil's hands, and holding it like precious
porcelain from China, that cautious, sure–footed lad got it
back to the <i>Nautilus</i> in one piece.</p>
      <p>There I put this rare egg inside one of the glass cases in the
museum. I ate supper, feasting with appetite on an excellent piece
of seal liver whose flavor reminded me of pork. Then I went to bed;
but not without praying, like a good Hindu, for the favors of the
radiant orb.</p>
      <p>The next day, March 21, bright and early at five o'clock in the
morning, I climbed onto the platform. I found Captain Nemo
there.</p>
      <p>"The weather is clearing a bit," he told me. "I have high hopes.
After breakfast we'll make our way ashore and choose an observation
post."</p>
      <p>This issue settled, I went to find Ned Land. I wanted to take
him with me. The obstinate Canadian refused, and I could clearly
see that his tight–lipped mood and his bad temper were
growing by the day. Under the circumstances I ultimately wasn't
sorry that he refused. In truth, there were too many seals ashore,
and it would never do to expose this impulsive fisherman to such
temptations.</p>
      <p>Breakfast over, I made my way ashore. The <i>Nautilus</i> had
gone a few more miles during the night. It lay well out, a good
league from the coast, which was crowned by a sharp peak 400 to 500
meters high. In addition to me, the skiff carried Captain Nemo, two
crewmen, and the instruments—in other words, a chronometer, a
spyglass, and a barometer.</p>
      <p>During our crossing I saw numerous baleen whales belonging to
the three species unique to these southernmost seas: the bowhead
whale (or "right whale," according to the English), which has no
dorsal fin; the humpback whale from the genus <i>Balaenoptera</i>
(in other words, "winged whales"), beasts with wrinkled bellies and
huge whitish fins that, genus name regardless, do not yet form
wings; and the finback whale, yellowish brown, the swiftest of all
<i>cetaceans</i>. This powerful animal is audible from far away
when it sends up towering spouts of air and steam that resemble
swirls of smoke. Herds of these different mammals were playing
about in the tranquil waters, and I could easily see that this
Antarctic polar basin now served as a refuge for those
<i>cetaceans</i> too relentlessly pursued by hunters.</p>
      <p>I also noted long, whitish strings of salps, a type of mollusk
found in clusters, and some jellyfish of large size that swayed in
the eddies of the billows.</p>
      <p>By nine o'clock we had pulled up to shore. The sky was growing
brighter. Clouds were fleeing to the south. Mists were rising from
the cold surface of the water. Captain Nemo headed toward the peak,
which he no doubt planned to make his observatory. It was an
arduous climb over sharp lava and pumice stones in the midst of air
often reeking with sulfurous fumes from the smoke holes. For a man
out of practice at treading land, the captain scaled the steepest
slopes with a supple agility I couldn't equal, and which would have
been envied by hunters of Pyrenees mountain goats.</p>
      <p>It took us two hours to reach the summit of this
half–crystal, half–basalt peak. From there our eyes
scanned a vast sea, which scrawled its boundary line firmly against
the background of the northern sky. At our feet: dazzling tracts of
white. Over our heads: a pale azure, clear of mists. North of us:
the sun's disk, like a ball of fire already cut into by the edge of
the horizon. From the heart of the waters: jets of liquid rising
like hundreds of magnificent bouquets. Far off, like a sleeping
<i>cetacean</i>: the <i>Nautilus</i>. Behind us to the south and
east: an immense shore, a chaotic heap of rocks and ice whose
limits we couldn't see.</p>
      <p>Arriving at the summit of this peak, Captain Nemo carefully
determined its elevation by means of his barometer, since he had to
take this factor into account in his noon sights.</p>
      <p>At 11:45 the sun, by then seen only by refraction, looked like a
golden disk, dispersing its last rays over this deserted continent
and down to these seas not yet plowed by the ships of man.</p>
      <p>Captain Nemo had brought a spyglass with a reticular eyepiece,
which corrected the sun's refraction by means of a mirror, and he
used it to observe the orb sinking little by little along a very
extended diagonal that reached below the horizon. I held the
chronometer. My heart was pounding mightily. If the lower half of
the sun's disk disappeared just as the chronometer said noon, we
were right at the pole.</p>
      <p>"Noon!" I called.</p>
      <p>"The South Pole!" Captain Nemo replied in a solemn voice,
handing me the spyglass, which showed the orb of day cut into two
exactly equal parts by the horizon.</p>
      <p>I stared at the last rays wreathing this peak, while shadows
were gradually climbing its gradients.</p>
      <p>Just then, resting his hand on my shoulder, Captain Nemo said to
me:</p>
      <p>"In 1600, sir, the Dutchman Gheritk was swept by storms and
currents, reaching latitude 64° south and discovering the South
Shetland Islands. On January 17, 1773, the famous Captain Cook went
along the 38th meridian, arriving at latitude 67° 30'; and on
January 30, 1774, along the 109th meridian, he reached latitude
71° 15'. In 1819 the Russian Bellinghausen lay on the 69th
parallel, and in 1821 on the 66th at longitude 111° west. In
1820 the Englishman Bransfield stopped at 65°. That same year
the American Morrel, whose reports are dubious, went along the 42nd
meridian, finding open sea at latitude 70° 14'. In 1825 the
Englishman Powell was unable to get beyond 62°. That same year
a humble seal fisherman, the Englishman Weddell, went as far as
latitude 72° 14' on the 35th meridian, and as far as 74°
15' on the 36th. In 1829 the Englishman Forster, commander of the
<i>Chanticleer</i>, laid claim to the Antarctic continent in
latitude 63° 26' and longitude 66° 26'. On February 1,
1831, the Englishman Biscoe discovered Enderby Land at latitude
68° 50', Adelaide Land at latitude 67° on February 5, 1832,
and Graham Land at latitude 64° 45' on February 21. In 1838 the
Frenchman Dumont d'Urville stopped at the Ice Bank in latitude
62° 57', sighting the Louis–Philippe Peninsula; on
January 21 two years later, at a new southerly position of 66°
30', he named the Adélie Coast and eight days later, the
Clarie Coast at 64° 40'. In 1838 the American Wilkes advanced
as far as the 69th parallel on the 100th meridian. In 1839 the
Englishman Balleny discovered the Sabrina Coast at the edge of the
polar circle. Lastly, on January 12, 1842, with his ships, the
<i>Erebus</i> and the <i>Terror</i>, the Englishman Sir James Clark
Ross found Victoria Land in latitude 70° 56' and longitude
171° 7' east; on the 23rd of that same month, he reached the
74th parallel, a position denoting the Farthest South attained
until then; on the 27th he lay at 76° 8'; on the 28th at
77° 32'; on February 2 at 78° 4'; and late in 1842 he
returned to 71° but couldn't get beyond it. Well now! In 1868,
on this 21st day of March, I myself, Captain Nemo, have reached the
South Pole at 90°, and I hereby claim this entire part of the
globe, equal to one–sixth of the known continents."</p>
      <p>"In the name of which sovereign, Captain?"</p>
      <p>"In my own name, sir!"</p>
      <p>So saying, Captain Nemo unfurled a black flag bearing a gold "N"
on its quartered bunting. Then, turning toward the orb of day,
whose last rays were licking at the sea's horizon:</p>
      <p>"Farewell, O sun!" he called. "Disappear, O radiant orb! Retire
beneath this open sea, and let six months of night spread their
shadows over my new domains!"</p>
   </body>
</topic>