<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<topic id="d2e1399">
   <title>
      <d4pSimpleEnumerator><!--1.5-->Chapter 5. </d4pSimpleEnumerator>
      <ph>At Random!</ph>
   </title>
   <body>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="size_plus_2">FOR SOME WHILE</ph> the voyage of the
<i>Abraham Lincoln</i> was marked by no incident. But one
circumstance arose that displayed Ned Land's marvelous skills and
showed just how much confidence we could place in him.</p>
      <p>Off the Falkland Islands on June 30, the frigate came in contact
with a fleet of American whalers, and we learned that they hadn't
seen the narwhale. But one of them, the captain of the
<i>Monroe</i>, knew that Ned Land had shipped aboard the <i>Abraham
Lincoln</i> and asked his help in hunting a baleen whale that was
in sight. Anxious to see Ned Land at work, Commander Farragut
authorized him to make his way aboard the <i>Monroe</i>. And the
Canadian had such good luck that with a right–and–left
shot, he harpooned not one whale but two, striking the first
straight to the heart and catching the other after a few minutes'
chase!</p>
      <p>Assuredly, if the monster ever had to deal with Ned Land's
harpoon, I wouldn't bet on the monster.</p>
      <p>The frigate sailed along the east coast of South America with
prodigious speed. By July 3 we were at the entrance to the Strait
of Magellan, abreast of Cabo de las Virgenes. But Commander
Farragut was unwilling to attempt this tortuous passageway and
maneuvered instead to double Cape Horn.</p>
      <p>The crew sided with him unanimously. Indeed, were we likely to
encounter the narwhale in such a cramped strait? Many of our
sailors swore that the monster couldn't negotiate this passageway
simply because "he's too big for it!"</p>
      <p>Near three o'clock in the afternoon on July 6, fifteen miles
south of shore, the <i>Abraham Lincoln</i> doubled that solitary
islet at the tip of the South American continent, that stray rock
Dutch seamen had named Cape Horn after their hometown of Hoorn. Our
course was set for the northwest, and the next day our frigate's
propeller finally churned the waters of the Pacific.</p>
      <p>"Open your eyes! Open your eyes!" repeated the sailors of the
<i>Abraham Lincoln</i>. And they opened amazingly wide. Eyes and
spyglasses (a bit dazzled, it is true, by the vista of $2,000.00)
didn't remain at rest for an instant. Day and night we observed the
surface of the ocean, and those with nyctalopic eyes, whose ability
to see in the dark increased their chances by fifty percent, had an
excellent shot at winning the prize.</p>
      <p>As for me, I was hardly drawn by the lure of money and yet was
far from the least attentive on board. Snatching only a few minutes
for meals and a few hours for sleep, come rain or come shine, I no
longer left the ship's deck. Sometimes bending over the forecastle
railings, sometimes leaning against the sternrail, I eagerly
scoured that cotton–colored wake that whitened the ocean as
far as the eye could see! And how many times I shared the
excitement of general staff and crew when some unpredictable whale
lifted its blackish back above the waves. In an instant the
frigate's deck would become densely populated. The cowls over the
companionways would vomit a torrent of sailors and officers. With
panting chests and anxious eyes, we each would observe the
<i>cetacean's</i> movements. I stared; I stared until I nearly went
blind from a worn–out retina, while Conseil, as stoic as
ever, kept repeating to me in a calm tone:</p>
      <p>"If master's eyes would kindly stop bulging, master will see
farther!"</p>
      <p>But what a waste of energy! The <i>Abraham Lincoln</i> would
change course and race after the animal sighted, only to find an
ordinary baleen whale or a common sperm whale that soon disappeared
amid a chorus of curses!</p>
      <p>However, the weather held good. Our voyage was proceeding under
the most favorable conditions. By then it was the bad season in
these southernmost regions, because July in this zone corresponds
to our January in Europe; but the sea remained smooth and easily
visible over a vast perimeter.</p>
      <p>Ned Land still kept up the most tenacious skepticism; beyond his
spells on watch, he pretended that he never even looked at the
surface of the waves, at least while no whales were in sight. And
yet the marvelous power of his vision could have performed yeoman
service. But this stubborn Canadian spent eight hours out of every
twelve reading or sleeping in his cabin. A hundred times I chided
him for his unconcern.</p>
      <p>"Bah!" he replied. "Nothing's out there, Professor Aronnax, and
if there is some animal, what chance would we have of spotting it?
Can't you see we're just wandering around at random? People say
they've sighted this slippery beast again in the Pacific high
seas—I'm truly willing to believe it, but two months have
already gone by since then, and judging by your narwhale's
personality, it hates growing moldy from hanging out too long in
the same waterways! It's blessed with a terrific gift for getting
around. Now, professor, you know even better than I that nature
doesn't violate good sense, and she wouldn't give some naturally
slow animal the ability to move swiftly if it hadn't a need to use
that talent. So if the beast does exist, it's already long
gone!"</p>
      <p>I had no reply to this. Obviously we were just groping blindly.
But how else could we go about it? All the same, our chances were
automatically pretty limited. Yet everyone still felt confident of
success, and not a sailor on board would have bet against the
narwhale appearing, and soon.</p>
      <p>On July 20 we cut the Tropic of Capricorn at longitude 105°,
and by the 27th of the same month, we had cleared the equator on
the 110<sup>th</sup> meridian. These bearings determined, the
frigate took a more decisive westward heading and tackled the seas
of the central Pacific. Commander Farragut felt, and with good
reason, that it was best to stay in deep waters and keep his
distance from continents or islands, whose neighborhoods the animal
always seemed to avoid—"No doubt," our bosun said, "because
there isn't enough water for him!" So the frigate kept well out
when passing the Tuamotu, Marquesas, and Hawaiian Islands, then cut
the Tropic of Cancer at longitude 132° and headed for the seas
of China.</p>
      <p>We were finally in the area of the monster's latest antics! And
in all honesty, shipboard conditions became life–threatening.
Hearts were pounding hideously, gearing up for futures full of
incurable aneurysms. The entire crew suffered from a nervous
excitement that it's beyond me to describe. Nobody ate, nobody
slept. Twenty times a day some error in perception, or the optical
illusions of some sailor perched in the crosstrees, would cause
intolerable anguish, and this emotion, repeated twenty times over,
kept us in a state of irritability so intense that a reaction was
bound to follow.</p>
      <p>And this reaction wasn't long in coming. For three months,
during which each day seemed like a century, the <i>Abraham
Lincoln</i> plowed all the northerly seas of the Pacific, racing
after whales sighted, abruptly veering off course, swerving sharply
from one tack to another, stopping suddenly, putting on steam and
reversing engines in quick succession, at the risk of stripping its
gears, and it didn't leave a single point unexplored from the
beaches of Japan to the coasts of America. And we found nothing!
Nothing except an immenseness of deserted waves! Nothing remotely
resembling a gigantic narwhale, or an underwater islet, or a
derelict shipwreck, or a runaway reef, or anything the least bit
unearthly!</p>
      <p>So the reaction set in. At first, discouragement took hold of
people's minds, opening the door to disbelief. A new feeling
appeared on board, made up of three–tenths shame and
seven–tenths fury. The crew called themselves
"out–and–out fools" for being hoodwinked by a fairy
tale, then grew steadily more furious! The mountains of arguments
amassed over a year collapsed all at once, and each man now wanted
only to catch up on his eating and sleeping, to make up for the
time he had so stupidly sacrificed.</p>
      <p>With typical human fickleness, they jumped from one extreme to
the other. Inevitably, the most enthusiastic supporters of the
undertaking became its most energetic opponents. This reaction
mounted upward from the bowels of the ship, from the quarters of
the bunker hands to the messroom of the general staff; and for
certain, if it hadn't been for Commander Farragut's characteristic
stubbornness, the frigate would ultimately have put back to that
cape in the south.</p>
      <p>But this futile search couldn't drag on much longer. The
<i>Abraham Lincoln</i> had done everything it could to succeed and
had no reason to blame itself. Never had the crew of an American
naval craft shown more patience and zeal; they weren't responsible
for this failure; there was nothing to do but go home.</p>
      <p>A request to this effect was presented to the commander. The
commander stood his ground. His sailors couldn't hide their
discontent, and their work suffered because of it. I'm unwilling to
say that there was mutiny on board, but after a reasonable period
of intransigence, Commander Farragut, like Christopher Columbus
before him, asked for a grace period of just three days more. After
this three–day delay, if the monster hadn't appeared, our
helmsman would give three turns of the wheel, and the <i>Abraham
Lincoln</i> would chart a course toward European seas.</p>
      <p>This promise was given on November 2. It had the immediate
effect of reviving the crew's failing spirits. The ocean was
observed with renewed care. Each man wanted one last look with
which to sum up his experience. Spyglasses functioned with feverish
energy. A supreme challenge had been issued to the giant narwhale,
and the latter had no acceptable excuse for ignoring this Summons
to Appear!</p>
      <p>Two days passed. The <i>Abraham Lincoln</i> stayed at half
steam. On the offchance that the animal might be found in these
waterways, a thousand methods were used to spark its interest or
rouse it from its apathy. Enormous sides of bacon were trailed in
our wake, to the great satisfaction, I must say, of assorted
sharks. While the <i>Abraham Lincoln</i> heaved to, its longboats
radiated in every direction around it and didn't leave a single
point of the sea unexplored. But the evening of November 4 arrived
with this underwater mystery still unsolved.</p>
      <p>At noon the next day, November 5, the agreed–upon delay
expired. After a position fix, true to his promise, Commander
Farragut would have to set his course for the southeast and leave
the northerly regions of the Pacific decisively behind.</p>
      <p>By then the frigate lay in latitude 31° 15' north and
longitude 136° 42' east. The shores of Japan were less than 200
miles to our leeward. Night was coming on. Eight o'clock had just
struck. Huge clouds covered the moon's disk, then in its first
quarter. The sea undulated placidly beneath the frigate's
stempost.</p>
      <p>Just then I was in the bow, leaning over the starboard rail.
Conseil, stationed beside me, stared straight ahead. Roosting in
the shrouds, the crew examined the horizon, which shrank and
darkened little by little. Officers were probing the increasing
gloom with their night glasses. Sometimes the murky ocean sparkled
beneath moonbeams that darted between the fringes of two clouds.
Then all traces of light vanished into the darkness.</p>
      <p>Observing Conseil, I discovered that, just barely, the gallant
lad had fallen under the general influence. At least so I thought.
Perhaps his nerves were twitching with curiosity for the first time
in history.</p>
      <p>"Come on, Conseil!" I told him. "Here's your last chance to
pocket that $2,000.00!"</p>
      <p>"If master will permit my saying so," Conseil replied, "I never
expected to win that prize, and the Union government could have
promised $100,000.00 and been none the poorer."</p>
      <p>"You're right, Conseil, it turned out to be a foolish business
after all, and we jumped into it too hastily. What a waste of time,
what a futile expense of emotion! Six months ago we could have been
back in France—"</p>
      <p>"In master's little apartment," Conseil answered. "In master's
museum! And by now I would have classified master's fossils. And
master's <i>babirusa</i> would be ensconced in its cage at the zoo
in the Botanical Gardens, and it would have attracted every
curiosity seeker in town!"</p>
      <p>"Quite so, Conseil, and what's more, I imagine that people will
soon be poking fun at us!"</p>
      <p>"To be sure," Conseil replied serenely, "I do think they'll have
fun at master's expense. And must it be said . . . ?"</p>
      <p>"It must be said, Conseil."</p>
      <p>"Well then, it will serve master right!"</p>
      <p>"How true!"</p>
      <p>"When one has the honor of being an expert as master is, one
mustn't lay himself open to—"</p>
      <p>Conseil didn't have time to complete the compliment. In the
midst of the general silence, a voice became audible. It was Ned
Land's voice, and it shouted:</p>
      <p>"Ahoy! There's the thing in question, abreast of us to
leeward!"</p>
   </body>
</topic>