<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<topic id="d2e13260">
   <title>
      <d4pSimpleEnumerator><!--2.16-->Chapter 16. </d4pSimpleEnumerator>
      <ph>Shortage of Air</ph>
   </title>
   <body>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="size_plus_2">CONSEQUENTLY</ph>, above, below, and around
the <i>Nautilus</i>, there were impenetrable frozen walls. We were
the Ice Bank's prisoners! The Canadian banged a table with his
fearsome fist. Conseil kept still. I stared at the captain. His
face had resumed its usual emotionlessness. He crossed his arms. He
pondered. The <i>Nautilus</i> did not stir.</p>
      <p>The captain then broke into speech:</p>
      <p>"Gentlemen," he said in a calm voice, "there are two ways of
dying under the conditions in which we're placed."</p>
      <p>This inexplicable individual acted like a mathematics professor
working out a problem for his pupils.</p>
      <p>"The first way," he went on, "is death by crushing. The second
is death by asphyxiation. I don't mention the possibility of death
by starvation because the <i>Nautilus's</i> provisions will
certainly last longer than we will. Therefore, let's concentrate on
our chances of being crushed or asphyxiated."</p>
      <p>"As for asphyxiation, Captain," I replied, "that isn't a cause
for alarm, because the air tanks are full."</p>
      <p>"True," Captain Nemo went on, "but they'll supply air for only
two days. Now then, we've been buried beneath the waters for
thirty–six hours, and the <i>Nautilus's</i> heavy atmosphere
already needs renewing. In another forty–eight hours, our
reserve air will be used up."</p>
      <p>"Well then, Captain, let's free ourselves within
forty–eight hours!"</p>
      <p>"We'll try to at least, by cutting through one of these walls
surrounding us."</p>
      <p>"Which one?" I asked.</p>
      <p>"Borings will tell us that. I'm going to ground the
<i>Nautilus</i> on the lower shelf, then my men will put on their
diving suits and attack the thinnest of these ice walls."</p>
      <p>"Can the panels in the lounge be left open?"</p>
      <p>"Without ill effect. We're no longer in motion."</p>
      <p>Captain Nemo went out. Hissing sounds soon told me that water
was being admitted into the ballast tanks. The <i>Nautilus</i>
slowly settled and rested on the icy bottom at a depth of 350
meters, the depth at which the lower shelf of ice lay
submerged.</p>
      <p>"My friends," I said, "we're in a serious predicament, but I'm
counting on your courage and energy."</p>
      <p>"Sir," the Canadian replied, "this is no time to bore you with
my complaints. I'm ready to do anything I can for the common
good."</p>
      <p>"Excellent, Ned," I said, extending my hand to the Canadian.</p>
      <p>"I might add," he went on, "that I'm as handy with a pick as a
harpoon. If I can be helpful to the captain, he can use me any way
he wants."</p>
      <p>"He won't turn down your assistance. Come along, Ned."</p>
      <p>I led the Canadian to the room where the <i>Nautilus's</i> men
were putting on their diving suits. I informed the captain of Ned's
proposition, which was promptly accepted. The Canadian got into his
underwater costume and was ready as soon as his fellow workers.
Each of them carried on his back a Rouquayrol device that the air
tanks had supplied with a generous allowance of fresh oxygen. A
considerable but necessary drain on the <i>Nautilus's</i> reserves.
As for the Ruhmkorff lamps, they were unnecessary in the midst of
these brilliant waters saturated with our electric rays.</p>
      <p>After Ned was dressed, I reentered the lounge, whose windows had
been uncovered; stationed next to Conseil, I examined the strata
surrounding and supporting the <i>Nautilus</i>.</p>
      <p>Some moments later, we saw a dozen crewmen set foot on the shelf
of ice, among them Ned Land, easily recognized by his tall figure.
Captain Nemo was with them.</p>
      <p>Before digging into the ice, the captain had to obtain borings,
to insure working in the best direction. Long bores were driven
into the side walls; but after fifteen meters, the instruments were
still impeded by the thickness of those walls. It was futile to
attack the ceiling since that surface was the Ice Bank itself, more
than 400 meters high. Captain Nemo then bored into the lower
surface. There we were separated from the sea by a ten–meter
barrier. That's how thick the iceberg was. From this point on, it
was an issue of cutting out a piece equal in surface area to the
<i>Nautilus's</i> waterline. This meant detaching about 6,500 cubic
meters, to dig a hole through which the ship could descend below
this tract of ice.</p>
      <p>Work began immediately and was carried on with tireless
tenacity. Instead of digging all around the <i>Nautilus</i>, which
would have entailed even greater difficulties, Captain Nemo had an
immense trench outlined on the ice, eight meters from our port
quarter. Then his men simultaneously staked it off at several
points around its circumference. Soon their picks were vigorously
attacking this compact matter, and huge chunks were loosened from
its mass. These chunks weighed less than the water, and by an
unusual effect of specific gravity, each chunk took wing, as it
were, to the roof of the tunnel, which thickened above by as much
as it diminished below. But this hardly mattered so long as the
lower surface kept growing thinner.</p>
      <p>After two hours of energetic work, Ned Land reentered,
exhausted. He and his companions were replaced by new workmen,
including Conseil and me. The <i>Nautilus's</i> chief officer
supervised us.</p>
      <p>The water struck me as unusually cold, but I warmed up promptly
while wielding my pick. My movements were quite free, although they
were executed under a pressure of thirty atmospheres.</p>
      <p>After two hours of work, reentering to snatch some food and
rest, I found a noticeable difference between the clean elastic
fluid supplied me by the Rouquayrol device and the
<i>Nautilus's</i> atmosphere, which was already charged with carbon
dioxide. The air hadn't been renewed in forty–eight hours,
and its life–giving qualities were considerably weakened.
Meanwhile, after twelve hours had gone by, we had removed from the
outlined surface area a slice of ice only one meter thick, hence
about 600 cubic meters. Assuming the same work would be
accomplished every twelve hours, it would still take five nights
and four days to see the undertaking through to completion.</p>
      <p>"Five nights and four days!" I told my companions. "And we have
oxygen in the air tanks for only two days."</p>
      <p>"Without taking into account," Ned answered, "that once we're
out of this damned prison, we'll still be cooped up beneath the Ice
Bank, without any possible contact with the open air!"</p>
      <p>An apt remark. For who could predict the minimum time we would
need to free ourselves? Before the <i>Nautilus</i> could return to
the surface of the waves, couldn't we all die of asphyxiation? Were
this ship and everyone on board doomed to perish in this tomb of
ice? It was a dreadful state of affairs. But we faced it
head–on, each one of us determined to do his duty to the
end.</p>
      <p>During the night, in line with my forecasts, a new
one–meter slice was removed from this immense socket. But in
the morning, wearing my diving suit, I was crossing through the
liquid mass in a temperature of –6° to –7°
centigrade, when I noted that little by little the side walls were
closing in on each other. The liquid strata farthest from the
trench, not warmed by the movements of workmen and tools, were
showing a tendency to solidify. In the face of this imminent new
danger, what would happen to our chances for salvation, and how
could we prevent this liquid medium from solidifying, then cracking
the <i>Nautilus's</i> hull like glass?</p>
      <p>I didn't tell my two companions about this new danger. There was
no point in dampening the energy they were putting into our arduous
rescue work. But when I returned on board, I mentioned this serious
complication to Captain Nemo.</p>
      <p>"I know," he told me in that calm tone the most dreadful outlook
couldn't change. "It's one more danger, but I don't know any way of
warding it off. Our sole chance for salvation is to work faster
than the water solidifies. We've got to get there first, that's
all."</p>
      <p>Get there first! By then I should have been used to this type of
talk!</p>
      <p>For several hours that day, I wielded my pick doggedly. The work
kept me going. Besides, working meant leaving the <i>Nautilus</i>,
which meant breathing the clean oxygen drawn from the air tanks and
supplied by our equipment, which meant leaving the thin, foul air
behind.</p>
      <p>Near evening one more meter had been dug from the trench. When I
returned on board, I was wellnigh asphyxiated by the carbon dioxide
saturating the air. Oh, if only we had the chemical methods that
would enable us to drive out this noxious gas! There was no lack of
oxygen. All this water contained a considerable amount, and after
it was decomposed by our powerful batteries, this life–giving
elastic fluid could have been restored to us. I had thought it all
out, but to no avail because the carbon dioxide produced by our
breathing permeated every part of the ship. To absorb it, we would
need to fill containers with potassium hydroxide and shake them
continually. But this substance was missing on board and nothing
else could replace it.</p>
      <p>That evening Captain Nemo was forced to open the spigots of his
air tanks and shoot a few spouts of fresh oxygen through the
<i>Nautilus's</i> interior. Without this precaution we wouldn't
have awakened the following morning.</p>
      <p>The next day, March 26, I returned to my miner's trade, working
to remove the fifth meter. The Ice Bank's side walls and underbelly
had visibly thickened. Obviously they would come together before
the <i>Nautilus</i> could break free. For an instant I was gripped
by despair. My pick nearly slipped from my hands. What was the
point of this digging if I was to die smothered and crushed by this
water turning to stone, a torture undreamed of by even the wildest
savages! I felt like I was lying in the jaws of a fearsome monster,
jaws irresistibly closing.</p>
      <p>Supervising our work, working himself, Captain Nemo passed near
me just then. I touched him with my hand and pointed to the walls
of our prison. The starboard wall had moved forward to a point less
than four meters from the <i>Nautilus's</i> hull.</p>
      <p>The captain understood and gave me a signal to follow him. We
returned on board. My diving suit removed, I went with him to the
lounge.</p>
      <p>"Professor Aronnax," he told me, "this calls for heroic
measures, or we'll be sealed up in this solidified water as if it
were cement."</p>
      <p>"Yes!" I said. "But what can we do?"</p>
      <p>"Oh," he exclaimed, "if only my <i>Nautilus</i> were strong
enough to stand that much pressure without being crushed!"</p>
      <p>"Well?" I asked, not catching the captain's meaning.</p>
      <p>"Don't you understand," he went on, "that the congealing of this
water could come to our rescue? Don't you see that by solidifying,
it could burst these tracts of ice imprisoning us, just as its
freezing can burst the hardest stones? Aren't you aware that this
force could be the instrument of our salvation rather than our
destruction?"</p>
      <p>"Yes, Captain, maybe so. But whatever resistance to crushing the
<i>Nautilus</i> may have, it still couldn't stand such dreadful
pressures, and it would be squashed as flat as a piece of sheet
iron."</p>
      <p>"I know it, sir. So we can't rely on nature to rescue us, only
our own efforts. We must counteract this solidification. We must
hold it in check. Not only are the side walls closing in, but there
aren't ten feet of water ahead or astern of the <i>Nautilus</i>.
All around us, this freeze is gaining fast."</p>
      <p>"How long," I asked, "will the oxygen in the air tanks enable us
to breathe on board?"</p>
      <p>The captain looked me straight in the eye.</p>
      <p>"After tomorrow," he said, "the air tanks will be empty!"</p>
      <p>I broke out in a cold sweat. But why should I have been startled
by this reply? On March 22 the <i>Nautilus</i> had dived under the
open waters at the pole. It was now the 26th. We had lived off the
ship's stores for five days! And all remaining breathable air had
to be saved for the workmen. Even today as I write these lines, my
sensations are so intense that an involuntary terror sweeps over
me, and my lungs still seem short of air!</p>
      <p>Meanwhile, motionless and silent, Captain Nemo stood lost in
thought. An idea visibly crossed his mind. But he seemed to brush
it aside. He told himself no. At last these words escaped his
lips:</p>
      <p>"Boiling water!" he muttered.</p>
      <p>"Boiling water?" I exclaimed.</p>
      <p>"Yes, sir. We're shut up in a relatively confined area. If the
<i>Nautilus's</i> pumps continually injected streams of boiling
water into this space, wouldn't that raise its temperature and
delay its freezing?"</p>
      <p>"It's worth trying!" I said resolutely.</p>
      <p>"So let's try it, Professor."</p>
      <p>By then the thermometer gave –7° centigrade outside.
Captain Nemo led me to the galley where a huge distilling mechanism
was at work, supplying drinking water via evaporation. The
mechanism was loaded with water, and the full electric heat of our
batteries was thrown into coils awash in liquid. In a few minutes
the water reached 100° centigrade. It was sent to the pumps
while new water replaced it in the process. The heat generated by
our batteries was so intense that after simply going through the
mechanism, water drawn cold from the sea arrived boiling hot at the
body of the pump.</p>
      <p>The steaming water was injected into the icy water outside, and
after three hours had passed, the thermometer gave the exterior
temperature as –6° centigrade. That was one degree
gained. Two hours later the thermometer gave only
–4°.</p>
      <p>After I monitored the operation's progress,
double–checking it with many inspections, I told the captain,
"It's working."</p>
      <p>"I think so," he answered me. "We've escaped being crushed. Now
we have only asphyxiation to fear."</p>
      <p>During the night the water temperature rose to –1°
centigrade. The injections couldn't get it to go a single degree
higher. But since salt water freezes only at –2°, I was
finally assured that there was no danger of it solidifying.</p>
      <p>By the next day, March 27, six meters of ice had been torn from
the socket. Only four meters were left to be removed. That still
meant forty–eight hours of work. The air couldn't be renewed
in the <i>Nautilus's</i> interior. Accordingly, that day it kept
getting worse.</p>
      <p>An unbearable heaviness weighed me down. Near three o'clock in
the afternoon, this agonizing sensation affected me to an intense
degree. Yawns dislocated my jaws. My lungs were gasping in their
quest for that enkindling elastic fluid required for breathing, now
growing scarcer and scarcer. My mind was in a daze. I lay
outstretched, strength gone, nearly unconscious. My gallant Conseil
felt the same symptoms, suffered the same sufferings, yet never
left my side. He held my hand, he kept encouraging me, and I even
heard him mutter:</p>
      <p>"Oh, if only I didn't have to breathe, to leave more air for
Master!"</p>
      <p>It brought tears to my eyes to hear him say these words.</p>
      <p>Since conditions inside were universally unbearable, how
eagerly, how happily, we put on our diving suits to take our turns
working! Picks rang out on that bed of ice. Arms grew weary, hands
were rubbed raw, but who cared about exhaustion, what difference
were wounds? Life–sustaining air reached our lungs! We could
breathe! We could breathe!</p>
      <p>And yet nobody prolonged his underwater work beyond the time
allotted him. His shift over, each man surrendered to a gasping
companion the air tank that would revive him. Captain Nemo set the
example and was foremost in submitting to this strict discipline.
When his time was up, he yielded his equipment to another and
reentered the foul air on board, always calm, unflinching, and
uncomplaining.</p>
      <p>That day the usual work was accomplished with even greater
energy. Over the whole surface area, only two meters were left to
be removed. Only two meters separated us from the open sea. But the
ship's air tanks were nearly empty. The little air that remained
had to be saved for the workmen. Not an atom for the
<i>Nautilus</i>!</p>
      <p>When I returned on board, I felt half suffocated. What a night!
I'm unable to depict it. Such sufferings are indescribable. The
next day I was short–winded. Headaches and staggering fits of
dizziness made me reel like a drunk. My companions were
experiencing the same symptoms. Some crewmen were at their last
gasp.</p>
      <p>That day, the sixth of our imprisonment, Captain Nemo concluded
that picks and mattocks were too slow to deal with the ice layer
still separating us from open water—and he decided to crush
this layer. The man had kept his energy and composure. He had
subdued physical pain with moral strength. He could still think,
plan, and act.</p>
      <p>At his orders the craft was eased off, in other words, it was
raised from its icy bed by a change in its specific gravity. When
it was afloat, the crew towed it, leading it right above the
immense trench outlined to match the ship's waterline. Next the
ballast tanks filled with water, the boat sank, and was fitted into
its socket.</p>
      <p>Just then the whole crew returned on board, and the double
outside door was closed. By this point the <i>Nautilus</i> was
resting on a bed of ice only one meter thick and drilled by bores
in a thousand places.</p>
      <p>The stopcocks of the ballast tanks were then opened wide, and
100 cubic meters of water rushed in, increasing the
<i>Nautilus's</i> weight by 100,000 kilograms.</p>
      <p>We waited, we listened, we forgot our sufferings, we hoped once
more. We had staked our salvation on this one last gamble.</p>
      <p>Despite the buzzing in my head, I soon could hear vibrations
under the <i>Nautilus's</i> hull. We tilted. The ice cracked with
an odd ripping sound, like paper tearing, and the <i>Nautilus</i>
began settling downward.</p>
      <p>"We're going through!" Conseil muttered in my ear.</p>
      <p>I couldn't answer him. I clutched his hand. I squeezed it in an
involuntary convulsion.</p>
      <p>All at once, carried away by its frightful excess load, the
<i>Nautilus</i> sank into the waters like a cannonball, in other
words, dropping as if in a vacuum!</p>
      <p>Our full electric power was then put on the pumps, which
instantly began to expel water from the ballast tanks. After a few
minutes we had checked our fall. The pressure gauge soon indicated
an ascending movement. Brought to full speed, the propeller made
the sheet–iron hull tremble down to its rivets, and we sped
northward.</p>
      <p>But how long would it take to navigate under the Ice Bank to the
open sea? Another day? I would be dead first!</p>
      <p>Half lying on a couch in the library, I was suffocating. My face
was purple, my lips blue, my faculties in abeyance. I could no
longer see or hear. I had lost all sense of time. My muscles had no
power to contract.</p>
      <p>I'm unable to estimate the hours that passed in this way. But I
was aware that my death throes had begun. I realized that I was
about to die . . .</p>
      <p>Suddenly I regained consciousness. A few whiffs of air had
entered my lungs. Had we risen to the surface of the waves? Had we
cleared the Ice Bank?</p>
      <p>No! Ned and Conseil, my two gallant friends, were sacrificing
themselves to save me. A few atoms of air were still left in the
depths of one Rouquayrol device. Instead of breathing it
themselves, they had saved it for me, and while they were
suffocating, they poured life into me drop by drop! I tried to push
the device away. They held my hands, and for a few moments I could
breathe luxuriously.</p>
      <p>My eyes flew toward the clock. It was eleven in the morning. It
had to be March 28. The <i>Nautilus</i> was traveling at the
frightful speed of forty miles per hour. It was writhing in the
waters.</p>
      <p>Where was Captain Nemo? Had he perished? Had his companions died
with him?</p>
      <p>Just then the pressure gauge indicated we were no more than
twenty feet from the surface. Separating us from the open air was a
mere tract of ice. Could we break through it?</p>
      <p>Perhaps! In any event the <i>Nautilus</i> was going to try. In
fact, I could feel it assuming an oblique position, lowering its
stern and raising its spur. The admission of additional water was
enough to shift its balance. Then, driven by its powerful
propeller, it attacked this ice field from below like a fearsome
battering ram. It split the barrier little by little, backing up,
then putting on full speed against the punctured tract of ice; and
finally, carried away by its supreme momentum, it lunged through
and onto this frozen surface, crushing the ice beneath its
weight.</p>
      <p>The hatches were opened—or torn off, if you
prefer—and waves of clean air were admitted into every part
of the <i>Nautilus</i>.</p>
   </body>
</topic>