<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<topic id="d2e12881">
   <title>
      <d4pSimpleEnumerator><!--2.15-->Chapter 15. </d4pSimpleEnumerator>
      <ph>Accident or Incident?</ph>
   </title>
   <body>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="size_plus_2">THE NEXT DAY</ph>, March 22, at six o'clock in
the morning, preparations for departure began. The last gleams of
twilight were melting into night. The cold was brisk. The
constellations were glittering with startling intensity. The
wonderful Southern Cross, polar star of the Antarctic regions,
twinkled at its zenith.</p>
      <p>The thermometer marked –12° centigrade, and a fresh
breeze left a sharp nip in the air. Ice floes were increasing over
the open water. The sea was starting to congeal everywhere.
Numerous blackish patches were spreading over its surface,
announcing the imminent formation of fresh ice. Obviously this
southernmost basin froze over during its six–month winter and
became utterly inaccessible. What happened to the whales during
this period? No doubt they went beneath the Ice Bank to find more
feasible seas. As for seals and walruses, they were accustomed to
living in the harshest climates and stayed on in these icy
waterways. These animals know by instinct how to gouge holes in the
ice fields and keep them continually open; they go to these holes
to breathe. Once the birds have migrated northward to escape the
cold, these marine mammals remain as sole lords of the polar
continent.</p>
      <p>Meanwhile the ballast tanks filled with water and the
<i>Nautilus</i> sank slowly. At a depth of 1,000 feet, it stopped.
Its propeller churned the waves and it headed due north at a speed
of fifteen miles per hour. Near the afternoon it was already
cruising under the immense frozen carapace of the Ice Bank.</p>
      <p>As a precaution, the panels in the lounge stayed closed, because
the <i>Nautilus's</i> hull could run afoul of some submerged block
of ice. So I spent the day putting my notes into final form. My
mind was completely wrapped up in my memories of the pole. We had
reached that inaccessible spot without facing exhaustion or danger,
as if our seagoing passenger carriage had glided there on railroad
tracks. And now we had actually started our return journey. Did it
still have comparable surprises in store for me? I felt sure it
did, so inexhaustible is this series of underwater wonders! As it
was, in the five and a half months since fate had brought us on
board, we had cleared 14,000 leagues, and over this track longer
than the earth's equator, so many fascinating or frightening
incidents had beguiled our voyage: that hunting trip in the Crespo
forests, our running aground in the Torres Strait, the coral
cemetery, the pearl fisheries of Ceylon, the Arabic tunnel, the
fires of Santorini, those millions in the Bay of Vigo, Atlantis,
the South Pole! During the night all these memories crossed over
from one dream to the next, not giving my brain a moment's
rest.</p>
      <p>At three o'clock in the morning, I was awakened by a violent
collision. I sat up in bed, listening in the darkness, and then was
suddenly hurled into the middle of my stateroom. Apparently the
<i>Nautilus</i> had gone aground, then heeled over sharply.</p>
      <p>Leaning against the walls, I dragged myself down the gangways to
the lounge, whose ceiling lights were on. The furniture had been
knocked over. Fortunately the glass cases were solidly secured at
the base and had stood fast. Since we were no longer vertical, the
starboard pictures were glued to the tapestries, while those to
port had their lower edges hanging a foot away from the wall. So
the <i>Nautilus</i> was lying on its starboard side, completely
stationary to boot.</p>
      <p>In its interior I heard the sound of footsteps and muffled
voices. But Captain Nemo didn't appear. Just as I was about to
leave the lounge, Ned Land and Conseil entered.</p>
      <p>"What happened?" I instantly said to them.</p>
      <p>"I came to ask Master that," Conseil replied.</p>
      <p>"Damnation!" the Canadian exclaimed. "I know full well what
happened! The <i>Nautilus</i> has gone aground, and judging from
the way it's listing, I don't think it'll pull through like that
first time in the Torres Strait."</p>
      <p>"But," I asked, "are we at least back on the surface of the
sea?"</p>
      <p>"We have no idea," Conseil replied.</p>
      <p>"It's easy to find out," I answered.</p>
      <p>I consulted the pressure gauge. Much to my surprise, it
indicated a depth of 360 meters.</p>
      <p>"What's the meaning of this?" I exclaimed.</p>
      <p>"We must confer with Captain Nemo," Conseil said.</p>
      <p>"But where do we find him?" Ned Land asked.</p>
      <p>"Follow me," I told my two companions.</p>
      <p>We left the lounge. Nobody in the library. Nobody by the central
companionway or the crew's quarters. I assumed that Captain Nemo
was stationed in the pilothouse. Best to wait. The three of us
returned to the lounge.</p>
      <p>I'll skip over the Canadian's complaints. He had good grounds
for an outburst. I didn't answer him back, letting him blow off all
the steam he wanted.</p>
      <p>We had been left to ourselves for twenty minutes, trying to
detect the tiniest noises inside the <i>Nautilus</i>, when Captain
Nemo entered. He didn't seem to see us. His facial features,
usually so emotionless, revealed a certain uneasiness. He studied
the compass and pressure gauge in silence, then went and put his
finger on the world map at a spot in the sector depicting the
southernmost seas.</p>
      <p>I hesitated to interrupt him. But some moments later, when he
turned to me, I threw back at him a phrase he had used in the
Torres Strait:</p>
      <p>"An incident, Captain?"</p>
      <p>"No, sir," he replied, "this time an accident."</p>
      <p>"Serious?"</p>
      <p>"Perhaps."</p>
      <p>"Is there any immediate danger?"</p>
      <p>"No."</p>
      <p>"The <i>Nautilus</i> has run aground?"</p>
      <p>"Yes."</p>
      <p>"And this accident came about . . . ?"</p>
      <p>"Through nature's unpredictability not man's incapacity. No
errors were committed in our maneuvers. Nevertheless, we can't
prevent a loss of balance from taking its toll. One may defy human
laws, but no one can withstand the laws of nature."</p>
      <p>Captain Nemo had picked an odd time to philosophize. All in all,
this reply told me nothing.</p>
      <p>"May I learn, sir," I asked him, "what caused this
accident?"</p>
      <p>"An enormous block of ice, an entire mountain, has toppled
over," he answered me. "When an iceberg is eroded at the base by
warmer waters or by repeated collisions, its center of gravity
rises. Then it somersaults, it turns completely upside down. That's
what happened here. When it overturned, one of these blocks hit the
<i>Nautilus</i> as it was cruising under the waters. Sliding under
our hull, this block then raised us with irresistible power,
lifting us into less congested strata where we now lie on our
side."</p>
      <p>"But can't we float the <i>Nautilus</i> clear by emptying its
ballast tanks, to regain our balance?"</p>
      <p>"That, sir, is being done right now. You can hear the pumps
working. Look at the needle on the pressure gauge. It indicates
that the <i>Nautilus</i> is rising, but this block of ice is rising
with us, and until some obstacle halts its upward movement, our
position won't change."</p>
      <p>Indeed, the <i>Nautilus</i> kept the same heel to starboard. No
doubt it would straighten up once the block came to a halt. But
before that happened, who knew if we might not hit the underbelly
of the Ice Bank and be hideously squeezed between two frozen
surfaces?</p>
      <p>I mused on all the consequences of this situation. Captain Nemo
didn't stop studying the pressure gauge. Since the toppling of this
iceberg, the <i>Nautilus</i> had risen about 150 feet, but it still
stayed at the same angle to the perpendicular.</p>
      <p>Suddenly a slight movement could be felt over the hull.
Obviously the <i>Nautilus</i> was straightening a bit. Objects
hanging in the lounge were visibly returning to their normal
positions. The walls were approaching the vertical. Nobody said a
word. Hearts pounding, we could see and feel the ship righting
itself. The floor was becoming horizontal beneath our feet. Ten
minutes went by.</p>
      <p>"Finally, we're upright!" I exclaimed.</p>
      <p>"Yes," Captain Nemo said, heading to the lounge door.</p>
      <p>"But will we float off?" I asked him.</p>
      <p>"Certainly," he replied, "since the ballast tanks aren't yet
empty, and when they are, the <i>Nautilus</i> must rise to the
surface of the sea."</p>
      <p>The captain went out, and soon I saw that at his orders, the
<i>Nautilus</i> had halted its upward movement. In fact, it soon
would have hit the underbelly of the Ice Bank, but it had stopped
in time and was floating in midwater.</p>
      <p>"That was a close call!" Conseil then said.</p>
      <p>"Yes. We could have been crushed between these masses of ice, or
at least imprisoned between them. And then, with no way to renew
our air supply. . . . Yes, that was a close call!"</p>
      <p>"If it's over with!" Ned Land muttered.</p>
      <p>I was unwilling to get into a pointless argument with the
Canadian and didn't reply. Moreover, the panels opened just then,
and the outside light burst through the uncovered windows.</p>
      <p>We were fully afloat, as I have said; but on both sides of the
<i>Nautilus</i>, about ten meters away, there rose dazzling walls
of ice. There also were walls above and below. Above, because the
Ice Bank's underbelly spread over us like an immense ceiling.
Below, because the somersaulting block, shifting little by little,
had found points of purchase on both side walls and had gotten
jammed between them. The <i>Nautilus</i> was imprisoned in a
genuine tunnel of ice about twenty meters wide and filled with
quiet water. So the ship could easily exit by going either ahead or
astern, sinking a few hundred meters deeper, and then taking an
open passageway beneath the Ice Bank.</p>
      <p>The ceiling lights were off, yet the lounge was still brightly
lit. This was due to the reflecting power of the walls of ice,
which threw the beams of our beacon right back at us. Words cannot
describe the effects produced by our galvanic rays on these huge,
whimsically sculpted blocks, whose every angle, ridge, and facet
gave off a different glow depending on the nature of the veins
running inside the ice. It was a dazzling mine of gems, in
particular sapphires and emeralds, whose jets of blue and green
crisscrossed. Here and there, opaline hues of infinite subtlety
raced among sparks of light that were like so many fiery diamonds,
their brilliance more than any eye could stand. The power of our
beacon was increased a hundredfold, like a lamp shining through the
biconvex lenses of a world–class lighthouse.</p>
      <p>"How beautiful!" Conseil exclaimed.</p>
      <p>"Yes," I said, "it's a wonderful sight! Isn't it, Ned?"</p>
      <p>"Oh damnation, yes!" Ned Land shot back. "It's superb! I'm
furious that I have to admit it. Nobody has ever seen the like. But
this sight could cost us dearly. And in all honesty, I think we're
looking at things God never intended for human eyes."</p>
      <p>Ned was right. It was too beautiful. All at once a yell from
Conseil made me turn around.</p>
      <p>"What is it?" I asked.</p>
      <p>"Master must close his eyes! Master mustn't look!"</p>
      <p>With that, Conseil clapped his hands over his eyes.</p>
      <p>"But what's wrong, my boy?"</p>
      <p>"I've been dazzled, struck blind!"</p>
      <p>Involuntarily my eyes flew to the window, but I couldn't stand
the fire devouring it.</p>
      <p>I realized what had happened. The <i>Nautilus</i> had just
started off at great speed. All the tranquil glimmers of the ice
walls had then changed into blazing streaks. The sparkles from
these myriads of diamonds were merging with each other. Swept along
by its propeller, the <i>Nautilus</i> was traveling through a
sheath of flashing light.</p>
      <p>Then the panels in the lounge closed. We kept our hands over our
eyes, which were utterly saturated with those concentric gleams
that swirl before the retina when sunlight strikes it too
intensely. It took some time to calm our troubled vision.</p>
      <p>Finally we lowered our hands.</p>
      <p>"Ye gods, I never would have believed it," Conseil said.</p>
      <p>"And I still don't believe it!" the Canadian shot back.</p>
      <p>"When we return to shore, jaded from all these natural wonders,"
Conseil added, "think how we'll look down on those pitiful land
masses, those puny works of man! No, the civilized world won't be
good enough for us!"</p>
      <p>Such words from the lips of this emotionless Flemish boy showed
that our enthusiasm was near the boiling point. But the Canadian
didn't fail to throw his dram of cold water over us.</p>
      <p>"The civilized world!" he said, shaking his head. "Don't worry,
Conseil my friend, we're never going back to that world!"</p>
      <p>By this point it was five o'clock in the morning. Just then
there was a collision in the <i>Nautilus's</i> bow. I realized that
its spur had just bumped a block of ice. It must have been a faulty
maneuver because this underwater tunnel was obstructed by such
blocks and didn't make for easy navigating. So I had assumed that
Captain Nemo, in adjusting his course, would go around each
obstacle or would hug the walls and follow the windings of the
tunnel. In either case our forward motion wouldn't receive an
absolute check. Nevertheless, contrary to my expectations, the
<i>Nautilus</i> definitely began to move backward.</p>
      <p>"We're going astern?" Conseil said.</p>
      <p>"Yes," I replied. "Apparently the tunnel has no way out at this
end."</p>
      <p>"And so . . . ?"</p>
      <p>"So," I said, "our maneuvers are quite simple. We'll return in
our tracks and go out the southern opening. That's all."</p>
      <p>As I spoke, I tried to sound more confident than I really felt.
Meanwhile the <i>Nautilus</i> accelerated its backward movement,
and running with propeller in reverse, it swept us along at great
speed.</p>
      <p>"This'll mean a delay," Ned said.</p>
      <p>"What are a few hours more or less, so long as we get out."</p>
      <p>"Yes," Ned Land repeated, "so long as we get out!"</p>
      <p>I strolled for a little while from the lounge into the library.
My companions kept their seats and didn't move. Soon I threw myself
down on a couch and picked up a book, which my eyes skimmed
mechanically.</p>
      <p>A quarter of an hour later, Conseil approached me, saying:</p>
      <p>"Is it deeply fascinating, this volume Master is reading?"</p>
      <p>"Tremendously fascinating," I replied.</p>
      <p>"I believe it. Master is reading his own book!"</p>
      <p>"My own book?"</p>
      <p>Indeed, my hands were holding my own work on the great ocean
depths. I hadn't even suspected. I closed the book and resumed my
strolling. Ned and Conseil stood up to leave.</p>
      <p>"Stay here, my friends," I said, stopping them. "Let's stay
together until we're out of this blind alley."</p>
      <p>"As Master wishes," Conseil replied.</p>
      <p>The hours passed. I often studied the instruments hanging on the
lounge wall. The pressure gauge indicated that the <i>Nautilus</i>
stayed at a constant depth of 300 meters, the compass that it kept
heading south, the log that it was traveling at a speed of twenty
miles per hour, an excessive speed in such a cramped area. But
Captain Nemo knew that by this point there was no such thing as too
fast, since minutes were now worth centuries.</p>
      <p>At 8:25 a second collision took place. This time astern. I grew
pale. My companions came over. I clutched Conseil's hand. Our eyes
questioned each other, and more directly than if our thoughts had
been translated into words.</p>
      <p>Just then the captain entered the lounge. I went to him.</p>
      <p>"Our path is barred to the south?" I asked him.</p>
      <p>"Yes, sir. When it overturned, that iceberg closed off every
exit."</p>
      <p>"We're boxed in?"</p>
      <p>"Yes."</p>
   </body>
</topic>