<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<topic id="d2e15768">
   <title>
      <d4pSimpleEnumerator><!--2.23-->Chapter 23. </d4pSimpleEnumerator>
      <ph>Conclusion</ph>
   </title>
   <body>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="size_plus_2">WE COME TO</ph> the conclusion of this voyage
under the seas. What happened that night, how the skiff escaped
from the Maelstrom's fearsome eddies, how Ned Land, Conseil, and I
got out of that whirlpool, I'm unable to say. But when I regained
consciousness, I was lying in a fisherman's hut on one of the
Lofoten Islands. My two companions, safe and sound, were at my
bedside clasping my hands. We embraced each other heartily.</p>
      <p>Just now we can't even dream of returning to France. Travel
between upper Norway and the south is limited. So I have to wait
for the arrival of a steamboat that provides bimonthly service from
North Cape.</p>
      <p>So it is here, among these gallant people who have taken us in,
that I'm reviewing my narrative of these adventures. It is
accurate. Not a fact has been omitted, not a detail has been
exaggerated. It's the faithful record of this inconceivable
expedition into an element now beyond human reach, but where
progress will someday make great inroads.</p>
      <p>Will anyone believe me? I don't know. Ultimately it's
unimportant. What I can now assert is that I've earned the right to
speak of these seas, beneath which in less than ten months, I've
cleared 20,000 leagues in this underwater tour of the world that
has shown me so many wonders across the Pacific, the Indian Ocean,
the Red Sea, the Mediterranean, the Atlantic, the southernmost and
northernmost seas!</p>
      <p>But what happened to the <i>Nautilus</i>? Did it withstand the
Maelstrom's clutches? Is Captain Nemo alive? Is he still under the
ocean pursuing his frightful program of revenge, or did he stop
after that latest mass execution? Will the waves someday deliver
that manuscript that contains his full life story? Will I finally
learn the man's name? Will the nationality of the stricken warship
tell us the nationality of Captain Nemo?</p>
      <p>I hope so. I likewise hope that his powerful submersible has
defeated the sea inside its most dreadful whirlpool, that the
<i>Nautilus</i> has survived where so many ships have perished! If
this is the case and Captain Nemo still inhabits the
ocean—his adopted country—may the hate be appeased in
that fierce heart! May the contemplation of so many wonders
extinguish the spirit of vengeance in him! May the executioner pass
away, and the scientist continue his peaceful exploration of the
seas! If his destiny is strange, it's also sublime. Haven't I
encompassed it myself? Didn't I lead ten months of this
otherworldly existence? Thus to that question asked 6,000 years ago
in the Book of Ecclesiastes—"Who can fathom the soundless
depths?"—two men out of all humanity have now earned the
right to reply. Captain Nemo and I.</p>
      
   </body>
</topic>