<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<topic id="d2e10304">
   <title>
      <d4pSimpleEnumerator><!--2.8-->Chapter 8. </d4pSimpleEnumerator>
      <ph>The Bay of Vigo</ph>
   </title>
   <body>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="size_plus_2">THE ATLANTIC!</ph> A vast expanse of water
whose surface area is 25,000,000 square miles, with a length of
9,000 miles and an average width of 2,700. A major sea nearly
unknown to the ancients, except perhaps the Carthaginians, those
Dutchmen of antiquity who went along the west coasts of Europe and
Africa on their commercial junkets! An ocean whose parallel winding
shores form an immense perimeter fed by the world's greatest
rivers: the St. Lawrence, Mississippi, Amazon, Plata, Orinoco,
Niger, Senegal, Elbe, Loire, and Rhine, which bring it waters from
the most civilized countries as well as the most undeveloped areas!
A magnificent plain of waves plowed continuously by ships of every
nation, shaded by every flag in the world, and ending in those two
dreadful headlands so feared by navigators, Cape Horn and the Cape
of Tempests!</p>
      <p>The <i>Nautilus</i> broke these waters with the edge of its spur
after doing nearly 10,000 leagues in three and a half months, a
track longer than a great circle of the earth. Where were we
heading now, and what did the future have in store for us?</p>
      <p>Emerging from the Strait of Gibraltar, the <i>Nautilus</i> took
to the high seas. It returned to the surface of the waves, so our
daily strolls on the platform were restored to us.</p>
      <p>I climbed onto it instantly, Ned Land and Conseil along with me.
Twelve miles away, Cape St. Vincent was hazily visible, the
southwestern tip of the Hispanic peninsula. The wind was blowing a
pretty strong gust from the south. The sea was swelling and
surging. Its waves made the <i>Nautilus</i> roll and jerk
violently. It was nearly impossible to stand up on the platform,
which was continuously buffeted by this enormously heavy sea. After
inhaling a few breaths of air, we went below once more.</p>
      <p>I repaired to my stateroom. Conseil returned to his cabin; but
the Canadian, looking rather worried, followed me. Our quick trip
through the Mediterranean hadn't allowed him to put his plans into
execution, and he could barely conceal his disappointment.</p>
      <p>After the door to my stateroom was closed, he sat and stared at
me silently.</p>
      <p>"Ned my friend," I told him, "I know how you feel, but you
mustn't blame yourself. Given the way the <i>Nautilus</i> was
navigating, it would have been sheer insanity to think of
escaping!"</p>
      <p>Ned Land didn't reply. His pursed lips and frowning brow
indicated that he was in the grip of his monomania.</p>
      <p>"Look here," I went on, "as yet there's no cause for despair.
We're going up the coast of Portugal. France and England aren't far
off, and there we'll easily find refuge. Oh, I grant you, if the
<i>Nautilus</i> had emerged from the Strait of Gibraltar and made
for that cape in the south, if it were taking us toward those
regions that have no continents, then I'd share your alarm. But we
now know that Captain Nemo doesn't avoid the seas of civilization,
and in a few days I think we can safely take action."</p>
      <p>Ned Land stared at me still more intently and finally unpursed
his lips:</p>
      <p>"We'll do it this evening," he said.</p>
      <p>I straightened suddenly. I admit that I was less than ready for
this announcement. I wanted to reply to the Canadian, but words
failed me.</p>
      <p>"We agreed to wait for the right circumstances," Ned Land went
on. "Now we've got those circumstances. This evening we'll be just
a few miles off the coast of Spain. It'll be cloudy tonight. The
wind's blowing toward shore. You gave me your promise, Professor
Aronnax, and I'm counting on you."</p>
      <p>Since I didn't say anything, the Canadian stood up and
approached me:</p>
      <p>"We'll do it this evening at nine o'clock," he said. "I've
alerted Conseil. By that time Captain Nemo will be locked in his
room and probably in bed. Neither the mechanics or the crewmen will
be able to see us. Conseil and I will go to the central
companionway. As for you, Professor Aronnax, you'll stay in the
library two steps away and wait for my signal. The oars, mast, and
sail are in the skiff. I've even managed to stow some provisions
inside. I've gotten hold of a monkey wrench to unscrew the nuts
bolting the skiff to the <i>Nautilus's</i> hull. So everything's
ready. I'll see you this evening."</p>
      <p>"The sea is rough," I said.</p>
      <p>"Admitted," the Canadian replied, "but we've got to risk it.
Freedom is worth paying for. Besides, the longboat's solidly built,
and a few miles with the wind behind us is no big deal. By
tomorrow, who knows if this ship won't be 100 leagues out to sea?
If circumstances are in our favor, between ten and eleven this
evening we'll be landing on some piece of solid ground, or we'll be
dead. So we're in God's hands, and I'll see you this evening!"</p>
      <p>This said, the Canadian withdrew, leaving me close to
dumbfounded. I had imagined that if it came to this, I would have
time to think about it, to talk it over. My stubborn companion
hadn't granted me this courtesy. But after all, what would I have
said to him? Ned Land was right a hundred times over. These were
near–ideal circumstances, and he was taking full advantage of
them. In my selfish personal interests, could I go back on my word
and be responsible for ruining the future lives of my companions?
Tomorrow, might not Captain Nemo take us far away from any
shore?</p>
      <p>Just then a fairly loud hissing told me that the ballast tanks
were filling, and the <i>Nautilus</i> sank beneath the waves of the
Atlantic.</p>
      <p>I stayed in my stateroom. I wanted to avoid the captain, to hide
from his eyes the agitation overwhelming me. What an agonizing day
I spent, torn between my desire to regain my free will and my
regret at abandoning this marvelous <i>Nautilus</i>, leaving my
underwater research incomplete! How could I relinquish this
ocean—"my own Atlantic," as I liked to call it—without
observing its lower strata, without wresting from it the kinds of
secrets that had been revealed to me by the seas of the East Indies
and the Pacific! I was putting down my novel half read, I was
waking up as my dream neared its climax! How painfully the hours
passed, as I sometimes envisioned myself safe on shore with my
companions, or, despite my better judgment, as I sometimes wished
that some unforeseen circumstances would prevent Ned Land from
carrying out his plans.</p>
      <p>Twice I went to the lounge. I wanted to consult the compass. I
wanted to see if the <i>Nautilus's</i> heading was actually taking
us closer to the coast or spiriting us farther away. But no. The
<i>Nautilus</i> was still in Portuguese waters. Heading north, it
was cruising along the ocean's beaches.</p>
      <p>So I had to resign myself to my fate and get ready to escape. My
baggage wasn't heavy. My notes, nothing more.</p>
      <p>As for Captain Nemo, I wondered what he would make of our
escaping, what concern or perhaps what distress it might cause him,
and what he would do in the twofold event of our attempt either
failing or being found out! Certainly I had no complaints to
register with him, on the contrary. Never was hospitality more
wholehearted than his. Yet in leaving him I couldn't be accused of
ingratitude. No solemn promises bound us to him. In order to keep
us captive, he had counted only on the force of circumstances and
not on our word of honor. But his avowed intention to imprison us
forever on his ship justified our every effort.</p>
      <p>I hadn't seen the captain since our visit to the island of
Santorini. Would fate bring me into his presence before our
departure? I both desired and dreaded it. I listened for footsteps
in the stateroom adjoining mine. Not a sound reached my ear. His
stateroom had to be deserted.</p>
      <p>Then I began to wonder if this eccentric individual was even on
board. Since that night when the skiff had left the <i>Nautilus</i>
on some mysterious mission, my ideas about him had subtly changed.
In spite of everything, I thought that Captain Nemo must have kept
up some type of relationship with the shore. Did he himself never
leave the <i>Nautilus</i>? Whole weeks had often gone by without my
encountering him. What was he doing all the while? During all those
times I'd thought he was convalescing in the grip of some
misanthropic fit, was he instead far away from the ship, involved
in some secret activity whose nature still eluded me?</p>
      <p>All these ideas and a thousand others assaulted me at the same
time. In these strange circumstances the scope for conjecture was
unlimited. I felt an unbearable queasiness. This day of waiting
seemed endless. The hours struck too slowly to keep up with my
impatience.</p>
      <p>As usual, dinner was served me in my stateroom. Full of anxiety,
I ate little. I left the table at seven o'clock. 120
minutes—I was keeping track of them—still separated me
from the moment I was to rejoin Ned Land. My agitation increased.
My pulse was throbbing violently. I couldn't stand still. I walked
up and down, hoping to calm my troubled mind with movement. The
possibility of perishing in our reckless undertaking was the least
of my worries; my heart was pounding at the thought that our plans
might be discovered before we had left the <i>Nautilus</i>, at the
thought of being hauled in front of Captain Nemo and finding him
angered, or worse, saddened by my deserting him.</p>
      <p>I wanted to see the lounge one last time. I went down the
gangways and arrived at the museum where I had spent so many
pleasant and productive hours. I stared at all its wealth, all its
treasures, like a man on the eve of his eternal exile, a man
departing to return no more. For so many days now, these natural
wonders and artistic masterworks had been central to my life, and I
was about to leave them behind forever. I wanted to plunge my eyes
through the lounge window and into these Atlantic waters; but the
panels were hermetically sealed, and a mantle of sheet iron
separated me from this ocean with which I was still unfamiliar.</p>
      <p>Crossing through the lounge, I arrived at the door, contrived in
one of the canted corners, that opened into the captain's
stateroom. Much to my astonishment, this door was ajar. I
instinctively recoiled. If Captain Nemo was in his stateroom, he
might see me. But, not hearing any sounds, I approached. The
stateroom was deserted. I pushed the door open. I took a few steps
inside. Still the same austere, monastic appearance.</p>
      <p>Just then my eye was caught by some etchings hanging on the
wall, which I hadn't noticed during my first visit. They were
portraits of great men of history who had spent their lives in
perpetual devotion to a great human ideal: Thaddeus Kosciusko, the
hero whose dying words had been <i>Finis Poloniae</i>;<fn callout="*">Latin: "Save Poland's
borders." Ed.</fn> Markos Botzaris, for modern Greece the
reincarnation of Sparta's King Leonidas; Daniel O'Connell,
Ireland's defender; George Washington, founder of the American
Union; Daniele Manin, the Italian patriot; Abraham Lincoln, dead
from the bullet of a believer in slavery; and finally, that martyr
for the redemption of the black race, John Brown, hanging from his
gallows as Victor Hugo's pencil has so terrifyingly depicted.</p>
      <p>What was the bond between these heroic souls and the soul of
Captain Nemo? From this collection of portraits could I finally
unravel the mystery of his existence? Was he a fighter for
oppressed peoples, a liberator of enslaved races? Had he figured in
the recent political or social upheavals of this century? Was he a
hero of that dreadful civil war in America, a war lamentable yet
forever glorious . . . ?</p>
      <p>Suddenly the clock struck eight. The first stroke of its hammer
on the chime snapped me out of my musings. I shuddered as if some
invisible eye had plunged into my innermost thoughts, and I rushed
outside the stateroom.</p>
      <p>There my eyes fell on the compass. Our heading was still
northerly. The log indicated a moderate speed, the pressure gauge a
depth of about sixty feet. So circumstances were in favor of the
Canadian's plans.</p>
      <p>I stayed in my stateroom. I dressed warmly: fishing boots, otter
cap, coat of fan–mussel fabric lined with sealskin. I was
ready. I was waiting. Only the propeller's vibrations disturbed the
deep silence reigning on board. I cocked an ear and listened. Would
a sudden outburst of voices tell me that Ned Land's escape plans
had just been detected? A ghastly uneasiness stole through me. I
tried in vain to recover my composure.</p>
      <p>A few minutes before nine o'clock, I glued my ear to the
captain's door. Not a sound. I left my stateroom and returned to
the lounge, which was deserted and plunged in near darkness.</p>
      <p>I opened the door leading to the library. The same inadequate
light, the same solitude. I went to man my post near the door
opening into the well of the central companionway. I waited for Ned
Land's signal.</p>
      <p>At this point the propeller's vibrations slowed down
appreciably, then they died out altogether. Why was the
<i>Nautilus</i> stopping? Whether this layover would help or hinder
Ned Land's schemes I couldn't have said.</p>
      <p>The silence was further disturbed only by the pounding of my
heart.</p>
      <p>Suddenly I felt a mild jolt. I realized the <i>Nautilus</i> had
come to rest on the ocean floor. My alarm increased. The Canadian's
signal hadn't reached me. I longed to rejoin Ned Land and urge him
to postpone his attempt. I sensed that we were no longer navigating
under normal conditions.</p>
      <p>Just then the door to the main lounge opened and Captain Nemo
appeared. He saw me, and without further preamble:</p>
      <p>"Ah, Professor," he said in an affable tone, "I've been looking
for you. Do you know your Spanish history?"</p>
      <p>Even if he knew it by heart, a man in my disturbed, befuddled
condition couldn't have quoted a syllable of his own country's
history.</p>
      <p>"Well?" Captain Nemo went on. "Did you hear my question? Do you
know the history of Spain?"</p>
      <p>"Very little of it," I replied.</p>
      <p>"The most learned men," the captain said, "still have much to
learn. Have a seat," he added, "and I'll tell you about an unusual
episode in this body of history."</p>
      <p>The captain stretched out on a couch, and I mechanically took a
seat near him, but half in the shadows.</p>
      <p>"Professor," he said, "listen carefully. This piece of history
concerns you in one definite respect, because it will answer a
question you've no doubt been unable to resolve."</p>
      <p>"I'm listening, Captain," I said, not knowing what my partner in
this dialogue was driving at, and wondering if this incident
related to our escape plans.</p>
      <p>"Professor," Captain Nemo went on, "if you're amenable, we'll go
back in time to 1702. You're aware of the fact that in those days
your King Louis XIV thought an imperial gesture would suffice to
humble the Pyrenees in the dust, so he inflicted his grandson, the
Duke of Anjou, on the Spaniards. Reigning more or less poorly under
the name King Philip V, this aristocrat had to deal with mighty
opponents abroad.</p>
      <p>"In essence, the year before, the royal houses of Holland,
Austria, and England had signed a treaty of alliance at The Hague,
aiming to wrest the Spanish crown from King Philip V and to place
it on the head of an archduke whom they prematurely dubbed King
Charles III.</p>
      <p>"Spain had to withstand these allies. But the country had
practically no army or navy. Yet it wasn't short of money, provided
that its galleons, laden with gold and silver from America, could
enter its ports. Now then, late in 1702 Spain was expecting a rich
convoy, which France ventured to escort with a fleet of
twenty–three vessels under the command of Admiral de
Chateau–Renault, because by that time the allied navies were
roving the Atlantic.</p>
      <p>"This convoy was supposed to put into Cadiz, but after learning
that the English fleet lay across those waterways, the admiral
decided to make for a French port.</p>
      <p>"The Spanish commanders in the convoy objected to this decision.
They wanted to be taken to a Spanish port, if not to Cadiz, then to
the Bay of Vigo, located on Spain's northwest coast and not
blockaded.</p>
      <p>"Admiral de Chateau–Renault was so indecisive as to obey
this directive, and the galleons entered the Bay of Vigo.</p>
      <p>"Unfortunately this bay forms an open, offshore mooring that's
impossible to defend. So it was essential to hurry and empty the
galleons before the allied fleets arrived, and there would have
been ample time for this unloading, if a wretched question of trade
agreements hadn't suddenly come up.</p>
      <p>"Are you clear on the chain of events?" Captain Nemo asked
me.</p>
      <p>"Perfectly clear," I said, not yet knowing why I was being given
this history lesson.</p>
      <p>"Then I'll continue. Here's what came to pass. The tradesmen of
Cadiz had negotiated a charter whereby they were to receive all
merchandise coming from the West Indies. Now then, unloading the
ingots from those galleons at the port of Vigo would have been a
violation of their rights. So they lodged a complaint in Madrid,
and they obtained an order from the indecisive King Philip V:
without unloading, the convoy would stay in custody at the offshore
mooring of Vigo until the enemy fleets had retreated.</p>
      <p>"Now then, just as this decision was being handed down, English
vessels arrived in the Bay of Vigo on October 22, 1702. Despite his
inferior forces, Admiral de Chateau–Renault fought
courageously. But when he saw that the convoy's wealth was about to
fall into enemy hands, he burned and scuttled the galleons, which
went to the bottom with their immense treasures."</p>
      <p>Captain Nemo stopped. I admit it: I still couldn't see how this
piece of history concerned me.</p>
      <p>"Well?" I asked him.</p>
      <p>"Well, Professor Aronnax," Captain Nemo answered me, "we're
actually in that Bay of Vigo, and all that's left is for you to
probe the mysteries of the place."</p>
      <p>The captain stood up and invited me to follow him. I'd had time
to collect myself. I did so. The lounge was dark, but the sea's
waves sparkled through the transparent windows. I stared.</p>
      <p>Around the <i>Nautilus</i> for a half–mile radius, the
waters seemed saturated with electric light. The sandy bottom was
clear and bright. Dressed in diving suits, crewmen were busy
clearing away half–rotted barrels and disemboweled trunks in
the midst of the dingy hulks of ships. Out of these trunks and kegs
spilled ingots of gold and silver, cascades of jewels, pieces of
eight. The sand was heaped with them. Then, laden with these
valuable spoils, the men returned to the <i>Nautilus</i>, dropped
off their burdens inside, and went to resume this inexhaustible
fishing for silver and gold.</p>
      <p>I understood. This was the setting of that battle on October 22,
1702. Here, in this very place, those galleons carrying treasure to
the Spanish government had gone to the bottom. Here, whenever he
needed, Captain Nemo came to withdraw these millions to ballast his
<i>Nautilus</i>. It was for him, for him alone, that America had
yielded up its precious metals. He was the direct, sole heir to
these treasures wrested from the Incas and those peoples conquered
by Hernando Cortez!</p>
      <p>"Did you know, professor," he asked me with a smile, "that the
sea contained such wealth?"</p>
      <p>"I know it's estimated," I replied, "that there are 2,000,000
metric tons of silver held in suspension in seawater."</p>
      <p>"Surely, but in extracting that silver, your expenses would
outweigh your profits. Here, by contrast, I have only to pick up
what other men have lost, and not only in this Bay of Vigo but at a
thousand other sites where ships have gone down, whose positions
are marked on my underwater chart. Do you understand now that I'm
rich to the tune of billions?"</p>
      <p>"I understand, Captain. Nevertheless, allow me to inform you
that by harvesting this very Bay of Vigo, you're simply
forestalling the efforts of a rival organization."</p>
      <p>"What organization?"</p>
      <p>"A company chartered by the Spanish government to search for
these sunken galleons. The company's investors were lured by the
bait of enormous gains, because this scuttled treasure is estimated
to be worth ₣500,000,000."</p>
      <p>"It was 500,000,000 francs," Captain Nemo replied, "but no
more!"</p>
      <p>"Right," I said. "Hence a timely warning to those investors
would be an act of charity. Yet who knows if it would be well
received? Usually what gamblers regret the most isn't the loss of
their money so much as the loss of their insane hopes. But
ultimately I feel less sorry for them than for the thousands of
unfortunate people who would have benefited from a fair
distribution of this wealth, whereas now it will be of no help to
them!"</p>
      <p>No sooner had I voiced this regret than I felt it must have
wounded Captain Nemo.</p>
      <p>"No help!" he replied with growing animation. "Sir, what makes
you assume this wealth goes to waste when I'm the one amassing it?
Do you think I toil to gather this treasure out of selfishness? Who
says I don't put it to good use? Do you think I'm unaware of the
suffering beings and oppressed races living on this earth, poor
people to comfort, victims to avenge? Don't you understand . . .
?"</p>
      <p>Captain Nemo stopped on these last words, perhaps sorry that he
had said too much. But I had guessed. Whatever motives had driven
him to seek independence under the seas, he remained a human being
before all else! His heart still throbbed for suffering humanity,
and his immense philanthropy went out both to downtrodden races and
to individuals!</p>
      <p>And now I knew where Captain Nemo had delivered those millions,
when the <i>Nautilus</i> navigated the waters where Crete was in
rebellion against the Ottoman Empire!</p>
   </body>
</topic>