<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<topic id="d2e12030">
   <title>
      <d4pSimpleEnumerator><!--2.13-->Chapter 13. </d4pSimpleEnumerator>
      <ph>The Ice Bank</ph>
   </title>
   <body>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="size_plus_2">THE</ph> 
         <i>Nautilus</i> resumed its unruffled
southbound heading. It went along the 50th meridian with
considerable speed. Would it go to the pole? I didn't think so,
because every previous attempt to reach this spot on the globe had
failed. Besides, the season was already quite advanced, since March
13 on Antarctic shores corresponds with September 13 in the
northernmost regions, which marks the beginning of the equinoctial
period.</p>
      <p>On March 14 at latitude 55°, I spotted floating ice, plain
pale bits of rubble twenty to twenty–five feet long, which
formed reefs over which the sea burst into foam. The
<i>Nautilus</i> stayed on the surface of the ocean. Having fished
in the Arctic seas, Ned Land was already familiar with the sight of
icebergs. Conseil and I were marveling at them for the first
time.</p>
      <p>In the sky toward the southern horizon, there stretched a
dazzling white band. English whalers have given this the name "ice
blink." No matter how heavy the clouds may be, they can't obscure
this phenomenon. It announces the presence of a pack, or shoal, of
ice.</p>
      <p>Indeed, larger blocks of ice soon appeared, their brilliance
varying at the whim of the mists. Some of these masses displayed
green veins, as if scrawled with undulating lines of copper
sulfate. Others looked like enormous amethysts, letting the light
penetrate their insides. The latter reflected the sun's rays from
the thousand facets of their crystals. The former, tinted with a
bright limestone sheen, would have supplied enough building
material to make a whole marble town.</p>
      <p>The farther down south we went, the more these floating islands
grew in numbers and prominence. Polar birds nested on them by the
thousands. These were petrels, cape pigeons, or puffins, and their
calls were deafening. Mistaking the <i>Nautilus</i> for the corpse
of a whale, some of them alighted on it and prodded its resonant
sheet iron with pecks of their beaks.</p>
      <p>During this navigating in the midst of the ice, Captain Nemo
often stayed on the platform. He observed these deserted waterways
carefully. I saw his calm eyes sometimes perk up. In these polar
seas forbidden to man, did he feel right at home, the lord of these
unreachable regions? Perhaps. But he didn't say. He stood still,
reviving only when his pilot's instincts took over. Then, steering
his <i>Nautilus</i> with consummate dexterity, he skillfully dodged
the masses of ice, some of which measured several miles in length,
their heights varying from seventy to eighty meters. Often the
horizon seemed completely closed off. Abreast of latitude 60°,
every passageway had disappeared. Searching with care, Captain Nemo
soon found a narrow opening into which he brazenly slipped, well
aware, however, that it would close behind him.</p>
      <p>Guided by his skillful hands, the <i>Nautilus</i> passed by all
these different masses of ice, which are classified by size and
shape with a precision that enraptured Conseil: "icebergs," or
mountains; "ice fields," or smooth, limitless tracts; "drift ice,"
or floating floes; "packs," or broken tracts, called "patches" when
they're circular and "streams" when they form long strips.</p>
      <p>The temperature was fairly low. Exposed to the outside air, the
thermometer marked –2° to –3° centigrade. But
we were warmly dressed in furs, for which seals and aquatic bears
had paid the price. Evenly heated by all its electric equipment,
the <i>Nautilus's</i> interior defied the most intense cold.
Moreover, to find a bearable temperature, the ship had only to sink
just a few meters beneath the waves.</p>
      <p>Two months earlier we would have enjoyed perpetual daylight in
this latitude; but night already fell for three or four hours, and
later it would cast six months of shadow over these circumpolar
regions.</p>
      <p>On March 15 we passed beyond the latitude of the South Shetland
and South Orkney Islands. The captain told me that many tribes of
seals used to inhabit these shores; but English and American
whalers, in a frenzy of destruction, slaughtered all the adults,
including pregnant females, and where life and activity once
existed, those fishermen left behind only silence and death.</p>
      <p>Going along the 55th meridian, the <i>Nautilus</i> cut the
Antarctic Circle on March 16 near eight o'clock in the morning. Ice
completely surrounded us and closed off the horizon. Nevertheless,
Captain Nemo went from passageway to passageway, always proceeding
south.</p>
      <p>"But where's he going?" I asked.</p>
      <p>"Straight ahead," Conseil replied. "Ultimately, when he can't go
any farther, he'll stop."</p>
      <p>"I wouldn't bet on it!" I replied.</p>
      <p>And in all honesty, I confess that this venturesome excursion
was far from displeasing to me. I can't express the intensity of my
amazement at the beauties of these new regions. The ice struck
superb poses. Here, its general effect suggested an oriental town
with countless minarets and mosques. There, a city in ruins, flung
to the ground by convulsions in the earth. These views were varied
continuously by the sun's oblique rays, or were completely
swallowed up by gray mists in the middle of blizzards. Then
explosions, cave–ins, and great iceberg somersaults would
occur all around us, altering the scenery like the changing
landscape in a diorama.</p>
      <p>If the <i>Nautilus</i> was submerged during these losses of
balance, we heard the resulting noises spread under the waters with
frightful intensity, and the collapse of these masses created
daunting eddies down to the ocean's lower strata. The
<i>Nautilus</i> then rolled and pitched like a ship left to the
fury of the elements.</p>
      <p>Often, no longer seeing any way out, I thought we were
imprisoned for good, but Captain Nemo, guided by his instincts,
discovered new passageways from the tiniest indications. He was
never wrong when he observed slender threads of bluish water
streaking through these ice fields. Accordingly, I was sure that he
had already risked his <i>Nautilus</i> in the midst of the
Antarctic seas.</p>
      <p>However, during the day of March 16, these tracts of ice
completely barred our path. It wasn't the Ice Bank as yet, just
huge ice fields cemented together by the cold. This obstacle
couldn't stop Captain Nemo, and he launched his ship against the
ice fields with hideous violence. The <i>Nautilus</i> went into
these brittle masses like a wedge, splitting them with dreadful
cracklings. It was an old–fashioned battering ram propelled
with infinite power. Hurled aloft, ice rubble fell back around us
like hail. Through brute force alone, the submersible carved out a
channel for itself. Carried away by its momentum, the ship
sometimes mounted on top of these tracts of ice and crushed them
with its weight, or at other times, when cooped up beneath the ice
fields, it split them with simple pitching movements, creating wide
punctures.</p>
      <p>Violent squalls assaulted us during the daytime. Thanks to
certain heavy mists, we couldn't see from one end of the platform
to the other. The wind shifted abruptly to every point on the
compass. The snow was piling up in such packed layers, it had to be
chipped loose with blows from picks. Even in a temperature of
merely –5° centigrade, every outside part of the
<i>Nautilus</i> was covered with ice. A ship's rigging would have
been unusable, because all its tackle would have jammed in the
grooves of the pulleys. Only a craft without sails, driven by an
electric motor that needed no coal, could face such high
latitudes.</p>
      <p>Under these conditions the barometer generally stayed quite low.
It fell as far as 73.5 centimeters. Our compass indications no
longer offered any guarantees. The deranged needles would mark
contradictory directions as we approached the southern magnetic
pole, which doesn't coincide with the South Pole proper. In fact,
according to the astronomer Hansteen, this magnetic pole is located
fairly close to latitude 70° and longitude 130°, or abiding
by the observations of Louis–Isidore Duperrey, in longitude
135° and latitude 70° 30'. Hence we had to transport
compasses to different parts of the ship, take many readings, and
strike an average. Often we could chart our course only by
guesswork, a less than satisfactory method in the midst of these
winding passageways whose landmarks change continuously.</p>
      <p>At last on March 18, after twenty futile assaults, the
<i>Nautilus</i> was decisively held in check. No longer was it an
ice stream, patch, or field—it was an endless, immovable
barrier formed by ice mountains fused to each other.</p>
      <p>"The Ice Bank!" the Canadian told me.</p>
      <p>For Ned Land, as well as for every navigator before us, I knew
that this was the great insurmountable obstacle. When the sun
appeared for an instant near noon, Captain Nemo took a reasonably
accurate sight that gave our position as longitude 51° 30' and
latitude 67° 39' south. This was a position already well along
in these Antarctic regions.</p>
      <p>As for the liquid surface of the sea, there was no longer any
semblance of it before our eyes. Before the <i>Nautilus's</i> spur
there lay vast broken plains, a tangle of confused chunks with all
the helter–skelter unpredictability typical of a river's
surface a short while before its ice breakup; but in this case the
proportions were gigantic. Here and there stood sharp peaks, lean
spires that rose as high as 200 feet; farther off, a succession of
steeply cut cliffs sporting a grayish tint, huge mirrors that
reflected the sparse rays of a sun half drowned in mist. Beyond, a
stark silence reigned in this desolate natural setting, a silence
barely broken by the flapping wings of petrels or puffins. By this
point everything was frozen, even sound.</p>
      <p>So the <i>Nautilus</i> had to halt in its venturesome course
among these tracts of ice.</p>
      <p>"Sir," Ned Land told me that day, "if your captain goes any
farther . . ."</p>
      <p>"Yes?"</p>
      <p>"He'll be a superman."</p>
      <p>"How so, Ned?"</p>
      <p>"Because nobody can clear the Ice Bank. Your captain's a
powerful man, but damnation, he isn't more powerful than nature. If
she draws a boundary line, there you stop, like it or not!"</p>
      <p>"Correct, Ned Land, but I still want to know what's behind this
Ice Bank! Behold my greatest source of irritation—a
wall!"</p>
      <p>"Master is right," Conseil said. "Walls were invented simply to
frustrate scientists. All walls should be banned."</p>
      <p>"Fine!" the Canadian put in. "But we already know what's behind
this Ice Bank."</p>
      <p>"What?" I asked.</p>
      <p>"Ice, ice, and more ice."</p>
      <p>"You may be sure of that, Ned," I answered, "but I'm not. That's
why I want to see for myself."</p>
      <p>"Well, Professor," the Canadian replied, "you can just drop that
idea! You've made it to the Ice Bank, which is already far enough,
but you won't get any farther, neither your Captain Nemo or his
<i>Nautilus</i>. And whether he wants to or not, we'll head north
again, in other words, to the land of sensible people."</p>
      <p>I had to agree that Ned Land was right, and until ships are
built to navigate over tracts of ice, they'll have to stop at the
Ice Bank.</p>
      <p>Indeed, despite its efforts, despite the powerful methods it
used to split this ice, the <i>Nautilus</i> was reduced to
immobility. Ordinarily, when someone can't go any farther, he still
has the option of returning in his tracks. But here it was just as
impossible to turn back as to go forward, because every passageway
had closed behind us, and if our submersible remained even slightly
stationary, it would be frozen in without delay. Which is exactly
what happened near two o'clock in the afternoon, and fresh ice kept
forming over the ship's sides with astonishing speed. I had to
admit that Captain Nemo's leadership had been most injudicious.</p>
      <p>Just then I was on the platform. Observing the situation for
some while, the captain said to me:</p>
      <p>"Well, Professor! What think you?"</p>
      <p>"I think we're trapped, Captain."</p>
      <p>"Trapped! What do you mean?"</p>
      <p>"I mean we can't go forward, backward, or sideways. I think
that's the standard definition of 'trapped,' at least in the
civilized world."</p>
      <p>"So, Professor Aronnax, you think the <i>Nautilus</i> won't be
able to float clear?"</p>
      <p>"Only with the greatest difficulty, Captain, since the season is
already too advanced for you to depend on an ice breakup."</p>
      <p>"Oh, Professor," Captain Nemo replied in an ironic tone, "you
never change! You see only impediments and obstacles! I promise
you, not only will the <i>Nautilus</i> float clear, it will go
farther still!"</p>
      <p>"Farther south?" I asked, gaping at the captain.</p>
      <p>"Yes, sir, it will go to the pole."</p>
      <p>"To the pole!" I exclaimed, unable to keep back a movement of
disbelief.</p>
      <p>"Yes," the captain replied coolly, "the Antarctic pole, that
unknown spot crossed by every meridian on the globe. As you know, I
do whatever I like with my <i>Nautilus</i>."</p>
      <p>Yes, I did know that! I knew this man was daring to the point of
being foolhardy. But to overcome all the obstacles around the South
Pole—even more unattainable than the North Pole, which still
hadn't been reached by the boldest navigators—wasn't this an
absolutely insane undertaking, one that could occur only in the
brain of a madman?</p>
      <p>It then dawned on me to ask Captain Nemo if he had already
discovered this pole, which no human being had ever trod
underfoot.</p>
      <p>"No, sir," he answered me, "but we'll discover it together.
Where others have failed, I'll succeed. Never before has my
<i>Nautilus</i> cruised so far into these southernmost seas, but I
repeat: it will go farther still."</p>
      <p>"I'd like to believe you, Captain," I went on in a tone of some
sarcasm. "Oh I do believe you! Let's forge ahead! There are no
obstacles for us! Let's shatter this Ice Bank! Let's blow it up,
and if it still resists, let's put wings on the <i>Nautilus</i> and
fly over it!"</p>
      <p>"Over it, Professor?" Captain Nemo replied serenely. "No, not
over it, but under it."</p>
      <p>"Under it!" I exclaimed.</p>
      <p>A sudden insight into Captain Nemo's plans had just flashed
through my mind. I understood. The marvelous talents of his
<i>Nautilus</i> would be put to work once again in this superhuman
undertaking!</p>
      <p>"I can see we're starting to understand each other, Professor,"
Captain Nemo told me with a half smile. "You already glimpse the
potential—myself, I'd say the success—of this attempt.
Maneuvers that aren't feasible for an ordinary ship are easy for
the <i>Nautilus</i>. If a continent emerges at the pole, we'll stop
at that continent. But on the other hand, if open sea washes the
pole, we'll go to that very place!"</p>
      <p>"Right," I said, carried away by the captain's logic. "Even
though the surface of the sea has solidified into ice, its lower
strata are still open, thanks to that divine justice that puts the
maximum density of salt water one degree above its freezing point.
And if I'm not mistaken, the submerged part of this Ice Bank is in
a four–to–one ratio to its emerging part."</p>
      <p>"Very nearly, Professor. For each foot of iceberg above the sea,
there are three more below. Now then, since these ice mountains
don't exceed a height of 100 meters, they sink only to a depth of
300 meters. And what are 300 meters to the <i>Nautilus</i>?"</p>
      <p>"A mere nothing, sir."</p>
      <p>"We could even go to greater depths and find that temperature
layer common to all ocean water, and there we'd brave with impunity
the –30° or –40° cold on the surface."</p>
      <p>"True, sir, very true," I replied with growing excitement.</p>
      <p>"Our sole difficulty," Captain Nemo went on, "lies in our
staying submerged for several days without renewing our air
supply."</p>
      <p>"That's all?" I answered. "The <i>Nautilus</i> has huge air
tanks; we'll fill them up and they'll supply all the oxygen we
need."</p>
      <p>"Good thinking, Professor Aronnax," the captain replied with a
smile. "But since I don't want to be accused of foolhardiness, I'm
giving you all my objections in advance."</p>
      <p>"You have more?"</p>
      <p>"Just one. If a sea exists at the South Pole, it's possible this
sea may be completely frozen over, so we couldn't come up to the
surface!"</p>
      <p>"My dear sir, have you forgotten that the <i>Nautilus</i> is
armed with a fearsome spur? Couldn't it be launched diagonally
against those tracts of ice, which would break open from the
impact?"</p>
      <p>"Ah, Professor, you're full of ideas today!"</p>
      <p>"Besides, Captain," I added with still greater enthusiasm, "why
wouldn't we find open sea at the South Pole just as at the North
Pole? The cold–temperature poles and the geographical poles
don't coincide in either the northern or southern hemispheres, and
until proof to the contrary, we can assume these two spots on the
earth feature either a continent or an ice–free ocean."</p>
      <p>"I think as you do, Professor Aronnax," Captain Nemo replied.
"I'll only point out that after raising so many objections against
my plan, you're now crushing me under arguments in its favor."</p>
      <p>Captain Nemo was right. I was outdoing him in daring! It was I
who was sweeping him to the pole. I was leading the way, I was out
in front . . . but no, you silly fool! Captain Nemo already knew
the pros and cons of this question, and it amused him to see you
flying off into impossible fantasies!</p>
      <p>Nevertheless, he didn't waste an instant. At his signal, the
chief officer appeared. The two men held a quick exchange in their
incomprehensible language, and either the chief officer had been
alerted previously or he found the plan feasible, because he showed
no surprise.</p>
      <p>But as unemotional as he was, he couldn't have been more
impeccably emotionless than Conseil when I told the fine lad our
intention of pushing on to the South Pole. He greeted my
announcement with the usual "As Master wishes," and I had to be
content with that. As for Ned Land, no human shoulders ever
executed a higher shrug than the pair belonging to our
Canadian.</p>
      <p>"Honestly, sir," he told me. "You and your Captain Nemo, I pity
you both!"</p>
      <p>"But we will go to the pole, Mr. Land."</p>
      <p>"Maybe, but you won't come back!"</p>
      <p>And Ned Land reentered his cabin, "to keep from doing something
desperate," he said as he left me.</p>
      <p>Meanwhile preparations for this daring attempt were getting
under way. The <i>Nautilus's</i> powerful pumps forced air down
into the tanks and stored it under high pressure. Near four o'clock
Captain Nemo informed me that the platform hatches were about to be
closed. I took a last look at the dense Ice Bank we were going to
conquer. The weather was fair, the skies reasonably clear, the cold
quite brisk, namely –12° centigrade; but after the wind
had lulled, this temperature didn't seem too unbearable.</p>
      <p>Equipped with picks, some ten men climbed onto the
<i>Nautilus's</i> sides and cracked loose the ice around the ship's
lower plating, which was soon set free. This operation was swiftly
executed because the fresh ice was still thin. We all reentered the
interior. The main ballast tanks were filled with the water that
hadn't yet congealed at our line of flotation. The <i>Nautilus</i>
submerged without delay.</p>
      <p>I took a seat in the lounge with Conseil. Through the open
window we stared at the lower strata of this southernmost ocean.
The thermometer rose again. The needle on the pressure gauge
swerved over its dial.</p>
      <p>About 300 meters down, just as Captain Nemo had predicted, we
cruised beneath the undulating surface of the Ice Bank. But the
<i>Nautilus</i> sank deeper still. It reached a depth of 800
meters. At the surface this water gave a temperature of
–12° centigrade, but now it gave no more than
–10°. Two degrees had already been gained. Thanks to its
heating equipment, the <i>Nautilus's</i> temperature, needless to
say, stayed at a much higher degree. Every maneuver was
accomplished with extraordinary precision.</p>
      <p>"With all due respect to Master," Conseil told me, "we'll pass
it by."</p>
      <p>"I fully expect to!" I replied in a tone of deep conviction.</p>
      <p>Now in open water, the <i>Nautilus</i> took a direct course to
the pole without veering from the 52nd meridian. From 67° 30'
to 90°, twenty–two and a half° of latitude were left
to cross, in other words, slightly more than 500 leagues. The
<i>Nautilus</i> adopted an average speed of twenty–six miles
per hour, the speed of an express train. If it kept up this pace,
forty hours would do it for reaching the pole.</p>
      <p>For part of the night, the novelty of our circumstances kept
Conseil and me at the lounge window. The sea was lit by our
beacon's electric rays. But the depths were deserted. Fish didn't
linger in these imprisoned waters. Here they found merely a
passageway for going from the Antarctic Ocean to open sea at the
pole. Our progress was swift. You could feel it in the vibrations
of the long steel hull.</p>
      <p>Near two o'clock in the morning, I went to snatch a few hours of
sleep. Conseil did likewise. I didn't encounter Captain Nemo while
going down the gangways. I assumed that he was keeping to the
pilothouse.</p>
      <p>The next day, March 19, at five o'clock in the morning, I was
back at my post in the lounge. The electric log indicated that the
<i>Nautilus</i> had reduced speed. By then it was rising to the
surface, but cautiously, while slowly emptying its ballast
tanks.</p>
      <p>My heart was pounding. Would we emerge into the open and find
the polar air again?</p>
      <p>No. A jolt told me that the <i>Nautilus</i> had bumped the
underbelly of the Ice Bank, still quite thick to judge from the
hollowness of the accompanying noise. Indeed, we had "struck
bottom," to use nautical terminology, but in the opposite direction
and at a depth of 3,000 feet. That gave us 4,000 feet of ice
overhead, of which 1,000 feet emerged above water. So the Ice Bank
was higher here than we had found it on the outskirts. A
circumstance less than encouraging.</p>
      <p>Several times that day, the <i>Nautilus</i> repeated the same
experiment and always it bumped against this surface that formed a
ceiling above it. At certain moments the ship encountered ice at a
depth of 900 meters, denoting a thickness of 1,200 meters, of which
300 meters rose above the level of the ocean. This height had
tripled since the moment the <i>Nautilus</i> had dived beneath the
waves.</p>
      <p>I meticulously noted these different depths, obtaining the
underwater profile of this upside–down mountain chain that
stretched beneath the sea.</p>
      <p>By evening there was still no improvement in our situation. The
ice stayed between 400 and 500 meters deep. It was obviously
shrinking, but what a barrier still lay between us and the surface
of the ocean!</p>
      <p>By then it was eight o'clock. The air inside the <i>Nautilus</i>
should have been renewed four hours earlier, following daily
practice on board. But I didn't suffer very much, although Captain
Nemo hadn't yet made demands on the supplementary oxygen in his air
tanks.</p>
      <p>That night my sleep was fitful. Hope and fear besieged me by
turns. I got up several times. The <i>Nautilus</i> continued
groping. Near three o'clock in the morning, I observed that we
encountered the Ice Bank's underbelly at a depth of only fifty
meters. So only 150 feet separated us from the surface of the
water. Little by little the Ice Bank was turning into an ice field
again. The mountains were changing back into plains.</p>
      <p>My eyes didn't leave the pressure gauge. We kept rising on a
diagonal, going along this shiny surface that sparkled beneath our
electric rays. Above and below, the Ice Bank was subsiding in long
gradients. Mile after mile it was growing thinner.</p>
      <p>Finally, at six o'clock in the morning on that memorable day of
March 19, the lounge door opened. Captain Nemo appeared.</p>
      <p>"Open sea!" he told me.</p>
   </body>
</topic>