<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<topic id="d2e11226">
   <title>
      <d4pSimpleEnumerator><!--2.11-->Chapter 11. </d4pSimpleEnumerator>
      <ph>The Sargasso Sea</ph>
   </title>
   <body>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="size_plus_2">THE</ph> 
         <i>Nautilus</i> didn't change
direction. For the time being, then, we had to set aside any hope
of returning to European seas. Captain Nemo kept his prow pointing
south. Where was he taking us? I was afraid to guess.</p>
      <p>That day the <i>Nautilus</i> crossed an odd part of the Atlantic
Ocean. No one is unaware of the existence of that great
warm–water current known by name as the Gulf Stream. After
emerging from channels off Florida, it heads toward Spitzbergen.
But before entering the Gulf of Mexico near latitude 44° north,
this current divides into two arms; its chief arm makes for the
shores of Ireland and Norway while the second flexes southward at
the level of the Azores; then it hits the coast of Africa, sweeps
in a long oval, and returns to the Caribbean Sea.</p>
      <p>Now then, this second arm—more accurately, a
collar—forms a ring of warm water around a section of cool,
tranquil, motionless ocean called the Sargasso Sea. This is an
actual lake in the open Atlantic, and the great current's waters
take at least three years to circle it.</p>
      <p>Properly speaking, the Sargasso Sea covers every submerged part
of Atlantis. Certain authors have even held that the many weeds
strewn over this sea were torn loose from the prairies of that
ancient continent. But it's more likely that these grasses, algae,
and fucus plants were carried off from the beaches of Europe and
America, then taken as far as this zone by the Gulf Stream. This is
one of the reasons why <i>Christopher Columbus</i> assumed the
existence of a New World. When the ships of that bold investigator
arrived in the Sargasso Sea, they had great difficulty navigating
in the midst of these weeds, which, much to their crews' dismay,
slowed them down to a halt; and they wasted three long weeks
crossing this sector.</p>
      <p>Such was the region our <i>Nautilus</i> was visiting just then:
a genuine prairie, a tightly woven carpet of algae, gulfweed, and
bladder wrack so dense and compact a craft's stempost couldn't tear
through it without difficulty. Accordingly, not wanting to entangle
his propeller in this weed–choked mass, Captain Nemo stayed
at a depth some meters below the surface of the waves.</p>
      <p>The name Sargasso comes from the Spanish word <i>sargazo</i>,
meaning gulfweed. This gulfweed, the swimming gulfweed or berry
carrier, is the chief substance making up this immense shoal. And
here's why these water plants collect in this placid Atlantic
basin, according to the expert on the subject, Commander Maury,
author of <i>The Physical Geography of the Sea</i>.</p>
      <p>The explanation he gives seems to entail a set of conditions
that everybody knows: "Now," Maury says, "if bits of cork or chaff,
or any floating substance, be put into a basin, and a circular
motion be given to the water, all the light substances will be
found crowding together near the center of the pool, where there is
the least motion. Just such a basin is the Atlantic Ocean to the
Gulf Stream, and the Sargasso Sea is the center of the whirl."</p>
      <p>I share Maury's view, and I was able to study the phenomenon in
this exclusive setting where ships rarely go. Above us, huddled
among the brown weeds, there floated objects originating from all
over: tree trunks ripped from the Rocky Mountains or the Andes and
sent floating down the Amazon or the Mississippi, numerous pieces
of wreckage, remnants of keels or undersides, bulwarks staved in
and so weighed down with seashells and barnacles, they couldn't
rise to the surface of the ocean. And the passing years will
someday bear out Maury's other view that by collecting in this way
over the centuries, these substances will be turned to stone by the
action of the waters and will then form inexhaustible coalfields.
Valuable reserves prepared by farseeing nature for that time when
man will have exhausted his mines on the continents.</p>
      <p>In the midst of this hopelessly tangled fabric of weeds and
fucus plants, I noted some delightful pink–colored,
star–shaped alcyon coral, sea anemone trailing the long
tresses of their tentacles, some green, red, and blue jellyfish,
and especially those big rhizostome jellyfish that Cuvier
described, whose bluish parasols are trimmed with violet
festoons.</p>
      <p>We spent the whole day of February 22 in the Sargasso Sea, where
fish that dote on marine plants and crustaceans find plenty to eat.
The next day the ocean resumed its usual appearance.</p>
      <p>From this moment on, for nineteen days from February 23 to March
12, the <i>Nautilus</i> stayed in the middle of the Atlantic,
hustling us along at a constant speed of 100 leagues every
twenty–four hours. It was obvious that Captain Nemo wanted to
carry out his underwater program, and I had no doubt that he
intended, after doubling Cape Horn, to return to the Pacific South
Seas.</p>
      <p>So Ned Land had good reason to worry. In these wide seas empty
of islands, it was no longer feasible to jump ship. Nor did we have
any way to counter Captain Nemo's whims. We had no choice but to
acquiesce; but if we couldn't attain our end through force or
cunning, I liked to think we might achieve it through persuasion.
Once this voyage was over, might not Captain Nemo consent to set us
free in return for our promise never to reveal his existence? Our
word of honor, which we sincerely would have kept. However, this
delicate question would have to be negotiated with the captain. But
how would he receive our demands for freedom? At the very outset
and in no uncertain terms, hadn't he declared that the secret of
his life required that we be permanently imprisoned on board the
<i>Nautilus</i>? Wouldn't he see my four–month silence as a
tacit acceptance of this situation? Would my returning to this
subject arouse suspicions that could jeopardize our escape plans,
if we had promising circumstances for trying again later on? I
weighed all these considerations, turned them over in my mind,
submitted them to Conseil, but he was as baffled as I was. In
short, although I'm not easily discouraged, I realized that my
chances of ever seeing my fellow men again were shrinking by the
day, especially at a time when Captain Nemo was recklessly racing
toward the south Atlantic!</p>
      <p>During those nineteen days just mentioned, no unique incidents
distinguished our voyage. I saw little of the captain. He was at
work. In the library I often found books he had left open,
especially books on natural history. He had thumbed through my work
on the great ocean depths, and the margins were covered with his
notes, which sometimes contradicted my theories and formulations.
But the captain remained content with this method of refining my
work, and he rarely discussed it with me. Sometimes I heard
melancholy sounds reverberating from the organ, which he played
very expressively, but only at night in the midst of the most
secretive darkness, while the <i>Nautilus</i> slumbered in the
wilderness of the ocean.</p>
      <p>During this part of our voyage, we navigated on the surface of
the waves for entire days. The sea was nearly deserted. A few
sailing ships, laden for the East Indies, were heading toward the
Cape of Good Hope. One day we were chased by the longboats of a
whaling vessel, which undoubtedly viewed us as some enormous baleen
whale of great value. But Captain Nemo didn't want these gallant
gentlemen wasting their time and energy, so he ended the hunt by
diving beneath the waters. This incident seemed to fascinate Ned
Land intensely. I'm sure the Canadian was sorry that these
fishermen couldn't harpoon our sheet–iron <i>cetacean</i> and
mortally wound it.</p>
      <p>During this period the fish Conseil and I observed differed
little from those we had already studied in other latitudes. Chief
among them were specimens of that dreadful <i>cartilaginous</i>
genus that's divided into three subgenera numbering at least
thirty–two species: striped sharks five meters long, the head
squat and wider than the body, the caudal fin curved, the back with
seven big, black, parallel lines running lengthwise; then perlon
sharks, ash gray, pierced with seven gill openings, furnished with
a single dorsal fin placed almost exactly in the middle of the
body.</p>
      <p>Some big dogfish also passed by, a voracious species of shark if
there ever was one. With some justice, fishermen's yarns aren't to
be trusted, but here's what a few of them relate. Inside the corpse
of one of these animals there were found a buffalo head and a whole
calf; in another, two tuna and a sailor in uniform; in yet another,
a soldier with his saber; in another, finally, a horse with its
rider. In candor, none of these sounds like divinely inspired
truth. But the fact remains that not a single dogfish let itself
get caught in the <i>Nautilus's</i> nets, so I can't vouch for
their voracity.</p>
      <p>Schools of elegant, playful dolphin swam alongside for entire
days. They went in groups of five or six, hunting in packs like
wolves over the countryside; moreover, they're just as voracious as
dogfish, if I can believe a certain Copenhagen professor who says
that from one dolphin's stomach, he removed thirteen porpoises and
fifteen seals. True, it was a killer whale, belonging to the
biggest known species, whose length sometimes exceeds
twenty–four feet. The family <i>Delphinia</i> numbers ten
genera, and the dolphins I saw were akin to the genus
<i>Delphinorhynchus</i>, remarkable for an extremely narrow muzzle
four times as long as the cranium. Measuring three meters, their
bodies were black on top, underneath a pinkish white strewn with
small, very scattered spots.</p>
      <p>From these seas I'll also mention some unusual specimens of
croakers, fish from the order <i>Acanthopterygia</i>, family
<i>Scienidea</i>. Some authors—more artistic than
scientific—claim that these fish are melodious singers, that
their voices in unison put on concerts unmatched by human
choristers. I don't say nay, but to my regret these croakers didn't
serenade us as we passed.</p>
      <p>Finally, to conclude, Conseil classified a large number of
flying fish. Nothing could have made a more unusual sight than the
marvelous timing with which dolphins hunt these fish. Whatever the
range of its flight, however evasive its trajectory (even up and
over the <i>Nautilus</i>), the hapless flying fish always found a
dolphin to welcome it with open mouth. These were either flying
gurnards or kitelike sea robins, whose lips glowed in the dark, at
night scrawling fiery streaks in the air before plunging into the
murky waters like so many shooting stars.</p>
      <p>Our navigating continued under these conditions until March 13.
That day the <i>Nautilus</i> was put to work in some
depth–sounding experiments that fascinated me deeply.</p>
      <p>By then we had fared nearly 13,000 leagues from our starting
point in the Pacific high seas. Our position fix placed us in
latitude 45° 37' south and longitude 37° 53' west. These
were the same waterways where Captain Denham, aboard the
<i>Herald</i>, payed out 14,000 meters of sounding line without
finding bottom. It was here too that Lieutenant Parker, aboard the
American frigate <i>Congress</i>, was unable to reach the
underwater soil at 15,149 meters.</p>
      <p>Captain Nemo decided to take his <i>Nautilus</i> down to the
lowest depths in order to double–check these different
soundings. I got ready to record the results of this experiment.
The panels in the lounge opened, and maneuvers began for reaching
those strata so prodigiously far removed.</p>
      <p>It was apparently considered out of the question to dive by
filling the ballast tanks. Perhaps they wouldn't sufficiently
increase the <i>Nautilus's</i> specific gravity. Moreover, in order
to come back up, it would be necessary to expel the excess water,
and our pumps might not have been strong enough to overcome the
outside pressure.</p>
      <p>Captain Nemo decided to make for the ocean floor by submerging
on an appropriately gradual diagonal with the help of his side
fins, which were set at a 45° angle to the <i>Nautilus's</i>
waterline. Then the propeller was brought to its maximum speed, and
its four blades churned the waves with indescribable violence.</p>
      <p>Under this powerful thrust the <i>Nautilus's</i> hull quivered
like a resonating chord, and the ship sank steadily under the
waters. Stationed in the lounge, the captain and I watched the
needle swerving swiftly over the pressure gauge. Soon we had gone
below the livable zone where most fish reside. Some of these
animals can thrive only at the surface of seas or rivers, but a
minority can dwell at fairly great depths. Among the latter I
observed a species of dogfish called the cow shark that's equipped
with six respiratory slits, the telescope fish with its enormous
eyes, the armored gurnard with gray thoracic fins plus black
pectoral fins and a breastplate protected by pale red slabs of
bone, then finally the grenadier, living at a depth of 1,200
meters, by that point tolerating a pressure of 120 atmospheres.</p>
      <p>I asked Captain Nemo if he had observed any fish at more
considerable depths.</p>
      <p>"Fish? Rarely!" he answered me. "But given the current state of
marine science, who are we to presume, what do we really know of
these depths?"</p>
      <p>"Just this, Captain. In going toward the ocean's lower strata,
we know that vegetable life disappears more quickly than animal
life. We know that moving creatures can still be encountered where
water plants no longer grow. We know that oysters and pilgrim
scallops live in 2,000 meters of water, and that Admiral
McClintock, England's hero of the polar seas, pulled in a live sea
star from a depth of 2,500 meters. We know that the crew of the
Royal Navy's <i>Bulldog</i> fished up a starfish from 2,620
fathoms, hence from a depth of more than one vertical league. Would
you still say, Captain Nemo, that we really know nothing?"</p>
      <p>"No, Professor," the captain replied, "I wouldn't be so
discourteous. Yet I'll ask you to explain how these creatures can
live at such depths?"</p>
      <p>"I explain it on two grounds," I replied. "In the first place,
because vertical currents, which are caused by differences in the
water's salinity and density, can produce enough motion to sustain
the rudimentary lifestyles of sea lilies and starfish."</p>
      <p>"True," the captain put in.</p>
      <p>"In the second place, because oxygen is the basis of life, and
we know that the amount of oxygen dissolved in salt water increases
rather than decreases with depth, that the pressure in these lower
strata helps to concentrate their oxygen content."</p>
      <p>"Oho! We know that, do we?" Captain Nemo replied in a tone of
mild surprise. "Well, Professor, we have good reason to know it
because it's the truth. I might add, in fact, that the air bladders
of fish contain more nitrogen than oxygen when these animals are
caught at the surface of the water, and conversely, more oxygen
than nitrogen when they're pulled up from the lower depths. Which
bears out your formulation. But let's continue our
observations."</p>
      <p>My eyes flew back to the pressure gauge. The instrument
indicated a depth of 6,000 meters. Our submergence had been going
on for an hour. The <i>Nautilus</i> slid downward on its slanting
fins, still sinking. These deserted waters were wonderfully clear,
with a transparency impossible to convey. An hour later we were at
13,000 meters—about three and a quarter vertical
leagues—and the ocean floor was nowhere in sight.</p>
      <p>However, at 14,000 meters I saw blackish peaks rising in the
midst of the waters. But these summits could have belonged to
mountains as high or even higher than the Himalayas or Mt. Blanc,
and the extent of these depths remained incalculable.</p>
      <p>Despite the powerful pressures it was undergoing, the
<i>Nautilus</i> sank still deeper. I could feel its
sheet–iron plates trembling down to their riveted joins;
metal bars arched; bulkheads groaned; the lounge windows seemed to
be warping inward under the water's pressure. And this whole sturdy
mechanism would surely have given way, if, as its captain had said,
it weren't capable of resisting like a solid block.</p>
      <p>While grazing these rocky slopes lost under the waters, I still
spotted some seashells, tube worms, lively annelid worms from the
genus <i>Spirorbis</i>, and certain starfish specimens.</p>
      <p>But soon these last representatives of animal life vanished, and
three vertical leagues down, the <i>Nautilus</i> passed below the
limits of underwater existence just as an air balloon rises above
the breathable zones in the sky. We reached a depth of 16,000
meters—four vertical leagues—and by then the
<i>Nautilus's</i> plating was tolerating a pressure of 1,600
atmospheres, in other words, 1,600 kilograms per each square
centimeter on its surface!</p>
      <p>"What an experience!" I exclaimed. "Traveling these deep regions
where no man has ever ventured before! Look, captain! Look at these
magnificent rocks, these uninhabited caves, these last global
haunts where life is no longer possible! What unheard–of
scenery, and why are we reduced to preserving it only as a
memory?"</p>
      <p>"Would you like," Captain Nemo asked me, "to bring back more
than just a memory?"</p>
      <p>"What do you mean?"</p>
      <p>"I mean that nothing could be easier than taking a photograph of
this underwater region!"</p>
      <p>Before I had time to express the surprise this new proposition
caused me, a camera was carried into the lounge at Captain Nemo's
request. The liquid setting, electrically lit, unfolded with
perfect clarity through the wide–open panels. No shadows, no
blurs, thanks to our artificial light. Not even sunshine could have
been better for our purposes. With the thrust of its propeller
curbed by the slant of its fins, the <i>Nautilus</i> stood still.
The camera was aimed at the scenery on the ocean floor, and in a
few seconds we had a perfect negative.</p>
      <p>I attach a print of the positive. In it you can view these
primordial rocks that have never seen the light of day, this nether
granite that forms the powerful foundation of our globe, the deep
caves cut into the stony mass, the outlines of incomparable
distinctness whose far edges stand out in black as if from the
brush of certain Flemish painters. In the distance is a mountainous
horizon, a wondrously undulating line that makes up the background
of this landscape. The general effect of these smooth rocks is
indescribable: black, polished, without moss or other blemish,
carved into strange shapes, sitting firmly on a carpet of sand that
sparkled beneath our streams of electric light.</p>
      <p>Meanwhile, his photographic operations over, Captain Nemo told
me:</p>
      <p>"Let's go back up, professor. We mustn't push our luck and
expose the <i>Nautilus</i> too long to these pressures."</p>
      <p>"Let's go back up!" I replied.</p>
      <p>"Hold on tight."</p>
      <p>Before I had time to realize why the captain made this
recommendation, I was hurled to the carpet.</p>
      <p>Its fins set vertically, its propeller thrown in gear at the
captain's signal, the <i>Nautilus</i> rose with lightning speed,
shooting upward like an air balloon into the sky. Vibrating
resonantly, it knifed through the watery mass. Not a single detail
was visible. In four minutes it had cleared the four vertical
leagues separating it from the surface of the ocean, and after
emerging like a flying fish, it fell back into the sea, making the
waves leap to prodigious heights.</p>
   </body>
</topic>