<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<topic id="d2e14446">
   <title>
      <d4pSimpleEnumerator><!--2.19-->Chapter 19. </d4pSimpleEnumerator>
      <ph>The Gulf Stream</ph>
   </title>
   <body>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="size_plus_2">THIS DREADFUL SCENE</ph> on April 20 none of
us will ever be able to forget. I wrote it up in a state of intense
excitement. Later I reviewed my narrative. I read it to Conseil and
the Canadian. They found it accurate in detail but deficient in
impact. To convey such sights, it would take the pen of our most
famous poet, Victor Hugo, author of <i>The Toilers of the
Sea</i>.</p>
      <p>As I said, Captain Nemo wept while staring at the waves. His
grief was immense. This was the second companion he had lost since
we had come aboard. And what a way to die! Smashed, strangled,
crushed by the fearsome arms of a devilfish, ground between its
iron mandibles, this friend would never rest with his companions in
the placid waters of their coral cemetery!</p>
      <p>As for me, what had harrowed my heart in the thick of this
struggle was the despairing yell given by this unfortunate man.
Forgetting his regulation language, this poor Frenchman had
reverted to speaking his own mother tongue to fling out one supreme
plea! Among the <i>Nautilus's</i> crew, allied body and soul with
Captain Nemo and likewise fleeing from human contact, I had found a
fellow countryman! Was he the only representative of France in this
mysterious alliance, obviously made up of individuals from
different nationalities? This was just one more of those insoluble
problems that kept welling up in my mind!</p>
      <p>Captain Nemo reentered his stateroom, and I saw no more of him
for a good while. But how sad, despairing, and irresolute he must
have felt, to judge from this ship whose soul he was, which
reflected his every mood! The <i>Nautilus</i> no longer kept to a
fixed heading. It drifted back and forth, riding with the waves
like a corpse. Its propeller had been disentangled but was barely
put to use. It was navigating at random. It couldn't tear itself
away from the setting of this last struggle, from this sea that had
devoured one of its own!</p>
      <p>Ten days went by in this way. It was only on May 1 that the
<i>Nautilus</i> openly resumed its northbound course, after raising
the Bahamas at the mouth of Old Bahama Channel. We then went with
the current of the sea's greatest river, which has its own banks,
fish, and temperature. I mean the Gulf Stream.</p>
      <p>It is indeed a river that runs independently through the middle
of the Atlantic, its waters never mixing with the ocean's waters.
It's a salty river, saltier than the sea surrounding it. Its
average depth is 3,000 feet, its average width sixty miles. In
certain localities its current moves at a speed of four kilometers
per hour. The unchanging volume of its waters is greater than that
of all the world's rivers combined.</p>
      <p>As discovered by Commander Maury, the true source of the Gulf
Stream, its starting point, if you prefer, is located in the Bay of
Biscay. There its waters, still weak in temperature and color,
begin to form. It goes down south, skirts equatorial Africa, warms
its waves in the rays of the Torrid Zone, crosses the Atlantic,
reaches Cape São Roque on the coast of Brazil, and forks
into two branches, one going to the Caribbean Sea for further
saturation with heat particles. Then, entrusted with restoring the
balance between hot and cold temperatures and with mixing tropical
and northern waters, the Gulf Stream begins to play its stabilizing
role. Attaining a white heat in the Gulf of Mexico, it heads north
up the American coast, advances as far as Newfoundland, swerves
away under the thrust of a cold current from the Davis Strait, and
resumes its ocean course by going along a great circle of the earth
on a rhumb line; it then divides into two arms near the 43rd
parallel; one, helped by the northeast trade winds, returns to the
Bay of Biscay and the Azores; the other washes the shores of
Ireland and Norway with lukewarm water, goes beyond Spitzbergen,
where its temperature falls to 4° centigrade, and fashions the
open sea at the pole.</p>
      <p>It was on this oceanic river that the <i>Nautilus</i> was then
navigating. Leaving Old Bahama Channel, which is fourteen leagues
wide by 350 meters deep, the Gulf Stream moves at the rate of eight
kilometers per hour. Its speed steadily decreases as it advances
northward, and we must pray that this steadiness continues,
because, as experts agree, if its speed and direction were to
change, the climates of Europe would undergo disturbances whose
consequences are incalculable.</p>
      <p>Near noon I was on the platform with Conseil. I shared with him
the relevant details on the Gulf Stream. When my explanation was
over, I invited him to dip his hands into its current.</p>
      <p>Conseil did so, and he was quite astonished to experience no
sensation of either hot or cold.</p>
      <p>"That comes," I told him, "from the water temperature of the
Gulf Stream, which, as it leaves the Gulf of Mexico, is barely
different from your blood temperature. This Gulf Stream is a huge
heat generator that enables the coasts of Europe to be decked in
eternal greenery. And if Commander Maury is correct, were one to
harness the full warmth of this current, it would supply enough
heat to keep molten a river of iron solder as big as the Amazon or
the Missouri."</p>
      <p>Just then the Gulf Stream's speed was 2.25 meters per second. So
distinct is its current from the surrounding sea, its confined
waters stand out against the ocean and operate on a different level
from the colder waters. Murky as well, and very rich in saline
material, their pure indigo contrasts with the green waves
surrounding them. Moreover, their line of demarcation is so clear
that abreast of the Carolinas, the <i>Nautilus's</i> spur cut the
waves of the Gulf Stream while its propeller was still churning
those belonging to the ocean.</p>
      <p>This current swept along with it a whole host of moving
creatures. Argonauts, so common in the Mediterranean, voyaged here
in schools of large numbers. Among cartilaginous fish, the most
remarkable were rays whose ultra slender tails made up nearly a
third of the body, which was shaped like a huge diamond
twenty–five feet long; then little one–meter sharks,
the head large, the snout short and rounded, the teeth sharp and
arranged in several rows, the body seemingly covered with
scales.</p>
      <p>Among bony fish, I noted grizzled wrasse unique to these seas,
deep–water gilthead whose iris has a fiery gleam,
one–meter croakers whose large mouths bristle with small
teeth and which let out thin cries, black rudderfish like those
I've already discussed, blue dorados accented with gold and silver,
rainbow–hued parrotfish that can rival the loveliest tropical
birds in coloring, banded blennies with triangular heads, bluish
flounder without scales, toadfish covered with a crosswise yellow
band in the shape of a Τ, swarms of little freckled gobies
stippled with brown spots, lungfish with silver heads and yellow
tails, various specimens of salmon, mullet with slim figures and a
softly glowing radiance that Lacépède dedicated to
the memory of his wife, and finally the American cavalla, a
handsome fish decorated by every honorary order, bedizened with
their every ribbon, frequenting the shores of this great nation
where ribbons and orders are held in such low esteem.</p>
      <p>I might add that during the night, the Gulf Stream's
phosphorescent waters rivaled the electric glow of our beacon,
especially in the stormy weather that frequently threatened us.</p>
      <p>On May 8, while abreast of North Carolina, we were across from
Cape Hatteras once more. There the Gulf Stream is
seventy–five miles wide and 210 meters deep. The
<i>Nautilus</i> continued to wander at random. Seemingly, all
supervision had been jettisoned. Under these conditions I admit
that we could easily have gotten away. In fact, the populous shores
offered ready refuge everywhere. The sea was plowed continuously by
the many steamers providing service between the Gulf of Mexico and
New York or Boston, and it was crossed night and day by little
schooners engaged in coastal trade over various points on the
American shore. We could hope to be picked up. So it was a
promising opportunity, despite the thirty miles that separated the
<i>Nautilus</i> from these Union coasts.</p>
      <p>But one distressing circumstance totally thwarted the Canadian's
plans. The weather was thoroughly foul. We were approaching
waterways where storms are commonplace, the very homeland of
tornadoes and cyclones specifically engendered by the Gulf Stream's
current. To face a frequently raging sea in a frail skiff was a
race to certain disaster. Ned Land conceded this himself. So he
champed at the bit, in the grip of an intense homesickness that
could be cured only by our escape.</p>
      <p>"Sir," he told me that day, "it's got to stop. I want to get to
the bottom of this. Your Nemo's veering away from shore and heading
up north. But believe you me, I had my fill at the South Pole and
I'm not going with him to the North Pole."</p>
      <p>"What can we do, Ned, since it isn't feasible to escape right
now?"</p>
      <p>"I keep coming back to my idea. We've got to talk to the
captain. When we were in your own country's seas, you didn't say a
word. Now that we're in mine, I intend to speak up. Before a few
days are out, I figure the <i>Nautilus</i> will lie abreast of Nova
Scotia, and from there to Newfoundland is the mouth of a large
gulf, and the St. Lawrence empties into that gulf, and the St.
Lawrence is my own river, the river running by Quebec, my
hometown—and when I think about all this, my gorge rises and
my hair stands on end! Honestly, sir, I'd rather jump overboard! I
can't stay here any longer! I'm suffocating!"</p>
      <p>The Canadian was obviously at the end of his patience. His
vigorous nature couldn't adapt to this protracted imprisonment. His
facial appearance was changing by the day. His moods grew gloomier
and gloomier. I had a sense of what he was suffering because I also
was gripped by homesickness. Nearly seven months had gone by
without our having any news from shore. Moreover, Captain Nemo's
reclusiveness, his changed disposition, and especially his total
silence since the battle with the devilfish all made me see things
in a different light. I no longer felt the enthusiasm of our first
days on board. You needed to be Flemish like Conseil to accept
these circumstances, living in a habitat designed for
<i>cetaceans</i> and other denizens of the deep. Truly, if that
gallant lad had owned gills instead of lungs, I think he would have
made an outstanding fish!</p>
      <p>"Well, sir?" Ned Land went on, seeing that I hadn't replied.</p>
      <p>"Well, Ned, you want me to ask Captain Nemo what he intends to
do with us?"</p>
      <p>"Yes, sir."</p>
      <p>"Even though he has already made that clear?"</p>
      <p>"Yes. I want it settled once and for all. Speak just for me,
strictly on my behalf, if you want."</p>
      <p>"But I rarely encounter him. He positively avoids me."</p>
      <p>"All the more reason you should go look him up."</p>
      <p>"I'll confer with him, Ned."</p>
      <p>"When?" the Canadian asked insistently.</p>
      <p>"When I encounter him."</p>
      <p>"Professor Aronnax, would you like me to go find him
myself?"</p>
      <p>"No, let me do it. Tomorrow—"</p>
      <p>"Today," Ned Land said.</p>
      <p>"So be it. I'll see him today," I answered the Canadian, who, if
he took action himself, would certainly have ruined everything.</p>
      <p>I was left to myself. His request granted, I decided to dispose
of it immediately. I like things over and done with.</p>
      <p>I reentered my stateroom. From there I could hear movements
inside Captain Nemo's quarters. I couldn't pass up this chance for
an encounter. I knocked on his door. I received no reply. I knocked
again, then tried the knob. The door opened.</p>
      <p>I entered. The captain was there. He was bending over his
worktable and hadn't heard me. Determined not to leave without
questioning him, I drew closer. He looked up sharply, with a
frowning brow, and said in a pretty stern tone:</p>
      <p>"Oh, it's you! What do you want?"</p>
      <p>"To speak with you, Captain."</p>
      <p>"But I'm busy, sir, I'm at work. I give you the freedom to enjoy
your privacy, can't I have the same for myself?"</p>
      <p>This reception was less than encouraging. But I was determined
to give as good as I got.</p>
      <p>"Sir," I said coolly, "I need to speak with you on a matter that
simply can't wait."</p>
      <p>"Whatever could that be, sir?" he replied sarcastically. "Have
you made some discovery that has escaped me? Has the sea yielded up
some novel secret to you?"</p>
      <p>We were miles apart. But before I could reply, he showed me a
manuscript open on the table and told me in a more serious
tone:</p>
      <p>"Here, Professor Aronnax, is a manuscript written in several
languages. It contains a summary of my research under the sea, and
God willing, it won't perish with me. Signed with my name, complete
with my life story, this manuscript will be enclosed in a small,
unsinkable contrivance. The last surviving man on the
<i>Nautilus</i> will throw this contrivance into the sea, and it
will go wherever the waves carry it."</p>
      <p>The man's name! His life story written by himself! So the secret
of his existence might someday be unveiled? But just then I saw
this announcement only as a lead–in to my topic.</p>
      <p>"Captain," I replied, "I'm all praise for this idea you're
putting into effect. The fruits of your research must not be lost.
But the methods you're using strike me as primitive. Who knows
where the winds will take that contrivance, into whose hands it may
fall? Can't you find something better? Can't you or one of your
men—"</p>
      <p>"Never, sir," the captain said, swiftly interrupting me.</p>
      <p>"But my companions and I would be willing to safeguard this
manuscript, and if you give us back our freedom—"</p>
      <p>"Your freedom!" Captain Nemo put in, standing up.</p>
      <p>"Yes, sir, and that's the subject on which I wanted to confer
with you. For seven months we've been aboard your vessel, and I ask
you today, in the name of my companions as well as myself, if you
intend to keep us here forever."</p>
      <p>"Professor Aronnax," Captain Nemo said, "I'll answer you today
just as I did seven months ago: whomever boards the <i>Nautilus</i>
must never leave it."</p>
      <p>"What you're inflicting on us is outright slavery!"</p>
      <p>"Call it anything you like."</p>
      <p>"But every slave has the right to recover his freedom! By any
worthwhile, available means!"</p>
      <p>"Who has denied you that right?" Captain Nemo replied. "Did I
ever try to bind you with your word of honor?"</p>
      <p>The captain stared at me, crossing his arms.</p>
      <p>"Sir," I told him, "to take up this subject a second time would
be distasteful to both of us. So let's finish what we've started. I
repeat: it isn't just for myself that I raise this issue. To me,
research is a relief, a potent diversion, an enticement, a passion
that can make me forget everything else. Like you, I'm a man
neglected and unknown, living in the faint hope that someday I can
pass on to future generations the fruits of my
labors—figuratively speaking, by means of some contrivance
left to the luck of winds and waves. In short, I can admire you and
comfortably go with you while playing a role I only partly
understand; but I still catch glimpses of other aspects of your
life that are surrounded by involvements and secrets that, alone on
board, my companions and I can't share. And even when our hearts
could beat with yours, moved by some of your griefs or stirred by
your deeds of courage and genius, we've had to stifle even the
slightest token of that sympathy that arises at the sight of
something fine and good, whether it comes from friend or enemy. All
right then! It's this feeling of being alien to your deepest
concerns that makes our situation unacceptable, impossible, even
impossible for me but especially for Ned Land. Every man, by virtue
of his very humanity, deserves fair treatment. Have you considered
how a love of freedom and hatred of slavery could lead to plans of
vengeance in a temperament like the Canadian's, what he might
think, attempt, endeavor . . . ?"</p>
      <p>I fell silent. Captain Nemo stood up.</p>
      <p>"Ned Land can think, attempt, or endeavor anything he wants,
what difference is it to me? I didn't go looking for him! I don't
keep him on board for my pleasure! As for you, Professor Aronnax,
you're a man able to understand anything, even silence. I have
nothing more to say to you. Let this first time you've come to
discuss this subject also be the last, because a second time I
won't even listen."</p>
      <p>I withdrew. From that day forward our position was very
strained. I reported this conversation to my two companions.</p>
      <p>"Now we know," Ned said, "that we can't expect a thing from this
man. The <i>Nautilus</i> is nearing Long Island. We'll escape, no
matter what the weather."</p>
      <p>But the skies became more and more threatening. There were
conspicuous signs of a hurricane on the way. The atmosphere was
turning white and milky. Slender sheaves of cirrus clouds were
followed on the horizon by layers of nimbocumulus. Other low clouds
fled swiftly. The sea grew towering, inflated by long swells. Every
bird had disappeared except a few petrels, friends of the storms.
The barometer fell significantly, indicating a tremendous tension
in the surrounding haze. The mixture in our stormglass decomposed
under the influence of the electricity charging the air. A struggle
of the elements was approaching.</p>
      <p>The storm burst during the daytime of May 13, just as the
<i>Nautilus</i> was cruising abreast of Long Island, a few miles
from the narrows to Upper New York Bay. I'm able to describe this
struggle of the elements because Captain Nemo didn't flee into the
ocean depths; instead, from some inexplicable whim, he decided to
brave it out on the surface.</p>
      <p>The wind was blowing from the southwest, initially a stiff
breeze, in other words, with a speed of fifteen meters per second,
which built to twenty–five meters near three o'clock in the
afternoon. This is the figure for major storms.</p>
      <p>Unshaken by these squalls, Captain Nemo stationed himself on the
platform. He was lashed around the waist to withstand the monstrous
breakers foaming over the deck. I hoisted and attached myself to
the same place, dividing my wonderment between the storm and this
incomparable man who faced it head–on.</p>
      <p>The raging sea was swept with huge tattered clouds drenched by
the waves. I saw no more of the small intervening billows that form
in the troughs of the big crests. Just long, soot–colored
undulations with crests so compact they didn't foam. They kept
growing taller. They were spurring each other on. The
<i>Nautilus</i>, sometimes lying on its side, sometimes standing on
end like a mast, rolled and pitched frightfully.</p>
      <p>Near five o'clock a torrential rain fell, but it lulled neither
wind nor sea. The hurricane was unleashed at a speed of
forty–five meters per second, hence almost forty leagues per
hour. Under these conditions houses topple, roof tiles puncture
doors, iron railings snap in two, and
twenty–four–pounder cannons relocate. And yet in the
midst of this turmoil, the <i>Nautilus</i> lived up to that saying
of an expert engineer: "A well–constructed hull can defy any
sea!" This submersible was no resisting rock that waves could
demolish; it was a steel spindle, obediently in motion, without
rigging or masting, and able to brave their fury with impunity.</p>
      <p>Meanwhile I was carefully examining these unleashed breakers.
They measured up to fifteen meters in height over a length of 150
to 175 meters, and the speed of their propagation (half that of the
wind) was fifteen meters per second. Their volume and power
increased with the depth of the waters. I then understood the role
played by these waves, which trap air in their flanks and release
it in the depths of the sea where its oxygen brings life. Their
utmost pressure—it has been calculated—can build to
3,000 kilograms on every square foot of surface they strike. It was
such waves in the Hebrides that repositioned a stone block weighing
84,000 pounds. It was their relatives in the tidal wave on December
23, 1854, that toppled part of the Japanese city of Tokyo, then
went that same day at 700 kilometers per hour to break on the
beaches of America.</p>
      <p>After nightfall the storm grew in intensity. As in the 1860
cyclone on Réunion Island, the barometer fell to 710
millimeters. At the close of day, I saw a big ship passing on the
horizon, struggling painfully. It lay to at half steam in an effort
to hold steady on the waves. It must have been a steamer on one of
those lines out of New York to Liverpool or Le Havre. It soon
vanished into the shadows.</p>
      <p>At ten o'clock in the evening, the skies caught on fire. The air
was streaked with violent flashes of lightning. I couldn't stand
this brightness, but Captain Nemo stared straight at it, as if to
inhale the spirit of the storm. A dreadful noise filled the air, a
complicated noise made up of the roar of crashing breakers, the
howl of the wind, claps of thunder. The wind shifted to every point
of the horizon, and the cyclone left the east to return there after
passing through north, west, and south, moving in the opposite
direction of revolving storms in the southern hemisphere.</p>
      <p>Oh, that Gulf Stream! It truly lives up to its nickname, the
Lord of Storms! All by itself it creates these fearsome cyclones
through the difference in temperature between its currents and the
superimposed layers of air.</p>
      <p>The rain was followed by a downpour of fire. Droplets of water
changed into exploding tufts. You would have thought Captain Nemo
was courting a death worthy of himself, seeking to be struck by
lightning. In one hideous pitching movement, the <i>Nautilus</i>
reared its steel spur into the air like a lightning rod, and I saw
long sparks shoot down it.</p>
      <p>Shattered, at the end of my strength, I slid flat on my belly to
the hatch. I opened it and went below to the lounge. By then the
storm had reached its maximum intensity. It was impossible to stand
upright inside the <i>Nautilus</i>.</p>
      <p>Captain Nemo reentered near midnight. I could hear the ballast
tanks filling little by little, and the <i>Nautilus</i> sank gently
beneath the surface of the waves.</p>
      <p>Through the lounge's open windows, I saw large, frightened fish
passing like phantoms in the fiery waters. Some were struck by
lightning right before my eyes!</p>
      <p>The <i>Nautilus</i> kept descending. I thought it would find
calm again at fifteen meters down. No. The upper strata were too
violently agitated. It needed to sink to fifty meters, searching
for a resting place in the bowels of the sea.</p>
      <p>But once there, what tranquility we found, what silence, what
peace all around us! Who would have known that a dreadful hurricane
was then unleashed on the surface of this ocean?</p>
   </body>
</topic>