<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<topic id="d2e1580">
   <title>
      <d4pSimpleEnumerator><!--1.6-->Chapter 6. </d4pSimpleEnumerator>
      <ph>At Full Steam</ph>
   </title>
   <body>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="size_plus_2">AT THIS SHOUT</ph> the entire crew rushed
toward the harpooner—commander, officers, mates,</p>
      <p>sailors, cabin boys, down to engineers leaving their machinery
and stokers neglecting their furnaces. The order was given to stop,
and the frigate merely coasted.</p>
      <p>By then the darkness was profound, and as good as the Canadian's
eyes were, I still wondered how he could see—and what he had
seen. My heart was pounding fit to burst.</p>
      <p>But Ned Land was not mistaken, and we all spotted the object his
hand was indicating.</p>
      <p>Two cable lengths off the <i>Abraham Lincoln's</i> starboard
quarter, the sea seemed to be lit up from underneath. This was no
mere phosphorescent phenomenon, that much was unmistakable.
Submerged some fathoms below the surface of the water, the monster
gave off that very intense but inexplicable glow that several
captains had mentioned in their reports. This magnificent radiance
had to come from some force with a great illuminating capacity. The
edge of its light swept over the sea in an immense, highly
elongated oval, condensing at the center into a blazing core whose
unbearable glow diminished by° outward.</p>
      <p>"It's only a cluster of phosphorescent particles!" exclaimed one
of the officers.</p>
      <p>"No, sir," I answered with conviction. "Not even
angel–wing clams or salps have ever given off such a powerful
light. That glow is basically electric in nature. Besides . . .
look, look! It's shifting! It's moving back and forth! It's darting
at us!"</p>
      <p>A universal shout went up from the frigate.</p>
      <p>"Quiet!" Commander Farragut said. "Helm hard to leeward! Reverse
engines!"</p>
      <p>Sailors rushed to the helm, engineers to their machinery. Under
reverse steam immediately, the <i>Abraham Lincoln</i> beat to port,
sweeping in a semicircle.</p>
      <p>"Right your helm! Engines forward!" Commander Farragut
called.</p>
      <p>These orders were executed, and the frigate swiftly retreated
from this core of light.</p>
      <p>My mistake. It wanted to retreat, but the unearthly animal came
at us with a speed double our own.</p>
      <p>We gasped. More stunned than afraid, we stood mute and
motionless. The animal caught up with us, played with us. It made a
full circle around the frigate—then doing fourteen
knots—and wrapped us in sheets of electricity that were like
luminous dust. Then it retreated two or three miles, leaving a
phosphorescent trail comparable to those swirls of steam that shoot
behind the locomotive of an express train. Suddenly, all the way
from the dark horizon where it had gone to gather momentum, the
monster abruptly dashed toward the <i>Abraham Lincoln</i> with
frightening speed, stopped sharply twenty feet from our side
plates, and died out—not by diving under the water, since its
glow did not recede gradually—but all at once, as if the
source of this brilliant emanation had suddenly dried up. Then it
reappeared on the other side of the ship, either by circling around
us or by gliding under our hull. At any instant a collision could
have occurred that would have been fatal to us.</p>
      <p>Meanwhile I was astonished at the frigate's maneuvers. It was
fleeing, not fighting. Built to pursue, it was being pursued, and I
commented on this to Commander Farragut. His face, ordinarily so
emotionless, was stamped with indescribable astonishment.</p>
      <p>"Professor Aronnax," he answered me, "I don't know what kind of
fearsome creature I'm up against, and I don't want my frigate
running foolish risks in all this darkness. Besides, how should we
attack this unknown creature, how should we defend ourselves
against it? Let's wait for daylight, and then we'll play a
different role."</p>
      <p>"You've no further doubts, commander, as to the nature of this
animal?"</p>
      <p>"No, sir, it's apparently a gigantic narwhale, and an electric
one to boot."</p>
      <p>"Maybe," I added, "it's no more approachable than an electric
eel or an electric ray!"</p>
      <p>"Right," the commander replied. "And if it has their power to
electrocute, it's surely the most dreadful animal ever conceived by
our Creator. That's why I'll keep on my guard, sir."</p>
      <p>The whole crew stayed on their feet all night long. No one even
thought of sleeping. Unable to compete with the monster's speed,
the <i>Abraham Lincoln</i> slowed down and stayed at half steam.
For its part, the narwhale mimicked the frigate, simply rode with
the waves, and seemed determined not to forsake the field of
battle.</p>
      <p>However, near midnight it disappeared, or to use a more
appropriate expression, "it went out," like a huge glowworm. Had it
fled from us? We were duty bound to fear so rather than hope so.
But at 12:53 in the morning, a deafening hiss became audible,
resembling the sound made by a waterspout expelled with tremendous
intensity.</p>
      <p>By then Commander Farragut, Ned Land, and I were on the
afterdeck, peering eagerly into the profound gloom.</p>
      <p>"Ned Land," the commander asked, "you've often heard whales
bellowing?"</p>
      <p>"Often, sir, but never a whale like this, whose sighting earned
me $2,000.00."</p>
      <p>"Correct, the prize is rightfully yours. But tell me, isn't that
the noise <i>cetaceans</i> make when they spurt water from their
blowholes?"</p>
      <p>"The very noise, sir, but this one's way louder. So there can be
no mistake. There's definitely a whale lurking in our waters. With
your permission, sir," the harpooner added, "tomorrow at daybreak
we'll have words with it."</p>
      <p>"If it's in a mood to listen to you, Mr. Land," I replied in a
tone far from convinced.</p>
      <p>"Let me get within four harpoon lengths of it," the Canadian
shot back, "and it had better listen!"</p>
      <p>"But to get near it," the commander went on, "I'd have to put a
whaleboat at your disposal?"</p>
      <p>"Certainly, sir."</p>
      <p>"That would be gambling with the lives of my men."</p>
      <p>"And with my own!" the harpooner replied simply.</p>
      <p>Near two o'clock in the morning, the core of light reappeared,
no less intense, five miles to windward of the <i>Abraham
Lincoln</i>. Despite the distance, despite the noise of wind and
sea, we could distinctly hear the fearsome thrashings of the
animal's tail, and even its panting breath. Seemingly, the moment
this enormous narwhale came up to breathe at the surface of the
ocean, air was sucked into its lungs like steam into the huge
cylinders of a 2,000–horsepower engine.</p>
      <p>"Hmm!" I said to myself. "A <i>cetacean</i> as powerful as a
whole cavalry regiment—now that's a whale of a whale!"</p>
      <p>We stayed on the alert until daylight, getting ready for action.
Whaling gear was set up along the railings. Our chief officer
loaded the blunderbusses, which can launch harpoons as far as a
mile, and long duck guns with exploding bullets that can mortally
wound even the most powerful animals. Ned Land was content to
sharpen his harpoon, a dreadful weapon in his hands.</p>
      <p>At six o'clock day began to break, and with the dawn's early
light, the narwhale's electric glow disappeared. At seven o'clock
the day was well along, but a very dense morning mist shrank the
horizon, and our best spyglasses were unable to pierce it. The
outcome: disappointment and anger.</p>
      <p>I hoisted myself up to the crosstrees of the mizzen sail. Some
officers were already perched on the mastheads.</p>
      <p>At eight o'clock the mist rolled ponderously over the waves, and
its huge curls were lifting little by little. The horizon grew
wider and clearer all at once.</p>
      <p>Suddenly, just as on the previous evening, Ned Land's voice was
audible.</p>
      <p>"There's the thing in question, astern to port!" the harpooner
shouted.</p>
      <p>Every eye looked toward the point indicated.</p>
      <p>There, a mile and a half from the frigate, a long blackish body
emerged a meter above the waves. Quivering violently, its tail was
creating a considerable eddy. Never had caudal equipment thrashed
the sea with such power. An immense wake of glowing whiteness
marked the animal's track, sweeping in a long curve.</p>
      <p>Our frigate drew nearer to the <i>cetacean</i>. I examined it
with a completely open mind. Those reports from the <i>Shannon</i>
and the <i>Helvetia</i> had slightly exaggerated its dimensions,
and I put its length at only 250 feet. Its girth was more difficult
to judge, but all in all, the animal seemed to be wonderfully
proportioned in all three dimensions.</p>
      <p>While I was observing this phenomenal creature, two jets of
steam and water sprang from its blowholes and rose to an altitude
of forty meters, which settled for me its mode of breathing. From
this I finally concluded that it belonged to the branch
<i>Vertebrata</i>, class <i>Mammalia</i>, subclass
<i>Monodelphia</i>, group <i>Pisciforma</i>, order <i>Cetacea</i>,
family . . . but here I couldn't make up my mind. The order
<i>Cetacea</i> consists of three families, baleen whales, sperm
whales, dolphins, and it's in this last group that narwhales are
placed. Each of these families is divided into several genera, each
genus into species, each species into varieties. So I was still
missing variety, species, genus, and family, but no doubt I would
complete my classifying with the aid of Heaven and Commander
Farragut.</p>
      <p>The crew were waiting impatiently for orders from their leader.
The latter, after carefully observing the animal, called for his
engineer. The engineer raced over.</p>
      <p>"Sir," the commander said, "are you up to pressure?"</p>
      <p>"Aye, sir," the engineer replied.</p>
      <p>"Fine. Stoke your furnaces and clap on full steam!"</p>
      <p>Three cheers greeted this order. The hour of battle had sounded.
A few moments later, the frigate's two funnels vomited torrents of
black smoke, and its deck quaked from the trembling of its
boilers.</p>
      <p>Driven forward by its powerful propeller, the <i>Abraham
Lincoln</i> headed straight for the animal. Unconcerned, the latter
let us come within half a cable length; then, not bothering to
dive, it got up a little speed, retreated, and was content to keep
its distance.</p>
      <p>This chase dragged on for about three–quarters of an hour
without the frigate gaining two fathoms on the <i>cetacean</i>. At
this rate, it was obvious that we would never catch up with it.</p>
      <p>Infuriated, Commander Farragut kept twisting the thick tuft of
hair that flourished below his chin.</p>
      <p>"Ned Land!" he called.</p>
      <p>The Canadian reported at once.</p>
      <p>"Well, Mr. Land," the commander asked, "do you still advise
putting my longboats to sea?"</p>
      <p>"No, sir," Ned Land replied, "because that beast won't be caught
against its will."</p>
      <p>"Then what should we do?"</p>
      <p>"Stoke up more steam, sir, if you can. As for me, with your
permission I'll go perch on the bobstays under the bowsprit, and if
we can get within a harpoon length, I'll harpoon the brute."</p>
      <p>"Go to it, Ned," Commander Farragut replied. "Engineer," he
called, "keep the pressure mounting!"</p>
      <p>Ned Land made his way to his post. The furnaces were urged into
greater activity; our propeller did forty–three revolutions
per minute, and steam shot from the valves. Heaving the log, we
verified that the <i>Abraham Lincoln</i> was going at the rate of
18.5 miles per hour.</p>
      <p>But that damned animal also did a speed of 18.5.</p>
      <p>For the next hour our frigate kept up this pace without gaining
a fathom! This was humiliating for one of the fastest racers in the
American navy. The crew were working up into a blind rage. Sailor
after sailor heaved insults at the monster, which couldn't be
bothered with answering back. Commander Farragut was no longer
content simply to twist his goatee; he chewed on it.</p>
      <p>The engineer was summoned once again.</p>
      <p>"You're up to maximum pressure?" the commander asked him.</p>
      <p>"Aye, sir," the engineer replied.</p>
      <p>"And your valves are charged to . . . ?"</p>
      <p>"To six and a half atmospheres."</p>
      <p>"Charge them to ten atmospheres."</p>
      <p>A typical American order if I ever heard one. It would have
sounded just fine during some Mississippi paddle–wheeler
race, to "outstrip the competition!"</p>
      <p>"Conseil," I said to my gallant servant, now at my side, "you
realize that we'll probably blow ourselves skyhigh?"</p>
      <p>"As master wishes!" Conseil replied.</p>
      <p>All right, I admit it: I did wish to run this risk!</p>
      <p>The valves were charged. More coal was swallowed by the
furnaces. Ventilators shot torrents of air over the braziers. The
<i>Abraham Lincoln's</i> speed increased. Its masts trembled down
to their blocks, and swirls of smoke could barely squeeze through
the narrow funnels.</p>
      <p>We heaved the log a second time.</p>
      <p>"Well, helmsman?" Commander Farragut asked.</p>
      <p>"19.3 miles per hour, sir."</p>
      <p>"Keep stoking the furnaces."</p>
      <p>The engineer did so. The pressure gauge marked ten atmospheres.
But no doubt the <i>cetacean</i> itself had "warmed up," because
without the least trouble, it also did 19.3.</p>
      <p>What a chase! No, I can't describe the excitement that shook my
very being. Ned Land stayed at his post, harpoon in hand. Several
times the animal let us approach.</p>
      <p>"We're overhauling it!" the Canadian would shout.</p>
      <p>Then, just as he was about to strike, the <i>cetacean</i> would
steal off with a swiftness I could estimate at no less than thirty
miles per hour. And even at our maximum speed, it took the liberty
of thumbing its nose at the frigate by running a full circle around
us! A howl of fury burst from every throat!</p>
      <p>By noon we were no farther along than at eight o'clock in the
morning.</p>
      <p>Commander Farragut then decided to use more direct methods.</p>
      <p>"Bah!" he said. "So that animal is faster than the <i>Abraham
Lincoln</i>. All right, we'll see if it can outrun our conical
shells! Mate, man the gun in the bow!"</p>
      <p>Our forecastle cannon was immediately loaded and leveled. The
cannoneer fired a shot, but his shell passed some feet above the
<i>cetacean</i>, which stayed half a mile off.</p>
      <p>"Over to somebody with better aim!" the commander shouted. "And
$500.00 to the man who can pierce that infernal beast!"</p>
      <p>Calm of eye, cool of feature, an old gray–bearded
gunner—I can see him to this day—approached the cannon,
put it in position, and took aim for a good while. There was a
mighty explosion, mingled with cheers from the crew.</p>
      <p>The shell reached its target; it hit the animal, but not in the
usual fashion—it bounced off that rounded surface and
vanished into the sea two miles out.</p>
      <p>"Oh drat!" said the old gunner in his anger. "That rascal must
be covered with six–inch armor plate!"</p>
      <p>"Curse the beast!" Commander Farragut shouted.</p>
      <p>The hunt was on again, and Commander Farragut leaned over to me,
saying:</p>
      <p>"I'll chase that animal till my frigate explodes!"</p>
      <p>"Yes," I replied, "and nobody would blame you!"</p>
      <p>We could still hope that the animal would tire out and not be as
insensitive to exhaustion as our steam engines. But no such luck.
Hour after hour went by without it showing the least sign of
weariness.</p>
      <p>However, to the <i>Abraham Lincoln's</i> credit, it must be said
that we struggled on with tireless persistence. I estimate that we
covered a distance of at least 500 kilometers during this
ill–fated day of November 6. But night fell and wrapped the
surging ocean in its shadows.</p>
      <p>By then I thought our expedition had come to an end, that we
would never see this fantastic animal again. I was mistaken.</p>
      <p>At 10:50 in the evening, that electric light reappeared three
miles to windward of the frigate, just as clear and intense as the
night before.</p>
      <p>The narwhale seemed motionless. Was it asleep perhaps, weary
from its workday, just riding with the waves? This was our chance,
and Commander Farragut was determined to take full advantage of
it.</p>
      <p>He gave his orders. The <i>Abraham Lincoln</i> stayed at half
steam, advancing cautiously so as not to awaken its adversary. In
midocean it's not unusual to encounter whales so sound asleep they
can successfully be attacked, and Ned Land had harpooned more than
one in its slumber. The Canadian went to resume his post on the
bobstays under the bowsprit.</p>
      <p>The frigate approached without making a sound, stopped two cable
lengths from the animal and coasted. Not a soul breathed on board.
A profound silence reigned over the deck. We were not 100 feet from
the blazing core of light, whose glow grew stronger and dazzled the
eyes.</p>
      <p>Just then, leaning over the forecastle railing, I saw Ned Land
below me, one hand grasping the martingale, the other brandishing
his dreadful harpoon. Barely twenty feet separated him from the
motionless animal.</p>
      <p>All at once his arm shot forward and the harpoon was launched. I
heard the weapon collide resonantly, as if it had hit some hard
substance.</p>
      <p>The electric light suddenly went out, and two enormous
waterspouts crashed onto the deck of the frigate, racing like a
torrent from stem to stern, toppling crewmen, breaking spare masts
and yardarms from their lashings.</p>
      <p>A hideous collision occurred, and thrown over the rail with no
time to catch hold of it, I was hurled into the sea.</p>
   </body>
</topic>