<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<topic id="d2e10884">
   <title>
      <d4pSimpleEnumerator><!--2.10-->Chapter 10. </d4pSimpleEnumerator>
      <ph>The Underwater Coalfields</ph>
   </title>
   <body>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="size_plus_2">THE NEXT DAY</ph>, February 20, I overslept. I
was so exhausted from the night before, I didn't get up until
eleven o'clock. I dressed quickly. I hurried to find out the
<i>Nautilus's</i> heading. The instruments indicated that it was
running southward at a speed of twenty miles per hour and a depth
of 100 meters.</p>
      <p>Conseil entered. I described our nocturnal excursion to him, and
since the panels were open, he could still catch a glimpse of this
submerged continent.</p>
      <p>In fact, the <i>Nautilus</i> was skimming only ten meters over
the soil of these Atlantis plains. The ship scudded along like an
air balloon borne by the wind over some prairie on land; but it
would be more accurate to say that we sat in the lounge as if we
were riding in a coach on an express train. As for the foregrounds
passing before our eyes, they were fantastically carved rocks,
forests of trees that had crossed over from the vegetable kingdom
into the mineral kingdom, their motionless silhouettes sprawling
beneath the waves. There also were stony masses buried beneath
carpets of axidia and sea anemone, bristling with long, vertical
water plants, then strangely contoured blocks of lava that
testified to all the fury of those plutonic developments.</p>
      <p>While this bizarre scenery was glittering under our electric
beams, I told Conseil the story of the Atlanteans, who had inspired
the old French scientist Jean Bailly to write so many
entertaining—albeit utterly fictitious—pages.<fn callout="*">Bailly believed that
Atlantis was located at the North Pole! Ed.</fn> I told the lad about the wars of these
heroic people. I discussed the question of Atlantis with the fervor
of a man who no longer had any doubts. But Conseil was so
distracted he barely heard me, and his lack of interest in any
commentary on this historical topic was soon explained.</p>
      <p>In essence, numerous fish had caught his eye, and when fish pass
by, Conseil vanishes into his world of classifying and leaves real
life behind. In which case I could only tag along and resume our
ichthyological research.</p>
      <p>Even so, these Atlantic fish were not noticeably different from
those we had observed earlier. There were rays of gigantic size,
five meters long and with muscles so powerful they could leap above
the waves, sharks of various species including a fifteen–foot
glaucous shark with sharp triangular teeth and so transparent it
was almost invisible amid the waters, brown lantern sharks,
prism–shaped humantin sharks armored with protuberant hides,
sturgeons resembling their relatives in the Mediterranean,
trumpet–snouted pipefish a foot and a half long, yellowish
brown with small gray fins and no teeth or tongue, unreeling like
slim, supple snakes.</p>
      <p>Among bony fish, Conseil noticed some blackish marlin three
meters long with a sharp sword jutting from the upper jaw,
bright–colored weevers known in Aristotle's day as sea
dragons and whose dorsal stingers make them quite dangerous to pick
up, then dolphinfish with brown backs striped in blue and edged in
gold, handsome dorados, moonlike opahs that look like azure disks
but which the sun's rays turn into spots of silver, finally
eight–meter swordfish from the genus Xiphias, swimming in
schools, sporting yellowish sickle–shaped fins and
six–foot broadswords, stalwart animals, plant eaters rather
than fish eaters, obeying the tiniest signals from their females
like henpecked husbands.</p>
      <p>But while observing these different specimens of marine fauna, I
didn't stop examining the long plains of Atlantis. Sometimes an
unpredictable irregularity in the seafloor would force the
<i>Nautilus</i> to slow down, and then it would glide into the
narrow channels between the hills with a <i>cetacean's</i>
dexterity. If the labyrinth became hopelessly tangled, the
submersible would rise above it like an airship, and after clearing
the obstacle, it would resume its speedy course just a few meters
above the ocean floor. It was an enjoyable and impressive way of
navigating that did indeed recall the maneuvers of an airship ride,
with the major difference that the <i>Nautilus</i> faithfully
obeyed the hands of its helmsman.</p>
      <p>The terrain consisted mostly of thick slime mixed with petrified
branches, but it changed little by little near four o'clock in the
afternoon; it grew rockier and seemed to be strewn with pudding
stones and a basaltic gravel called "tuff," together with bits of
lava and sulfurous obsidian. I expected these long plains to change
into mountain regions, and in fact, as the <i>Nautilus</i> was
executing certain turns, I noticed that the southerly horizon was
blocked by a high wall that seemed to close off every exit. Its
summit obviously poked above the level of the ocean. It had to be a
continent or at least an island, either one of the Canaries or one
of the Cape Verde Islands. Our bearings hadn't been marked on the
chart—perhaps deliberately—and I had no idea what our
position was. In any case this wall seemed to signal the end of
Atlantis, of which, all in all, we had crossed only a small
part.</p>
      <p>Nightfall didn't interrupt my observations. I was left to
myself. Conseil had repaired to his cabin. The <i>Nautilus</i>
slowed down, hovering above the muddled masses on the seafloor,
sometimes grazing them as if wanting to come to rest, sometimes
rising unpredictably to the surface of the waves. Then I glimpsed a
few bright constellations through the crystal waters, specifically
five or six of those zodiacal stars trailing from the tail end of
Orion.</p>
      <p>I would have stayed longer at my window, marveling at these
beauties of sea and sky, but the panels closed. Just then the
<i>Nautilus</i> had arrived at the perpendicular face of that high
wall. How the ship would maneuver I hadn't a guess. I repaired to
my stateroom. The <i>Nautilus</i> did not stir. I fell asleep with
the firm intention of waking up in just a few hours.</p>
      <p>But it was eight o'clock the next day when I returned to the
lounge. I stared at the pressure gauge. It told me that the
<i>Nautilus</i> was afloat on the surface of the ocean.
Furthermore, I heard the sound of footsteps on the platform. Yet
there were no rolling movements to indicate the presence of waves
undulating above me.</p>
      <p>I climbed as far as the hatch. It was open. But instead of the
broad daylight I was expecting, I found that I was surrounded by
total darkness. Where were we? Had I been mistaken? Was it still
night? No! Not one star was twinkling, and nighttime is never so
utterly black.</p>
      <p>I wasn't sure what to think, when a voice said to me:</p>
      <p>"Is that you, Professor?"</p>
      <p>"Ah, Captain Nemo!" I replied. "Where are we?"</p>
      <p>"Underground, Professor."</p>
      <p>"Underground!" I exclaimed. "And the <i>Nautilus</i> is still
floating?"</p>
      <p>"It always floats."</p>
      <p>"But I don't understand!"</p>
      <p>"Wait a little while. Our beacon is about to go on, and if you
want some light on the subject, you'll be satisfied."</p>
      <p>I set foot on the platform and waited. The darkness was so
profound I couldn't see even Captain Nemo. However, looking at the
zenith directly overhead, I thought I caught sight of a feeble
glimmer, a sort of twilight filtering through a circular hole. Just
then the beacon suddenly went on, and its intense brightness made
that hazy light vanish.</p>
      <p>This stream of electricity dazzled my eyes, and after
momentarily shutting them, I looked around. The <i>Nautilus</i> was
stationary. It was floating next to an embankment shaped like a
wharf. As for the water now buoying the ship, it was a lake
completely encircled by an inner wall about two miles in diameter,
hence six miles around. Its level—as indicated by the
pressure gauge—would be the same as the outside level,
because some connection had to exist between this lake and the sea.
Slanting inward over their base, these high walls converged to form
a vault shaped like an immense upside–down funnel that
measured 500 or 600 meters in height. At its summit there gaped the
circular opening through which I had detected that faint glimmer,
obviously daylight.</p>
      <p>Before more carefully examining the interior features of this
enormous cavern, and before deciding if it was the work of nature
or humankind, I went over to Captain Nemo.</p>
      <p>"Where are we?" I said.</p>
      <p>"In the very heart of an extinct volcano," the captain answered
me, "a volcano whose interior was invaded by the sea after some
convulsion in the earth. While you were sleeping, professor, the
<i>Nautilus</i> entered this lagoon through a natural channel that
opens ten meters below the surface of the ocean. This is our home
port, secure, convenient, secret, and sheltered against winds from
any direction! Along the coasts of your continents or islands, show
me any offshore mooring that can equal this safe refuge for
withstanding the fury of hurricanes."</p>
      <p>"Indeed," I replied, "here you're in perfect safety, Captain
Nemo. Who could reach you in the heart of a volcano? But don't I
see an opening at its summit?"</p>
      <p>"Yes, its crater, a crater formerly filled with lava, steam, and
flames, but which now lets in this life–giving air we're
breathing."</p>
      <p>"But which volcanic mountain is this?" I asked.</p>
      <p>"It's one of the many islets with which this sea is strewn. For
ships a mere reef, for us an immense cavern. I discovered it by
chance, and chance served me well."</p>
      <p>"But couldn't someone enter through the mouth of its
crater?"</p>
      <p>"No more than I could exit through it. You can climb about 100
feet up the inner base of this mountain, but then the walls
overhang, they lean too far in to be scaled."</p>
      <p>"I can see, Captain, that nature is your obedient servant, any
time or any place. You're safe on this lake, and nobody else can
visit its waters. But what's the purpose of this refuge? The
<i>Nautilus</i> doesn't need a harbor."</p>
      <p>"No, professor, but it needs electricity to run, batteries to
generate its electricity, sodium to feed its batteries, coal to
make its sodium, and coalfields from which to dig its coal. Now
then, right at this spot the sea covers entire forests that sank
underwater in prehistoric times; today, turned to stone,
transformed into carbon fuel, they offer me inexhaustible coal
mines."</p>
      <p>"So, Captain, your men practice the trade of miners here?"</p>
      <p>"Precisely. These mines extend under the waves like the
coalfields at Newcastle. Here, dressed in diving suits, pick and
mattock in hand, my men go out and dig this carbon fuel for which I
don't need a single mine on land. When I burn this combustible to
produce sodium, the smoke escaping from the mountain's crater gives
it the appearance of a still–active volcano."</p>
      <p>"And will we see your companions at work?"</p>
      <p>"No, at least not this time, because I'm eager to continue our
underwater tour of the world. Accordingly, I'll rest content with
drawing on my reserve stock of sodium. We'll stay here long enough
to load it on board, in other words, a single workday, then we'll
resume our voyage. So, Professor Aronnax, if you'd like to explore
this cavern and circle its lagoon, seize the day."</p>
      <p>I thanked the captain and went to look for my two companions,
who hadn't yet left their cabin. I invited them to follow me, not
telling them where we were.</p>
      <p>They climbed onto the platform. Conseil, whom nothing could
startle, saw it as a perfectly natural thing to fall asleep under
the waves and wake up under a mountain. But Ned Land had no idea in
his head other than to see if this cavern offered some way out.</p>
      <p>After breakfast near ten o'clock, we went down onto the
embankment.</p>
      <p>"So here we are, back on shore," Conseil said.</p>
      <p>"I'd hardly call this shore," the Canadian replied. "And
besides, we aren't on it but under it."</p>
      <p>A sandy beach unfolded before us, measuring 500 feet at its
widest point between the waters of the lake and the foot of the
mountain's walls. Via this strand you could easily circle the lake.
But the base of these high walls consisted of broken soil over
which there lay picturesque piles of volcanic blocks and enormous
pumice stones. All these crumbling masses were covered with an
enamel polished by the action of underground fires, and they
glistened under the stream of electric light from our beacon.
Stirred up by our footsteps, the mica–rich dust on this beach
flew into the air like a cloud of sparks.</p>
      <p>The ground rose appreciably as it moved away from the sand flats
by the waves, and we soon arrived at some long, winding gradients,
genuinely steep paths that allowed us to climb little by little;
but we had to tread cautiously in the midst of pudding stones that
weren't cemented together, and our feet kept skidding on glassy
trachyte, made of feldspar and quartz crystals.</p>
      <p>The volcanic nature of this enormous pit was apparent all around
us. I ventured to comment on it to my companions.</p>
      <p>"Can you picture," I asked them, "what this funnel must have
been like when it was filled with boiling lava, and the level of
that incandescent liquid rose right to the mountain's mouth, like
cast iron up the insides of a furnace?"</p>
      <p>"I can picture it perfectly," Conseil replied. "But will Master
tell me why this huge smelter suspended operations, and how it is
that an oven was replaced by the tranquil waters of a lake?"</p>
      <p>"In all likelihood, Conseil, because some convulsion created an
opening below the surface of the ocean, the opening that serves as
a passageway for the <i>Nautilus</i>. Then the waters of the
Atlantic rushed inside the mountain. There ensued a dreadful
struggle between the elements of fire and water, a struggle ending
in King Neptune's favor. But many centuries have passed since then,
and this submerged volcano has changed into a peaceful cavern."</p>
      <p>"That's fine," Ned Land answered. "I accept the explanation, but
in our personal interests, I'm sorry this opening the professor
mentions wasn't made above sea level."</p>
      <p>"But Ned my friend," Conseil answered, "if it weren't an
underwater passageway, the <i>Nautilus</i> couldn't enter it!"</p>
      <p>"And I might add, Mr. Land," I said, "that the waters wouldn't
have rushed under the mountain, and the volcano would still be a
volcano. So you have nothing to be sorry about."</p>
      <p>Our climb continued. The gradients got steeper and narrower.
Sometimes they were cut across by deep pits that had to be cleared.
Masses of overhanging rock had to be gotten around. You slid on
your knees, you crept on your belly. But helped by the Canadian's
strength and Conseil's dexterity, we overcame every obstacle.</p>
      <p>At an elevation of about thirty meters, the nature of the
terrain changed without becoming any easier. Pudding stones and
trachyte gave way to black basaltic rock: here, lying in slabs all
swollen with blisters; there, shaped like actual prisms and
arranged into a series of columns that supported the springings of
this immense vault, a wonderful sample of natural architecture.
Then, among this basaltic rock, there snaked long, hardened lava
flows inlaid with veins of bituminous coal and in places covered by
wide carpets of sulfur. The sunshine coming through the crater had
grown stronger, shedding a hazy light over all the volcanic waste
forever buried in the heart of this extinct mountain.</p>
      <p>But when we had ascended to an elevation of about 250 feet, we
were stopped by insurmountable obstacles. The converging inside
walls changed into overhangs, and our climb into a circular stroll.
At this topmost level the vegetable kingdom began to challenge the
mineral kingdom. Shrubs, and even a few trees, emerged from
crevices in the walls. I recognized some spurges that let their
caustic, purgative sap trickle out. There were heliotropes, very
remiss at living up to their sun–worshipping reputations
since no sunlight ever reached them; their clusters of flowers
drooped sadly, their colors and scents were faded. Here and there
chrysanthemums sprouted timidly at the feet of aloes with long,
sad, sickly leaves. But between these lava flows I spotted little
violets that still gave off a subtle fragrance, and I confess that
I inhaled it with delight. The soul of a flower is its scent, and
those splendid water plants, flowers of the sea, have no souls!</p>
      <p>We had arrived at the foot of a sturdy clump of dragon trees,
which were splitting the rocks with exertions of their muscular
roots, when Ned Land exclaimed:</p>
      <p>"Oh, sir, a hive!"</p>
      <p>"A hive?" I answered, with a gesture of utter disbelief.</p>
      <p>"Yes, a hive," the Canadian repeated, "with bees buzzing
around!"</p>
      <p>I went closer and was forced to recognize the obvious. At the
mouth of a hole cut in the trunk of a dragon tree, there swarmed
thousands of these ingenious insects so common to all the Canary
Islands, where their output is especially prized.</p>
      <p>Naturally enough, the Canadian wanted to lay in a supply of
honey, and it would have been ill–mannered of me to say no.
He mixed sulfur with some dry leaves, set them on fire with a spark
from his tinderbox, and proceeded to smoke the bees out. Little by
little the buzzing died down and the disemboweled hive yielded
several pounds of sweet honey. Ned Land stuffed his haversack with
it.</p>
      <p>"When I've mixed this honey with our breadfruit batter," he told
us, "I'll be ready to serve you a delectable piece of cake."</p>
      <p>"But of course," Conseil put in, "it will be gingerbread!"</p>
      <p>"I'm all for gingerbread," I said, "but let's resume this
fascinating stroll."</p>
      <p>At certain turns in the trail we were going along, the lake
appeared in its full expanse. The ship's beacon lit up that whole
placid surface, which experienced neither ripples nor undulations.
The <i>Nautilus</i> lay perfectly still. On its platform and on the
embankment, crewmen were bustling around, black shadows that stood
out clearly in the midst of the luminous air.</p>
      <p>Just then we went around the highest ridge of these rocky
foothills that supported the vault. Then I saw that bees weren't
the animal kingdom's only representatives inside this volcano. Here
and in the shadows, birds of prey soared and whirled, flying away
from nests perched on tips of rock. There were sparrow hawks with
white bellies, and screeching kestrels. With all the speed their
stiltlike legs could muster, fine fat bustards scampered over the
slopes. I'll let the reader decide whether the Canadian's appetite
was aroused by the sight of this tasty game, and whether he
regretted having no rifle in his hands. He tried to make stones do
the work of bullets, and after several fruitless attempts, he
managed to wound one of these magnificent bustards. To say he
risked his life twenty times in order to capture this bird is
simply the unadulterated truth; but he fared so well, the animal
went into his sack to join the honeycombs.</p>
      <p>By then we were forced to go back down to the beach because the
ridge had become impossible. Above us, the yawning crater looked
like the wide mouth of a well. From where we stood, the sky was
pretty easy to see, and I watched clouds race by, disheveled by the
west wind, letting tatters of mist trail over the mountain's
summit. Proof positive that those clouds kept at a moderate
altitude, because this volcano didn't rise more than 1,800 feet
above the level of the ocean.</p>
      <p>Half an hour after the Canadian's latest exploits, we were back
on the inner beach. There the local flora was represented by a wide
carpet of samphire, a small <i>umbelliferous</i> plant that keeps
quite nicely, which also boasts the names glasswort, saxifrage, and
sea fennel. Conseil picked a couple bunches. As for the local
fauna, it included thousands of crustaceans of every type:
lobsters, hermit crabs, prawns, mysid shrimps, daddy longlegs, rock
crabs, and a prodigious number of seashells, such as cowries, murex
snails, and limpets.</p>
      <p>In this locality there gaped the mouth of a magnificent cave. My
companions and I took great pleasure in stretching out on its
fine–grained sand. Fire had polished the sparkling enamel of
its inner walls, sprinkled all over with mica–rich dust. Ned
Land tapped these walls and tried to probe their thickness. I
couldn't help smiling. Our conversation then turned to his
everlasting escape plans, and without going too far, I felt I could
offer him this hope: Captain Nemo had gone down south only to
replenish his sodium supplies. So I hoped he would now hug the
coasts of Europe and America, which would allow the Canadian to try
again with a greater chance of success.</p>
      <p>We were stretched out in this delightful cave for an hour. Our
conversation, lively at the outset, then languished. A definite
drowsiness overcame us. Since I saw no good reason to resist the
call of sleep, I fell into a heavy doze. I dreamed—one
doesn't choose his dreams—that my life had been reduced to
the vegetating existence of a simple mollusk. It seemed to me that
this cave made up my double–valved shell. . . .</p>
      <p>Suddenly Conseil's voice startled me awake.</p>
      <p>"Get up! Get up!" shouted the fine lad.</p>
      <p>"What is it?" I asked, in a sitting position.</p>
      <p>"The water's coming up to us!"</p>
      <p>I got back on my feet. Like a torrent the sea was rushing into
our retreat, and since we definitely were not mollusks, we had to
clear out.</p>
      <p>In a few seconds we were safe on top of the cave.</p>
      <p>"What happened?" Conseil asked. "Some new phenomenon?"</p>
      <p>"Not quite, my friends!" I replied. "It was the tide, merely the
tide, which wellnigh caught us by surprise just as it did Sir
Walter Scott's hero! The ocean outside is rising, and by a
perfectly natural law of balance, the level of this lake is also
rising. We've gotten off with a mild dunking. Let's go change
clothes on the <i>Nautilus</i>."</p>
      <p>Three–quarters of an hour later, we had completed our
circular stroll and were back on board. Just then the crewmen
finished loading the sodium supplies, and the <i>Nautilus</i> could
have departed immediately.</p>
      <p>But Captain Nemo gave no orders. Would he wait for nightfall and
exit through his underwater passageway in secrecy? Perhaps.</p>
      <p>Be that as it may, by the next day the <i>Nautilus</i> had left
its home port and was navigating well out from any shore, a few
meters beneath the waves of the Atlantic.</p>
   </body>
</topic>