<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<topic id="d2e14007">
   <title>
      <d4pSimpleEnumerator><!--2.18-->Chapter 18. </d4pSimpleEnumerator>
      <ph>The Devilfish</ph>
   </title>
   <body>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="size_plus_2">FOR SOME DAYS</ph> the <i>Nautilus</i> kept
veering away from the American coast. It obviously didn't want to
frequent the waves of the Gulf of Mexico or the Caribbean Sea. Yet
there was no shortage of water under its keel, since the average
depth of these seas is 1,800 meters; but these waterways, strewn
with islands and plowed by steamers, probably didn't agree with
Captain Nemo.</p>
      <p>On April 16 we raised Martinique and Guadalupe from a distance
of about thirty miles. For one instant I could see their lofty
peaks.</p>
      <p>The Canadian was quite disheartened, having counted on putting
his plans into execution in the gulf, either by reaching shore or
by pulling alongside one of the many boats plying a coastal trade
from one island to another. An escape attempt would have been quite
feasible, assuming Ned Land managed to seize the skiff without the
captain's knowledge. But in midocean it was unthinkable.</p>
      <p>The Canadian, Conseil, and I had a pretty long conversation on
this subject. For six months we had been prisoners aboard the
<i>Nautilus</i>. We had fared 17,000 leagues, and as Ned Land put
it, there was no end in sight. So he made me a proposition I hadn't
anticipated. We were to ask Captain Nemo this question straight
out: did the captain mean to keep us on board his vessel
permanently?</p>
      <p>This measure was distasteful to me. To my mind it would lead
nowhere. We could hope for nothing from the <i>Nautilus's</i>
commander but could depend only on ourselves. Besides, for some
time now the man had been gloomier, more withdrawn, less sociable.
He seemed to be avoiding me. I encountered him only at rare
intervals. He used to take pleasure in explaining the underwater
wonders to me; now he left me to my research and no longer entered
the lounge.</p>
      <p>What changes had come over him? From what cause? I had no reason
to blame myself. Was our presence on board perhaps a burden to him?
Even so, I cherished no hopes that the man would set us free.</p>
      <p>So I begged Ned to let me think about it before taking action.
If this measure proved fruitless, it could arouse the captain's
suspicions, make our circumstances even more arduous, and
jeopardize the Canadian's plans. I might add that I could hardly
use our state of health as an argument. Except for that grueling
ordeal under the Ice Bank at the South Pole, we had never felt
better, neither Ned, Conseil, nor I. The nutritious food,
life–giving air, regular routine, and uniform temperature
kept illness at bay; and for a man who didn't miss his past
existence on land, for a Captain Nemo who was at home here, who
went where he wished, who took paths mysterious to others if not
himself in attaining his ends, I could understand such a life. But
we ourselves hadn't severed all ties with humanity. For my part, I
didn't want my new and unusual research to be buried with my bones.
I had now earned the right to pen the definitive book on the sea,
and sooner or later I wanted that book to see the light of day.</p>
      <p>There once more, through the panels opening into these Caribbean
waters ten meters below the surface of the waves, I found so many
fascinating exhibits to describe in my daily notes! Among other
zoophytes there were Portuguese men–of–war known by the
name <i>Physalia pelagica</i>, like big, oblong bladders with a
pearly sheen, spreading their membranes to the wind, letting their
blue tentacles drift like silken threads; to the eye delightful
jellyfish, to the touch actual nettles that ooze a corrosive
liquid. Among the articulates there were annelid worms one and a
half meters long, furnished with a pink proboscis, equipped with
1,700 organs of locomotion, snaking through the waters, and as they
went, throwing off every gleam in the solar spectrum. From the fish
branch there were manta rays, enormous cartilaginous fish ten feet
long and weighing 600 pounds, their pectoral fin triangular, their
midback slightly arched, their eyes attached to the edges of the
face at the front of the head; they floated like wreckage from a
ship, sometimes fastening onto our windows like opaque shutters.
There were American triggerfish for which nature has ground only
black and white pigments, feather–shaped gobies that were
long and plump with yellow fins and jutting jaws,
sixteen–decimeter mackerel with short, sharp teeth, covered
with small scales, and related to the albacore species. Next came
swarms of red mullet corseted in gold stripes from head to tail,
their shining fins all aquiver, genuine masterpieces of jewelry,
formerly sacred to the goddess Diana, much in demand by rich
Romans, and about which the old saying goes: "He who catches them
doesn't eat them!" Finally, adorned with emerald ribbons and
dressed in velvet and silk, golden angelfish passed before our eyes
like courtiers in the paintings of Veronese; spurred gilthead stole
by with their swift thoracic fins; thread herring fifteen inches
long were wrapped in their phosphorescent glimmers; gray mullet
thrashed the sea with their big fleshy tails; red salmon seemed to
mow the waves with their slicing pectorals; and silver moonfish,
worthy of their name, rose on the horizon of the waters like the
whitish reflections of many moons.</p>
      <p>How many other marvelous new specimens I still could have
observed if, little by little, the <i>Nautilus</i> hadn't settled
to the lower strata! Its slanting fins drew it to depths of 2,000
and 3,500 meters. There animal life was represented by nothing more
than sea lilies, starfish, delightful <i>crinoids</i> with
bell–shaped heads like little chalices on straight stems,
top–shell snails, blood–red tooth shells, and
<i>fissurella</i> snails, a large species of coastal mollusk.</p>
      <p>By April 20 we had risen to an average level of 1,500 meters.
The nearest land was the island group of the Bahamas, scattered
like a batch of cobblestones over the surface of the water. There
high underwater cliffs reared up, straight walls made of craggy
chunks arranged like big stone foundations, among which there gaped
black caves so deep our electric rays couldn't light them to the
far ends.</p>
      <p>These rocks were hung with huge weeds, immense sea tangle,
gigantic <i>fucus</i>—a genuine trellis of water plants fit
for a world of giants.</p>
      <p>In discussing these colossal plants, Conseil, Ned, and I were
naturally led into mentioning the sea's gigantic animals. The
former were obviously meant to feed the latter. However, through
the windows of our almost motionless <i>Nautilus</i>, I could see
nothing among these long filaments other than the chief articulates
of the division <i>Brachyura</i>: long–legged spider crabs,
violet crabs, and sponge crabs unique to the waters of the
Caribbean.</p>
      <p>It was about eleven o'clock when Ned Land drew my attention to a
fearsome commotion out in this huge seaweed.</p>
      <p>"Well," I said, "these are real devilfish caverns, and I
wouldn't be surprised to see some of those monsters
hereabouts."</p>
      <p>"What!" Conseil put in. "Squid, ordinary squid from the class
<i>Cephalopoda</i>?"</p>
      <p>"No," I said, "devilfish of large dimensions. But friend Land is
no doubt mistaken, because I don't see a thing."</p>
      <p>"That's regrettable," Conseil answered. "I'd like to come face
to face with one of those devilfish I've heard so much about, which
can drag ships down into the depths. Those beasts go by the name of
krake—"</p>
      <p>"Fake is more like it," the Canadian replied sarcastically.</p>
      <p>"Krakens!" Conseil shot back, finishing his word without wincing
at his companion's witticism.</p>
      <p>"Nobody will ever make me believe," Ned Land said, "that such
animals exist."</p>
      <p>"Why not?" Conseil replied. "We sincerely believed in Master's
narwhale."</p>
      <p>"We were wrong, Conseil."</p>
      <p>"No doubt, but there are others with no doubts who believe to
this day!"</p>
      <p>"Probably, Conseil. But as for me, I'm bound and determined not
to accept the existence of any such monster till I've dissected it
with my own two hands."</p>
      <p>"Yet," Conseil asked me, "doesn't Master believe in gigantic
devilfish?"</p>
      <p>"Yikes! Who in Hades ever believed in them?" the Canadian
exclaimed.</p>
      <p>"Many people, Ned my friend," I said.</p>
      <p>"No fishermen. Scientists maybe!"</p>
      <p>"Pardon me, Ned. Fishermen and scientists!"</p>
      <p>"Why, I to whom you speak," Conseil said with the world's
straightest face, "I recall perfectly seeing a large boat dragged
under the waves by the arms of a <i>cephalopod</i>."</p>
      <p>"You saw that?" the Canadian asked.</p>
      <p>"Yes, Ned."</p>
      <p>"With your own two eyes?"</p>
      <p>"With my own two eyes."</p>
      <p>"Where, may I ask?"</p>
      <p>"In Saint–Malo," Conseil returned unflappably.</p>
      <p>"In the harbor?" Ned Land said sarcastically.</p>
      <p>"No, in a church," Conseil replied.</p>
      <p>"In a church!" the Canadian exclaimed.</p>
      <p>"Yes, Ned my friend. It had a picture that portrayed the
devilfish in question."</p>
      <p>"Oh good!" Ned Land exclaimed with a burst of laughter. "Mr.
Conseil put one over on me!"</p>
      <p>"Actually he's right," I said. "I've heard about that picture.
But the subject it portrays is taken from a legend, and you know
how to rate legends in matters of natural history! Besides, when
it's an issue of monsters, the human imagination always tends to
run wild. People not only claimed these devilfish could drag ships
under, but a certain Olaus Magnus tells of a <i>cephalopod</i> a
mile long that looked more like an island than an animal. There's
also the story of how the Bishop of Trondheim set up an altar one
day on an immense rock. After he finished saying mass, this rock
started moving and went back into the sea. The rock was a
devilfish."</p>
      <p>"And that's everything we know?" the Canadian asked.</p>
      <p>"No," I replied, "another bishop, Pontoppidan of Bergen, also
tells of a devilfish so large a whole cavalry regiment could
maneuver on it."</p>
      <p>"They sure did go on, those oldtime bishops!" Ned Land said.</p>
      <p>"Finally, the naturalists of antiquity mention some monsters
with mouths as big as a gulf, which were too huge to get through
the Strait of Gibraltar."</p>
      <p>"Good work, men!" the Canadian put in.</p>
      <p>"But in all these stories, is there any truth?" Conseil
asked.</p>
      <p>"None at all, my friends, at least in those that go beyond the
bounds of credibility and fly off into fable or legend. Yet for the
imaginings of these storytellers there had to be, if not a cause,
at least an excuse. It can't be denied that some species of squid
and other devilfish are quite large, though still smaller than
<i>cetaceans</i>. Aristotle put the dimensions of one squid at five
cubits, or 3.1 meters. Our fishermen frequently see specimens over
1.8 meters long. The museums in Trieste and Montpellier have
preserved some devilfish carcasses measuring two meters. Besides,
according to the calculations of naturalists, one of these animals
only six feet long would have tentacles as long as
twenty–seven. Which is enough to make a fearsome
monster."</p>
      <p>"Does anybody fish for 'em nowadays?" the Canadian asked.</p>
      <p>"If they don't fish for them, sailors at least sight them. A
friend of mine, Captain Paul Bos of Le Havre, has often sworn to me
that he encountered one of these monsters of colossal size in the
seas of the East Indies. But the most astonishing event, which
proves that these gigantic animals undeniably exist, took place a
few years ago in 1861."</p>
      <p>"What event was that?" Ned Land asked.</p>
      <p>"Just this. In 1861, to the northeast of Tenerife and fairly
near the latitude where we are right now, the crew of the gunboat
<i>Alecto</i> spotted a monstrous squid swimming in their waters.
Commander Bouguer approached the animal and attacked it with blows
from harpoons and blasts from rifles, but without much success
because bullets and harpoons crossed its soft flesh as if it were
semiliquid jelly. After several fruitless attempts, the crew
managed to slip a noose around the mollusk's body. This noose slid
as far as the caudal fins and came to a halt. Then they tried to
haul the monster on board, but its weight was so considerable that
when they tugged on the rope, the animal parted company with its
tail; and deprived of this adornment, it disappeared beneath the
waters."</p>
      <p>"Finally, an actual event," Ned Land said.</p>
      <p>"An indisputable event, my gallant Ned. Accordingly, people have
proposed naming this devilfish Bouguer's Squid."</p>
      <p>"And how long was it?" the Canadian asked.</p>
      <p>"Didn't it measure about six meters?" said Conseil, who was
stationed at the window and examining anew the crevices in the
cliff.</p>
      <p>"Precisely," I replied.</p>
      <p>"Wasn't its head," Conseil went on, "crowned by eight tentacles
that quivered in the water like a nest of snakes?"</p>
      <p>"Precisely."</p>
      <p>"Weren't its eyes prominently placed and considerably
enlarged?"</p>
      <p>"Yes, Conseil."</p>
      <p>"And wasn't its mouth a real parrot's beak but of fearsome
size?"</p>
      <p>"Correct, Conseil."</p>
      <p>"Well, with all due respect to Master," Conseil replied
serenely, "if this isn't Bouguer's Squid, it's at least one of his
close relatives!"</p>
      <p>I stared at Conseil. Ned Land rushed to the window.</p>
      <p>"What an awful animal!" he exclaimed.</p>
      <p>I stared in my turn and couldn't keep back a movement of
revulsion. Before my eyes there quivered a horrible monster worthy
of a place among the most farfetched teratological legends.</p>
      <p>It was a squid of colossal dimensions, fully eight meters long.
It was traveling backward with tremendous speed in the same
direction as the <i>Nautilus</i>. It gazed with enormous, staring
eyes that were tinted sea green. Its eight arms (or more
accurately, feet) were rooted in its head, which has earned these
animals the name <i>cephalopod</i>; its arms stretched a distance
twice the length of its body and were writhing like the serpentine
hair of the Furies. You could plainly see its 250 suckers, arranged
over the inner sides of its tentacles and shaped like semispheric
capsules. Sometimes these suckers fastened onto the lounge window
by creating vacuums against it. The monster's mouth—a beak
made of horn and shaped like that of a parrot—opened and
closed vertically. Its tongue, also of horn substance and armed
with several rows of sharp teeth, would flicker out from between
these genuine shears. What a freak of nature! A bird's beak on a
mollusk! Its body was spindle–shaped and swollen in the
middle, a fleshy mass that must have weighed 20,000 to 25,000
kilograms. Its unstable color would change with tremendous speed as
the animal grew irritated, passing successively from bluish gray to
reddish brown.</p>
      <p>What was irritating this mollusk? No doubt the presence of the
<i>Nautilus</i>, even more fearsome than itself, and which it
couldn't grip with its mandibles or the suckers on its arms. And
yet what monsters these devilfish are, what vitality our Creator
has given them, what vigor in their movements, thanks to their
owning a triple heart!</p>
      <p>Sheer chance had placed us in the presence of this squid, and I
didn't want to lose this opportunity to meticulously study such a
<i>cephalopod</i> specimen. I overcame the horror that its
appearance inspired in me, picked up a pencil, and began to sketch
it.</p>
      <p>"Perhaps this is the same as the <i>Alecto's</i>," Conseil
said.</p>
      <p>"Can't be," the Canadian replied, "because this one's complete
while the other one lost its tail!"</p>
      <p>"That doesn't necessarily follow," I said. "The arms and tails
of these animals grow back through regeneration, and in seven years
the tail on Bouguer's Squid has surely had time to sprout
again."</p>
      <p>"Anyhow," Ned shot back, "if it isn't this fellow, maybe it's
one of those!"</p>
      <p>Indeed, other devilfish had appeared at the starboard window. I
counted seven of them. They provided the <i>Nautilus</i> with an
escort, and I could hear their beaks gnashing on the
sheet–iron hull. We couldn't have asked for a more devoted
following.</p>
      <p>I continued sketching. These monsters kept pace in our waters
with such precision, they seemed to be standing still, and I could
have traced their outlines in miniature on the window. But we were
moving at a moderate speed.</p>
      <p>All at once the <i>Nautilus</i> stopped. A jolt made it tremble
through its entire framework.</p>
      <p>"Did we strike bottom?" I asked.</p>
      <p>"In any event we're already clear," the Canadian replied,
"because we're afloat."</p>
      <p>The <i>Nautilus</i> was certainly afloat, but it was no longer
in motion. The blades of its propeller weren't churning the waves.
A minute passed. Followed by his chief officer, Captain Nemo
entered the lounge.</p>
      <p>I hadn't seen him for a good while. He looked gloomy to me.
Without speaking to us, without even seeing us perhaps, he went to
the panel, stared at the devilfish, and said a few words to his
chief officer.</p>
      <p>The latter went out. Soon the panels closed. The ceiling lit
up.</p>
      <p>I went over to the captain.</p>
      <p>"An unusual assortment of devilfish," I told him, as carefree as
a collector in front of an aquarium.</p>
      <p>"Correct, Mr. Naturalist," he answered me, "and we're going to
fight them at close quarters."</p>
      <p>I gaped at the captain. I thought my hearing had gone bad.</p>
      <p>"At close quarters?" I repeated.</p>
      <p>"Yes, sir. Our propeller is jammed. I think the
horn–covered mandibles of one of these squid are entangled in
the blades. That's why we aren't moving."</p>
      <p>"And what are you going to do?"</p>
      <p>"Rise to the surface and slaughter the vermin."</p>
      <p>"A difficult undertaking."</p>
      <p>"Correct. Our electric bullets are ineffective against such soft
flesh, where they don't meet enough resistance to go off. But we'll
attack the beasts with axes."</p>
      <p>"And harpoons, sir," the Canadian said, "if you don't turn down
my help."</p>
      <p>"I accept it, Mr. Land."</p>
      <p>"We'll go with you," I said. And we followed Captain Nemo,
heading to the central companionway.</p>
      <p>There some ten men were standing by for the assault, armed with
boarding axes. Conseil and I picked up two more axes. Ned Land
seized a harpoon.</p>
      <p>By then the <i>Nautilus</i> had returned to the surface of the
waves. Stationed on the top steps, one of the seamen undid the
bolts of the hatch. But he had scarcely unscrewed the nuts when the
hatch flew up with tremendous violence, obviously pulled open by
the suckers on a devilfish's arm.</p>
      <p>Instantly one of those long arms glided like a snake into the
opening, and twenty others were quivering above. With a sweep of
the ax, Captain Nemo chopped off this fearsome tentacle, which slid
writhing down the steps.</p>
      <p>Just as we were crowding each other to reach the platform, two
more arms lashed the air, swooped on the seaman stationed in front
of Captain Nemo, and carried the fellow away with irresistible
violence.</p>
      <p>Captain Nemo gave a shout and leaped outside. We rushed after
him.</p>
      <p>What a scene! Seized by the tentacle and glued to its suckers,
the unfortunate man was swinging in the air at the mercy of this
enormous appendage. He gasped, he choked, he yelled: "Help! Help!"
These words, pronounced in French, left me deeply stunned! So I had
a fellow countryman on board, perhaps several! I'll hear his
harrowing plea the rest of my life!</p>
      <p>The poor fellow was done for. Who could tear him from such a
powerful grip? Even so, Captain Nemo rushed at the devilfish and
with a sweep of the ax hewed one more of its arms. His chief
officer struggled furiously with other monsters crawling up the
<i>Nautilus's</i> sides. The crew battled with flailing axes. The
Canadian, Conseil, and I sank our weapons into these fleshy masses.
An intense, musky odor filled the air. It was horrible.</p>
      <p>For an instant I thought the poor man entwined by the devilfish
might be torn loose from its powerful suction. Seven arms out of
eight had been chopped off. Brandishing its victim like a feather,
one lone tentacle was writhing in the air. But just as Captain Nemo
and his chief officer rushed at it, the animal shot off a spout of
blackish liquid, secreted by a pouch located in its abdomen. It
blinded us. When this cloud had dispersed, the squid was gone, and
so was my poor fellow countryman!</p>
      <p>What rage then drove us against these monsters! We lost all
self–control. Ten or twelve devilfish had overrun the
<i>Nautilus's</i> platform and sides. We piled helter–skelter
into the thick of these sawed–off snakes, which darted over
the platform amid waves of blood and sepia ink. It seemed as if
these viscous tentacles grew back like the many heads of Hydra. At
every thrust Ned Land's harpoon would plunge into a squid's
sea–green eye and burst it. But my daring companion was
suddenly toppled by the tentacles of a monster he could not
avoid.</p>
      <p>Oh, my heart nearly exploded with excitement and horror! The
squid's fearsome beak was wide open over Ned Land. The poor man was
about to be cut in half. I ran to his rescue. But Captain Nemo got
there first. His ax disappeared between the two enormous mandibles,
and the Canadian, miraculously saved, stood and plunged his harpoon
all the way into the devilfish's triple heart.</p>
      <p>"Tit for tat," Captain Nemo told the Canadian. "I owed it to
myself!"</p>
      <p>Ned bowed without answering him.</p>
      <p>This struggle had lasted a quarter of an hour. Defeated,
mutilated, battered to death, the monsters finally yielded to us
and disappeared beneath the waves.</p>
      <p>Red with blood, motionless by the beacon, Captain Nemo stared at
the sea that had swallowed one of his companions, and large tears
streamed from his eyes.</p>
   </body>
</topic>