<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<topic id="d2e11496">
   <title>
      <d4pSimpleEnumerator><!--2.12-->Chapter 12. </d4pSimpleEnumerator>
      <ph>Sperm Whales and Baleen Whales</ph>
   </title>
   <body>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="size_plus_2">DURING THE NIGHT</ph> of March 13–14,
the <i>Nautilus</i> resumed its southward heading. Once it was
abreast of Cape Horn, I thought it would strike west of the cape,
make for Pacific seas, and complete its tour of the world. It did
nothing of the sort and kept moving toward the southernmost
regions. So where was it bound? The pole? That was insanity. I was
beginning to think that the captain's recklessness more than
justified Ned Land's worst fears.</p>
      <p>For a good while the Canadian had said nothing more to me about
his escape plans. He had become less sociable, almost sullen. I
could see how heavily this protracted imprisonment was weighing on
him. I could feel the anger building in him. Whenever he
encountered the captain, his eyes would flicker with dark fire, and
I was in constant dread that his natural vehemence would cause him
to do something rash.</p>
      <p>That day, March 14, he and Conseil managed to find me in my
stateroom. I asked them the purpose of their visit.</p>
      <p>"To put a simple question to you, sir," the Canadian answered
me.</p>
      <p>"Go on, Ned."</p>
      <p>"How many men do you think are on board the
<i>Nautilus</i>?"</p>
      <p>"I'm unable to say, my friend."</p>
      <p>"It seems to me," Ned Land went on, "that it wouldn't take much
of a crew to run a ship like this one."</p>
      <p>"Correct," I replied. "Under existing conditions some ten men at
the most should be enough to operate it."</p>
      <p>"All right," the Canadian said, "then why should there be any
more than that?"</p>
      <p>"Why?" I answered.</p>
      <p>I stared at Ned Land, whose motives were easy to guess.</p>
      <p>"Because," I said, "if I can trust my hunches, if I truly
understand the captain's way of life, his <i>Nautilus</i> isn't
simply a ship. It's meant to be a refuge for people like its
commander, people who have severed all ties with the shore."</p>
      <p>"Perhaps," Conseil said, "but in a nutshell, the <i>Nautilus</i>
can hold only a certain number of men, so couldn't Master estimate
their maximum?"</p>
      <p>"How, Conseil?"</p>
      <p>"By calculating it. Master is familiar with the ship's capacity,
hence the amount of air it contains; on the other hand, Master
knows how much air each man consumes in the act of breathing, and
he can compare this data with the fact that the <i>Nautilus</i>
must rise to the surface every twenty–four hours . . ."</p>
      <p>Conseil didn't finish his sentence, but I could easily see what
he was driving at.</p>
      <p>"I follow you," I said. "But while they're simple to do, such
calculations can give only a very uncertain figure."</p>
      <p>"No problem," the Canadian went on insistently.</p>
      <p>"Then here's how to calculate it," I replied. "In one hour each
man consumes the oxygen contained in 100 liters of air, hence
during twenty–four hours the oxygen contained in 2,400
liters. Therefore, we must look for the multiple of 2,400 liters of
air that gives us the amount found in the <i>Nautilus</i>."</p>
      <p>"Precisely," Conseil said.</p>
      <p>"Now then," I went on, "the <i>Nautilus's</i> capacity is 1,500
metric tons, and that of a ton is 1,000 liters, so the
<i>Nautilus</i> holds 1,500,000 liters of air, which, divided by
2,400 . . ."</p>
      <p>I did a quick pencil calculation.</p>
      <p>". . . gives us the quotient of 625. Which is tantamount to
saying that the air contained in the <i>Nautilus</i> would be
exactly enough for 625 men over twenty–four hours."</p>
      <p>"625!" Ned repeated.</p>
      <p>"But rest assured," I added, "that between passengers, seamen,
or officers, we don't total one–tenth of that figure."</p>
      <p>"Which is still too many for three men!" Conseil muttered.</p>
      <p>"So, my poor Ned, I can only counsel patience."</p>
      <p>"And," Conseil replied, "even more than patience,
resignation."</p>
      <p>Conseil had said the true word.</p>
      <p>"Even so," he went on, "Captain Nemo can't go south forever!
He'll surely have to stop, if only at the Ice Bank, and he'll
return to the seas of civilization! Then it will be time to resume
Ned Land's plans."</p>
      <p>The Canadian shook his head, passed his hand over his brow, made
no reply, and left us.</p>
      <p>"With Master's permission, I'll make an observation to him,"
Conseil then told me. "Our poor Ned broods about all the things he
can't have. He's haunted by his former life. He seems to miss
everything that's denied us. He's obsessed by his old memories and
it's breaking his heart. We must understand him. What does he have
to occupy him here? Nothing. He isn't a scientist like Master, and
he doesn't share our enthusiasm for the sea's wonders. He would
risk anything just to enter a tavern in his own country!"</p>
      <p>To be sure, the monotony of life on board must have seemed
unbearable to the Canadian, who was accustomed to freedom and
activity. It was a rare event that could excite him. That day,
however, a development occurred that reminded him of his happy
years as a harpooner.</p>
      <p>Near eleven o'clock in the morning, while on the surface of the
ocean, the <i>Nautilus</i> fell in with a herd of baleen whales.
This encounter didn't surprise me, because I knew these animals
were being hunted so relentlessly that they took refuge in the
ocean basins of the high latitudes.</p>
      <p>In the maritime world and in the realm of geographic
exploration, whales have played a major role. This is the animal
that first dragged the Basques in its wake, then Asturian
Spaniards, Englishmen, and Dutchmen, emboldening them against the
ocean's perils, and leading them to the ends of the earth. Baleen
whales like to frequent the southernmost and northernmost seas. Old
legends even claim that these <i>cetaceans</i> led fishermen to
within a mere seven leagues of the North Pole. Although this feat
is fictitious, it will someday come true, because it's likely that
by hunting whales in the Arctic or Antarctic regions, man will
finally reach this unknown spot on the globe.</p>
      <p>We were seated on the platform next to a tranquil sea. The month
of March, since it's the equivalent of October in these latitudes,
was giving us some fine autumn days. It was the Canadian—on
this topic he was never mistaken—who sighted a baleen whale
on the eastern horizon. If you looked carefully, you could see its
blackish back alternately rise and fall above the waves, five miles
from the <i>Nautilus</i>.</p>
      <p>"Wow!" Ned Land exclaimed. "If I were on board a whaler, there's
an encounter that would be great fun! That's one big animal! Look
how high its blowholes are spouting all that air and steam!
Damnation! Why am I chained to this hunk of sheet iron!"</p>
      <p>"Why, Ned!" I replied. "You still aren't over your old fishing
urges?"</p>
      <p>"How could a whale fisherman forget his old trade, sir? Who
could ever get tired of such exciting hunting?"</p>
      <p>"You've never fished these seas, Ned?"</p>
      <p>"Never, sir. Just the northernmost seas, equally in the Bering
Strait and the Davis Strait."</p>
      <p>"So the southern right whale is still unknown to you. Until now
it's the bowhead whale you've hunted, and it won't risk going past
the warm waters of the equator."</p>
      <p>"Oh, professor, what are you feeding me?" the Canadian answered
in a tolerably skeptical tone.</p>
      <p>"I'm feeding you the facts."</p>
      <p>"By thunder! In '65, just two and a half years ago, I to whom
you speak, I myself stepped onto the carcass of a whale near
Greenland, and its flank still carried the marked harpoon of a
whaling ship from the Bering Sea. Now I ask you, after it had been
wounded west of America, how could this animal be killed in the
east, unless it had cleared the equator and doubled Cape Horn or
the Cape of Good Hope?"</p>
      <p>"I agree with our friend Ned," Conseil said, "and I'm waiting to
hear how Master will reply to him."</p>
      <p>"Master will reply, my friends, that baleen whales are
localized, according to species, within certain seas that they
never leave. And if one of these animals went from the Bering
Strait to the Davis Strait, it's quite simply because there's some
passageway from the one sea to the other, either along the coasts
of Canada or Siberia."</p>
      <p>"You expect us to fall for that?" the Canadian asked, tipping me
a wink.</p>
      <p>"If Master says so," Conseil replied.</p>
      <p>"Which means," the Canadian went on, "since I've never fished
these waterways, I don't know the whales that frequent them?"</p>
      <p>"That's what I've been telling you, Ned."</p>
      <p>"All the more reason to get to know them," Conseil answered.</p>
      <p>"Look! Look!" the Canadian exclaimed, his voice full of
excitement. "It's approaching! It's coming toward us! It's thumbing
its nose at me! It knows I can't do a blessed thing to it!"</p>
      <p>Ned stamped his foot. Brandishing an imaginary harpoon, his
hands positively trembled.</p>
      <p>"These <i>cetaceans</i>," he asked, "are they as big as the ones
in the northernmost seas?"</p>
      <p>"Pretty nearly, Ned."</p>
      <p>"Because I've seen big baleen whales, sir, whales measuring up
to 100 feet long! I've even heard that those rorqual whales off the
Aleutian Islands sometimes get over 150 feet."</p>
      <p>"That strikes me as exaggerated," I replied. "Those animals are
only members of the genus <i>Balaenoptera</i> furnished with dorsal
fins, and like sperm whales, they're generally smaller than the
bowhead whale."</p>
      <p>"Oh!" exclaimed the Canadian, whose eyes hadn't left the ocean.
"It's getting closer, it's coming into the <i>Nautilus's</i>
waters!"</p>
      <p>Then, going on with his conversation:</p>
      <p>"You talk about sperm whales," he said, "as if they were little
beasts! But there are stories of gigantic sperm whales. They're
shrewd <i>cetaceans</i>. I hear that some will cover themselves
with algae and fucus plants. People mistake them for islets. They
pitch camp on top, make themselves at home, light a
fire—"</p>
      <p>"Build houses," Conseil said.</p>
      <p>"Yes, funny man," Ned Land replied. "Then one fine day the
animal dives and drags all its occupants down into the depths."</p>
      <p>"Like in the voyages of Sinbad the Sailor," I answered,
laughing. "Oh, Mr. Land, you're addicted to tall tales! What sperm
whales you're handing us! I hope you don't really believe in
them!"</p>
      <p>"Mr. Naturalist," the Canadian replied in all seriousness, "when
it comes to whales, you can believe anything! (Look at that one
move! Look at it stealing away!) People claim these animals can
circle around the world in just fifteen days."</p>
      <p>"I don't say nay."</p>
      <p>"But what you undoubtedly don't know, Professor Aronnax, is that
at the beginning of the world, whales traveled even quicker."</p>
      <p>"Oh really, Ned! And why so?"</p>
      <p>"Because in those days their tails moved side to side, like
those on fish, in other words, their tails were straight up,
thrashing the water from left to right, right to left. But spotting
that they swam too fast, our Creator twisted their tails, and ever
since they've been thrashing the waves up and down, at the expense
of their speed."</p>
      <p>"Fine, Ned," I said, then resurrected one of the Canadian's
expressions. "You expect us to fall for that?"</p>
      <p>"Not too terribly," Ned Land replied, "and no more than if I
told you there are whales that are 300 feet long and weigh
1,000,000 pounds."</p>
      <p>"That's indeed considerable," I said. "But you must admit that
certain <i>cetaceans</i> do grow to significant size, since they're
said to supply as much as 120 metric tons of oil."</p>
      <p>"That I've seen," the Canadian said.</p>
      <p>"I can easily believe it, Ned, just as I can believe that
certain baleen whales equal 100 elephants in bulk. Imagine the
impact of such a mass if it were launched at full speed!"</p>
      <p>"Is it true," Conseil asked, "that they can sink ships?"</p>
      <p>"Ships? I doubt it," I replied. "However, they say that in 1820,
right in these southern seas, a baleen whale rushed at the
<i>Essex</i> and pushed it backward at a speed of four meters per
second. Its stern was flooded, and the <i>Essex</i> went down
fast."</p>
      <p>Ned looked at me with a bantering expression.</p>
      <p>"Speaking for myself," he said, "I once got walloped by a
whale's tail—in my longboat, needless to say. My companions
and I were launched to an altitude of six meters. But next to the
Professor's whale, mine was just a baby."</p>
      <p>"Do these animals live a long time?" Conseil asked.</p>
      <p>"A thousand years," the Canadian replied without hesitation.</p>
      <p>"And how, Ned," I asked, "do you know that's so?"</p>
      <p>"Because people say so."</p>
      <p>"And why do people say so?"</p>
      <p>"Because people know so."</p>
      <p>"No, Ned! People don't know so, they suppose so, and here's the
logic with which they back up their beliefs. When fishermen first
hunted whales 400 years ago, these animals grew to bigger sizes
than they do today. Reasonably enough, it's assumed that today's
whales are smaller because they haven't had time to reach their
full growth. That's why the Count de Buffon's encyclopedia says
that <i>cetaceans</i> can live, and even must live, for a thousand
years. You understand?"</p>
      <p>Ned Land didn't understand. He no longer even heard me. That
baleen whale kept coming closer. His eyes devoured it.</p>
      <p>"Oh!" he exclaimed. "It's not just one whale, it's ten, twenty,
a whole gam! And I can't do a thing! I'm tied hand and foot!"</p>
      <p>"But Ned my friend," Conseil said, "why not ask Captain Nemo for
permission to hunt—"</p>
      <p>Before Conseil could finish his sentence, Ned Land scooted down
the hatch and ran to look for the captain. A few moments later, the
two of them reappeared on the platform.</p>
      <p>Captain Nemo observed the herd of <i>cetaceans</i> cavorting on
the waters a mile from the <i>Nautilus</i>.</p>
      <p>"They're southern right whales," he said. "There goes the
fortune of a whole whaling fleet."</p>
      <p>"Well, sir," the Canadian asked, "couldn't I hunt them, just so
I don't forget my old harpooning trade?"</p>
      <p>"Hunt them? What for?" Captain Nemo replied. "Simply to destroy
them? We have no use for whale oil on this ship."</p>
      <p>"But, sir," the Canadian went on, "in the Red Sea you authorized
us to chase a dugong!"</p>
      <p>"There it was an issue of obtaining fresh meat for my crew. Here
it would be killing for the sake of killing. I'm well aware that's
a privilege reserved for mankind, but I don't allow such murderous
pastimes. When your peers, Mr. Land, destroy decent, harmless
creatures like the southern right whale or the bowhead whale, they
commit a reprehensible offense. Thus they've already depopulated
all of Baffin Bay, and they'll wipe out a whole class of useful
animals. So leave these poor <i>cetaceans</i> alone. They have
quite enough natural enemies, such as sperm whales, swordfish, and
sawfish, without you meddling with them."</p>
      <p>I'll let the reader decide what faces the Canadian made during
this lecture on hunting ethics. Furnishing such arguments to a
professional harpooner was a waste of words. Ned Land stared at
Captain Nemo and obviously missed his meaning. But the captain was
right. Thanks to the mindless, barbaric bloodthirstiness of
fishermen, the last baleen whale will someday disappear from the
ocean.</p>
      <p>Ned Land whistled "Yankee Doodle" between his teeth, stuffed his
hands in his pockets, and turned his back on us.</p>
      <p>Meanwhile Captain Nemo studied the herd of <i>cetaceans</i>,
then addressed me:</p>
      <p>"I was right to claim that baleen whales have enough natural
enemies without counting man. These specimens will soon have to
deal with mighty opponents. Eight miles to leeward, Professor
Aronnax, can you see those blackish specks moving about?"</p>
      <p>"Yes, Captain," I replied.</p>
      <p>"Those are sperm whales, dreadful animals that I've sometimes
encountered in herds of 200 or 300! As for them, they're cruel,
destructive beasts, and they deserve to be exterminated."</p>
      <p>The Canadian turned swiftly at these last words.</p>
      <p>"Well, Captain," I said, "on behalf of the baleen whales,
there's still time—"</p>
      <p>"It's pointless to run any risks, professor. The <i>Nautilus</i>
will suffice to disperse these sperm whales. It's armed with a
steel spur quite equal to Mr. Land's harpoon, I imagine."</p>
      <p>The Canadian didn't even bother shrugging his shoulders.
Attacking <i>cetaceans</i> with thrusts from a spur! Who ever heard
of such malarkey!</p>
      <p>"Wait and see, Professor Aronnax," Captain Nemo said. "We'll
show you a style of hunting with which you aren't yet familiar.
We'll take no pity on these ferocious <i>cetaceans</i>. They're
merely mouth and teeth!"</p>
      <p>Mouth and teeth! There's no better way to describe the
long–skulled sperm whale, whose length sometimes exceeds
twenty–five meters. The enormous head of this <i>cetacean</i>
occupies about a third of its body. Better armed than a baleen
whale, whose upper jaw is adorned solely with whalebone, the sperm
whale is equipped with twenty–five huge teeth that are twenty
centimeters high, have cylindrical, conical summits, and weigh two
pounds each. In the top part of this enormous head, inside big
cavities separated by cartilage, you'll find 300 to 400 kilograms
of that valuable oil called "spermaceti." The sperm whale is an
awkward animal, more tadpole than fish, as Professor Frédol
has noted. It's poorly constructed, being "defective," so to speak,
over the whole left side of its frame, with good eyesight only in
its right eye.</p>
      <p>Meanwhile that monstrous herd kept coming closer. It had seen
the baleen whales and was preparing to attack. You could tell in
advance that the sperm whales would be victorious, not only because
they were better built for fighting than their harmless
adversaries, but also because they could stay longer underwater
before returning to breathe at the surface.</p>
      <p>There was just time to run to the rescue of the baleen whales.
The <i>Nautilus</i> proceeded to midwater. Conseil, Ned, and I sat
in front of the lounge windows. Captain Nemo made his way to the
helmsman's side to operate his submersible as an engine of
destruction. Soon I felt the beats of our propeller getting faster,
and we picked up speed.</p>
      <p>The battle between sperm whales and baleen whales had already
begun when the <i>Nautilus</i> arrived. It maneuvered to cut into
the herd of long–skulled predators. At first the latter
showed little concern at the sight of this new monster meddling in
the battle. But they soon had to sidestep its thrusts.</p>
      <p>What a struggle! Ned Land quickly grew enthusiastic and even
ended up applauding. Brandished in its captain's hands, the
<i>Nautilus</i> was simply a fearsome harpoon. He hurled it at
those fleshy masses and ran them clean through, leaving behind two
squirming animal halves. As for those daunting strokes of the tail
hitting our sides, the ship never felt them. No more than the
collisions it caused. One sperm whale exterminated, it ran at
another, tacked on the spot so as not to miss its prey, went ahead
or astern, obeyed its rudder, dived when the <i>cetacean</i> sank
to deeper strata, rose with it when it returned to the surface,
struck it head–on or slantwise, hacked at it or tore it, and
from every direction and at any speed, skewered it with its
dreadful spur.</p>
      <p>What bloodshed! What a hubbub on the surface of the waves! What
sharp hisses and snorts unique to these frightened animals! Their
tails churned the normally peaceful strata into actual billows.</p>
      <p>This Homeric slaughter dragged on for an hour, and the
long–skulled predators couldn't get away. Several times ten
or twelve of them teamed up, trying to crush the <i>Nautilus</i>
with their sheer mass. Through the windows you could see their
enormous mouths paved with teeth, their fearsome eyes. Losing all
self–control, Ned Land hurled threats and insults at them.
You could feel them clinging to the submersible like hounds atop a
wild boar in the underbrush. But by forcing the pace of its
propeller, the <i>Nautilus</i> carried them off, dragged them
under, or brought them back to the upper level of the waters,
untroubled by their enormous weight or their powerful grip.</p>
      <p>Finally this mass of sperm whales thinned out. The waves grew
tranquil again. I felt us rising to the surface of the ocean. The
hatch opened and we rushed onto the platform.</p>
      <p>The sea was covered with mutilated corpses. A fearsome explosion
couldn't have slashed, torn, or shredded these fleshy masses with
greater violence. We were floating in the midst of gigantic bodies,
bluish on the back, whitish on the belly, and all deformed by
enormous protuberances. A few frightened sperm whales were fleeing
toward the horizon. The waves were dyed red over an area of several
miles, and the <i>Nautilus</i> was floating in the middle of a sea
of blood.</p>
      <p>Captain Nemo rejoined us.</p>
      <p>"Well, Mr. Land?" he said.</p>
      <p>"Well, sir," replied the Canadian, whose enthusiasm had
subsided, "it's a dreadful sight for sure. But I'm a hunter not a
butcher, and this is plain butchery."</p>
      <p>"It was a slaughter of destructive animals," the captain
replied, "and the <i>Nautilus</i> is no butcher knife."</p>
      <p>"I prefer my harpoon," the Canadian answered.</p>
      <p>"To each his own," the captain replied, staring intently at Ned
Land.</p>
      <p>I was in dread the latter would give way to some violent
outburst that might have had deplorable consequences. But his anger
was diverted by the sight of a baleen whale that the
<i>Nautilus</i> had pulled alongside of just then.</p>
      <p>This animal had been unable to escape the teeth of those sperm
whales. I recognized the southern right whale, its head squat, its
body dark all over. Anatomically, it's distinguished from the white
whale and the black right whale by the fusion of its seven cervical
vertebrae, and it numbers two more ribs than its relatives.
Floating on its side, its belly riddled with bites, the poor
<i>cetacean</i> was dead. Still hanging from the tip of its
mutilated fin was a little baby whale that it had been unable to
rescue from the slaughter. Its open mouth let water flow through
its whalebone like a murmuring surf.</p>
      <p>Captain Nemo guided the <i>Nautilus</i> next to the animal's
corpse. Two of his men climbed onto the whale's flank, and to my
astonishment, I saw them draw from its udders all the milk they
held, in other words, enough to fill two or three casks.</p>
      <p>The captain offered me a cup of this still–warm milk. I
couldn't help showing my distaste for such a beverage. He assured
me that this milk was excellent, no different from cow's milk.</p>
      <p>I sampled it and agreed. So this milk was a worthwhile reserve
ration for us, because in the form of salt butter or cheese, it
would provide a pleasant change of pace from our standard fare.</p>
      <p>From that day on, I noted with some uneasiness that Ned Land's
attitudes toward Captain Nemo grew worse and worse, and I decided
to keep a close watch on the Canadian's movements and
activities.</p>
   </body>
</topic>