<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<topic id="d2e15073">
   <title>
      <d4pSimpleEnumerator><!--2.21-->Chapter 21. </d4pSimpleEnumerator>
      <ph>A Mass Execution</ph>
   </title>
   <body>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="size_plus_2">THE WAY HE SAID THIS</ph>, the unexpectedness
of this scene, first the biography of this patriotic ship, then the
excitement with which this eccentric individual pronounced these
last words—the name <i>Avenger</i> whose significance could
not escape me—all this, taken together, had a profound impact
on my mind. My eyes never left the captain. Hands outstretched
toward the sea, he contemplated the proud wreck with blazing eyes.
Perhaps I would never learn who he was, where he came from or where
he was heading, but more and more I could see a distinction between
the man and the scientist. It was no ordinary misanthropy that kept
Captain Nemo and his companions sequestered inside the
<i>Nautilus's</i> plating, but a hate so monstrous or so sublime
that the passing years could never weaken it.</p>
      <p>Did this hate also hunger for vengeance? Time would soon
tell.</p>
      <p>Meanwhile the <i>Nautilus</i> rose slowly to the surface of the
sea, and I watched the <i>Avenger's</i> murky shape disappearing
little by little. Soon a gentle rolling told me that we were afloat
in the open air.</p>
      <p>Just then a hollow explosion was audible. I looked at the
captain. The captain did not stir.</p>
      <p>"Captain?" I said.</p>
      <p>He didn't reply.</p>
      <p>I left him and climbed onto the platform. Conseil and the
Canadian were already there.</p>
      <p>"What caused that explosion?" I asked.</p>
      <p>"A cannon going off," Ned Land replied.</p>
      <p>I stared in the direction of the ship I had spotted. It was
heading toward the <i>Nautilus</i>, and you could tell it had put
on steam. Six miles separated it from us.</p>
      <p>"What sort of craft is it, Ned?"</p>
      <p>"From its rigging and its low masts," the Canadian replied, "I
bet it's a warship. Here's hoping it pulls up and sinks this damned
<i>Nautilus</i>!"</p>
      <p>"Ned my friend," Conseil replied, "what harm could it do the
<i>Nautilus</i>? Will it attack us under the waves? Will it
cannonade us at the bottom of the sea?"</p>
      <p>"Tell me, Ned," I asked, "can you make out the nationality of
that craft?"</p>
      <p>Creasing his brow, lowering his lids, and puckering the corners
of his eyes, the Canadian focused the full power of his gaze on the
ship for a short while.</p>
      <p>"No, sir," he replied. "I can't make out what nation it's from.
It's flying no flag. But I'll swear it's a warship, because there's
a long pennant streaming from the peak of its mainmast."</p>
      <p>For a quarter of an hour, we continued to watch the craft
bearing down on us. But it was inconceivable to me that it had
discovered the <i>Nautilus</i> at such a distance, still less that
it knew what this underwater machine really was.</p>
      <p>Soon the Canadian announced that the craft was a big battleship,
a double–decker ironclad complete with ram. Dark, dense smoke
burst from its two funnels. Its furled sails merged with the lines
of its yardarms. The gaff of its fore–and–aft sail flew
no flag. Its distance still kept us from distinguishing the colors
of its pennant, which was fluttering like a thin ribbon.</p>
      <p>It was coming on fast. If Captain Nemo let it approach, a chance
for salvation might be available to us.</p>
      <p>"Sir," Ned Land told me, "if that boat gets within a mile of us,
I'm jumping overboard, and I suggest you follow suit."</p>
      <p>I didn't reply to the Canadian's proposition but kept watching
the ship, which was looming larger on the horizon. Whether it was
English, French, American, or Russian, it would surely welcome us
aboard if we could just get to it.</p>
      <p>"Master may recall," Conseil then said, "that we have some
experience with swimming. He can rely on me to tow him to that
vessel, if he's agreeable to going with our friend Ned."</p>
      <p>Before I could reply, white smoke streamed from the battleship's
bow. Then, a few seconds later, the waters splashed astern of the
<i>Nautilus</i>, disturbed by the fall of a heavy object. Soon
after, an explosion struck my ears.</p>
      <p>"What's this? They're firing at us!" I exclaimed.</p>
      <p>"Good lads!" the Canadian muttered.</p>
      <p>"That means they don't see us as castaways clinging to some
wreckage!"</p>
      <p>"With all due respect to Master—gracious!" Conseil put in,
shaking off the water that had sprayed over him from another shell.
"With all due respect to master, they've discovered the narwhale
and they're cannonading the same."</p>
      <p>"But it must be clear to them," I exclaimed, "that they're
dealing with human beings."</p>
      <p>"Maybe that's why!" Ned Land replied, staring hard at me.</p>
      <p>The full truth dawned on me. Undoubtedly people now knew where
they stood on the existence of this so–called monster.
Undoubtedly the latter's encounter with the <i>Abraham Lincoln</i>,
when the Canadian hit it with his harpoon, had led Commander
Farragut to recognize the narwhale as actually an underwater boat,
more dangerous than any unearthly <i>cetacean</i>!</p>
      <p>Yes, this had to be the case, and undoubtedly they were now
chasing this dreadful engine of destruction on every sea!</p>
      <p>Dreadful indeed, if, as we could assume, Captain Nemo had been
using the <i>Nautilus</i> in works of vengeance! That night in the
middle of the Indian Ocean, when he imprisoned us in the cell,
hadn't he attacked some ship? That man now buried in the coral
cemetery, wasn't he the victim of some collision caused by the
<i>Nautilus</i>? Yes, I repeat: this had to be the case. One part
of Captain Nemo's secret life had been unveiled. And now, even
though his identity was still unknown, at least the nations allied
against him knew they were no longer hunting some fairy–tale
monster, but a man who had sworn an implacable hate toward
them!</p>
      <p>This whole fearsome sequence of events appeared in my mind's
eye. Instead of encountering friends on this approaching ship, we
would find only pitiless enemies.</p>
      <p>Meanwhile shells fell around us in increasing numbers. Some,
meeting the liquid surface, would ricochet and vanish into the sea
at considerable distances. But none of them reached the
<i>Nautilus</i>.</p>
      <p>By then the ironclad was no more than three miles off. Despite
its violent cannonade, Captain Nemo hadn't appeared on the
platform. And yet if one of those conical shells had scored a
routine hit on the <i>Nautilus's</i> hull, it could have been fatal
to him.</p>
      <p>The Canadian then told me:</p>
      <p>"Sir, we've got to do everything we can to get out of this jam!
Let's signal them! Damnation! Maybe they'll realize we're decent
people!"</p>
      <p>Ned Land pulled out his handkerchief to wave it in the air. But
he had barely unfolded it when he was felled by an iron fist, and
despite his great strength, he tumbled to the deck.</p>
      <p>"Scum!" the captain shouted. "Do you want to be nailed to the
<i>Nautilus's</i> spur before it charges that ship?"</p>
      <p>Dreadful to hear, Captain Nemo was even more dreadful to see.
His face was pale from some spasm of his heart, which must have
stopped beating for an instant. His pupils were hideously
contracted. His voice was no longer speaking, it was bellowing.
Bending from the waist, he shook the Canadian by the shoulders.</p>
      <p>Then, dropping Ned and turning to the battleship, whose shells
were showering around him:</p>
      <p>"O ship of an accursed nation, you know who I am!" he shouted in
his powerful voice. "And I don't need your colors to recognize you!
Look! I'll show you mine!"</p>
      <p>And in the bow of the platform, Captain Nemo unfurled a black
flag, like the one he had left planted at the South Pole.</p>
      <p>Just then a shell hit the <i>Nautilus's</i> hull obliquely,
failed to breach it, ricocheted near the captain, and vanished into
the sea.</p>
      <p>Captain Nemo shrugged his shoulders. Then, addressing me:</p>
      <p>"Go below!" he told me in a curt tone. "You and your companions,
go below!"</p>
      <p>"Sir," I exclaimed, "are you going to attack this ship?"</p>
      <p>"Sir, I'm going to sink it."</p>
      <p>"You wouldn't!"</p>
      <p>"I will," Captain Nemo replied icily. "You're ill–advised
to pass judgment on me, sir. Fate has shown you what you weren't
meant to see. The attack has come. Our reply will be dreadful. Get
back inside!"</p>
      <p>"From what country is that ship?"</p>
      <p>"You don't know? Fine, so much the better! At least its
nationality will remain a secret to you. Go below!"</p>
      <p>The Canadian, Conseil, and I could only obey. Some fifteen of
the <i>Nautilus's</i> seamen surrounded their captain and stared
with a feeling of implacable hate at the ship bearing down on them.
You could feel the same spirit of vengeance enkindling their every
soul.</p>
      <p>I went below just as another projectile scraped the
<i>Nautilus's</i> hull, and I heard the captain exclaim:</p>
      <lq>
         <p>"Shoot, you demented vessel! Shower your futile shells! You
won't escape the <i>Nautilus's</i> spur! But this isn't the place
where you'll perish! I don't want your wreckage mingling with that
of the <i>Avenger</i>!"</p>
      </lq>
      <p>I repaired to my stateroom. The captain and his chief officer
stayed on the platform. The propeller was set in motion. The
<i>Nautilus</i> swiftly retreated, putting us outside the range of
the vessel's shells. But the chase continued, and Captain Nemo was
content to keep his distance.</p>
      <p>Near four o'clock in the afternoon, unable to control the
impatience and uneasiness devouring me, I went back to the central
companionway. The hatch was open. I ventured onto the platform. The
captain was still strolling there, his steps agitated. He stared at
the ship, which stayed to his leeward five or six miles off. He was
circling it like a wild beast, drawing it eastward, letting it
chase after him. Yet he didn't attack. Was he, perhaps, still
undecided?</p>
      <p>I tried to intervene one last time. But I had barely queried
Captain Nemo when the latter silenced me:</p>
      <p>"I'm the law, I'm the tribunal! I'm the oppressed, and there are
my oppressors! Thanks to them, I've witnessed the destruction of
everything I loved, cherished, and venerated—homeland, wife,
children, father, and mother! There lies everything I hate! Not
another word out of you!"</p>
      <p>I took a last look at the battleship, which was putting on
steam. Then I rejoined Ned and Conseil.</p>
      <p>"We'll escape!" I exclaimed.</p>
      <p>"Good," Ned put in. "Where's that ship from?"</p>
      <p>"I've no idea. But wherever it's from, it will sink before
nightfall. In any event, it's better to perish with it than be
accomplices in some act of revenge whose merits we can't
gauge."</p>
      <p>"That's my feeling," Ned Land replied coolly. "Let's wait for
nightfall."</p>
      <p>Night fell. A profound silence reigned on board. The compass
indicated that the <i>Nautilus</i> hadn't changed direction. I
could hear the beat of its propeller, churning the waves with
steady speed. Staying on the surface of the water, it rolled
gently, sometimes to one side, sometimes to the other.</p>
      <p>My companions and I had decided to escape as soon as the vessel
came close enough for us to be heard—or seen, because the
moon would wax full in three days and was shining brightly. Once we
were aboard that ship, if we couldn't ward off the blow that
threatened it, at least we could do everything that circumstances
permitted. Several times I thought the <i>Nautilus</i> was about to
attack. But it was content to let its adversary approach, and then
it would quickly resume its retreating ways.</p>
      <p>Part of the night passed without incident. We kept watch for an
opportunity to take action. We talked little, being too keyed up.
Ned Land was all for jumping overboard. I forced him to wait. As I
saw it, the <i>Nautilus</i> would attack the double–decker on
the surface of the waves, and then it would be not only possible
but easy to escape.</p>
      <p>At three o'clock in the morning, full of uneasiness, I climbed
onto the platform. Captain Nemo hadn't left it. He stood in the bow
next to his flag, which a mild breeze was unfurling above his head.
His eyes never left that vessel. The extraordinary intensity of his
gaze seemed to attract it, beguile it, and draw it more surely than
if he had it in tow!</p>
      <p>The moon then passed its zenith. Jupiter was rising in the east.
In the midst of this placid natural setting, sky and ocean competed
with each other in tranquility, and the sea offered the orb of
night the loveliest mirror ever to reflect its image.</p>
      <p>And when I compared this deep calm of the elements with all the
fury seething inside the plating of this barely perceptible
<i>Nautilus</i>, I shivered all over.</p>
      <p>The vessel was two miles off. It drew nearer, always moving
toward the phosphorescent glow that signaled the <i>Nautilus's</i>
presence. I saw its green and red running lights, plus the white
lantern hanging from the large stay of its foremast. Hazy
flickerings were reflected on its rigging and indicated that its
furnaces were pushed to the limit. Showers of sparks and cinders of
flaming coal escaped from its funnels, spangling the air with
stars.</p>
      <p>I stood there until six o'clock in the morning, Captain Nemo
never seeming to notice me. The vessel lay a mile and a half off,
and with the first glimmers of daylight, it resumed its cannonade.
The time couldn't be far away when the <i>Nautilus</i> would attack
its adversary, and my companions and I would leave forever this man
I dared not judge.</p>
      <p>I was about to go below to alert them, when the chief officer
climbed onto the platform. Several seamen were with him. Captain
Nemo didn't see them, or didn't want to see them. They carried out
certain procedures that, on the <i>Nautilus</i>, you could call
"clearing the decks for action." They were quite simple. The
manropes that formed a handrail around the platform were lowered.
Likewise the pilothouse and the beacon housing were withdrawn into
the hull until they lay exactly flush with it. The surface of this
long sheet–iron cigar no longer offered a single protrusion
that could hamper its maneuvers.</p>
      <p>I returned to the lounge. The <i>Nautilus</i> still emerged
above the surface. A few morning gleams infiltrated the liquid
strata. Beneath the undulations of the billows, the windows were
enlivened by the blushing of the rising sun. That dreadful day of
June 2 had dawned.</p>
      <p>At seven o'clock the log told me that the <i>Nautilus</i> had
reduced speed. I realized that it was letting the warship approach.
Moreover, the explosions grew more intensely audible. Shells
furrowed the water around us, drilling through it with an odd
hissing sound.</p>
      <p>"My friends," I said, "it's time. Let's shake hands, and may God
be with us!"</p>
      <p>Ned Land was determined, Conseil calm, I myself nervous and
barely in control.</p>
      <p>We went into the library. Just as I pushed open the door leading
to the well of the central companionway, I heard the hatch close
sharply overhead.</p>
      <p>The Canadian leaped up the steps, but I stopped him. A
well–known hissing told me that water was entering the ship's
ballast tanks. Indeed, in a few moments the <i>Nautilus</i> had
submerged some meters below the surface of the waves.</p>
      <p>I understood this maneuver. It was too late to take action. The
<i>Nautilus</i> wasn't going to strike the double–decker
where it was clad in impenetrable iron armor, but below its
waterline, where the metal carapace no longer protected its
planking.</p>
      <p>We were prisoners once more, unwilling spectators at the
performance of this gruesome drama. But we barely had time to
think. Taking refuge in my stateroom, we stared at each other
without pronouncing a word. My mind was in a total daze. My mental
processes came to a dead stop. I hovered in that painful state that
predominates during the period of anticipation before some
frightful explosion. I waited, I listened, I lived only through my
sense of hearing!</p>
      <p>Meanwhile the <i>Nautilus's</i> speed had increased appreciably.
So it was gathering momentum. Its entire hull was vibrating.</p>
      <p>Suddenly I let out a yell. There had been a collision, but it
was comparatively mild. I could feel the penetrating force of the
steel spur. I could hear scratchings and scrapings. Carried away
with its driving power, the <i>Nautilus</i> had passed through the
vessel's mass like a sailmaker's needle through canvas!</p>
      <p>I couldn't hold still. Frantic, going insane, I leaped out of my
stateroom and rushed into the lounge.</p>
      <p>Captain Nemo was there. Mute, gloomy, implacable, he was staring
through the port panel.</p>
      <p>An enormous mass was sinking beneath the waters, and the
<i>Nautilus</i>, missing none of its death throes, was descending
into the depths with it. Ten meters away, I could see its gaping
hull, into which water was rushing with a sound of thunder, then
its double rows of cannons and railings. Its deck was covered with
dark, quivering shadows.</p>
      <p>The water was rising. Those poor men leaped up into the shrouds,
clung to the masts, writhed beneath the waters. It was a human
anthill that an invading sea had caught by surprise!</p>
      <p>Paralyzed, rigid with anguish, my hair standing on end, my eyes
popping out of my head, short of breath, suffocating, speechless, I
stared—I too! I was glued to the window by an irresistible
allure!</p>
      <p>The enormous vessel settled slowly. Following it down, the
<i>Nautilus</i> kept watch on its every movement. Suddenly there
was an eruption. The air compressed inside the craft sent its decks
flying, as if the powder stores had been ignited. The thrust of the
waters was so great, the <i>Nautilus</i> swerved away.</p>
      <p>The poor ship then sank more swiftly. Its mastheads appeared,
laden with victims, then its crosstrees bending under clusters of
men, finally the peak of its mainmast. Then the dark mass
disappeared, and with it a crew of corpses dragged under by
fearsome eddies. . . .</p>
      <p>I turned to Captain Nemo. This dreadful executioner, this true
archangel of hate, was still staring. When it was all over, Captain
Nemo headed to the door of his stateroom, opened it, and entered. I
followed him with my eyes.</p>
      <p>On the rear paneling, beneath the portraits of his heroes, I saw
the portrait of a still–youthful woman with two little
children. Captain Nemo stared at them for a few moments, stretched
out his arms to them, sank to his knees, and melted into sobs.</p>
   </body>
</topic>