<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<topic id="d2e1150">
   <title>
      <d4pSimpleEnumerator><!--1.4-->Chapter 4. </d4pSimpleEnumerator>
      <ph>Ned Land</ph>
   </title>
   <body>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="size_plus_2">COMMANDER FARRAGUT</ph> was a good seaman,
worthy of the frigate he commanded. His ship and he were one. He
was its very soul. On the <i>cetacean</i> question no doubts arose
in his mind, and he didn't allow the animal's existence to be
disputed aboard his vessel. He believed in it as certain pious
women believe in the leviathan from the Book of Job—out of
faith, not reason. The monster existed, and he had vowed to rid the
seas of it. The man was a sort of Knight of Rhodes, a
latter–day Sir Dieudonné of Gozo, on his way to fight
an encounter with the dragon devastating the island. Either
Commander Farragut would slay the narwhale, or the narwhale would
slay Commander Farragut. No middle of the road for these two.</p>
      <p>The ship's officers shared the views of their leader. They could
be heard chatting, discussing, arguing, calculating the different
chances of an encounter, and observing the vast expanse of the
ocean. Voluntary watches from the crosstrees of the topgallant sail
were self–imposed by more than one who would have cursed such
toil under any other circumstances. As often as the sun swept over
its daily arc, the masts were populated with sailors whose feet
itched and couldn't hold still on the planking of the deck below!
And the <i>Abraham Lincoln's</i> stempost hadn't even cut the
suspected waters of the Pacific.</p>
      <p>As for the crew, they only wanted to encounter the unicorn,
harpoon it, haul it on board, and carve it up. They surveyed the
sea with scrupulous care. Besides, Commander Farragut had mentioned
that a certain sum of $2,000.00 was waiting for the man who first
sighted the animal, be he cabin boy or sailor, mate or officer.
I'll let the reader decide whether eyes got proper exercise aboard
the <i>Abraham Lincoln</i>.</p>
      <p>As for me, I didn't lag behind the others and I yielded to no
one my share in these daily observations. Our frigate would have
had fivescore good reasons for renaming itself the <i>Argus</i>,
after that mythological beast with 100 eyes! The lone rebel among
us was Conseil, who seemed utterly uninterested in the question
exciting us and was out of step with the general enthusiasm on
board.</p>
      <p>As I said, Commander Farragut had carefully equipped his ship
with all the gear needed to fish for a gigantic <i>cetacean</i>. No
whaling vessel could have been better armed. We had every known
mechanism, from the hand–hurled harpoon, to the blunderbuss
firing barbed arrows, to the duck gun with exploding bullets. On
the forecastle was mounted the latest model breech–loading
cannon, very heavy of barrel and narrow of bore, a weapon that
would figure in the Universal Exhibition of 1867. Made in America,
this valuable instrument could fire a four–kilogram conical
projectile an average distance of sixteen kilometers without the
least bother.</p>
      <p>So the <i>Abraham Lincoln</i> wasn't lacking in means of
destruction. But it had better still. It had Ned Land, the King of
Harpooners.</p>
      <p>Gifted with uncommon manual ability, Ned Land was a Canadian who
had no equal in his dangerous trade. Dexterity, coolness, bravery,
and cunning were virtues he possessed to a high degree, and it took
a truly crafty baleen whale or an exceptionally astute sperm whale
to elude the thrusts of his harpoon.</p>
      <p>Ned Land was about forty years old. A man of great
height—over six English feet—he was powerfully built,
serious in manner, not very sociable, sometimes headstrong, and
quite ill–tempered when crossed. His looks caught the
attention, and above all the strength of his gaze, which gave a
unique emphasis to his facial appearance.</p>
      <p>Commander Farragut, to my thinking, had made a wise move in
hiring on this man. With his eye and his throwing arm, he was worth
the whole crew all by himself. I can do no better than to compare
him with a powerful telescope that could double as a cannon always
ready to fire.</p>
      <p>To say Canadian is to say French, and as unsociable as Ned Land
was, I must admit he took a definite liking to me. No doubt it was
my nationality that attracted him. It was an opportunity for him to
speak, and for me to hear, that old Rabelaisian dialect still used
in some Canadian provinces. The harpooner's family originated in
Quebec, and they were already a line of bold fishermen back in the
days when this town still belonged to France.</p>
      <p>Little by little Ned developed a taste for chatting, and I loved
hearing the tales of his adventures in the polar seas. He described
his fishing trips and his battles with great natural lyricism. His
tales took on the form of an epic poem, and I felt I was hearing
some Canadian Homer reciting his <i>Iliad</i> of the High Arctic
regions.</p>
      <p>I'm writing of this bold companion as I currently know him.
Because we've become old friends, united in that permanent
comradeship born and cemented during only the most frightful
crises! Ah, my gallant Ned! I ask only to live 100 years more, the
longer to remember you!</p>
      <p>And now, what were Ned Land's views on this question of a marine
monster? I must admit that he flatly didn't believe in the unicorn,
and alone on board, he didn't share the general conviction. He
avoided even dealing with the subject, for which one day I felt
compelled to take him to task.</p>
      <p>During the magnificent evening of June 25—in other words,
three weeks after our departure—the frigate lay abreast of
Cabo Blanco, thirty miles to leeward of the coast of Patagonia. We
had crossed the Tropic of Capricorn, and the Strait of Magellan
opened less than 700 miles to the south. Before eight days were
out, the <i>Abraham Lincoln</i> would plow the waves of the
Pacific.</p>
      <p>Seated on the afterdeck, Ned Land and I chatted about one thing
and another, staring at that mysterious sea whose depths to this
day are beyond the reach of human eyes. Quite naturally, I led our
conversation around to the giant unicorn, and I weighed our
expedition's various chances for success or failure. Then, seeing
that Ned just let me talk without saying much himself, I pressed
him more closely.</p>
      <p>"Ned," I asked him, "how can you still doubt the reality of this
<i>cetacean</i> we're after? Do you have any particular reasons for
being so skeptical?"</p>
      <p>The harpooner stared at me awhile before replying, slapped his
broad forehead in one of his standard gestures, closed his eyes as
if to collect himself, and finally said:</p>
      <p>"Just maybe, Professor Aronnax."</p>
      <p>"But Ned, you're a professional whaler, a man familiar with all
the great marine mammals—your mind should easily accept this
hypothesis of an enormous <i>cetacean</i>, and you ought to be the
last one to doubt it under these circumstances!"</p>
      <p>"That's just where you're mistaken, professor," Ned replied.
"The common man may still believe in fabulous comets crossing outer
space, or in prehistoric monsters living at the earth's core, but
astronomers and geologists don't swallow such fairy tales. It's the
same with whalers. I've chased plenty of <i>cetaceans</i>, I've
harpooned a good number, I've killed several. But no matter how
powerful and well armed they were, neither their tails or their
tusks could puncture the sheet–iron plates of a steamer."</p>
      <p>"Even so, Ned, people mention vessels that narwhale tusks have
run clean through."</p>
      <p>"Wooden ships maybe," the Canadian replied. "But I've never seen
the like. So till I have proof to the contrary, I'll deny that
baleen whales, sperm whales, or unicorns can do any such
thing."</p>
      <p>"Listen to me, Ned—"</p>
      <p>"No, no, professor. I'll go along with anything you want except
that. Some gigantic devilfish maybe . . . ?"</p>
      <p>"Even less likely, Ned. The devilfish is merely a mollusk, and
even this name hints at its semiliquid flesh, because it's Latin
meaning, 'soft one.' The devilfish doesn't belong to the vertebrate
branch, and even if it were 500 feet long, it would still be
utterly harmless to ships like the <i>Scotia</i> or the <i>Abraham
Lincoln</i>. Consequently, the feats of krakens or other monsters
of that ilk must be relegated to the realm of fiction."</p>
      <p>"So, Mr. Naturalist," Ned Land continued in a bantering tone,
"you'll just keep on believing in the existence of some enormous
<i>cetacean</i> . . . ?"</p>
      <p>"Yes, Ned, I repeat it with a conviction backed by factual
logic. I believe in the existence of a mammal with a powerful
constitution, belonging to the vertebrate branch like baleen
whales, sperm whales, or dolphins, and armed with a tusk made of
horn that has tremendous penetrating power."</p>
      <p>"Humph!" the harpooner put in, shaking his head with the
attitude of a man who doesn't want to be convinced.</p>
      <p>"Note well, my fine Canadian," I went on, "if such an animal
exists, if it lives deep in the ocean, if it frequents the liquid
strata located miles beneath the surface of the water, it needs to
have a constitution so solid, it defies all comparison."</p>
      <p>"And why this powerful constitution?" Ned asked.</p>
      <p>"Because it takes incalculable strength just to live in those
deep strata and withstand their pressure."</p>
      <p>"Oh really?" Ned said, tipping me a wink.</p>
      <p>"Oh really, and I can prove it to you with a few simple
figures."</p>
      <p>"Bosh!" Ned replied. "You can make figures do anything you
want!"</p>
      <p>"In business, Ned, but not in mathematics. Listen to me. Let's
accept that the pressure of one atmosphere is represented by the
pressure of a column of water thirty–two feet high. In
reality, such a column of water wouldn't be quite so high because
here we're dealing with salt water, which is denser than fresh
water. Well then, when you dive under the waves, Ned, for every
thirty–two feet of water above you, your body is tolerating
the pressure of one more atmosphere, in other words, one more
kilogram per each square centimeter on your body's surface. So it
follows that at 320 feet down, this pressure is equal to ten
atmospheres, to 100 atmospheres at 3,200 feet, and to 1,000
atmospheres at 32,000 feet, that is, at about two and a half
vertical leagues down. Which is tantamount to saying that if you
could reach such a depth in the ocean, each square centimeter on
your body's surface would be experiencing 1,000 kilograms of
pressure. Now, my gallant Ned, do you know how many square
centimeters you have on your bodily surface?"</p>
      <p>"I haven't the foggiest notion, Professor Aronnax."</p>
      <p>"About 17,000."</p>
      <p>"As many as that?"</p>
      <p>"Yes, and since the atmosphere's pressure actually weighs
slightly more than one kilogram per square centimeter, your 17,000
square centimeters are tolerating 17,568 kilograms at this very
moment."</p>
      <p>"Without my noticing it?"</p>
      <p>"Without your noticing it. And if you aren't crushed by so much
pressure, it's because the air penetrates the interior of your body
with equal pressure. When the inside and outside pressures are in
perfect balance, they neutralize each other and allow you to
tolerate them without discomfort. But in the water it's another
story."</p>
      <p>"Yes, I see," Ned replied, growing more interested. "Because the
water surrounds me but doesn't penetrate me."</p>
      <p>"Precisely, Ned. So at thirty–two feet beneath the surface
of the sea, you'll undergo a pressure of 17,568 kilograms; at 320
feet, or ten times greater pressure, it's 175,680 kilograms; at
3,200 feet, or 100 times greater pressure, it's 1,756,800
kilograms; finally, at 32,000 feet, or 1,000 times greater
pressure, it's 17,568,000 kilograms; in other words, you'd be
squashed as flat as if you'd just been yanked from between the
plates of a hydraulic press!"</p>
      <p>"Fire and brimstone!" Ned put in.</p>
      <p>"All right then, my fine harpooner, if vertebrates several
hundred meters long and proportionate in bulk live at such depths,
their surface areas make up millions of square centimeters, and the
pressure they undergo must be assessed in billions of kilograms.
Calculate, then, how much resistance of bone structure and strength
of constitution they'd need in order to withstand such
pressures!"</p>
      <p>"They'd need to be manufactured," Ned Land replied, "from
sheet–iron plates eight inches thick, like ironclad
frigates."</p>
      <p>"Right, Ned, and then picture the damage such a mass could
inflict if it were launched with the speed of an express train
against a ship's hull."</p>
      <p>"Yes . . . indeed . . . maybe," the Canadian replied, staggered
by these figures but still not willing to give in.</p>
      <p>"Well, have I convinced you?"</p>
      <p>"You've convinced me of one thing, Mr. Naturalist. That deep in
the sea, such animals would need to be just as strong as you
say—if they exist."</p>
      <p>"But if they don't exist, my stubborn harpooner, how do you
explain the accident that happened to the <i>Scotia</i>?"</p>
      <p>"It's maybe . . . ," Ned said, hesitating.</p>
      <p>"Go on!"</p>
      <p>"Because . . . it just couldn't be true!" the Canadian replied,
unconsciously echoing a famous catchphrase of the scientist
Arago.</p>
      <p>But this reply proved nothing, other than how bullheaded the
harpooner could be. That day I pressed him no further. The
<i>Scotia's</i> accident was undeniable. Its hole was real enough
that it had to be plugged up, and I don't think a hole's existence
can be more emphatically proven. Now then, this hole didn't make
itself, and since it hadn't resulted from underwater rocks or
underwater machines, it must have been caused by the perforating
tool of some animal.</p>
      <p>Now, for all the reasons put forward to this point, I believed
that this animal was a member of the branch <i>Vertebrata</i>,
class <i>Mammalia</i>, group <i>Pisciforma</i>, and finally, order
<i>Cetacea</i>. As for the family in which it would be placed
(baleen whale, sperm whale, or dolphin), the genus to which it
belonged, and the species in which it would find its proper home,
these questions had to be left for later. To answer them called for
dissecting this unknown monster; to dissect it called for catching
it; to catch it called for harpooning it—which was Ned Land's
business; to harpoon it called for sighting it—which was the
crew's business; and to sight it called for encountering
it—which was a chancy business.</p>
   </body>
</topic>