<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<topic id="d2e2316">
   <title>
      <d4pSimpleEnumerator><!--1.8-->Chapter 8. </d4pSimpleEnumerator>
      <ph>"Mobilis in Mobili"</ph>
   </title>
   <body>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="size_plus_2">THIS BRUTALLY EXECUTED</ph> capture was
carried out with lightning speed. My companions and I had no time
to collect ourselves. I don't know how they felt about being shoved
inside this aquatic prison, but as for me, I was shivering all
over. With whom were we dealing? Surely with some new breed of
pirates, exploiting the sea after their own fashion.</p>
      <p>The narrow hatch had barely closed over me when I was surrounded
by profound darkness. Saturated with the outside light, my eyes
couldn't make out a thing. I felt my naked feet clinging to the
steps of an iron ladder. Forcibly seized, Ned Land and Conseil were
behind me. At the foot of the ladder, a door opened and instantly
closed behind us with a loud clang.</p>
      <p>We were alone. Where? I couldn't say, could barely even imagine.
All was darkness, but such utter darkness that after several
minutes, my eyes were still unable to catch a single one of those
hazy gleams that drift through even the blackest nights.</p>
      <p>Meanwhile, furious at these goings on, Ned Land gave free rein
to his indignation.</p>
      <p>"Damnation!" he exclaimed. "These people are about as hospitable
as the savages of New Caledonia! All that's lacking is for them to
be cannibals! I wouldn't be surprised if they were, but believe you
me, they won't eat me without my kicking up a protest!"</p>
      <p>"Calm yourself, Ned my friend," Conseil replied serenely. "Don't
flare up so quickly! We aren't in a kettle yet!"</p>
      <p>"In a kettle, no," the Canadian shot back, "but in an oven for
sure. It's dark enough for one. Luckily my Bowie knife hasn't left
me, and I can still see well enough to put it to use.<fn callout="*">Author's Note: A Bowie
knife is a wide–bladed dagger that Americans are forever
carrying around.</fn> The first one of these bandits who lays a
hand on me—"</p>
      <p>"Don't be so irritable, Ned," I then told the harpooner, "and
don't ruin things for us with pointless violence. Who knows whether
they might be listening to us? Instead, let's try to find out where
we are!"</p>
      <p>I started moving, groping my way. After five steps I encountered
an iron wall made of riveted boilerplate. Then, turning around, I
bumped into a wooden table next to which several stools had been
set. The floor of this prison lay hidden beneath thick, hempen
matting that deadened the sound of footsteps. Its naked walls
didn't reveal any trace of a door or window. Going around the
opposite way, Conseil met up with me, and we returned to the middle
of this cabin, which had to be twenty feet long by ten wide. As for
its height, not even Ned Land, with his great stature, was able to
determine it.</p>
      <p>Half an hour had already gone by without our situation changing,
when our eyes were suddenly spirited from utter darkness into
blinding light. Our prison lit up all at once; in other words, it
filled with luminescent matter so intense that at first I couldn't
stand the brightness of it. From its glare and whiteness, I
recognized the electric glow that had played around this underwater
boat like some magnificent phosphorescent phenomenon. After
involuntarily closing my eyes, I reopened them and saw that this
luminous force came from a frosted half globe curving out of the
cabin's ceiling.</p>
      <p>"Finally! It's light enough to see!" Ned Land exclaimed, knife
in hand, staying on the defensive.</p>
      <p>"Yes," I replied, then ventured the opposite view. "But as for
our situation, we're still in the dark."</p>
      <p>"Master must learn patience," said the emotionless Conseil.</p>
      <p>This sudden illumination of our cabin enabled me to examine its
tiniest details. It contained only a table and five stools. Its
invisible door must have been hermetically sealed. Not a sound
reached our ears. Everything seemed dead inside this boat. Was it
in motion, or stationary on the surface of the ocean, or sinking
into the depths? I couldn't tell.</p>
      <p>But this luminous globe hadn't been turned on without good
reason. Consequently, I hoped that some crewmen would soon make an
appearance. If you want to consign people to oblivion, you don't
light up their dungeons.</p>
      <p>I was not mistaken. Unlocking noises became audible, a door
opened, and two men appeared.</p>
      <p>One was short and stocky, powerfully muscled, broad shouldered,
robust of limbs, the head squat, the hair black and luxuriant, the
mustache heavy, the eyes bright and penetrating, and his whole
personality stamped with that southern–blooded zest that, in
France, typifies the people of Provence. The philosopher Diderot
has very aptly claimed that a man's bearing is the clue to his
character, and this stocky little man was certainly a living proof
of this claim. You could sense that his everyday conversation must
have been packed with such vivid figures of speech as
personification, symbolism, and misplaced modifiers. But I was
never in a position to verify this because, around me, he used only
an odd and utterly incomprehensible dialect.</p>
      <p>The second stranger deserves a more detailed description. A
disciple of such character–judging anatomists as Gratiolet or
Engel could have read this man's features like an open book.
Without hesitation, I identified his dominant
qualities—self–confidence, since his head reared like a
nobleman's above the arc formed by the lines of his shoulders, and
his black eyes gazed with icy assurance; calmness, since his skin,
pale rather than ruddy, indicated tranquility of blood; energy,
shown by the swiftly knitting muscles of his brow; and finally
courage, since his deep breathing denoted tremendous reserves of
vitality.</p>
      <p>I might add that this was a man of great pride, that his calm,
firm gaze seemed to reflect thinking on an elevated plane, and that
the harmony of his facial expressions and bodily movements resulted
in an overall effect of unquestionable candor—according to
the findings of physiognomists, those analysts of facial
character.</p>
      <p>I felt "involuntarily reassured" in his presence, and this boded
well for our interview.</p>
      <p>Whether this individual was thirty–five or fifty years of
age, I could not precisely state. He was tall, his forehead broad,
his nose straight, his mouth clearly etched, his teeth magnificent,
his hands refined, tapered, and to use a word from palmistry,
highly "psychic," in other words, worthy of serving a lofty and
passionate spirit. This man was certainly the most wonderful
physical specimen I had ever encountered. One unusual detail: his
eyes were spaced a little far from each other and could instantly
take in nearly a quarter of the horizon. This ability—as I
later verified—was strengthened by a range of vision even
greater than Ned Land's. When this stranger focused his gaze on an
object, his eyebrow lines gathered into a frown, his heavy eyelids
closed around his pupils to contract his huge field of vision, and
he looked! What a look—as if he could magnify objects
shrinking into the distance; as if he could probe your very soul;
as if he could pierce those sheets of water so opaque to our eyes
and scan the deepest seas . . . !</p>
      <p>Wearing caps made of sea–otter fur, and shod in sealskin
fishing boots, these two strangers were dressed in clothing made
from some unique fabric that flattered the figure and allowed great
freedom of movement.</p>
      <p>The taller of the two—apparently the leader on
board—examined us with the greatest care but without
pronouncing a word. Then, turning to his companion, he conversed
with him in a language I didn't recognize. It was a sonorous,
harmonious, flexible dialect whose vowels seemed to undergo a
highly varied accentuation.</p>
      <p>The other replied with a shake of the head and added two or
three utterly incomprehensible words. Then he seemed to question me
directly with a long stare.</p>
      <p>I replied in clear French that I wasn't familiar with his
language; but he didn't seem to understand me, and the situation
grew rather baffling.</p>
      <p>"Still, master should tell our story," Conseil said to me.
"Perhaps these gentlemen will grasp a few words of it!"</p>
      <p>I tried again, telling the tale of our adventures, clearly
articulating my every syllable, and not leaving out a single
detail. I stated our names and titles; then, in order, I introduced
Professor Aronnax, his manservant Conseil, and Mr. Ned Land,
harpooner.</p>
      <p>The man with calm, gentle eyes listened to me serenely, even
courteously, and paid remarkable attention. But nothing in his
facial expression indicated that he understood my story. When I
finished, he didn't pronounce a single word.</p>
      <p>One resource still left was to speak English. Perhaps they would
be familiar with this nearly universal language. But I only knew
it, as I did the German language, well enough to read it fluently,
not well enough to speak it correctly. Here, however, our
overriding need was to make ourselves understood.</p>
      <p>"Come on, it's your turn," I told the harpooner. "Over to you,
Mr. Land. Pull out of your bag of tricks the best English ever
spoken by an Anglo–Saxon, and try for a more favorable result
than mine."</p>
      <p>Ned needed no persuading and started our story all over again,
most of which I could follow. Its content was the same, but the
form differed. Carried away by his volatile temperament, the
Canadian put great animation into it. He complained vehemently
about being imprisoned in defiance of his civil rights, asked by
virtue of which law he was hereby detained, invoked writs of habeas
corpus, threatened to press charges against anyone holding him in
illegal custody, ranted, gesticulated, shouted, and finally
conveyed by an expressive gesture that we were dying of hunger.</p>
      <p>This was perfectly true, but we had nearly forgotten the
fact.</p>
      <p>Much to his amazement, the harpooner seemed no more intelligible
than I had been. Our visitors didn't bat an eye. Apparently they
were engineers who understood the languages of neither the French
physicist Arago nor the English physicist Faraday.</p>
      <p>Thoroughly baffled after vainly exhausting our philological
resources, I no longer knew what tactic to pursue, when Conseil
told me:</p>
      <p>"If master will authorize me, I'll tell the whole business in
German."</p>
      <p>"What! You know German?" I exclaimed.</p>
      <p>"Like most Flemish people, with all due respect to master."</p>
      <p>"On the contrary, my respect is due you. Go to it, my boy."</p>
      <p>And Conseil, in his serene voice, described for the third time
the various vicissitudes of our story. But despite our narrator's
fine accent and stylish turns of phrase, the German language met
with no success.</p>
      <p>Finally, as a last resort, I hauled out everything I could
remember from my early schooldays, and I tried to narrate our
adventures in Latin. Cicero would have plugged his ears and sent me
to the scullery, but somehow I managed to pull through. With the
same negative result.</p>
      <p>This last attempt ultimately misfiring, the two strangers
exchanged a few words in their incomprehensible language and
withdrew, not even favoring us with one of those encouraging
gestures that are used in every country in the world. The door
closed again.</p>
      <p>"This is outrageous!" Ned Land shouted, exploding for the
twentieth time. "I ask you! We speak French, English, German, and
Latin to these rogues, and neither of them has the decency to even
answer back!"</p>
      <p>"Calm down, Ned," I told the seething harpooner. "Anger won't
get us anywhere."</p>
      <p>"But professor," our irascible companion went on, "can't you see
that we could die of hunger in this iron cage?"</p>
      <p>"Bah!" Conseil put in philosophically. "We can hold out a good
while yet!"</p>
      <p>"My friends," I said, "we mustn't despair. We've gotten out of
tighter spots. So please do me the favor of waiting a bit before
you form your views on the commander and crew of this boat."</p>
      <p>"My views are fully formed," Ned Land shot back. "They're
rogues!"</p>
      <p>"Oh good! And from what country?"</p>
      <p>"Roguedom!"</p>
      <p>"My gallant Ned, as yet that country isn't clearly marked on
maps of the world, but I admit that the nationality of these two
strangers is hard to make out! Neither English, French, nor German,
that's all we can say. But I'm tempted to think that the commander
and his chief officer were born in the low latitudes. There must be
southern blood in them. But as to whether they're Spaniards, Turks,
Arabs, or East Indians, their physical characteristics don't give
me enough to go on. And as for their speech, it's utterly
incomprehensible."</p>
      <p>"That's the nuisance in not knowing every language," Conseil
replied, "or the drawback in not having one universal
language!"</p>
      <p>"Which would all go out the window!" Ned Land replied. "Don't
you see, these people have a language all to themselves, a language
they've invented just to cause despair in decent people who ask for
a little dinner! Why, in every country on earth, when you open your
mouth, snap your jaws, smack your lips and teeth, isn't that the
world's most understandable message? From Quebec to the Tuamotu
Islands, from Paris to the Antipodes, doesn't it mean: I'm hungry,
give me a bite to eat!"</p>
      <p>"Oh," Conseil put in, "there are some people so unintelligent by
nature . . ."</p>
      <p>As he was saying these words, the door opened. A steward
entered.<xref href="F8.2" scope="external" format="html">
            <sup>*</sup>
         </xref> He brought us some clothes,
jackets and sailor's pants, made out of a fabric whose nature I
didn't recognize. I hurried to change into them, and my companions
followed suit.</p>
      <p>Meanwhile our silent steward, perhaps a deaf–mute, set the
table and laid three place settings.</p>
      <p>"There's something serious afoot," Conseil said, "and it bodes
well."</p>
      <p>"Bah!" replied the rancorous harpooner. "What the devil do you
suppose they eat around here? Turtle livers, loin of shark, dogfish
steaks?"</p>
      <p>"We'll soon find out!" Conseil said.</p>
      <p>Overlaid with silver dish covers, various platters had been
neatly positioned on the table cloth, and we sat down to eat.
Assuredly, we were dealing with civilized people, and if it hadn't
been for this electric light flooding over us, I would have thought
we were in the dining room of the Hotel Adelphi in Liverpool, or
the Grand Hotel in Paris. However, I feel compelled to mention that
bread and wine were totally absent. The water was fresh and clear,
but it was still water—which wasn't what Ned Land had in
mind. Among the foods we were served, I was able to identify
various daintily dressed fish; but I couldn't make up my mind about
certain otherwise excellent dishes, and I couldn't even tell
whether their contents belonged to the vegetable or the animal
kingdom. As for the tableware, it was elegant and in perfect taste.
Each utensil, spoon, fork, knife, and plate, bore on its reverse a
letter encircled by a Latin motto, and here is its exact
duplicate:</p>
      <lq>
         <p>MOBILIS IN MOBILI</p>
         <p>N</p>
      </lq>
      <p>Moving within the moving element! It was a highly appropriate
motto for this underwater machine, so long as the preposition in is
translated as within and not upon. The letter "N" was no doubt the
initial of the name of that mystifying individual in command
beneath the seas!</p>
      <p>Ned and Conseil had no time for such musings. They were wolfing
down their food, and without further ado I did the same. By now I
felt reassured about our fate, and it seemed obvious that our hosts
didn't intend to let us die of starvation.</p>
      <p>But all earthly things come to an end, all things must pass,
even the hunger of people who haven't eaten for fifteen hours. Our
appetites appeased, we felt an urgent need for sleep. A natural
reaction after that interminable night of fighting for our
lives.</p>
      <p>"Ye gods, I'll sleep soundly," Conseil said.</p>
      <p>"Me, I'm out like a light!" Ned Land replied.</p>
      <p>My two companions lay down on the cabin's carpeting and were
soon deep in slumber.</p>
      <p>As for me, I gave in less readily to this intense need for
sleep. Too many thoughts had piled up in my mind, too many
insoluble questions had arisen, too many images were keeping my
eyelids open! Where were we? What strange power was carrying us
along? I felt—or at least I thought I did—the
submersible sinking toward the sea's lower strata. Intense
nightmares besieged me. In these mysterious marine sanctuaries, I
envisioned hosts of unknown animals, and this underwater boat
seemed to be a blood relation of theirs: living, breathing, just as
fearsome . . . ! Then my mind grew calmer, my imagination melted
into hazy drowsiness, and I soon fell into an uneasy slumber.</p>
   </body>
</topic>