<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<topic id="d2e2803">
   <title>
      <d4pSimpleEnumerator><!--1.10-->Chapter 10. </d4pSimpleEnumerator>
      <ph>The Man of the Waters</ph>
   </title>
   <body>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="size_plus_2">IT WAS THE</ph> ship's commander who had just
spoken.</p>
      <p>At these words Ned Land stood up quickly. Nearly strangled, the
steward staggered out at a signal from his superior; but such was
the commander's authority aboard his vessel, not one gesture gave
away the resentment that this man must have felt toward the
Canadian. In silence we waited for the outcome of this scene;
Conseil, in spite of himself, seemed almost fascinated, I was
stunned.</p>
      <p>Arms crossed, leaning against a corner of the table, the
commander studied us with great care. Was he reluctant to speak
further? Did he regret those words he had just pronounced in
French? You would have thought so.</p>
      <p>After a few moments of silence, which none of us would have
dreamed of interrupting:</p>
      <p>"Gentlemen," he said in a calm, penetrating voice, "I speak
French, English, German, and Latin with equal fluency. Hence I
could have answered you as early as our initial interview, but
first I wanted to make your acquaintance and then think things
over. Your four versions of the same narrative, perfectly
consistent by and large, established your personal identities for
me. I now know that sheer chance has placed in my presence
Professor Pierre Aronnax, specialist in natural history at the
Paris Museum and entrusted with a scientific mission abroad, his
manservant Conseil, and Ned Land, a harpooner of Canadian origin
aboard the <i>Abraham Lincoln</i>, a frigate in the national navy
of the United States of America."</p>
      <p>I bowed in agreement. The commander hadn't put a question to me.
So no answer was called for. This man expressed himself with
perfect ease and without a trace of an accent. His phrasing was
clear, his words well chosen, his facility in elocution remarkable.
And yet, to me, he didn't have "the feel" of a fellow
countryman.</p>
      <p>He went on with the conversation as follows:</p>
      <p>"No doubt, sir, you've felt that I waited rather too long before
paying you this second visit. After discovering your identities, I
wanted to weigh carefully what policy to pursue toward you. I had
great difficulty deciding. Some extremely inconvenient
circumstances have brought you into the presence of a man who has
cut himself off from humanity. Your coming has disrupted my whole
existence."</p>
      <p>"Unintentionally," I said.</p>
      <p>"Unintentionally?" the stranger replied, raising his voice a
little. "Was it unintentionally that the <i>Abraham Lincoln</i>
hunted me on every sea? Was it unintentionally that you traveled
aboard that frigate? Was it unintentionally that your shells
bounced off my ship's hull? Was it unintentionally that Mr. Ned
Land hit me with his harpoon?"</p>
      <p>I detected a controlled irritation in these words. But there was
a perfectly natural reply to these charges, and I made it.</p>
      <p>"Sir," I said, "you're surely unaware of the discussions that
have taken place in Europe and America with yourself as the
subject. You don't realize that various accidents, caused by
collisions with your underwater machine, have aroused public
passions on those two continents. I'll spare you the innumerable
hypotheses with which we've tried to explain this inexplicable
phenomenon, whose secret is yours alone. But please understand that
the <i>Abraham Lincoln</i> chased you over the Pacific high seas in
the belief it was hunting some powerful marine monster, which had
to be purged from the ocean at all cost."</p>
      <p>A half smile curled the commander's lips; then, in a calmer
tone:</p>
      <p>"Professor Aronnax," he replied, "do you dare claim that your
frigate wouldn't have chased and cannonaded an underwater boat as
readily as a monster?"</p>
      <p>This question baffled me, since Commander Farragut would
certainly have shown no such hesitation. He would have seen it as
his sworn duty to destroy a contrivance of this kind just as
promptly as a gigantic narwhale.</p>
      <p>"So you understand, sir," the stranger went on, "that I have a
right to treat you as my enemy."</p>
      <p>I kept quiet, with good reason. What was the use of debating
such a proposition, when superior force can wipe out the best
arguments?</p>
      <p>"It took me a good while to decide," the commander went on.
"Nothing obliged me to grant you hospitality. If I were to part
company with you, I'd have no personal interest in ever seeing you
again. I could put you back on the platform of this ship that has
served as your refuge. I could sink under the sea, and I could
forget you ever existed. Wouldn't that be my right?"</p>
      <p>"Perhaps it would be the right of a savage," I replied. "But not
that of a civilized man."</p>
      <p>"Professor," the commander replied swiftly, "I'm not what you
term a civilized man! I've severed all ties with society, for
reasons that I alone have the right to appreciate. Therefore I obey
none of its regulations, and I insist that you never invoke them in
front of me!"</p>
      <p>This was plain speaking. A flash of anger and scorn lit up the
stranger's eyes, and I glimpsed a fearsome past in this man's life.
Not only had he placed himself beyond human laws, he had rendered
himself independent, out of all reach, free in the strictest sense
of the word! For who would dare chase him to the depths of the sea
when he thwarted all attacks on the surface? What ship could
withstand a collision with his underwater <i>Monitor</i>? What
armor plate, no matter how heavy, could bear the thrusts of his
spur? No man among men could call him to account for his actions.
God, if he believed in Him, his conscience if he had
one—these were the only judges to whom he was answerable.</p>
      <p>These thoughts swiftly crossed my mind while this strange
individual fell silent, like someone completely
self–absorbed. I regarded him with a mixture of fear and
fascination, in the same way, no doubt, that Œdipus regarded
the Sphinx.</p>
      <p>After a fairly long silence, the commander went on with our
conversation.</p>
      <p>"So I had difficulty deciding," he said. "But I concluded that
my personal interests could be reconciled with that natural
compassion to which every human being has a right. Since fate has
brought you here, you'll stay aboard my vessel. You'll be free
here, and in exchange for that freedom, moreover totally related to
it, I'll lay on you just one condition. Your word that you'll
submit to it will be sufficient."</p>
      <p>"Go on, sir," I replied. "I assume this condition is one an
honest man can accept?"</p>
      <p>"Yes, sir. Just this. It's possible that certain unforeseen
events may force me to confine you to your cabins for some hours,
or even for some days as the case may be. Since I prefer never to
use violence, I expect from you in such a case, even more than in
any other, your unquestioning obedience. By acting in this way, I
shield you from complicity, I absolve you of all responsibility,
since I myself make it impossible for you to see what you aren't
meant to see. Do you accept this condition?"</p>
      <p>So things happened on board that were quite odd to say the
least, things never to be seen by people not placing themselves
beyond society's laws! Among all the surprises the future had in
store for me, this would not be the mildest.</p>
      <p>"We accept," I replied. "Only, I'll ask your permission, sir, to
address a question to you, just one."</p>
      <p>"Go ahead, sir."</p>
      <p>"You said we'd be free aboard your vessel?"</p>
      <p>"Completely."</p>
      <p>"Then I would ask what you mean by this freedom."</p>
      <p>"Why, the freedom to come, go, see, and even closely observe
everything happening here—except under certain rare
circumstances—in short, the freedom we ourselves enjoy, my
companions and I."</p>
      <p>It was obvious that we did not understand each other.</p>
      <p>"Pardon me, sir," I went on, "but that's merely the freedom that
every prisoner has, the freedom to pace his cell! That's not enough
for us."</p>
      <p>"Nevertheless, it will have to do!"</p>
      <p>"What! We must give up seeing our homeland, friends, and
relatives ever again?"</p>
      <p>"Yes, sir. But giving up that intolerable earthly yoke that some
men call freedom is perhaps less painful than you think!"</p>
      <p>"By thunder!" Ned Land shouted. "I'll never promise I won't try
getting out of here!"</p>
      <p>"I didn't ask for such a promise, Mr. Land," the commander
replied coldly.</p>
      <p>"Sir," I replied, flaring up in spite of myself, "you're taking
unfair advantage of us! This is sheer cruelty!"</p>
      <p>"No, sir, it's an act of mercy! You're my prisoners of war! I've
cared for you when, with a single word, I could plunge you back
into the ocean depths! You attacked me! You've just stumbled on a
secret no living man must probe, the secret of my entire existence!
Do you think I'll send you back to a world that must know nothing
more of me? Never! By keeping you on board, it isn't you whom I
care for, it's me!"</p>
      <p>These words indicated that the commander pursued a policy
impervious to arguments.</p>
      <p>"Then, sir," I went on, "you give us, quite simply, a choice
between life and death?"</p>
      <p>"Quite simply."</p>
      <p>"My friends," I said, "to a question couched in these terms, our
answer can be taken for granted. But no solemn promises bind us to
the commander of this vessel."</p>
      <p>"None, sir," the stranger replied.</p>
      <p>Then, in a gentler voice, he went on:</p>
      <p>"Now, allow me to finish what I have to tell you. I've heard of
you, Professor Aronnax. You, if not your companions, won't perhaps
complain too much about the stroke of fate that has brought us
together. Among the books that make up my favorite reading, you'll
find the work you've published on the great ocean depths. I've
pored over it. You've taken your studies as far as terrestrial
science can go. But you don't know everything because you haven't
seen everything. Let me tell you, professor, you won't regret the
time you spend aboard my vessel. You're going to voyage through a
land of wonders. Stunned amazement will probably be your habitual
state of mind. It will be a long while before you tire of the
sights constantly before your eyes. I'm going to make another
underwater tour of the world—perhaps my last, who
knows?—and I'll review everything I've studied in the depths
of these seas that I've crossed so often, and you can be my fellow
student. Starting this very day, you'll enter a new element, you'll
see what no human being has ever seen before—since my men and
I no longer count—and thanks to me, you're going to learn the
ultimate secrets of our planet."</p>
      <p>I can't deny it; the commander's words had a tremendous effect
on me. He had caught me on my weak side, and I momentarily forgot
that not even this sublime experience was worth the loss of my
freedom. Besides, I counted on the future to resolve this important
question. So I was content to reply:</p>
      <p>"Sir, even though you've cut yourself off from humanity, I can
see that you haven't disowned all human feeling. We're castaways
whom you've charitably taken aboard, we'll never forget that.
Speaking for myself, I don't rule out that the interests of science
could override even the need for freedom, which promises me that,
in exchange, our encounter will provide great rewards."</p>
      <p>I thought the commander would offer me his hand, to seal our
agreement. He did nothing of the sort. I regretted that.</p>
      <p>"One last question," I said, just as this inexplicable being
seemed ready to withdraw.</p>
      <p>"Ask it, professor."</p>
      <p>"By what name am I to call you?"</p>
      <p>"Sir," the commander replied, "to you, I'm simply Captain
Nemo;<fn callout="*">Bailly believed that
Atlantis was located at the North Pole! Ed.</fn> to me, you and your
companions are simply passengers on the <i>Nautilus</i>."</p>
      <p>
         <xref href="F10.1" scope="external" format="html">
            <sup>*</sup>
         </xref>Latin: nemo means "no one."
Ed.</p>
      <p>Captain Nemo called out. A steward appeared. The captain gave
him his orders in that strange language I couldn't even identify.
Then, turning to the Canadian and Conseil:</p>
      <p>"A meal is waiting for you in your cabin," he told them. "Kindly
follow this man."</p>
      <p>"That's an offer I can't refuse!" the harpooner replied.</p>
      <p>After being confined for over thirty hours, he and Conseil were
finally out of this cell.</p>
      <p>"And now, Professor Aronnax, our own breakfast is ready. Allow
me to lead the way."</p>
      <p>"Yours to command, Captain."</p>
      <p>I followed Captain Nemo, and as soon as I passed through the
doorway, I went down a kind of electrically lit passageway that
resembled a gangway on a ship. After a stretch of some ten meters,
a second door opened before me.</p>
      <p>I then entered a dining room, decorated and furnished in austere
good taste. Inlaid with ebony trim, tall oaken sideboards stood at
both ends of this room, and sparkling on their shelves were
staggered rows of earthenware, porcelain, and glass of incalculable
value. There silver–plated dinnerware gleamed under rays
pouring from light fixtures in the ceiling, whose glare was
softened and tempered by delicately painted designs.</p>
      <p>In the center of this room stood a table, richly spread. Captain
Nemo indicated the place I was to occupy.</p>
      <p>"Be seated," he told me, "and eat like the famished man you must
be."</p>
      <p>Our breakfast consisted of several dishes whose contents were
all supplied by the sea, and some foods whose nature and derivation
were unknown to me. They were good, I admit, but with a peculiar
flavor to which I would soon grow accustomed. These various food
items seemed to be rich in phosphorous, and I thought that they,
too, must have been of marine origin.</p>
      <p>Captain Nemo stared at me. I had asked him nothing, but he read
my thoughts, and on his own he answered the questions I was itching
to address him.</p>
      <p>"Most of these dishes are new to you," he told me. "But you can
consume them without fear. They're healthy and nourishing. I
renounced terrestrial foods long ago, and I'm none the worse for
it. My crew are strong and full of energy, and they eat what I
eat."</p>
      <p>"So," I said, "all these foods are products of the sea?"</p>
      <p>"Yes, professor, the sea supplies all my needs. Sometimes I cast
my nets in our wake, and I pull them up ready to burst. Sometimes I
go hunting right in the midst of this element that has long seemed
so far out of man's reach, and I corner the game that dwells in my
underwater forests. Like the flocks of old Proteus, King Neptune's
shepherd, my herds graze without fear on the ocean's immense
prairies. There I own vast properties that I harvest myself, and
which are forever sown by the hand of the Creator of All
Things."</p>
      <p>I stared at Captain Nemo in definite astonishment, and I
answered him:</p>
      <p>"Sir, I understand perfectly how your nets can furnish excellent
fish for your table; I understand less how you can chase aquatic
game in your underwater forests; but how a piece of red meat, no
matter how small, can figure in your menu, that I don't understand
at all."</p>
      <p>"Nor I, sir," Captain Nemo answered me. "I never touch the flesh
of land animals."</p>
      <p>"Nevertheless, this . . . ," I went on, pointing to a dish where
some slices of loin were still left.</p>
      <p>"What you believe to be red meat, professor, is nothing other
than loin of sea turtle. Similarly, here are some dolphin livers
you might mistake for stewed pork. My chef is a skillful food
processor who excels at pickling and preserving these various
exhibits from the ocean. Feel free to sample all of these foods.
Here are some preserves of sea cucumber that a Malaysian would
declare to be unrivaled in the entire world, here's cream from milk
furnished by the udders of <i>cetaceans</i>, and sugar from the
huge fucus plants in the North Sea; and finally, allow me to offer
you some marmalade of sea anemone, equal to that from the tastiest
fruits."</p>
      <p>So I sampled away, more as a curiosity seeker than an epicure,
while Captain Nemo delighted me with his incredible anecdotes.</p>
      <p>"But this sea, Professor Aronnax," he told me, "this prodigious,
inexhaustible wet nurse of a sea not only feeds me, she dresses me
as well. That fabric covering you was woven from the masses of
filaments that anchor certain seashells; as the ancients were wont
to do, it was dyed with purple ink from the murex snail and shaded
with violet tints that I extract from a marine slug, the
Mediterranean sea hare. The perfumes you'll find on the washstand
in your cabin were produced from the oozings of marine plants. Your
mattress was made from the ocean's softest eelgrass. Your quill pen
will be whalebone, your ink a juice secreted by cuttlefish or
squid. Everything comes to me from the sea, just as someday
everything will return to it!"</p>
      <p>"You love the sea, Captain."</p>
      <p>"Yes, I love it! The sea is the be all and end all! It covers
seven–tenths of the planet earth. Its breath is clean and
healthy. It's an immense wilderness where a man is never lonely,
because he feels life astir on every side. The sea is simply the
vehicle for a prodigious, unearthly mode of existence; it's simply
movement and love; it's living infinity, as one of your poets put
it. And in essence, professor, nature is here made manifest by all
three of her kingdoms, mineral, vegetable, and animal. The last of
these is amply represented by the four zoophyte groups, three
classes of articulates, five classes of mollusks, and three
vertebrate classes: mammals, reptiles, and those countless legions
of fish, an infinite order of animals totaling more than 13,000
species, of which only one–tenth belong to fresh water. The
sea is a vast pool of nature. Our globe began with the sea, so to
speak, and who can say we won't end with it! Here lies supreme
tranquility. The sea doesn't belong to tyrants. On its surface they
can still exercise their iniquitous claims, battle each other,
devour each other, haul every earthly horror. But thirty feet below
sea level, their dominion ceases, their influence fades, their
power vanishes! Ah, sir, live! Live in the heart of the seas! Here
alone lies independence! Here I recognize no superiors! Here I'm
free!"</p>
      <p>Captain Nemo suddenly fell silent in the midst of this
enthusiastic outpouring. Had he let himself get carried away, past
the bounds of his habitual reserve? Had he said too much? For a few
moments he strolled up and down, all aquiver. Then his nerves grew
calmer, his facial features recovered their usual icy composure,
and turning to me:</p>
      <p>"Now, professor," he said, "if you'd like to inspect the
<i>Nautilus</i>, I'm yours to command."</p>
   </body>
</topic>