<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<topic id="d2e3305">
   <title>
      <d4pSimpleEnumerator><!--1.12-->Chapter 12. </d4pSimpleEnumerator>
      <ph>Everything through Electricity</ph>
   </title>
   <body>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="size_plus_2">"SIR," CAPTAIN NEMO SAID</ph>, showing me the
instruments hanging on the walls of his stateroom, "these are the
devices needed to navigate the <i>Nautilus</i>. Here, as in the
lounge, I always have them before my eyes, and they indicate my
position and exact heading in the midst of the ocean. You're
familiar with some of them, such as the thermometer, which gives
the temperature inside the <i>Nautilus</i>; the barometer, which
measures the heaviness of the outside air and forecasts changes in
the weather; the humidistat, which indicates the degree of dryness
in the atmosphere; the storm glass, whose mixture decomposes to
foretell the arrival of tempests; the compass, which steers my
course; the sextant, which takes the sun's altitude and tells me my
latitude; chronometers, which allow me to calculate my longitude;
and finally, spyglasses for both day and night, enabling me to
scrutinize every point of the horizon once the <i>Nautilus</i> has
risen to the surface of the waves."</p>
      <p>"These are the normal navigational instruments," I replied, "and
I'm familiar with their uses. But no doubt these others answer
pressing needs unique to the <i>Nautilus</i>. That dial I see
there, with the needle moving across it—isn't it a pressure
gauge?"</p>
      <p>"It is indeed a pressure gauge. It's placed in contact with the
water, and it indicates the outside pressure on our hull, which in
turn gives me the depth at which my submersible is sitting."</p>
      <p>"And these are some new breed of sounding line?"</p>
      <p>"They're thermometric sounding lines that report water
temperatures in the different strata."</p>
      <p>"And these other instruments, whose functions I can't even
guess?"</p>
      <p>"Here, professor, I need to give you some background
information," Captain Nemo said. "So kindly hear me out."</p>
      <p>He fell silent for some moments, then he said:</p>
      <p>"There's a powerful, obedient, swift, and effortless force that
can be bent to any use and which reigns supreme aboard my vessel.
It does everything. It lights me, it warms me, it's the soul of my
mechanical equipment. This force is electricity."</p>
      <p>"Electricity!" I exclaimed in some surprise.</p>
      <p>"Yes, sir."</p>
      <p>"But, Captain, you have a tremendous speed of movement that
doesn't square with the strength of electricity. Until now, its
dynamic potential has remained quite limited, capable of producing
only small amounts of power!"</p>
      <p>"Professor," Captain Nemo replied, "my electricity isn't the
run–of–the–mill variety, and with your
permission, I'll leave it at that."</p>
      <p>"I won't insist, sir, and I'll rest content with simply being
flabbergasted at your results. I would ask one question, however,
which you needn't answer if it's indiscreet. The electric cells you
use to generate this marvelous force must be depleted very quickly.
Their zinc component, for example: how do you replace it, since you
no longer stay in contact with the shore?"</p>
      <p>"That question deserves an answer," Captain Nemo replied. "First
off, I'll mention that at the bottom of the sea there exist veins
of zinc, iron, silver, and gold whose mining would quite certainly
be feasible. But I've tapped none of these land–based metals,
and I wanted to make demands only on the sea itself for the sources
of my electricity."</p>
      <p>"The sea itself?"</p>
      <p>"Yes, professor, and there was no shortage of such sources. In
fact, by establishing a circuit between two wires immersed to
different depths, I'd be able to obtain electricity through the
diverging temperatures they experience; but I preferred to use a
more practical procedure."</p>
      <p>"And that is?"</p>
      <p>"You're familiar with the composition of salt water. In 1,000
grams one finds 96.5% water and about 2.66% sodium chloride; then
small quantities of magnesium chloride, potassium chloride,
magnesium bromide, sulfate of magnesia, calcium sulfate, and
calcium carbonate. Hence you observe that sodium chloride is
encountered there in significant proportions. Now then, it's this
sodium that I extract from salt water and with which I compose my
electric cells."</p>
      <p>"Sodium?"</p>
      <p>"Yes, sir. Mixed with mercury, it forms an amalgam that takes
the place of zinc in Bunsen cells. The mercury is never depleted.
Only the sodium is consumed, and the sea itself gives me that.
Beyond this, I'll mention that sodium batteries have been found to
generate the greater energy, and their electro–motor strength
is twice that of zinc batteries."</p>
      <p>"Captain, I fully understand the excellence of sodium under the
conditions in which you're placed. The sea contains it. Fine. But
it still has to be produced, in short, extracted. And how do you
accomplish this? Obviously your batteries could do the extracting;
but if I'm not mistaken, the consumption of sodium needed by your
electric equipment would be greater than the quantity you'd
extract. It would come about, then, that in the process of
producing your sodium, you'd use up more than you'd make!"</p>
      <p>"Accordingly, professor, I don't extract it with batteries;
quite simply, I utilize the heat of coal from the earth."</p>
      <p>"From the earth?" I said, my voice going up on the word.</p>
      <p>"We'll say coal from the seafloor, if you prefer," Captain Nemo
replied.</p>
      <p>"And you can mine these veins of underwater coal?"</p>
      <p>"You'll watch me work them, Professor Aronnax. I ask only a
little patience of you, since you'll have ample time to be patient.
Just remember one thing: I owe everything to the ocean; it
generates electricity, and electricity gives the <i>Nautilus</i>
heat, light, motion, and, in a word, life itself."</p>
      <p>"But not the air you breathe?"</p>
      <p>"Oh, I could produce the air needed on board, but it would be
pointless, since I can rise to the surface of the sea whenever I
like. However, even though electricity doesn't supply me with
breathable air, it at least operates the powerful pumps that store
it under pressure in special tanks; which, if need be, allows me to
extend my stay in the lower strata for as long as I want."</p>
      <p>"Captain," I replied, "I'll rest content with marveling. You've
obviously found what all mankind will surely find one day, the true
dynamic power of electricity."</p>
      <p>"I'm not so certain they'll find it," Captain Nemo replied
icily. "But be that as it may, you're already familiar with the
first use I've found for this valuable force. It lights us, and
with a uniformity and continuity not even possessed by sunlight.
Now, look at that clock: it's electric, it runs with an accuracy
rivaling the finest chronometers. I've had it divided into
twenty–four hours like Italian clocks, since neither day nor
night, sun nor moon, exist for me, but only this artificial light
that I import into the depths of the seas! See, right now it's ten
o'clock in the morning."</p>
      <p>"That's perfect."</p>
      <p>"Another use for electricity: that dial hanging before our eyes
indicates how fast the <i>Nautilus</i> is going. An electric wire
puts it in contact with the patent log; this needle shows me the
actual speed of my submersible. And . . . hold on . . . just now
we're proceeding at the moderate pace of fifteen miles per
hour."</p>
      <p>"It's marvelous," I replied, "and I truly see, Captain, how
right you are to use this force; it's sure to take the place of
wind, water, and steam."</p>
      <p>"But that's not all, Professor Aronnax," Captain Nemo said,
standing up. "And if you'd care to follow me, we'll inspect the
<i>Nautilus's</i> stern."</p>
      <p>In essence, I was already familiar with the whole forward part
of this underwater boat, and here are its exact subdivisions going
from amidships to its spur: the dining room, 5 meters long and
separated from the library by a watertight bulkhead, in other
words, it couldn't be penetrated by the sea; the library, 5 meters
long; the main lounge, 10 meters long, separated from the captain's
stateroom by a second watertight bulkhead; the aforesaid stateroom,
5 meters long; mine, 2.5 meters long; and finally, air tanks 7.5
meters long and extending to the stempost. Total: a length of 35
meters. Doors were cut into the watertight bulkheads and were shut
hermetically by means of india–rubber seals, which insured
complete safety aboard the <i>Nautilus</i> in the event of a leak
in any one section.</p>
      <p>I followed Captain Nemo down gangways located for easy transit,
and I arrived amidships. There I found a sort of shaft heading
upward between two watertight bulkheads. An iron ladder, clamped to
the wall, led to the shaft's upper end. I asked the Captain what
this ladder was for.</p>
      <p>"It goes to the skiff," he replied.</p>
      <p>"What! You have a skiff?" I replied in some astonishment.</p>
      <p>"Surely. An excellent longboat, light and unsinkable, which is
used for excursions and fishing trips."</p>
      <p>"But when you want to set out, don't you have to return to the
surface of the sea?"</p>
      <p>"By no means. The skiff is attached to the topside of the
<i>Nautilus's</i> hull and is set in a cavity expressly designed to
receive it. It's completely decked over, absolutely watertight, and
held solidly in place by bolts. This ladder leads to a manhole cut
into the <i>Nautilus's</i> hull and corresponding to a comparable
hole cut into the side of the skiff. I insert myself through this
double opening into the longboat. My crew close up the hole
belonging to the <i>Nautilus</i>; I close up the one belonging to
the skiff, simply by screwing it into place. I undo the bolts
holding the skiff to the submersible, and the longboat rises with
prodigious speed to the surface of the sea. I then open the deck
paneling, carefully closed until that point; I up mast and hoist
sail—or I take out my oars—and I go for a spin."</p>
      <p>"But how do you return to the ship?"</p>
      <p>"I don't, Professor Aronnax; the <i>Nautilus</i> returns to
me."</p>
      <p>"At your command?"</p>
      <p>"At my command. An electric wire connects me to the ship. I fire
off a telegram, and that's that."</p>
      <p>"Right," I said, tipsy from all these wonders, "nothing to
it!"</p>
      <p>After passing the well of the companionway that led to the
platform, I saw a cabin 2 meters long in which Conseil and Ned
Land, enraptured with their meal, were busy devouring it to the
last crumb. Then a door opened into the galley, 3 meters long and
located between the vessel's huge storage lockers.</p>
      <p>There, even more powerful and obedient than gas, electricity did
most of the cooking. Arriving under the stoves, wires transmitted
to platinum griddles a heat that was distributed and sustained with
perfect consistency. It also heated a distilling mechanism that,
via evaporation, supplied excellent drinking water. Next to this
galley was a bathroom, conveniently laid out, with faucets
supplying hot or cold water at will.</p>
      <p>After the galley came the crew's quarters, 5 meters long. But
the door was closed and I couldn't see its accommodations, which
might have told me the number of men it took to operate the
<i>Nautilus</i>.</p>
      <p>At the far end stood a fourth watertight bulkhead, separating
the crew's quarters from the engine room. A door opened, and I
stood in the compartment where Captain Nemo, indisputably a
world–class engineer, had set up his locomotive
equipment.</p>
      <p>Brightly lit, the engine room measured at least 20 meters in
length. It was divided, by function, into two parts: the first
contained the cells for generating electricity, the second that
mechanism transmitting movement to the propeller.</p>
      <p>Right off, I detected an odor permeating the compartment that
was <i>sui generis</i>.<fn callout="*">Latin: "in a class by
itself." Ed.</fn> Captain
Nemo noticed the negative impression it made on me.</p>
      <p>"That," he told me, "is a gaseous discharge caused by our use of
sodium, but it's only a mild inconvenience. In any event, every
morning we sanitize the ship by ventilating it in the open
air."</p>
      <p>Meanwhile I examined the <i>Nautilus's</i> engine with a
fascination easy to imagine.</p>
      <p>"You observe," Captain Nemo told me, "that I use Bunsen cells,
not Ruhmkorff cells. The latter would be ineffectual. One uses
fewer Bunsen cells, but they're big and strong, and experience has
proven their superiority. The electricity generated here makes its
way to the stern, where electromagnets of huge size activate a
special system of levers and gears that transmit movement to the
propeller's shaft. The latter has a diameter of 6 meters, a pitch
of 7.5 meters, and can do up to 120 revolutions per minute."</p>
      <p>"And that gives you?"</p>
      <p>"A speed of fifty miles per hour."</p>
      <p>There lay a mystery, but I didn't insist on exploring it. How
could electricity work with such power? Where did this nearly
unlimited energy originate? Was it in the extraordinary voltage
obtained from some new kind of induction coil? Could its
transmission have been immeasurably increased by some unknown
system of levers?<fn callout="*">Author's Note: And
sure enough, there's now talk of such a discovery, in which a new
set of levers generates considerable power. Did its inventor meet
up with Captain Nemo?</fn> This was the
point I couldn't grasp.</p>
      <p>"Captain Nemo," I said, "I'll vouch for the results and not try
to explain them. I've seen the <i>Nautilus</i> at work out in front
of the <i>Abraham Lincoln</i>, and I know where I stand on its
speed. But it isn't enough just to move, we have to see where we're
going! We must be able to steer right or left, up or down! How do
you reach the lower depths, where you meet an increasing resistance
that's assessed in hundreds of atmospheres? How do you rise back to
the surface of the ocean? Finally, how do you keep your ship at
whatever level suits you? Am I indiscreet in asking you all these
things?"</p>
      <p>"Not at all, professor," the Captain answered me after a slight
hesitation, "since you'll never leave this underwater boat. Come
into the lounge. It's actually our work room, and there you'll
learn the full story about the <i>Nautilus</i>!"</p>
   </body>
</topic>