<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<topic id="d2e3585">
   <title>
      <d4pSimpleEnumerator><!--1.13-->Chapter 13. </d4pSimpleEnumerator>
      <ph>Some Figures</ph>
   </title>
   <body>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="size_plus_2">A MOMENT LATER</ph> we were seated on a couch
in the lounge, cigars between our lips. The Captain placed before
my eyes a working drawing that gave the ground plan, cross section,
and side view of the <i>Nautilus</i>. Then he began his description
as follows:</p>
      <p>"Here, Professor Aronnax, are the different dimensions of this
boat now transporting you. It's a very long cylinder with conical
ends. It noticeably takes the shape of a cigar, a shape already
adopted in London for several projects of the same kind. The length
of this cylinder from end to end is exactly seventy meters, and its
maximum breadth of beam is eight meters. So it isn't quite built on
the ten–to–one ratio of your high–speed steamers;
but its lines are sufficiently long, and their tapering gradual
enough, so that the displaced water easily slips past and poses no
obstacle to the ship's movements.</p>
      <p>"These two dimensions allow you to obtain, via a simple
calculation, the surface area and volume of the <i>Nautilus</i>.
Its surface area totals 1,011.45 square meters, its volume 1,507.2
cubic meters—which is tantamount to saying that when it's
completely submerged, it displaces 1,500 cubic meters of water, or
weighs 1,500 metric tons.</p>
      <p>"In drawing up plans for a ship meant to navigate underwater, I
wanted it, when floating on the waves, to lie nine–tenths
below the surface and to emerge only one–tenth. Consequently,
under these conditions it needed to displace only nine–tenths
of its volume, hence 1,356.48 cubic meters; in other words, it was
to weigh only that same number of metric tons. So I was obliged not
to exceed this weight while building it to the aforesaid
dimensions.</p>
      <p>"The <i>Nautilus</i> is made up of two hulls, one inside the
other; between them, joining them together, are iron T–bars
that give this ship the utmost rigidity. In fact, thanks to this
cellular arrangement, it has the resistance of a stone block, as if
it were completely solid. Its plating can't give way; it's
self–adhering and not dependent on the tightness of its
rivets; and due to the perfect union of its materials, the
solidarity of its construction allows it to defy the most violent
seas.</p>
      <p>"The two hulls are manufactured from boilerplate steel, whose
relative density is 7.8 times that of water. The first hull has a
thickness of no less than five centimeters and weighs 394.96 metric
tons. My second hull, the outer cover, includes a keel fifty
centimeters high by twenty–five wide, which by itself weighs
62 metric tons; this hull, the engine, the ballast, the various
accessories and accommodations, plus the bulkheads and interior
braces, have a combined weight of 961.52 metric tons, which when
added to 394.96 metric tons, gives us the desired total of 1,356.48
metric tons. Clear?"</p>
      <p>"Clear," I replied.</p>
      <p>"So," the captain went on, "when the <i>Nautilus</i> lies on the
waves under these conditions, one–tenth of it does emerge
above water. Now then, if I provide some ballast tanks equal in
capacity to that one–tenth, hence able to hold 150.72 metric
tons, and if I fill them with water, the boat then displaces
1,507.2 metric tons—or it weighs that much—and it would
be completely submerged. That's what comes about, professor. These
ballast tanks exist within easy access in the lower reaches of the
<i>Nautilus</i>. I open some stopcocks, the tanks fill, the boat
sinks, and it's exactly flush with the surface of the water."</p>
      <p>"Fine, captain, but now we come to a genuine difficulty. You're
able to lie flush with the surface of the ocean, that I understand.
But lower down, while diving beneath that surface, isn't your
submersible going to encounter a pressure, and consequently undergo
an upward thrust, that must be assessed at one atmosphere per every
thirty feet of water, hence at about one kilogram per each square
centimeter?"</p>
      <p>"Precisely, sir."</p>
      <p>"Then unless you fill up the whole <i>Nautilus</i>, I don't see
how you can force it down into the heart of these liquid
masses."</p>
      <p>"Professor," Captain Nemo replied, "static objects mustn't be
confused with dynamic ones, or we'll be open to serious error.
Comparatively little effort is spent in reaching the ocean's lower
regions, because all objects have a tendency to become 'sinkers.'
Follow my logic here."</p>
      <p>"I'm all ears, captain."</p>
      <p>"When I wanted to determine what increase in weight the
<i>Nautilus</i> needed to be given in order to submerge, I had only
to take note of the proportionate reduction in volume that salt
water experiences in deeper and deeper strata."</p>
      <p>"That's obvious," I replied.</p>
      <p>"Now then, if water isn't absolutely incompressible, at least it
compresses very little. In fact, according to the most recent
calculations, this reduction is only .0000436 per atmosphere, or
per every thirty feet of depth. For instance, to go 1,000 meters
down, I must take into account the reduction in volume that occurs
under a pressure equivalent to that from a 1,000–meter column
of water, in other words, under a pressure of 100 atmospheres. In
this instance the reduction would be .00436. Consequently, I'd have
to increase my weight from 1,507.2 metric tons to 1,513.77. So the
added weight would only be 6.57 metric tons."</p>
      <p>"That's all?"</p>
      <p>"That's all, Professor Aronnax, and the calculation is easy to
check. Now then, I have supplementary ballast tanks capable of
shipping 100 metric tons of water. So I can descend to considerable
depths. When I want to rise again and lie flush with the surface,
all I have to do is expel that water; and if I desire that the
<i>Nautilus</i> emerge above the waves to one–tenth of its
total capacity, I empty all the ballast tanks completely."</p>
      <p>This logic, backed up by figures, left me without a single
objection.</p>
      <p>"I accept your calculations, Captain," I replied, "and I'd be
ill–mannered to dispute them, since your daily experience
bears them out. But at this juncture, I have a hunch that we're
still left with one real difficulty."</p>
      <p>"What's that, sir?"</p>
      <p>"When you're at a depth of 1,000 meters, the <i>Nautilus's</i>
plating bears a pressure of 100 atmospheres. If at this point you
want to empty the supplementary ballast tanks in order to lighten
your boat and rise to the surface, your pumps must overcome that
pressure of 100 atmospheres, which is 100 kilograms per each square
centimeter. This demands a strength—"</p>
      <p>"That electricity alone can give me," Captain Nemo said swiftly.
"Sir, I repeat: the dynamic power of my engines is nearly infinite.
The <i>Nautilus's</i> pumps have prodigious strength, as you must
have noticed when their waterspouts swept like a torrent over the
<i>Abraham Lincoln</i>. Besides, I use my supplementary ballast
tanks only to reach an average depth of 1,500 to 2,000 meters, and
that with a view to conserving my machinery. Accordingly, when I
have a mind to visit the ocean depths two or three vertical leagues
beneath the surface, I use maneuvers that are more
time–consuming but no less infallible."</p>
      <p>"What are they, Captain?" I asked.</p>
      <p>"Here I'm naturally led into telling you how the <i>Nautilus</i>
is maneuvered."</p>
      <p>"I can't wait to find out."</p>
      <p>"In order to steer this boat to port or starboard, in short, to
make turns on a horizontal plane, I use an ordinary,
wide–bladed rudder that's fastened to the rear of the
sternpost and worked by a wheel and tackle. But I can also move the
<i>Nautilus</i> upward and downward on a vertical plane by the
simple method of slanting its two fins, which are attached to its
sides at its center of flotation; these fins are flexible, able to
assume any position, and can be operated from inside by means of
powerful levers. If these fins stay parallel with the boat, the
latter moves horizontally. If they slant, the <i>Nautilus</i>
follows the angle of that slant and, under its propeller's thrust,
either sinks on a diagonal as steep as it suits me, or rises on
that diagonal. And similarly, if I want to return more swiftly to
the surface, I throw the propeller in gear, and the water's
pressure makes the <i>Nautilus</i> rise vertically, as an air
balloon inflated with hydrogen lifts swiftly into the skies."</p>
      <p>"Bravo, Captain!" I exclaimed. "But in the midst of the waters,
how can your helmsman follow the course you've given him?"</p>
      <p>"My helmsman is stationed behind the windows of a pilothouse,
which protrudes from the topside of the <i>Nautilus's</i> hull and
is fitted with biconvex glass."</p>
      <p>"Is glass capable of resisting such pressures?"</p>
      <p>"Perfectly capable. Though fragile on impact, crystal can still
offer considerable resistance. In 1864, during experiments on
fishing by electric light in the middle of the North Sea, glass
panes less than seven millimeters thick were seen to resist a
pressure of sixteen atmospheres, all the while letting through
strong, heat–generating rays whose warmth was unevenly
distributed. Now then, I use glass windows measuring no less than
twenty–one centimeters at their centers; in other words,
they've thirty times the thickness."</p>
      <p>"Fair enough, captain, but if we're going to see, we need light
to drive away the dark, and in the midst of the murky waters, I
wonder how your helmsman can—"</p>
      <p>"Set astern of the pilothouse is a powerful electric reflector
whose rays light up the sea for a distance of half a mile."</p>
      <p>"Oh, bravo! Bravo three times over, Captain! That explains the
phosphorescent glow from this so–called narwhale that so
puzzled us scientists! Pertinent to this, I'll ask you if the
<i>Nautilus's</i> running afoul of the <i>Scotia</i>, which caused
such a great uproar, was the result of an accidental
encounter?"</p>
      <p>"Entirely accidental, sir. I was navigating two meters beneath
the surface of the water when the collision occurred. However, I
could see that it had no dire consequences."</p>
      <p>"None, sir. But as for your encounter with the <i>Abraham
Lincoln</i> . . . ?"</p>
      <p>"Professor, that troubled me, because it's one of the best ships
in the gallant American navy, but they attacked me and I had to
defend myself! All the same, I was content simply to put the
frigate in a condition where it could do me no harm; it won't have
any difficulty getting repairs at the nearest port."</p>
      <p>"Ah, Commander," I exclaimed with conviction, "your
<i>Nautilus</i> is truly a marvelous boat!"</p>
      <p>"Yes, professor," Captain Nemo replied with genuine excitement,
"and I love it as if it were my own flesh and blood! Aboard a
conventional ship, facing the ocean's perils, danger lurks
everywhere; on the surface of the sea, your chief sensation is the
constant feeling of an underlying chasm, as the Dutchman Jansen so
aptly put it; but below the waves aboard the <i>Nautilus</i>, your
heart never fails you! There are no structural deformities to worry
about, because the double hull of this boat has the rigidity of
iron; no rigging to be worn out by rolling and pitching on the
waves; no sails for the wind to carry off; no boilers for steam to
burst open; no fires to fear, because this submersible is made of
sheet iron not wood; no coal to run out of, since electricity is
its mechanical force; no collisions to fear, because it navigates
the watery deep all by itself; no storms to brave, because just a
few meters beneath the waves, it finds absolute tranquility! There,
sir. There's the ideal ship! And if it's true that the engineer has
more confidence in a craft than the builder, and the builder more
than the captain himself, you can understand the utter abandon with
which I place my trust in this <i>Nautilus</i>, since I'm its
captain, builder, and engineer all in one!"</p>
      <p>Captain Nemo spoke with winning eloquence. The fire in his eyes
and the passion in his gestures transfigured him. Yes, he loved his
ship the same way a father loves his child!</p>
      <p>But one question, perhaps indiscreet, naturally popped up, and I
couldn't resist asking it.</p>
      <p>"You're an engineer, then, Captain Nemo?"</p>
      <p>"Yes, professor," he answered me. "I studied in London, Paris,
and New York back in the days when I was a resident of the Earth's
continents."</p>
      <p>"But how were you able to build this wonderful <i>Nautilus</i>
in secret?"</p>
      <p>"Each part of it, Professor Aronnax, came from a different spot
on the globe and reached me at a cover address. Its keel was forged
by Creusot in France, its propeller shaft by Pen &amp; Co. in
London, the sheet–iron plates for its hull by Laird's in
Liverpool, its propeller by Scott's in Glasgow. Its tanks were
manufactured by Cail &amp; Co. in Paris, its engine by Krupp in
Prussia, its spur by the Motala workshops in Sweden, its precision
instruments by Hart Bros. in New York, etc.; and each of these
suppliers received my specifications under a different name."</p>
      <p>"But," I went on, "once these parts were manufactured, didn't
they have to be mounted and adjusted?"</p>
      <p>"Professor, I set up my workshops on a deserted islet in
midocean. There our <i>Nautilus</i> was completed by me and my
workmen, in other words, by my gallant companions whom I've molded
and educated. Then, when the operation was over, we burned every
trace of our stay on that islet, which if I could have, I'd have
blown up."</p>
      <p>"From all this, may I assume that such a boat costs a
fortune?"</p>
      <p>"An iron ship, Professor Aronnax, runs ₣1,125 per metric
ton. Now then, the <i>Nautilus</i> has a burden of 1,500 metric
tons. Consequently, it cost ₣1,687,000, hence
₣2,000,000 including its accommodations, and ₣4,000,000
or ₣5,000,000 with all the collections and works of art it
contains."</p>
      <p>"One last question, Captain Nemo."</p>
      <p>"Ask, professor."</p>
      <p>"You're rich, then?"</p>
      <p>"Infinitely rich, sir, and without any trouble, I could pay off
the ten–billion–franc French national debt!"</p>
      <p>I gaped at the bizarre individual who had just spoken these
words. Was he playing on my credulity? Time would tell.</p>
   </body>
</topic>