<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<topic id="d2e3106">
   <title>
      <d4pSimpleEnumerator><!--1.11-->Chapter 11. </d4pSimpleEnumerator>
      <ph>The <i>Nautilus</i>
      </ph>
   </title>
   <body>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="size_plus_2">CAPTAIN NEMO</ph> stood up. I followed him.
Contrived at the rear of the dining room, a double door opened, and
I entered a room whose dimensions equaled the one I had just
left.</p>
      <p>It was a library. Tall, black–rosewood bookcases, inlaid
with copperwork, held on their wide shelves a large number of
uniformly bound books. These furnishings followed the contours of
the room, their lower parts leading to huge couches upholstered in
maroon leather and curved for maximum comfort. Light, movable
reading stands, which could be pushed away or pulled near as
desired, allowed books to be positioned on them for easy study. In
the center stood a huge table covered with pamphlets, among which
some newspapers, long out of date, were visible. Electric light
flooded this whole harmonious totality, falling from four frosted
half globes set in the scrollwork of the ceiling. I stared in
genuine wonderment at this room so ingeniously laid out, and I
couldn't believe my eyes.</p>
      <p>"Captain Nemo," I told my host, who had just stretched out on a
couch, "this is a library that would do credit to more than one
continental palace, and I truly marvel to think it can go with you
into the deepest seas."</p>
      <p>"Where could one find greater silence or solitude, professor?"
Captain Nemo replied. "Did your study at the museum afford you such
a perfect retreat?"</p>
      <p>"No, sir, and I might add that it's quite a humble one next to
yours. You own 6,000 or 7,000 volumes here . . ."</p>
      <p>"12,000, Professor Aronnax. They're my sole remaining ties with
dry land. But I was done with the shore the day my <i>Nautilus</i>
submerged for the first time under the waters. That day I purchased
my last volumes, my last pamphlets, my last newspapers, and ever
since I've chosen to believe that humanity no longer thinks or
writes. In any event, professor, these books are at your disposal,
and you may use them freely."</p>
      <p>I thanked Captain Nemo and approached the shelves of this
library. Written in every language, books on science, ethics, and
literature were there in abundance, but I didn't see a single work
on economics—they seemed to be strictly banned on board. One
odd detail: all these books were shelved indiscriminately without
regard to the language in which they were written, and this jumble
proved that the <i>Nautilus's</i> captain could read fluently
whatever volumes he chanced to pick up.</p>
      <p>Among these books I noted masterpieces by the greats of ancient
and modern times, in other words, all of humanity's finest
achievements in history, poetry, fiction, and science, from Homer
to Victor Hugo, from Xenophon to Michelet, from Rabelais to Madame
George Sand. But science, in particular, represented the major
investment of this library: books on mechanics, ballistics,
hydrography, meteorology, geography, geology, etc., held a place
there no less important than works on natural history, and I
realized that they made up the captain's chief reading. There I saw
the complete works of Humboldt, the complete Arago, as well as
works by Foucault, Henri Sainte–Claire Deville, Chasles,
Milne–Edwards, Quatrefages, John Tyndall, Faraday, Berthelot,
Father Secchi, Petermann, Commander Maury, Louis Agassiz, etc.,
plus the transactions of France's Academy of Sciences, bulletins
from the various geographical societies, etc., and in a prime
location, those two volumes on the great ocean depths that had
perhaps earned me this comparatively charitable welcome from
Captain Nemo. Among the works of Joseph Bertrand, his book entitled
The Founders of Astronomy even gave me a definite date; and since I
knew it had appeared in the course of 1865, I concluded that the
fitting out of the <i>Nautilus</i> hadn't taken place before then.
Accordingly, three years ago at the most, Captain Nemo had begun
his underwater existence. Moreover, I hoped some books even more
recent would permit me to pinpoint the date precisely; but I had
plenty of time to look for them, and I didn't want to put off any
longer our stroll through the wonders of the <i>Nautilus</i>.</p>
      <p>"Sir," I told the captain, "thank you for placing this library
at my disposal. There are scientific treasures here, and I'll take
advantage of them."</p>
      <p>"This room isn't only a library," Captain Nemo said, "it's also
a smoking room."</p>
      <p>"A smoking room?" I exclaimed. "Then one may smoke on
board?"</p>
      <p>"Surely."</p>
      <p>"In that case, sir, I'm forced to believe that you've kept up
relations with Havana."</p>
      <p>"None whatever," the captain replied. "Try this cigar, Professor
Aronnax, and even though it doesn't come from Havana, it will
satisfy you if you're a connoisseur."</p>
      <p>I took the cigar offered me, whose shape recalled those from
Cuba; but it seemed to be made of gold leaf. I lit it at a small
brazier supported by an elegant bronze stand, and I inhaled my
first whiffs with the relish of a smoker who hasn't had a puff in
days.</p>
      <p>"It's excellent," I said, "but it's not from the tobacco
plant."</p>
      <p>"Right," the captain replied, "this tobacco comes from neither
Havana nor the Orient. It's a kind of nicotine–rich seaweed
that the ocean supplies me, albeit sparingly. Do you still miss
your Cubans, sir?"</p>
      <p>"Captain, I scorn them from this day forward."</p>
      <p>"Then smoke these cigars whenever you like, without debating
their origin. They bear no government seal of approval, but I
imagine they're none the worse for it."</p>
      <p>"On the contrary."</p>
      <p>Just then Captain Nemo opened a door facing the one by which I
had entered the library, and I passed into an immense, splendidly
lit lounge.</p>
      <p>It was a huge quadrilateral with canted corners, ten meters
long, six wide, five high. A luminous ceiling, decorated with
delicate arabesques, distributed a soft, clear daylight over all
the wonders gathered in this museum. For a museum it truly was, in
which clever hands had spared no expense to amass every natural and
artistic treasure, displaying them with the helter–skelter
picturesqueness that distinguishes a painter's studio.</p>
      <p>Some thirty pictures by the masters, uniformly framed and
separated by gleaming panoplies of arms, adorned walls on which
were stretched tapestries of austere design. There I saw canvases
of the highest value, the likes of which I had marveled at in
private European collections and art exhibitions. The various
schools of the old masters were represented by a Raphael Madonna, a
Virgin by Leonardo da Vinci, a nymph by Correggio, a woman by
Titian, an adoration of the Magi by Veronese, an assumption of the
Virgin by Murillo, a Holbein portrait, a monk by Velazquez, a
martyr by Ribera, a village fair by Rubens, two Flemish landscapes
by Teniers, three little genre paintings by Gerard Dow, Metsu, and
Paul Potter, two canvases by Gericault and Prud'hon, plus seascapes
by Backhuysen and Vernet. Among the works of modern art were
pictures signed by Delacroix, Ingres, Decamps, Troyon, Meissonier,
Daubigny, etc., and some wonderful miniature statues in marble or
bronze, modeled after antiquity's finest originals, stood on their
pedestals in the corners of this magnificent museum. As the
<i>Nautilus's</i> commander had predicted, my mind was already
starting to fall into that promised state of stunned amazement.</p>
      <p>"Professor," this strange man then said, "you must excuse the
informality with which I receive you, and the disorder reigning in
this lounge."</p>
      <p>"Sir," I replied, "without prying into who you are, might I
venture to identify you as an artist?"</p>
      <p>"A collector, sir, nothing more. Formerly I loved acquiring
these beautiful works created by the hand of man. I sought them
greedily, ferreted them out tirelessly, and I've been able to
gather some objects of great value. They're my last mementos of
those shores that are now dead for me. In my eyes, your modern
artists are already as old as the ancients. They've existed for
2,000 or 3,000 years, and I mix them up in my mind. The masters are
ageless."</p>
      <p>"What about these composers?" I said, pointing to sheet music by
Weber, Rossini, Mozart, Beethoven, Haydn, Meyerbeer, Hérold,
Wagner, Auber, Gounod, Victor Massé, and a number of others
scattered over a full size piano–organ, which occupied one of
the wall panels in this lounge.</p>
      <p>"These composers," Captain Nemo answered me, "are the
contemporaries of Orpheus, because in the annals of the dead, all
chronological differences fade; and I'm dead, professor, quite as
dead as those friends of yours sleeping six feet under!"</p>
      <p>Captain Nemo fell silent and seemed lost in reverie. I regarded
him with intense excitement, silently analyzing his strange facial
expression. Leaning his elbow on the corner of a valuable mosaic
table, he no longer saw me, he had forgotten my very presence.</p>
      <p>I didn't disturb his meditations but continued to pass in review
the curiosities that enriched this lounge.</p>
      <p>After the works of art, natural rarities predominated. They
consisted chiefly of plants, shells, and other exhibits from the
ocean that must have been Captain Nemo's own personal finds. In the
middle of the lounge, a jet of water, electrically lit, fell back
into a basin made from a single giant clam. The delicately
festooned rim of this shell, supplied by the biggest mollusk in the
class <i>Acephala</i>, measured about six meters in circumference;
so it was even bigger than those fine giant clams given to King
François I by the Republic of Venice, and which the Church
of Saint–Sulpice in Paris has made into two gigantic
holy–water fonts.</p>
      <p>Around this basin, inside elegant glass cases fastened with
copper bands, there were classified and labeled the most valuable
marine exhibits ever put before the eyes of a naturalist. My
professorial glee may easily be imagined.</p>
      <p>The zoophyte branch offered some very unusual specimens from its
two groups, the polyps and the echinoderms. In the first group:
organ–pipe coral, gorgonian coral arranged into fan shapes,
soft sponges from Syria, isis coral from the Molucca Islands,
sea–pen coral, wonderful coral of the genus Virgularia from
the waters of Norway, various coral of the genus Umbellularia,
alcyonarian coral, then a whole series of those madrepores that my
mentor Professor Milne–Edwards has so shrewdly classified
into divisions and among which I noted the wonderful genus
Flabellina as well as the genus Oculina from Réunion Island,
plus a <i>Neptune's chariot</i> from the Caribbean Sea—every
superb variety of coral, and in short, every species of these
unusual polyparies that congregate to form entire islands that will
one day turn into continents. Among the echinoderms, notable for
being covered with spines: starfish, feather stars, sea lilies,
free–swimming crinoids, brittle stars, sea urchins, sea
cucumbers, etc., represented a complete collection of the
individuals in this group.</p>
      <p>An excitable conchologist would surely have fainted dead away
before other, more numerous glass cases in which were classified
specimens from the mollusk branch. There I saw a collection of
incalculable value that I haven't time to describe completely.
Among these exhibits I'll mention, just for the record: an elegant
royal hammer shell from the Indian Ocean, whose evenly spaced white
spots stood out sharply against a base of red and brown; an
imperial spiny oyster, brightly colored, bristling with thorns, a
specimen rare to European museums, whose value I estimated at
₣20,000; a common hammer shell from the seas near Queensland,
very hard to come by; exotic cockles from Senegal, fragile white
bivalve shells that a single breath could pop like a soap bubble;
several varieties of watering–pot shell from Java, a sort of
limestone tube fringed with leafy folds and much fought over by
collectors; a whole series of top–shell snails—greenish
yellow ones fished up from American seas, others colored reddish
brown that patronize the waters off Queensland, the former coming
from the Gulf of Mexico and notable for their overlapping shells,
the latter some sun–carrier shells found in the southernmost
seas, finally and rarest of all, the magnificent spurred–star
shell from New Zealand; then some wonderful peppery–furrow
shells; several valuable species of cythera clams and venus clams;
the trellis wentletrap snail from Tranquebar on India's eastern
shore; a marbled turban snail gleaming with
mother–of–pearl; green parrot shells from the seas of
China; the virtually unknown cone snail from the genus
<i>Coenodullus</i>; every variety of cowry used as money in India
and Africa; a "glory–of–the–seas," the most
valuable shell in the East Indies; finally, common periwinkles,
delphinula snails, turret snails, violet snails, European cowries,
volute snails, olive shells, miter shells, helmet shells, murex
snails, whelks, harp shells, spiky periwinkles, triton snails, horn
shells, spindle shells, conch shells, spider conchs, limpets, glass
snails, sea butterflies—every kind of delicate, fragile
seashell that science has baptized with its most delightful
names.</p>
      <p>Aside and in special compartments, strings of supremely
beautiful pearls were spread out, the electric light flecking them
with little fiery sparks: pink pearls pulled from saltwater fan
shells in the Red Sea; green pearls from the rainbow abalone;
yellow, blue, and black pearls, the unusual handiwork of various
mollusks from every ocean and of certain mussels from rivers up
north; in short, several specimens of incalculable worth that had
been oozed by the rarest of shellfish. Some of these pearls were
bigger than a pigeon egg; they more than equaled the one that the
explorer Tavernier sold the Shah of Persia for ₣3,000,000,
and they surpassed that other pearl owned by the Imam of Muscat,
which I had believed to be unrivaled in the entire world.</p>
      <p>Consequently, to calculate the value of this collection was, I
should say, impossible. Captain Nemo must have spent millions in
acquiring these different specimens, and I was wondering what
financial resources he tapped to satisfy his collector's fancies,
when these words interrupted me:</p>
      <p>"You're examining my shells, professor? They're indeed able to
fascinate a naturalist; but for me they have an added charm, since
I've collected every one of them with my own two hands, and not a
sea on the globe has escaped my investigations."</p>
      <p>"I understand, Captain, I understand your delight at strolling
in the midst of this wealth. You're a man who gathers his treasure
in person. No museum in Europe owns such a collection of exhibits
from the ocean. But if I exhaust all my wonderment on them, I'll
have nothing left for the ship that carries them! I have absolutely
no wish to probe those secrets of yours! But I confess that my
curiosity is aroused to the limit by this <i>Nautilus</i>, the
motor power it contains, the equipment enabling it to operate, the
ultra powerful force that brings it to life. I see some instruments
hanging on the walls of this lounge whose purposes are unknown to
me. May I learn—"</p>
      <p>"Professor Aronnax," Captain Nemo answered me, "I've said you'd
be free aboard my vessel, so no part of the <i>Nautilus</i> is
off–limits to you. You may inspect it in detail, and I'll be
delighted to act as your guide."</p>
      <p>"I don't know how to thank you, sir, but I won't abuse your good
nature. I would only ask you about the uses intended for these
instruments of physical measure—"</p>
      <p>"Professor, these same instruments are found in my stateroom,
where I'll have the pleasure of explaining their functions to you.
But beforehand, come inspect the cabin set aside for you. You need
to learn how you'll be lodged aboard the <i>Nautilus</i>."</p>
      <p>I followed Captain Nemo, who, via one of the doors cut into the
lounge's canted corners, led me back down the ship's gangways. He
took me to the bow, and there I found not just a cabin but an
elegant stateroom with a bed, a washstand, and various other
furnishings.</p>
      <p>I could only thank my host.</p>
      <p>"Your stateroom adjoins mine," he told me, opening a door, "and
mine leads into that lounge we've just left."</p>
      <p>I entered the captain's stateroom. It had an austere, almost
monastic appearance. An iron bedstead, a worktable, some washstand
fixtures. Subdued lighting. No luxuries. Just the bare
necessities.</p>
      <p>Captain Nemo showed me to a bench.</p>
      <p>"Kindly be seated," he told me.</p>
      <p>I sat, and he began speaking as follows:</p>
   </body>
</topic>