<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<topic id="d2e3843">
   <title>
      <d4pSimpleEnumerator><!--1.14-->Chapter 14. </d4pSimpleEnumerator>
      <ph>The Black Current</ph>
   </title>
   <body>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="size_plus_2">THE PART OF THE</ph> planet earth that the
seas occupy has been assessed at 3,832,558 square myriameters,
hence more than 38,000,000,000 hectares. This liquid mass totals
2,250,000,000 cubic miles and could form a sphere with a diameter
of sixty leagues, whose weight would be three quintillion metric
tons. To appreciate such a number, we should remember that a
quintillion is to a billion what a billion is to one, in other
words, there are as many billions in a quintillion as ones in a
billion! Now then, this liquid mass nearly equals the total amount
of water that has poured through all the earth's rivers for the
past 40,000 years!</p>
      <p>During prehistoric times, an era of fire was followed by an era
of water. At first there was ocean everywhere. Then, during the
Silurian period, the tops of mountains gradually appeared above the
waves, islands emerged, disappeared beneath temporary floods, rose
again, were fused to form continents, and finally the earth's
geography settled into what we have today. Solid matter had wrested
from liquid matter some 37,657,000 square miles, hence
12,916,000,000 hectares.</p>
      <p>The outlines of the continents allow the seas to be divided into
five major parts: the frozen Arctic and Antarctic oceans, the
Indian Ocean, the Atlantic Ocean, and the Pacific Ocean.</p>
      <p>The Pacific Ocean extends north to south between the two polar
circles and east to west between America and Asia over an expanse
of 145° of longitude. It's the most tranquil of the seas; its
currents are wide and slow–moving, its tides moderate, its
rainfall abundant. And this was the ocean that I was first destined
to cross under these strangest of auspices.</p>
      <p>"If you don't mind, professor," Captain Nemo told me, "we'll
determine our exact position and fix the starting point of our
voyage. It's fifteen minutes before noon. I'm going to rise to the
surface of the water."</p>
      <p>The captain pressed an electric bell three times. The pumps
began to expel water from the ballast tanks; on the pressure gauge,
a needle marked the decreasing pressures that indicated the
<i>Nautilus's</i> upward progress; then the needle stopped.</p>
      <p>"Here we are," the Captain said.</p>
      <p>I made my way to the central companionway, which led to the
platform. I climbed its metal steps, passed through the open
hatches, and arrived topside on the <i>Nautilus</i>.</p>
      <p>The platform emerged only eighty centimeters above the waves.
The <i>Nautilus's</i> bow and stern boasted that
spindle–shaped outline that had caused the ship to be
compared appropriately to a long cigar. I noted the slight overlap
of its sheet–iron plates, which resembled the scales covering
the bodies of our big land reptiles. So I had a perfectly natural
explanation for why, despite the best spyglasses, this boat had
always been mistaken for a marine animal.</p>
      <p>Near the middle of the platform, the skiff was half set in the
ship's hull, making a slight bulge. Fore and aft stood two cupolas
of moderate height, their sides slanting and partly inset with
heavy biconvex glass, one reserved for the helmsman steering the
<i>Nautilus</i>, the other for the brilliance of the powerful
electric beacon lighting his way.</p>
      <p>The sea was magnificent, the skies clear. This long aquatic
vehicle could barely feel the broad undulations of the ocean. A
mild breeze out of the east rippled the surface of the water. Free
of all mist, the horizon was ideal for taking sights.</p>
      <p>There was nothing to be seen. Not a reef, not an islet. No more
<i>Abraham Lincoln</i>. A deserted immenseness.</p>
      <p>Raising his sextant, Captain Nemo took the altitude of the sun,
which would give him his latitude. He waited for a few minutes
until the orb touched the rim of the horizon. While he was taking
his sights, he didn't move a muscle, and the instrument couldn't
have been steadier in hands made out of marble.</p>
      <p>"Noon," he said. "Professor, whenever you're ready. . . ."</p>
      <p>I took one last look at the sea, a little yellowish near the
landing places of Japan, and I went below again to the main
lounge.</p>
      <p>There the captain fixed his position and used a chronometer to
calculate his longitude, which he double–checked against his
previous observations of hour angles. Then he told me:</p>
      <p>"Professor Aronnax, we're in longitude 137° 15'
west—"</p>
      <p>"West of which meridian?" I asked quickly, hoping the captain's
reply might give me a clue to his nationality.</p>
      <p>"Sir," he answered me, "I have chronometers variously set to the
meridians of Paris, Greenwich, and Washington, D.C. But in your
honor, I'll use the one for Paris."</p>
      <p>This reply told me nothing. I bowed, and the commander went
on:</p>
      <p>"We're in longitude 137° 15' west of the meridian of Paris,
and latitude 30° 7' north, in other words, about 300 miles from
the shores of Japan. At noon on this day of November 8, we hereby
begin our voyage of exploration under the waters."</p>
      <p>"May God be with us!" I replied.</p>
      <p>"And now, professor," the captain added, "I'll leave you to your
intellectual pursuits. I've set our course east–northeast at
a depth of fifty meters. Here are some large–scale charts on
which you'll be able to follow that course. The lounge is at your
disposal, and with your permission, I'll take my leave."</p>
      <p>Captain Nemo bowed. I was left to myself, lost in my thoughts.
They all centered on the <i>Nautilus's</i> commander. Would I ever
learn the nationality of this eccentric man who had boasted of
having none? His sworn hate for humanity, a hate that perhaps was
bent on some dreadful revenge—what had provoked it? Was he
one of those unappreciated scholars, one of those geniuses
"embittered by the world," as Conseil expressed it, a
latter–day Galileo, or maybe one of those men of science,
like America's Commander Maury, whose careers were ruined by
political revolutions? I couldn't say yet. As for me, whom fate had
just brought aboard his vessel, whose life he had held in the
balance: he had received me coolly but hospitably. Only, he never
took the hand I extended to him. He never extended his own.</p>
      <p>For an entire hour I was deep in these musings, trying to probe
this mystery that fascinated me so. Then my eyes focused on a huge
world map displayed on the table, and I put my finger on the very
spot where our just–determined longitude and latitude
intersected.</p>
      <p>Like the continents, the sea has its rivers. These are exclusive
currents that can be identified by their temperature and color, the
most remarkable being the one called the Gulf Stream. Science has
defined the global paths of five chief currents: one in the north
Atlantic, a second in the south Atlantic, a third in the north
Pacific, a fourth in the south Pacific, and a fifth in the southern
Indian Ocean. Also it's likely that a sixth current used to exist
in the northern Indian Ocean, when the Caspian and Aral Seas joined
up with certain large Asian lakes to form a single uniform expanse
of water.</p>
      <p>Now then, at the spot indicated on the world map, one of these
seagoing rivers was rolling by, the Kuroshio of the Japanese, the
Black Current: heated by perpendicular rays from the tropical sun,
it leaves the Bay of Bengal, crosses the Strait of Malacca, goes up
the shores of Asia, and curves into the north Pacific as far as the
Aleutian Islands, carrying along trunks of camphor trees and other
local items, the pure indigo of its warm waters sharply contrasting
with the ocean's waves. It was this current the <i>Nautilus</i> was
about to cross. I watched it on the map with my eyes, I saw it lose
itself in the immenseness of the Pacific, and I felt myself swept
along with it, when Ned Land and Conseil appeared in the lounge
doorway.</p>
      <p>My two gallant companions stood petrified at the sight of the
wonders on display.</p>
      <p>"Where are we?" the Canadian exclaimed. "In the Quebec
Museum?"</p>
      <p>"Begging master's pardon," Conseil answered, "but this seems
more like the Sommerard artifacts exhibition!"</p>
      <p>"My friends," I replied, signaling them to enter, "you're in
neither Canada nor France, but securely aboard the <i>Nautilus</i>,
fifty meters below sea level."</p>
      <p>"If master says so, then so be it," Conseil answered. "But in
all honesty, this lounge is enough to astonish even someone Flemish
like myself."</p>
      <p>"Indulge your astonishment, my friend, and have a look, because
there's plenty of work here for a classifier of your talents."</p>
      <p>Conseil needed no encouraging. Bending over the glass cases, the
gallant lad was already muttering choice words from the
naturalist's vocabulary: class <i>Gastropoda</i>, family
<i>Buccinoidea</i>, genus <i>Cowry</i>, species <i>Cypraea
madagascariensis</i>, etc.</p>
      <p>Meanwhile Ned Land, less dedicated to conchology, questioned me
about my interview with Captain Nemo. Had I discovered who he was,
where he came from, where he was heading, how deep he was taking
us? In short, a thousand questions I had no time to answer.</p>
      <p>I told him everything I knew—or, rather, everything I
didn't know—and I asked him what he had seen or heard on his
part.</p>
      <p>"Haven't seen or heard a thing!" the Canadian replied. "I
haven't even spotted the crew of this boat. By any chance, could
they be electric too?"</p>
      <p>"Electric?"</p>
      <p>"Oh ye gods, I'm half tempted to believe it! But back to you,
Professor Aronnax," Ned Land said, still hanging on to his ideas.
"Can't you tell me how many men are on board? Ten, twenty, fifty, a
hundred?"</p>
      <p>"I'm unable to answer you, Mr. Land. And trust me on this: for
the time being, get rid of these notions of taking over the
<i>Nautilus</i> or escaping from it. This boat is a masterpiece of
modern technology, and I'd be sorry to have missed it! Many people
would welcome the circumstances that have been handed us, just to
walk in the midst of these wonders. So keep calm, and let's see
what's happening around us."</p>
      <p>"See!" the harpooner exclaimed. "There's nothing to see, nothing
we'll ever see from this sheet–iron prison! We're simply
running around blindfolded—"</p>
      <p>Ned Land was just pronouncing these last words when we were
suddenly plunged into darkness, utter darkness. The ceiling lights
went out so quickly, my eyes literally ached, just as if we had
experienced the opposite sensation of going from the deepest gloom
to the brightest sunlight.</p>
      <p>We stood stock–still, not knowing what surprise was
waiting for us, whether pleasant or unpleasant. But a sliding sound
became audible. You could tell that some panels were shifting over
the <i>Nautilus's</i> sides.</p>
      <p>"It's the beginning of the end!" Ned Land said.</p>
      <p>". . . order <i>Hydromedusa</i>," Conseil muttered.</p>
      <p>Suddenly, through two oblong openings, daylight appeared on both
sides of the lounge. The liquid masses came into view, brightly lit
by the ship's electric outpourings. We were separated from the sea
by two panes of glass. Initially I shuddered at the thought that
these fragile partitions could break; but strong copper bands
secured them, giving them nearly infinite resistance.</p>
      <p>The sea was clearly visible for a one–mile radius around
the <i>Nautilus</i>. What a sight! What pen could describe it? Who
could portray the effects of this light through these translucent
sheets of water, the subtlety of its progressive shadings into the
ocean's upper and lower strata?</p>
      <p>The transparency of salt water has long been recognized. Its
clarity is believed to exceed that of spring water. The mineral and
organic substances it holds in suspension actually increase its
translucency. In certain parts of the Caribbean Sea, you can see
the sandy bottom with startling distinctness as deep as 145 meters
down, and the penetrating power of the sun's rays seems to give out
only at a depth of 300 meters. But in this fluid setting traveled
by the <i>Nautilus</i>, our electric glow was being generated in
the very heart of the waves. It was no longer illuminated water, it
was liquid light.</p>
      <p>If we accept the hypotheses of the microbiologist
Ehrenberg—who believes that these underwater depths are lit
up by phosphorescent organisms—nature has certainly saved one
of her most prodigious sights for residents of the sea, and I could
judge for myself from the thousandfold play of the light. On both
sides I had windows opening over these unexplored depths. The
darkness in the lounge enhanced the brightness outside, and we
stared as if this clear glass were the window of an immense
aquarium.</p>
      <p>The <i>Nautilus</i> seemed to be standing still. This was due to
the lack of landmarks. But streaks of water, parted by the ship's
spur, sometimes threaded before our eyes with extraordinary
speed.</p>
      <p>In wonderment, we leaned on our elbows before these show
windows, and our stunned silence remained unbroken until Conseil
said:</p>
      <p>"You wanted to see something, Ned my friend; well, now you have
something to see!"</p>
      <p>"How unusual!" the Canadian put in, setting aside his tantrums
and getaway schemes while submitting to this irresistible allure.
"A man would go an even greater distance just to stare at such a
sight!"</p>
      <p>"Ah!" I exclaimed. "I see our captain's way of life! He's found
himself a separate world that saves its most astonishing wonders
just for him!"</p>
      <p>"But where are the fish?" the Canadian ventured to observe. "I
don't see any fish!"</p>
      <p>"Why would you care, Ned my friend?" Conseil replied. "Since you
have no knowledge of them."</p>
      <p>"Me? A fisherman!" Ned Land exclaimed.</p>
      <p>And on this subject a dispute arose between the two friends,
since both were knowledgeable about fish, but from totally
different standpoints.</p>
      <p>Everyone knows that fish make up the fourth and last class in
the vertebrate branch. They have been quite aptly defined as:</p>
      <lq>"cold–blooded vertebrates with a double
circulatory system, breathing through gills, and designed to live
in water."</lq>
      <p>They consist of two distinct series: the series of bony fish, in
other words, those whose spines have vertebrae made of bone; and
cartilaginous fish, in other words, those whose spines have
vertebrae made of cartilage.</p>
      <p>Possibly the Canadian was familiar with this distinction, but
Conseil knew far more about it; and since he and Ned were now fast
friends, he just had to show off. So he told the harpooner:</p>
      <p>"Ned my friend, you're a slayer of fish, a highly skilled
fisherman. You've caught a large number of these fascinating
animals. But I'll bet you don't know how they're classified."</p>
      <p>"Sure I do," the harpooner replied in all seriousness. "They're
classified into fish we eat and fish we don't eat!"</p>
      <p>"Spoken like a true glutton," Conseil replied. "But tell me, are
you familiar with the differences between bony fish and
cartilaginous fish?"</p>
      <p>"Just maybe, Conseil."</p>
      <p>"And how about the subdivisions of these two large classes?"</p>
      <p>"I haven't the foggiest notion," the Canadian replied.</p>
      <p>"All right, listen and learn, Ned my friend! Bony fish are
subdivided into six orders. Primo, the <i>acanthopterygians</i>,
whose upper jaw is fully formed and free–moving, and whose
gills take the shape of a comb. This order consists of fifteen
families, in other words, three–quarters of all known fish.
Example: the common perch."</p>
      <p>"Pretty fair eating," Ned Land replied.</p>
      <p>"Secundo," Conseil went on, "the <i>abdominals</i>, whose pelvic
fins hang under the abdomen to the rear of the pectorals but aren't
attached to the shoulder bone, an order that's divided into five
families and makes up the great majority of freshwater fish.
Examples: carp, pike."</p>
      <p>"Ugh!" the Canadian put in with distinct scorn. "You can keep
the freshwater fish!"</p>
      <p>"Tertio," Conseil said, "the <i>subbrachians</i>, whose pelvic
fins are attached under the pectorals and hang directly from the
shoulder bone. This order contains four families. Examples:
flatfish such as sole, turbot, dab, plaice, brill, etc."</p>
      <p>"Excellent, really excellent!" the harpooner exclaimed,
interested in fish only from an edible viewpoint.</p>
      <p>"Quarto," Conseil went on, unabashed, "the <i>apods</i>, with
long bodies that lack pelvic fins and are covered by a heavy, often
glutinous skin, an order consisting of only one family. Examples:
common eels and electric eels."</p>
      <p>"So–so, just so–so!" Ned Land replied.</p>
      <p>"Quinto," Conseil said, "the <i>lophobranchians</i>, which have
fully formed, free–moving jaws but whose gills consist of
little tufts arranged in pairs along their gill arches. This order
includes only one family. Examples: seahorses and dragonfish."</p>
      <p>"Bad, very bad!" the harpooner replied.</p>
      <p>"Sexto and last," Conseil said, "the <i>plectognaths</i>, whose
maxillary bone is firmly attached to the side of the intermaxillary
that forms the jaw, and whose palate arch is locked to the skull by
sutures that render the jaw immovable, an order lacking true pelvic
fins and which consists of two families. Examples: puffers and
moonfish."</p>
      <p>"They're an insult to a frying pan!" the Canadian exclaimed.</p>
      <p>"Are you grasping all this, Ned my friend?" asked the scholarly
Conseil.</p>
      <p>"Not a lick of it, Conseil my friend," the harpooner replied.
"But keep going, because you fill me with fascination."</p>
      <p>"As for cartilaginous fish," Conseil went on unflappably, "they
consist of only three orders."</p>
      <p>"Good news," Ned put in.</p>
      <p>"Primo, the <i>cyclostomes</i>, whose jaws are fused into a
flexible ring and whose gill openings are simply a large number of
holes, an order consisting of only one family. Example: the
lamprey."</p>
      <p>"An acquired taste," Ned Land replied.</p>
      <p>"Secundo, the <i>selacians</i>, with gills resembling those of
the cyclostomes but whose lower jaw is free–moving. This
order, which is the most important in the class, consists of two
families. Examples: the ray and the shark."</p>
      <p>"What!" Ned Land exclaimed. "Rays and man–eaters in the
same order? Well, Conseil my friend, on behalf of the rays, I
wouldn't advise you to put them in the same fish tank!"</p>
      <p>"Tertio," Conseil replied, "The <i>sturionians</i>, whose gill
opening is the usual single slit adorned with a gill cover, an
order consisting of four genera. Example: the sturgeon."</p>
      <p>"Ah, Conseil my friend, you saved the best for last, in my
opinion anyhow! And that's all of 'em?"</p>
      <p>"Yes, my gallant Ned," Conseil replied. "And note well, even
when one has grasped all this, one still knows next to nothing,
because these families are subdivided into genera, subgenera,
species, varieties—"</p>
      <p>"All right, Conseil my friend," the harpooner said, leaning
toward the glass panel, "here come a couple of your varieties
now!"</p>
      <p>"Yes! Fish!" Conseil exclaimed. "One would think he was in front
of an aquarium!"</p>
      <p>"No," I replied, "because an aquarium is nothing more than a
cage, and these fish are as free as birds in the air!"</p>
      <p>"Well, Conseil my friend, identify them! Start naming them!" Ned
Land exclaimed.</p>
      <p>"Me?" Conseil replied. "I'm unable to! That's my employer's
bailiwick!"</p>
      <p>And in truth, although the fine lad was a classifying maniac, he
was no naturalist, and I doubt that he could tell a bonito from a
tuna. In short, he was the exact opposite of the Canadian, who knew
nothing about classification but could instantly put a name to any
fish.</p>
      <p>"A triggerfish," I said.</p>
      <p>"It's a Chinese triggerfish," Ned Land replied.</p>
      <p>"Genus <i>Balistes</i>, family <i>Scleroderma</i>, order
<i>Plectognatha</i>," Conseil muttered.</p>
      <p>Assuredly, Ned and Conseil in combination added up to one
outstanding naturalist.</p>
      <p>The Canadian was not mistaken. Cavorting around the
<i>Nautilus</i> was a school of triggerfish with flat bodies,
grainy skins, armed with stings on their dorsal fins, and with four
prickly rows of quills quivering on both sides of their tails.
Nothing could have been more wonderful than the skin covering them:
white underneath, gray above, with spots of gold sparkling in the
dark eddies of the waves. Around them, rays were undulating like
sheets flapping in the wind, and among these I spotted, much to my
glee, a Chinese ray, yellowish on its topside, a dainty pink on its
belly, and armed with three stings behind its eyes; a rare species
whose very existence was still doubted in Lacépède's
day, since that pioneering classifier of fish had seen one only in
a portfolio of Japanese drawings.</p>
      <p>For two hours a whole aquatic army escorted the <i>Nautilus</i>.
In the midst of their leaping and cavorting, while they competed
with each other in beauty, radiance, and speed, I could distinguish
some green wrasse, bewhiskered mullet marked with pairs of black
lines, white gobies from the genus <i>Eleotris</i> with curved
caudal fins and violet spots on the back, wonderful Japanese
mackerel from the genus <i>Scomber</i> with blue bodies and silver
heads, glittering azure goldfish whose name by itself gives their
full description, several varieties of porgy or gilthead (some
banded gilthead with fins variously blue and yellow, some with
horizontal heraldic bars and enhanced by a black strip around their
caudal area, some with color zones and elegantly corseted in their
six waistbands), trumpetfish with flutelike beaks that looked like
genuine seafaring woodcocks and were sometimes a meter long,
Japanese salamanders, serpentine moray eels from the genus
<i>Echidna</i> that were six feet long with sharp little eyes and a
huge mouth bristling with teeth; etc.</p>
      <p>Our wonderment stayed at an all–time fever pitch. Our
exclamations were endless. Ned identified the fish, Conseil
classified them, and as for me, I was in ecstasy over the verve of
their movements and the beauty of their forms. Never before had I
been given the chance to glimpse these animals alive and at large
in their native element.</p>
      <p>Given such a complete collection from the seas of Japan and
China, I won't mention every variety that passed before our dazzled
eyes. More numerous than birds in the air, these fish raced right
up to us, no doubt attracted by the brilliant glow of our electric
beacon.</p>
      <p>Suddenly daylight appeared in the lounge. The sheet–iron
panels slid shut. The magical vision disappeared. But for a good
while I kept dreaming away, until the moment my eyes focused on the
instruments hanging on the wall. The compass still showed our
heading as east–northeast, the pressure gauge indicated a
pressure of five atmospheres (corresponding to a depth of fifty
meters), and the electric log gave our speed as fifteen miles per
hour.</p>
      <p>I waited for Captain Nemo. But he didn't appear. The clock
marked the hour of five.</p>
      <p>Ned Land and Conseil returned to their cabin. As for me, I
repaired to my stateroom. There I found dinner ready for me. It
consisted of turtle soup made from the daintiest hawksbill, a red
mullet with white, slightly flaky flesh, whose liver, when
separately prepared, makes delicious eating, plus loin of imperial
angelfish, whose flavor struck me as even better than salmon.</p>
      <p>I spent the evening in reading, writing, and thinking. Then
drowsiness overtook me, I stretched out on my eelgrass mattress,
and I fell into a deep slumber, while the <i>Nautilus</i> glided
through the swiftly flowing Black Current.</p>
   </body>
</topic>