<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<topic id="d2e485">
   <title>
      <d4pSimpleEnumerator><!--1.1-->Chapter 1. </d4pSimpleEnumerator>
      <ph>A Runaway Reef</ph>
   </title>
   <body>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="size_plus_2">THE YEAR</ph> 1866 was marked by a bizarre
development, an unexplained and downright inexplicable phenomenon
that surely no one has forgotten. Without getting into those rumors
that upset civilians in the seaports and deranged the public mind
even far inland, it must be said that professional seamen were
especially alarmed. Traders, shipowners, captains of vessels,
skippers, and master mariners from Europe and America, naval
officers from every country, and at their heels the various
national governments on these two continents, were all extremely
disturbed by the business.</p>
      <p>In essence, over a period of time several ships had encountered
"an enormous thing" at sea, a long spindle–shaped object,
sometimes giving off a phosphorescent glow, infinitely bigger and
faster than any whale.</p>
      <p>The relevant data on this apparition, as recorded in various
logbooks, agreed pretty closely as to the structure of the object
or creature in question, its unprecedented speed of movement, its
startling locomotive power, and the unique vitality with which it
seemed to be gifted. If it was a <i>cetacean</i>, it exceeded in
bulk any whale previously classified by science. No naturalist,
neither Cuvier nor Lacépède, neither Professor
Dumeril nor Professor de Quatrefages, would have accepted the
existence of such a monster sight unseen—specifically, unseen
by their own scientific eyes.</p>
      <p>Striking an average of observations taken at different
times—rejecting those timid estimates that gave the object a
length of 200 feet, and ignoring those exaggerated views that saw
it as a mile wide and three long—you could still assert that
this phenomenal creature greatly exceeded the dimensions of
anything then known to ichthyologists, if it existed at all.</p>
      <p>Now then, it did exist, this was an undeniable fact; and since
the human mind dotes on objects of wonder, you can understand the
worldwide excitement caused by this unearthly apparition. As for
relegating it to the realm of fiction, that charge had to be
dropped.</p>
      <p>In essence, on July 20, 1866, the steamer <i>Governor
Higginson</i>, from the Calcutta &amp; Burnach Steam Navigation
Co., encountered this moving mass five miles off the eastern shores
of Australia.</p>
      <p>Captain Baker at first thought he was in the presence of an
unknown reef; he was even about to fix its exact position when two
waterspouts shot out of this inexplicable object and sprang hissing
into the air some 150 feet. So, unless this reef was subject to the
intermittent eruptions of a geyser, the <i>Governor Higginson</i>
had fair and honest dealings with some aquatic mammal, until then
unknown, that could spurt from its blowholes waterspouts mixed with
air and steam.</p>
      <p>Similar events were likewise observed in Pacific seas, on July
23 of the same year, by the <i>Christopher Columbus</i> from the
West India &amp; Pacific Steam Navigation Co. Consequently, this
extraordinary <i>cetacean</i> could transfer itself from one
locality to another with startling swiftness, since within an
interval of just three days, the <i>Governor Higginson</i> and the
<i>Christopher Columbus</i> had observed it at two positions on the
charts separated by a distance of more than 700 nautical
leagues.</p>
      <p>Fifteen days later and 2,000 leagues farther, the
<i>Helvetia</i> from the Compagnie Nationale and the <i>Shannon</i>
from the Royal Mail line, running on opposite tacks in that part of
the Atlantic lying between the United States and Europe,
respectively signaled each other that the monster had been sighted
in latitude 42° 15' north and longitude 60° 35' west of the
meridian of Greenwich. From their simultaneous observations, they
were able to estimate the mammal's minimum length at more than 350
English feet;<fn callout="*">Author's Note: About 106 meters.
An English foot is only 30.4 centimeters.</fn> this was because both the
<i>Shannon</i> and the <i>Helvetia</i> were of smaller dimensions,
although each measured 100 meters stem to stern. Now then, the
biggest whales, those rorqual whales that frequent the waterways of
the Aleutian Islands, have never exceeded a length of 56
meters—if they reach even that.</p>
      <p>One after another, reports arrived that would profoundly affect
public opinion: new observations taken by the transatlantic liner
<i>Pereire</i>, the Inman line's <i>Etna</i> running afoul of the
monster, an official report drawn up by officers on the French
frigate <i>Normandy</i>, dead–earnest reckonings obtained by
the general staff of Commodore Fitz–James aboard the <i>Lord
Clyde</i>. In lighthearted countries, people joked about this
phenomenon, but such serious, practical countries as England,
America, and Germany were deeply concerned.</p>
      <p>In every big city the monster was the latest rage; they sang
about it in the coffee houses, they ridiculed it in the newspapers,
they dramatized it in the theaters. The tabloids found it a fine
opportunity for hatching all sorts of hoaxes. In those newspapers
short of copy, you saw the reappearance of every gigantic imaginary
creature, from "Moby Dick," that dreadful white whale from the High
Arctic regions, to the stupendous kraken whose tentacles could
entwine a 500–ton craft and drag it into the ocean depths.
They even reprinted reports from ancient times: the views of
Aristotle and Pliny accepting the existence of such monsters, then
the Norwegian stories of Bishop Pontoppidan, the narratives of Paul
Egede, and finally the reports of Captain Harrington—whose
good faith is above suspicion—in which he claims he saw,
while aboard the <i>Castilian</i> in 1857, one of those enormous
serpents that, until then, had frequented only the seas of France's
old extremist newspaper, <i>The Constitutionalist</i>.</p>
      <p>An interminable debate then broke out between believers and
skeptics in the scholarly societies and scientific journals. The
"monster question" inflamed all minds. During this memorable
campaign, journalists making a profession of science battled with
those making a profession of wit, spilling waves of ink and some of
them even two or three drops of blood, since they went from sea
serpents to the most offensive personal remarks.</p>
      <p>For six months the war seesawed. With inexhaustible zest, the
popular press took potshots at feature articles from the Geographic
Institute of Brazil, the Royal Academy of Science in Berlin, the
British Association, the Smithsonian Institution in Washington,
D.C., at discussions in The Indian Archipelago, in <i>Cosmos</i>
published by Father Moigno, in Petermann's
<i>Mittheilungen</i>,<fn callout="*">German: "Bulletin."
Ed.</fn> and at
scientific chronicles in the great French and foreign newspapers.
When the monster's detractors cited a saying by the botanist
Linnaeus that "nature doesn't make leaps," witty writers in the
popular periodicals parodied it, maintaining in essence that
"nature doesn't make lunatics," and ordering their contemporaries
never to give the lie to nature by believing in krakens, sea
serpents, "Moby Dicks," and other all–out efforts from
drunken seamen. Finally, in a much–feared satirical journal,
an article by its most popular columnist finished off the monster
for good, spurning it in the style of Hippolytus repulsing the
amorous advances of his stepmother Phædra, and giving the
creature its quietus amid a universal burst of laughter. Wit had
defeated science.</p>
      <p>During the first months of the year 1867, the question seemed to
be buried, and it didn't seem due for resurrection, when new facts
were brought to the public's attention. But now it was no longer an
issue of a scientific problem to be solved, but a quite real and
serious danger to be avoided. The question took an entirely new
turn. The monster again became an islet, rock, or reef, but a
runaway reef, unfixed and elusive.</p>
      <p>On March 5, 1867, the <i>Moravian</i> from the Montreal Ocean
Co., lying during the night in latitude 27° 30' and longitude
72° 15', ran its starboard quarter afoul of a rock marked on no
charts of these waterways. Under the combined efforts of wind and
400–horsepower steam, it was traveling at a speed of thirteen
knots. Without the high quality of its hull, the <i>Moravian</i>
would surely have split open from this collision and gone down
together with those 237 passengers it was bringing back from
Canada.</p>
      <p>This accident happened around five o'clock in the morning, just
as day was beginning to break. The officers on watch rushed to the
craft's stern. They examined the ocean with the most scrupulous
care. They saw nothing except a strong eddy breaking three cable
lengths out, as if those sheets of water had been violently
churned. The site's exact bearings were taken, and the
<i>Moravian</i> continued on course apparently undamaged. Had it
run afoul of an underwater rock or the wreckage of some enormous
derelict ship? They were unable to say. But when they examined its
undersides in the service yard, they discovered that part of its
keel had been smashed.</p>
      <p>This occurrence, extremely serious in itself, might perhaps have
been forgotten like so many others, if three weeks later it hadn't
been reenacted under identical conditions. Only, thanks to the
nationality of the ship victimized by this new ramming, and thanks
to the reputation of the company to which this ship belonged, the
event caused an immense uproar.</p>
      <p>No one is unaware of the name of that famous English shipowner,
Cunard. In 1840 this shrewd industrialist founded a postal service
between Liverpool and Halifax, featuring three wooden ships with
400–horsepower paddle wheels and a burden of 1,162 metric
tons. Eight years later, the company's assets were increased by
four 650–horsepower ships at 1,820 metric tons, and in two
more years, by two other vessels of still greater power and
tonnage. In 1853 the Cunard Co., whose mail–carrying charter
had just been renewed, successively added to its assets the
<i>Arabia</i>, the <i>Persia</i>, the <i>China</i>, the
<i>Scotia</i>, the <i>Java</i>, and the <i>Russia</i>, all ships of
top speed and, after the <i>Great Eastern</i>, the biggest ever to
plow the seas. So in 1867 this company owned twelve ships, eight
with paddle wheels and four with propellers.</p>
      <p>If I give these highly condensed details, it is so everyone can
fully understand the importance of this maritime transportation
company, known the world over for its shrewd management. No
transoceanic navigational undertaking has been conducted with more
ability, no business dealings have been crowned with greater
success. In twenty–six years Cunard ships have made 2,000
Atlantic crossings without so much as a voyage canceled, a delay
recorded, a man, a craft, or even a letter lost. Accordingly,
despite strong competition from France, passengers still choose the
Cunard line in preference to all others, as can be seen in a recent
survey of official documents. Given this, no one will be astonished
at the uproar provoked by this accident involving one of its finest
steamers.</p>
      <p>On April 13, 1867, with a smooth sea and a moderate breeze, the
<i>Scotia</i> lay in longitude 15° 12' and latitude 45°
37'. It was traveling at a speed of 13.43 knots under the thrust of
its 1,000–horsepower engines. Its paddle wheels were churning
the sea with perfect steadiness. It was then drawing 6.7 meters of
water and displacing 6,624 cubic meters.</p>
      <p>At 4:17 in the afternoon, during a high tea for passengers
gathered in the main lounge, a collision occurred, scarcely
noticeable on the whole, affecting the <i>Scotia's</i> hull in that
quarter a little astern of its port paddle wheel.</p>
      <p>The <i>Scotia</i> hadn't run afoul of something, it had been
fouled, and by a cutting or perforating instrument rather than a
blunt one. This encounter seemed so minor that nobody on board
would have been disturbed by it, had it not been for the shouts of
crewmen in the hold, who climbed on deck yelling:</p>
      <p>"We're sinking! We're sinking!"</p>
      <p>At first the passengers were quite frightened, but Captain
Anderson hastened to reassure them. In fact, there could be no
immediate danger. Divided into seven compartments by watertight
bulkheads, the <i>Scotia</i> could brave any leak with
impunity.</p>
      <p>Captain Anderson immediately made his way into the hold. He
discovered that the fifth compartment had been invaded by the sea,
and the speed of this invasion proved that the leak was
considerable. Fortunately this compartment didn't contain the
boilers, because their furnaces would have been abruptly
extinguished.</p>
      <p>Captain Anderson called an immediate halt, and one of his
sailors dived down to assess the damage. Within moments they had
located a hole two meters in width on the steamer's underside. Such
a leak could not be patched, and with its paddle wheels half
swamped, the <i>Scotia</i> had no choice but to continue its
voyage. By then it lay 300 miles from Cape Clear, and after three
days of delay that filled Liverpool with acute anxiety, it entered
the company docks.</p>
      <p>The engineers then proceeded to inspect the <i>Scotia</i>, which
had been put in dry dock. They couldn't believe their eyes. Two and
a half meters below its waterline, there gaped a symmetrical gash
in the shape of an isosceles triangle. This breach in the sheet
iron was so perfectly formed, no punch could have done a cleaner
job of it. Consequently, it must have been produced by a
perforating tool of uncommon toughness—plus, after being
launched with prodigious power and then piercing four centimeters
of sheet iron, this tool had needed to withdraw itself by a
backward motion truly inexplicable.</p>
      <p>This was the last straw, and it resulted in arousing public
passions all over again. Indeed, from this moment on, any maritime
casualty without an established cause was charged to the monster's
account. This outrageous animal had to shoulder responsibility for
all derelict vessels, whose numbers are unfortunately considerable,
since out of those 3,000 ships whose losses are recorded annually
at the marine insurance bureau, the figure for steam or sailing
ships supposedly lost with all hands, in the absence of any news,
amounts to at least 200!</p>
      <p>Now then, justly or unjustly, it was the "monster" who stood
accused of their disappearance; and since, thanks to it, travel
between the various continents had become more and more dangerous,
the public spoke up and demanded straight out that, at all cost,
the seas be purged of this fearsome <i>cetacean</i>.</p>
   </body>
</topic>