<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<topic id="d2e4859">
   <title>
      <d4pSimpleEnumerator><!--1.17-->Chapter 17. </d4pSimpleEnumerator>
      <ph>An Underwater Forest</ph>
   </title>
   <body>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="size_plus_2">WE HAD FINALLY</ph> arrived on the outskirts
of this forest, surely one of the finest in Captain Nemo's immense
domains. He regarded it as his own and had laid the same claim to
it that, in the first days of the world, the first men had to their
forests on land. Besides, who else could dispute his ownership of
this underwater property? What other, bolder pioneer would come, ax
in hand, to clear away its dark underbrush?</p>
      <p>This forest was made up of big treelike plants, and when we
entered beneath their huge arches, my eyes were instantly struck by
the unique arrangement of their branches—an arrangement that
I had never before encountered.</p>
      <p>None of the weeds carpeting the seafloor, none of the branches
bristling from the shrubbery, crept, or leaned, or stretched on a
horizontal plane. They all rose right up toward the surface of the
ocean. Every filament or ribbon, no matter how thin, stood ramrod
straight. Fucus plants and creepers were growing in stiff
perpendicular lines, governed by the density of the element that
generated them. After I parted them with my hands, these otherwise
motionless plants would shoot right back to their original
positions. It was the regime of verticality.</p>
      <p>I soon grew accustomed to this bizarre arrangement, likewise to
the comparative darkness surrounding us. The seafloor in this
forest was strewn with sharp chunks of stone that were hard to
avoid. Here the range of underwater flora seemed pretty
comprehensive to me, as well as more abundant than it might have
been in the arctic or tropical zones, where such exhibits are less
common. But for a few minutes I kept accidentally confusing the two
kingdoms, mistaking zoophytes for water plants, animals for
vegetables. And who hasn't made the same blunder? Flora and fauna
are so closely associated in the underwater world!</p>
      <p>I observed that all these exhibits from the vegetable kingdom
were attached to the seafloor by only the most makeshift methods.
They had no roots and didn't care which solid objects secured them,
sand, shells, husks, or pebbles; they didn't ask their hosts for
sustenance, just a point of purchase. These plants are entirely
self–propagating, and the principle of their existence lies
in the water that sustains and nourishes them. In place of leaves,
most of them sprouted blades of unpredictable shape, which were
confined to a narrow gamut of colors consisting only of pink,
crimson, green, olive, tan, and brown. There I saw again, but not
yet pressed and dried like the <i>Nautilus's</i> specimens, some
peacock's tails spread open like fans to stir up a cooling breeze,
scarlet rosetangle, sea tangle stretching out their young and
edible shoots, twisting strings of kelp from the genus
<i>Nereocystis</i> that bloomed to a height of fifteen meters,
bouquets of mermaid's cups whose stems grew wider at the top, and a
number of other open–sea plants, all without flowers. "It's
an odd anomaly in this bizarre element!" as one witty naturalist
puts it. "The animal kingdom blossoms, and the vegetable kingdom
doesn't!"</p>
      <p>These various types of shrubbery were as big as trees in the
temperate zones; in the damp shade between them, there were
clustered actual bushes of moving flowers, hedges of zoophytes in
which there grew stony coral striped with twisting furrows,
yellowish sea anemone from the genus <i>Caryophylia</i> with
translucent tentacles, plus anemone with grassy tufts from the
genus <i>Zoantharia</i>; and to complete the illusion, minnows
flitted from branch to branch like a swarm of hummingbirds, while
there rose underfoot, like a covey of snipe, yellow fish from the
genus <i>Lepisocanthus</i> with bristling jaws and sharp scales,
flying gurnards, and pinecone fish.</p>
      <p>Near one o'clock, Captain Nemo gave the signal to halt. Speaking
for myself, I was glad to oblige, and we stretched out beneath an
arbor of winged kelp, whose long thin tendrils stood up like
arrows.</p>
      <p>This short break was a delight. It lacked only the charm of
conversation. But it was impossible to speak, impossible to reply.
I simply nudged my big copper headpiece against Conseil's
headpiece. I saw a happy gleam in the gallant lad's eyes, and to
communicate his pleasure, he jiggled around inside his carapace in
the world's silliest way.</p>
      <p>After four hours of strolling, I was quite astonished not to
feel any intense hunger. What kept my stomach in such a good mood
I'm unable to say. But, in exchange, I experienced that
irresistible desire for sleep that comes over every diver.
Accordingly, my eyes soon closed behind their heavy glass windows
and I fell into an uncontrollable doze, which until then I had been
able to fight off only through the movements of our walking.
Captain Nemo and his muscular companion were already stretched out
in this clear crystal, setting us a fine naptime example.</p>
      <p>How long I was sunk in this torpor I cannot estimate; but when I
awoke, it seemed as if the sun were settling toward the horizon.
Captain Nemo was already up, and I had started to stretch my limbs,
when an unexpected apparition brought me sharply to my feet.</p>
      <p>A few paces away, a monstrous, meter–high sea spider was
staring at me with beady eyes, poised to spring at me. Although my
diving suit was heavy enough to protect me from this animal's
bites, I couldn't keep back a shudder of horror. Just then Conseil
woke up, together with the <i>Nautilus's</i> sailor. Captain Nemo
alerted his companion to this hideous crustacean, which a swing of
the rifle butt quickly brought down, and I watched the monster's
horrible legs writhing in dreadful convulsions.</p>
      <p>This encounter reminded me that other, more daunting animals
must be lurking in these dark reaches, and my diving suit might not
be adequate protection against their attacks. Such thoughts hadn't
previously crossed my mind, and I was determined to keep on my
guard. Meanwhile I had assumed this rest period would be the
turning point in our stroll, but I was mistaken; and instead of
heading back to the <i>Nautilus</i>, Captain Nemo continued his
daring excursion.</p>
      <p>The seafloor kept sinking, and its significantly steeper slope
took us to greater depths. It must have been nearly three o'clock
when we reached a narrow valley gouged between high, vertical walls
and located 150 meters down. Thanks to the perfection of our
equipment, we had thus gone ninety meters below the limit that
nature had, until then, set on man's underwater excursions.</p>
      <p>I say 150 meters, although I had no instruments for estimating
this distance. But I knew that the sun's rays, even in the clearest
seas, could reach no deeper. So at precisely this point the
darkness became profound. Not a single object was visible past ten
paces. Consequently, I had begun to grope my way when suddenly I
saw the glow of an intense white light. Captain Nemo had just
activated his electric device. His companion did likewise. Conseil
and I followed suit. By turning a switch, I established contact
between the induction coil and the glass spiral, and the sea, lit
up by our four lanterns, was illuminated for a radius of
twenty–five meters.</p>
      <p>Captain Nemo continued to plummet into the dark depths of this
forest, whose shrubbery grew ever more sparse. I observed that
vegetable life was disappearing more quickly than animal life. The
open–sea plants had already left behind the increasingly arid
seafloor, where a prodigious number of animals were still swarming:
zoophytes, articulates, mollusks, and fish.</p>
      <p>While we were walking, I thought the lights of our Ruhmkorff
devices would automatically attract some inhabitants of these dark
strata. But if they did approach us, at least they kept at a
distance regrettable from the hunter's standpoint. Several times I
saw Captain Nemo stop and take aim with his rifle; then, after
sighting down its barrel for a few seconds, he would straighten up
and resume his walk.</p>
      <p>Finally, at around four o'clock, this marvelous excursion came
to an end. A wall of superb rocks stood before us, imposing in its
sheer mass: a pile of gigantic stone blocks, an enormous granite
cliffside pitted with dark caves but not offering a single gradient
we could climb up. This was the underpinning of Crespo Island. This
was land.</p>
      <p>The captain stopped suddenly. A gesture from him brought us to a
halt, and however much I wanted to clear this wall, I had to stop.
Here ended the domains of Captain Nemo. He had no desire to pass
beyond them. Farther on lay a part of the globe he would no longer
tread underfoot.</p>
      <p>Our return journey began. Captain Nemo resumed the lead in our
little band, always heading forward without hesitation. I noted
that we didn't follow the same path in returning to the
<i>Nautilus</i>. This new route, very steep and hence very arduous,
quickly took us close to the surface of the sea. But this return to
the upper strata wasn't so sudden that decompression took place too
quickly, which could have led to serious organic disorders and
given us those internal injuries so fatal to divers. With great
promptness, the light reappeared and grew stronger; and the
refraction of the sun, already low on the horizon, again ringed the
edges of various objects with the entire color spectrum.</p>
      <p>At a depth of ten meters, we walked amid a swarm of small fish
from every species, more numerous than birds in the air, more agile
too; but no aquatic game worthy of a gunshot had yet been offered
to our eyes.</p>
      <p>Just then I saw the captain's weapon spring to his shoulder and
track a moving object through the bushes. A shot went off, I heard
a faint hissing, and an animal dropped a few paces away, literally
struck by lightning.</p>
      <p>It was a magnificent sea otter from the genus <i>Enhydra</i>,
the only exclusively marine quadruped. One and a half meters long,
this otter had to be worth a good high price. Its coat, chestnut
brown above and silver below, would have made one of those
wonderful fur pieces so much in demand in the Russian and Chinese
markets; the fineness and luster of its pelt guaranteed that it
would go for at least ₣2,000. I was full of wonderment at
this unusual mammal, with its circular head adorned by short ears,
its round eyes, its white whiskers like those on a cat, its webbed
and clawed feet, its bushy tail. Hunted and trapped by fishermen,
this valuable carnivore has become extremely rare, and it takes
refuge chiefly in the northernmost parts of the Pacific, where in
all likelihood its species will soon be facing extinction.</p>
      <p>Captain Nemo's companion picked up the animal, loaded it on his
shoulder, and we took to the trail again.</p>
      <p>For an hour plains of sand unrolled before our steps. Often the
seafloor rose to within two meters of the surface of the water. I
could then see our images clearly mirrored on the underside of the
waves, but reflected upside down: above us there appeared an
identical band that duplicated our every movement and gesture; in
short, a perfect likeness of the quartet near which it walked, but
with heads down and feet in the air.</p>
      <p>Another unusual effect. Heavy clouds passed above us, forming
and fading swiftly. But after thinking it over, I realized that
these so–called clouds were caused simply by the changing
densities of the long ground swells, and I even spotted the foaming
"white caps" that their breaking crests were proliferating over the
surface of the water. Lastly, I couldn't help seeing the actual
shadows of large birds passing over our heads, swiftly skimming the
surface of the sea.</p>
      <p>On this occasion I witnessed one of the finest gunshots ever to
thrill the marrow of a hunter. A large bird with a wide wingspan,
quite clearly visible, approached and hovered over us. When it was
just a few meters above the waves, Captain Nemo's companion took
aim and fired. The animal dropped, electrocuted, and its descent
brought it within reach of our adroit hunter, who promptly took
possession of it. It was an albatross of the finest species, a
wonderful specimen of these open–sea fowl.</p>
      <p>This incident did not interrupt our walk. For two hours we were
sometimes led over plains of sand, sometimes over prairies of
seaweed that were quite arduous to cross. In all honesty, I was
dead tired by the time I spotted a hazy glow half a mile away,
cutting through the darkness of the waters. It was the
<i>Nautilus's</i> beacon. Within twenty minutes we would be on
board, and there I could breathe easy again—because my tank's
current air supply seemed to be quite low in oxygen. But I was
reckoning without an encounter that slightly delayed our
arrival.</p>
      <p>I was lagging behind some twenty paces when I saw Captain Nemo
suddenly come back toward me. With his powerful hands he sent me
buckling to the ground, while his companion did the same to
Conseil. At first I didn't know what to make of this sudden
assault, but I was reassured to observe the captain lying
motionless beside me.</p>
      <p>I was stretched out on the seafloor directly beneath some bushes
of algae, when I raised my head and spied two enormous masses
hurtling by, throwing off phosphorescent glimmers.</p>
      <p>My blood turned cold in my veins! I saw that we were under
threat from a fearsome pair of sharks. They were blue sharks,
dreadful man–eaters with enormous tails, dull, glassy stares,
and phosphorescent matter oozing from holes around their snouts.
They were like monstrous fireflies that could thoroughly pulverize
a man in their iron jaws! I don't know if Conseil was busy with
their classification, but as for me, I looked at their silver
bellies, their fearsome mouths bristling with teeth, from a
viewpoint less than scientific—more as a victim than as a
professor of natural history.</p>
      <p>Luckily these voracious animals have poor eyesight. They went by
without noticing us, grazing us with their brownish fins; and
miraculously, we escaped a danger greater than encountering a tiger
deep in the jungle.</p>
      <p>Half an hour later, guided by its electric trail, we reached the
<i>Nautilus</i>. The outside door had been left open, and Captain
Nemo closed it after we reentered the first cell. Then he pressed a
button. I heard pumps operating within the ship, I felt the water
lowering around me, and in a few moments the cell was completely
empty. The inside door opened, and we passed into the wardrobe.</p>
      <p>There our diving suits were removed, not without difficulty; and
utterly exhausted, faint from lack of food and rest, I repaired to
my stateroom, full of wonder at this startling excursion on the
bottom of the sea.</p>
   </body>
</topic>