<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<topic id="d2e4691">
   <title>
      <d4pSimpleEnumerator><!--1.16-->Chapter 16. </d4pSimpleEnumerator>
      <ph>Strolling the Plains</ph>
   </title>
   <body>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="size_plus_2">THIS CELL</ph>, properly speaking, was the
<i>Nautilus's</i> arsenal and wardrobe. Hanging from its walls, a
dozen diving outfits were waiting for anybody who wanted to take a
stroll.</p>
      <p>After seeing these, Ned Land exhibited an obvious distaste for
the idea of putting one on.</p>
      <p>"But my gallant Ned," I told him, "the forests of Crespo Island
are simply underwater forests!"</p>
      <p>"Oh great!" put in the disappointed harpooner, watching his
dreams of fresh meat fade away. "And you, Professor Aronnax, are
you going to stick yourself inside these clothes?"</p>
      <p>"It has to be, Mr. Ned."</p>
      <p>"Have it your way, sir," the harpooner replied, shrugging his
shoulders. "But speaking for myself, I'll never get into those
things unless they force me!"</p>
      <p>"No one will force you, Mr. Land," Captain Nemo said.</p>
      <p>"And is Conseil going to risk it?" Ned asked.</p>
      <p>"Where master goes, I go," Conseil replied.</p>
      <p>At the captain's summons, two crewmen came to help us put on
these heavy, waterproof clothes, made from seamless india rubber
and expressly designed to bear considerable pressures. They were
like suits of armor that were both yielding and resistant, you
might say. These clothes consisted of jacket and pants. The pants
ended in bulky footwear adorned with heavy lead soles. The fabric
of the jacket was reinforced with copper mail that shielded the
chest, protected it from the water's pressure, and allowed the
lungs to function freely; the sleeves ended in supple gloves that
didn't impede hand movements.</p>
      <p>These perfected diving suits, it was easy to see, were a far cry
from such misshapen costumes as the cork breastplates, leather
jumpers, seagoing tunics, barrel helmets, etc., invented and
acclaimed in the 18th century.</p>
      <p>Conseil and I were soon dressed in these diving suits, as were
Captain Nemo and one of his companions—a herculean type who
must have been prodigiously strong. All that remained was to encase
one's head in its metal sphere. But before proceeding with this
operation, I asked the captain for permission to examine the rifles
set aside for us.</p>
      <p>One of the <i>Nautilus's</i> men presented me with a streamlined
rifle whose butt was boilerplate steel, hollow inside, and of
fairly large dimensions. This served as a tank for the compressed
air, which a trigger–operated valve could release into the
metal chamber. In a groove where the butt was heaviest, a cartridge
clip held some twenty electric bullets that, by means of a spring,
automatically took their places in the barrel of the rifle. As soon
as one shot had been fired, another was ready to go off.</p>
      <p>"Captain Nemo," I said, "this is an ideal,
easy–to–use weapon. I ask only to put it to the test.
But how will we reach the bottom of the sea?"</p>
      <p>"Right now, professor, the <i>Nautilus</i> is aground in ten
meters of water, and we've only to depart."</p>
      <p>"But how will we set out?"</p>
      <p>"You'll see."</p>
      <p>Captain Nemo inserted his cranium into its spherical headgear.
Conseil and I did the same, but not without hearing the Canadian
toss us a sarcastic "happy hunting." On top, the suit ended in a
collar of threaded copper onto which the metal helmet was screwed.
Three holes, protected by heavy glass, allowed us to see in any
direction with simply a turn of the head inside the sphere. Placed
on our backs, the Rouquayrol device went into operation as soon as
it was in position, and for my part, I could breathe with ease.</p>
      <p>The Ruhmkorff lamp hanging from my belt, my rifle in hand, I was
ready to go forth. But in all honesty, while imprisoned in these
heavy clothes and nailed to the deck by my lead soles, it was
impossible for me to take a single step.</p>
      <p>But this circumstance had been foreseen, because I felt myself
propelled into a little room adjoining the wardrobe. Towed in the
same way, my companions went with me. I heard a door with
watertight seals close after us, and we were surrounded by profound
darkness.</p>
      <p>After some minutes a sharp hissing reached my ears. I felt a
distinct sensation of cold rising from my feet to my chest.
Apparently a stopcock inside the boat was letting in water from
outside, which overran us and soon filled up the room. Contrived in
the <i>Nautilus's</i> side, a second door then opened. We were lit
by a subdued light. An instant later our feet were treading the
bottom of the sea.</p>
      <p>And now, how can I convey the impressions left on me by this
stroll under the waters. Words are powerless to describe such
wonders! When even the painter's brush can't depict the effects
unique to the liquid element, how can the writer's pen hope to
reproduce them?</p>
      <p>Captain Nemo walked in front, and his companion followed us a
few steps to the rear. Conseil and I stayed next to each other, as
if daydreaming that through our metal carapaces, a little polite
conversation might still be possible! Already I no longer felt the
bulkiness of my clothes, footwear, and air tank, nor the weight of
the heavy sphere inside which my head was rattling like an almond
in its shell. Once immersed in water, all these objects lost a part
of their weight equal to the weight of the liquid they displaced,
and thanks to this law of physics discovered by Archimedes, I did
just fine. I was no longer an inert mass, and I had, comparatively
speaking, great freedom of movement.</p>
      <p>Lighting up the seafloor even thirty feet beneath the surface of
the ocean, the sun astonished me with its power. The solar rays
easily crossed this aqueous mass and dispersed its dark colors. I
could easily distinguish objects 100 meters away. Farther on, the
bottom was tinted with fine shades of ultramarine; then, off in the
distance, it turned blue and faded in the midst of a hazy darkness.
Truly, this water surrounding me was just a kind of air, denser
than the atmosphere on land but almost as transparent. Above me I
could see the calm surface of the ocean.</p>
      <p>We were walking on sand that was fine–grained and smooth,
not wrinkled like beach sand, which preserves the impressions left
by the waves. This dazzling carpet was a real mirror, throwing back
the sun's rays with startling intensity. The outcome: an immense
vista of reflections that penetrated every liquid molecule. Will
anyone believe me if I assert that at this thirty–foot depth,
I could see as if it was broad daylight?</p>
      <p>For a quarter of an hour, I trod this blazing sand, which was
strewn with tiny crumbs of seashell. Looming like a long reef, the
<i>Nautilus's</i> hull disappeared little by little, but when night
fell in the midst of the waters, the ship's beacon would surely
facilitate our return on board, since its rays carried with perfect
distinctness. This effect is difficult to understand for anyone who
has never seen light beams so sharply defined on shore. There the
dust that saturates the air gives such rays the appearance of a
luminous fog; but above water as well as underwater, shafts of
electric light are transmitted with incomparable clarity.</p>
      <p>Meanwhile we went ever onward, and these vast plains of sand
seemed endless. My hands parted liquid curtains that closed again
behind me, and my footprints faded swiftly under the water's
pressure.</p>
      <p>Soon, scarcely blurred by their distance from us, the forms of
some objects took shape before my eyes. I recognized the lower
slopes of some magnificent rocks carpeted by the finest zoophyte
specimens, and right off, I was struck by an effect unique to this
medium.</p>
      <p>By then it was ten o'clock in the morning. The sun's rays hit
the surface of the waves at a fairly oblique angle, decomposing by
refraction as though passing through a prism; and when this light
came in contact with flowers, rocks, buds, seashells, and polyps,
the edges of these objects were shaded with all seven hues of the
solar spectrum. This riot of rainbow tints was a wonder, a feast
for the eyes: a genuine kaleidoscope of red, green, yellow, orange,
violet, indigo, and blue; in short, the whole palette of a
color–happy painter! If only I had been able to share with
Conseil the intense sensations rising in my brain, competing with
him in exclamations of wonderment! If only I had known, like
Captain Nemo and his companion, how to exchange thoughts by means
of prearranged signals! So, for lack of anything better, I talked
to myself: I declaimed inside this copper box that topped my head,
spending more air on empty words than was perhaps advisable.</p>
      <p>Conseil, like me, had stopped before this splendid sight.
Obviously, in the presence of these zoophyte and mollusk specimens,
the fine lad was classifying his head off. Polyps and echinoderms
abounded on the seafloor: various isis coral, cornularian coral
living in isolation, tufts of virginal genus <i>Oculina</i>
formerly known by the name "white coral," prickly fungus coral in
the shape of mushrooms, sea anemone holding on by their muscular
disks, providing a literal flowerbed adorned by jellyfish from the
genus <i>Porpita</i> wearing collars of azure tentacles, and
starfish that spangled the sand, including veinlike feather stars
from the genus <i>Asterophyton</i> that were like fine lace
embroidered by the hands of water nymphs, their festoons swaying to
the faint undulations caused by our walking. It filled me with real
chagrin to crush underfoot the gleaming mollusk samples that
littered the seafloor by the thousands: concentric comb shells,
hammer shells, coquina (seashells that actually hop around),
top–shell snails, red helmet shells, angel–wing conchs,
sea hares, and so many other exhibits from this inexhaustible
ocean. But we had to keep walking, and we went forward while
overhead there scudded schools of Portuguese men–of–war
that let their ultramarine tentacles drift in their wakes, medusas
whose milky white or dainty pink parasols were festooned with azure
tassels and shaded us from the sun's rays, plus jellyfish of the
species <i>Pelagia panopyra</i> that, in the dark, would have
strewn our path with phosphorescent glimmers!</p>
      <p>All these wonders I glimpsed in the space of a quarter of a
mile, barely pausing, following Captain Nemo whose gestures kept
beckoning me onward. Soon the nature of the seafloor changed. The
plains of sand were followed by a bed of that viscous slime
Americans call "ooze," which is composed exclusively of seashells
rich in limestone or silica. Then we crossed a prairie of algae,
open–sea plants that the waters hadn't yet torn loose, whose
vegetation grew in wild profusion. Soft to the foot, these densely
textured lawns would have rivaled the most luxuriant carpets woven
by the hand of man. But while this greenery was sprawling under our
steps, it didn't neglect us overhead. The surface of the water was
crisscrossed by a floating arbor of marine plants belonging to that
superabundant algae family that numbers more than 2,000 known
species. I saw long ribbons of fucus drifting above me, some
globular, others tubular: <i>Laurencia</i>, <i>Cladostephus</i>
with the slenderest foliage, <i>Rhodymenia palmata</i> resembling
the fan shapes of cactus. I observed that green–colored
plants kept closer to the surface of the sea, while reds occupied a
medium depth, which left blacks and browns in charge of designing
gardens and flowerbeds in the ocean's lower strata.</p>
      <p>These algae are a genuine prodigy of creation, one of the
wonders of world flora. This family produces both the biggest and
smallest vegetables in the world. Because, just as 40,000
near–invisible buds have been counted in one
five–square–millimeter space, so also have fucus plants
been gathered that were over 500 meters long!</p>
      <p>We had been gone from the <i>Nautilus</i> for about an hour and
a half. It was almost noon. I spotted this fact in the
perpendicularity of the sun's rays, which were no longer refracted.
The magic of these solar colors disappeared little by little, with
emerald and sapphire shades vanishing from our surroundings
altogether. We walked with steady steps that rang on the seafloor
with astonishing intensity. The tiniest sounds were transmitted
with a speed to which the ear is unaccustomed on shore. In fact,
water is a better conductor of sound than air, and under the waves
noises carry four times as fast.</p>
      <p>Just then the seafloor began to slope sharply downward. The
light took on a uniform hue. We reached a depth of 100 meters, by
which point we were undergoing a pressure of ten atmospheres. But
my diving clothes were built along such lines that I never suffered
from this pressure. I felt only a certain tightness in the joints
of my fingers, and even this discomfort soon disappeared. As for
the exhaustion bound to accompany a two–hour stroll in such
unfamiliar trappings—it was nil. Helped by the water, my
movements were executed with startling ease.</p>
      <p>Arriving at this 300–foot depth, I still detected the
sun's rays, but just barely. Their intense brilliance had been
followed by a reddish twilight, a midpoint between day and night.
But we could see well enough to find our way, and it still wasn't
necessary to activate the Ruhmkorff device.</p>
      <p>Just then Captain Nemo stopped. He waited until I joined him,
then he pointed a finger at some dark masses outlined in the
shadows a short distance away.</p>
      <p>"It's the forest of Crespo Island," I thought; and I was not
mistaken.</p>
   </body>
</topic>