<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<topic id="d2e4308">
   <title>
      <d4pSimpleEnumerator><!--1.15-->Chapter 15. </d4pSimpleEnumerator>
      <ph>An Invitation in Writing</ph>
   </title>
   <body>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="size_plus_2">THE NEXT DAY</ph>, November 9, I woke up only
after a long, twelve–hour slumber. Conseil, a creature of
habit, came to ask "how master's night went," and to offer his
services. He had left his Canadian friend sleeping like a man who
had never done anything else.</p>
      <p>I let the gallant lad babble as he pleased, without giving him
much in the way of a reply. I was concerned about Captain Nemo's
absence during our session the previous afternoon, and I hoped to
see him again today.</p>
      <p>Soon I had put on my clothes, which were woven from strands of
seashell tissue. More than once their composition provoked comments
from Conseil. I informed him that they were made from the smooth,
silken filaments with which the fan mussel, a type of seashell
quite abundant along Mediterranean beaches, attaches itself to
rocks. In olden times, fine fabrics, stockings, and gloves were
made from such filaments, because they were both very soft and very
warm. So the <i>Nautilus's</i> crew could dress themselves at
little cost, without needing a thing from cotton growers, sheep, or
silkworms on shore.</p>
      <p>As soon as I was dressed, I made my way to the main lounge. It
was deserted.</p>
      <p>I dove into studying the conchological treasures amassed inside
the glass cases. I also investigated the huge plant albums that
were filled with the rarest marine herbs, which, although they were
pressed and dried, still kept their wonderful colors. Among these
valuable water plants, I noted various seaweed: some
<i>Cladostephus verticillatus</i>, peacock's tails,
fig–leafed caulerpa, grain–bearing beauty bushes,
delicate rosetangle tinted scarlet, sea colander arranged into fan
shapes, mermaid's cups that looked like the caps of squat mushrooms
and for years had been classified among the zoophytes; in short, a
complete series of algae.</p>
      <p>The entire day passed without my being honored by a visit from
Captain Nemo. The panels in the lounge didn't open. Perhaps they
didn't want us to get tired of these beautiful things.</p>
      <p>The <i>Nautilus</i> kept to an east–northeasterly heading,
a speed of twelve miles per hour, and a depth between fifty and
sixty meters.</p>
      <p>Next day, November 10: the same neglect, the same solitude. I
didn't see a soul from the crew. Ned and Conseil spent the better
part of the day with me. They were astonished at the captain's
inexplicable absence. Was this eccentric man ill? Did he want to
change his plans concerning us?</p>
      <p>But after all, as Conseil noted, we enjoyed complete freedom, we
were daintily and abundantly fed. Our host had kept to the terms of
his agreement. We couldn't complain, and moreover the very
uniqueness of our situation had such generous rewards in store for
us, we had no grounds for criticism.</p>
      <p>That day I started my diary of these adventures, which has
enabled me to narrate them with the most scrupulous accuracy; and
one odd detail: I wrote it on paper manufactured from marine
eelgrass.</p>
      <p>Early in the morning on November 11, fresh air poured through
the <i>Nautilus's</i> interior, informing me that we had returned
to the surface of the ocean to renew our oxygen supply. I headed
for the central companionway and climbed onto the platform.</p>
      <p>It was six o'clock. I found the weather overcast, the sea gray
but calm. Hardly a billow. I hoped to encounter Captain Nemo
there—would he come? I saw only the helmsman imprisoned in
his glass–windowed pilothouse. Seated on the ledge furnished
by the hull of the skiff, I inhaled the sea's salty aroma with
great pleasure.</p>
      <p>Little by little, the mists were dispersed under the action of
the sun's rays. The radiant orb cleared the eastern horizon. Under
its gaze, the sea caught on fire like a trail of gunpowder.
Scattered on high, the clouds were colored in bright, wonderfully
shaded hues, and numerous "ladyfingers"<fn callout="*">Author's Note:
"Ladyfingers" are small, thin, white clouds with ragged edges.</fn> warned of daylong winds.</p>
      <p>But what were mere winds to this <i>Nautilus</i>, which no
storms could intimidate!</p>
      <p>So I was marveling at this delightful sunrise, so
life–giving and cheerful, when I heard someone climbing onto
the platform.</p>
      <p>I was prepared to greet Captain Nemo, but it was his chief
officer who appeared—whom I had already met during our first
visit with the captain. He advanced over the platform, not seeming
to notice my presence. A powerful spyglass to his eye, he
scrutinized every point of the horizon with the utmost care. Then,
his examination over, he approached the hatch and pronounced a
phrase whose exact wording follows below. I remember it because,
every morning, it was repeated under the same circumstances. It ran
like this:</p>
      <lq>
         <p>"Nautron respoc lorni virch."</p>
      </lq>
      <p>What it meant I was unable to say.</p>
      <p>These words pronounced, the chief officer went below again. I
thought the <i>Nautilus</i> was about to resume its underwater
navigating. So I went down the hatch and back through the gangways
to my stateroom.</p>
      <p>Five days passed in this way with no change in our situation.
Every morning I climbed onto the platform. The same phrase was
pronounced by the same individual. Captain Nemo did not appear.</p>
      <p>I was pursuing the policy that we had seen the last of him, when
on November 16, while reentering my stateroom with Ned and Conseil,
I found a note addressed to me on the table.</p>
      <p>I opened it impatiently. It was written in a script that was
clear and neat but a bit "Old English" in style, its characters
reminding me of German calligraphy.</p>
      <p>The note was worded as follows:</p>
      <lq>
         <p>Professor Aronnax</p>
         <p>Aboard the <i>Nautilus</i>
         </p>
         <p>November 16, 1867</p>
         <p>Captain Nemo invites Professor Aronnax on a hunting trip that
will take place tomorrow morning in his Crespo Island forests. He
hopes nothing will prevent the professor from attending, and he
looks forward with pleasure to the professor's companions joining
him.</p>
         <p>CAPTAIN NEMO,</p>
         <p>Commander of the <i>Nautilus</i>.</p>
      </lq>
      <p>"A hunting trip!" Ned exclaimed.</p>
      <p>"And in his forests on Crespo Island!" Conseil added.</p>
      <p>"But does this mean the old boy goes ashore?" Ned Land went
on.</p>
      <p>"That seems to be the gist of it," I said, rereading the
letter.</p>
      <p>"Well, we've got to accept!" the Canadian answered. "Once we're
on solid ground, we'll figure out a course of action. Besides, it
wouldn't pain me to eat a couple slices of fresh venison!"</p>
      <p>Without trying to reconcile the contradictions between Captain
Nemo's professed horror of continents or islands and his invitation
to go hunting in a forest, I was content to reply:</p>
      <p>"First let's look into this Crespo Island."</p>
      <p>I consulted the world map; and in latitude 32° 40' north and
longitude 167° 50' west, I found an islet that had been
discovered in 1801 by Captain Crespo, which old Spanish charts
called Rocca de la Plata, in other words, "Silver Rock." So we were
about 1,800 miles from our starting point, and by a slight change
of heading, the <i>Nautilus</i> was bringing us back toward the
southeast.</p>
      <p>I showed my companions this small, stray rock in the middle of
the north Pacific.</p>
      <p>"If Captain Nemo does sometimes go ashore," I told them, "at
least he only picks desert islands!"</p>
      <p>Ned Land shook his head without replying; then he and Conseil
left me. After supper was served me by the mute and emotionless
steward, I fell asleep; but not without some anxieties.</p>
      <p>When I woke up the next day, November 17, I sensed that the
<i>Nautilus</i> was completely motionless. I dressed hurriedly and
entered the main lounge.</p>
      <p>Captain Nemo was there waiting for me. He stood up, bowed, and
asked if it suited me to come along.</p>
      <p>Since he made no allusion to his absence the past eight days, I
also refrained from mentioning it, and I simply answered that my
companions and I were ready to go with him.</p>
      <p>"Only, sir," I added, "I'll take the liberty of addressing a
question to you."</p>
      <p>"Address away, Professor Aronnax, and if I'm able to answer, I
will."</p>
      <p>"Well then, Captain, how is it that you've severed all ties with
the shore, yet you own forests on Crespo Island?"</p>
      <p>"Professor," the captain answered me, "these forests of mine
don't bask in the heat and light of the sun. They aren't frequented
by lions, tigers, panthers, or other quadrupeds. They're known only
to me. They grow only for me. These forests aren't on land, they're
actual underwater forests."</p>
      <p>"Underwater forests!" I exclaimed.</p>
      <p>"Yes, professor."</p>
      <p>"And you're offering to take me to them?"</p>
      <p>"Precisely."</p>
      <p>"On foot?"</p>
      <p>"Without getting your feet wet."</p>
      <p>"While hunting?"</p>
      <p>"While hunting."</p>
      <p>"Rifles in hand?"</p>
      <p>"Rifles in hand."</p>
      <p>I stared at the <i>Nautilus's</i> commander with an air anything
but flattering to the man.</p>
      <p>"Assuredly," I said to myself, "he's contracted some mental
illness. He's had a fit that's lasted eight days and isn't over
even yet. What a shame! I liked him better eccentric than
insane!"</p>
      <p>These thoughts were clearly readable on my face; but Captain
Nemo remained content with inviting me to follow him, and I did so
like a man resigned to the worst.</p>
      <p>We arrived at the dining room, where we found breakfast
served.</p>
      <p>"Professor Aronnax," the captain told me, "I beg you to share my
breakfast without formality. We can chat while we eat. Because,
although I promised you a stroll in my forests, I made no pledge to
arrange for your encountering a restaurant there. Accordingly, eat
your breakfast like a man who'll probably eat dinner only when it's
extremely late."</p>
      <p>I did justice to this meal. It was made up of various fish and
some slices of sea cucumber, that praiseworthy zoophyte, all
garnished with such highly appetizing seaweed as the <i>Porphyra
laciniata</i> and the <i>Laurencia primafetida</i>. Our beverage
consisted of clear water to which, following the captain's example,
I added some drops of a fermented liquor extracted by the Kamchatka
process from the seaweed known by name as <i>Rhodymenia
palmata</i>.</p>
      <p>At first Captain Nemo ate without pronouncing a single word.
Then he told me:</p>
      <p>"Professor, when I proposed that you go hunting in my Crespo
forests, you thought I was contradicting myself. When I informed
you that it was an issue of underwater forests, you thought I'd
gone insane. Professor, you must never make snap judgments about
your fellow man."</p>
      <p>"But, Captain, believe me—"</p>
      <p>"Kindly listen to me, and you'll see if you have grounds for
accusing me of insanity or self–contradiction."</p>
      <p>"I'm all attention."</p>
      <p>"Professor, you know as well as I do that a man can live
underwater so long as he carries with him his own supply of
breathable air. For underwater work projects, the workman wears a
waterproof suit with his head imprisoned in a metal capsule, while
he receives air from above by means of force pumps and flow
regulators."</p>
      <p>"That's the standard equipment for a diving suit," I said.</p>
      <p>"Correct, but under such conditions the man has no freedom. He's
attached to a pump that sends him air through an india–rubber
hose; it's an actual chain that fetters him to the shore, and if we
were to be bound in this way to the <i>Nautilus</i>, we couldn't go
far either."</p>
      <p>"Then how do you break free?" I asked.</p>
      <p>"We use the Rouquayrol–Denayrouze device, invented by two
of your fellow countrymen but refined by me for my own special
uses, thereby enabling you to risk these new physiological
conditions without suffering any organic disorders. It consists of
a tank built from heavy sheet iron in which I store air under a
pressure of fifty atmospheres. This tank is fastened to the back by
means of straps, like a soldier's knapsack. Its top part forms a
box where the air is regulated by a bellows mechanism and can be
released only at its proper tension. In the Rouquayrol device that
has been in general use, two india–rubber hoses leave this
box and feed to a kind of tent that imprisons the operator's nose
and mouth; one hose is for the entrance of air to be inhaled, the
other for the exit of air to be exhaled, and the tongue closes off
the former or the latter depending on the breather's needs. But in
my case, since I face considerable pressures at the bottom of the
sea, I needed to enclose my head in a copper sphere, like those
found on standard diving suits, and the two hoses for inhalation
and exhalation now feed to that sphere."</p>
      <p>"That's perfect, Captain Nemo, but the air you carry must be
quickly depleted; and once it contains no more than 15% oxygen, it
becomes unfit for breathing."</p>
      <p>"Surely, but as I told you, Professor Aronnax, the
<i>Nautilus's</i> pumps enable me to store air under considerable
pressure, and given this circumstance, the tank on my diving
equipment can supply breathable air for nine or ten hours."</p>
      <p>"I've no more objections to raise," I replied. "I'll only ask
you, Captain: how can you light your way at the bottom of the
ocean?"</p>
      <p>"With the Ruhmkorff device, Professor Aronnax. If the first is
carried on the back, the second is fastened to the belt. It
consists of a Bunsen battery that I activate not with potassium
dichromate but with sodium. An induction coil gathers the
electricity generated and directs it to a specially designed
lantern. In this lantern one finds a glass spiral that contains
only a residue of carbon dioxide gas. When the device is operating,
this gas becomes luminous and gives off a continuous whitish light.
Thus provided for, I breathe and I see."</p>
      <p>"Captain Nemo, to my every objection you give such crushing
answers, I'm afraid to entertain a single doubt. However, though I
have no choice but to accept both the Rouquayrol and Ruhmkorff
devices, I'd like to register some reservations about the rifle
with which you'll equip me."</p>
      <p>"But it isn't a rifle that uses gunpowder," the captain
replied.</p>
      <p>"Then it's an air gun?"</p>
      <p>"Surely. How can I make gunpowder on my ship when I have no
saltpeter, sulfur, or charcoal?"</p>
      <p>"Even so," I replied, "to fire underwater in a medium that's 855
times denser than air, you'd have to overcome considerable
resistance."</p>
      <p>"That doesn't necessarily follow. There are certain
Fulton–style guns perfected by the Englishmen
Philippe–Coles and Burley, the Frenchman Furcy, and the
Italian Landi; they're equipped with a special system of airtight
fastenings and can fire in underwater conditions. But I repeat:
having no gunpowder, I've replaced it with air at high pressure,
which is abundantly supplied me by the <i>Nautilus's</i>
pumps."</p>
      <p>"But this air must be swiftly depleted."</p>
      <p>"Well, in a pinch can't my Rouquayrol tank supply me with more?
All I have to do is draw it from an ad hoc spigot.<fn callout="*">Latin: a spigot "just
for that purpose." Ed.</fn> Besides, Professor Aronnax, you'll see
for yourself that during these underwater hunting trips, we make no
great expenditure of either air or bullets."</p>
      <p>"But it seems to me that in this semidarkness, amid this liquid
that's so dense in comparison to the atmosphere, a gunshot couldn't
carry far and would prove fatal only with difficulty!"</p>
      <p>"On the contrary, sir, with this rifle every shot is fatal; and
as soon as the animal is hit, no matter how lightly, it falls as if
struck by lightning."</p>
      <p>"Why?"</p>
      <p>"Because this rifle doesn't shoot ordinary bullets but little
glass capsules invented by the Austrian chemist Leniebroek, and I
have a considerable supply of them. These glass capsules are
covered with a strip of steel and weighted with a lead base;
they're genuine little Leyden jars charged with high–voltage
electricity. They go off at the slightest impact, and the animal,
no matter how strong, drops dead. I might add that these capsules
are no bigger than number 4 shot, and the chamber of any ordinary
rifle could hold ten of them."</p>
      <p>"I'll quit debating," I replied, getting up from the table. "And
all that's left is for me to shoulder my rifle. So where you go,
I'll go."</p>
      <p>Captain Nemo led me to the <i>Nautilus's</i> stern, and passing
by Ned and Conseil's cabin, I summoned my two companions, who
instantly followed us.</p>
      <p>Then we arrived at a cell located within easy access of the
engine room; in this cell we were to get dressed for our
stroll.</p>
   </body>
</topic>