<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<topic id="d2e5009">
   <title>
      <d4pSimpleEnumerator><!--1.18-->Chapter 18. </d4pSimpleEnumerator>
      <ph>Four Thousand Leagues Under the Pacific</ph>
   </title>
   <body>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="size_plus_2">BY THE NEXT MORNING</ph>, November 18, I was
fully recovered from my exhaustion of the day before, and I climbed
onto the platform just as the <i>Nautilus's</i> chief officer was
pronouncing his daily phrase. It then occurred to me that these
words either referred to the state of the sea, or that they meant:
"There's nothing in sight."</p>
      <p>And in truth, the ocean was deserted. Not a sail on the horizon.
The tips of Crespo Island had disappeared during the night. The
sea, absorbing every color of the prism except its blue rays,
reflected the latter in every direction and sported a wonderful
indigo tint. The undulating waves regularly took on the appearance
of watered silk with wide stripes.</p>
      <p>I was marveling at this magnificent ocean view when Captain Nemo
appeared. He didn't seem to notice my presence and began a series
of astronomical observations. Then, his operations finished, he
went and leaned his elbows on the beacon housing, his eyes straying
over the surface of the ocean.</p>
      <p>Meanwhile some twenty of the <i>Nautilus's</i> sailors—all
energetic, well–built fellows—climbed onto the
platform. They had come to pull up the nets left in our wake during
the night. These seamen obviously belonged to different
nationalities, although indications of European physical traits
could be seen in them all. If I'm not mistaken, I recognized some
Irishmen, some Frenchmen, a few Slavs, and a native of either
Greece or Crete. Even so, these men were frugal of speech and used
among themselves only that bizarre dialect whose origin I couldn't
even guess. So I had to give up any notions of questioning
them.</p>
      <p>The nets were hauled on board. They were a breed of trawl
resembling those used off the Normandy coast, huge pouches held
half open by a floating pole and a chain laced through the lower
meshes. Trailing in this way from these iron glove makers, the
resulting receptacles scoured the ocean floor and collected every
marine exhibit in their path. That day they gathered up some
unusual specimens from these fish–filled waterways:
anglerfish whose comical movements qualify them for the epithet
"clowns," black Commerson anglers equipped with their antennas,
undulating triggerfish encircled by little red bands, bloated
puffers whose venom is extremely insidious, some olive–hued
lampreys, snipefish covered with silver scales, cutlass fish whose
electrocuting power equals that of the electric eel and the
electric ray, scaly featherbacks with brown crosswise bands,
greenish codfish, several varieties of goby, etc.; finally, some
fish of larger proportions: a one–meter jack with a prominent
head, several fine bonito from the genus <i>Scomber</i> decked out
in the colors blue and silver, and three magnificent tuna whose
high speeds couldn't save them from our trawl.</p>
      <p>I estimate that this cast of the net brought in more than 1,000
pounds of fish. It was a fine catch but not surprising. In essence,
these nets stayed in our wake for several hours, incarcerating an
entire aquatic world in prisons made of thread. So we were never
lacking in provisions of the highest quality, which the
<i>Nautilus's</i> speed and the allure of its electric light could
continually replenish.</p>
      <p>These various exhibits from the sea were immediately lowered
down the hatch in the direction of the storage lockers, some to be
eaten fresh, others to be preserved.</p>
      <p>After its fishing was finished and its air supply renewed, I
thought the <i>Nautilus</i> would resume its underwater excursion,
and I was getting ready to return to my stateroom, when Captain
Nemo turned to me and said without further preamble:</p>
      <p>"Look at this ocean, professor! Doesn't it have the actual gift
of life? Doesn't it experience both anger and affection? Last
evening it went to sleep just as we did, and there it is, waking up
after a peaceful night!"</p>
      <p>No hellos or good mornings for this gent! You would have thought
this eccentric individual was simply continuing a conversation we'd
already started!</p>
      <p>"See!" he went on. "It's waking up under the sun's caresses!
It's going to relive its daily existence! What a fascinating field
of study lies in watching the play of its organism. It owns a pulse
and arteries, it has spasms, and I side with the scholarly
Commander Maury, who discovered that it has a circulation as real
as the circulation of blood in animals."</p>
      <p>I'm sure that Captain Nemo expected no replies from me, and it
seemed pointless to pitch in with "Ah yes," "Exactly," or "How
right you are!" Rather, he was simply talking to himself, with long
pauses between sentences. He was meditating out loud.</p>
      <p>"Yes," he said, "the ocean owns a genuine circulation, and to
start it going, the Creator of All Things has only to increase its
heat, salt, and microscopic animal life. In essence, heat creates
the different densities that lead to currents and countercurrents.
Evaporation, which is nil in the High Arctic regions and very
active in equatorial zones, brings about a constant interchange of
tropical and polar waters. What's more, I've detected those falling
and rising currents that make up the ocean's true breathing. I've
seen a molecule of salt water heat up at the surface, sink into the
depths, reach maximum density at –2° centigrade, then
cool off, grow lighter, and rise again. At the poles you'll see the
consequences of this phenomenon, and through this law of farseeing
nature, you'll understand why water can freeze only at the
surface!"</p>
      <p>As the captain was finishing his sentence, I said to myself:
"The pole! Is this brazen individual claiming he'll take us even to
that location?"</p>
      <p>Meanwhile the captain fell silent and stared at the element he
had studied so thoroughly and unceasingly. Then, going on:</p>
      <p>"Salts," he said, "fill the sea in considerable quantities,
professor, and if you removed all its dissolved saline content,
you'd create a mass measuring 4,500,000 cubic leagues, which if it
were spread all over the globe, would form a layer more than ten
meters high. And don't think that the presence of these salts is
due merely to some whim of nature. No. They make ocean water less
open to evaporation and prevent winds from carrying off excessive
amounts of steam, which, when condensing, would submerge the
temperate zones. Salts play a leading role, the role of stabilizer
for the general ecology of the globe!"</p>
      <p>Captain Nemo stopped, straightened up, took a few steps along
the platform, and returned to me:</p>
      <p>"As for those billions of tiny animals," he went on, "those
infusoria that live by the millions in one droplet of water,
800,000 of which are needed to weigh one milligram, their role is
no less important. They absorb the marine salts, they assimilate
the solid elements in the water, and since they create coral and
madrepores, they're the true builders of limestone continents! And
so, after they've finished depriving our water drop of its mineral
nutrients, the droplet gets lighter, rises to the surface, there
absorbs more salts left behind through evaporation, gets heavier,
sinks again, and brings those tiny animals new elements to absorb.
The outcome: a double current, rising and falling, constant
movement, constant life! More intense than on land, more abundant,
more infinite, such life blooms in every part of this ocean, an
element fatal to man, they say, but vital to myriads of
animals—and to me!"</p>
      <p>When Captain Nemo spoke in this way, he was transfigured, and he
filled me with extraordinary excitement.</p>
      <p>"There," he added, "out there lies true existence! And I can
imagine the founding of nautical towns, clusters of underwater
households that, like the <i>Nautilus</i>, would return to the
surface of the sea to breathe each morning, free towns if ever
there were, independent cities! Then again, who knows whether some
tyrant . . ."</p>
      <p>Captain Nemo finished his sentence with a vehement gesture.
Then, addressing me directly, as if to drive away an ugly
thought:</p>
      <p>"Professor Aronnax," he asked me, "do you know the depth of the
ocean floor?"</p>
      <p>"At least, Captain, I know what the major soundings tell
us."</p>
      <p>"Could you quote them to me, so I can double–check them as
the need arises?"</p>
      <p>"Here," I replied, "are a few of them that stick in my memory.
If I'm not mistaken, an average depth of 8,200 meters was found in
the north Atlantic, and 2,500 meters in the Mediterranean. The most
remarkable soundings were taken in the south Atlantic near the 35th
parallel, and they gave 12,000 meters, 14,091 meters, and 15,149
meters. All in all, it's estimated that if the sea bottom were made
level, its average depth would be about seven kilometers."</p>
      <p>"Well, professor," Captain Nemo replied, "we'll show you better
than that, I hope. As for the average depth of this part of the
Pacific, I'll inform you that it's a mere 4,000 meters."</p>
      <p>This said, Captain Nemo headed to the hatch and disappeared down
the ladder. I followed him and went back to the main lounge. The
propeller was instantly set in motion, and the log gave our speed
as twenty miles per hour.</p>
      <p>Over the ensuing days and weeks, Captain Nemo was very frugal
with his visits. I saw him only at rare intervals. His chief
officer regularly fixed the positions I found reported on the
chart, and in such a way that I could exactly plot the
<i>Nautilus's</i> course.</p>
      <p>Conseil and Land spent the long hours with me. Conseil had told
his friend about the wonders of our undersea stroll, and the
Canadian was sorry he hadn't gone along. But I hoped an opportunity
would arise for a visit to the forests of Oceania.</p>
      <p>Almost every day the panels in the lounge were open for some
hours, and our eyes never tired of probing the mysteries of the
underwater world.</p>
      <p>The <i>Nautilus's</i> general heading was southeast, and it
stayed at a depth between 100 and 150 meters. However, from
Lord–knows–what whim, one day it did a diagonal dive by
means of its slanting fins, reaching strata located 2,000 meters
underwater. The thermometer indicated a temperature of 4.25°
centigrade, which at this depth seemed to be a temperature common
to all latitudes.</p>
      <p>On November 26, at three o'clock in the morning, the
<i>Nautilus</i> cleared the Tropic of Cancer at longitude 172°.
On the 27th it passed in sight of the Hawaiian Islands, where the
famous Captain Cook met his death on February 14, 1779. By then we
had fared 4,860 leagues from our starting point. When I arrived on
the platform that morning, I saw the Island of Hawaii two miles to
leeward, the largest of the seven islands making up this group. I
could clearly distinguish the tilled soil on its outskirts, the
various mountain chains running parallel with its coastline, and
its volcanoes, crowned by Mauna Kea, whose elevation is 5,000
meters above sea level. Among other specimens from these waterways,
our nets brought up some peacock–tailed flabellarian coral,
polyps flattened into stylish shapes and unique to this part of the
ocean.</p>
      <p>The <i>Nautilus</i> kept to its southeasterly heading. On
December 1 it cut the equator at longitude 142°, and on the 4th
of the same month, after a quick crossing marked by no incident, we
raised the Marquesas Islands. Three miles off, in latitude 8°
57' south and longitude 139° 32' west, I spotted Martin Point
on Nuku Hiva, chief member of this island group that belongs to
France. I could make out only its wooded mountains on the horizon,
because Captain Nemo hated to hug shore. There our nets brought up
some fine fish samples: dolphinfish with azure fins, gold tails,
and flesh that's unrivaled in the entire world, wrasse from the
genus <i>Hologymnosus</i> that were nearly denuded of scales but
exquisite in flavor, knifejaws with bony beaks, yellowish albacore
that were as tasty as bonito, all fish worth classifying in the
ship's pantry.</p>
      <p>After leaving these delightful islands to the protection of the
French flag, the <i>Nautilus</i> covered about 2,000 miles from
December 4 to the 11th. Its navigating was marked by an encounter
with an immense school of squid, unusual mollusks that are near
neighbors of the cuttlefish. French fishermen give them the name
"cuckoldfish," and they belong to the class <i>Cephalopoda</i>,
family <i>Dibranchiata</i>, consisting of themselves together with
cuttlefish and argonauts. The naturalists of antiquity made a
special study of them, and these animals furnished many ribald
figures of speech for soapbox orators in the Greek marketplace, as
well as excellent dishes for the tables of rich citizens, if we're
to believe Athenæus, a Greek physician predating Galen.</p>
      <p>It was during the night of December 9–10 that the
<i>Nautilus</i> encountered this army of distinctly nocturnal
mollusks. They numbered in the millions. They were migrating from
the temperate zones toward zones still warmer, following the
itineraries of herring and sardines. We stared at them through our
thick glass windows: they swam backward with tremendous speed,
moving by means of their locomotive tubes, chasing fish and
mollusks, eating the little ones, eaten by the big ones, and
tossing in indescribable confusion the ten feet that nature has
rooted in their heads like a hairpiece of pneumatic snakes. Despite
its speed, the <i>Nautilus</i> navigated for several hours in the
midst of this school of animals, and its nets brought up an
incalculable number, among which I recognized all nine species that
Professor Orbigny has classified as native to the Pacific
Ocean.</p>
      <p>During this crossing, the sea continually lavished us with the
most marvelous sights. Its variety was infinite. It changed its
setting and decor for the mere pleasure of our eyes, and we were
called upon not simply to contemplate the works of our Creator in
the midst of the liquid element, but also to probe the ocean's most
daunting mysteries.</p>
      <p>During the day of December 11, I was busy reading in the main
lounge. Ned Land and Conseil were observing the luminous waters
through the gaping panels. The <i>Nautilus</i> was motionless. Its
ballast tanks full, it was sitting at a depth of 1,000 meters in a
comparatively unpopulated region of the ocean where only larger
fish put in occasional appearances.</p>
      <p>Just then I was studying a delightful book by Jean Macé,
<i>The Servants of the Stomach</i>, and savoring its ingenious
teachings, when Conseil interrupted my reading.</p>
      <p>"Would master kindly come here for an instant?" he said to me in
an odd voice.</p>
      <p>"What is it, Conseil?"</p>
      <p>"It's something that master should see."</p>
      <p>I stood up, went, leaned on my elbows before the window, and I
saw it.</p>
      <p>In the broad electric daylight, an enormous black mass, quite
motionless, hung suspended in the midst of the waters. I observed
it carefully, trying to find out the nature of this gigantic
<i>cetacean</i>. Then a sudden thought crossed my mind.</p>
      <p>"A ship!" I exclaimed.</p>
      <p>"Yes," the Canadian replied, "a disabled craft that's sinking
straight down!"</p>
      <p>Ned Land was not mistaken. We were in the presence of a ship
whose severed shrouds still hung from their clasps. Its hull looked
in good condition, and it must have gone under only a few hours
before. The stumps of three masts, chopped off two feet above the
deck, indicated a flooding ship that had been forced to sacrifice
its masting. But it had heeled sideways, filling completely, and it
was listing to port even yet. A sorry sight, this carcass lost
under the waves, but sorrier still was the sight on its deck,
where, lashed with ropes to prevent their being washed overboard,
some human corpses still lay! I counted four of them—four
men, one still standing at the helm—then a woman, halfway out
of a skylight on the afterdeck, holding a child in her arms. This
woman was young. Under the brilliant lighting of the
<i>Nautilus's</i> rays, I could make out her features, which the
water hadn't yet decomposed. With a supreme effort, she had lifted
her child above her head, and the poor little creature's arms were
still twined around its mother's neck! The postures of the four
seamen seemed ghastly to me, twisted from convulsive movements, as
if making a last effort to break loose from the ropes that bound
them to their ship. And the helmsman, standing alone, calmer, his
face smooth and serious, his grizzled hair plastered to his brow,
his hands clutching the wheel, seemed even yet to be guiding his
wrecked three–master through the ocean depths!</p>
      <p>What a scene! We stood dumbstruck, hearts pounding, before this
shipwreck caught in the act, as if it had been photographed in its
final moments, so to speak! And already I could see enormous sharks
moving in, eyes ablaze, drawn by the lure of human flesh!</p>
      <p>Meanwhile, turning, the <i>Nautilus</i> made a circle around the
sinking ship, and for an instant I could read the board on its
stern:</p>
      <lq>
         <p>The Florida<ph outputclass="br"/>
Sunderland, England</p>
      </lq>
   </body>
</topic>