<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<topic id="d2e5927">
   <title>
      <d4pSimpleEnumerator><!--1.21-->Chapter 21. </d4pSimpleEnumerator>
      <ph>Some Days Ashore</ph>
   </title>
   <body>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="size_plus_2">STEPPING ASHORE</ph> had an exhilarating
effect on me. Ned Land tested the soil with his foot, as if he were
laying claim to it. Yet it had been only two months since we had
become, as Captain Nemo expressed it, "passengers on the
<i>Nautilus</i>," in other words, the literal prisoners of its
commander.</p>
      <p>In a few minutes we were a gunshot away from the coast. The soil
was almost entirely madreporic, but certain dry stream beds were
strewn with granite rubble, proving that this island was of
primordial origin. The entire horizon was hidden behind a curtain
of wonderful forests. Enormous trees, sometimes as high as 200
feet, were linked to each other by garlands of tropical creepers,
genuine natural hammocks that swayed in a mild breeze. There were
mimosas, banyan trees, beefwood, teakwood, hibiscus, screw pines,
palm trees, all mingling in wild profusion; and beneath the shade
of their green canopies, at the feet of their gigantic trunks,
there grew orchids, leguminous plants, and ferns.</p>
      <p>Meanwhile, ignoring all these fine specimens of Papuan flora,
the Canadian passed up the decorative in favor of the functional.
He spotted a coconut palm, beat down some of its fruit, broke them
open, and we drank their milk and ate their meat with a pleasure
that was a protest against our standard fare on the
<i>Nautilus</i>.</p>
      <p>"Excellent!" Ned Land said.</p>
      <p>"Exquisite!" Conseil replied.</p>
      <p>"And I don't think," the Canadian said, "that your Nemo would
object to us stashing a cargo of coconuts aboard his vessel?"</p>
      <p>"I imagine not," I replied, "but he won't want to sample
them."</p>
      <p>"Too bad for him!" Conseil said.</p>
      <p>"And plenty good for us!" Ned Land shot back. "There'll be more
left over!"</p>
      <p>"A word of caution, Mr. Land," I told the harpooner, who was
about to ravage another coconut palm. "Coconuts are admirable
things, but before we stuff the skiff with them, it would be wise
to find out whether this island offers other substances just as
useful. Some fresh vegetables would be well received in the
<i>Nautilus's</i> pantry."</p>
      <p>"Master is right," Conseil replied, "and I propose that we set
aside three places in our longboat: one for fruit, another for
vegetables, and a third for venison, of which I still haven't
glimpsed the tiniest specimen."</p>
      <p>"Don't give up so easily, Conseil," the Canadian replied.</p>
      <p>"So let's continue our excursion," I went on, "but keep a sharp
lookout. This island seems uninhabited, but it still might harbor
certain individuals who aren't so finicky about the sort of game
they eat!"</p>
      <p>"Hee hee!" Ned put in, with a meaningful movement of his
jaws.</p>
      <p>"Ned! Oh horrors!" Conseil exclaimed.</p>
      <p>"Ye gods," the Canadian shot back, "I'm starting to appreciate
the charms of cannibalism!"</p>
      <p>"Ned, Ned! Don't say that!" Conseil answered. "You a cannibal?
Why, I'll no longer be safe next to you, I who share your cabin!
Does this mean I'll wake up half devoured one fine day?"</p>
      <p>"I'm awfully fond of you, Conseil my friend, but not enough to
eat you when there's better food around."</p>
      <p>"Then I daren't delay," Conseil replied. "The hunt is on! We
absolutely must bag some game to placate this man–eater, or
one of these mornings master won't find enough pieces of his
manservant to serve him."</p>
      <p>While exchanging this chitchat, we entered beneath the dark
canopies of the forest, and for two hours we explored it in every
direction.</p>
      <p>We couldn't have been luckier in our search for edible
vegetation, and some of the most useful produce in the tropical
zones supplied us with a valuable foodstuff missing on board.</p>
      <p>I mean the breadfruit tree, which is quite abundant on Gueboroa
Island, and there I chiefly noted the seedless variety that in
Malaysia is called "rima."</p>
      <p>This tree is distinguished from other trees by a straight trunk
forty feet high. To the naturalist's eye, its gracefully rounded
crown, formed of big multilobed leaves, was enough to denote the
artocarpus that has been so successfully transplanted to the
Mascarene Islands east of</p>
      <p>Madagascar. From its mass of greenery, huge globular fruit stood
out, a decimeter wide and furnished on the outside with creases
that assumed a hexangular pattern. It's a handy plant that nature
gives to regions lacking in wheat; without needing to be
cultivated, it bears fruit eight months out of the year.</p>
      <p>Ned Land was on familiar terms with this fruit. He had already
eaten it on his many voyages and knew how to cook its edible
substance. So the very sight of it aroused his appetite, and he
couldn't control himself.</p>
      <p>"Sir," he told me, "I'll die if I don't sample a little
breadfruit pasta!"</p>
      <p>"Sample some, Ned my friend, sample all you like. We're here to
conduct experiments, let's conduct them."</p>
      <p>"It won't take a minute," the Canadian replied.</p>
      <p>Equipped with a magnifying glass, he lit a fire of deadwood that
was soon crackling merrily. Meanwhile Conseil and I selected the
finest <i>artocarpus</i> fruit. Some still weren't ripe enough, and
their thick skins covered white, slightly fibrous pulps. But a
great many others were yellowish and gelatinous, just begging to be
picked.</p>
      <p>This fruit contained no pits. Conseil brought a dozen of them to
Ned Land, who cut them into thick slices and placed them over a
fire of live coals, all the while repeating:</p>
      <p>"You'll see, sir, how tasty this bread is!"</p>
      <p>"Especially since we've gone without baked goods for so long,"
Conseil said.</p>
      <p>"It's more than just bread," the Canadian added. "It's a dainty
pastry. You've never eaten any, sir?"</p>
      <p>"No, Ned."</p>
      <p>"All right, get ready for something downright delectable! If you
don't come back for seconds, I'm no longer the King of
Harpooners!"</p>
      <p>After a few minutes, the parts of the fruit exposed to the fire
were completely toasted. On the inside there appeared some white
pasta, a sort of soft bread center whose flavor reminded me of
artichoke.</p>
      <p>This bread was excellent, I must admit, and I ate it with great
pleasure.</p>
      <p>"Unfortunately," I said, "this pasta won't stay fresh, so it
seems pointless to make a supply for on board."</p>
      <p>"By thunder, sir!" Ned Land exclaimed. "There you go, talking
like a naturalist, but meantime I'll be acting like a baker!
Conseil, harvest some of this fruit to take with us when we go
back."</p>
      <p>"And how will you prepare it?" I asked the Canadian.</p>
      <p>"I'll make a fermented batter from its pulp that'll keep
indefinitely without spoiling. When I want some, I'll just cook it
in the galley on board—it'll have a slightly tart flavor, but
you'll find it excellent."</p>
      <p>"So, Mr. Ned, I see that this bread is all we need—"</p>
      <p>"Not quite, professor," the Canadian replied. "We need some
fruit to go with it, or at least some vegetables."</p>
      <p>"Then let's look for fruit and vegetables."</p>
      <p>When our breadfruit harvesting was done, we took to the trail to
complete this "dry–land dinner."</p>
      <p>We didn't search in vain, and near noontime we had an ample
supply of bananas. This delicious produce from the Torrid Zones
ripens all year round, and Malaysians, who give them the name
"pisang," eat them without bothering to cook them. In addition to
bananas, we gathered some enormous jackfruit with a very tangy
flavor, some tasty mangoes, and some pineapples of unbelievable
size. But this foraging took up a good deal of our time, which,
even so, we had no cause to regret.</p>
      <p>Conseil kept Ned under observation. The harpooner walked in the
lead, and during his stroll through this forest, he gathered with
sure hands some excellent fruit that should have completed his
provisions.</p>
      <p>"So," Conseil asked, "you have everything you need, Ned my
friend?"</p>
      <p>"Humph!" the Canadian put in.</p>
      <p>"What! You're complaining?"</p>
      <p>"All this vegetation doesn't make a meal," Ned replied. "Just
side dishes, dessert. But where's the soup course? Where's the
roast?"</p>
      <p>"Right," I said. "Ned promised us cutlets, which seems highly
questionable to me."</p>
      <p>"Sir," the Canadian replied, "our hunting not only isn't over,
it hasn't even started. Patience! We're sure to end up bumping into
some animal with either feathers or fur, if not in this locality,
then in another."</p>
      <p>"And if not today, then tomorrow, because we mustn't wander too
far off," Conseil added. "That's why I propose that we return to
the skiff."</p>
      <p>"What! Already!" Ned exclaimed.</p>
      <p>"We ought to be back before nightfall," I said.</p>
      <p>"But what hour is it, then?" the Canadian asked.</p>
      <p>"Two o'clock at least," Conseil replied.</p>
      <p>"How time flies on solid ground!" exclaimed Mr. Ned Land with a
sigh of regret.</p>
      <p>"Off we go!" Conseil replied.</p>
      <p>So we returned through the forest, and we completed our harvest
by making a clean sweep of some palm cabbages that had to be picked
from the crowns of their trees, some small beans that I recognized
as the "abrou" of the Malaysians, and some high–quality
yams.</p>
      <p>We were overloaded when we arrived at the skiff. However, Ned
Land still found these provisions inadequate. But fortune smiled on
him. Just as we were boarding, he spotted several trees
twenty–five to thirty feet high, belonging to the palm
species. As valuable as the <i>actocarpus</i>, these trees are
justly ranked among the most useful produce in Malaysia.</p>
      <p>They were sago palms, vegetation that grows without being
cultivated; like mulberry trees, they reproduce by means of shoots
and seeds.</p>
      <p>Ned Land knew how to handle these trees. Taking his ax and
wielding it with great vigor, he soon stretched out on the ground
two or three sago palms, whose maturity was revealed by the white
dust sprinkled over their palm fronds.</p>
      <p>I watched him more as a naturalist than as a man in hunger. He
began by removing from each trunk an inch–thick strip of bark
that covered a network of long, hopelessly tangled fibers that were
puttied with a sort of gummy flour. This flour was the
starch–like sago, an edible substance chiefly consumed by the
Melanesian peoples.</p>
      <p>For the time being, Ned Land was content to chop these trunks
into pieces, as if he were making firewood; later he would extract
the flour by sifting it through cloth to separate it from its
fibrous ligaments, let it dry out in the sun, and leave it to
harden inside molds.</p>
      <p>Finally, at five o'clock in the afternoon, laden with all our
treasures, we left the island beach and half an hour later pulled
alongside the <i>Nautilus</i>. Nobody appeared on our arrival. The
enormous sheet–iron cylinder seemed deserted. Our provisions
loaded on board, I went below to my stateroom. There I found my
supper ready. I ate and then fell asleep.</p>
      <p>The next day, January 6: nothing new on board. Not a sound
inside, not a sign of life. The skiff stayed alongside in the same
place we had left it. We decided to return to Gueboroa Island. Ned
Land hoped for better luck in his hunting than on the day before,
and he wanted to visit a different part of the forest.</p>
      <p>By sunrise we were off. Carried by an inbound current, the
longboat reached the island in a matter of moments.</p>
      <p>We disembarked, and thinking it best to abide by the Canadian's
instincts, we followed Ned Land, whose long legs threatened to
outpace us.</p>
      <p>Ned Land went westward up the coast; then, fording some stream
beds, he reached open plains that were bordered by wonderful
forests. Some kingfishers lurked along the watercourses, but they
didn't let us approach. Their cautious behavior proved to me that
these winged creatures knew where they stood on bipeds of our
species, and I concluded that if this island wasn't inhabited, at
least human beings paid it frequent visits.</p>
      <p>After crossing a pretty lush prairie, we arrived on the
outskirts of a small wood, enlivened by the singing and soaring of
a large number of birds.</p>
      <p>"Still, they're merely birds," Conseil said.</p>
      <p>"But some are edible," the harpooner replied.</p>
      <p>"Wrong, Ned my friend," Conseil answered, "because I see only
ordinary parrots here."</p>
      <p>"Conseil my friend," Ned replied in all seriousness, "parrots
are like pheasant to people with nothing else on their plates."</p>
      <p>"And I might add," I said, "that when these birds are properly
cooked, they're at least worth a stab of the fork."</p>
      <p>Indeed, under the dense foliage of this wood, a whole host of
parrots fluttered from branch to branch, needing only the proper
upbringing to speak human dialects. At present they were cackling
in chorus with parakeets of every color, with solemn cockatoos that
seemed to be pondering some philosophical problem, while bright red
lories passed by like pieces of bunting borne on the breeze, in the
midst of kalao parrots raucously on the wing, Papuan lories painted
the subtlest shades of azure, and a whole variety of delightful
winged creatures, none terribly edible.</p>
      <p>However, one bird unique to these shores, which never passes
beyond the boundaries of the Aru and Papuan Islands, was missing
from this collection. But I was given a chance to marvel at it soon
enough.</p>
      <p>After crossing through a moderately dense thicket, we again
found some plains obstructed by bushes. There I saw some
magnificent birds soaring aloft, the arrangement of their long
feathers causing them to head into the wind. Their undulating
flight, the grace of their aerial curves, and the play of their
colors allured and delighted the eye. I had no trouble identifying
them.</p>
      <p>"Birds of paradise!" I exclaimed.</p>
      <p>"Order <i>Passeriforma</i>, division <i>Clystomora</i>," Conseil
replied.</p>
      <p>"Partridge family?" Ned Land asked.</p>
      <p>"I doubt it, Mr. Land. Nevertheless, I'm counting on your
dexterity to catch me one of these delightful representatives of
tropical nature!"</p>
      <p>"I'll give it a try, professor, though I'm handier with a
harpoon than a rifle."</p>
      <p>Malaysians, who do a booming business in these birds with the
Chinese, have various methods for catching them that we couldn't
use. Sometimes they set snares on the tops of the tall trees that
the bird of paradise prefers to inhabit. At other times they
capture it with a tenacious glue that paralyzes its movements. They
will even go so far as to poison the springs where these fowl
habitually drink. But in our case, all we could do was fire at them
on the wing, which left us little chance of getting one. And in
truth, we used up a good part of our ammunition in vain.</p>
      <p>Near eleven o'clock in the morning, we cleared the lower slopes
of the mountains that form the island's center, and we still hadn't
bagged a thing. Hunger spurred us on. The hunters had counted on
consuming the proceeds of their hunting, and they had
miscalculated. Luckily, and much to his surprise, Conseil pulled
off a right–and–left shot and insured our breakfast. He
brought down a white pigeon and a ringdove, which were briskly
plucked, hung from a spit, and roasted over a blazing fire of
deadwood. While these fascinating animals were cooking, Ned
prepared some bread from the <i>artocarpus</i>. Then the pigeon and
ringdove were devoured to the bones and declared excellent. Nutmeg,
on which these birds habitually gorge themselves, sweetens their
flesh and makes it delicious eating.</p>
      <p>"They taste like chicken stuffed with truffles," Conseil
said.</p>
      <p>"All right, Ned," I asked the Canadian, "now what do you
need?"</p>
      <p>"Game with four paws, Professor Aronnax," Ned Land replied. "All
these pigeons are only appetizers, snacks. So till I've bagged an
animal with cutlets, I won't be happy!"</p>
      <p>"Nor I, Ned, until I've caught a bird of paradise."</p>
      <p>"Then let's keep hunting," Conseil replied, "but while heading
back to the sea. We've arrived at the foothills of these mountains,
and I think we'll do better if we return to the forest
regions."</p>
      <p>It was good advice and we took it. After an hour's walk we
reached a genuine sago palm forest. A few harmless snakes fled
underfoot. Birds of paradise stole off at our approach, and I was
in real despair of catching one when Conseil, walking in the lead,
stooped suddenly, gave a triumphant shout, and came back to me,
carrying a magnificent bird of paradise.</p>
      <p>"Oh bravo, Conseil!" I exclaimed.</p>
      <p>"Master is too kind," Conseil replied.</p>
      <p>"Not at all, my boy. That was a stroke of genius, catching one
of these live birds with your bare hands!"</p>
      <p>"If master will examine it closely, he'll see that I deserve no
great praise."</p>
      <p>"And why not, Conseil?"</p>
      <p>"Because this bird is as drunk as a lord."</p>
      <p>"Drunk?"</p>
      <p>"Yes, master, drunk from the nutmegs it was devouring under that
nutmeg tree where I caught it. See, Ned my friend, see the
monstrous results of intemperance!"</p>
      <p>"Damnation!" the Canadian shot back. "Considering the amount of
gin I've had these past two months, you've got nothing to complain
about!"</p>
      <p>Meanwhile I was examining this unusual bird. Conseil was not
mistaken. Tipsy from that potent juice, our bird of paradise had
been reduced to helplessness. It was unable to fly. It was barely
able to walk. But this didn't alarm me, and I just let it sleep off
its nutmeg.</p>
      <p>This bird belonged to the finest of the eight species credited
to Papua and its neighboring islands. It was a "great emerald," one
of the rarest birds of paradise. It measured three decimeters long.
Its head was comparatively small, and its eyes, placed near the
opening of its beak, were also small. But it offered a wonderful
mixture of hues: a yellow beak, brown feet and claws, hazel wings
with purple tips, pale yellow head and scruff of the neck, emerald
throat, the belly and chest maroon to brown. Two strands, made of a
horn substance covered with down, rose over its tail, which was
lengthened by long, very light feathers of wonderful fineness, and
they completed the costume of this marvelous bird that the
islanders have poetically named "the sun bird."</p>
      <p>How I wished I could take this superb bird of paradise back to
Paris, to make a gift of it to the zoo at the Botanical Gardens,
which doesn't own a single live specimen.</p>
      <p>"So it must be a rarity or something?" the Canadian asked, in
the tone of a hunter who, from the viewpoint of his art, gives the
game a pretty low rating.</p>
      <p>"A great rarity, my gallant comrade, and above all very hard to
capture alive. And even after they're dead, there's still a major
market for these birds. So the natives have figured out how to
create fake ones, like people create fake pearls or diamonds."</p>
      <p>"What!" Conseil exclaimed. "They make counterfeit birds of
paradise?"</p>
      <p>"Yes, Conseil."</p>
      <p>"And is master familiar with how the islanders go about it?"</p>
      <p>"Perfectly familiar. During the easterly monsoon season, birds
of paradise lose the magnificent feathers around their tails that
naturalists call 'below–the–wing' feathers. These
feathers are gathered by the fowl forgers and skillfully fitted
onto some poor previously mutilated parakeet. Then they paint over
the suture, varnish the bird, and ship the fruits of their unique
labors to museums and collectors in Europe."</p>
      <p>"Good enough!" Ned Land put in. "If it isn't the right bird,
it's still the right feathers, and so long as the merchandise isn't
meant to be eaten, I see no great harm!"</p>
      <p>But if my desires were fulfilled by the capture of this bird of
paradise, those of our Canadian huntsman remained unsatisfied.
Luckily, near two o'clock Ned Land brought down a magnificent wild
pig of the type the natives call "bari–outang." This animal
came in the nick of time for us to bag some real quadruped meat,
and it was warmly welcomed. Ned Land proved himself quite
gloriously with his gunshot. Hit by an electric bullet, the pig
dropped dead on the spot.</p>
      <p>The Canadian properly skinned and cleaned it, after removing
half a dozen cutlets destined to serve as the grilled meat course
of our evening meal. Then the hunt was on again, and once more
would be marked by the exploits of Ned and Conseil.</p>
      <p>In essence, beating the bushes, the two friends flushed a herd
of kangaroos that fled by bounding away on their elastic paws. But
these animals didn't flee so swiftly that our electric capsules
couldn't catch up with them.</p>
      <p>"Oh, professor!" shouted Ned Land, whose hunting fever had gone
to his brain. "What excellent game, especially in a stew! What a
supply for the <i>Nautilus</i>! Two, three, five down! And just
think how we'll devour all this meat ourselves, while those
numbskulls on board won't get a shred!"</p>
      <p>In his uncontrollable glee, I think the Canadian might have
slaughtered the whole horde, if he hadn't been so busy talking! But
he was content with a dozen of these fascinating marsupials, which
make up the first order of aplacental mammals, as Conseil just had
to tell us.</p>
      <p>These animals were small in stature. They were a species of
those "rabbit kangaroos" that usually dwell in the hollows of trees
and are tremendously fast; but although of moderate dimensions,
they at least furnish a meat that's highly prized.</p>
      <p>We were thoroughly satisfied with the results of our hunting. A
gleeful Ned proposed that we return the next day to this magic
island, which he planned to depopulate of its every edible
quadruped. But he was reckoning without events.</p>
      <p>By six o'clock in the evening, we were back on the beach. The
skiff was aground in its usual place. The <i>Nautilus</i>, looking
like a long reef, emerged from the waves two miles offshore.</p>
      <p>Without further ado, Ned Land got down to the important business
of dinner. He came wonderfully to terms with its entire cooking.
Grilling over the coals, those cutlets from the "bari–outang"
soon gave off a succulent aroma that perfumed the air.</p>
      <p>But I catch myself following in the Canadian's footsteps. Look
at me—in ecstasy over freshly grilled pork! Please grant me a
pardon as I've already granted one to Mr. Land, and on the same
grounds!</p>
      <p>In short, dinner was excellent. Two ringdoves rounded out this
extraordinary menu. Sago pasta, bread from the <i>artocarpus</i>,
mangoes, half a dozen pineapples, and the fermented liquor from
certain coconuts heightened our glee. I suspect that my two fine
companions weren't quite as clearheaded as one could wish.</p>
      <p>"What if we don't return to the <i>Nautilus</i> this evening?"
Conseil said.</p>
      <p>"What if we never return to it?" Ned Land added.</p>
      <p>Just then a stone whizzed toward us, landed at our feet, and cut
short the harpooner's proposition.</p>
   </body>
</topic>