<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<topic id="d2e5603">
   <title>
      <d4pSimpleEnumerator><!--1.20-->Chapter 20. </d4pSimpleEnumerator>
      <ph>The Torres Strait</ph>
   </title>
   <body>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="size_plus_2">DURING THE NIGHT</ph> of December 27–28,
the <i>Nautilus</i> left the waterways of Vanikoro behind with
extraordinary speed. Its heading was southwesterly, and in three
days it had cleared the 750 leagues that separated La
Pérouse's islands from the southeastern tip of Papua.</p>
      <p>On January 1, 1868, bright and early, Conseil joined me on the
platform.</p>
      <p>"Will master," the gallant lad said to me, "allow me to wish him
a happy new year?"</p>
      <p>"Good heavens, Conseil, it's just like old times in my office at
the Botanical Gardens in Paris! I accept your kind wishes and I
thank you for them. Only, I'd like to know what you mean by a
'happy year' under the circumstances in which we're placed. Is it a
year that will bring our imprisonment to an end, or a year that
will see this strange voyage continue?"</p>
      <p>"Ye gods," Conseil replied, "I hardly know what to tell master.
We're certainly seeing some unusual things, and for two months
we've had no time for boredom. The latest wonder is always the most
astonishing, and if this progression keeps up, I can't imagine what
its climax will be. In my opinion, we'll never again have such an
opportunity."</p>
      <p>"Never, Conseil."</p>
      <p>"Besides, Mr. Nemo really lives up to his Latin name, since he
couldn't be less in the way if he didn't exist."</p>
      <p>"True enough, Conseil."</p>
      <p>"Therefore, with all due respect to master, I think a 'happy
year' would be a year that lets us see everything—"</p>
      <p>"Everything, Conseil? No year could be that long. But what does
Ned Land think about all this?"</p>
      <p>"Ned Land's thoughts are exactly the opposite of mine," Conseil
replied. "He has a practical mind and a demanding stomach. He's
tired of staring at fish and eating them day in and day out. This
shortage of wine, bread, and meat isn't suitable for an upstanding
Anglo–Saxon, a man accustomed to beefsteak and unfazed by
regular doses of brandy or gin!"</p>
      <p>"For my part, Conseil, that doesn't bother me in the least, and
I've adjusted very nicely to the diet on board."</p>
      <p>"So have I," Conseil replied. "Accordingly, I think as much
about staying as Mr. Land about making his escape. Thus, if this
new year isn't a happy one for me, it will be for him, and vice
versa. No matter what happens, one of us will be pleased. So, in
conclusion, I wish master to have whatever his heart desires."</p>
      <p>"Thank you, Conseil. Only I must ask you to postpone the
question of new year's gifts, and temporarily accept a hearty
handshake in their place. That's all I have on me."</p>
      <p>"Master has never been more generous," Conseil replied.</p>
      <p>And with that, the gallant lad went away.</p>
      <p>By January 2 we had fared 11,340 miles, hence 5,250 leagues,
from our starting point in the seas of Japan. Before the
<i>Nautilus's</i> spur there stretched the dangerous waterways of
the Coral Sea, off the northeast coast of Australia. Our boat
cruised along a few miles away from that daunting shoal where
Captain Cook's ships wellnigh miscarried on June 10, 1770. The
craft that Cook was aboard charged into some coral rock, and if his
vessel didn't go down, it was thanks to the circumstance that a
piece of coral broke off in the collision and plugged the very hole
it had made in the hull.</p>
      <p>I would have been deeply interested in visiting this long,
360–league reef, against which the ever–surging sea
broke with the fearsome intensity of thunderclaps. But just then
the <i>Nautilus's</i> slanting fins took us to great depths, and I
could see nothing of those high coral walls. I had to rest content
with the various specimens of fish brought up by our nets. Among
others I noted some long–finned albacore, a species in the
genus <i>Scomber</i>, as big as tuna, bluish on the flanks, and
streaked with crosswise stripes that disappear when the animal
dies. These fish followed us in schools and supplied our table with
very dainty flesh. We also caught a large number of
yellow–green gilthead, half a decimeter long and tasting like
dorado, plus some flying gurnards, authentic underwater swallows
that, on dark nights, alternately streak air and water with their
phosphorescent glimmers. Among mollusks and zoophytes, I found in
our trawl's meshes various species of alcyonarian coral, sea
urchins, hammer shells, spurred–star shells, wentletrap
snails, horn shells, glass snails. The local flora was represented
by fine floating algae: sea tangle, and kelp from the genus
<i>Macrocystis</i>, saturated with the mucilage their pores
perspire, from which I selected a wonderful <i>Nemastoma
geliniaroidea</i>, classifying it with the natural curiosities in
the museum.</p>
      <p>On January 4, two days after crossing the Coral Sea, we raised
the coast of Papua. On this occasion Captain Nemo told me that he
intended to reach the Indian Ocean via the Torres Strait. This was
the extent of his remarks. Ned saw with pleasure that this course
would bring us, once again, closer to European seas.</p>
      <p>The Torres Strait is regarded as no less dangerous for its
bristling reefs than for the savage inhabitants of its coasts. It
separates Queensland from the huge island of Papua, also called New
Guinea.</p>
      <p>Papua is 400 leagues long by 130 leagues wide, with a surface
area of 40,000 geographic leagues. It's located between latitude
0° 19' and 10° 2' south, and between longitude 128° 23'
and 146° 15'. At noon, while the chief officer was taking the
sun's altitude, I spotted the summits of the Arfak Mountains,
rising in terraces and ending in sharp peaks.</p>
      <p>Discovered in 1511 by the Portuguese Francisco Serrano, these
shores were successively visited by Don Jorge de Meneses in 1526,
by Juan de Grijalva in 1527, by the Spanish general Alvaro de
Saavedra in 1528, by Inigo Ortiz in 1545, by the Dutchman Schouten
in 1616, by Nicolas Sruick in 1753, by Tasman, Dampier, Fumel,
Carteret, Edwards, Bougainville, Cook, McClure, and Thomas Forrest,
by Rear Admiral d'Entrecasteaux in 1792, by Louis–Isidore
Duperrey in 1823, and by Captain Dumont d'Urville in 1827. "It's
the heartland of the blacks who occupy all Malaysia," Mr. de Rienzi
has said; and I hadn't the foggiest inkling that sailors' luck was
about to bring me face to face with these daunting Andaman
aborigines.</p>
      <p>So the <i>Nautilus</i> hove before the entrance to the world's
most dangerous strait, a passageway that even the boldest
navigators hesitated to clear: the strait that Luis Vaez de Torres
faced on returning from the South Seas in Melanesia, the strait in
which sloops of war under Captain Dumont d'Urville ran aground in
1840 and nearly miscarried with all hands. And even the
<i>Nautilus</i>, rising superior to every danger in the sea, was
about to become intimate with its coral reefs.</p>
      <p>The Torres Strait is about thirty–four leagues wide, but
it's obstructed by an incalculable number of islands, islets,
breakers, and rocks that make it nearly impossible to navigate.
Consequently, Captain Nemo took every desired precaution in
crossing it. Floating flush with the water, the <i>Nautilus</i>
moved ahead at a moderate pace. Like a <i>cetacean's</i> tail, its
propeller churned the waves slowly.</p>
      <p>Taking advantage of this situation, my two companions and I
found seats on the ever–deserted platform. In front of us
stood the pilothouse, and unless I'm extremely mistaken, Captain
Nemo must have been inside, steering his <i>Nautilus</i>
himself.</p>
      <p>Under my eyes I had the excellent charts of the Torres Strait
that had been surveyed and drawn up by the hydrographic engineer
Vincendon Dumoulin and Sublieutenant (now Admiral)
Coupvent–Desbois, who were part of Dumont d'Urville's general
staff during his final voyage to circumnavigate the globe. These,
along with the efforts of Captain King, are the best charts for
untangling the snarl of this narrow passageway, and I consulted
them with scrupulous care.</p>
      <p>Around the <i>Nautilus</i> the sea was boiling furiously. A
stream of waves, bearing from southeast to northwest at a speed of
two and a half miles per hour, broke over heads of coral emerging
here and there.</p>
      <p>"That's one rough sea!" Ned Land told me.</p>
      <p>"Abominable indeed," I replied, "and hardly suitable for a craft
like the <i>Nautilus</i>."</p>
      <p>"That damned captain," the Canadian went on, "must really be
sure of his course, because if these clumps of coral so much as
brush us, they'll rip our hull into a thousand pieces!"</p>
      <p>The situation was indeed dangerous, but as if by magic, the
<i>Nautilus</i> seemed to glide right down the middle of these
rampaging reefs. It didn't follow the exact course of the
<i>Zealous</i> and the new <i>Astrolabe</i>, which had proved so
ill–fated for Captain Dumont d'Urville. It went more to the
north, hugged the Murray Islands, and returned to the southwest
near Cumberland Passage. I thought it was about to charge
wholeheartedly into this opening, but it went up to the northwest,
through a large number of little–known islands and islets,
and steered toward Tound Island and the Bad Channel.</p>
      <p>I was already wondering if Captain Nemo, rash to the point of
sheer insanity, wanted his ship to tackle the narrows where Dumont
d'Urville's two sloops of war had gone aground, when he changed
direction a second time and cut straight to the west, heading
toward Gueboroa Island.</p>
      <p>By then it was three o'clock in the afternoon. The current was
slacking off, it was almost full tide. The <i>Nautilus</i> drew
near this island, which I can see to this day with its remarkable
fringe of screw pines. We hugged it from less than two miles
out.</p>
      <p>A sudden jolt threw me down. The <i>Nautilus</i> had just struck
a reef, and it remained motionless, listing slightly to port.</p>
      <p>When I stood up, I saw Captain Nemo and his chief officer on the
platform. They were examining the ship's circumstances, exchanging
a few words in their incomprehensible dialect.</p>
      <p>Here is what those circumstances entailed. Two miles to
starboard lay Gueboroa Island, its coastline curving north to west
like an immense arm. To the south and east, heads of coral were
already on display, left uncovered by the ebbing waters. We had run
aground at full tide and in one of those seas whose tides are
moderate, an inconvenient state of affairs for floating the
<i>Nautilus</i> off. However, the ship hadn't suffered in any way,
so solidly joined was its hull. But although it could neither sink
nor split open, it was in serious danger of being permanently
attached to these reefs, and that would have been the finish of
Captain Nemo's submersible.</p>
      <p>I was mulling this over when the captain approached, cool and
calm, forever in control of himself, looking neither alarmed nor
annoyed.</p>
      <p>"An accident?" I said to him.</p>
      <p>"No, an incident," he answered me.</p>
      <p>"But an incident," I replied, "that may oblige you to become a
resident again of these shores you avoid!"</p>
      <p>Captain Nemo gave me an odd look and gestured no. Which told me
pretty clearly that nothing would ever force him to set foot on a
land mass again. Then he said:</p>
      <p>"No, Professor Aronnax, the <i>Nautilus</i> isn't consigned to
perdition. It will still carry you through the midst of the ocean's
wonders. Our voyage is just beginning, and I've no desire to
deprive myself so soon of the pleasure of your company."</p>
      <p>"Even so, Captain Nemo," I went on, ignoring his ironic turn of
phrase, "the <i>Nautilus</i> has run aground at a moment when the
sea is full. Now then, the tides aren't strong in the Pacific, and
if you can't unballast the <i>Nautilus</i>, which seems impossible
to me, I don't see how it will float off."</p>
      <p>"You're right, professor, the Pacific tides aren't strong,"
Captain Nemo replied. "But in the Torres Strait, one still finds a
meter–and–a–half difference in level between high
and low seas. Today is January 4, and in five days the moon will be
full. Now then, I'll be quite astonished if that good–natured
satellite doesn't sufficiently raise these masses of water and do
me a favor for which I'll be forever grateful."</p>
      <p>This said, Captain Nemo went below again to the
<i>Nautilus's</i> interior, followed by his chief officer. As for
our craft, it no longer stirred, staying as motionless as if these
coral polyps had already walled it in with their indestructible
cement.</p>
      <p>"Well, sir?" Ned Land said to me, coming up after the captain's
departure.</p>
      <p>"Well, Ned my friend, we'll serenely wait for the tide on the
9th, because it seems the moon will have the good nature to float
us away!"</p>
      <p>"As simple as that?"</p>
      <p>"As simple as that."</p>
      <p>"So our captain isn't going to drop his anchors, put his engines
on the chains, and do anything to haul us off?"</p>
      <p>"Since the tide will be sufficient," Conseil replied simply.</p>
      <p>The Canadian stared at Conseil, then he shrugged his shoulders.
The seaman in him was talking now.</p>
      <p>"Sir," he answered, "you can trust me when I say this hunk of
iron will never navigate again, on the seas or under them. It's
only fit to be sold for its weight. So I think it's time we gave
Captain Nemo the slip."</p>
      <p>"Ned my friend," I replied, "unlike you, I haven't given up on
our valiant <i>Nautilus</i>, and in four days we'll know where we
stand on these Pacific tides. Besides, an escape attempt might be
timely if we were in sight of the coasts of England or Provence,
but in the waterways of Papua it's another story. And we'll always
have that as a last resort if the <i>Nautilus</i> doesn't right
itself, which I'd regard as a real calamity."</p>
      <p>"But couldn't we at least get the lay of the land?" Ned went on.
"Here's an island. On this island there are trees. Under those
trees land animals loaded with cutlets and roast beef, which I'd be
happy to sink my teeth into."</p>
      <p>"In this instance our friend Ned is right," Conseil said, "and I
side with his views. Couldn't master persuade his friend Captain
Nemo to send the three of us ashore, if only so our feet don't lose
the knack of treading on the solid parts of our planet?"</p>
      <p>"I can ask him," I replied, "but he'll refuse."</p>
      <p>"Let master take the risk," Conseil said, "and we'll know where
we stand on the captain's affability."</p>
      <p>Much to my surprise, Captain Nemo gave me the permission I asked
for, and he did so with grace and alacrity, not even exacting my
promise to return on board. But fleeing across the New Guinea
territories would be extremely dangerous, and I wouldn't have
advised Ned Land to try it. Better to be prisoners aboard the
<i>Nautilus</i> than to fall into the hands of Papuan natives.</p>
      <p>The skiff was put at our disposal for the next morning. I hardly
needed to ask whether Captain Nemo would be coming along. I
likewise assumed that no crewmen would be assigned to us, that Ned
Land would be in sole charge of piloting the longboat. Besides, the
shore lay no more than two miles off, and it would be child's play
for the Canadian to guide that nimble skiff through those rows of
reefs so ill–fated for big ships.</p>
      <p>The next day, January 5, after its deck paneling was opened, the
skiff was wrenched from its socket and launched to sea from the top
of the platform. Two men were sufficient for this operation. The
oars were inside the longboat and we had only to take our
seats.</p>
      <p>At eight o'clock, armed with rifles and axes, we pulled clear of
the <i>Nautilus</i>. The sea was fairly calm. A mild breeze blew
from shore. In place by the oars, Conseil and I rowed vigorously,
and Ned steered us into the narrow lanes between the breakers. The
skiff handled easily and sped swiftly.</p>
      <p>Ned Land couldn't conceal his glee. He was a prisoner escaping
from prison and never dreaming he would need to reenter it.</p>
      <p>"Meat!" he kept repeating. "Now we'll eat red meat! Actual game!
A real mess call, by thunder! I'm not saying fish aren't good for
you, but we mustn't overdo 'em, and a slice of fresh venison
grilled over live coals will be a nice change from our standard
fare."</p>
      <p>"You glutton," Conseil replied, "you're making my mouth
water!"</p>
      <p>"It remains to be seen," I said, "whether these forests do
contain game, and if the types of game aren't of such size that
they can hunt the hunter."</p>
      <p>"Fine, Professor Aronnax!" replied the Canadian, whose teeth
seemed to be as honed as the edge of an ax. "But if there's no
other quadruped on this island, I'll eat tiger—tiger
sirloin."</p>
      <p>"Our friend Ned grows disturbing," Conseil replied.</p>
      <p>"Whatever it is," Ned Land went on, "any animal having four feet
without feathers, or two feet with feathers, will be greeted by my
very own one–gun salute."</p>
      <p>"Oh good!" I replied. "The reckless Mr. Land is at it
again!"</p>
      <p>"Don't worry, Professor Aronnax, just keep rowing!" the Canadian
replied. "I only need twenty–five minutes to serve you one of
my own special creations."</p>
      <p>By 8:30 the <i>Nautilus's</i> skiff had just run gently aground
on a sandy strand, after successfully clearing the ring of coral
that surrounds Gueboroa Island.</p>
   </body>
</topic>