<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<topic id="d2e5244">
   <title>
      <d4pSimpleEnumerator><!--1.19-->Chapter 19. </d4pSimpleEnumerator>
      <ph>Vanikoro</ph>
   </title>
   <body>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="size_plus_2">THIS DREADFUL SIGHT</ph> was the first of a
whole series of maritime catastrophes that the <i>Nautilus</i>
would encounter on its run. When it plied more heavily traveled
seas, we often saw wrecked hulls rotting in midwater, and farther
down, cannons, shells, anchors, chains, and a thousand other iron
objects rusting away.</p>
      <p>Meanwhile, continuously swept along by the <i>Nautilus</i>,
where we lived in near isolation, we raised the Tuamotu Islands on
December 11, that old "dangerous group" associated with the French
global navigator Commander Bougainville; it stretches from Ducie
Island to Lazareff Island over an area of 500 leagues from the
east–southeast to the west–northwest, between latitude
13° 30' and 23° 50' south, and between longitude 125°
30' and 151° 30' west. This island group covers a surface area
of 370 square leagues, and it's made up of some sixty subgroups,
among which we noted the Gambier group, which is a French
protectorate. These islands are coral formations. Thanks to the
work of polyps, a slow but steady upheaval will someday connect
these islands to each other. Later on, this new island will be
fused to its neighboring island groups, and a fifth continent will
stretch from New Zealand and New Caledonia as far as the Marquesas
Islands.</p>
      <p>The day I expounded this theory to Captain Nemo, he answered me
coldly:</p>
      <p>"The earth doesn't need new continents, but new men!"</p>
      <p>Sailors' luck led the <i>Nautilus</i> straight to Reao Island,
one of the most unusual in this group, which was discovered in 1822
by Captain Bell aboard the Minerva. So I was able to study the
madreporic process that has created the islands in this ocean.</p>
      <p>
         <i>Madrepores</i>, which one must guard against confusing with
precious coral, clothe their tissue in a limestone crust, and their
variations in structure have led my famous mentor Professor
Milne–Edwards to classify them into five divisions. The tiny
microscopic animals that secrete this polypary live by the billions
in the depths of their cells. Their limestone deposits build up
into rocks, reefs, islets, islands. In some places, they form
atolls, a circular ring surrounding a lagoon or small inner lake
that gaps place in contact with the sea. Elsewhere, they take the
shape of barrier reefs, such as those that exist along the coasts
of New Caledonia and several of the Tuamotu Islands. In still other
localities, such as Réunion Island and the island of
Mauritius, they build fringing reefs, high, straight walls next to
which the ocean's depth is considerable.</p>
      <p>While cruising along only a few cable lengths from the
underpinning of Reao Island, I marveled at the gigantic piece of
work accomplished by these microscopic laborers. These walls were
the express achievements of <i>madrepores</i> known by the names
fire coral, finger coral, star coral, and stony coral. These polyps
grow exclusively in the agitated strata at the surface of the sea,
and so it's in the upper reaches that they begin these
substructures, which sink little by little together with the
secreted rubble binding them. This, at least, is the theory of Mr.
Charles Darwin, who thus explains the formation of atolls—a
theory superior, in my view, to the one that says these madreporic
edifices sit on the summits of mountains or volcanoes submerged a
few feet below sea level.</p>
      <p>I could observe these strange walls quite closely: our sounding
lines indicated that they dropped perpendicularly for more than 300
meters, and our electric beams made the bright limestone positively
sparkle.</p>
      <p>In reply to a question Conseil asked me about the growth rate of
these colossal barriers, I thoroughly amazed him by saying that
scientists put it at an eighth of an inch per biennium.</p>
      <p>"Therefore," he said to me, "to build these walls, it took . . .
?"</p>
      <p>"192,000 years, my gallant Conseil, which significantly extends
the biblical Days of Creation. What's more, the formation of
coal—in other words, the petrification of forests swallowed
by floods—and the cooling of basaltic rocks likewise call for
a much longer period of time. I might add that those 'days' in the
Bible must represent whole epochs and not literally the lapse of
time between two sunrises, because according to the Bible itself,
the sun doesn't date from the first day of Creation."</p>
      <p>When the <i>Nautilus</i> returned to the surface of the ocean, I
could take in Reao Island over its whole flat, wooded expanse.
Obviously its madreporic rocks had been made fertile by tornadoes
and thunderstorms. One day, carried off by a hurricane from
neighboring shores, some seed fell onto these limestone beds,
mixing with decomposed particles of fish and marine plants to form
vegetable humus. Propelled by the waves, a coconut arrived on this
new coast. Its germ took root. Its tree grew tall, catching steam
off the water. A brook was born. Little by little, vegetation
spread. Tiny animals—worms, insects—rode ashore on tree
trunks snatched from islands to windward. Turtles came to lay their
eggs. Birds nested in the young trees. In this way animal life
developed, and drawn by the greenery and fertile soil, man
appeared. And that's how these islands were formed, the immense
achievement of microscopic animals.</p>
      <p>Near evening Reao Island melted into the distance, and the
<i>Nautilus</i> noticeably changed course. After touching the
Tropic of Capricorn at longitude 135°, it headed
west–northwest, going back up the whole intertropical zone.
Although the summer sun lavished its rays on us, we never suffered
from the heat, because thirty or forty meters underwater, the
temperature didn't go over 10° to 12° centigrade.</p>
      <p>By December 15 we had left the alluring Society Islands in the
west, likewise elegant Tahiti, queen of the Pacific. In the morning
I spotted this island's lofty summits a few miles to leeward. Its
waters supplied excellent fish for the tables on board: mackerel,
bonito, albacore, and a few varieties of that sea serpent named the
moray eel.</p>
      <p>The <i>Nautilus</i> had cleared 8,100 miles. We logged 9,720
miles when we passed between the Tonga Islands, where crews from
the Argo, Port–au–Prince, and Duke of Portland had
perished, and the island group of Samoa, scene of the slaying of
Captain de Langle, friend of that long–lost navigator, the
Count de La Pérouse. Then we raised the Fiji Islands, where
savages slaughtered sailors from the <i>Union</i>, as well as
Captain Bureau, commander of the <i>Darling Josephine</i> out of
Nantes, France.</p>
      <p>Extending over an expanse of 100 leagues north to south, and
over 90 leagues east to west, this island group lies between
latitude 2° and 6° south, and between longitude 174°
and 179° west. It consists of a number of islands, islets, and
reefs, among which we noted the islands of Viti Levu, Vanua Levu,
and Kadavu.</p>
      <p>It was the Dutch navigator Tasman who discovered this group in
1643, the same year the Italian physicist Torricelli invented the
barometer and King Louis XIV ascended the French throne. I'll let
the reader decide which of these deeds was more beneficial to
humanity. Coming later, Captain Cook in 1774, Rear Admiral
d'Entrecasteaux in 1793, and finally Captain Dumont d'Urville in
1827, untangled the whole chaotic geography of this island group.
The <i>Nautilus</i> drew near Wailea Bay, an unlucky place for
England's Captain Dillon, who was the first to shed light on the
longstanding mystery surrounding the disappearance of ships under
the Count de La Pérouse.</p>
      <p>This bay, repeatedly dredged, furnished a huge supply of
excellent oysters. As the Roman playwright Seneca recommended, we
opened them right at our table, then stuffed ourselves. These
mollusks belonged to the species known by name as <i>Ostrea
lamellosa</i>, whose members are quite common off Corsica. This
Wailea oysterbank must have been extensive, and for certain, if
they hadn't been controlled by numerous natural checks, these
clusters of shellfish would have ended up jam–packing the
bay, since as many as 2,000,000 eggs have been counted in a single
individual.</p>
      <p>And if Mr. Ned Land did not repent of his gluttony at our oyster
fest, it's because oysters are the only dish that never causes
indigestion. In fact, it takes no less than sixteen dozen of these
headless mollusks to supply the 315 grams that satisfy one man's
minimum daily requirement for nitrogen.</p>
      <p>On December 25 the <i>Nautilus</i> navigated amid the island
group of the New Hebrides, which the Portuguese seafarer
Queirós discovered in 1606, which Commander Bougainville
explored in 1768, and to which Captain Cook gave its current name
in 1773. This group is chiefly made up of nine large islands and
forms a 120–league strip from the north–northwest to
the south–southeast, lying between latitude 2° and
15° south, and between longitude 164° and 168°. At the
moment of our noon sights, we passed fairly close to the island of
Aurou, which looked to me like a mass of green woods crowned by a
peak of great height.</p>
      <p>That day it was yuletide, and it struck me that Ned Land badly
missed celebrating "Christmas," that genuine family holiday where
Protestants are such zealots.</p>
      <p>I hadn't seen Captain Nemo for over a week, when, on the morning
of the 27th, he entered the main lounge, as usual acting as if he'd
been gone for just five minutes. I was busy tracing the
<i>Nautilus's</i> course on the world map. The captain approached,
placed a finger over a position on the chart, and pronounced just
one word:</p>
      <p>"Vanikoro."</p>
      <p>This name was magic! It was the name of those islets where
vessels under the Count de La Pérouse had miscarried. I
straightened suddenly.</p>
      <p>"The <i>Nautilus</i> is bringing us to Vanikoro?" I asked.</p>
      <p>"Yes, professor," the captain replied.</p>
      <p>"And I'll be able to visit those famous islands where the
<i>Compass</i> and the <i>Astrolabe</i> came to grief?"</p>
      <p>"If you like, professor."</p>
      <p>"When will we reach Vanikoro?"</p>
      <p>"We already have, professor."</p>
      <p>Followed by Captain Nemo, I climbed onto the platform, and from
there my eyes eagerly scanned the horizon.</p>
      <p>In the northeast there emerged two volcanic islands of unequal
size, surrounded by a coral reef whose circuit measured forty
miles. We were facing the island of Vanikoro proper, to which
Captain Dumont d'Urville had given the name "Island of the Search";
we lay right in front of the little harbor of Vana, located in
latitude 16° 4' south and longitude 164° 32' east. Its
shores seemed covered with greenery from its beaches to its summits
inland, crowned by Mt. Kapogo, which is 476 fathoms high.</p>
      <p>After clearing the outer belt of rocks via a narrow passageway,
the <i>Nautilus</i> lay inside the breakers where the sea had a
depth of thirty to forty fathoms. Under the green shade of some
tropical evergreens, I spotted a few savages who looked extremely
startled at our approach. In this long, blackish object advancing
flush with the water, didn't they see some fearsome <i>cetacean</i>
that they were obliged to view with distrust?</p>
      <p>Just then Captain Nemo asked me what I knew about the shipwreck
of the Count de La Pérouse.</p>
      <p>"What everybody knows, captain," I answered him.</p>
      <p>"And could you kindly tell me what everybody knows?" he asked me
in a gently ironic tone.</p>
      <p>"Very easily."</p>
      <p>I related to him what the final deeds of Captain Dumont
d'Urville had brought to light, deeds described here in this
heavily condensed summary of the whole matter.</p>
      <p>In 1785 the Count de La Pérouse and his subordinate,
Captain de Langle, were sent by King Louis XVI of France on a
voyage to circumnavigate the globe. They boarded two sloops of war,
the <i>Compass</i> and the <i>Astrolabe</i>, which were never seen
again.</p>
      <p>In 1791, justly concerned about the fate of these two sloops of
war, the French government fitted out two large cargo boats, the
<i>Search</i> and the <i>Hope</i>, which left Brest on September 28
under orders from Rear Admiral Bruni d'Entrecasteaux. Two months
later, testimony from a certain Commander Bowen, aboard the
<i>Albemarle</i>, alleged that rubble from shipwrecked vessels had
been seen on the coast of New Georgia. But d'Entrecasteaux was
unaware of this news—which seemed a bit dubious
anyhow—and headed toward the Admiralty Islands, which had
been named in a report by one Captain Hunter as the site of the
Count de La Pérouse's shipwreck.</p>
      <p>They looked in vain. The <i>Hope</i> and the <i>Search</i>
passed right by Vanikoro without stopping there; and overall, this
voyage was plagued by misfortune, ultimately costing the lives of
Rear Admiral d'Entrecasteaux, two of his subordinate officers, and
several seamen from his crew.</p>
      <p>It was an old hand at the Pacific, the English adventurer
Captain Peter Dillon, who was the first to pick up the trail left
by castaways from the wrecked vessels. On May 15, 1824, his ship,
the <i>St. Patrick</i>, passed by Tikopia Island, one of the New
Hebrides. There a native boatman pulled alongside in a dugout canoe
and sold Dillon a silver sword hilt bearing the imprint of
characters engraved with a cutting tool known as a burin.
Furthermore, this native boatman claimed that during a stay in
Vanikoro six years earlier, he had seen two Europeans belonging to
ships that had run aground on the island's reefs many years
before.</p>
      <p>Dillon guessed that the ships at issue were those under the
Count de La Pérouse, ships whose disappearance had shaken
the entire world. He tried to reach Vanikoro, where, according to
the native boatman, a good deal of rubble from the shipwreck could
still be found, but winds and currents prevented his doing so.</p>
      <p>Dillon returned to Calcutta. There he was able to interest the
Asiatic Society and the East India Company in his discovery. A ship
named after the <i>Search</i> was placed at his disposal, and he
departed on January 23, 1827, accompanied by a French deputy.</p>
      <p>This new <i>Search</i>, after putting in at several stops over
the Pacific, dropped anchor before Vanikoro on July 7, 1827, in the
same harbor of Vana where the <i>Nautilus</i> was currently
floating.</p>
      <p>There Dillon collected many relics of the shipwreck: iron
utensils, anchors, eyelets from pulleys, swivel guns, an
eighteen–pound shell, the remains of some astronomical
instruments, a piece of sternrail, and a bronze bell bearing the
inscription "Made by Bazin," the foundry mark at Brest Arsenal
around 1785. There could no longer be any doubt.</p>
      <p>Finishing his investigations, Dillon stayed at the site of the
casualty until the month of October. Then he left Vanikoro, headed
toward New Zealand, dropped anchor at Calcutta on April 7, 1828,
and returned to France, where he received a very cordial welcome
from King Charles X.</p>
      <p>But just then the renowned French explorer Captain Dumont
d'Urville, unaware of Dillon's activities, had already set sail to
search elsewhere for the site of the shipwreck. In essence, a
whaling vessel had reported that some medals and a Cross of St.
Louis had been found in the hands of savages in the Louisiade
Islands and New Caledonia.</p>
      <p>So Captain Dumont d'Urville had put to sea in command of a
vessel named after the <i>Astrolabe</i>, and just two months after
Dillon had left Vanikoro, Dumont d'Urville dropped anchor before
Hobart. There he heard about Dillon's findings, and he further
learned that a certain James Hobbs, chief officer on the
<i>Union</i> out of Calcutta, had put to shore on an island located
in latitude 8° 18' south and longitude 156° 30' east, and
had noted the natives of those waterways making use of iron bars
and red fabrics.</p>
      <p>Pretty perplexed, Dumont d'Urville didn't know if he should give
credence to these reports, which had been carried in some of the
less reliable newspapers; nevertheless, he decided to start on
Dillon's trail.</p>
      <p>On February 10, 1828, the new <i>Astrolabe</i> hove before
Tikopia Island, took on a guide and interpreter in the person of a
deserter who had settled there, plied a course toward Vanikoro,
raised it on February 12, sailed along its reefs until the 14th,
and only on the 20th dropped anchor inside its barrier in the
harbor of Vana.</p>
      <p>On the 23rd, several officers circled the island and brought
back some rubble of little importance. The natives, adopting a
system of denial and evasion, refused to guide them to the site of
the casualty. This rather shady conduct aroused the suspicion that
the natives had mistreated the castaways; and in truth, the natives
seemed afraid that Dumont d'Urville had come to avenge the Count de
La Pérouse and his unfortunate companions.</p>
      <p>But on the 26th, appeased with gifts and seeing that they didn't
need to fear any reprisals, the natives led the chief officer, Mr.
Jacquinot, to the site of the shipwreck.</p>
      <p>At this location, in three or four fathoms of water between the
Paeu and Vana reefs, there lay some anchors, cannons, and ingots of
iron and lead, all caked with limestone concretions. A launch and
whaleboat from the new <i>Astrolabe</i> were steered to this
locality, and after going to exhausting lengths, their crews
managed to dredge up an anchor weighing 1,800 pounds, a
cast–iron eight–pounder cannon, a lead ingot, and two
copper swivel guns.</p>
      <p>Questioning the natives, Captain Dumont d'Urville also learned
that after La Pérouse's two ships had miscarried on the
island's reefs, the count had built a smaller craft, only to go off
and miscarry a second time. Where? Nobody knew.</p>
      <p>The commander of the new <i>Astrolabe</i> then had a monument
erected under a tuft of mangrove, in memory of the famous navigator
and his companions. It was a simple quadrangular pyramid, set on a
coral base, with no ironwork to tempt the natives' avarice.</p>
      <p>Then Dumont d'Urville tried to depart; but his crews were run
down from the fevers raging on these unsanitary shores, and quite
ill himself, he was unable to weigh anchor until March 17.</p>
      <p>Meanwhile, fearing that Dumont d'Urville wasn't abreast of
Dillon's activities, the French government sent a sloop of war to
Vanikoro, the Bayonnaise under Commander Legoarant de Tromelin, who
had been stationed on the American west coast. Dropping anchor
before Vanikoro a few months after the new <i>Astrolabe's</i>
departure, the Bayonnaise didn't find any additional evidence but
verified that the savages hadn't disturbed the memorial honoring
the Count de La Pérouse.</p>
      <p>This is the substance of the account I gave Captain Nemo.</p>
      <p>"So," he said to me, "the castaways built a third ship on
Vanikoro Island, and to this day, nobody knows where it went and
perished?"</p>
      <p>"Nobody knows."</p>
      <p>Captain Nemo didn't reply but signaled me to follow him to the
main lounge. The <i>Nautilus</i> sank a few meters beneath the
waves, and the panels opened.</p>
      <p>I rushed to the window and saw crusts of coral: fungus coral,
siphonula coral, alcyon coral, sea anemone from the genus
<i>Caryophylia</i>, plus myriads of charming fish including
greenfish, damselfish, sweepers, snappers, and squirrelfish;
underneath this coral covering I detected some rubble the old
dredges hadn't been able to tear free—iron stirrups, anchors,
cannons, shells, tackle from a capstan, a stempost, all objects
hailing from the wrecked ships and now carpeted in moving
flowers.</p>
      <p>And as I stared at this desolate wreckage, Captain Nemo told me
in a solemn voice:</p>
      <p>"Commander La Pérouse set out on December 7, 1785, with
his ships, the <i>Compass</i> and the <i>Astrolabe</i>. He dropped
anchor first at Botany Bay, visited the Tonga Islands and New
Caledonia, headed toward the Santa Cruz Islands, and put in at
Nomuka, one of the islands in the Ha'apai group. Then his ships
arrived at the unknown reefs of Vanikoro. Traveling in the lead,
the <i>Compass</i> ran afoul of breakers on the southerly coast.
The <i>Astrolabe</i> went to its rescue and also ran aground. The
first ship was destroyed almost immediately. The second, stranded
to leeward, held up for some days. The natives gave the castaways a
fair enough welcome. The latter took up residence on the island and
built a smaller craft with rubble from the two large ones. A few
seamen stayed voluntarily in Vanikoro. The others, weak and ailing,
set sail with the Count de La Pérouse. They headed to the
Solomon Islands, and they perished with all hands on the westerly
coast of the chief island in that group, between Cape Deception and
Cape Satisfaction!"</p>
      <p>"And how do you know all this?" I exclaimed.</p>
      <p>"Here's what I found at the very site of that final
shipwreck!"</p>
      <p>Captain Nemo showed me a tin box, stamped with the coat of arms
of France and all corroded by salt water. He opened it and I saw a
bundle of papers, yellowed but still legible.</p>
      <p>They were the actual military orders given by France's Minister
of the Navy to Commander La Pérouse, with notes along the
margin in the handwriting of King Louis XVI!</p>
      <p>"Ah, what a splendid death for a seaman!" Captain Nemo then
said. "A coral grave is a tranquil grave, and may Heaven grant that
my companions and I rest in no other!"</p>
   </body>
</topic>