<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<topic id="d2e6935">
   <title>
      <d4pSimpleEnumerator><!--1.23-->CHAPTER 23. </d4pSimpleEnumerator>
      <ph>"Aegri Somnia"<fn callout="*">Latin: "troubled
dreams." Ed.</fn>
      </ph>
   </title>
   <body>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="size_plus_2">THE FOLLOWING DAY</ph>, January 10, the
<i>Nautilus</i> resumed its travels in midwater but at a remarkable
speed that I estimated to be at least thirty–five miles per
hour. The propeller was going so fast I could neither follow nor
count its revolutions.</p>
      <p>I thought about how this marvelous electric force not only gave
motion, heat, and light to the <i>Nautilus</i> but even protected
it against outside attack, transforming it into a sacred ark no
profane hand could touch without being blasted; my wonderment was
boundless, and it went from the submersible itself to the engineer
who had created it.</p>
      <p>We were traveling due west and on January 11 we doubled Cape
Wessel, located in longitude 135° and latitude 10° north,
the western tip of the Gulf of Carpentaria. Reefs were still
numerous but more widely scattered and were fixed on the chart with
the greatest accuracy. The <i>Nautilus</i> easily avoided the Money
breakers to port and the Victoria reefs to starboard, positioned at
longitude 130° on the tenth parallel, which we went along
rigorously.</p>
      <p>On January 13, arriving in the Timor Sea, Captain Nemo raised
the island of that name at longitude 122°. This island, whose
surface area measures 1,625 square leagues, is governed by rajahs.
These aristocrats deem themselves the sons of crocodiles, in other
words, descendants with the most exalted origins to which a human
being can lay claim. Accordingly, their scaly ancestors infest the
island's rivers and are the subjects of special veneration. They
are sheltered, nurtured, flattered, pampered, and offered a ritual
diet of nubile maidens; and woe to the foreigner who lifts a finger
against these sacred <i>saurians</i>.</p>
      <p>But the <i>Nautilus</i> wanted nothing to do with these nasty
animals. Timor Island was visible for barely an instant at noon
while the chief officer determined his position. I also caught only
a glimpse of little Roti Island, part of this same group, whose
women have a well–established reputation for beauty in the
Malaysian marketplace.</p>
      <p>After our position fix, the <i>Nautilus's</i> latitude bearings
were modulated to the southwest. Our prow pointed to the Indian
Ocean. Where would Captain Nemo's fancies take us? Would he head up
to the shores of Asia? Would he pull nearer to the beaches of
Europe? Unlikely choices for a man who avoided populated areas! So
would he go down south? Would he double the Cape of Good Hope, then
Cape Horn, and push on to the Antarctic pole? Finally, would he
return to the seas of the Pacific, where his <i>Nautilus</i> could
navigate freely and easily? Time would tell.</p>
      <p>After cruising along the Cartier, Hibernia, Seringapatam, and
Scott reefs, the solid element's last exertions against the liquid
element, we were beyond all sight of shore by January 14. The
<i>Nautilus</i> slowed down in an odd manner, and very
unpredictable in its ways, it sometimes swam in the midst of the
waters, sometimes drifted on their surface.</p>
      <p>During this phase of our voyage, Captain Nemo conducted
interesting experiments on the different temperatures in various
strata of the sea. Under ordinary conditions, such readings are
obtained using some pretty complicated instruments whose findings
are dubious to say the least, whether they're thermometric sounding
lines, whose glass often shatters under the water's pressure, or
those devices based on the varying resistance of metals to electric
currents. The results so obtained can't be adequately
double–checked. By contrast, Captain Nemo would seek the
sea's temperature by going himself into its depths, and when he
placed his thermometer in contact with the various layers of
liquid, he found the sought–for degree immediately and with
certainty.</p>
      <p>And so, by loading up its ballast tanks, or by sinking obliquely
with its slanting fins, the <i>Nautilus</i> successively reached
depths of 3,000, 4,000, 5,000, 7,000, 9,000, and 10,000 meters, and
the ultimate conclusion from these experiments was that, in all
latitudes, the sea had a permanent temperature of 4.5°
centigrade at a depth of 1,000 meters.</p>
      <p>I watched these experiments with the most intense fascination.
Captain Nemo brought a real passion to them. I often wondered why
he took these observations. Were they for the benefit of his fellow
man? It was unlikely, because sooner or later his work would perish
with him in some unknown sea! Unless he intended the results of his
experiments for me. But that meant this strange voyage of mine
would come to an end, and no such end was in sight.</p>
      <p>Be that as it may, Captain Nemo also introduced me to the
different data he had obtained on the relative densities of the
water in our globe's chief seas. From this news I derived some
personal enlightenment having nothing to do with science.</p>
      <p>It happened the morning of January 15. The captain, with whom I
was strolling on the platform, asked me if I knew how salt water
differs in density from sea to sea. I said no, adding that there
was a lack of rigorous scientific observations on this subject.</p>
      <p>"I've taken such observations," he told me, "and I can vouch for
their reliability."</p>
      <p>"Fine," I replied, "but the <i>Nautilus</i> lives in a separate
world, and the secrets of its scientists don't make their way
ashore."</p>
      <p>"You're right, professor," he told me after a few moments of
silence. "This is a separate world. It's as alien to the earth as
the planets accompanying our globe around the sun, and we'll never
become familiar with the work of scientists on Saturn or Jupiter.
But since fate has linked our two lives, I can reveal the results
of my observations to you."</p>
      <p>"I'm all attention, Captain."</p>
      <p>"You're aware, Professor, that salt water is denser than fresh
water, but this density isn't uniform. In essence, if I represent
the density of fresh water by 1.000, then I find 1.028 for the
waters of the Atlantic, 1.026 for the waters of the Pacific, 1.030
for the waters of the Mediterranean—"</p>
      <p>Aha, I thought, so he ventures into the Mediterranean?</p>
      <p>"—1.018 for the waters of the Ionian Sea, and 1.029 for
the waters of the Adriatic."</p>
      <p>Assuredly, the <i>Nautilus</i> didn't avoid the heavily traveled
seas of Europe, and from this insight I concluded that the ship
would take us back—perhaps very soon—to more civilized
shores. I expected Ned Land to greet this news with unfeigned
satisfaction.</p>
      <p>For several days our work hours were spent in all sorts of
experiments, on the degree of salinity in waters of different
depths, or on their electric properties, coloration, and
transparency, and in every instance Captain Nemo displayed an
ingenuity equaled only by his graciousness toward me. Then I saw no
more of him for some days and again lived on board in
seclusion.</p>
      <p>On January 16 the <i>Nautilus</i> seemed to have fallen asleep
just a few meters beneath the surface of the water. Its electric
equipment had been turned off, and the motionless propeller let it
ride with the waves. I assumed that the crew were busy with
interior repairs, required by the engine's strenuous mechanical
action.</p>
      <p>My companions and I then witnessed an unusual sight. The panels
in the lounge were open, and since the <i>Nautilus's</i> beacon was
off, a hazy darkness reigned in the midst of the waters. Covered
with heavy clouds, the stormy sky gave only the faintest light to
the ocean's upper strata.</p>
      <p>I was observing the state of the sea under these conditions, and
even the largest fish were nothing more than ill–defined
shadows, when the <i>Nautilus</i> was suddenly transferred into
broad daylight. At first I thought the beacon had gone back on and
was casting its electric light into the liquid mass. I was
mistaken, and after a hasty examination I discovered my error.</p>
      <p>The <i>Nautilus</i> had drifted into the midst of some
phosphorescent strata, which, in this darkness, came off as
positively dazzling. This effect was caused by myriads of tiny,
luminous animals whose brightness increased when they glided over
the metal hull of our submersible. In the midst of these luminous
sheets of water, I then glimpsed flashes of light, like those seen
inside a blazing furnace from streams of molten lead or from masses
of metal brought to a white heat—flashes so intense that
certain areas of the light became shadows by comparison, in a fiery
setting from which every shadow should seemingly have been
banished. No, this was no longer the calm emission of our usual
lighting! This light throbbed with unprecedented vigor and
activity! You sensed that it was alive!</p>
      <p>In essence, it was a cluster of countless open–sea
<i>infusoria</i>, of <i>noctiluca</i> an eighth of an inch wide,
actual globules of transparent jelly equipped with a threadlike
tentacle, up to 25,000 of which have been counted in thirty cubic
centimeters of water. And the power of their light was increased by
those glimmers unique to medusas, starfish, common jellyfish,
angel–wing clams, and other phosphorescent zoophytes, which
were saturated with grease from organic matter decomposed by the
sea, and perhaps with mucus secreted by fish.</p>
      <p>For several hours the <i>Nautilus</i> drifted in this brilliant
tide, and our wonderment grew when we saw huge marine animals
cavorting in it, like the fire–dwelling salamanders of myth.
In the midst of these flames that didn't burn, I could see swift,
elegant porpoises, the tireless pranksters of the seas, and
sailfish three meters long, those shrewd heralds of hurricanes,
whose fearsome broadswords sometimes banged against the lounge
window. Then smaller fish appeared: miscellaneous triggerfish,
leather jacks, unicornfish, and a hundred others that left stripes
on this luminous atmosphere in their course.</p>
      <p>Some magic lay behind this dazzling sight! Perhaps some
atmospheric condition had intensified this phenomenon? Perhaps a
storm had been unleashed on the surface of the waves? But only a
few meters down, the <i>Nautilus</i> felt no tempest's fury, and
the ship rocked peacefully in the midst of the calm waters.</p>
      <p>And so it went, some new wonder constantly delighting us.
Conseil observed and classified his zoophytes, articulates,
mollusks, and fish. The days passed quickly, and I no longer kept
track of them. Ned, as usual, kept looking for changes of pace from
our standard fare. Like actual snails, we were at home in our
shell, and I can vouch that it's easy to turn into a
full–fledged snail.</p>
      <p>So this way of living began to seem simple and natural to us,
and we no longer envisioned a different lifestyle on the surface of
the planet earth, when something happened to remind us of our
strange circumstances.</p>
      <p>On January 18 the <i>Nautilus</i> lay in longitude 105° and
latitude 15° south. The weather was threatening, the sea rough
and billowy. The wind was blowing a strong gust from the east. The
barometer, which had been falling for some days, forecast an
approaching struggle of the elements.</p>
      <p>I had climbed onto the platform just as the chief officer was
taking his readings of hour angles. Out of habit I waited for him
to pronounce his daily phrase. But that day it was replaced by a
different phrase, just as incomprehensible. Almost at once I saw
Captain Nemo appear, lift his spyglass, and inspect the
horizon.</p>
      <p>For some minutes the captain stood motionless, rooted to the
spot contained within the field of his lens. Then he lowered his
spyglass and exchanged about ten words with his chief officer. The
latter seemed to be in the grip of an excitement he tried in vain
to control. More in command of himself, Captain Nemo remained cool.
Furthermore, he seemed to be raising certain objections that his
chief officer kept answering with flat assurances. At least that's
what I gathered from their differences in tone and gesture.</p>
      <p>As for me, I stared industriously in the direction under
observation but without spotting a thing. Sky and water merged into
a perfectly clean horizon line.</p>
      <p>Meanwhile Captain Nemo strolled from one end of the platform to
the other, not glancing at me, perhaps not even seeing me. His step
was firm but less regular than usual. Sometimes he would stop,
cross his arms over his chest, and observe the sea. What could he
be looking for over that immense expanse? By then the
<i>Nautilus</i> lay hundreds of miles from the nearest coast!</p>
      <p>The chief officer kept lifting his spyglass and stubbornly
examining the horizon, walking up and down, stamping his foot, in
his nervous agitation a sharp contrast to his superior.</p>
      <p>But this mystery would inevitably be cleared up, and soon,
because Captain Nemo gave orders to increase speed; at once the
engine stepped up its drive power, setting the propeller in swifter
rotation.</p>
      <p>Just then the chief officer drew the captain's attention anew.
The latter interrupted his strolling and aimed his spyglass at the
point indicated. He observed it a good while. As for me, deeply
puzzled, I went below to the lounge and brought back an excellent
long–range telescope I habitually used. Leaning my elbows on
the beacon housing, which jutted from the stern of the platform, I
got set to scour that whole stretch of sky and sea.</p>
      <p>But no sooner had I peered into the eyepiece than the instrument
was snatched from my hands.</p>
      <p>I spun around. Captain Nemo was standing before me, but I almost
didn't recognize him. His facial features were transfigured.
Gleaming with dark fire, his eyes had shrunk beneath his frowning
brow. His teeth were half bared. His rigid body, clenched fists,
and head drawn between his shoulders, all attested to a fierce hate
breathing from every pore. He didn't move. My spyglass fell from
his hand and rolled at his feet.</p>
      <p>Had I accidentally caused these symptoms of anger? Did this
incomprehensible individual think I had detected some secret
forbidden to guests on the <i>Nautilus</i>?</p>
      <p>No! I wasn't the subject of his hate because he wasn't even
looking at me; his eyes stayed stubbornly focused on that
inscrutable point of the horizon.</p>
      <p>Finally Captain Nemo regained his self–control. His facial
appearance, so profoundly changed, now resumed its usual calm. He
addressed a few words to his chief officer in their strange
language, then he turned to me:</p>
      <p>"Professor Aronnax," he told me in a tone of some urgency, "I
ask that you now honor one of the binding agreements between
us."</p>
      <p>"Which one, Captain?"</p>
      <p>"You and your companions must be placed in confinement until I
see fit to set you free."</p>
      <p>"You're in command," I answered, gaping at him. "But may I
address a question to you?"</p>
      <p>"You may not, sir."</p>
      <p>After that, I stopped objecting and started obeying, since
resistance was useless.</p>
      <p>I went below to the cabin occupied by Ned Land and Conseil, and
I informed them of the captain's decision. I'll let the reader
decide how this news was received by the Canadian. In any case,
there was no time for explanations. Four crewmen were waiting at
the door, and they led us to the cell where we had spent our first
night aboard the <i>Nautilus</i>.</p>
      <p>Ned Land tried to lodge a complaint, but the only answer he got
was a door shut in his face.</p>
      <p>"Will master tell me what this means?" Conseil asked me.</p>
      <p>I told my companions what had happened. They were as astonished
as I was, but no wiser.</p>
      <p>Then I sank into deep speculation, and Captain Nemo's strange
facial seizure kept haunting me. I was incapable of connecting two
ideas in logical order, and I had strayed into the most absurd
hypotheses, when I was snapped out of my mental struggles by these
words from Ned Land:</p>
      <p>"Well, look here! Lunch is served!"</p>
      <p>Indeed, the table had been laid. Apparently Captain Nemo had
given this order at the same time he commanded the <i>Nautilus</i>
to pick up speed.</p>
      <p>"Will master allow me to make him a recommendation?" Conseil
asked me.</p>
      <p>"Yes, my boy," I replied.</p>
      <p>"Well, master needs to eat his lunch! It's prudent, because we
have no idea what the future holds."</p>
      <p>"You're right, Conseil."</p>
      <p>"Unfortunately," Ned Land said, "they've only given us the
standard menu."</p>
      <p>"Ned my friend," Conseil answered, "what would you say if they'd
given us no lunch at all?"</p>
      <p>This dose of sanity cut the harpooner's complaints clean
off.</p>
      <p>We sat down at the table. Our meal proceeded pretty much in
silence. I ate very little. Conseil, everlastingly prudent,
"force–fed" himself; and despite the menu, Ned Land didn't
waste a bite. Then, lunch over, each of us propped himself in a
corner.</p>
      <p>Just then the luminous globe lighting our cell went out, leaving
us in profound darkness. Ned Land soon dozed off, and to my
astonishment, Conseil also fell into a heavy slumber. I was
wondering what could have caused this urgent need for sleep, when I
felt a dense torpor saturate my brain. I tried to keep my eyes
open, but they closed in spite of me. I was in the grip of
anguished hallucinations. Obviously some sleep–inducing
substance had been laced into the food we'd just eaten! So
imprisonment wasn't enough to conceal Captain Nemo's plans from
us—sleep was needed as well!</p>
      <p>Then I heard the hatches close. The sea's undulations, which had
been creating a gentle rocking motion, now ceased. Had the
<i>Nautilus</i> left the surface of the ocean? Was it reentering
the motionless strata deep in the sea?</p>
      <p>I tried to fight off this drowsiness. It was impossible. My
breathing grew weaker. I felt a mortal chill freeze my dull, nearly
paralyzed limbs. Like little domes of lead, my lids fell over my
eyes. I couldn't raise them. A morbid sleep, full of
hallucinations, seized my whole being. Then the visions disappeared
and left me in utter oblivion.</p>
   </body>
</topic>