<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<topic id="d2e6378">
   <title>
      <d4pSimpleEnumerator><!--1.22-->Chapter 22. </d4pSimpleEnumerator>
      <ph>The Lightning Bolts of Captain Nemo</ph>
   </title>
   <body>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="size_plus_2">WITHOUT STANDING UP</ph>, we stared in the
direction of the forest, my hand stopping halfway to my mouth, Ned
Land's completing its assignment.</p>
      <p>"Stones don't fall from the sky," Conseil said, "or else they
deserve to be called meteorites."</p>
      <p>A second well–polished stone removed a tasty ringdove leg
from Conseil's hand, giving still greater relevance to his
observation.</p>
      <p>We all three stood up, rifles to our shoulders, ready to answer
any attack.</p>
      <p>"Apes maybe?" Ned Land exclaimed.</p>
      <p>"Nearly," Conseil replied. "Savages."</p>
      <p>"Head for the skiff!" I said, moving toward the sea.</p>
      <p>Indeed, it was essential to beat a retreat because some twenty
natives, armed with bows and slings, appeared barely a hundred
paces off, on the outskirts of a thicket that masked the horizon to
our right.</p>
      <p>The skiff was aground ten fathoms away from us.</p>
      <p>The savages approached without running, but they favored us with
a show of the greatest hostility. It was raining stones and
arrows.</p>
      <p>Ned Land was unwilling to leave his provisions behind, and
despite the impending danger, he clutched his pig on one side, his
kangaroos on the other, and scampered off with respectable
speed.</p>
      <p>In two minutes we were on the strand. Loading provisions and
weapons into the skiff, pushing it to sea, and positioning its two
oars were the work of an instant. We hadn't gone two cable lengths
when a hundred savages, howling and gesticulating, entered the
water up to their waists. I looked to see if their appearance might
draw some of the <i>Nautilus's</i> men onto the platform. But no.
Lying well out, that enormous machine still seemed completely
deserted.</p>
      <p>Twenty minutes later we boarded ship. The hatches were open.
After mooring the skiff, we reentered the <i>Nautilus's</i>
interior.</p>
      <p>I went below to the lounge, from which some chords were wafting.
Captain Nemo was there, leaning over the organ, deep in a musical
trance.</p>
      <p>"Captain!" I said to him.</p>
      <p>He didn't hear me.</p>
      <p>"Captain!" I went on, touching him with my hand.</p>
      <p>He trembled, and turning around:</p>
      <p>"Ah, it's you, professor!" he said to me. "Well, did you have a
happy hunt? Was your herb gathering a success?"</p>
      <p>"Yes, captain," I replied, "but unfortunately we've brought back
a horde of bipeds whose proximity worries me."</p>
      <p>"What sort of bipeds?"</p>
      <p>"Savages."</p>
      <p>"Savages!" Captain Nemo replied in an ironic tone. "You set foot
on one of the shores of this globe, professor, and you're surprised
to find savages there? Where aren't there savages? And besides, are
they any worse than men elsewhere, these people you call
savages?"</p>
      <p>"But Captain—"</p>
      <p>"Speaking for myself, sir, I've encountered them
everywhere."</p>
      <p>"Well then," I replied, "if you don't want to welcome them
aboard the <i>Nautilus</i>, you'd better take some
precautions!"</p>
      <p>"Easy, professor, no cause for alarm."</p>
      <p>"But there are a large number of these natives."</p>
      <p>"What's your count?"</p>
      <p>"At least a hundred."</p>
      <p>"Professor Aronnax," replied Captain Nemo, whose fingers took
their places again on the organ keys, "if every islander in Papua
were to gather on that beach, the <i>Nautilus</i> would still have
nothing to fear from their attacks!"</p>
      <p>The captain's fingers then ran over the instrument's keyboard,
and I noticed that he touched only its black keys, which gave his
melodies a basically Scottish color. Soon he had forgotten my
presence and was lost in a reverie that I no longer tried to
dispel.</p>
      <p>I climbed onto the platform. Night had already fallen, because
in this low latitude the sun sets quickly, without any twilight. I
could see Gueboroa Island only dimly. But numerous fires had been
kindled on the beach, attesting that the natives had no thoughts of
leaving it.</p>
      <p>For several hours I was left to myself, sometimes musing on the
islanders—but no longer fearing them because the captain's
unflappable confidence had won me over—and sometimes
forgetting them to marvel at the splendors of this tropical night.
My memories took wing toward France, in the wake of those zodiacal
stars due to twinkle over it in a few hours. The moon shone in the
midst of the constellations at their zenith. I then remembered that
this loyal, good–natured satellite would return to this same
place the day after tomorrow, to raise the tide and tear the
<i>Nautilus</i> from its coral bed. Near midnight, seeing that all
was quiet over the darkened waves as well as under the waterside
trees, I repaired to my cabin and fell into a peaceful sleep.</p>
      <p>The night passed without mishap. No doubt the Papuans had been
frightened off by the mere sight of this monster aground in the
bay, because our hatches stayed open, offering easy access to the
<i>Nautilus's</i> interior.</p>
      <p>At six o'clock in the morning, January 8, I climbed onto the
platform. The morning shadows were lifting. The island was soon on
view through the dissolving mists, first its beaches, then its
summits.</p>
      <p>The islanders were still there, in greater numbers than on the
day before, perhaps 500 or 600 of them. Taking advantage of the low
tide, some of them had moved forward over the heads of coral to
within two cable lengths of the <i>Nautilus</i>. I could easily
distinguish them. They obviously were true Papuans, men of fine
stock, athletic in build, forehead high and broad, nose large but
not flat, teeth white. Their woolly, red–tinted hair was in
sharp contrast to their bodies, which were black and glistening
like those of Nubians. Beneath their pierced, distended earlobes
there dangled strings of beads made from bone. Generally these
savages were naked. I noted some women among them, dressed from hip
to knee in grass skirts held up by belts made of vegetation. Some
of the chieftains adorned their necks with crescents and with
necklaces made from beads of red and white glass. Armed with bows,
arrows, and shields, nearly all of them carried from their
shoulders a sort of net, which held those polished stones their
slings hurl with such dexterity.</p>
      <p>One of these chieftains came fairly close to the
<i>Nautilus</i>, examining it with care. He must have been a "mado"
of high rank, because he paraded in a mat of banana leaves that had
ragged edges and was accented with bright colors.</p>
      <p>I could easily have picked off this islander, he stood at such
close range; but I thought it best to wait for an actual show of
hostility. Between Europeans and savages, it's acceptable for
Europeans to shoot back but not to attack first.</p>
      <p>During this whole time of low tide, the islanders lurked near
the <i>Nautilus</i>, but they weren't boisterous. I often heard
them repeat the word "assai," and from their gestures I understood
they were inviting me to go ashore, an invitation I felt obliged to
decline.</p>
      <p>So the skiff didn't leave shipside that day, much to the
displeasure of Mr. Land who couldn't complete his provisions. The
adroit Canadian spent his time preparing the meat and flour
products he had brought from Gueboroa Island. As for the savages,
they went back to shore near eleven o'clock in the morning, when
the heads of coral began to disappear under the waves of the rising
tide. But I saw their numbers swell considerably on the beach. It
was likely that they had come from neighboring islands or from the
mainland of Papua proper. However, I didn't see one local dugout
canoe.</p>
      <p>Having nothing better to do, I decided to dredge these
beautiful, clear waters, which exhibited a profusion of shells,
zoophytes, and open–sea plants. Besides, it was the last day
the <i>Nautilus</i> would spend in these waterways, if, tomorrow,
it still floated off to the open sea as Captain Nemo had
promised.</p>
      <p>So I summoned Conseil, who brought me a small, light dragnet
similar to those used in oyster fishing.</p>
      <p>"What about these savages?" Conseil asked me. "With all due
respect to master, they don't strike me as very wicked!"</p>
      <p>"They're cannibals even so, my boy."</p>
      <p>"A person can be both a cannibal and a decent man," Conseil
replied, "just as a person can be both gluttonous and honorable.
The one doesn't exclude the other."</p>
      <p>"Fine, Conseil! And I agree that there are honorable cannibals
who decently devour their prisoners. However, I'm opposed to being
devoured, even in all decency, so I'll keep on my guard, especially
since the <i>Nautilus's</i> commander seems to be taking no
precautions. And now let's get to work!"</p>
      <p>For two hours our fishing proceeded energetically but without
bringing up any rarities. Our dragnet was filled with Midas
abalone, harp shells, obelisk snails, and especially the finest
hammer shells I had seen to that day. We also gathered in a few sea
cucumbers, some pearl oysters, and a dozen small turtles that we
saved for the ship's pantry.</p>
      <p>But just when I least expected it, I laid my hands on a wonder,
a natural deformity I'd have to call it, something very seldom
encountered. Conseil had just made a cast of the dragnet, and his
gear had come back up loaded with a variety of fairly ordinary
seashells, when suddenly he saw me plunge my arms swiftly into the
net, pull out a shelled animal, and give a conchological yell, in
other words, the most piercing yell a human throat can produce.</p>
      <p>"Eh? What happened to master?" Conseil asked, very startled.
"Did master get bitten?"</p>
      <p>"No, my boy, but I'd gladly have sacrificed a finger for such a
find!"</p>
      <p>"What find?"</p>
      <p>"This shell," I said, displaying the subject of my triumph.</p>
      <p>"But that's simply an olive shell of the 'tent olive' species,
genus <i>Oliva</i>, order <i>Pectinibranchia</i>, class
<i>Gastropoda</i>, branch <i>Mollusca</i>—"</p>
      <p>"Yes, yes, Conseil! But instead of coiling from right to left,
this olive shell rolls from left to right!"</p>
      <p>"It can't be!" Conseil exclaimed.</p>
      <p>"Yes, my boy, it's a left–handed shell!"</p>
      <p>"A left–handed shell!" Conseil repeated, his heart
pounding.</p>
      <p>"Look at its spiral!"</p>
      <p>"Oh, master can trust me on this," Conseil said, taking the
valuable shell in trembling hands, "but never have I felt such
excitement!"</p>
      <p>And there was good reason to be excited! In fact, as naturalists
have ventured to observe, "dextrality" is a well–known law of
nature. In their rotational and orbital movements, stars and their
satellites go from right to left. Man uses his right hand more
often than his left, and consequently his various instruments and
equipment (staircases, locks, watch springs, etc.) are designed to
be used in a right–to–left manner. Now then, nature has
generally obeyed this law in coiling her shells. They're
right–handed with only rare exceptions, and when by chance a
shell's spiral is left–handed, collectors will pay its weight
in gold for it.</p>
      <p>So Conseil and I were deep in the contemplation of our treasure,
and I was solemnly promising myself to enrich the Paris Museum with
it, when an ill–timed stone, hurled by one of the islanders,
whizzed over and shattered the valuable object in Conseil's
hands.</p>
      <p>I gave a yell of despair! Conseil pounced on his rifle and aimed
at a savage swinging a sling just ten meters away from him. I tried
to stop him, but his shot went off and shattered a bracelet of
amulets dangling from the islander's arm.</p>
      <p>"Conseil!" I shouted. "Conseil!"</p>
      <p>"Eh? What? Didn't master see that this man–eater initiated
the attack?"</p>
      <p>"A shell isn't worth a human life!" I told him.</p>
      <p>"Oh, the rascal!" Conseil exclaimed. "I'd rather he cracked my
shoulder!"</p>
      <p>Conseil was in dead earnest, but I didn't subscribe to his
views. However, the situation had changed in only a short time and
we hadn't noticed. Now some twenty dugout canoes were surrounding
the <i>Nautilus</i>. Hollowed from tree trunks, these dugouts were
long, narrow, and well designed for speed, keeping their balance by
means of two bamboo poles that floated on the surface of the water.
They were maneuvered by skillful, half–naked paddlers, and I
viewed their advance with definite alarm.</p>
      <p>It was obvious these Papuans had already entered into relations
with Europeans and knew their ships. But this long, iron cylinder
lying in the bay, with no masts or funnels—what were they to
make of it? Nothing good, because at first they kept it at a
respectful distance. However, seeing that it stayed motionless,
they regained confidence little by little and tried to become more
familiar with it. Now then, it was precisely this familiarity that
we needed to prevent. Since our weapons made no sound when they
went off, they would have only a moderate effect on these
islanders, who reputedly respect nothing but noisy mechanisms.
Without thunderclaps, lightning bolts would be much less
frightening, although the danger lies in the flash, not the
noise.</p>
      <p>Just then the dugout canoes drew nearer to the <i>Nautilus</i>,
and a cloud of arrows burst over us.</p>
      <p>"Fire and brimstone, it's hailing!" Conseil said. "And poisoned
hail perhaps!"</p>
      <p>"We've got to alert Captain Nemo," I said, reentering the
hatch.</p>
      <p>I went below to the lounge. I found no one there. I ventured a
knock at the door opening into the captain's stateroom.</p>
      <p>The word "Enter!" answered me. I did so and found Captain Nemo
busy with calculations in which there was no shortage of X and
other algebraic signs.</p>
      <p>"Am I disturbing you?" I said out of politeness.</p>
      <p>"Correct, Professor Aronnax," the captain answered me. "But I
imagine you have pressing reasons for looking me up?"</p>
      <p>"Very pressing. Native dugout canoes are surrounding us, and in
a few minutes we're sure to be assaulted by several hundred
savages."</p>
      <p>"Ah!" Captain Nemo put in serenely. "They've come in their
dugouts?"</p>
      <p>"Yes, sir."</p>
      <p>"Well, sir, closing the hatches should do the trick."</p>
      <p>"Precisely, and that's what I came to tell you—"</p>
      <p>"Nothing easier," Captain Nemo said.</p>
      <p>And he pressed an electric button, transmitting an order to the
crew's quarters.</p>
      <p>"There, sir, all under control!" he told me after a few moments.
"The skiff is in place and the hatches are closed. I don't imagine
you're worried that these gentlemen will stave in walls that shells
from your frigate couldn't breach?"</p>
      <p>"No, Captain, but one danger still remains."</p>
      <p>"What's that, sir?"</p>
      <p>"Tomorrow at about this time, we'll need to reopen the hatches
to renew the <i>Nautilus's</i> air."</p>
      <p>"No argument, sir, since our craft breathes in the manner
favored by <i>cetaceans</i>."</p>
      <p>"But if these Papuans are occupying the platform at that moment,
I don't see how you can prevent them from entering."</p>
      <p>"Then, sir, you assume they'll board the ship?"</p>
      <p>"I'm certain of it."</p>
      <p>"Well, sir, let them come aboard. I see no reason to prevent
them. Deep down they're just poor devils, these Papuans, and I
don't want my visit to Gueboroa Island to cost the life of a single
one of these unfortunate people!"</p>
      <p>On this note I was about to withdraw; but Captain Nemo detained
me and invited me to take a seat next to him. He questioned me with
interest on our excursions ashore and on our hunting, but seemed
not to understand the Canadian's passionate craving for red meat.
Then our conversation skimmed various subjects, and without being
more forthcoming, Captain Nemo proved more affable.</p>
      <p>Among other things, we came to talk of the <i>Nautilus's</i>
circumstances, aground in the same strait where Captain Dumont
d'Urville had nearly miscarried. Then, pertinent to this:</p>
      <p>"He was one of your great seamen," the captain told me, "one of
your shrewdest navigators, that d'Urville! He was the Frenchman's
Captain Cook. A man wise but unlucky! Braving the ice banks of the
South Pole, the coral of Oceania, the cannibals of the Pacific,
only to perish wretchedly in a train wreck! If that energetic man
was able to think about his life in its last seconds, imagine what
his final thoughts must have been!"</p>
      <p>As he spoke, Captain Nemo seemed deeply moved, an emotion I felt
was to his credit.</p>
      <p>Then, chart in hand, we returned to the deeds of the French
navigator: his voyages to circumnavigate the globe, his double
attempt at the South Pole, which led to his discovery of the
Adélie Coast and the Louis–Philippe Peninsula, finally
his hydrographic surveys of the chief islands in Oceania.</p>
      <p>"What your d'Urville did on the surface of the sea," Captain
Nemo told me, "I've done in the ocean's interior, but more easily,
more completely than he. Constantly tossed about by hurricanes, the
<i>Zealous</i> and the new <i>Astrolabe</i> couldn't compare with
the <i>Nautilus</i>, a quiet work room truly at rest in the midst
of the waters!"</p>
      <p>"Even so, Captain," I said, "there is one major similarity
between Dumont d'Urville's sloops of war and the
<i>Nautilus</i>."</p>
      <p>"What's that, sir?"</p>
      <p>"Like them, the <i>Nautilus</i> has run aground!"</p>
      <p>"The <i>Nautilus</i> is not aground, sir," Captain Nemo replied
icily. "The <i>Nautilus</i> was built to rest on the ocean floor,
and I don't need to undertake the arduous labors, the maneuvers
d'Urville had to attempt in order to float off his sloops of war.
The <i>Zealous</i> and the new <i>Astrolabe</i> wellnigh perished,
but my <i>Nautilus</i> is in no danger. Tomorrow, on the day stated
and at the hour stated, the tide will peacefully lift it off, and
it will resume its navigating through the seas."</p>
      <p>"Captain," I said, "I don't doubt—"</p>
      <p>"Tomorrow," Captain Nemo added, standing up, "tomorrow at 2:40
in the afternoon, the <i>Nautilus</i> will float off and exit the
Torres Strait undamaged."</p>
      <p>Pronouncing these words in an extremely sharp tone, Captain Nemo
gave me a curt bow. This was my dismissal, and I reentered my
stateroom.</p>
      <p>There I found Conseil, who wanted to know the upshot of my
interview with the captain.</p>
      <p>"My boy," I replied, "when I expressed the belief that these
Papuan natives were a threat to his <i>Nautilus</i>, the captain
answered me with great irony. So I've just one thing to say to you:
have faith in him and sleep in peace."</p>
      <p>"Master has no need for my services?"</p>
      <p>"No, my friend. What's Ned Land up to?"</p>
      <p>"Begging master's indulgence," Conseil replied, "but our friend
Ned is concocting a kangaroo pie that will be the eighth
wonder!"</p>
      <p>I was left to myself; I went to bed but slept pretty poorly. I
kept hearing noises from the savages, who were stamping on the
platform and letting out deafening yells. The night passed in this
way, without the crew ever emerging from their usual inertia. They
were no more disturbed by the presence of these man–eaters
than soldiers in an armored fortress are troubled by ants running
over the armor plate.</p>
      <p>I got up at six o'clock in the morning. The hatches weren't
open. So the air inside hadn't been renewed; but the air tanks were
kept full for any eventuality and would function appropriately to
shoot a few cubic meters of oxygen into the <i>Nautilus's</i> thin
atmosphere.</p>
      <p>I worked in my stateroom until noon without seeing Captain Nemo
even for an instant. Nobody on board seemed to be making any
preparations for departure.</p>
      <p>I still waited for a while, then I made my way to the main
lounge. Its timepiece marked 2:30. In ten minutes the tide would
reach its maximum elevation, and if Captain Nemo hadn't made a rash
promise, the <i>Nautilus</i> would immediately break free. If not,
many months might pass before it could leave its coral bed.</p>
      <p>But some preliminary vibrations could soon be felt over the
boat's hull. I heard its plating grind against the limestone
roughness of that coral base.</p>
      <p>At 2:35 Captain Nemo appeared in the lounge.</p>
      <p>"We're about to depart," he said.</p>
      <p>"Ah!" I put in.</p>
      <p>"I've given orders to open the hatches."</p>
      <p>"What about the Papuans?"</p>
      <p>"What about them?" Captain Nemo replied, with a light shrug of
his shoulders.</p>
      <p>"Won't they come inside the <i>Nautilus</i>?"</p>
      <p>"How will they manage that?"</p>
      <p>"By jumping down the hatches you're about to open."</p>
      <p>"Professor Aronnax," Captain Nemo replied serenely, "the
<i>Nautilus's</i> hatches aren't to be entered in that fashion even
when they're open."</p>
      <p>I gaped at the captain.</p>
      <p>"You don't understand?" he said to me.</p>
      <p>"Not in the least."</p>
      <p>"Well, come along and you'll see!"</p>
      <p>I headed to the central companionway. There, very puzzled, Ned
Land and Conseil watched the crewmen opening the hatches, while a
frightful clamor and furious shouts resounded outside.</p>
      <p>The hatch lids fell back onto the outer plating. Twenty horrible
faces appeared. But when the first islander laid hands on the
companionway railing, he was flung backward by some invisible
power, lord knows what! He ran off, howling in terror and wildly
prancing around.</p>
      <p>Ten of his companions followed him. All ten met the same
fate.</p>
      <p>Conseil was in ecstasy. Carried away by his violent instincts,
Ned Land leaped up the companionway. But as soon as his hands
seized the railing, he was thrown backward in his turn.</p>
      <p>"Damnation!" he exclaimed. "I've been struck by a lightning
bolt!"</p>
      <p>These words explained everything to me. It wasn't just a railing
that led to the platform, it was a metal cable fully charged with
the ship's electricity. Anyone who touched it got a fearsome
shock—and such a shock would have been fatal if Captain Nemo
had thrown the full current from his equipment into this conducting
cable! It could honestly be said that he had stretched between
himself and his assailants a network of electricity no one could
clear with impunity.</p>
      <p>Meanwhile, crazed with terror, the unhinged Papuans beat a
retreat. As for us, half laughing, we massaged and comforted poor
Ned Land, who was swearing like one possessed.</p>
      <p>But just then, lifted off by the tide's final undulations, the
<i>Nautilus</i> left its coral bed at exactly that fortieth minute
pinpointed by the captain. Its propeller churned the waves with
lazy majesty. Gathering speed little by little, the ship navigated
on the surface of the ocean, and safe and sound, it left behind the
dangerous narrows of the Torres Strait.</p>
   </body>
</topic>