<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<topic id="d2e716">
   <title>
      <d4pSimpleEnumerator><!--1.2-->Chapter 2. </d4pSimpleEnumerator>
      <ph>The Pros and Cons</ph>
   </title>
   <body>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="size_plus_2">DURING THE PERIOD</ph> in which these
developments were occurring, I had returned from a scientific
undertaking organized to explore the Nebraska badlands in the
United States. In my capacity as Assistant Professor at the Paris
Museum of Natural History, I had been attached to this expedition
by the French government. After spending six months in Nebraska, I
arrived in New York laden with valuable collections near the end of
March. My departure for France was set for early May. In the
meantime, then, I was busy classifying my mineralogical, botanical,
and zoological treasures when that incident took place with the
<i>Scotia</i>.</p>
      <p>I was perfectly abreast of this question, which was the big news
of the day, and how could I not have been? I had read and reread
every American and European newspaper without being any farther
along. This mystery puzzled me. Finding it impossible to form any
views, I drifted from one extreme to the other. Something was out
there, that much was certain, and any doubting Thomas was invited
to place his finger on the <i>Scotia's</i> wound.</p>
      <p>When I arrived in New York, the question was at the boiling
point. The hypothesis of a drifting islet or an elusive reef, put
forward by people not quite in their right minds, was completely
eliminated. And indeed, unless this reef had an engine in its
belly, how could it move about with such prodigious speed?</p>
      <p>Also discredited was the idea of a floating hull or some other
enormous wreckage, and again because of this speed of movement.</p>
      <p>So only two possible solutions to the question were left,
creating two very distinct groups of supporters: on one side, those
favoring a monster of colossal strength; on the other, those
favoring an "underwater boat" of tremendous motor power.</p>
      <p>Now then, although the latter hypothesis was completely
admissible, it couldn't stand up to inquiries conducted in both the
New World and the Old. That a private individual had such a
mechanism at his disposal was less than probable. Where and when
had he built it, and how could he have built it in secret?</p>
      <p>Only some government could own such an engine of destruction,
and in these disaster–filled times, when men tax their
ingenuity to build increasingly powerful aggressive weapons, it was
possible that, unknown to the rest of the world, some nation could
have been testing such a fearsome machine. The Chassepot rifle led
to the torpedo, and the torpedo has led to this underwater
battering ram, which in turn will lead to the world putting its
foot down. At least I hope it will.</p>
      <p>But this hypothesis of a war machine collapsed in the face of
formal denials from the various governments. Since the public
interest was at stake and transoceanic travel was suffering, the
sincerity of these governments could not be doubted. Besides, how
could the assembly of this underwater boat have escaped public
notice? Keeping a secret under such circumstances would be
difficult enough for an individual, and certainly impossible for a
nation whose every move is under constant surveillance by rival
powers.</p>
      <p>So, after inquiries conducted in England, France, Russia,
Prussia, Spain, Italy, America, and even Turkey, the hypothesis of
an underwater <i>Monitor</i> was ultimately rejected.</p>
      <p>And so the monster surfaced again, despite the endless
witticisms heaped on it by the popular press, and the human
imagination soon got caught up in the most ridiculous
ichthyological fantasies.</p>
      <p>After I arrived in New York, several people did me the honor of
consulting me on the phenomenon in question. In France I had
published a two–volume work, in quarto, entitled <i>The
Mysteries of the Great Ocean Depths</i>. Well received in scholarly
circles, this book had established me as a specialist in this
pretty obscure field of natural history. My views were in demand.
As long as I could deny the reality of the business, I confined
myself to a flat "no comment." But soon, pinned to the wall, I had
to explain myself straight out. And in this vein, "the honorable
Pierre Aronnax, Professor at the Paris Museum," was summoned by
<i>The New York Herald</i> to formulate his views no matter
what.</p>
      <p>I complied. Since I could no longer hold my tongue, I let it
wag. I discussed the question in its every aspect, both political
and scientific, and this is an excerpt from the well–padded
article I published in the issue of April 30.</p>
      <p>"Therefore," I wrote, "after examining these different
hypotheses one by one, we are forced, every other supposition
having been refuted, to accept the existence of an extremely
powerful marine animal.</p>
      <p>"The deepest parts of the ocean are totally unknown to us. No
soundings have been able to reach them. What goes on in those
distant depths? What creatures inhabit, or could inhabit, those
regions twelve or fifteen miles beneath the surface of the water?
What is the constitution of these animals? It's almost beyond
conjecture.</p>
      <p>"However, the solution to this problem submitted to me can take
the form of a choice between two alternatives.</p>
      <p>"Either we know every variety of creature populating our planet,
or we do not.</p>
      <p>"If we do not know every one of them, if nature still keeps
ichthyological secrets from us, nothing is more admissible than to
accept the existence of fish or <i>cetacean</i>s of new species or
even new genera, animals with a basically 'cast–iron'
constitution that inhabit strata beyond the reach of our soundings,
and which some development or other, an urge or a whim if you
prefer, can bring to the upper level of the ocean for long
intervals.</p>
      <p>"If, on the other hand, we do know every living species, we must
look for the animal in question among those marine creatures
already cataloged, and in this event I would be inclined to accept
the existence of a giant narwhale.</p>
      <p>"The common narwhale, or sea unicorn, often reaches a length of
sixty feet. Increase its dimensions fivefold or even tenfold, then
give this <i>cetacean</i> a strength in proportion to its size
while enlarging its offensive weapons, and you have the animal
we're looking for. It would have the proportions determined by the
officers of the <i>Shannon</i>, the instrument needed to perforate
the <i>Scotia</i>, and the power to pierce a steamer's hull.</p>
      <p>"In essence, the narwhale is armed with a sort of ivory sword,
or lance, as certain naturalists have expressed it. It's a
king–sized tooth as hard as steel. Some of these teeth have
been found buried in the bodies of baleen whales, which the
narwhale attacks with invariable success. Others have been
wrenched, not without difficulty, from the undersides of vessels
that narwhales have pierced clean through, as a gimlet pierces a
wine barrel. The museum at the Faculty of Medicine in Paris owns
one of these tusks with a length of 2.25 meters and a width at its
base of forty–eight centimeters!</p>
      <p>"All right then! Imagine this weapon to be ten times stronger
and the animal ten times more powerful, launch it at a speed of
twenty miles per hour, multiply its mass times its velocity, and
you get just the collision we need to cause the specified
catastrophe.</p>
      <p>"So, until information becomes more abundant, I plump for a sea
unicorn of colossal dimensions, no longer armed with a mere lance
but with an actual spur, like ironclad frigates or those warships
called 'rams,' whose mass and motor power it would possess
simultaneously.</p>
      <p>"This inexplicable phenomenon is thus explained
away—unless it's something else entirely, which, despite
everything that has been sighted, studied, explored and
experienced, is still possible!"</p>
      <p>These last words were cowardly of me; but as far as I could, I
wanted to protect my professorial dignity and not lay myself open
to laughter from the Americans, who when they do laugh, laugh
raucously. I had left myself a loophole. Yet deep down, I had
accepted the existence of "the monster."</p>
      <p>My article was hotly debated, causing a fine old uproar. It
rallied a number of supporters. Moreover, the solution it proposed
allowed for free play of the imagination. The human mind enjoys
impressive visions of unearthly creatures. Now then, the sea is
precisely their best medium, the only setting suitable for the
breeding and growing of such giants—next to which such land
animals as elephants or rhinoceroses are mere dwarves. The liquid
masses support the largest known species of mammals and perhaps
conceal mollusks of incomparable size or crustaceans too frightful
to contemplate, such as 100–meter lobsters or crabs weighing
200 metric tons! Why not? Formerly, in prehistoric days, land
animals (quadrupeds, apes, reptiles, birds) were built on a
gigantic scale. Our Creator cast them using a colossal mold that
time has gradually made smaller. With its untold depths, couldn't
the sea keep alive such huge specimens of life from another age,
this sea that never changes while the land masses undergo almost
continuous alteration? Couldn't the heart of the ocean hide the
last–remaining varieties of these titanic species, for whom
years are centuries and centuries millennia?</p>
      <p>But I mustn't let these fantasies run away with me! Enough of
these fairy tales that time has changed for me into harsh
realities. I repeat: opinion had crystallized as to the nature of
this phenomenon, and the public accepted without argument the
existence of a prodigious creature that had nothing in common with
the fabled sea serpent.</p>
      <p>Yet if some saw it purely as a scientific problem to be solved,
more practical people, especially in America and England, were
determined to purge the ocean of this daunting monster, to insure
the safety of transoceanic travel. The industrial and commercial
newspapers dealt with the question chiefly from this viewpoint. The
Shipping &amp; Mercantile Gazette, the Lloyd's List, France's
Packetboat and Maritime &amp; Colonial Review, all the rags devoted
to insurance companies—who threatened to raise their premium
rates—were unanimous on this point.</p>
      <p>Public opinion being pronounced, the States of the Union were
the first in the field. In New York preparations were under way for
an expedition designed to chase this narwhale. A high–speed
frigate, the <i>Abraham Lincoln</i>, was fitted out for putting to
sea as soon as possible. The naval arsenals were unlocked for
Commander Farragut, who pressed energetically forward with the
arming of his frigate.</p>
      <p>But, as it always happens, just when a decision had been made to
chase the monster, the monster put in no further appearances. For
two months nobody heard a word about it. Not a single ship
encountered it. Apparently the unicorn had gotten wise to these
plots being woven around it. People were constantly babbling about
the creature, even via the Atlantic Cable! Accordingly, the wags
claimed that this slippery rascal had waylaid some passing telegram
and was making the most of it.</p>
      <p>So the frigate was equipped for a far–off voyage and armed
with fearsome fishing gear, but nobody knew where to steer it. And
impatience grew until, on June 2, word came that the
<i>Tampico</i>, a steamer on the San Francisco line sailing from
California to Shanghai, had sighted the animal again, three weeks
before in the northerly seas of the Pacific.</p>
      <p>This news caused intense excitement. Not even a 24–hour
breather was granted to Commander Farragut. His provisions were
loaded on board. His coal bunkers were overflowing. Not a crewman
was missing from his post. To cast off, he needed only to fire and
stoke his furnaces! Half a day's delay would have been
unforgivable! But Commander Farragut wanted nothing more than to go
forth.</p>
      <p>I received a letter three hours before the <i>Abraham
Lincoln</i> left its Brooklyn pier;<fn callout="*">Author's Note: A pier
is a type of wharf expressly set aside for an individual
vessel.</fn>
the letter read as follows:</p>
      <lq>
         <p>Pierre Aronnax<ph outputclass="br"/>
Professor at the Paris Museum<ph outputclass="br"/>
Fifth Avenue Hotel<ph outputclass="br"/>
New York<ph outputclass="br"/>
         </p>
         <p>Sir:</p>
         <p>If you would like to join the expedition on the <i>Abraham
Lincoln</i>, the government of the Union will be pleased to regard
you as France's representative in this undertaking. Commander
Farragut has a cabin at your disposal.</p>
         <p>Very cordially yours,</p>
         <p>J. B. HOBSON,<ph outputclass="br"/>
Secretary of the Navy.</p>
      </lq>
   </body>
</topic>