<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<topic id="d2e7830">
   <title>
      <d4pSimpleEnumerator><!--2.2-->Chapter 2. </d4pSimpleEnumerator>
      <ph>A New Proposition from Captain Nemo</ph>
   </title>
   <body>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="size_plus_2">ON JANUARY 28</ph>, in latitude 9° 4'
north, when the <i>Nautilus</i> returned at noon to the surface of
the sea, it lay in sight of land some eight miles to the west.
Right off, I observed a cluster of mountains about 2,000 feet high,
whose shapes were very whimsically sculpted. After our position
fix, I reentered the lounge, and when our bearings were reported on
the chart, I saw that we were off the island of Ceylon, that pearl
dangling from the lower lobe of the Indian peninsula.</p>
      <p>I went looking in the library for a book about this island, one
of the most fertile in the world. Sure enough, I found a volume
entitled <i>Ceylon and the Singhalese</i> by H. C. Sirr, Esq.
Reentering the lounge, I first noted the bearings of Ceylon, on
which antiquity lavished so many different names. It was located
between latitude 5° 55' and 9° 49' north, and between
longitude 79° 42' and 82° 4' east of the meridian of
Greenwich; its length is 275 miles; its maximum width, 150 miles;
its circumference, 900 miles; its surface area, 24,448 square
miles, in other words, a little smaller than that of Ireland.</p>
      <p>Just then Captain Nemo and his chief officer appeared.</p>
      <p>The captain glanced at the chart. Then, turning to me:</p>
      <p>"The island of Ceylon," he said, "is famous for its pearl
fisheries. Would you be interested, Professor Aronnax, in visiting
one of those fisheries?"</p>
      <p>"Certainly, Captain."</p>
      <p>"Fine. It's easily done. Only, when we see the fisheries, we'll
see no fishermen. The annual harvest hasn't yet begun. No matter.
I'll give orders to make for the Gulf of Mannar, and we'll arrive
there late tonight."</p>
      <p>The captain said a few words to his chief officer who went out
immediately. Soon the <i>Nautilus</i> reentered its liquid element,
and the pressure gauge indicated that it was staying at a depth of
thirty feet.</p>
      <p>With the chart under my eyes, I looked for the Gulf of Mannar. I
found it by the 9th parallel off the northwestern shores of Ceylon.
It was formed by the long curve of little Mannar Island. To reach
it we had to go all the way up Ceylon's west coast.</p>
      <p>"Professor," Captain Nemo then told me, "there are pearl
fisheries in the Bay of Bengal, the seas of the East Indies, the
seas of China and Japan, plus those seas south of the United
States, the Gulf of Panama and the Gulf of California; but it's off
Ceylon that such fishing reaps its richest rewards. No doubt we'll
be arriving a little early. Fishermen gather in the Gulf of Mannar
only during the month of March, and for thirty days some 300 boats
concentrate on the lucrative harvest of these treasures from the
sea. Each boat is manned by ten oarsmen and ten fishermen. The
latter divide into two groups, dive in rotation, and descend to a
depth of twelve meters with the help of a heavy stone clutched
between their feet and attached by a rope to their boat."</p>
      <p>"You mean," I said, "that such primitive methods are still all
that they use?"</p>
      <p>"All," Captain Nemo answered me, "although these fisheries
belong to the most industrialized people in the world, the English,
to whom the Treaty of Amiens granted them in 1802."</p>
      <p>"Yet it strikes me that diving suits like yours could perform
yeoman service in such work."</p>
      <p>"Yes, since those poor fishermen can't stay long underwater. On
his voyage to Ceylon, the Englishman Percival made much of a Kaffir
who stayed under five minutes without coming up to the surface, but
I find that hard to believe. I know that some divers can last up to
fifty–seven seconds, and highly skillful ones to
eighty–seven; but such men are rare, and when the poor
fellows climb back on board, the water coming out of their noses
and ears is tinted with blood. I believe the average time
underwater that these fishermen can tolerate is thirty seconds,
during which they hastily stuff their little nets with all the
pearl oysters they can tear loose. But these fishermen generally
don't live to advanced age: their vision weakens, ulcers break out
on their eyes, sores form on their bodies, and some are even
stricken with apoplexy on the ocean floor."</p>
      <p>"Yes," I said, "it's a sad occupation, and one that exists only
to gratify the whims of fashion. But tell me, Captain, how many
oysters can a boat fish up in a workday?"</p>
      <p>"About 40,000 to 50,000. It's even said that in 1814, when the
English government went fishing on its own behalf, its divers
worked just twenty days and brought up 76,000,000 oysters."</p>
      <p>"At least," I asked, "the fishermen are well paid, aren't
they?"</p>
      <p>"Hardly, professor. In Panama they make just $1.00 per week. In
most places they earn only a penny for each oyster that has a
pearl, and they bring up so many that have none!"</p>
      <p>"Only one penny to those poor people who make their employers
rich! That's atrocious!"</p>
      <p>"On that note, professor," Captain Nemo told me, "you and your
companions will visit the Mannar oysterbank, and if by chance some
eager fisherman arrives early, well, we can watch him at work."</p>
      <p>"That suits me, captain."</p>
      <p>"By the way, Professor Aronnax, you aren't afraid of sharks, are
you?"</p>
      <p>"Sharks?" I exclaimed.</p>
      <p>This struck me as a pretty needless question, to say the
least.</p>
      <p>"Well?" Captain Nemo went on.</p>
      <p>"I admit, Captain, I'm not yet on very familiar terms with that
genus of fish."</p>
      <p>"We're used to them, the rest of us," Captain Nemo answered.
"And in time you will be too. Anyhow, we'll be armed, and on our
way we might hunt a man–eater or two. It's a fascinating
sport. So, professor, I'll see you tomorrow, bright and early."</p>
      <p>This said in a carefree tone, Captain Nemo left the lounge.</p>
      <p>If you're invited to hunt bears in the Swiss mountains, you
might say: "Oh good, I get to go bear hunting tomorrow!" If you're
invited to hunt lions on the Atlas plains or tigers in the jungles
of India, you might say: "Ha! Now's my chance to hunt lions and
tigers!" But if you're invited to hunt sharks in their native
element, you might want to think it over before accepting.</p>
      <p>As for me, I passed a hand over my brow, where beads of cold
sweat were busy forming.</p>
      <p>"Let's think this over," I said to myself, "and let's take our
time. Hunting otters in underwater forests, as we did in the
forests of Crespo Island, is an acceptable activity. But to roam
the bottom of the sea when you're almost certain to meet
man–eaters in the neighborhood, that's another story! I know
that in certain countries, particularly the Andaman Islands,
Negroes don't hesitate to attack sharks, dagger in one hand and
noose in the other; but I also know that many who face those
fearsome animals don't come back alive. Besides, I'm not a Negro,
and even if I were a Negro, in this instance I don't think a little
hesitation on my part would be out of place."</p>
      <p>And there I was, fantasizing about sharks, envisioning huge jaws
armed with multiple rows of teeth and capable of cutting a man in
half. I could already feel a definite pain around my pelvic girdle.
And how I resented the offhand manner in which the captain had
extended his deplorable invitation! You would have thought it was
an issue of going into the woods on some harmless fox hunt!</p>
      <p>"Thank heavens!" I said to myself. "Conseil will never want to
come along, and that'll be my excuse for not going with the
captain."</p>
      <p>As for Ned Land, I admit I felt less confident of his wisdom.
Danger, however great, held a perennial attraction for his
aggressive nature.</p>
      <p>I went back to reading Sirr's book, but I leafed through it
mechanically. Between the lines I kept seeing fearsome,
wide–open jaws.</p>
      <p>Just then Conseil and the Canadian entered with a calm, even
gleeful air. Little did they know what was waiting for them.</p>
      <p>"Ye gods, sir!" Ned Land told me. "Your Captain Nemo—the
devil take him—has just made us a very pleasant
proposition!"</p>
      <p>"Oh!" I said "You know about—"</p>
      <p>"With all due respect to master," Conseil replied, "the
<i>Nautilus's</i> commander has invited us, together with master,
for a visit tomorrow to Ceylon's magnificent pearl fisheries. He
did so in the most cordial terms and conducted himself like a true
gentleman."</p>
      <p>"He didn't tell you anything else?"</p>
      <p>"Nothing, sir," the Canadian replied. "He said you'd already
discussed this little stroll."</p>
      <p>"Indeed," I said. "But didn't he give you any details
on—"</p>
      <p>"Not a one, Mr. Naturalist. You will be going with us,
right?"</p>
      <p>"Me? Why yes, certainly, of course! I can see that you like the
idea, Mr. Land."</p>
      <p>"Yes! It will be a really unusual experience!"</p>
      <p>"And possibly dangerous!" I added in an insinuating tone.</p>
      <p>"Dangerous?" Ned Land replied. "A simple trip to an
oysterbank?"</p>
      <p>Assuredly, Captain Nemo hadn't seen fit to plant the idea of
sharks in the minds of my companions. For my part, I stared at them
with anxious eyes, as if they were already missing a limb or two.
Should I alert them? Yes, surely, but I hardly knew how to go about
it.</p>
      <p>"Would master," Conseil said to me, "give us some background on
pearl fishing?"</p>
      <p>"On the fishing itself?" I asked. "Or on the occupational
hazards that—"</p>
      <p>"On the fishing," the Canadian replied. "Before we tackle the
terrain, it helps to be familiar with it."</p>
      <p>"All right, sit down, my friends, and I'll teach you everything
I myself have just been taught by the Englishman H. C. Sirr!"</p>
      <p>Ned and Conseil took seats on a couch, and right off the
Canadian said to me:</p>
      <p>"Sir, just what is a pearl exactly?"</p>
      <p>"My gallant Ned," I replied, "for poets a pearl is a tear from
the sea; for Orientals it's a drop of solidified dew; for the
ladies it's a jewel they can wear on their fingers, necks, and ears
that's oblong in shape, glassy in luster, and formed from
mother–of–pearl; for chemists it's a mixture of calcium
phosphate and calcium carbonate with a little gelatin protein; and
finally, for naturalists it's a simple festering secretion from the
organ that produces mother–of–pearl in certain
bivalves."</p>
      <p>"Branch <i>Mollusca</i>," Conseil said, "class <i>Acephala</i>,
order <i>Testacea</i>."</p>
      <p>"Correct, my scholarly Conseil. Now then, those <i>Testacea</i>
capable of producing pearls include rainbow abalone, turbo snails,
giant clams, and saltwater scallops—briefly, all those that
secrete mother–of–pearl, in other words, that blue,
azure, violet, or white substance lining the insides of their
valves."</p>
      <p>"Are mussels included too?" the Canadian asked.</p>
      <p>"Yes! The mussels of certain streams in Scotland, Wales,
Ireland, Saxony, Bohemia, and France."</p>
      <p>"Good!" the Canadian replied. "From now on we'll pay closer
attention to 'em."</p>
      <p>"But," I went on, "for secreting pearls, the ideal mollusk is
the pearl oyster <i>Meleagrina margaritifera</i>, that valuable
shellfish. Pearls result simply from mother–of–pearl
solidifying into a globular shape. Either they stick to the
oyster's shell, or they become embedded in the creature's folds. On
the valves a pearl sticks fast; on the flesh it lies loose. But its
nucleus is always some small, hard object, say a sterile egg or a
grain of sand, around which the mother–of–pearl is
deposited in thin, concentric layers over several years in
succession."</p>
      <p>"Can one find several pearls in the same oyster?" Conseil
asked.</p>
      <p>"Yes, my boy. There are some shellfish that turn into real jewel
coffers. They even mention one oyster, about which I remain
dubious, that supposedly contained at least 150 sharks."</p>
      <p>"150 sharks!" Ned Land yelped.</p>
      <p>"Did I say sharks?" I exclaimed hastily. "I meant 150 pearls.
Sharks wouldn't make sense."</p>
      <p>"Indeed," Conseil said. "But will master now tell us how one
goes about extracting these pearls?"</p>
      <p>"One proceeds in several ways, and often when pearls stick to
the valves, fishermen even pull them loose with pliers. But usually
the shellfish are spread out on mats made from the esparto grass
that covers the beaches. Thus they die in the open air, and by the
end of ten days they've rotted sufficiently. Next they're immersed
in huge tanks of salt water, then they're opened up and washed. At
this point the sorters begin their twofold task. First they remove
the layers of mother–of–pearl, which are known in the
industry by the names legitimate silver, bastard white, or bastard
black, and these are shipped out in cases weighing 125 to 150
kilograms. Then they remove the oyster's meaty tissue, boil it, and
finally strain it, in order to extract even the smallest
pearls."</p>
      <p>"Do the prices of these pearls differ depending on their size?"
Conseil asked.</p>
      <p>"Not only on their size," I replied, "but also according to
their shape, their water—in other words, their
color—and their orient—in other words, that dappled,
shimmering glow that makes them so delightful to the eye. The
finest pearls are called virgin pearls, or paragons; they form in
isolation within the mollusk's tissue. They're white, often opaque
but sometimes of opalescent transparency, and usually spherical or
pear–shaped. The spherical ones are made into bracelets; the
pear–shaped ones into earrings, and since they're the most
valuable, they're priced individually. The other pearls that stick
to the oyster's shell are more erratically shaped and are priced by
weight. Finally, classed in the lowest order, the smallest pearls
are known by the name seed pearls; they're priced by the measuring
cup and are used mainly in the creation of embroidery for church
vestments."</p>
      <p>"But it must be a long, hard job, sorting out these pearls by
size," the Canadian said.</p>
      <p>"No, my friend. That task is performed with eleven strainers, or
sieves, that are pierced with different numbers of holes. Those
pearls staying in the strainers with twenty to eighty holes are in
the first order. Those not slipping through the sieves pierced with
100 to 800 holes are in the second order. Finally, those pearls for
which one uses strainers pierced with 900 to 1,000 holes make up
the seed pearls."</p>
      <p>"How ingenious," Conseil said, "to reduce dividing and
classifying pearls to a mechanical operation. And could master tell
us the profits brought in by harvesting these banks of pearl
oysters?"</p>
      <p>"According to Sirr's book," I replied, "these Ceylon fisheries
are farmed annually for a total profit of 3,000,000
man–eaters."</p>
      <p>"Francs!" Conseil rebuked.</p>
      <p>"Yes, francs! ₣3,000,000!" I went on. "But I don't think
these fisheries bring in the returns they once did. Similarly, the
Central American fisheries used to make an annual profit of
₣4,000,000 during the reign of King Charles V, but now they
bring in only two–thirds of that amount. All in all, it's
estimated that ₣9,000,000 is the current yearly return for
the whole pearl–harvesting industry."</p>
      <p>"But," Conseil asked, "haven't certain famous pearls been quoted
at extremely high prices?"</p>
      <p>"Yes, my boy. They say Julius Caesar gave Servilia a pearl worth
₣120,000 in our currency."</p>
      <p>"I've even heard stories," the Canadian said, "about some lady
in ancient times who drank pearls in vinegar."</p>
      <p>"Cleopatra," Conseil shot back.</p>
      <p>"It must have tasted pretty bad," Ned Land added.</p>
      <p>"Abominable, Ned my friend," Conseil replied. "But when a little
glass of vinegar is worth ₣1,500,000, its taste is a small
price to pay."</p>
      <p>"I'm sorry I didn't marry the gal," the Canadian said, throwing
up his hands with an air of discouragement.</p>
      <p>"Ned Land married to Cleopatra?" Conseil exclaimed.</p>
      <p>"But I was all set to tie the knot, Conseil," the Canadian
replied in all seriousness, "and it wasn't my fault the whole
business fell through. I even bought a pearl necklace for my
fiancée, Kate Tender, but she married somebody else instead.
Well, that necklace cost me only $1.50, but you can absolutely
trust me on this, professor, its pearls were so big, they wouldn't
have gone through that strainer with twenty holes."</p>
      <p>"My gallant Ned," I replied, laughing, "those were artificial
pearls, ordinary glass beads whose insides were coated with Essence
of Orient."</p>
      <p>"Wow!" the Canadian replied. "That Essence of Orient must sell
for quite a large sum."</p>
      <p>"As little as zero! It comes from the scales of a European carp,
it's nothing more than a silver substance that collects in the
water and is preserved in ammonia. It's worthless."</p>
      <p>"Maybe that's why Kate Tender married somebody else," replied
Mr. Land philosophically.</p>
      <p>"But," I said, "getting back to pearls of great value, I don't
think any sovereign ever possessed one superior to the pearl owned
by Captain Nemo."</p>
      <p>"This one?" Conseil said, pointing to a magnificent jewel in its
glass case.</p>
      <p>"Exactly. And I'm certainly not far off when I estimate its
value at 2,000,000 . . . uh . . ."</p>
      <p>"Francs!" Conseil said quickly.</p>
      <p>"Yes," I said, "₣2,000,000, and no doubt all it cost our
captain was the effort to pick it up."</p>
      <p>"Ha!" Ned Land exclaimed. "During our stroll tomorrow, who says
we won't run into one just like it?"</p>
      <p>"Bah!" Conseil put in.</p>
      <p>"And why not?"</p>
      <p>"What good would a pearl worth millions do us here on the
<i>Nautilus</i>?"</p>
      <p>"Here, no," Ned Land said. "But elsewhere. . . ."</p>
      <p>"Oh! Elsewhere!" Conseil put in, shaking his head.</p>
      <p>"In fact," I said, "Mr. Land is right. And if we ever brought
back to Europe or America a pearl worth millions, it would make the
story of our adventures more authentic—and much more
rewarding."</p>
      <p>"That's how I see it," the Canadian said.</p>
      <p>"But," said Conseil, who perpetually returned to the didactic
side of things, "is this pearl fishing ever dangerous?"</p>
      <p>"No," I replied quickly, "especially if one takes certain
precautions."</p>
      <p>"What risks would you run in a job like that?" Ned Land said.
"Swallowing a few gulps of salt water?"</p>
      <p>"Whatever you say, Ned." Then, trying to imitate Captain Nemo's
carefree tone, I asked, "By the way, gallant Ned, are you afraid of
sharks?"</p>
      <p>"Me?" the Canadian replied. "I'm a professional harpooner! It's
my job to make a mockery of them!"</p>
      <p>"It isn't an issue," I said, "of fishing for them with a swivel
hook, hoisting them onto the deck of a ship, chopping off the tail
with a sweep of the ax, opening the belly, ripping out the heart,
and tossing it into the sea."</p>
      <p>"So it's an issue of . . . ?"</p>
      <p>"Yes, precisely."</p>
      <p>"In the water?"</p>
      <p>"In the water."</p>
      <p>"Ye gods, just give me a good harpoon! You see, sir, these
sharks are badly designed. They have to roll their bellies over to
snap you up, and in the meantime . . ."</p>
      <p>Ned Land had a way of pronouncing the word "snap" that sent
chills down the spine.</p>
      <p>"Well, how about you, Conseil? What are your feelings about
these man–eaters?"</p>
      <p>"Me?" Conseil said. "I'm afraid I must be frank with
master."</p>
      <p>Good for you, I thought.</p>
      <p>"If master faces these sharks," Conseil said, "I think his loyal
manservant should face them with him!"</p>
   </body>
</topic>