<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<topic id="d2e7545">
   <title>
      <d4pSimpleEnumerator><!--2.1-->Chapter 1. </d4pSimpleEnumerator>
      <ph>The Indian Ocean</ph>
   </title>
   <body>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="size_plus_2">NOW WE BEGIN</ph> the second part of this
voyage under the seas. The first ended in that moving scene at the
coral cemetery, which left a profound impression on my mind. And so
Captain Nemo would live out his life entirely in the heart of this
immense sea, and even his grave lay ready in its impenetrable
depths. There the last sleep of the <i>Nautilus's</i> occupants,
friends bound together in death as in life, would be disturbed by
no monster of the deep! "No man either!" the captain had added.</p>
      <p>Always that same fierce, implacable defiance of human
society!</p>
      <p>As for me, I was no longer content with the hypotheses that
satisfied Conseil. That fine lad persisted in seeing the
<i>Nautilus's</i> commander as merely one of those unappreciated
scientists who repay humanity's indifference with contempt. For
Conseil, the captain was still a misunderstood genius who, tired of
the world's deceptions, had been driven to take refuge in this
inaccessible environment where he was free to follow his instincts.
But to my mind, this hypothesis explained only one side of Captain
Nemo.</p>
      <p>In fact, the mystery of that last afternoon when we were locked
in prison and put to sleep, the captain's violent precaution of
snatching from my grasp a spyglass poised to scour the horizon, and
the fatal wound given that man during some unexplained collision
suffered by the <i>Nautilus</i>, all led me down a plain trail. No!
Captain Nemo wasn't content simply to avoid humanity! His fearsome
submersible served not only his quest for freedom, but also,
perhaps, it was used in Lord–knows–what schemes of
dreadful revenge.</p>
      <p>Right now, nothing is clear to me, I still glimpse only glimmers
in the dark, and I must limit my pen, as it were, to taking
dictation from events.</p>
      <p>But nothing binds us to Captain Nemo. He believes that escaping
from the <i>Nautilus</i> is impossible. We are not even constrained
by our word of honor. No promises fetter us. We're simply captives,
prisoners masquerading under the name "guests" for the sake of
everyday courtesy. Even so, Ned Land hasn't given up all hope of
recovering his freedom. He's sure to take advantage of the first
chance that comes his way. No doubt I will do likewise. And yet I
will feel some regret at making off with the <i>Nautilus's</i>
secrets, so generously unveiled for us by Captain Nemo! Because,
ultimately, should we detest or admire this man? Is he the
persecutor or the persecuted? And in all honesty, before I leave
him forever, I want to finish this underwater tour of the world,
whose first stages have been so magnificent. I want to observe the
full series of these wonders gathered under the seas of our globe.
I want to see what no man has seen yet, even if I must pay for this
insatiable curiosity with my life! What are my discoveries to date?
Nothing, relatively speaking—since so far we've covered only
6,000 leagues across the Pacific!</p>
      <p>Nevertheless, I'm well aware that the <i>Nautilus</i> is drawing
near to populated shores, and if some chance for salvation becomes
available to us, it would be sheer cruelty to sacrifice my
companions to my passion for the unknown. I must go with them,
perhaps even guide them. But will this opportunity ever arise? The
human being, robbed of his free will, craves such an opportunity;
but the scientist, forever inquisitive, dreads it.</p>
      <p>That day, January 21, 1868, the chief officer went at noon to
take the sun's altitude. I climbed onto the platform, lit a cigar,
and watched him at work. It seemed obvious to me that this man
didn't understand French, because I made several remarks in a loud
voice that were bound to provoke him to some involuntary show of
interest had he understood them; but he remained mute and
emotionless.</p>
      <p>While he took his sights with his sextant, one of the
<i>Nautilus's</i> sailors—that muscular man who had gone with
us to Crespo Island during our first underwater
excursion—came up to clean the glass panes of the beacon. I
then examined the fittings of this mechanism, whose power was
increased a hundredfold by biconvex lenses that were designed like
those in a lighthouse and kept its rays productively focused. This
electric lamp was so constructed as to yield its maximum
illuminating power. In essence, its light was generated in a
vacuum, insuring both its steadiness and intensity. Such a vacuum
also reduced wear on the graphite points between which the luminous
arc expanded. This was an important savings for Captain Nemo, who
couldn't easily renew them. But under these conditions, wear and
tear were almost nonexistent.</p>
      <p>When the <i>Nautilus</i> was ready to resume its underwater
travels, I went below again to the lounge. The hatches closed once
more, and our course was set due west.</p>
      <p>We then plowed the waves of the Indian Ocean, vast liquid plains
with an area of 550,000,000 hectares, whose waters are so
transparent it makes you dizzy to lean over their surface. There
the <i>Nautilus</i> generally drifted at a depth between 100 and
200 meters. It behaved in this way for some days. To anyone without
my grand passion for the sea, these hours would surely have seemed
long and monotonous; but my daily strolls on the platform where I
was revived by the life–giving ocean air, the sights in the
rich waters beyond the lounge windows, the books to be read in the
library, and the composition of my memoirs, took up all my time and
left me without a moment of weariness or boredom.</p>
      <p>All in all, we enjoyed a highly satisfactory state of health.
The diet on board agreed with us perfectly, and for my part, I
could easily have gone without those changes of pace that Ned Land,
in a spirit of protest, kept taxing his ingenuity to supply us.
What's more, in this constant temperature we didn't even have to
worry about catching colds. Besides, the ship had a good stock of
the <i>madrepore Dendrophylia</i>, known in Provence by the name
sea fennel, and a poultice made from the dissolved flesh of its
polyps will furnish an excellent cough medicine.</p>
      <p>For some days we saw a large number of aquatic birds with webbed
feet, known as gulls or sea mews. Some were skillfully slain, and
when cooked in a certain fashion, they make a very acceptable
platter of water game. Among the great wind riders—carried
over long distances from every shore and resting on the waves from
their exhausting flights—I spotted some magnificent
albatross, birds belonging to the <i>Longipennes</i>
(long–winged) family, whose discordant calls sound like the
braying of an ass. The <i>Totipalmes</i> (fully webbed) family was
represented by swift frigate birds, nimbly catching fish at the
surface, and by numerous tropic birds of the genus Phaeton, among
others the red–tailed tropic bird, the size of a pigeon, its
white plumage shaded with pink tints that contrasted with its
dark–hued wings.</p>
      <p>The <i>Nautilus's</i> nets hauled up several types of sea turtle
from the <i>hawksbill</i> genus with arching backs whose scales are
highly prized. Diving easily, these reptiles can remain a good
while underwater by closing the fleshy valves located at the
external openings of their nasal passages. When they were captured,
some hawksbills were still asleep inside their carapaces, a refuge
from other marine animals. The flesh of these turtles was nothing
memorable, but their eggs made an excellent feast.</p>
      <p>As for fish, they always filled us with wonderment when, staring
through the open panels, we could unveil the secrets of their
aquatic lives. I noted several species I hadn't previously been
able to observe.</p>
      <p>I'll mention chiefly some trunkfish unique to the Red Sea, the
sea of the East Indies, and that part of the ocean washing the
coasts of equinoctial America. Like turtles, armadillos, sea
urchins, and crustaceans, these fish are protected by armor plate
that's neither chalky nor stony but actual bone. Sometimes this
armor takes the shape of a solid triangle, sometimes that of a
solid quadrangle. Among the triangular type, I noticed some half a
decimeter long, with brown tails, yellow fins, and wholesome,
exquisitely tasty flesh; I even recommend that they be acclimatized
to fresh water, a change, incidentally, that a number of saltwater
fish can make with ease. I'll also mention some quadrangular
trunkfish topped by four large protuberances along the back;
trunkfish sprinkled with white spots on the underside of the body,
which make good house pets like certain birds; boxfish armed with
stings formed by extensions of their bony crusts, and whose odd
grunting has earned them the nickname "sea pigs"; then some
trunkfish known as dromedaries, with tough, leathery flesh and big
conical humps.</p>
      <p>From the daily notes kept by Mr. Conseil, I also retrieve
certain fish from the genus <i>Tetradon</i> unique to these seas:
southern puffers with red backs and white chests distinguished by
three lengthwise rows of filaments, and jugfish, seven inches long,
decked out in the brightest colors. Then, as specimens of other
genera, blowfish resembling a dark brown egg, furrowed with white
bands, and lacking tails; globefish, genuine porcupines of the sea,
armed with stings and able to inflate themselves until they look
like a pin cushion bristling with needles; seahorses common to
every ocean; flying dragonfish with long snouts and highly
distended pectoral fins shaped like wings, which enable them, if
not to fly, at least to spring into the air; spatula–shaped
paddlefish whose tails are covered with many scaly rings; snipefish
with long jaws, excellent animals twenty–five centimeters
long and gleaming with the most cheerful colors; bluish gray
dragonets with wrinkled heads; myriads of leaping blennies with
black stripes and long pectoral fins, gliding over the surface of
the water with prodigious speed; delicious sailfish that can hoist
their fins in a favorable current like so many unfurled sails;
splendid nurseryfish on which nature has lavished yellow, azure,
silver, and gold; yellow mackerel with wings made of filaments;
bullheads forever spattered with mud, which make distinct hissing
sounds; sea robins whose livers are thought to be poisonous;
ladyfish that can flutter their eyelids; finally, archerfish with
long, tubular snouts, real oceangoing flycatchers, armed with a
rifle unforeseen by either Remington or Chassepot: it slays insects
by shooting them with a simple drop of water.</p>
      <p>From the eighty–ninth fish genus in
Lacépède's system of classification, belonging to his
second subclass of bony fish (characterized by gill covers and a
bronchial membrane), I noted some scorpionfish whose heads are
adorned with stings and which have only one dorsal fin; these
animals are covered with small scales, or have none at all,
depending on the subgenus to which they belong. The second subgenus
gave us some <i>Didactylus</i> specimens three to four decimeters
long, streaked with yellow, their heads having a phantasmagoric
appearance. As for the first subgenus, it furnished several
specimens of that bizarre fish aptly nicknamed "toadfish," whose
big head is sometimes gouged with deep cavities, sometimes swollen
with protuberances; bristling with stings and strewn with nodules,
it sports hideously irregular horns; its body and tail are adorned
with callosities; its stings can inflict dangerous injuries; it's
repulsive and horrible.</p>
      <p>From January 21 to the 23rd, the <i>Nautilus</i> traveled at the
rate of 250 leagues in twenty–four hours, hence 540 miles at
twenty–two miles per hour. If, during our trip, we were able
to identify these different varieties of fish, it's because they
were attracted by our electric light and tried to follow alongside;
but most of them were outdistanced by our speed and soon fell
behind; temporarily, however, a few managed to keep pace in the
<i>Nautilus's</i> waters.</p>
      <p>On the morning of the 24th, in latitude 12° 5' south and
longitude 94° 33', we raised Keeling Island, a madreporic
upheaving planted with magnificent coconut trees, which had been
visited by Mr. Darwin and Captain Fitzroy. The <i>Nautilus</i>
cruised along a short distance off the shore of this desert island.
Our dragnets brought up many specimens of polyps and echinoderms
plus some unusual shells from the branch <i>Mollusca</i>. Captain
Nemo's treasures were enhanced by some valuable exhibits from the
<i>delphinula</i> snail species, to which I joined some pointed
star coral, a sort of parasitic polypary that often attaches itself
to seashells.</p>
      <p>Soon Keeling Island disappeared below the horizon, and our
course was set to the northwest, toward the tip of the Indian
peninsula.</p>
      <p>"Civilization!" Ned Land told me that day. "Much better than
those Papuan Islands where we ran into more savages than venison!
On this Indian shore, professor, there are roads and railways,
English, French, and Hindu villages. We wouldn't go five miles
without bumping into a fellow countryman. Come on now, isn't it
time for our sudden departure from Captain Nemo?"</p>
      <p>"No, no, Ned," I replied in a very firm tone. "Let's ride it
out, as you seafaring fellows say. The <i>Nautilus</i> is
approaching populated areas. It's going back toward Europe, let it
take us there. After we arrive in home waters, we can do as we see
fit. Besides, I don't imagine Captain Nemo will let us go hunting
on the coasts of Malabar or Coromandel as he did in the forests of
New Guinea."</p>
      <p>"Well, sir, can't we manage without his permission?"</p>
      <p>I didn't answer the Canadian. I wanted no arguments. Deep down,
I was determined to fully exploit the good fortune that had put me
on board the <i>Nautilus</i>.</p>
      <p>After leaving Keeling Island, our pace got generally slower. It
also got more unpredictable, often taking us to great depths.
Several times we used our slanting fins, which internal levers
could set at an oblique angle to our waterline. Thus we went as
deep as two or three kilometers down but without ever verifying the
lowest depths of this sea near India, which soundings of 13,000
meters have been unable to reach. As for the temperature in these
lower strata, the thermometer always and invariably indicated
4° centigrade. I merely observed that in the upper layers, the
water was always colder over shallows than in the open sea.</p>
      <p>On January 25, the ocean being completely deserted, the
<i>Nautilus</i> spent the day on the surface, churning the waves
with its powerful propeller and making them spurt to great heights.
Under these conditions, who wouldn't have mistaken it for a
gigantic <i>cetacean</i>? I spent three–quarters of the day
on the platform. I stared at the sea. Nothing on the horizon,
except near four o'clock in the afternoon a long steamer to the
west, running on our opposite tack. Its masting was visible for an
instant, but it couldn't have seen the <i>Nautilus</i> because we
were lying too low in the water. I imagine that steamboat belonged
to the Peninsular &amp; Oriental line, which provides service from
the island of Ceylon to Sidney, also calling at King George Sound
and Melbourne.</p>
      <p>At five o'clock in the afternoon, just before that brief
twilight that links day with night in tropical zones, Conseil and I
marveled at an unusual sight.</p>
      <p>It was a delightful animal whose discovery, according to the
ancients, is a sign of good luck. Aristotle, Athenaeus, Pliny, and
Oppian studied its habits and lavished on its behalf all the
scientific poetry of Greece and Italy. They called it "nautilus"
and "pompilius." But modern science has not endorsed these
designations, and this mollusk is now known by the name
argonaut.</p>
      <p>Anyone consulting Conseil would soon learn from the gallant lad
that the branch <i>Mollusca</i> is divided into five classes; that
the first class features the <i>Cephalopoda</i> (whose members are
sometimes naked, sometimes covered with a shell), which consists of
two families, the <i>Dibranchiata</i> and the
<i>Tetrabranchiata</i>, which are distinguished by their number of
gills; that the family <i>Dibranchiata</i> includes three genera,
the argonaut, the squid, and the cuttlefish, and that the family
<i>Tetrabranchiata</i> contains only one genus, the nautilus. After
this catalog, if some recalcitrant listener confuses the argonaut,
which is <i>acetabuliferous</i> (in other words, a bearer of
suction tubes), with the nautilus, which is <i>tentaculiferous</i>
(a bearer of tentacles), it will be simply unforgivable.</p>
      <p>Now, it was a school of argonauts then voyaging on the surface
of the ocean. We could count several hundred of them. They belonged
to that species of argonaut covered with protuberances and
exclusive to the seas near India.</p>
      <p>These graceful mollusks were swimming backward by means of their
locomotive tubes, sucking water into these tubes and then expelling
it. Six of their eight tentacles were long, thin, and floated on
the water, while the other two were rounded into palms and spread
to the wind like light sails. I could see perfectly their
undulating, spiral–shaped shells, which Cuvier aptly compared
to an elegant cockleboat. It's an actual boat indeed. It transports
the animal that secretes it without the animal sticking to it.</p>
      <p>"The argonaut is free to leave its shell," I told Conseil, "but
it never does."</p>
      <p>"Not unlike Captain Nemo," Conseil replied sagely. "Which is why
he should have christened his ship the <i>Argonaut</i>."</p>
      <p>For about an hour the <i>Nautilus</i> cruised in the midst of
this school of mollusks. Then, lord knows why, they were gripped
with a sudden fear. As if at a signal, every sail was abruptly
lowered; arms folded, bodies contracted, shells turned over by
changing their center of gravity, and the whole flotilla
disappeared under the waves. It was instantaneous, and no squadron
of ships ever maneuvered with greater togetherness.</p>
      <p>Just then night fell suddenly, and the waves barely surged in
the breeze, spreading placidly around the <i>Nautilus's</i> side
plates.</p>
      <p>The next day, January 26, we cut the equator on the 82nd
meridian and we reentered the northern hemisphere.</p>
      <p>During that day a fearsome school of sharks provided us with an
escort. Dreadful animals that teem in these seas and make them
extremely dangerous. There were Port Jackson sharks with a brown
back, a whitish belly, and eleven rows of teeth, bigeye sharks with
necks marked by a large black spot encircled in white and
resembling an eye, and Isabella sharks whose rounded snouts were
strewn with dark speckles. Often these powerful animals rushed at
the lounge window with a violence less than comforting. By this
point Ned Land had lost all self–control. He wanted to rise
to the surface of the waves and harpoon the monsters, especially
certain smooth–hound sharks whose mouths were paved with
teeth arranged like a mosaic, and some big five–meter tiger
sharks that insisted on personally provoking him. But the
<i>Nautilus</i> soon picked up speed and easily left astern the
fastest of these man–eaters.</p>
      <p>On January 27, at the entrance to the huge Bay of Bengal, we
repeatedly encountered a gruesome sight: human corpses floating on
the surface of the waves! Carried by the Ganges to the high seas,
these were deceased Indian villagers who hadn't been fully devoured
by vultures, the only morticians in these parts. But there was no
shortage of sharks to assist them with their undertaking
chores.</p>
      <p>Near seven o'clock in the evening, the <i>Nautilus</i> lay half
submerged, navigating in the midst of milky white waves. As far as
the eye could see, the ocean seemed lactified. Was it an effect of
the moon's rays? No, because the new moon was barely two days old
and was still lost below the horizon in the sun's rays. The entire
sky, although lit up by stellar radiation, seemed pitch–black
in comparison with the whiteness of these waters.</p>
      <p>Conseil couldn't believe his eyes, and he questioned me about
the causes of this odd phenomenon. Luckily I was in a position to
answer him.</p>
      <p>"That's called a milk sea," I told him, "a vast expanse of white
waves often seen along the coasts of Amboina and in these
waterways."</p>
      <p>"But," Conseil asked, "could master tell me the cause of this
effect, because I presume this water hasn't really changed into
milk!"</p>
      <p>"No, my boy, and this whiteness that amazes you is merely due to
the presence of myriads of tiny creatures called infusoria, a sort
of diminutive glowworm that's colorless and gelatinous in
appearance, as thick as a strand of hair, and no longer than
one–fifth of a millimeter. Some of these tiny creatures stick
together over an area of several leagues."</p>
      <p>"Several leagues!" Conseil exclaimed.</p>
      <p>"Yes, my boy, and don't even try to compute the number of these
infusoria. You won't pull it off, because if I'm not mistaken,
certain navigators have cruised through milk seas for more than
forty miles."</p>
      <p>I'm not sure that Conseil heeded my recommendation, because he
seemed to be deep in thought, no doubt trying to calculate how many
one–fifths of a millimeter are found in forty square miles.
As for me, I continued to observe this phenomenon. For several
hours the <i>Nautilus's</i> spur sliced through these whitish
waves, and I watched it glide noiselessly over this soapy water, as
if it were cruising through those foaming eddies that a bay's
currents and countercurrents sometimes leave between each
other.</p>
      <p>Near midnight the sea suddenly resumed its usual hue, but behind
us all the way to the horizon, the skies kept mirroring the
whiteness of those waves and for a good while seemed imbued with
the hazy glow of an aurora borealis.</p>
   </body>
</topic>