<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<topic id="d2e7243">
   <title>
      <d4pSimpleEnumerator><!--1.24-->Chapter 24. </d4pSimpleEnumerator>
      <ph>The Coral Realm</ph>
   </title>
   <body>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="size_plus_2">THE NEXT DAY</ph> I woke up with my head
unusually clear. Much to my surprise, I was in my stateroom. No
doubt my companions had been put back in their cabin without
noticing it any more than I had. Like me, they would have no idea
what took place during the night, and to unravel this mystery I
could count only on some future happenstance.</p>
      <p>I then considered leaving my stateroom. Was I free or still a
prisoner? Perfectly free. I opened my door, headed down the
gangways, and climbed the central companionway. Hatches that had
been closed the day before were now open. I arrived on the
platform.</p>
      <p>Ned Land and Conseil were there waiting for me. I questioned
them. They knew nothing. Lost in a heavy sleep of which they had no
memory, they were quite startled to be back in their cabin.</p>
      <p>As for the <i>Nautilus</i>, it seemed as tranquil and mysterious
as ever. It was cruising on the surface of the waves at a moderate
speed. Nothing seemed to have changed on board.</p>
      <p>Ned Land observed the sea with his penetrating eyes. It was
deserted. The Canadian sighted nothing new on the horizon, neither
sail nor shore. A breeze was blowing noisily from the west, and
disheveled by the wind, long billows made the submersible roll very
noticeably.</p>
      <p>After renewing its air, the <i>Nautilus</i> stayed at an average
depth of fifteen meters, enabling it to return quickly to the
surface of the waves. And, contrary to custom, it executed such a
maneuver several times during that day of January 19. The chief
officer would then climb onto the platform, and his usual phrase
would ring through the ship's interior.</p>
      <p>As for Captain Nemo, he didn't appear. Of the other men on
board, I saw only my emotionless steward, who served me with his
usual mute efficiency.</p>
      <p>Near two o'clock I was busy organizing my notes in the lounge,
when the captain opened the door and appeared. I bowed to him. He
gave me an almost imperceptible bow in return, without saying a
word to me. I resumed my work, hoping he might give me some
explanation of the previous afternoon's events. He did nothing of
the sort. I stared at him. His face looked exhausted; his reddened
eyes hadn't been refreshed by sleep; his facial features expressed
profound sadness, real chagrin. He walked up and down, sat and
stood, picked up a book at random, discarded it immediately,
consulted his instruments without taking his customary notes, and
seemed unable to rest easy for an instant.</p>
      <p>Finally he came over to me and said:</p>
      <p>"Are you a physician, Professor Aronnax?"</p>
      <p>This inquiry was so unexpected that I stared at him a good while
without replying.</p>
      <p>"Are you a physician?" he repeated. "Several of your scientific
colleagues took their degrees in medicine, such as Gratiolet,
Moquin–Tandon, and others."</p>
      <p>"That's right," I said, "I am a doctor, I used to be on call at
the hospitals. I was in practice for several years before joining
the museum."</p>
      <p>"Excellent, sir."</p>
      <p>My reply obviously pleased Captain Nemo. But not knowing what he
was driving at, I waited for further questions, ready to reply as
circumstances dictated.</p>
      <p>"Professor Aronnax," the captain said to me, "would you consent
to give your medical attentions to one of my men?"</p>
      <p>"Someone is sick?"</p>
      <p>"Yes."</p>
      <p>"I'm ready to go with you."</p>
      <p>"Come."</p>
      <p>I admit that my heart was pounding. Lord knows why, but I saw a
definite connection between this sick crewman and yesterday's
happenings, and the mystery of those events concerned me at least
as much as the man's sickness.</p>
      <p>Captain Nemo led me to the <i>Nautilus's</i> stern and invited
me into a cabin located next to the sailors' quarters.</p>
      <p>On a bed there lay a man some forty years old, with strongly
molded features, the very image of an Anglo–Saxon.</p>
      <p>I bent over him. Not only was he sick, he was wounded. Swathed
in blood–soaked linen, his head was resting on a folded
pillow. I undid the linen bandages, while the wounded man gazed
with great staring eyes and let me proceed without making a single
complaint.</p>
      <p>It was a horrible wound. The cranium had been smashed open by
some blunt instrument, leaving the naked brains exposed, and the
cerebral matter had suffered deep abrasions. Blood clots had formed
in this dissolving mass, taking on the color of wine dregs. Both
contusion and concussion of the brain had occurred. The sick man's
breathing was labored, and muscle spasms quivered in his face.
Cerebral inflammation was complete and had brought on a paralysis
of movement and sensation.</p>
      <p>I took the wounded man's pulse. It was intermittent. The body's
extremities were already growing cold, and I saw that death was
approaching without any possibility of my holding it in check.
After dressing the poor man's wound, I redid the linen bandages
around his head, and I turned to Captain Nemo.</p>
      <p>"How did he get this wound?" I asked him.</p>
      <p>"That's not important," the captain replied evasively. "The
<i>Nautilus</i> suffered a collision that cracked one of the engine
levers, and it struck this man. My chief officer was standing
beside him. This man leaped forward to intercept the blow. A
brother lays down his life for his brother, a friend for his
friend, what could be simpler? That's the law for everyone on board
the <i>Nautilus</i>. But what's your diagnosis of his
condition?"</p>
      <p>I hesitated to speak my mind.</p>
      <p>"You may talk freely," the captain told me. "This man doesn't
understand French."</p>
      <p>I took a last look at the wounded man, then I replied:</p>
      <p>"This man will be dead in two hours."</p>
      <p>"Nothing can save him?"</p>
      <p>"Nothing."</p>
      <p>Captain Nemo clenched his fists, and tears slid from his eyes,
which I had thought incapable of weeping.</p>
      <p>For a few moments more I observed the dying man, whose life was
ebbing little by little. He grew still more pale under the electric
light that bathed his deathbed. I looked at his intelligent head,
furrowed with premature wrinkles that misfortune, perhaps misery,
had etched long before. I was hoping to detect the secret of his
life in the last words that might escape from his lips!</p>
      <p>"You may go, Professor Aronnax," Captain Nemo told me.</p>
      <p>I left the captain in the dying man's cabin and I repaired to my
stateroom, very moved by this scene. All day long I was aquiver
with gruesome forebodings. That night I slept poorly, and between
my fitful dreams, I thought I heard a distant moaning, like a
funeral dirge. Was it a prayer for the dead, murmured in that
language I couldn't understand?</p>
      <p>The next morning I climbed on deck. Captain Nemo was already
there. As soon as he saw me, he came over.</p>
      <p>"Professor," he said to me, "would it be convenient for you to
make an underwater excursion today?"</p>
      <p>"With my companions?" I asked.</p>
      <p>"If they're agreeable."</p>
      <p>"We're yours to command, Captain."</p>
      <p>"Then kindly put on your diving suits."</p>
      <p>As for the dead or dying man, he hadn't come into the picture. I
rejoined Ned Land and Conseil. I informed them of Captain Nemo's
proposition. Conseil was eager to accept, and this time the
Canadian proved perfectly amenable to going with us.</p>
      <p>It was eight o'clock in the morning. By 8:30 we were suited up
for this new stroll and equipped with our two devices for lighting
and breathing. The double door opened, and accompanied by Captain
Nemo with a dozen crewmen following, we set foot on the firm
seafloor where the <i>Nautilus</i> was resting, ten meters
down.</p>
      <p>A gentle slope gravitated to an uneven bottom whose depth was
about fifteen fathoms. This bottom was completely different from
the one I had visited during my first excursion under the waters of
the Pacific Ocean. Here I saw no fine–grained sand, no
underwater prairies, not one open–sea forest. I immediately
recognized the wondrous region in which Captain Nemo did the honors
that day. It was the coral realm.</p>
      <p>In the zoophyte branch, class <i>Alcyonaria</i>, one finds the
order <i>Gorgonaria</i>, which contains three groups: sea fans,
isidian polyps, and coral polyps. It's in this last that precious
coral belongs, an unusual substance that, at different times, has
been classified in the mineral, vegetable, and animal kingdoms.
Medicine to the ancients, jewelry to the moderns, it wasn't
decisively placed in the animal kingdom until 1694, by Peysonnel of
Marseilles.</p>
      <p>A coral is a unit of tiny animals assembled over a polypary
that's brittle and stony in nature. These polyps have a unique
generating mechanism that reproduces them via the budding process,
and they have an individual existence while also participating in a
communal life. Hence they embody a sort of natural socialism. I was
familiar with the latest research on this bizarre
zoophyte—which turns to stone while taking on a tree form, as
some naturalists have very aptly observed—and nothing could
have been more fascinating to me than to visit one of these
petrified forests that nature has planted on the bottom of the
sea.</p>
      <p>We turned on our Ruhmkorff devices and went along a coral shoal
in the process of forming, which, given time, will someday close
off this whole part of the Indian Ocean. Our path was bordered by
hopelessly tangled bushes, formed from snarls of shrubs all covered
with little star–shaped, white–streaked flowers. Only,
contrary to plants on shore, these tree forms become attached to
rocks on the seafloor by heading from top to bottom.</p>
      <p>Our lights produced a thousand delightful effects while playing
over these brightly colored boughs. I fancied I saw these
cylindrical, membrane–filled tubes trembling beneath the
water's undulations. I was tempted to gather their fresh petals,
which were adorned with delicate tentacles, some newly in bloom,
others barely opened, while nimble fish with fluttering fins
brushed past them like flocks of birds. But if my hands came near
the moving flowers of these sensitive, lively creatures, an alarm
would instantly sound throughout the colony. The white petals
retracted into their red sheaths, the flowers vanished before my
eyes, and the bush changed into a chunk of stony nipples.</p>
      <p>Sheer chance had placed me in the presence of the most valuable
specimens of this zoophyte. This coral was the equal of those
fished up from the Mediterranean off the Barbary Coast or the
shores of France and Italy. With its bright colors, it lived up to
those poetic names of blood flower and blood foam that the industry
confers on its finest exhibits. Coral sells for as much as
₣500 per kilogram, and in this locality the liquid strata hid
enough to make the fortunes of a whole host of coral fishermen.
This valuable substance often merges with other polyparies, forming
compact, hopelessly tangled units known as "macciota," and I noted
some wonderful pink samples of this coral.</p>
      <p>But as the bushes shrank, the tree forms magnified. Actual
petrified thickets and long alcoves from some fantastic school of
architecture kept opening up before our steps. Captain Nemo entered
beneath a dark gallery whose gentle slope took us to a depth of 100
meters. The light from our glass coils produced magical effects at
times, lingering on the wrinkled roughness of some natural arch, or
some overhang suspended like a chandelier, which our lamps flecked
with fiery sparks. Amid these shrubs of precious coral, I observed
other polyps no less unusual: melita coral, rainbow coral with
jointed outgrowths, then a few tufts of genus Corallina, some green
and others red, actually a type of seaweed encrusted with limestone
salts, which, after long disputes, naturalists have finally placed
in the vegetable kingdom. But as one intellectual has remarked,
"Here, perhaps, is the actual point where life rises humbly out of
slumbering stone, but without breaking away from its crude starting
point."</p>
      <p>Finally, after two hours of walking, we reached a depth of about
300 meters, in other words, the lowermost limit at which coral can
begin to form. But here it was no longer some isolated bush or a
modest grove of low timber. It was an immense forest, huge mineral
vegetation, enormous petrified trees linked by garlands of elegant
hydras from the genus Plumularia, those tropical creepers of the
sea, all decked out in shades and gleams. We passed freely under
their lofty boughs, lost up in the shadows of the waves, while at
our feet organ–pipe coral, stony coral, star coral, fungus
coral, and sea anemone from the genus Caryophylia formed a carpet
of flowers all strewn with dazzling gems.</p>
      <p>What an indescribable sight! Oh, if only we could share our
feelings! Why were we imprisoned behind these masks of metal and
glass! Why were we forbidden to talk with each other! At least let
us lead the lives of the fish that populate this liquid element, or
better yet, the lives of amphibians, which can spend long hours
either at sea or on shore, traveling through their double domain as
their whims dictate!</p>
      <p>Meanwhile Captain Nemo had called a halt. My companions and I
stopped walking, and turning around, I saw the crewmen form a
semicircle around their leader. Looking with greater care, I
observed that four of them were carrying on their shoulders an
object that was oblong in shape.</p>
      <p>At this locality we stood in the center of a huge clearing
surrounded by the tall tree forms of this underwater forest. Our
lamps cast a sort of brilliant twilight over the area, making
inordinately long shadows on the seafloor. Past the boundaries of
the clearing, the darkness deepened again, relieved only by little
sparkles given off by the sharp crests of coral.</p>
      <p>Ned Land and Conseil stood next to me. We stared, and it dawned
on me that I was about to witness a strange scene. Observing the
seafloor, I saw that it swelled at certain points from low bulges
that were encrusted with limestone deposits and arranged with a
symmetry that betrayed the hand of man.</p>
      <p>In the middle of the clearing, on a pedestal of roughly piled
rocks, there stood a cross of coral, extending long arms you would
have thought were made of petrified blood.</p>
      <p>At a signal from Captain Nemo, one of his men stepped forward
and, a few feet from this cross, detached a mattock from his belt
and began to dig a hole.</p>
      <p>I finally understood! This clearing was a cemetery, this hole a
grave, that oblong object the body of the man who must have died
during the night! Captain Nemo and his men had come to bury their
companion in this communal resting place on the inaccessible ocean
floor!</p>
      <p>No! My mind was reeling as never before! Never had ideas of such
impact raced through my brain! I didn't want to see what my eyes
saw!</p>
      <p>Meanwhile the grave digging went slowly. Fish fled here and
there as their retreat was disturbed. I heard the pick ringing on
the limestone soil, its iron tip sometimes giving off sparks when
it hit a stray piece of flint on the sea bottom. The hole grew
longer, wider, and soon was deep enough to receive the body.</p>
      <p>Then the pallbearers approached. Wrapped in white fabric made
from filaments of the fan mussel, the body was lowered into its
watery grave. Captain Nemo, arms crossed over his chest, knelt in a
posture of prayer, as did all the friends of him who had loved
them. . . . My two companions and I bowed reverently.</p>
      <p>The grave was then covered over with the rubble dug from the
seafloor, and it formed a low mound.</p>
      <p>When this was done, Captain Nemo and his men stood up; then they
all approached the grave, sank again on bended knee, and extended
their hands in a sign of final farewell. . . .</p>
      <p>Then the funeral party went back up the path to the
<i>Nautilus</i>, returning beneath the arches of the forest,
through the thickets, along the coral bushes, going steadily
higher.</p>
      <p>Finally the ship's rays appeared. Their luminous trail guided us
to the <i>Nautilus</i>. By one o'clock we had returned.</p>
      <p>After changing clothes, I climbed onto the platform, and in the
grip of dreadfully obsessive thoughts, I sat next to the
beacon.</p>
      <p>Captain Nemo rejoined me. I stood up and said to him:</p>
      <p>"So, as I predicted, that man died during the night?"</p>
      <p>"Yes, Professor Aronnax," Captain Nemo replied.</p>
      <p>"And now he rests beside his companions in that coral
cemetery?"</p>
      <p>"Yes, forgotten by the world but not by us! We dig the graves,
then entrust the polyps with sealing away our dead for
eternity!"</p>
      <p>And with a sudden gesture, the captain hid his face in his
clenched fists, vainly trying to hold back a sob. Then he
added:</p>
      <p>"There lies our peaceful cemetery, hundreds of feet beneath the
surface of the waves!"</p>
      <p>"At least, captain, your dead can sleep serenely there, out of
the reach of sharks!"</p>
      <p>"Yes, sir," Captain Nemo replied solemnly, "of sharks and
men!"</p>
   </body>
</topic>