<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<topic id="d2e8242">
   <title>
      <d4pSimpleEnumerator><!--2.3-->Chapter 3. </d4pSimpleEnumerator>
      <ph>A Pearl Worth Ten Million</ph>
   </title>
   <body>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="size_plus_2">NIGHT FELL</ph>. I went to bed. I slept pretty
poorly. Man–eaters played a major role in my dreams. And I
found it more or less appropriate that the French word for shark,
<i>requin</i>, has its linguistic roots in the word
<i>requiem</i>.</p>
      <p>The next day at four o'clock in the morning, I was awakened by
the steward whom Captain Nemo had placed expressly at my service. I
got up quickly, dressed, and went into the lounge.</p>
      <p>Captain Nemo was waiting for me.</p>
      <p>"Professor Aronnax," he said to me, "are you ready to
start?"</p>
      <p>"I'm ready."</p>
      <p>"Kindly follow me."</p>
      <p>"What about my companions, Captain?"</p>
      <p>"They've been alerted and are waiting for us."</p>
      <p>"Aren't we going to put on our diving suits?" I asked.</p>
      <p>"Not yet. I haven't let the <i>Nautilus</i> pull too near the
coast, and we're fairly well out from the Mannar oysterbank. But I
have the skiff ready, and it will take us to the exact spot where
we'll disembark, which will save us a pretty long trek. It's
carrying our diving equipment, and we'll suit up just before we
begin our underwater exploring."</p>
      <p>Captain Nemo took me to the central companionway whose steps led
to the platform. Ned and Conseil were there, enraptured with the
"pleasure trip" getting under way. Oars in position, five of the
<i>Nautilus's</i> sailors were waiting for us aboard the skiff,
which was moored alongside. The night was still dark. Layers of
clouds cloaked the sky and left only a few stars in view. My eyes
flew to the side where land lay, but I saw only a blurred line
covering three–quarters of the horizon from southwest to
northwest. Going up Ceylon's west coast during the night, the
<i>Nautilus</i> lay west of the bay, or rather that gulf formed by
the mainland and Mannar Island. Under these dark waters there
stretched the bank of shellfish, an inexhaustible field of pearls
more than twenty miles long.</p>
      <p>Captain Nemo, Conseil, Ned Land, and I found seats in the stern
of the skiff. The longboat's coxswain took the tiller; his four
companions leaned into their oars; the moorings were cast off and
we pulled clear.</p>
      <p>The skiff headed southward. The oarsmen took their time. I
watched their strokes vigorously catch the water, and they always
waited ten seconds before rowing again, following the practice used
in most navies. While the longboat coasted, drops of liquid flicked
from the oars and hit the dark troughs of the waves,
pitter–pattering like splashes of molten lead. Coming from
well out, a mild swell made the skiff roll gently, and a few
cresting billows lapped at its bow.</p>
      <p>We were silent. What was Captain Nemo thinking? Perhaps that
this approaching shore was too close for comfort, contrary to the
Canadian's views in which it still seemed too far away. As for
Conseil, he had come along out of simple curiosity.</p>
      <p>Near 5:30 the first glimmers of light on the horizon defined the
upper lines of the coast with greater distinctness. Fairly flat to
the east, it swelled a little toward the south. Five miles still
separated it from us, and its beach merged with the misty waters.
Between us and the shore, the sea was deserted. Not a boat, not a
diver. Profound solitude reigned over this gathering place of pearl
fishermen. As Captain Nemo had commented, we were arriving in these
waterways a month too soon.</p>
      <p>At six o'clock the day broke suddenly, with that speed unique to
tropical regions, which experience no real dawn or dusk. The sun's
rays pierced the cloud curtain gathered on the easterly horizon,
and the radiant orb rose swiftly.</p>
      <p>I could clearly see the shore, which featured a few sparse trees
here and there.</p>
      <p>The skiff advanced toward Mannar Island, which curved to the
south. Captain Nemo stood up from his thwart and studied the
sea.</p>
      <p>At his signal the anchor was lowered, but its chain barely ran
because the bottom lay no more than a meter down, and this locality
was one of the shallowest spots near the bank of shellfish.
Instantly the skiff wheeled around under the ebb tide's outbound
thrust.</p>
      <p>"Here we are, Professor Aronnax," Captain Nemo then said. "You
observe this confined bay? A month from now in this very place, the
numerous fishing boats of the harvesters will gather, and these are
the waters their divers will ransack so daringly. This bay is
felicitously laid out for their type of fishing. It's sheltered
from the strongest winds, and the sea is never very turbulent here,
highly favorable conditions for diving work. Now let's put on our
underwater suits, and we'll begin our stroll."</p>
      <p>I didn't reply, and while staring at these suspicious waves, I
began to put on my heavy aquatic clothes, helped by the longboat's
sailors. Captain Nemo and my two companions suited up as well. None
of the <i>Nautilus's</i> men were to go with us on this new
excursion.</p>
      <p>Soon we were imprisoned up to the neck in india–rubber
clothing, and straps fastened the air devices onto our backs. As
for the Ruhmkorff device, it didn't seem to be in the picture.
Before inserting my head into its copper capsule, I commented on
this to the captain.</p>
      <p>"Our lighting equipment would be useless to us," the captain
answered me. "We won't be going very deep, and the sun's rays will
be sufficient to light our way. Besides, it's unwise to carry
electric lanterns under these waves. Their brightness might
unexpectedly attract certain dangerous occupants of these
waterways."</p>
      <p>As Captain Nemo pronounced these words, I turned to Conseil and
Ned Land. But my two friends had already encased their craniums in
their metal headgear, and they could neither hear nor reply.</p>
      <p>I had one question left to address to Captain Nemo.</p>
      <p>"What about our weapons?" I asked him. "Our rifles?"</p>
      <p>"Rifles! What for? Don't your mountaineers attack bears dagger
in hand? And isn't steel surer than lead? Here's a sturdy blade.
Slip it under your belt and let's be off."</p>
      <p>I stared at my companions. They were armed in the same fashion,
and Ned Land was also brandishing an enormous harpoon he had stowed
in the skiff before leaving the <i>Nautilus</i>.</p>
      <p>Then, following the captain's example, I let myself be crowned
with my heavy copper sphere, and our air tanks immediately went
into action.</p>
      <p>An instant later, the longboat's sailors helped us overboard one
after the other, and we set foot on level sand in a meter and a
half of water. Captain Nemo gave us a hand signal. We followed him
down a gentle slope and disappeared under the waves.</p>
      <p>There the obsessive fears in my brain left me. I became
surprisingly calm again. The ease with which I could move increased
my confidence, and the many strange sights captivated my
imagination.</p>
      <p>The sun was already sending sufficient light under these waves.
The tiniest objects remained visible. After ten minutes of walking,
we were in five meters of water, and the terrain had become almost
flat.</p>
      <p>Like a covey of snipe over a marsh, there rose underfoot schools
of unusual fish from the genus <i>Monopterus</i>, whose members
have no fin but their tail. I recognized the Javanese eel, a
genuine eight–decimeter serpent with a bluish gray belly,
which, without the gold lines over its flanks, could easily be
confused with the conger eel. From the butterfish genus, whose oval
bodies are very flat, I observed several adorned in brilliant
colors and sporting a dorsal fin like a sickle, edible fish that,
when dried and marinated, make an excellent dish known by the name
"karawade"; then some sea poachers, fish belonging to the genus
<i>Aspidophoroides</i>, whose bodies are covered with scaly armor
divided into eight lengthwise sections.</p>
      <p>Meanwhile, as the sun got progressively higher, it lit up the
watery mass more and more. The seafloor changed little by little.
Its fine–grained sand was followed by a genuine causeway of
smooth crags covered by a carpet of mollusks and zoophytes. Among
other specimens in these two branches, I noted some windowpane
oysters with thin valves of unequal size, a type of ostracod unique
to the Red Sea and the Indian Ocean, then orange–hued lucina
with circular shells, awl–shaped auger shells, some of those
Persian murex snails that supply the <i>Nautilus</i> with such
wonderful dye, spiky periwinkles fifteen centimeters long that rose
under the waves like hands ready to grab you, turban snails with
shells made of horn and bristling all over with spines, lamp
shells, edible duck clams that feed the Hindu marketplace, subtly
luminous jellyfish of the species <i>Pelagia panopyra</i>, and
finally some wonderful <i>Oculina flabelliforma</i>, magnificent
sea fans that fashion one of the most luxuriant tree forms in this
ocean.</p>
      <p>In the midst of this moving vegetation, under arbors of water
plants, there raced legions of clumsy articulates, in particular
some fanged frog crabs whose carapaces form a slightly rounded
triangle, robber crabs exclusive to these waterways, and horrible
parthenope crabs whose appearance was repulsive to the eye. One
animal no less hideous, which I encountered several times, was the
enormous crab that Mr. Darwin observed, to which nature has given
the instinct and requisite strength to eat coconuts; it scrambles
up trees on the beach and sends the coconuts tumbling; they
fracture in their fall and are opened by its powerful pincers.
Here, under these clear waves, this crab raced around with
matchless agility, while green turtles from the species frequenting
the Malabar coast moved sluggishly among the crumbling rocks.</p>
      <p>Near seven o'clock we finally surveyed the bank of shellfish,
where pearl oysters reproduce by the millions. These valuable
mollusks stick to rocks, where they're strongly attached by a mass
of brown filaments that forbids their moving about. In this respect
oysters are inferior even to mussels, to whom nature has not denied
all talent for locomotion.</p>
      <p>The shellfish Meleagrina, that womb for pearls whose valves are
nearly equal in size, has the shape of a round shell with thick
walls and a very rough exterior. Some of these shells were furrowed
with flaky, greenish bands that radiated down from the top. These
were the young oysters. The others had rugged black surfaces,
measured up to fifteen centimeters in width, and were ten or more
years old.</p>
      <p>Captain Nemo pointed to this prodigious heap of shellfish, and I
saw that these mines were genuinely inexhaustible, since nature's
creative powers are greater than man's destructive instincts. True
to those instincts, Ned Land greedily stuffed the finest of these
mollusks into a net he carried at his side.</p>
      <p>But we couldn't stop. We had to follow the captain, who headed
down trails seemingly known only to himself. The seafloor rose
noticeably, and when I lifted my arms, sometimes they would pass
above the surface of the sea. Then the level of the oysterbank
would lower unpredictably. Often we went around tall, pointed rocks
rising like pyramids. In their dark crevices huge crustaceans,
aiming their long legs like heavy artillery, watched us with
unblinking eyes, while underfoot there crept millipedes,
bloodworms, aricia worms, and annelid worms, whose antennas and
tubular tentacles were incredibly long.</p>
      <p>Just then a huge cave opened up in our path, hollowed from a
picturesque pile of rocks whose smooth heights were completely hung
with underwater flora. At first this cave looked pitch–black
to me. Inside, the sun's rays seemed to diminish by degrees. Their
hazy transparency was nothing more than drowned light.</p>
      <p>Captain Nemo went in. We followed him. My eyes soon grew
accustomed to this comparative gloom. I distinguished the
unpredictably contoured springings of a vault, supported by natural
pillars firmly based on a granite foundation, like the weighty
columns of Tuscan architecture. Why had our incomprehensible guide
taken us into the depths of this underwater crypt? I would soon
find out.</p>
      <p>After going down a fairly steep slope, our feet trod the floor
of a sort of circular pit. There Captain Nemo stopped, and his hand
indicated an object that I hadn't yet noticed.</p>
      <p>It was an oyster of extraordinary dimensions, a titanic giant
clam, a holy–water font that could have held a whole lake, a
basin more than two meters wide, hence even bigger than the one
adorning the <i>Nautilus's</i> lounge.</p>
      <p>I approached this phenomenal mollusk. Its mass of filaments
attached it to a table of granite, and there it grew by itself in
the midst of the cave's calm waters. I estimated the weight of this
giant clam at 300 kilograms. Hence such an oyster held fifteen
kilos of meat, and you'd need the stomach of King Gargantua to eat
a couple dozen.</p>
      <p>Captain Nemo was obviously familiar with this bivalve's
existence. This wasn't the first time he'd paid it a visit, and I
thought his sole reason for leading us to this locality was to show
us a natural curiosity. I was mistaken. Captain Nemo had an
explicit personal interest in checking on the current condition of
this giant clam.</p>
      <p>The mollusk's two valves were partly open. The captain
approached and stuck his dagger vertically between the shells to
discourage any ideas about closing; then with his hands he raised
the fringed, membrane–filled tunic that made up the animal's
mantle.</p>
      <p>There, between its leaflike folds, I saw a loose pearl as big as
a coconut. Its globular shape, perfect clarity, and wonderful
orient made it a jewel of incalculable value. Carried away by
curiosity, I stretched out my hand to take it, weigh it, fondle it!
But the captain stopped me, signaled no, removed his dagger in one
swift motion, and let the two valves snap shut.</p>
      <p>I then understood Captain Nemo's intent. By leaving the pearl
buried beneath the giant clam's mantle, he allowed it to grow
imperceptibly. With each passing year the mollusk's secretions
added new concentric layers. The captain alone was familiar with
the cave where this wonderful fruit of nature was "ripening"; he
alone reared it, so to speak, in order to transfer it one day to
his dearly beloved museum. Perhaps, following the examples of
oyster farmers in China and India, he had even predetermined the
creation of this pearl by sticking under the mollusk's folds some
piece of glass or metal that was gradually covered with
mother–of–pearl. In any case, comparing this pearl to
others I already knew about, and to those shimmering in the
captain's collection, I estimated that it was worth at least
₣10,000,000. It was a superb natural curiosity rather than a
luxurious piece of jewelry, because I don't know of any female ear
that could handle it.</p>
      <p>Our visit to this opulent giant clam came to an end. Captain
Nemo left the cave, and we climbed back up the bank of shellfish in
the midst of these clear waters not yet disturbed by divers at
work.</p>
      <p>We walked by ourselves, genuine loiterers stopping or straying
as our fancies dictated. For my part, I was no longer worried about
those dangers my imagination had so ridiculously exaggerated. The
shallows drew noticeably closer to the surface of the sea, and
soon, walking in only a meter of water, my head passed well above
the level of the ocean. Conseil rejoined me, and gluing his huge
copper capsule to mine, his eyes gave me a friendly greeting. But
this lofty plateau measured only a few fathoms, and soon we
reentered Our Element. I think I've now earned the right to dub it
that.</p>
      <p>Ten minutes later, Captain Nemo stopped suddenly. I thought he'd
called a halt so that we could turn and start back. No. With a
gesture he ordered us to crouch beside him at the foot of a wide
crevice. His hand motioned toward a spot within the liquid mass,
and I looked carefully.</p>
      <p>Five meters away a shadow appeared and dropped to the seafloor.
The alarming idea of sharks crossed my mind. But I was mistaken,
and once again we didn't have to deal with monsters of the
deep.</p>
      <p>It was a man, a living man, a black Indian fisherman, a poor
devil who no doubt had come to gather what he could before harvest
time. I saw the bottom of his dinghy, moored a few feet above his
head. He would dive and go back up in quick succession. A stone cut
in the shape of a sugar loaf, which he gripped between his feet
while a rope connected it to his boat, served to lower him more
quickly to the ocean floor. This was the extent of his equipment.
Arriving on the seafloor at a depth of about five meters, he fell
to his knees and stuffed his sack with shellfish gathered at
random. Then he went back up, emptied his sack, pulled up his
stone, and started all over again, the whole process lasting only
thirty seconds.</p>
      <p>This diver didn't see us. A shadow cast by our crag hid us from
his view. And besides, how could this poor Indian ever have guessed
that human beings, creatures like himself, were near him under the
waters, eavesdropping on his movements, not missing a single detail
of his fishing!</p>
      <p>So he went up and down several times. He gathered only about ten
shellfish per dive, because he had to tear them from the banks
where each clung with its tough mass of filaments. And how many of
these oysters for which he risked his life would have no pearl in
them!</p>
      <p>I observed him with great care. His movements were
systematically executed, and for half an hour no danger seemed to
threaten him. So I had gotten used to the sight of this fascinating
fishing when all at once, just as the Indian was kneeling on the
seafloor, I saw him make a frightened gesture, stand, and gather
himself to spring back to the surface of the waves.</p>
      <p>I understood his fear. A gigantic shadow appeared above the poor
diver. It was a shark of huge size, moving in diagonally, eyes
ablaze, jaws wide open!</p>
      <p>I was speechless with horror, unable to make a single
movement.</p>
      <p>With one vigorous stroke of its fins, the voracious animal shot
toward the Indian, who jumped aside and avoided the shark's bite
but not the thrashing of its tail, because that tail struck him
across the chest and stretched him out on the seafloor.</p>
      <p>This scene lasted barely a few seconds. The shark returned,
rolled over on its back, and was getting ready to cut the Indian in
half, when Captain Nemo, who was stationed beside me, suddenly
stood up. Then he strode right toward the monster, dagger in hand,
ready to fight it at close quarters.</p>
      <p>Just as it was about to snap up the poor fisherman, the
man–eater saw its new adversary, repositioned itself on its
belly, and headed swiftly toward him.</p>
      <p>I can see Captain Nemo's bearing to this day. Bracing himself,
he waited for the fearsome man–eater with wonderful
composure, and when the latter rushed at him, the captain leaped
aside with prodigious quickness, avoided a collision, and sank his
dagger into its belly. But that wasn't the end of the story. A
dreadful battle was joined.</p>
      <p>The shark bellowed, so to speak. Blood was pouring into the
waves from its wounds. The sea was dyed red, and through this
opaque liquid I could see nothing else.</p>
      <p>Nothing else until the moment when, through a rift in the
clouds, I saw the daring captain clinging to one of the animal's
fins, fighting the monster at close quarters, belaboring his
enemy's belly with stabs of the dagger yet unable to deliver the
deciding thrust, in other words, a direct hit to the heart. In its
struggles the man–eater churned the watery mass so furiously,
its eddies threatened to knock me over.</p>
      <p>I wanted to run to the captain's rescue. But I was transfixed
with horror, unable to move.</p>
      <p>I stared, wild–eyed. I saw the fight enter a new phase.
The captain fell to the seafloor, toppled by the enormous mass
weighing him down. Then the shark's jaws opened astoundingly wide,
like a pair of industrial shears, and that would have been the
finish of Captain Nemo had not Ned Land, quick as thought, rushed
forward with his harpoon and driven its dreadful point into the
shark's underside.</p>
      <p>The waves were saturated with masses of blood. The waters shook
with the movements of the man–eater, which thrashed about
with indescribable fury. Ned Land hadn't missed his target. This
was the monster's death rattle. Pierced to the heart, it was
struggling with dreadful spasms whose aftershocks knocked Conseil
off his feet.</p>
      <p>Meanwhile Ned Land pulled the captain clear. Uninjured, the
latter stood up, went right to the Indian, quickly cut the rope
binding the man to his stone, took the fellow in his arms, and with
a vigorous kick of the heel, rose to the surface of the sea.</p>
      <p>The three of us followed him, and a few moments later,
miraculously safe, we reached the fisherman's longboat.</p>
      <p>Captain Nemo's first concern was to revive this unfortunate man.
I wasn't sure he would succeed. I hoped so, since the poor devil
hadn't been under very long. But that stroke from the shark's tail
could have been his deathblow.</p>
      <p>Fortunately, after vigorous massaging by Conseil and the
captain, I saw the nearly drowned man regain consciousness little
by little. He opened his eyes. How startled he must have felt, how
frightened even, at seeing four huge, copper craniums leaning over
him!</p>
      <p>And above all, what must he have thought when Captain Nemo
pulled a bag of pearls from a pocket in his diving suit and placed
it in the fisherman's hands? This magnificent benefaction from the
Man of the Waters to the poor Indian from Ceylon was accepted by
the latter with trembling hands. His bewildered eyes indicated that
he didn't know to what superhuman creatures he owed both his life
and his fortune.</p>
      <p>At the captain's signal we returned to the bank of shellfish,
and retracing our steps, we walked for half an hour until we
encountered the anchor connecting the seafloor with the
<i>Nautilus's</i> skiff.</p>
      <p>Back on board, the sailors helped divest us of our heavy copper
carapaces.</p>
      <p>Captain Nemo's first words were spoken to the Canadian.</p>
      <p>"Thank you, Mr. Land," he told him.</p>
      <p>"Tit for tat, Captain," Ned Land replied. "I owed it to
you."</p>
      <p>The ghost of a smile glided across the captain's lips, and that
was all.</p>
      <p>"To the <i>Nautilus</i>," he said.</p>
      <p>The longboat flew over the waves. A few minutes later we
encountered the shark's corpse again, floating.</p>
      <p>From the black markings on the tips of its fins, I recognized
the dreadful <i>Squalus melanopterus</i> from the seas of the East
Indies, a variety in the species of sharks proper. It was more than
twenty–five feet long; its enormous mouth occupied a third of
its body. It was an adult, as could be seen from the six rows of
teeth forming an isosceles triangle in its upper jaw.</p>
      <p>Conseil looked at it with purely scientific fascination, and I'm
sure he placed it, not without good reason, in the class of
cartilaginous fish, order <i>Chondropterygia</i> with fixed gills,
family <i>Selacia</i>, genus <i>Squalus</i>.</p>
      <p>While I was contemplating this inert mass, suddenly a dozen of
these voracious <i>melanoptera</i> appeared around our longboat;
but, paying no attention to us, they pounced on the corpse and
quarreled over every scrap of it.</p>
      <p>By 8:30 we were back on board the <i>Nautilus</i>.</p>
      <p>There I fell to thinking about the incidents that marked our
excursion over the Mannar oysterbank. Two impressions inevitably
stood out. One concerned Captain Nemo's matchless bravery, the
other his devotion to a human being, a representative of that race
from which he had fled beneath the seas. In spite of everything,
this strange man hadn't yet succeeded in completely stifling his
heart.</p>
      <p>When I shared these impressions with him, he answered me in a
tone touched with emotion:</p>
      <p>"That Indian, professor, lives in the land of the oppressed, and
I am to this day, and will be until my last breath, a native of
that same land!"</p>
   </body>
</topic>