<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<topic id="d2e8593">
   <title>
      <d4pSimpleEnumerator><!--2.4-->Chapter 4. </d4pSimpleEnumerator>
      <ph>The Red Sea</ph>
   </title>
   <body>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="size_plus_2">DURING THE DAY</ph> of January 29, the island
of Ceylon disappeared below the horizon, and at a speed of twenty
miles per hour, the <i>Nautilus</i> glided into the labyrinthine
channels that separate the Maldive and Laccadive Islands. It
likewise hugged Kiltan Island, a shore of madreporic origin
discovered by Vasco da Gama in 1499 and one of nineteen chief
islands in the island group of the Laccadives, located between
latitude 10° and 14° 30' north, and between longitude
50° 72' and 69° east.</p>
      <p>By then we had fared 16,220 miles, or 7,500 leagues, from our
starting point in the seas of Japan.</p>
      <p>The next day, January 30, when the <i>Nautilus</i> rose to the
surface of the ocean, there was no more land in sight. Setting its
course to the north–northwest, the ship headed toward the
Gulf of Oman, carved out between Arabia and the Indian peninsula
and providing access to the Persian Gulf.</p>
      <p>This was obviously a blind alley with no possible outlet. So
where was Captain Nemo taking us? I was unable to say. Which didn't
satisfy the Canadian, who that day asked me where we were
going.</p>
      <p>"We're going, Mr. Ned, where the Captain's fancy takes us."</p>
      <p>"His fancy," the Canadian replied, "won't take us very far. The
Persian Gulf has no outlet, and if we enter those waters, it won't
be long before we return in our tracks."</p>
      <p>"All right, we'll return, Mr. Land, and after the Persian Gulf,
if the <i>Nautilus</i> wants to visit the Red Sea, the Strait of
Bab el Mandeb is still there to let us in!"</p>
      <p>"I don't have to tell you, sir," Ned Land replied, "that the Red
Sea is just as landlocked as the gulf, since the Isthmus of Suez
hasn't been cut all the way through yet; and even if it was, a boat
as secretive as ours wouldn't risk a canal intersected with locks.
So the Red Sea won't be our way back to Europe either."</p>
      <p>"But I didn't say we'd return to Europe."</p>
      <p>"What do you figure, then?"</p>
      <p>"I figure that after visiting these unusual waterways of Arabia
and Egypt, the <i>Nautilus</i> will go back down to the Indian
Ocean, perhaps through Mozambique Channel, perhaps off the
Mascarene Islands, and then make for the Cape of Good Hope."</p>
      <p>"And once we're at the Cape of Good Hope?" the Canadian asked
with typical persistence.</p>
      <p>"Well then, we'll enter that Atlantic Ocean with which we aren't
yet familiar. What's wrong, Ned my friend? Are you tired of this
voyage under the seas? Are you bored with the constantly changing
sight of these underwater wonders? Speaking for myself, I'll be
extremely distressed to see the end of a voyage so few men will
ever have a chance to make."</p>
      <p>"But don't you realize, Professor Aronnax," the Canadian
replied, "that soon we'll have been imprisoned for three whole
months aboard this <i>Nautilus</i>?"</p>
      <p>"No, Ned, I didn't realize it, I don't want to realize it, and I
don't keep track of every day and every hour."</p>
      <p>"But when will it be over?"</p>
      <p>"In its appointed time. Meanwhile there's nothing we can do
about it, and our discussions are futile. My gallant Ned, if you
come and tell me, 'A chance to escape is available to us,' then
I'll discuss it with you. But that isn't the case, and in all
honesty, I don't think Captain Nemo ever ventures into European
seas."</p>
      <p>This short dialogue reveals that in my mania for the
<i>Nautilus</i>, I was turning into the spitting image of its
commander.</p>
      <p>As for Ned Land, he ended our talk in his best speechifying
style: "That's all fine and dandy. But in my humble opinion, a life
in jail is a life without joy."</p>
      <p>For four days until February 3, the <i>Nautilus</i> inspected
the Gulf of Oman at various speeds and depths. It seemed to be
traveling at random, as if hesitating over which course to follow,
but it never crossed the Tropic of Cancer.</p>
      <p>After leaving this gulf we raised Muscat for an instant, the
most important town in the country of Oman. I marveled at its
strange appearance in the midst of the black rocks surrounding it,
against which the white of its houses and forts stood out sharply.
I spotted the rounded domes of its mosques, the elegant tips of its
minarets, and its fresh, leafy terraces. But it was only a fleeting
vision, and the <i>Nautilus</i> soon sank beneath the dark waves of
these waterways.</p>
      <p>Then our ship went along at a distance of six miles from the
Arabic coasts of Mahra and Hadhramaut, their undulating lines of
mountains relieved by a few ancient ruins. On February 5 we finally
put into the Gulf of Aden, a genuine funnel stuck into the neck of
Bab el Mandeb and bottling these Indian waters in the Red Sea.</p>
      <p>On February 6 the <i>Nautilus</i> cruised in sight of the city
of Aden, perched on a promontory connected to the continent by a
narrow isthmus, a sort of inaccessible Gibraltar whose
fortifications the English rebuilt after capturing it in 1839. I
glimpsed the octagonal minarets of this town, which used to be one
of the wealthiest, busiest commercial centers along this coast, as
the Arab historian Idrisi tells it.</p>
      <p>I was convinced that when Captain Nemo reached this point, he
would back out again; but I was mistaken, and much to my surprise,
he did nothing of the sort.</p>
      <p>The next day, February 7, we entered the Strait of Bab el
Mandeb, whose name means "Gate of Tears" in the Arabic language.
Twenty miles wide, it's only fifty–two kilometers long, and
with the <i>Nautilus</i> launched at full speed, clearing it was
the work of barely an hour. But I didn't see a thing, not even
Perim Island where the British government built fortifications to
strengthen Aden's position. There were many English and French
steamers plowing this narrow passageway, liners going from Suez to
Bombay, Calcutta, Melbourne, Réunion Island, and Mauritius;
far too much traffic for the <i>Nautilus</i> to make an appearance
on the surface. So it wisely stayed in midwater.</p>
      <p>Finally, at noon, we were plowing the waves of the Red Sea.</p>
      <p>The Red Sea: that great lake so famous in biblical traditions,
seldom replenished by rains, fed by no important rivers,
continually drained by a high rate of evaporation, its water level
dropping a meter and a half every year! If it were fully landlocked
like a lake, this odd gulf might dry up completely; on this score
it's inferior to its neighbors, the Caspian Sea and the Dead Sea,
whose levels lower only to the point where their evaporation
exactly equals the amounts of water they take to their hearts.</p>
      <p>This Red Sea is 2,600 kilometers long with an average width of
240. In the days of the Ptolemies and the Roman emperors, it was a
great commercial artery for the world, and when its isthmus has
been cut through, it will completely regain that bygone importance
that the Suez railways have already brought back in part.</p>
      <p>I would not even attempt to understand the whim that induced
Captain Nemo to take us into this gulf. But I wholeheartedly
approved of the <i>Nautilus's</i> entering it. It adopted a medium
pace, sometimes staying on the surface, sometimes diving to avoid
some ship, and so I could observe both the inside and topside of
this highly unusual sea.</p>
      <p>On February 8, as early as the first hours of daylight, Mocha
appeared before us: a town now in ruins, whose walls would collapse
at the mere sound of a cannon, and which shelters a few leafy date
trees here and there. This once–important city used to
contain six public marketplaces plus twenty–six mosques, and
its walls, protected by fourteen forts, fashioned a
three–kilometer girdle around it.</p>
      <p>Then the <i>Nautilus</i> drew near the beaches of Africa, where
the sea is considerably deeper. There, through the open panels and
in a midwater of crystal clarity, our ship enabled us to study
wonderful bushes of shining coral and huge chunks of rock wrapped
in splendid green furs of algae and fucus. What an indescribable
sight, and what a variety of settings and scenery where these reefs
and volcanic islands leveled off by the Libyan coast! But soon the
<i>Nautilus</i> hugged the eastern shore where these tree forms
appeared in all their glory. This was off the coast of Tihama, and
there such zoophyte displays not only flourished below sea level
but they also fashioned picturesque networks that unreeled as high
as ten fathoms above it; the latter were more whimsical but less
colorful than the former, which kept their bloom thanks to the
moist vitality of the waters.</p>
      <p>How many delightful hours I spent in this way at the lounge
window! How many new specimens of underwater flora and fauna I
marveled at beneath the light of our electric beacon!
Mushroom–shaped fungus coral, some slate–colored sea
anemone including the species Thalassianthus aster among others,
organ–pipe coral arranged like flutes and just begging for a
puff from the god Pan, shells unique to this sea that dwell in
madreporic cavities and whose bases are twisted into squat spirals,
and finally a thousand samples of a polypary I hadn't observed
until then: the common sponge.</p>
      <p>First division in the polyp group, the class <i>Spongiaria</i>
has been created by scientists precisely for this unusual exhibit
whose usefulness is beyond dispute. The sponge is definitely not a
plant, as some naturalists still believe, but an animal of the
lowest order, a polypary inferior even to coral. Its animal nature
isn't in doubt, and we can't accept even the views of the ancients,
who regarded it as halfway between plant and animal. But I must say
that naturalists are not in agreement on the structural mode of
sponges. For some it's a polypary, and for others, such as
Professor Milne–Edwards, it's a single, solitary
individual.</p>
      <p>The class Spongiaria contains about 300 species that are
encountered in a large number of seas and even in certain streams,
where they've been given the name freshwater sponges. But their
waters of choice are the Red Sea and the Mediterranean near the
Greek Islands or the coast of Syria. These waters witness the
reproduction and growth of soft, delicate bath sponges whose prices
run as high as ₣150 apiece: the yellow sponge from Syria, the
horn sponge from Barbary, etc. But since I had no hope of studying
these zoophytes in the seaports of the Levant, from which we were
separated by the insuperable Isthmus of Suez, I had to be content
with observing them in the waters of the Red Sea.</p>
      <p>So I called Conseil to my side, while at an average depth of
eight to nine meters, the <i>Nautilus</i> slowly skimmed every
beautiful rock on the easterly coast.</p>
      <p>There sponges grew in every shape, globular, stalklike,
leaflike, fingerlike. With reasonable accuracy, they lived up to
their nicknames of basket sponges, chalice sponges, distaff
sponges, elkhorn sponges, lion's paws, peacock's tails, and
Neptune's gloves—designations bestowed on them by fishermen,
more poetically inclined than scientists. A gelatinous, semifluid
substance coated the fibrous tissue of these sponges, and from this
tissue there escaped a steady trickle of water that, after carrying
sustenance to each cell, was being expelled by a contracting
movement. This jellylike substance disappears when the polyp dies,
emitting ammonia as it rots. Finally nothing remains but the
fibers, either gelatinous or made of horn, that constitute your
household sponge, which takes on a russet hue and is used for
various tasks depending on its degree of elasticity, permeability,
or resistance to saturation.</p>
      <p>These polyparies were sticking to rocks, shells of mollusks, and
even the stalks of water plants. They adorned the smallest
crevices, some sprawling, others standing or hanging like coral
outgrowths. I told Conseil that sponges are fished up in two ways,
either by dragnet or by hand. The latter method calls for the
services of a diver, but it's preferable because it spares the
polypary's tissue, leaving it with a much higher market value.</p>
      <p>Other zoophytes swarming near the sponges consisted chiefly of a
very elegant species of jellyfish; mollusks were represented by
varieties of squid that, according to Professor Orbigny, are unique
to the Red Sea; and reptiles by virgata turtles belonging to the
genus <i>Chelonia</i>, which furnished our table with a dainty but
wholesome dish.</p>
      <p>As for fish, they were numerous and often remarkable. Here are
the ones that the <i>Nautilus's</i> nets most frequently hauled on
board: rays, including spotted rays that were oval in shape and
brick red in color, their bodies strewn with erratic blue speckles
and identifiable by their jagged double stings, silver–backed
skates, common stingrays with stippled tails, butterfly rays that
looked like huge two–meter cloaks flapping at middepth,
toothless guitarfish that were a type of cartilaginous fish closer
to the shark, trunkfish known as dromedaries that were one and a
half feet long and had humps ending in backward–curving
stings, serpentine moray eels with silver tails and bluish backs
plus brown pectorals trimmed in gray piping, a species of
butterfish called the fiatola decked out in thin gold stripes and
the three colors of the French flag, Montague blennies four
decimeters long, superb jacks handsomely embellished by seven black
crosswise streaks with blue and yellow fins plus gold and silver
scales, snooks, standard mullet with yellow heads, parrotfish,
wrasse, triggerfish, gobies, etc., plus a thousand other fish
common to the oceans we had already crossed.</p>
      <p>On February 9 the <i>Nautilus</i> cruised in the widest part of
the Red Sea, measuring 190 miles straight across from Suakin on the
west coast to Qunfidha on the east coast.</p>
      <p>At noon that day after our position fix, Captain Nemo climbed
onto the platform, where I happened to be. I vowed not to let him
go below again without at least sounding him out on his future
plans. As soon as he saw me, he came over, graciously offered me a
cigar, and said to me:</p>
      <p>"Well, professor, are you pleased with this Red Sea? Have you
seen enough of its hidden wonders, its fish and zoophytes, its
gardens of sponges and forests of coral? Have you glimpsed the
towns built on its shores?"</p>
      <p>"Yes, Captain Nemo," I replied, "and the <i>Nautilus</i> is
wonderfully suited to this whole survey. Ah, it's a clever
boat!"</p>
      <p>"Yes, sir, clever, daring, and invulnerable! It fears neither
the Red Sea's dreadful storms nor its currents and reefs."</p>
      <p>"Indeed," I said, "this sea is mentioned as one of the worst,
and in the days of the ancients, if I'm not mistaken, it had an
abominable reputation."</p>
      <p>"Thoroughly abominable, Professor Aronnax. The Greek and Latin
historians can find nothing to say in its favor, and the Greek
geographer Strabo adds that it's especially rough during the rainy
season and the period of summer prevailing winds. The Arab Idrisi,
referring to it by the name Gulf of Colzoum, relates that ships
perished in large numbers on its sandbanks and that no one risked
navigating it by night. This, he claims, is a sea subject to
fearful hurricanes, strewn with inhospitable islands, and 'with
nothing good to offer,' either on its surface or in its depths. As
a matter of fact, the same views can also be found in Arrian,
Agatharchides, and Artemidorus."</p>
      <p>"One can easily see," I answered, "that those historians didn't
navigate aboard the <i>Nautilus</i>."</p>
      <p>"Indeed," the captain replied with a smile, "and in this
respect, the moderns aren't much farther along than the ancients.
It took many centuries to discover the mechanical power of steam!
Who knows whether we'll see a second <i>Nautilus</i> within the
next 100 years! Progress is slow, Professor Aronnax."</p>
      <p>"It's true," I replied. "Your ship is a century ahead of its
time, perhaps several centuries. It would be most unfortunate if
such a secret were to die with its inventor!"</p>
      <p>Captain Nemo did not reply. After some minutes of silence:</p>
      <p>"We were discussing," he said, "the views of ancient historians
on the dangers of navigating this Red Sea?"</p>
      <p>"True," I replied. "But weren't their fears exaggerated?"</p>
      <p>"Yes and no, Professor Aronnax," answered Captain Nemo, who
seemed to know "his Red Sea" by heart. "To a modern ship, well
rigged, solidly constructed, and in control of its course thanks to
obedient steam, some conditions are no longer hazardous that
offered all sorts of dangers to the vessels of the ancients.
Picture those early navigators venturing forth in sailboats built
from planks lashed together with palm–tree ropes, caulked
with powdered resin, and coated with dogfish grease. They didn't
even have instruments for taking their bearings, they went by
guesswork in the midst of currents they barely knew. Under such
conditions, shipwrecks had to be numerous. But nowadays steamers
providing service between Suez and the South Seas have nothing to
fear from the fury of this gulf, despite the contrary winds of its
monsoons. Their captains and passengers no longer prepare for
departure with sacrifices to placate the gods, and after returning,
they don't traipse in wreaths and gold ribbons to say thanks at the
local temple."</p>
      <p>"Agreed," I said. "And steam seems to have killed off all
gratitude in seamen's hearts. But since you seem to have made a
special study of this sea, Captain, can you tell me how it got its
name?"</p>
      <p>"Many explanations exist on the subject, Professor Aronnax.
Would you like to hear the views of one chronicler in the 14th
century?"</p>
      <p>"Gladly."</p>
      <p>"This fanciful fellow claims the sea was given its name after
the crossing of the Israelites, when the Pharaoh perished in those
waves that came together again at Moses' command:</p>
      <p>To mark that miraculous sequel, the sea turned a red without
equal.</p>
      <p>Thus no other course would do but to name it for its hue."</p>
      <p>"An artistic explanation, Captain Nemo," I replied, "but I'm
unable to rest content with it. So I'll ask you for your own
personal views."</p>
      <p>"Here they come. To my thinking, Professor Aronnax, this 'Red
Sea' designation must be regarded as a translation of the Hebrew
word <i>Edrom</i>, and if the ancients gave it that name, it was
because of the unique color of its waters."</p>
      <p>"Until now, however, I've seen only clear waves, without any
unique hue."</p>
      <p>"Surely, but as we move ahead to the far end of this gulf,
you'll note its odd appearance. I recall seeing the bay of El Tur
completely red, like a lake of blood."</p>
      <p>"And you attribute this color to the presence of microscopic
algae?"</p>
      <p>"Yes. It's a purplish, mucilaginous substance produced by those
tiny buds known by the name <i>trichodesmia</i>, 40,000 of which
are needed to occupy the space of one square millimeter. Perhaps
you'll encounter them when we reach El Tur."</p>
      <p>"Hence, Captain Nemo, this isn't the first time you've gone
through the Red Sea aboard the <i>Nautilus</i>?"</p>
      <p>"No, sir."</p>
      <p>"Then, since you've already mentioned the crossing of the
Israelites and the catastrophe that befell the Egyptians, I would
ask if you've ever discovered any traces under the waters of that
great historic event?"</p>
      <p>"No, professor, and for an excellent reason."</p>
      <p>"What's that?"</p>
      <p>"It's because that same locality where Moses crossed with all
his people is now so clogged with sand, camels can barely get their
legs wet. You can understand that my <i>Nautilus</i> wouldn't have
enough water for itself."</p>
      <p>"And that locality is . . . ?" I asked.</p>
      <p>"That locality lies a little above Suez in a sound that used to
form a deep estuary when the Red Sea stretched as far as the Bitter
Lakes. Now, whether or not their crossing was literally miraculous,
the Israelites did cross there in returning to the Promised Land,
and the Pharaoh's army did perish at precisely that locality. So I
think that excavating those sands would bring to light a great many
weapons and tools of Egyptian origin."</p>
      <p>"Obviously," I replied. "And for the sake of archaeology, let's
hope that sooner or later such excavations do take place, once new
towns are settled on the isthmus after the Suez Canal has been cut
through—a canal, by the way, of little use to a ship such as
the <i>Nautilus</i>!"</p>
      <p>"Surely, but of great use to the world at large," Captain Nemo
said. "The ancients well understood the usefulness to commerce of
connecting the Red Sea with the Mediterranean, but they never
dreamed of cutting a canal between the two, and instead they picked
the Nile as their link. If we can trust tradition, it was probably
Egypt's King Sesostris who started digging the canal needed to join
the Nile with the Red Sea. What's certain is that in 615 B.C. King
Necho II was hard at work on a canal that was fed by Nile water and
ran through the Egyptian plains opposite Arabia. This canal could
be traveled in four days, and it was so wide, two
triple–tiered galleys could pass through it abreast. Its
construction was continued by Darius the Great, son of Hystaspes,
and probably completed by King Ptolemy II. Strabo saw it used for
shipping; but the weakness of its slope between its starting point,
near Bubastis, and the Red Sea left it navigable only a few months
out of the year. This canal served commerce until the century of
Rome's Antonine emperors; it was then abandoned and covered with
sand, subsequently reinstated by Arabia's Caliph Omar I, and
finally filled in for good in 761 or 762 A.D. by Caliph
Al–Mansur, in an effort to prevent supplies from reaching
Mohammed ibn Abdullah, who had rebelled against him. During his
Egyptian campaign, your General Napoleon Bonaparte discovered
traces of this old canal in the Suez desert, and when the tide
caught him by surprise, he wellnigh perished just a few hours
before rejoining his regiment at Hadjaroth, the very place where
Moses had pitched camp 3,300 years before him."</p>
      <p>"Well, Captain, what the ancients hesitated to undertake, Mr. de
Lesseps is now finishing up; his joining of these two seas will
shorten the route from Cadiz to the East Indies by 9,000
kilometers, and he'll soon change Africa into an immense
island."</p>
      <p>"Yes, Professor Aronnax, and you have every right to be proud of
your fellow countryman. Such a man brings a nation more honor than
the greatest commanders! Like so many others, he began with
difficulties and setbacks, but he triumphed because he has the
volunteer spirit. And it's sad to think that this deed, which
should have been an international deed, which would have insured
that any administration went down in history, will succeed only
through the efforts of one man. So all hail to Mr. de Lesseps!"</p>
      <p>"Yes, all hail to that great French citizen," I replied, quite
startled by how emphatically Captain Nemo had just spoken.</p>
      <p>"Unfortunately," he went on, "I can't take you through that Suez
Canal, but the day after tomorrow, you'll be able to see the long
jetties of Port Said when we're in the Mediterranean."</p>
      <p>"In the Mediterranean!" I exclaimed.</p>
      <p>"Yes, professor. Does that amaze you?"</p>
      <p>"What amazes me is thinking we'll be there the day after
tomorrow."</p>
      <p>"Oh really?"</p>
      <p>"Yes, captain, although since I've been aboard your vessel, I
should have formed the habit of not being amazed by anything!"</p>
      <p>"But what is it that startles you?"</p>
      <p>"The thought of how hideously fast the <i>Nautilus</i> will need
to go, if it's to double the Cape of Good Hope, circle around
Africa, and lie in the open Mediterranean by the day after
tomorrow."</p>
      <p>"And who says it will circle Africa, professor? What's this talk
about doubling the Cape of Good Hope?"</p>
      <p>"But unless the <i>Nautilus</i> navigates on dry land and
crosses over the isthmus—"</p>
      <p>"Or under it, Professor Aronnax."</p>
      <p>"Under it?"</p>
      <p>"Surely," Captain Nemo replied serenely. "Under that tongue of
land, nature long ago made what man today is making on its
surface."</p>
      <p>"What! There's a passageway?"</p>
      <p>"Yes, an underground passageway that I've named the Arabian
Tunnel. It starts below Suez and leads to the Bay of Pelusium."</p>
      <p>"But isn't that isthmus only composed of quicksand?"</p>
      <p>"To a certain depth. But at merely fifty meters, one encounters
a firm foundation of rock."</p>
      <p>"And it's by luck that you discovered this passageway?" I asked,
more and more startled.</p>
      <p>"Luck plus logic, professor, and logic even more than luck."</p>
      <p>"Captain, I hear you, but I can't believe my ears."</p>
      <p>"Oh, sir! The old saying still holds good: <i>Aures habent et
non audient!</i>
         <fn callout="*">Latin: "They have ears
but hear not." Ed.</fn> Not only does this
passageway exist, but I've taken advantage of it on several
occasions. Without it, I wouldn't have ventured today into such a
blind alley as the Red Sea."</p>
      <p>"Is it indiscreet to ask how you discovered this tunnel?"</p>
      <p>"Sir," the captain answered me, "there can be no secrets between
men who will never leave each other."</p>
      <p>I ignored this innuendo and waited for Captain Nemo's
explanation.</p>
      <p>"Professor," he told me, "the simple logic of the naturalist led
me to discover this passageway, and I alone am familiar with it.
I'd noted that in the Red Sea and the Mediterranean there exist a
number of absolutely identical species of fish: eels, butterfish,
greenfish, bass, jewelfish, flying fish. Certain of this fact, I
wondered if there weren't a connection between the two seas. If
there were, its underground current had to go from the Red Sea to
the Mediterranean simply because of their difference in level. So I
caught a large number of fish in the vicinity of Suez. I slipped
copper rings around their tails and tossed them back into the sea.
A few months later off the coast of Syria, I recaptured a few
specimens of my fish, adorned with their telltale rings. So this
proved to me that some connection existed between the two seas. I
searched for it with my <i>Nautilus</i>, I discovered it, I
ventured into it; and soon, professor, you also will have cleared
my Arabic tunnel!"</p>
   </body>
</topic>