<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<topic id="d2e9034">
   <title>
      <d4pSimpleEnumerator><!--2.5-->Chapter 5. </d4pSimpleEnumerator>
      <ph>Arabian Tunnel</ph>
   </title>
   <body>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="size_plus_2">THE SAME DAY</ph>, I reported to Conseil and
Ned Land that part of the foregoing conversation directly
concerning them. When I told them we would be lying in
Mediterranean waters within two days, Conseil clapped his hands,
but the Canadian shrugged his shoulders.</p>
      <p>"An underwater tunnel!" he exclaimed. "A connection between two
seas! Who ever heard of such malarkey!"</p>
      <p>"Ned my friend," Conseil replied, "had you ever heard of the
<i>Nautilus</i>? No, yet here it is! So don't shrug your shoulders
so blithely, and don't discount something with the feeble excuse
that you've never heard of it."</p>
      <p>"We'll soon see!" Ned Land shot back, shaking his head. "After
all, I'd like nothing better than to believe in your captain's
little passageway, and may Heaven grant it really does take us to
the Mediterranean."</p>
      <p>The same evening, at latitude 21° 30' north, the
<i>Nautilus</i> was afloat on the surface of the sea and drawing
nearer to the Arab coast. I spotted Jidda, an important financial
center for Egypt, Syria, Turkey, and the East Indies. I could
distinguish with reasonable clarity the overall effect of its
buildings, the ships made fast along its wharves, and those bigger
vessels whose draft of water required them to drop anchor at the
port's offshore mooring. The sun, fairly low on the horizon, struck
full force on the houses in this town, accenting their whiteness.
Outside the city limits, some wood or reed huts indicated the
quarter where the bedouins lived.</p>
      <p>Soon Jidda faded into the shadows of evening, and the
<i>Nautilus</i> went back beneath the mildly phosphorescent
waters.</p>
      <p>The next day, February 10, several ships appeared, running on
our opposite tack. The <i>Nautilus</i> resumed its underwater
navigating; but at the moment of our noon sights, the sea was
deserted and the ship rose again to its waterline.</p>
      <p>With Ned and Conseil, I went to sit on the platform. The coast
to the east looked like a slightly blurred mass in a damp fog.</p>
      <p>Leaning against the sides of the skiff, we were chatting of one
thing and another, when Ned Land stretched his hand toward a point
in the water, saying to me:</p>
      <p>"See anything out there, professor?"</p>
      <p>"No, Ned," I replied, "but you know I don't have your eyes."</p>
      <p>"Take a good look," Ned went on. "There, ahead to starboard,
almost level with the beacon! Don't you see a mass that seems to be
moving around?"</p>
      <p>"Right," I said after observing carefully, "I can make out
something like a long, blackish object on the surface of the
water."</p>
      <p>"A second <i>Nautilus</i>?" Conseil said.</p>
      <p>"No," the Canadian replied, "unless I'm badly mistaken, that's
some marine animal."</p>
      <p>"Are there whales in the Red Sea?" Conseil asked.</p>
      <p>"Yes, my boy," I replied, "they're sometimes found here."</p>
      <p>"That's no whale," continued Ned Land, whose eyes never strayed
from the object they had sighted. "We're old chums, whales and I,
and I couldn't mistake their little ways."</p>
      <p>"Let's wait and see," Conseil said. "The <i>Nautilus</i> is
heading that direction, and we'll soon know what we're in for."</p>
      <p>In fact, that blackish object was soon only a mile away from us.
It looked like a huge reef stranded in midocean. What was it? I
still couldn't make up my mind.</p>
      <p>"Oh, it's moving off! It's diving!" Ned Land exclaimed.
"Damnation! What can that animal be? It doesn't have a forked tail
like baleen whales or sperm whales, and its fins look like
sawed–off limbs."</p>
      <p>"But in that case—" I put in.</p>
      <p>"Good lord," the Canadian went on, "it's rolled over on its
back, and it's raising its breasts in the air!"</p>
      <p>"It's a siren!" Conseil exclaimed. "With all due respect to
master, it's an actual mermaid!"</p>
      <p>That word "siren" put me back on track, and I realized that the
animal belonged to the order <i>Sirenia</i>: marine creatures that
legends have turned into mermaids, half woman, half fish.</p>
      <p>"No," I told Conseil, "that's no mermaid, it's an unusual
creature of which only a few specimens are left in the Red Sea.
That's a dugong."</p>
      <p>"Order <i>Sirenia</i>, group <i>Pisciforma</i>, subclass
<i>Monodelphia</i>, class <i>Mammalia</i>, branch
<i>Vertebrata</i>," Conseil replied.</p>
      <p>And when Conseil has spoken, there's nothing else to be
said.</p>
      <p>Meanwhile Ned Land kept staring. His eyes were gleaming with
desire at the sight of that animal. His hands were ready to hurl a
harpoon. You would have thought he was waiting for the right moment
to jump overboard and attack the creature in its own element.</p>
      <p>"Oh, sir," he told me in a voice trembling with excitement,
"I've never killed anything like that!"</p>
      <p>His whole being was concentrated in this last word.</p>
      <p>Just then Captain Nemo appeared on the platform. He spotted the
dugong. He understood the Canadian's frame of mind and addressed
him directly:</p>
      <p>"If you held a harpoon, Mr. Land, wouldn't your hands be itching
to put it to work?"</p>
      <p>"Positively, sir."</p>
      <p>"And just for one day, would it displease you to return to your
fisherman's trade and add this <i>cetacean</i> to the list of those
you've already hunted down?"</p>
      <p>"It wouldn't displease me one bit."</p>
      <p>"All right, you can try your luck!"</p>
      <p>"Thank you, sir," Ned Land replied, his eyes ablaze.</p>
      <p>"Only," the captain went on, "I urge you to aim carefully at
this animal, in your own personal interest."</p>
      <p>"Is the dugong dangerous to attack?" I asked, despite the
Canadian's shrug of the shoulders.</p>
      <p>"Yes, sometimes," the captain replied. "These animals have been
known to turn on their assailants and capsize their longboats. But
with Mr. Land that danger isn't to be feared. His eye is sharp, his
arm is sure. If I recommend that he aim carefully at this dugong,
it's because the animal is justly regarded as fine game, and I know
Mr. Land doesn't despise a choice morsel."</p>
      <p>"Aha!" the Canadian put in. "This beast offers the added luxury
of being good to eat?"</p>
      <p>"Yes, Mr. Land. Its flesh is actual red meat, highly prized, and
set aside throughout Malaysia for the tables of aristocrats.
Accordingly, this excellent animal has been hunted so
bloodthirstily that, like its manatee relatives, it has become more
and more scarce."</p>
      <p>"In that case, Captain," Conseil said in all seriousness, "on
the offchance that this creature might be the last of its line,
wouldn't it be advisable to spare its life, in the interests of
science?"</p>
      <p>"Maybe," the Canadian answered, "it would be better to hunt it
down, in the interests of mealtime."</p>
      <p>"Then proceed, Mr. Land," Captain Nemo replied.</p>
      <p>Just then, as mute and emotionless as ever, seven crewmen
climbed onto the platform. One carried a harpoon and line similar
to those used in whale fishing. Its deck paneling opened, the skiff
was wrenched from its socket and launched to sea. Six rowers sat on
the thwarts, and the coxswain took the tiller. Ned, Conseil, and I
found seats in the stern.</p>
      <p>"Aren't you coming, Captain?" I asked.</p>
      <p>"No, sir, but I wish you happy hunting."</p>
      <p>The skiff pulled clear, and carried off by its six oars, it
headed swiftly toward the dugong, which by then was floating two
miles from the <i>Nautilus</i>.</p>
      <p>Arriving within a few cable lengths of the <i>cetacean</i>, our
longboat slowed down, and the sculls dipped noiselessly into the
tranquil waters. Harpoon in hand, Ned Land went to take his stand
in the skiff's bow. Harpoons used for hunting whales are usually
attached to a very long rope that pays out quickly when the wounded
animal drags it with him. But this rope measured no more than about
ten fathoms, and its end had simply been fastened to a small barrel
that, while floating, would indicate the dugong's movements beneath
the waters.</p>
      <p>I stood up and could clearly observe the Canadian's adversary.
This dugong—which also boasts the name halicore—closely
resembled a manatee. Its oblong body ended in a very long caudal
fin and its lateral fins in actual fingers. It differs from the
manatee in that its upper jaw is armed with two long, pointed teeth
that form diverging tusks on either side.</p>
      <p>This dugong that Ned Land was preparing to attack was of
colossal dimensions, easily exceeding seven meters in length. It
didn't stir and seemed to be sleeping on the surface of the waves,
a circumstance that should have made it easier to capture.</p>
      <p>The skiff approached cautiously to within three fathoms of the
animal. The oars hung suspended above their rowlocks. I was
crouching. His body leaning slightly back, Ned Land brandished his
harpoon with expert hands.</p>
      <p>Suddenly a hissing sound was audible, and the dugong
disappeared. Although the harpoon had been forcefully hurled, it
apparently had hit only water.</p>
      <p>"Damnation!" exclaimed the furious Canadian. "I missed it!"</p>
      <p>"No," I said, "the animal's wounded, there's its blood; but your
weapon didn't stick in its body."</p>
      <p>"My harpoon! Get my harpoon!" Ned Land exclaimed.</p>
      <p>The sailors went back to their sculling, and the coxswain
steered the longboat toward the floating barrel. We fished up the
harpoon, and the skiff started off in pursuit of the animal.</p>
      <p>The latter returned from time to time to breathe at the surface
of the sea. Its wound hadn't weakened it because it went with
tremendous speed. Driven by energetic arms, the longboat flew on
its trail. Several times we got within a few fathoms of it, and the
Canadian hovered in readiness to strike; but then the dugong would
steal away with a sudden dive, and it proved impossible to overtake
the beast.</p>
      <p>I'll let you assess the degree of anger consuming our impatient
Ned Land. He hurled at the hapless animal the most potent
swearwords in the English language. For my part, I was simply
distressed to see this dugong outwit our every scheme.</p>
      <p>We chased it unflaggingly for a full hour, and I'd begun to
think it would prove too difficult to capture, when the animal got
the untimely idea of taking revenge on us, a notion it would soon
have cause to regret. It wheeled on the skiff, to assault us in its
turn.</p>
      <p>This maneuver did not escape the Canadian.</p>
      <p>"Watch out!" he said.</p>
      <p>The coxswain pronounced a few words in his bizarre language, and
no doubt he alerted his men to keep on their guard.</p>
      <p>Arriving within twenty feet of the skiff, the dugong stopped,
sharply sniffing the air with its huge nostrils, pierced not at the
tip of its muzzle but on its topside. Then it gathered itself and
sprang at us.</p>
      <p>The skiff couldn't avoid the collision. Half overturned, it
shipped a ton or two of water that we had to bail out. But thanks
to our skillful coxswain, we were fouled on the bias rather than
broadside, so we didn't capsize. Clinging to the stempost, Ned Land
thrust his harpoon again and again into the gigantic animal, which
imbedded its teeth in our gunwale and lifted the longboat out of
the water as a lion would lift a deer. We were thrown on top of
each other, and I have no idea how the venture would have ended had
not the Canadian, still thirsting for the beast's blood, finally
pierced it to the heart.</p>
      <p>I heard its teeth grind on sheet iron, and the dugong
disappeared, taking our harpoon along with it. But the barrel soon
popped up on the surface, and a few moments later the animal's body
appeared and rolled over on its back. Our skiff rejoined it, took
it in tow, and headed to the <i>Nautilus</i>.</p>
      <p>It took pulleys of great strength to hoist this dugong onto the
platform. The beast weighed 5,000 kilograms. It was carved up in
sight of the Canadian, who remained to watch every detail of the
operation. At dinner the same day, my steward served me some slices
of this flesh, skillfully dressed by the ship's cook. I found it
excellent, even better than veal if not beef.</p>
      <p>The next morning, February 11, the <i>Nautilus's</i> pantry was
enriched by more dainty game. A covey of terns alighted on the
<i>Nautilus</i>. They were a species of <i>Sterna nilotica</i>
unique to Egypt: beak black, head gray and stippled, eyes
surrounded by white dots, back, wings, and tail grayish, belly and
throat white, feet red. Also caught were a couple dozen Nile duck,
superior–tasting wildfowl whose neck and crown of the head
are white speckled with black.</p>
      <p>By then the <i>Nautilus</i> had reduced speed. It moved ahead at
a saunter, so to speak. I observed that the Red Sea's water was
becoming less salty the closer we got to Suez.</p>
      <p>Near five o'clock in the afternoon, we sighted Cape Ras Mohammed
to the north. This cape forms the tip of Arabia Petraea, which lies
between the Gulf of Suez and the Gulf of Aqaba.</p>
      <p>The <i>Nautilus</i> entered the Strait of Jubal, which leads to
the Gulf of Suez. I could clearly make out a high mountain crowning
Ras Mohammed between the two gulfs. It was Mt. Horeb, that biblical
Mt. Sinai on whose summit Moses met God face to face, that summit
the mind's eye always pictures as wreathed in lightning.</p>
      <p>At six o'clock, sometimes afloat and sometimes submerged, the
<i>Nautilus</i> passed well out from El Tur, which sat at the far
end of a bay whose waters seemed to be dyed red, as Captain Nemo
had already mentioned. Then night fell in the midst of a heavy
silence occasionally broken by the calls of pelicans and nocturnal
birds, by the sound of surf chafing against rocks, or by the
distant moan of a steamer churning the waves of the gulf with noisy
blades.</p>
      <p>From eight to nine o'clock, the <i>Nautilus</i> stayed a few
meters beneath the waters. According to my calculations, we had to
be quite close to Suez. Through the panels in the lounge, I spotted
rocky bottoms brightly lit by our electric rays. It seemed to me
that the strait was getting narrower and narrower.</p>
      <p>At 9:15 when our boat returned to the surface, I climbed onto
the platform. I was quite impatient to clear Captain Nemo's tunnel,
couldn't sit still, and wanted to breathe the fresh night air.</p>
      <p>Soon, in the shadows, I spotted a pale signal light glimmering a
mile away, half discolored by mist.</p>
      <p>"A floating lighthouse," said someone next to me.</p>
      <p>I turned and discovered the captain.</p>
      <p>"That's the floating signal light of Suez," he went on. "It
won't be long before we reach the entrance to the tunnel."</p>
      <p>"It can't be very easy to enter it."</p>
      <p>"No, sir. Accordingly, I'm in the habit of staying in the
pilothouse and directing maneuvers myself. And now if you'll kindly
go below, Professor Aronnax, the <i>Nautilus</i> is about to sink
beneath the waves, and it will only return to the surface after
we've cleared the Arabian Tunnel."</p>
      <p>I followed Captain Nemo. The hatch closed, the ballast tanks
filled with water, and the submersible sank some ten meters
down.</p>
      <p>Just as I was about to repair to my stateroom, the captain
stopped me.</p>
      <p>"Professor," he said to me, "would you like to go with me to the
wheelhouse?"</p>
      <p>"I was afraid to ask," I replied.</p>
      <p>"Come along, then. This way, you'll learn the full story about
this combination underwater and underground navigating."</p>
      <p>Captain Nemo led me to the central companionway. In midstair he
opened a door, went along the upper gangways, and arrived at the
wheelhouse, which, as you know, stands at one end of the
platform.</p>
      <p>It was a cabin measuring six feet square and closely resembling
those occupied by the helmsmen of steamboats on the Mississippi or
Hudson rivers. In the center stood an upright wheel geared to
rudder cables running to the <i>Nautilus's</i> stern. Set in the
cabin's walls were four deadlights, windows of biconvex glass that
enabled the man at the helm to see in every direction.</p>
      <p>The cabin was dark; but my eyes soon grew accustomed to its
darkness and I saw the pilot, a muscular man whose hands rested on
the pegs of the wheel. Outside, the sea was brightly lit by the
beacon shining behind the cabin at the other end of the
platform.</p>
      <p>"Now," Captain Nemo said, "let's look for our passageway."</p>
      <p>Electric wires linked the pilothouse with the engine room, and
from this cabin the captain could simultaneously signal heading and
speed to his <i>Nautilus</i>. He pressed a metal button and at once
the propeller slowed down significantly.</p>
      <p>I stared in silence at the high, sheer wall we were skirting
just then, the firm base of the sandy mountains on the coast. For
an hour we went along it in this fashion, staying only a few meters
away. Captain Nemo never took his eyes off the two concentric
circles of the compass hanging in the cabin. At a mere gesture from
him, the helmsman would instantly change the <i>Nautilus's</i>
heading.</p>
      <p>Standing by the port deadlight, I spotted magnificent coral
substructures, zoophytes, algae, and crustaceans with enormous
quivering claws that stretched forth from crevices in the rock.</p>
      <p>At 10:15 Captain Nemo himself took the helm. Dark and deep, a
wide gallery opened ahead of us. The <i>Nautilus</i> was brazenly
swallowed up. Strange rumblings were audible along our sides. It
was the water of the Red Sea, hurled toward the Mediterranean by
the tunnel's slope. Our engines tried to offer resistance by
churning the waves with propeller in reverse, but the
<i>Nautilus</i> went with the torrent, as swift as an arrow.</p>
      <p>Along the narrow walls of this passageway, I saw only brilliant
streaks, hard lines, fiery furrows, all scrawled by our speeding
electric light. With my hand I tried to curb the pounding of my
heart.</p>
      <p>At 10:35 Captain Nemo left the steering wheel and turned to
me:</p>
      <p>"The Mediterranean," he told me.</p>
      <p>In less than twenty minutes, swept along by the torrent, the
<i>Nautilus</i> had just cleared the Isthmus of Suez.</p>
   </body>
</topic>