<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<topic id="d2e9961">
   <title>
      <d4pSimpleEnumerator><!--2.7-->Chapter 7. </d4pSimpleEnumerator>
      <ph>The Mediterranean in Forty–Eight Hours</ph>
   </title>
   <body>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="size_plus_2">THE MEDITERRANEAN</ph>, your ideal blue sea:
to Greeks simply "the sea," to Hebrews "the great sea," to Romans
<i>mare nostrum</i>.<fn callout="*">Latin: "our sea."
Ed.</fn> Bordered by
orange trees, aloes, cactus, and maritime pine trees, perfumed with
the scent of myrtle, framed by rugged mountains, saturated with
clean, transparent air but continuously under construction by fires
in the earth, this sea is a genuine battlefield where Neptune and
Pluto still struggle for world domination. Here on these beaches
and waters, says the French historian Michelet, a man is revived by
one of the most invigorating climates in the world.</p>
      <p>But as beautiful as it was, I could get only a quick look at
this basin whose surface area comprises 2,000,000 square
kilometers. Even Captain Nemo's personal insights were denied me,
because that mystifying individual didn't appear one single time
during our high–speed crossing. I estimate that the
<i>Nautilus</i> covered a track of some 600 leagues under the waves
of this sea, and this voyage was accomplished in just
twenty–four hours times two. Departing from the waterways of
Greece on the morning of February 16, we cleared the Strait of
Gibraltar by sunrise on the 18th.</p>
      <p>It was obvious to me that this Mediterranean, pinned in the
middle of those shores he wanted to avoid, gave Captain Nemo no
pleasure. Its waves and breezes brought back too many memories, if
not too many regrets. Here he no longer had the ease of movement
and freedom of maneuver that the oceans allowed him, and his
<i>Nautilus</i> felt cramped so close to the coasts of both Africa
and Europe.</p>
      <p>Accordingly, our speed was twenty–five miles (that is,
twelve four–kilometer leagues) per hour. Needless to say, Ned
Land had to give up his escape plans, much to his distress. Swept
along at the rate of twelve to thirteen meters per second, he could
hardly make use of the skiff. Leaving the <i>Nautilus</i> under
these conditions would have been like jumping off a train racing at
this speed, a rash move if there ever was one. Moreover, to renew
our air supply, the submersible rose to the surface of the waves
only at night, and relying solely on compass and log, it steered by
dead reckoning.</p>
      <p>Inside the Mediterranean, then, I could catch no more of its
fast–passing scenery than a traveler might see from an
express train; in other words, I could view only the distant
horizons because the foregrounds flashed by like lightning. But
Conseil and I were able to observe those Mediterranean fish whose
powerful fins kept pace for a while in the <i>Nautilus's</i>
waters. We stayed on watch before the lounge windows, and our notes
enable me to reconstruct, in a few words, the ichthyology of this
sea.</p>
      <p>Among the various fish inhabiting it, some I viewed, others I
glimpsed, and the rest I missed completely because of the
<i>Nautilus's</i> speed. Kindly allow me to sort them out using
this whimsical system of classification. It will at least convey
the quickness of my observations.</p>
      <p>In the midst of the watery mass, brightly lit by our electric
beams, there snaked past those one–meter lampreys that are
common to nearly every clime. A type of ray from the genus
<i>Oxyrhynchus</i>, five feet wide, had a white belly with a
spotted, ash–gray back and was carried along by the currents
like a huge, wide–open shawl. Other rays passed by so quickly
I couldn't tell if they deserved that name "eagle ray" coined by
the ancient Greeks, or those designations of "rat ray," "bat ray,"
and "toad ray" that modern fishermen have inflicted on them.
Dogfish known as topes, twelve feet long and especially feared by
divers, were racing with each other. Looking like big bluish
shadows, thresher sharks went by, eight feet long and gifted with
an extremely acute sense of smell. Dorados from the genus
<i>Sparus</i>, some measuring up to thirteen decimeters, appeared
in silver and azure costumes encircled with ribbons, which
contrasted with the dark color of their fins; fish sacred to the
goddess Venus, their eyes set in brows of gold; a valuable species
that patronizes all waters fresh or salt, equally at home in
rivers, lakes, and oceans, living in every clime, tolerating any
temperature, their line dating back to prehistoric times on this
earth yet preserving all its beauty from those far–off days.
Magnificent sturgeons, nine to ten meters long and extremely fast,
banged their powerful tails against the glass of our panels,
showing bluish backs with small brown spots; they resemble sharks,
without equaling their strength, and are encountered in every sea;
in the spring they delight in swimming up the great rivers,
fighting the currents of the Volga, Danube, Po, Rhine, Loire, and
Oder, while feeding on herring, mackerel, salmon, and codfish;
although they belong to the class of cartilaginous fish, they rate
as a delicacy; they're eaten fresh, dried, marinated, or
salt–preserved, and in olden times they were borne in triumph
to the table of the Roman epicure Lucullus.</p>
      <p>But whenever the <i>Nautilus</i> drew near the surface, those
denizens of the Mediterranean I could observe most productively
belonged to the sixty–third genus of bony fish. These were
tuna from the genus <i>Scomber</i>, blue–black on top, silver
on the belly armor, their dorsal stripes giving off a golden gleam.
They are said to follow ships in search of refreshing shade from
the hot tropical sun, and they did just that with the
<i>Nautilus</i>, as they had once done with the vessels of the
Count de La Pérouse. For long hours they competed in speed
with our submersible. I couldn't stop marveling at these animals so
perfectly cut out for racing, their heads small, their bodies
sleek, spindle–shaped, and in some cases over three meters
long, their pectoral fins gifted with remarkable strength, their
caudal fins forked. Like certain flocks of birds, whose speed they
equal, these tuna swim in triangle formation, which prompted the
ancients to say they'd boned up on geometry and military strategy.
And yet they can't escape the Provençal fishermen, who prize
them as highly as did the ancient inhabitants of Turkey and Italy;
and these valuable animals, as oblivious as if they were deaf and
blind, leap right into the Marseilles tuna nets and perish by the
thousands.</p>
      <p>Just for the record, I'll mention those Mediterranean fish that
Conseil and I barely glimpsed. There were whitish eels of the
species <i>Gymnotus fasciatus</i> that passed like elusive wisps of
steam, conger eels three to four meters long that were tricked out
in green, blue, and yellow, three–foot hake with a liver that
makes a dainty morsel, wormfish drifting like thin seaweed, sea
robins that poets call lyrefish and seamen pipers and whose snouts
have two jagged triangular plates shaped like old Homer's lyre,
swallowfish swimming as fast as the bird they're named after,
redheaded groupers whose dorsal fins are trimmed with filaments,
some shad (spotted with black, gray, brown, blue, yellow, and
green) that actually respond to tinkling handbells, splendid
diamond–shaped turbot that were like aquatic pheasants with
yellowish fins stippled in brown and the left topside mostly
marbled in brown and yellow, finally schools of wonderful red
mullet, real oceanic birds of paradise that ancient Romans bought
for as much as 10,000 sesterces apiece, and which they killed at
the table, so they could heartlessly watch it change color from
cinnabar red when alive to pallid white when dead.</p>
      <p>And as for other fish common to the Atlantic and Mediterranean,
I was unable to observe miralets, triggerfish, puffers, seahorses,
jewelfish, trumpetfish, blennies, gray mullet, wrasse, smelt,
flying fish, anchovies, sea bream, porgies, garfish, or any of the
chief representatives of the order Pleuronecta, such as sole,
flounder, plaice, dab, and brill, simply because of the dizzying
speed with which the <i>Nautilus</i> hustled through these opulent
waters.</p>
      <p>As for marine mammals, on passing by the mouth of the Adriatic
Sea, I thought I recognized two or three sperm whales equipped with
the single dorsal fin denoting the genus <i>Physeter</i>, some
pilot whales from the genus <i>Globicephalus</i> exclusive to the
Mediterranean, the forepart of the head striped with small distinct
lines, and also a dozen seals with white bellies and black coats,
known by the name monk seals and just as solemn as if they were
three–meter Dominicans.</p>
      <p>For his part, Conseil thought he spotted a turtle six feet wide
and adorned with three protruding ridges that ran lengthwise. I was
sorry to miss this reptile, because from Conseil's description, I
believe I recognized the leatherback turtle, a pretty rare species.
For my part, I noted only some loggerhead turtles with long
carapaces.</p>
      <p>As for zoophytes, for a few moments I was able to marvel at a
wonderful, orange–hued hydra from the genus <i>Galeolaria</i>
that clung to the glass of our port panel; it consisted of a long,
lean filament that spread out into countless branches and ended in
the most delicate lace ever spun by the followers of Arachne.
Unfortunately I couldn't fish up this wonderful specimen, and
surely no other Mediterranean zoophytes would have been offered to
my gaze, if, on the evening of the 16th, the <i>Nautilus</i> hadn't
slowed down in an odd fashion. This was the situation.</p>
      <p>By then we were passing between Sicily and the coast of Tunisia.
In the cramped space between Cape Bon and the Strait of Messina,
the sea bottom rises almost all at once. It forms an actual ridge
with only seventeen meters of water remaining above it, while the
depth on either side is 170 meters. Consequently, the
<i>Nautilus</i> had to maneuver with caution so as not to bump into
this underwater barrier.</p>
      <p>I showed Conseil the position of this long reef on our chart of
the Mediterranean.</p>
      <p>"But with all due respect to Master," Conseil ventured to
observe, "it's like an actual isthmus connecting Europe to
Africa."</p>
      <p>"Yes, my boy," I replied, "it cuts across the whole Strait of
Sicily, and Smith's soundings prove that in the past, these two
continents were genuinely connected between Cape Boeo and Cape
Farina."</p>
      <p>"I can easily believe it," Conseil said.</p>
      <p>"I might add," I went on, "that there's a similar barrier
between Gibraltar and Ceuta, and in prehistoric times it closed off
the Mediterranean completely."</p>
      <p>"Gracious!" Conseil put in. "Suppose one day some volcanic
upheaval raises these two barriers back above the waves!"</p>
      <p>"That's most unlikely, Conseil."</p>
      <p>"If Master will allow me to finish, I mean that if this
phenomenon occurs, it might prove distressing to Mr. de Lesseps,
who has gone to such pains to cut through his isthmus!"</p>
      <p>"Agreed, but I repeat, Conseil: such a phenomenon won't occur.
The intensity of these underground forces continues to diminish.
Volcanoes were quite numerous in the world's early days, but
they're going extinct one by one; the heat inside the earth is
growing weaker, the temperature in the globe's lower strata is
cooling appreciably every century, and to our globe's detriment,
because its heat is its life."</p>
      <p>"But the sun—"</p>
      <p>"The sun isn't enough, Conseil. Can it restore heat to a
corpse?"</p>
      <p>"Not that I've heard."</p>
      <p>"Well, my friend, someday the earth will be just such a cold
corpse. Like the moon, which long ago lost its vital heat, our
globe will become lifeless and unlivable."</p>
      <p>"In how many centuries?" Conseil asked.</p>
      <p>"In hundreds of thousands of years, my boy."</p>
      <p>"Then we have ample time to finish our voyage," Conseil replied,
"if Ned Land doesn't mess things up!"</p>
      <p>Thus reassured, Conseil went back to studying the shallows that
the <i>Nautilus</i> was skimming at moderate speed.</p>
      <p>On the rocky, volcanic seafloor, there bloomed quite a
collection of moving flora: sponges, sea cucumbers, jellyfish
called sea gooseberries that were adorned with reddish tendrils and
gave off a subtle phosphorescence, members of the genus Beroe that
are commonly known by the name melon jellyfish and are bathed in
the shimmer of the whole solar spectrum, free–swimming
crinoids one meter wide that reddened the waters with their crimson
hue, treelike basket stars of the greatest beauty, sea fans from
the genus Pavonacea with long stems, numerous edible sea urchins of
various species, plus green sea anemones with a grayish trunk and a
brown disk lost beneath the olive–colored tresses of their
tentacles.</p>
      <p>Conseil kept especially busy observing mollusks and articulates,
and although his catalog is a little dry, I wouldn't want to wrong
the gallant lad by leaving out his personal observations.</p>
      <p>From the branch <i>Mollusca</i>, he mentions numerous
comb–shaped scallops, hooflike spiny oysters piled on top of
each other, triangular coquina, three–pronged glass snails
with yellow fins and transparent shells, orange snails from the
genus <i>Pleurobranchus</i> that looked like eggs spotted or
speckled with greenish dots, members of the genus <i>Aplysia</i>
also known by the name sea hares, other sea hares from the genus
<i>Dolabella</i>, plump paper–bubble shells, umbrella shells
exclusive to the Mediterranean, abalone whose shell produces a
mother–of–pearl much in demand, pilgrim scallops,
saddle shells that diners in the French province of Languedoc are
said to like better than oysters, some of those cockleshells so
dear to the citizens of Marseilles, fat white venus shells that are
among the clams so abundant off the coasts of North America and
eaten in such quantities by New Yorkers, variously colored comb
shells with gill covers, burrowing date mussels with a peppery
flavor I relish, furrowed heart cockles whose shells have riblike
ridges on their arching summits, triton shells pocked with scarlet
bumps, carniaira snails with backward–curving tips that make
them resemble flimsy gondolas, crowned ferola snails, atlanta
snails with spiral shells, gray nudibranchs from the genus
<i>Tethys</i> that were spotted with white and covered by fringed
mantles, nudibranchs from the suborder <i>Eolidea</i> that looked
like small slugs, sea butterflies crawling on their backs,
seashells from the genus <i>Auricula</i> including the
oval–shaped <i>Auricula myosotis</i>, tan wentletrap snails,
common periwinkles, violet snails, cineraira snails, rock borers,
ear shells, cabochon snails, pandora shells, etc.</p>
      <p>As for the articulates, in his notes Conseil has very
appropriately divided them into six classes, three of which belong
to the marine world. These classes are the <i>Crustacea</i>,
<i>Cirripedia</i>, and <i>Annelida</i>.</p>
      <p>Crustaceans are subdivided into nine orders, and the first of
these consists of the decapods, in other words, animals whose head
and thorax are usually fused, whose cheek–and–mouth
mechanism is made up of several pairs of appendages, and whose
thorax has four, five, or six pairs of walking legs. Conseil used
the methods of our mentor Professor Milne–Edwards, who puts
the decapods in three divisions: <i>Brachyura</i>, <i>Macrura</i>,
and <i>Anomura</i>. These names may look a tad fierce, but they're
accurate and appropriate. Among the <i>Brachyura</i>, Conseil
mentions some amanthia crabs whose fronts were armed with two big
diverging tips, those inachus scorpions that—lord knows
why—symbolized wisdom to the ancient Greeks, spider crabs of
the <i>massena</i> and <i>spinimane</i> varieties that had probably
gone astray in these shallows because they usually live in the
lower depths, xanthid crabs, pilumna crabs, rhomboid crabs,
granular box crabs (easy on the digestion, as Conseil ventured to
observe), toothless masked crabs, ebalia crabs, cymopolia crabs,
woolly–handed crabs, etc. Among the <i>Macrura</i> (which are
subdivided into five families: hardshells, burrowers, crayfish,
prawns, and ghost crabs) Conseil mentions some common spiny
lobsters whose females supply a meat highly prized, slipper
lobsters or common shrimp, waterside gebia shrimp, and all sorts of
edible species, but he says nothing of the crayfish subdivision
that includes the true lobster, because spiny lobsters are the only
type in the Mediterranean. Finally, among the <i>Anomura</i>, he
saw common drocina crabs dwelling inside whatever abandoned
seashells they could take over, homola crabs with spiny fronts,
hermit crabs, hairy porcelain crabs, etc.</p>
      <p>There Conseil's work came to a halt. He didn't have time to
finish off the class <i>Crustacea</i> through an examination of its
<i>stomatopods</i>, <i>amphipods</i>, <i>homopods</i>,
<i>isopods</i>, <i>trilobites</i>, <i>branchiopods</i>,
<i>ostracods</i>, and <i>entomostraceans</i>. And in order to
complete his study of marine articulates, he needed to mention the
class <i>Cirripedia</i>, which contains water fleas and carp lice,
plus the class <i>Annelida</i>, which he would have divided without
fail into <i>tubifex</i> worms and <i>dorsibranchian</i> worms. But
having gone past the shallows of the Strait of Sicily, the
<i>Nautilus</i> resumed its usual deep–water speed. From then
on, no more mollusks, no more zoophytes, no more articulates. Just
a few large fish sweeping by like shadows.</p>
      <p>During the night of February 16–17, we entered the second
Mediterranean basin, whose maximum depth we found at 3,000 meters.
The <i>Nautilus</i>, driven downward by its propeller and slanting
fins, descended to the lowest strata of this sea.</p>
      <p>There, in place of natural wonders, the watery mass offered some
thrilling and dreadful scenes to my eyes. In essence, we were then
crossing that part of the whole Mediterranean so fertile in
casualties. From the coast of Algiers to the beaches of Provence,
how many ships have wrecked, how many vessels have vanished!
Compared to the vast liquid plains of the Pacific, the
Mediterranean is a mere lake, but it's an unpredictable lake with
fickle waves, today kindly and affectionate to those frail
single–masters drifting between a double ultramarine of sky
and water, tomorrow bad–tempered and turbulent, agitated by
the winds, demolishing the strongest ships beneath sudden waves
that smash down with a headlong wallop.</p>
      <p>So, in our swift cruise through these deep strata, how many
vessels I saw lying on the seafloor, some already caked with coral,
others clad only in a layer of rust, plus anchors, cannons, shells,
iron fittings, propeller blades, parts of engines, cracked
cylinders, staved–in boilers, then hulls floating in
midwater, here upright, there overturned.</p>
      <p>Some of these wrecked ships had perished in collisions, others
from hitting granite reefs. I saw a few that had sunk straight
down, their masting still upright, their rigging stiffened by the
water. They looked like they were at anchor by some immense, open,
offshore mooring where they were waiting for their departure time.
When the <i>Nautilus</i> passed between them, covering them with
sheets of electricity, they seemed ready to salute us with their
colors and send us their serial numbers! But no, nothing but
silence and death filled this field of catastrophes!</p>
      <p>I observed that these Mediterranean depths became more and more
cluttered with such gruesome wreckage as the <i>Nautilus</i> drew
nearer to the Strait of Gibraltar. By then the shores of Africa and
Europe were converging, and in this narrow space collisions were
commonplace. There I saw numerous iron undersides, the
phantasmagoric ruins of steamers, some lying down, others rearing
up like fearsome animals. One of these boats made a dreadful first
impression: sides torn open, funnel bent, paddle wheels stripped to
the mountings, rudder separated from the sternpost and still
hanging from an iron chain, the board on its stern eaten away by
marine salts! How many lives were dashed in this shipwreck! How
many victims were swept under the waves! Had some sailor on board
lived to tell the story of this dreadful disaster, or do the waves
still keep this casualty a secret? It occurred to me, lord knows
why, that this boat buried under the sea might have been the
<i>Atlas</i>, lost with all hands some twenty years ago and never
heard from again! Oh, what a gruesome tale these Mediterranean
depths could tell, this huge boneyard where so much wealth has been
lost, where so many victims have met their deaths!</p>
      <p>Meanwhile, briskly unconcerned, the <i>Nautilus</i> ran at full
propeller through the midst of these ruins. On February 18, near
three o'clock in the morning, it hove before the entrance to the
Strait of Gibraltar.</p>
      <p>There are two currents here: an upper current, long known to
exist, that carries the ocean's waters into the Mediterranean
basin; then a lower countercurrent, the only present–day
proof of its existence being logic. In essence, the Mediterranean
receives a continual influx of water not only from the Atlantic but
from rivers emptying into it; since local evaporation isn't enough
to restore the balance, the total amount of added water should make
this sea's level higher every year. Yet this isn't the case, and
we're naturally forced to believe in the existence of some lower
current that carries the Mediterranean's surplus through the Strait
of Gibraltar and into the Atlantic basin.</p>
      <p>And so it turned out. The <i>Nautilus</i> took full advantage of
this countercurrent. It advanced swiftly through this narrow
passageway. For an instant I could glimpse the wonderful ruins of
the Temple of Hercules, buried undersea, as Pliny and Avianus have
mentioned, together with the flat island they stand on; and a few
minutes later, we were floating on the waves of the Atlantic.</p>
   </body>
</topic>