<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<topic id="d2e906">
   <title>
      <d4pSimpleEnumerator><!--1.3-->Chapter 3. </d4pSimpleEnumerator>
      <ph>As Master Wishes</ph>
   </title>
   <body>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="size_plus_2">THREE SECONDS</ph> before the arrival of J. B.
Hobson's letter, I no more dreamed of chasing the unicorn than of
trying for the Northwest Passage. Three seconds after reading this
letter from the honorable Secretary of the Navy, I understood at
last that my true vocation, my sole purpose in life, was to hunt
down this disturbing monster and rid the world of it.</p>
      <p>Even so, I had just returned from an arduous journey, exhausted
and badly needing a rest. I wanted nothing more than to see my
country again, my friends, my modest quarters by the Botanical
Gardens, my dearly beloved collections! But now nothing could hold
me back. I forgot everything else, and without another thought of
exhaustion, friends, or collections, I accepted the American
government's offer.</p>
      <p>"Besides," I mused, "all roads lead home to Europe, and our
unicorn may be gracious enough to take me toward the coast of
France! That fine animal may even let itself be captured in
European seas—as a personal favor to me—and I'll bring
back to the Museum of Natural History at least half a meter of its
ivory lance!"</p>
      <p>But in the meantime I would have to look for this narwhale in
the northern Pacific Ocean; which meant returning to France by way
of the Antipodes.</p>
      <p>"Conseil!" I called in an impatient voice.</p>
      <p>Conseil was my manservant. A devoted lad who went with me on all
my journeys; a gallant Flemish boy whom I genuinely liked and who
returned the compliment; a born stoic, punctilious on principle,
habitually hardworking, rarely startled by life's surprises, very
skillful with his hands, efficient in his every duty, and despite
his having a name that means "counsel," never giving
advice—not even the unsolicited kind!</p>
      <p>From rubbing shoulders with scientists in our little universe by
the Botanical Gardens, the boy had come to know a thing or two. In
Conseil I had a seasoned specialist in biological classification,
an enthusiast who could run with acrobatic agility up and down the
whole ladder of branches, groups, classes, subclasses, orders,
families, genera, subgenera, species, and varieties. But there his
science came to a halt. Classifying was everything to him, so he
knew nothing else. Well versed in the theory of classification, he
was poorly versed in its practical application, and I doubt that he
could tell a sperm whale from a baleen whale! And yet, what a fine,
gallant lad!</p>
      <p>For the past ten years, Conseil had gone with me wherever
science beckoned. Not once did he comment on the length or the
hardships of a journey. Never did he object to buckling up his
suitcase for any country whatever, China or the Congo, no matter
how far off it was. He went here, there, and everywhere in perfect
contentment. Moreover, he enjoyed excellent health that defied all
ailments, owned solid muscles, but hadn't a nerve in him, not a
sign of nerves—the mental type, I mean.</p>
      <p>The lad was thirty years old, and his age to that of his
employer was as fifteen is to twenty. Please forgive me for this
underhanded way of admitting I had turned forty.</p>
      <p>But Conseil had one flaw. He was a fanatic on formality, and he
only addressed me in the third person—to the point where it
got tiresome.</p>
      <p>"Conseil!" I repeated, while feverishly beginning my
preparations for departure.</p>
      <p>To be sure, I had confidence in this devoted lad. Ordinarily, I
never asked whether or not it suited him to go with me on my
journeys; but this time an expedition was at issue that could drag
on indefinitely, a hazardous undertaking whose purpose was to hunt
an animal that could sink a frigate as easily as a walnut shell!
There was good reason to stop and think, even for the world's most
emotionless man. What would Conseil say?</p>
      <p>"Conseil!" I called a third time.</p>
      <p>Conseil appeared.</p>
      <p>"Did master summon me?" he said, entering.</p>
      <p>"Yes, my boy. Get my things ready, get yours ready. We're
departing in two hours."</p>
      <p>"As master wishes," Conseil replied serenely.</p>
      <p>"We haven't a moment to lose. Pack as much into my trunk as you
can, my traveling kit, my suits, shirts, and socks, don't bother
counting, just squeeze it all in—and hurry!"</p>
      <p>"What about master's collections?" Conseil ventured to
observe.</p>
      <p>"We'll deal with them later."</p>
      <p>"What! The <i>archaeotherium</i>, <i>hyracotherium</i>,
<i>oreodonts</i>, <i>cheiropotamus</i>, and master's other fossil
skeletons?"</p>
      <p>"The hotel will keep them for us."</p>
      <p>"What about master's live <i>babirusa</i>?"</p>
      <p>"They'll feed it during our absence. Anyhow, we'll leave
instructions to ship the whole menagerie to France."</p>
      <p>"Then we aren't returning to Paris?" Conseil asked.</p>
      <p>"Yes, we are . . . certainly . . . ," I replied evasively, "but
after we make a detour."</p>
      <p>"Whatever detour master wishes."</p>
      <p>"Oh, it's nothing really! A route slightly less direct, that's
all. We're leaving on the <i>Abraham Lincoln</i>."</p>
      <p>"As master thinks best," Conseil replied placidly.</p>
      <p>"You see, my friend, it's an issue of the monster, the notorious
narwhale. We're going to rid the seas of it! The author of a
two–volume work, in quarto, on The Mysteries of the Great
Ocean Depths has no excuse for not setting sail with Commander
Farragut. It's a glorious mission but also a dangerous one! We
don't know where it will take us! These beasts can be quite
unpredictable! But we're going just the same! We have a commander
who's game for anything!"</p>
      <p>"What master does, I'll do," Conseil replied.</p>
      <p>"But think it over, because I don't want to hide anything from
you. This is one of those voyages from which people don't always
come back!"</p>
      <p>"As master wishes."</p>
      <p>A quarter of an hour later, our trunks were ready. Conseil did
them in a flash, and I was sure the lad hadn't missed a thing,
because he classified shirts and suits as expertly as birds and
mammals.</p>
      <p>The hotel elevator dropped us off in the main vestibule on the
mezzanine. I went down a short stair leading to the ground floor. I
settled my bill at that huge counter that was always under siege by
a considerable crowd. I left instructions for shipping my
containers of stuffed animals and dried plants to Paris, France. I
opened a line of credit sufficient to cover the <i>babirusa</i>
and, Conseil at my heels, I jumped into a carriage.</p>
      <p>For a fare of twenty francs, the vehicle went down Broadway to
Union Square, took Fourth Ave. to its junction with Bowery St.,
turned into Katrin St. and halted at Pier 34. There the Katrin
ferry transferred men, horses, and carriage to Brooklyn, that great
New York annex located on the left bank of the East River, and in a
few minutes we arrived at the wharf next to which the <i>Abraham
Lincoln</i> was vomiting torrents of black smoke from its two
funnels.</p>
      <p>Our baggage was immediately carried to the deck of the frigate.
I rushed aboard. I asked for Commander Farragut. One of the sailors
led me to the afterdeck, where I stood in the presence of a
smart–looking officer who extended his hand to me.</p>
      <p>"Professor Pierre Aronnax?" he said to me.</p>
      <p>"The same," I replied. "Commander Farragut?"</p>
      <p>"In person. Welcome aboard, professor. Your cabin is waiting for
you."</p>
      <p>I bowed, and letting the commander attend to getting under way,
I was taken to the cabin that had been set aside for me.</p>
      <p>The <i>Abraham Lincoln</i> had been perfectly chosen and fitted
out for its new assignment. It was a high–speed frigate
furnished with superheating equipment that allowed the tension of
its steam to build to seven atmospheres. Under this pressure the
<i>Abraham Lincoln</i> reached an average speed of 18.3 miles per
hour, a considerable speed but still not enough to cope with our
gigantic <i>cetacean</i>.</p>
      <p>The frigate's interior accommodations complemented its nautical
virtues. I was well satisfied with my cabin, which was located in
the stern and opened into the officers' mess.</p>
      <p>"We'll be quite comfortable here," I told Conseil.</p>
      <p>"With all due respect to master," Conseil replied, "as
comfortable as a hermit crab inside the shell of a whelk."</p>
      <p>I left Conseil to the proper stowing of our luggage and climbed
on deck to watch the preparations for getting under way.</p>
      <p>Just then Commander Farragut was giving orders to cast off the
last moorings holding the <i>Abraham Lincoln</i> to its Brooklyn
pier. And so if I'd been delayed by a quarter of an hour or even
less, the frigate would have gone without me, and I would have
missed out on this unearthly, extraordinary, and inconceivable
expedition, whose true story might well meet with some
skepticism.</p>
      <p>But Commander Farragut didn't want to waste a single day, or
even a single hour, in making for those seas where the animal had
just been sighted. He summoned his engineer.</p>
      <p>"Are we up to pressure?" he asked the man.</p>
      <p>"Aye, sir," the engineer replied.</p>
      <p>"Go ahead, then!" Commander Farragut called.</p>
      <p>At this order, which was relayed to the engine by means of a
compressed–air device, the mechanics activated the
start–up wheel. Steam rushed whistling into the gaping
valves. Long horizontal pistons groaned and pushed the tie rods of
the drive shaft. The blades of the propeller churned the waves with
increasing speed, and the <i>Abraham Lincoln</i> moved out
majestically amid a spectator–laden escort of some 100
ferries and tenders.<fn callout="*">Author's Note: Tenders
are small steamboats that assist the big liners.</fn>
      </p>
      <p>The wharves of Brooklyn, and every part of New York bordering
the East River, were crowded with curiosity seekers. Departing from
500,000 throats, three cheers burst forth in succession. Thousands
of handkerchiefs were waving above these tightly packed masses,
hailing the <i>Abraham Lincoln</i> until it reached the waters of
the Hudson River, at the tip of the long peninsula that forms New
York City.</p>
      <p>The frigate then went along the New Jersey coast—the
wonderful right bank of this river, all loaded down with country
homes—and passed by the forts to salutes from their biggest
cannons. The <i>Abraham Lincoln</i> replied by three times lowering
and hoisting the American flag, whose thirty–nine stars
gleamed from the gaff of the mizzen sail; then, changing speed to
take the buoy–marked channel that curved into the inner bay
formed by the spit of Sandy Hook, it hugged this sand–covered
strip of land where thousands of spectators acclaimed us one more
time.</p>
      <p>The escort of boats and tenders still followed the frigate and
only left us when we came abreast of the lightship, whose two
signal lights mark the entrance of the narrows to Upper New York
Bay.</p>
      <p>Three o'clock then sounded. The harbor pilot went down into his
dinghy and rejoined a little schooner waiting for him to leeward.
The furnaces were stoked; the propeller churned the waves more
swiftly; the frigate skirted the flat, yellow coast of Long Island;
and at eight o'clock in the evening, after the lights of Fire
Island had vanished into the northwest, we ran at full steam onto
the dark waters of the Atlantic.</p>
   </body>
</topic>