<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<topic id="d2e9449">
   <title>
      <d4pSimpleEnumerator><!--2.6-->Chapter 6. </d4pSimpleEnumerator>
      <ph>The Greek Islands</ph>
   </title>
   <body>
      <p>
         <ph outputclass="size_plus_2">AT SUNRISE</ph> the next morning, February 12,
the <i>Nautilus</i> rose to the surface of the waves.</p>
      <p>I rushed onto the platform. The hazy silhouette of Pelusium was
outlined three miles to the south. A torrent had carried us from
one sea to the other. But although that tunnel was easy to descend,
going back up must have been impossible.</p>
      <p>Near seven o'clock Ned and Conseil joined me. Those two
inseparable companions had slept serenely, utterly unaware of the
<i>Nautilus's</i> feat.</p>
      <p>"Well, Mr. Naturalist," the Canadian asked in a gently mocking
tone, "and how about that Mediterranean?"</p>
      <p>"We're floating on its surface, Ned my friend."</p>
      <p>"What!" Conseil put in. "Last night . . . ?"</p>
      <p>"Yes, last night, in a matter of minutes, we cleared that
insuperable isthmus."</p>
      <p>"I don't believe a word of it," the Canadian replied.</p>
      <p>"And you're in the wrong, Mr. Land," I went on. "That flat
coastline curving southward is the coast of Egypt."</p>
      <p>"Tell it to the marines, sir," answered the stubborn
Canadian.</p>
      <p>"But if Master says so," Conseil told him, "then so be it."</p>
      <p>"What's more, Ned," I said, "Captain Nemo himself did the honors
in his tunnel, and I stood beside him in the pilothouse while he
steered the <i>Nautilus</i> through that narrow passageway."</p>
      <p>"You hear, Ned?" Conseil said.</p>
      <p>"And you, Ned, who have such good eyes," I added, "you can spot
the jetties of Port Said stretching out to sea."</p>
      <p>The Canadian looked carefully.</p>
      <p>"Correct," he said. "You're right, Professor, and your captain's
a superman. We're in the Mediterranean. Fine. So now let's have a
chat about our little doings, if you please, but in such a way that
nobody overhears."</p>
      <p>I could easily see what the Canadian was driving at. In any
event, I thought it best to let him have his chat, and we all three
went to sit next to the beacon, where we were less exposed to the
damp spray from the billows.</p>
      <p>"Now, Ned, we're all ears," I said. "What have you to tell
us?"</p>
      <p>"What I've got to tell you is very simple," the Canadian
replied. "We're in Europe, and before Captain Nemo's whims take us
deep into the polar seas or back to Oceania, I say we should leave
this <i>Nautilus</i>."</p>
      <p>I confess that such discussions with the Canadian always baffled
me. I didn't want to restrict my companions' freedom in any way,
and yet I had no desire to leave Captain Nemo. Thanks to him and
his submersible, I was finishing my undersea research by the day,
and I was rewriting my book on the great ocean depths in the midst
of its very element. Would I ever again have such an opportunity to
observe the ocean's wonders? Absolutely not! So I couldn't
entertain this idea of leaving the <i>Nautilus</i> before
completing our course of inquiry.</p>
      <p>"Ned my friend," I said, "answer me honestly. Are you bored with
this ship? Are you sorry that fate has cast you into Captain Nemo's
hands?"</p>
      <p>The Canadian paused for a short while before replying. Then,
crossing his arms:</p>
      <p>"Honestly," he said, "I'm not sorry about this voyage under the
seas. I'll be glad to have done it, but in order to have done it,
it has to finish. That's my feeling."</p>
      <p>"It will finish, Ned."</p>
      <p>"Where and when?"</p>
      <p>"Where? I don't know. When? I can't say. Or, rather, I suppose
it will be over when these seas have nothing more to teach us.
Everything that begins in this world must inevitably come to an
end."</p>
      <p>"I think as Master does," Conseil replied, "and it's extremely
possible that after crossing every sea on the globe, Captain Nemo
will bid the three of us a fond farewell."</p>
      <p>"Bid us a fond farewell?" the Canadian exclaimed. "You mean beat
us to a fare–thee–well!"</p>
      <p>"Let's not exaggerate, Mr. Land," I went on. "We have nothing to
fear from the captain, but neither do I share Conseil's views.
We're privy to the <i>Nautilus's</i> secrets, and I don't expect
that its commander, just to set us free, will meekly stand by while
we spread those secrets all over the world."</p>
      <p>"But in that case what do you expect?" the Canadian asked.</p>
      <p>"That we'll encounter advantageous conditions for escaping just
as readily in six months as now."</p>
      <p>"Great Scott!" Ned Land put in. "And where, if you please, will
we be in six months, Mr. Naturalist?"</p>
      <p>"Perhaps here, perhaps in China. You know how quickly the
<i>Nautilus</i> moves. It crosses oceans like swallows cross the
air or express trains continents. It doesn't fear heavily traveled
seas. Who can say it won't hug the coasts of France, England, or
America, where an escape attempt could be carried out just as
effectively as here."</p>
      <p>"Professor Aronnax," the Canadian replied, "your arguments are
rotten to the core. You talk way off in the future: 'We'll be here,
we'll be there!' Me, I'm talking about right now: we are here, and
we must take advantage of it!"</p>
      <p>I was hard pressed by Ned Land's common sense, and I felt myself
losing ground. I no longer knew what arguments to put forward on my
behalf.</p>
      <p>"Sir," Ned went on, "let's suppose that by some impossibility,
Captain Nemo offered your freedom to you this very day. Would you
accept?"</p>
      <p>"I don't know," I replied.</p>
      <p>"And suppose he adds that this offer he's making you today won't
ever be repeated, then would you accept?"</p>
      <p>I did not reply.</p>
      <p>"And what thinks our friend Conseil?" Ned Land asked.</p>
      <p>"Your friend Conseil," the fine lad replied serenely, "has
nothing to say for himself. He's a completely disinterested party
on this question. Like his master, like his comrade Ned, he's a
bachelor. Neither wife, parents, nor children are waiting for him
back home. He's in Master's employ, he thinks like Master, he
speaks like Master, and much to his regret, he can't be counted on
to form a majority. Only two persons face each other here: Master
on one side, Ned Land on the other. That said, your friend Conseil
is listening, and he's ready to keep score."</p>
      <p>I couldn't help smiling as Conseil wiped himself out of
existence. Deep down, the Canadian must have been overjoyed at not
having to contend with him.</p>
      <p>"Then, sir," Ned Land said, "since Conseil is no more, we'll
have this discussion between just the two of us. I've talked,
you've listened. What's your reply?"</p>
      <p>It was obvious that the matter had to be settled, and evasions
were distasteful to me.</p>
      <p>"Ned my friend," I said, "here's my reply. You have right on
your side and my arguments can't stand up to yours. It will never
do to count on Captain Nemo's benevolence. The most ordinary good
sense would forbid him to set us free. On the other hand, good
sense decrees that we take advantage of our first opportunity to
leave the <i>Nautilus</i>."</p>
      <p>"Fine, Professor Aronnax, that's wisely said."</p>
      <p>"But one proviso," I said, "just one. The opportunity must be
the real thing. Our first attempt to escape must succeed, because
if it misfires, we won't get a second chance, and Captain Nemo will
never forgive us."</p>
      <p>"That's also well put," the Canadian replied. "But your proviso
applies to any escape attempt, whether it happens in two years or
two days. So this is still the question: if a promising opportunity
comes up, we have to grab it."</p>
      <p>"Agreed. And now, Ned, will you tell me what you mean by a
promising opportunity?"</p>
      <p>"One that leads the <i>Nautilus</i> on a cloudy night within a
short distance of some European coast."</p>
      <p>"And you'll try to get away by swimming?"</p>
      <p>"Yes, if we're close enough to shore and the ship's afloat on
the surface. No, if we're well out and the ship's navigating under
the waters."</p>
      <p>"And in that event?"</p>
      <p>"In that event I'll try to get hold of the skiff. I know how to
handle it. We'll stick ourselves inside, undo the bolts, and rise
to the surface, without the helmsman in the bow seeing a
thing."</p>
      <p>"Fine, Ned. Stay on the lookout for such an opportunity, but
don't forget, one slipup will finish us."</p>
      <p>"I won't forget, sir."</p>
      <p>"And now, Ned, would you like to know my overall thinking on
your plan?"</p>
      <p>"Gladly, Professor Aronnax."</p>
      <p>"Well then, I think—and I don't mean 'I hope'—that
your promising opportunity won't ever arise."</p>
      <p>"Why not?"</p>
      <p>"Because Captain Nemo recognizes that we haven't given up all
hope of recovering our freedom, and he'll keep on his guard, above
all in seas within sight of the coasts of Europe."</p>
      <p>"I'm of Master's opinion," Conseil said.</p>
      <p>"We'll soon see," Ned Land replied, shaking his head with a
determined expression.</p>
      <p>"And now, Ned Land," I added, "let's leave it at that. Not
another word on any of this. The day you're ready, alert us and
we're with you. I turn it all over to you."</p>
      <p>That's how we ended this conversation, which later was to have
such serious consequences. At first, I must say, events seemed to
confirm my forecasts, much to the Canadian's despair. Did Captain
Nemo view us with distrust in these heavily traveled seas, or did
he simply want to hide from the sight of those ships of every
nation that plowed the Mediterranean? I have no idea, but usually
he stayed in midwater and well out from any coast. Either the
<i>Nautilus</i> surfaced only enough to let its pilothouse emerge,
or it slipped away to the lower depths, although, between the Greek
Islands and Asia Minor, we didn't find bottom even at 2,000 meters
down.</p>
      <p>Accordingly, I became aware of the isle of Karpathos, one of the
Sporades Islands, only when Captain Nemo placed his finger over a
spot on the world map and quoted me this verse from Virgil:</p>
      <lq>
         <p>Est in Carpathio Neptuni gurgite vates</p>
         <p>Caeruleus Proteus . . .<fn callout="*">Latin: "There in King
Neptune's domain by Karpathos, his spokesman / is azure–hued
Proteus . . . " Ed.</fn>
         </p>
      </lq>
      <p>It was indeed that bygone abode of Proteus, the old shepherd of
King Neptune's flocks: an island located between Rhodes and Crete,
which Greeks now call Karpathos, Italians Scarpanto. Through the
lounge window I could see only its granite bedrock.</p>
      <p>The next day, February 14, I decided to spend a few hours
studying the fish of this island group; but for whatever reason,
the panels remained hermetically sealed. After determining the
<i>Nautilus's</i> heading, I noted that it was proceeding toward
the ancient island of Crete, also called Candia. At the time I had
shipped aboard the <i>Abraham Lincoln</i>, this whole island was in
rebellion against its tyrannical rulers, the Ottoman Empire of
Turkey. But since then I had absolutely no idea what happened to
this revolution, and Captain Nemo, deprived of all contact with the
shore, was hardly the man to keep me informed.</p>
      <p>So I didn't allude to this event when, that evening, I chanced
to be alone with the captain in the lounge. Besides, he seemed
silent and preoccupied. Then, contrary to custom, he ordered that
both panels in the lounge be opened, and going from the one to the
other, he carefully observed the watery mass. For what purpose? I
hadn't a guess, and for my part, I spent my time studying the fish
that passed before my eyes.</p>
      <p>Among others I noted that sand goby mentioned by Aristotle and
commonly known by the name sea loach, which is encountered
exclusively in the salty waters next to the Nile Delta. Near them
some semiphosphorescent red porgy rolled by, a variety of gilthead
that the Egyptians ranked among their sacred animals, lauding them
in religious ceremonies when their arrival in the river's waters
announced the fertile flood season. I also noticed some wrasse
known as the tapiro, three decimeters long, bony fish with
transparent scales whose bluish gray color is mixed with red spots;
they're enthusiastic eaters of marine vegetables, which gives them
an exquisite flavor; hence these tapiro were much in demand by the
epicures of ancient Rome, and their entrails were dressed with
brains of peacock, tongue of flamingo, and testes of moray to make
that divine platter that so enraptured the Roman emperor
Vitellius.</p>
      <p>Another resident of these seas caught my attention and revived
all my memories of antiquity. This was the remora, which travels
attached to the bellies of sharks; as the ancients tell it, when
these little fish cling to the undersides of a ship, they can bring
it to a halt, and by so impeding Mark Antony's vessel during the
Battle of Actium, one of them facilitated the victory of Augustus
Caesar. From such slender threads hang the destinies of nations! I
also observed some wonderful snappers belonging to the order
<i>Lutianida</i>, sacred fish for the Greeks, who claimed they
could drive off sea monsters from the waters they frequent; their
Greek name <i>anthias</i> means "flower," and they live up to it in
the play of their colors and in those fleeting reflections that
turn their dorsal fins into watered silk; their hues are confined
to a gamut of reds, from the pallor of pink to the glow of ruby. I
couldn't take my eyes off these marine wonders, when I was suddenly
jolted by an unexpected apparition.</p>
      <p>In the midst of the waters, a man appeared, a diver carrying a
little leather bag at his belt. It was no corpse lost in the waves.
It was a living man, swimming vigorously, sometimes disappearing to
breathe at the surface, then instantly diving again.</p>
      <p>I turned to Captain Nemo, and in an agitated voice:</p>
      <p>"A man! A castaway!" I exclaimed. "We must rescue him at all
cost!"</p>
      <p>The captain didn't reply but went to lean against the
window.</p>
      <p>The man drew near, and gluing his face to the panel, he stared
at us.</p>
      <p>To my deep astonishment, Captain Nemo gave him a signal. The
diver answered with his hand, immediately swam up to the surface of
the sea, and didn't reappear.</p>
      <p>"Don't be alarmed," the captain told me. "That's Nicolas from
Cape Matapan, nicknamed 'Il Pesce.'<fn callout="*">Italian: "The Fish."
Ed.</fn>
He's well known throughout the Cyclades Islands. A bold diver!
Water is his true element, and he lives in the sea more than on
shore, going constantly from one island to another, even to
Crete."</p>
      <p>"You know him, captain?"</p>
      <p>"Why not, Professor Aronnax?"</p>
      <p>This said, Captain Nemo went to a cabinet standing near the
lounge's left panel. Next to this cabinet I saw a chest bound with
hoops of iron, its lid bearing a copper plaque that displayed the
<i>Nautilus's</i> monogram with its motto <i>Mobilis in
Mobili</i>.</p>
      <p>Just then, ignoring my presence, the captain opened this
cabinet, a sort of safe that contained a large number of
ingots.</p>
      <p>They were gold ingots. And they represented an enormous sum of
money. Where had this precious metal come from? How had the captain
amassed this gold, and what was he about to do with it?</p>
      <p>I didn't pronounce a word. I gaped. Captain Nemo took out the
ingots one by one and arranged them methodically inside the chest,
filling it to the top. At which point I estimate that it held more
than 1,000 kilograms of gold, in other words, close to
₣5,000,000.</p>
      <p>After securely fastening the chest, Captain Nemo wrote an
address on its lid in characters that must have been modern
Greek.</p>
      <p>This done, the captain pressed a button whose wiring was in
communication with the crew's quarters. Four men appeared and, not
without difficulty, pushed the chest out of the lounge. Then I
heard them hoist it up the iron companionway by means of
pulleys.</p>
      <p>Just then Captain Nemo turned to me:</p>
      <p>"You were saying, Professor?" he asked me.</p>
      <p>"I wasn't saying a thing, Captain."</p>
      <p>"Then, sir, with your permission, I'll bid you good
evening."</p>
      <p>And with that, Captain Nemo left the lounge.</p>
      <p>I reentered my stateroom, very puzzled, as you can imagine. I
tried in vain to fall asleep. I kept searching for a relationship
between the appearance of the diver and that chest filled with
gold. Soon, from certain rolling and pitching movements, I sensed
that the <i>Nautilus</i> had left the lower strata and was back on
the surface of the water.</p>
      <p>Then I heard the sound of footsteps on the platform. I realized
that the skiff was being detached and launched to sea. For an
instant it bumped the <i>Nautilus's</i> side, then all sounds
ceased.</p>
      <p>Two hours later, the same noises, the same comings and goings,
were repeated. Hoisted on board, the longboat was readjusted into
its socket, and the <i>Nautilus</i> plunged back beneath the
waves.</p>
      <p>So those millions had been delivered to their address. At what
spot on the continent? Who was the recipient of Captain Nemo's
gold?</p>
      <p>The next day I related the night's events to Conseil and the
Canadian, events that had aroused my curiosity to a fever pitch. My
companions were as startled as I was.</p>
      <p>"But where does he get those millions?" Ned Land asked.</p>
      <p>To this no reply was possible. After breakfast I made my way to
the lounge and went about my work. I wrote up my notes until five
o'clock in the afternoon. Just then—was it due to some
personal indisposition?—I felt extremely hot and had to take
off my jacket made of fan mussel fabric. A perplexing circumstance
because we weren't in the low latitudes, and besides, once the
<i>Nautilus</i> was submerged, it shouldn't be subject to any rise
in temperature. I looked at the pressure gauge. It marked a depth
of sixty feet, a depth beyond the reach of atmospheric heat.</p>
      <p>I kept on working, but the temperature rose to the point of
becoming unbearable.</p>
      <p>"Could there be a fire on board?" I wondered.</p>
      <p>I was about to leave the lounge when Captain Nemo entered. He
approached the thermometer, consulted it, and turned to me:</p>
      <p>"42° centigrade," he said.</p>
      <p>"I've detected as much, Captain," I replied, "and if it gets
even slightly hotter, we won't be able to stand it."</p>
      <p>"Oh, professor, it won't get any hotter unless we want it
to!"</p>
      <p>"You mean you can control this heat?"</p>
      <p>"No, but I can back away from the fireplace producing it."</p>
      <p>"So it's outside?"</p>
      <p>"Surely. We're cruising in a current of boiling water."</p>
      <p>"It can't be!" I exclaimed.</p>
      <p>"Look."</p>
      <p>The panels had opened, and I could see a completely white sea
around the <i>Nautilus</i>. Steaming sulfurous fumes uncoiled in
the midst of waves bubbling like water in a boiler. I leaned my
hand against one of the windows, but the heat was so great, I had
to snatch it back.</p>
      <p>"Where are we?" I asked.</p>
      <p>"Near the island of Santorini, professor," the captain answered
me, "and right in the channel that separates the volcanic islets of
Nea Kameni and Palea Kameni. I wanted to offer you the unusual
sight of an underwater eruption."</p>
      <p>"I thought," I said, "that the formation of such new islands had
come to an end."</p>
      <p>"Nothing ever comes to an end in these volcanic waterways,"
Captain Nemo replied, "and thanks to its underground fires, our
globe is continuously under construction in these regions.
According to the Latin historians Cassiodorus and Pliny, by the
year 19 of the Christian era, a new island, the divine Thera, had
already appeared in the very place these islets have more recently
formed. Then Thera sank under the waves, only to rise and sink once
more in the year 69 A.D. From that day to this, such plutonic
construction work has been in abeyance. But on February 3, 1866, a
new islet named George Island emerged in the midst of sulfurous
steam near Nea Kameni and was fused to it on the 6th of the same
month. Seven days later, on February 13, the islet of Aphroessa
appeared, leaving a ten–meter channel between itself and Nea
Kameni. I was in these seas when that phenomenon occurred and I was
able to observe its every phase. The islet of Aphroessa was
circular in shape, measuring 300 feet in diameter and thirty feet
in height. It was made of black, glassy lava mixed with bits of
feldspar. Finally, on March 10, a smaller islet called Reka
appeared next to Nea Kameni, and since then, these three islets
have fused to form one single, selfsame island."</p>
      <p>"What about this channel we're in right now?" I asked.</p>
      <p>"Here it is," Captain Nemo replied, showing me a chart of the
Greek Islands. "You observe that I've entered the new islets in
their place."</p>
      <p>"But will this channel fill up one day?"</p>
      <p>"Very likely, Professor Aronnax, because since 1866 eight little
lava islets have surged up in front of the port of St. Nicolas on
Palea Kameni. So it's obvious that Nea and Palea will join in days
to come. In the middle of the Pacific, tiny infusoria build
continents, but here they're built by volcanic phenomena. Look,
sir! Look at the construction work going on under these waves."</p>
      <p>I returned to the window. The <i>Nautilus</i> was no longer
moving. The heat had become unbearable. From the white it had
recently been, the sea was turning red, a coloration caused by the
presence of iron salts. Although the lounge was hermetically
sealed, it was filling with an intolerable stink of sulfur, and I
could see scarlet flames of such brightness, they overpowered our
electric light.</p>
      <p>I was swimming in perspiration, I was stifling, I was about to
be cooked. Yes, I felt myself cooking in actual fact!</p>
      <p>"We can't stay any longer in this boiling water," I told the
captain.</p>
      <p>"No, it wouldn't be advisable," replied Nemo the
Emotionless.</p>
      <p>He gave an order. The <i>Nautilus</i> tacked about and retreated
from this furnace it couldn't brave with impunity. A quarter of an
hour later, we were breathing fresh air on the surface of the
waves.</p>
      <p>It then occurred to me that if Ned had chosen these waterways
for our escape attempt, we wouldn't have come out alive from this
sea of fire.</p>
      <p>The next day, February 16, we left this basin, which tallies
depths of 3,000 meters between Rhodes and Alexandria, and passing
well out from Cerigo Island after doubling Cape Matapan, the
<i>Nautilus</i> left the Greek Islands behind.</p>
   </body>
</topic>