<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<topic id="topic-1">
  <title>Introduction</title>
  <body>
    <p>"The deepest parts of the ocean are totally unknown to us,"
      admits Professor Aronnax early in this novel. "What goes on in
      those distant depths? What creatures inhabit, or could inhabit,
      those regions twelve or fifteen miles beneath the surface of the
      water? It's almost beyond conjecture."</p>
    <p>Jules Verne (1828-1905) published the French equivalents
      of these words in 1869, and little has changed since. 126 years
      later, a <i>Time</i> cover story on deep-sea exploration made
      much the same admission: "We know more about Mars than we know
      about the oceans." This reality begins to explain the dark power
      and otherworldly fascination of <i>Twenty Thousand Leagues Under
        the Seas</i>.</p>
    <p>Born in the French river town of Nantes, Verne had a lifelong
      passion for the sea. First as a Paris stockbroker, later as a
      celebrated author and yachtsman, he went on frequent
      voyages&#x2014;to Britain, America, the Mediterranean. But the
      specific stimulus for this novel was an 1865 fan letter from a
      fellow writer, Madame George Sand. She praised Verne's two early
      novels <i>Five Weeks in a Balloon</i> (1863) and <i>Journey to the
        Center of the Earth</i> (1864), then added: "Soon I hope you'll
      take us into the ocean depths, your characters traveling in diving
      equipment perfected by your science and your imagination." Thus
      inspired, Verne created one of literature's great rebels, a freedom
      fighter who plunged beneath the waves to wage a unique form of
      guerilla warfare.</p>
    <p>Initially, Verne's narrative was influenced by the 1863 uprising
      of Poland against Tsarist Russia. The Poles were quashed with a
      violence that appalled not only Verne but all Europe. As originally
      conceived, Verne's Captain Nemo was a Polish nobleman whose entire
      family had been slaughtered by Russian troops. Nemo builds a
      fabulous futuristic submarine, the <i>Nautilus</i>, then conducts
      an underwater campaign of vengeance against his imperialist
      oppressor.</p>
    <p>But in the 1860s France had to treat the Tsar as an ally, and
      Verne's publisher, Pierre Hetzel, pronounced the book unprintable.
      Verne reworked its political content, devising new nationalities
      for Nemo and his great enemy&#x2014;information revealed only in a
      later novel, <i>The Mysterious Island</i> (1875); in the present
      work Nemo's background remains a dark secret. In all, the novel had
      a difficult gestation. Verne and Hetzel were in constant conflict
      and the book went through multiple drafts, struggles reflected in
      its several working titles over the period 1865-69: early on,
      it was variously called <i>Voyage Under the Waters</i>,
      <i>Twenty-five Thousand Leagues Under the Waters</i>,
      <i>Twenty Thousand Leagues Under the Waters</i>, and <i>A Thousand
        Leagues Under the Oceans</i>.</p>
    <p>Verne is often dubbed, in Isaac Asimov's phrase, "the world's
      first science-fiction writer." And it's true, many of his
      sixty-odd books do anticipate future events and technologies:
      <i>From the Earth to the Moon</i> (1865) and <i>Hector Servadac</i>
      (1877) deal in space travel, while <i>Journey to the Center of the
        Earth</i> features travel to the earth's core. But with Verne the
      operative word is "travel," and some of his best-known titles
      don't really qualify as sci-fi: <i>Around the World in Eighty
        Days</i> (1872) and <i>Michael Strogoff</i> (1876) are closer to
      "travelogs"&#x2014;adventure yarns in far-away places.</p>
    <p>These observations partly apply here. The subtitle of the
      present book is <i>An Underwater Tour of the World</i>, so in good
      travelog style, the <i>Nautilus's</i> exploits supply an episodic
      story line. Shark attacks, giant squid, cannibals, hurricanes,
      whale hunts, and other rip-roaring adventures erupt almost at
      random. Yet this loose structure gives the novel an air of
      documentary realism. What's more, Verne adds backbone to the action
      by developing three recurring motifs: the deepening mystery of
      Nemo's past life and future intentions, the mounting tension
      between Nemo and hot-tempered harpooner Ned Land, and Ned's
      ongoing schemes to escape from the <i>Nautilus</i>. These unifying
      threads tighten the narrative and accelerate its momentum.</p>
    <p>Other subtleties occur inside each episode, the textures
      sparkling with wit, information, and insight. Verne regards the sea
      from many angles: in the domain of marine biology, he gives us
      thumbnail sketches of fish, seashells, coral, sometimes in great
      catalogs that swirl past like musical cascades; in the realm of
      geology, he studies volcanoes literally inside and out; in the
      world of commerce, he celebrates the high-energy
      entrepreneurs who lay the Atlantic Cable or dig the Suez Canal. And
      Verne's marine engineering proves especially authoritative. His
      specifications for an open-sea submarine and a
      self-contained diving suit were decades before their time,
      yet modern technology bears them out triumphantly.</p>
    <p>True, today's scientists know a few things he didn't: the South
      Pole isn't at the water's edge but far inland; sharks don't flip
      over before attacking; giant squid sport ten tentacles not eight;
      sperm whales don't prey on their whalebone cousins. This
      notwithstanding, Verne furnishes the most evocative portrayal of
      the ocean depths before the arrival of Jacques Cousteau and
      technicolor film.</p>
    <p>Lastly the book has stature as a novel of character. Even the
      supporting cast is shrewdly drawn: Professor Aronnax, the career
      scientist caught in an ethical conflict; Conseil, the compulsive
      classifier who supplies humorous tag lines for Verne's fast facts;
      the harpooner Ned Land, a creature of constant appetites, man as
      heroic animal.</p>
    <p>But much of the novel's brooding power comes from Captain Nemo.
      Inventor, musician, Renaissance genius, he's a trail-blazing
      creation, the prototype not only for countless renegade scientists
      in popular fiction, but even for such varied figures as Sherlock
      Holmes or Wolf Larsen. However, Verne gives his hero's brilliance
      and benevolence a dark underside&#x2014;the man's obsessive hate for
      his old enemy. This compulsion leads Nemo into ugly contradictions:
      he's a fighter for freedom, yet all who board his ship are
      imprisoned there for good; he works to save lives, both human and
      animal, yet he himself creates a holocaust; he detests imperialism,
      yet he lays personal claim to the South Pole. And in this last
      action he falls into the classic sin of Pride. He's swiftly
      punished. The <i>Nautilus</i> nearly perishes in the Antarctic and
      Nemo sinks into a growing depression.</p>
    <p>Like Shakespeare's <i>King Lear</i> he courts death and madness
      in a great storm, then commits mass murder, collapses in catatonic
      paralysis, and suicidally runs his ship into the ocean's most
      dangerous whirlpool. Hate swallows him whole.</p>
    <p>For many, then, this book has been a source of fascination,
      surely one of the most influential novels ever written, an
      inspiration for such scientists and discoverers as engineer Simon
      Lake, oceanographer William Beebe, polar traveler Sir Ernest
      Shackleton. Likewise Dr. Robert D. Ballard, finder of the sunken
      Titanic, confesses that this was his favorite book as a teenager,
      and Cousteau himself, most renowned of marine explorers, called it
      his shipboard bible.</p>
    <p>The present translation is a faithful yet communicative
      rendering of the original French texts published in Paris by J.
      Hetzel et Cie.&#x2014;the hardcover first edition issued in the
      autumn of 1871, collated with the softcover editions of the First
      and Second Parts issued separately in the autumn of 1869 and the
      summer of 1870. Although prior English versions have often been
      heavily abridged, this new translation is complete to the smallest
      substantive detail.</p>
    <p>Because, as that <i>Time</i> cover story suggests, we still
      haven't caught up with Verne. Even in our era of satellite dishes
      and video games, the seas keep their secrets. We've seen progress
      in sonar, torpedoes, and other belligerent machinery, but sailors
      and scientists&#x2014;to say nothing of tourists&#x2014;have yet to
      voyage in a submarine with the luxury and efficiency of the
      <i>Nautilus</i>.</p>
    <p>F. P. WALTER</p>
    <p>University of Houston</p>
  </body>
</topic>
