<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.org:doctypes:dita:concept" "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.org:doctypes:dita:concept">
<concept id="conceptId">
 <title>Getting Started With The Word2DITA Transform</title>
 <shortdesc>How to set up an Ant task to convert a Word document to DITA using the Open Toolkit</shortdesc>
  <prolog>
    <metadata>
      <keywords>
        <indexterm></indexterm>
      </keywords>
    </metadata>
  </prolog>
 <conbody>
    <p>The Word2DITA transform is packaged as an Open Toolkit plugin (see <xref
      format="dita"
      href="word-to-dita-plugin.xml#conceptId"/>). This makes it easy to apply the transform to Word documents using an existing Open Toolkit installation. You can also apply the transform directly to the document.xml file within a DOCX package, e.g., using OxygenXML. The Word2DITA transform is not dependent on any Open Toolkit preprocessing or Toolkit-provided components.</p>
    <p>To convert one of the sample files, follow these steps:<ol
        id="ol_9afef18a-a29f-4275-acee-d51a88dacadd">
        <li>Deploy the DITA for Publishers Toolkit plugins to your Open Toolkit (see <xref
            format="dita" href="../tasks/plugin-installation.xml#taskId"/>).</li>
        <li>Create a file named <filepath>build.properties</filepath> in your home directory (e.g.,
            <filepath>/Users/ekimber</filepath>) and in that file put a line like
            this:<codeblock>dita-ot-dir=<b>c:/DITA-OT</b></codeblock><p>Where the part in bold
            reflects the location of the Toolkit on your machine.</p></li>
        <li>From the DITA for Publishers sample data (provided as a separate Zip file in the main installation), copy the <filepath>word2dita/all_defaults</filepath> directory to a convenient place
        (e.g., to <filepath>/Users/ekimber/w2d_transforms/all_defaults</filepath>). </li>
        <li>If necessary, run the <filepath>startcmd</filepath> file that is applicable for your
          operating system. This displays a DITA-OT shell. The DITA-OT shell makes sure that certain
          libraries required for the transformation are available. <p>You do not need to run the
              <filepath>startcmd</filepath> file if you already have a DITA-OT shell (a
            command-prompt or terminal window that was invoked by the <filepath>startcmd</filepath>
            file open). </p></li>
        <li>In the DITA-OT shell, change to the directory with the Word document.
            <codeblock>cd <b>~/w2d_transforms</b>/all_defaults/word</codeblock><p>Where the part in
            bold reflects the location of the sample files on your machine.</p></li>
        <li>In the DITA-OT shell, run the <filepath>dita-ot-run-word2dita.xml</filepath> build file
          with Ant:<codeblock>ant -f dita-ot-run-word2dita.xml</codeblock><p>It should run and you
            should get some output in <filepath>all_defaults/dita</filepath>. You should get a map
            and some number of topics, one for each Heading 1, Heading 2, Heading 3, and Heading 4
            paragraph in your Word document.</p></li>
      </ol></p>
    <p>To convert one of your own Word documents, follow these steps:<ol id="ol_zlj_hkl_y3">
        <li>Copy of the <filepath>word2dita/all_defaults</filepath> directory once again and store
          it under a new name (e.g., in
            <filepath>/Users/ekimber/w2d_transforms/my_transform</filepath>). This will be the
          starting point for your Word-to-DITA transformation configuration.</li>
        <li>Replace the Word document in that directory with the Word document you want to
          convert.</li>
        <li>Edit your Word document and make sure that the first paragraph in the document is styled
          with the "Title" paragraph style—you may need to add a new paragraph. This paragraph
          defines the map title and signals the generation of the root output map. This setup is
          required by the default style-to-tag mapping.</li>
        <li>Edit the file <filepath>dita-ot-run-word2dita.xml</filepath> in that directory and
          change this
            line:<codeblock>&lt;property name="args.input" 
  location="${myAntFile.dir}/<b>word2dita_single_doc_to_map_and_topics_01.docx</b>"
/></codeblock><p>To
            reflect the filename of your Word document. For
            example:<codeblock>&lt;property name="args.input" 
  location="${myAntFile.dir}/my_document.docx"
/></codeblock></p></li>
        <li>In a DITA-OT shell, change to the directory with your Word document.
            <codeblock>cd <b>~/w2d_transforms/my_transform</b>/word</codeblock><p>Where the part in
            bold reflects the location of your Word document on your machine.</p></li>
        <li>In a DITA-OT shell, run the <filepath>dita-ot-run-word2dita.xml</filepath> build file
          with Ant:<codeblock>ant -f dita-ot-run-word2dita.xml</codeblock><p>It should run and you
            should get some output (e.g., in <filepath>my_transform/dita</filepath>).</p></li>
      </ol></p>
    <p>The Toolkit log will include messages from the Word-to-DITA transform, which will report
      unmapped paragraph and character styles. By default, any unmapped paragraph style is mapped to
        <xmlelem>p</xmlelem>, so you will usually get valid, if not ideal, output from the default
      mapping.</p>
    <p>Once you have verified that you can get <i>something</i> from the transform you are ready to
      start configuring the style-to-tag mapping to reflect your specific requirements and Word
      documents. You will likely find that you also need to refine how your documents are styled so
      that they map most effectively.</p>
    <p>Finally, remember that the Word-to-DITA process is a work in progress and there is always room for improvement. Please report any bugs or feature requests to the DITA for Publishers bug tracker
      on GitHub (<xref
      format="html"
      href="https://github.com/dita4publishers/d4p-word2dita/issues">https://github.com/dita4publishers/d4p-word2dita/issues</xref></p>
    <p>Remember too that the Word to DITA framework is open source, which means I welcome fixes and
      enhancements from the community.</p>
  </conbody>
</concept>
