<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.org:doctypes:dita:concept" "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.org:doctypes:dita:concept">
<concept id="conceptId">
 <title>Word-to-DITA Ant Parameters</title>
 <shortdesc>Ant parameters for the Word-to-DITA transformation type</shortdesc>
  <prolog>
    <metadata>
      <keywords>
        <indexterm></indexterm>
      </keywords>
    </metadata>
  </prolog>
 <conbody>
   <p>To run the Word-to-DITA transformation using the Open Toolkit plugin, specify the following Ant parameters.</p>
    <section>
      <title>Required Parameters</title>
      <parml>
        <plentry>
          <pt>args.input</pt>
          <pd>The absolute filename and path of the DOCX file to process.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>word.doc</pt>
          <pd>The path and filename of the Word DOCX file to process.</pd>
        </plentry>
      </parml>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Optional Parameters</title>
      <parml>
        <plentry>
          <pt>output.dir</pt>
          <pd>Specifies the absolute path of of the directory to contain the generated output.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>w2d.clean.output.dir</pt>
          <pd>Set to "true" to have the output directory cleaned out before
            running the transform. The default is "false".</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>w2d.debug.xslt</pt>
          <pd>Turns on debugging of the XSLT transform. Default is "false".</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>w2d.defaultStyleToTagMap</pt>
          <pd>Specifies the location of the style-to-tag map to use as the
            default if no style-to-tag-map is specified. The default is the
            word-builtin-styles-style2tagmap.xml file. This parameter is mostly
            useful for setting as a default in installation-specific properties
            files. You would not normally specify it for a specific
            document.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>w2d.filename.prefix</pt>
          <pd>The prefix to use for generated files other than submaps. The
            default is no prefix.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>w2d.filter.br</pt>
          <pd>Control whether or not <xmlelem>br</xmlelem> elements generated
            from the Word data will be filtered out of the result DITA. Set to
            "true" to filter out <xmlelem>br</xmlelem> elements. The default is
            "false" (<xmlelem>br</xmlelem> elements are included in the result
            DITA). The <xmlelem>br</xmlelem> element is provided by the DITA for
            Publishers formatting vocabulary domain module.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>w2d.filter.tabs</pt>
          <pd>Control whether or not <xmlelem>tab</xmlelem> elements generated
            from the Word data will be filtered out of the result DITA. Set to
            "true" to filter out <xmlelem>tab</xmlelem> elements. The default is
            "false" (<xmlelem>tab</xmlelem> elements are included in the result
            DITA). The <xmlelem>tab</xmlelem> element is provided by the DITA
            for Publishers formatting vocabulary domain module.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>w2d.include.word.backpointers</pt>
          <pd>Set to "false" to turn off inclusion of <xmlatt>xtrc</xmlatt>
            attributes in the generated DITA files that point back to the
            original paragraphs in the Word document. Default is "true"
            (<xmlatt>xtrc</xmlatt> attributes are generated).</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>w2d.include.word.bookmarks</pt>
          <pd>Set to "true" to turn inclusion of <xmlelem>data</xmlelem>
            elements reflecting any Word bookmark start and end markers. Default
            is "false".</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>w2d.root.map.name</pt>
          <pd>The filename (without extension) to use for the root map if one is
            generated. By default uses the filename of the input DOCX file. Only
            specify this property if the style-to-tag mapping will result in a
            map. If the style-to-tag mapping only produces topics, then do not
            specify this property.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>w2d.root.output.filename</pt>
          <pd>Specifies the complete filename (including extension), of the root
            output file, whether it's a topic or a map. You would not normally
            specify this property unless the behavior of
            <parmname>w2d.root.map.name</parmname> or
            <parmname>w2d.root.topic.name</parmname> doesn't give you the result
            you want.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>w2d.root.topic.name</pt>
          <pd>The filename (without extension) to use for the root topic. By
            default, uses the filename of the input DOCX file. This property is
            ignored if <parmname>w2d.root.topic.name</parmname> is also
            specified.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>w2d.style-to-tag-map</pt>
          <pd>The absolute filename and path of the style-to-tag mapping to use.
            If not specified, the built-in mapping file
            <filepath>org.dita4publishers.word2dita/xsl/word-builtin-styles-style2tagmap.xml</filepath>
            is used.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>w2d.submap.name.prefix</pt>
          <pd>The prefix to use for generated submaps. The default is
            "map".</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>w2d.temp.dir</pt>
          <pd>The temporary directory to use for word2dita process. Default is
            ${basedir}/temp.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>w2d.topic.extension</pt>
          <pd>The extension to use for generated topic files. The default is
            ".dita".</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>w2d.word2dita.xslt</pt>
          <pd>Specifies the name of the XSLT transform to use to convert the DOCX file to DITA. Default is the <filepath>docx2dita.xsl</filepath> transform in the word2dita Toolkit plugin.</pd>
        </plentry>
      </parml>
    </section>
 </conbody>
</concept>
