<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.org:doctypes:dita:concept" "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.org:doctypes:dita:concept">
<concept
  id="concept-id">
  <title>DOCX to DITA Transform Overview</title>
  <shortdesc>The DOCX-to-DITA transformation provides a configuration-driven transformation from
    styled Microsoft Word DOCX (Office 2007) documents to DITA-based XML. The Word templates and
    corresponding style-to-tag mappings are of course specific to a particular use but the transform
    itself is completely generic. In addition, the base transform can be extended or overridden
    using normal XSLT override and extension mechanisms to add any needed use-case-specific
    processing. The transform can generate DITA map and topic documents using any
    specialization.</shortdesc>
  <conbody>
    <p>The DOCX-to-DITA processor has been designed to minimize the effort required to set up and
      maintain transformations from Word documents to DITA XML. While setting up the
      style-to-mapping requires knowledge of the target DITA XML structures to be generated, it does
      not require any programming knowledge. The general design goal for the DOCX-to-DITA process is
      to be entirely configuration driven for as many use cases as possible so that no programming
      is required.</p>
    <p>The transform uses a configuration file, the "style to tag mapping" document, to determine
      how to map paragraph and character styles in the Word document to DITA markup in the result
      maps and topics. The transformation can generate multiple map and topic documents from a
      single Word document. The simplest case is a single Word document results in exactly one topic
      document.</p>
    <p>In order for the transform to work, the Word document must follow a few rules:<ul
        id="ul_b9c9e14f-8bb8-470d-80e3-a35e3e68399e">
        <li>The transform only recognizes named styles. Manual formatting is not recognized. This
          means, for example, that you must use character styles for things like bold, italic, and
          so on, as well as for more semantic items, such as person names, emails, etc.<fn>This
            restriction may be removed in a future release.</fn></li>
        <li>Nested structures within topic bodies and sections require unique style names for each
          distinct level. This means you need different styles for first and second-level list
          items. For things like list items this is usually the case, but some structures may nest
          in the DITA but have no visual distinction in the Word document.</li>
        <li>All the content for a given topic body needs to be contiguous. For example, if you have
          content that will result in a subordinate topic in the DITA result, it must come after any
          body content for the parent topic. </li>
      </ul></p>
    <p>These rules mean that you won't be able to take just any Word document, code up a style
      mapping, and get good DITA out. You will likely need to do a little work to define any
      necessary styles and apply them consistently. However, that effort shouldn't be too hard. If
      you create document templates and then use them consistently thing should work. For documents
      that are mostly paragraphs, lists, and so on, the styling requirements are pretty simple.
      Documents that need to result in more sophisticated structures, such as learning and training
      assessments or complex reference structures obviously require more effort to style and more
      care in authoring.</p>
    <p>The DOCX-to-DITA transform is intended primarily to handle the use case of getting materials
      from subject matter experts that is then converted to DITA as part of a one-time conversion
      activity. Because of the inherently fragile nature of this type of conversion (because of the
      lack of structural controls in word processing systems), the conversion is necessarily a
      hands-on activity, often requiring preparation of the word before the transform will work. The
      transform can be used in a batch manner, but only if the incoming Word is reliable and the
      batch process provides good error reporting and feedback when things go wrong. Fortunately,
      it's easy to validate the DITA result using, for example, the DITA Open Toolkit to try to
      generate HTML.</p>
  </conbody>
</concept>
