<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:shakespear:dtd:act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-1">
   <title>ACT I</title>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  Rome. A street.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter FLAVIUS, MARULLUS, and certain Commoners</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLAVIUS</speaker>
            <line>Hence! home, you idle creatures get you home:</line>
            <line>Is this a holiday? what! know you not,</line>
            <line>Being mechanical, you ought not walk</line>
            <line>Upon a labouring day without the sign</line>
            <line>Of your profession? Speak, what trade art thou?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Commoner</speaker>
            <line>Why, sir, a carpenter.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARULLUS</speaker>
            <line>Where is thy leather apron and thy rule?</line>
            <line>What dost thou with thy best apparel on?</line>
            <line>You, sir, what trade are you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Commoner</speaker>
            <line>Truly, sir, in respect of a fine workman, I am but,</line>
            <line>as you would say, a cobbler.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARULLUS</speaker>
            <line>But what trade art thou? answer me directly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Commoner</speaker>
            <line>A trade, sir, that, I hope, I may use with a safe</line>
            <line>conscience; which is, indeed, sir, a mender of bad soles.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARULLUS</speaker>
            <line>What trade, thou knave? thou naughty knave, what trade?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Commoner</speaker>
            <line>Nay, I beseech you, sir, be not out with me: yet,</line>
            <line>if you be out, sir, I can mend you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARULLUS</speaker>
            <line>What meanest thou by that? mend me, thou saucy fellow!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Commoner</speaker>
            <line>Why, sir, cobble you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLAVIUS</speaker>
            <line>Thou art a cobbler, art thou?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Commoner</speaker>
            <line>Truly, sir, all that I live by is with the awl: I</line>
            <line>meddle with no tradesman's matters, nor women's</line>
            <line>matters, but with awl. I am, indeed, sir, a surgeon</line>
            <line>to old shoes; when they are in great danger, I</line>
            <line>recover them. As proper men as ever trod upon</line>
            <line>neat's leather have gone upon my handiwork.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLAVIUS</speaker>
            <line>But wherefore art not in thy shop today?</line>
            <line>Why dost thou lead these men about the streets?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Commoner</speaker>
            <line>Truly, sir, to wear out their shoes, to get myself</line>
            <line>into more work. But, indeed, sir, we make holiday,</line>
            <line>to see Caesar and to rejoice in his triumph.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARULLUS</speaker>
            <line>Wherefore rejoice? What conquest brings he home?</line>
            <line>What tributaries follow him to Rome,</line>
            <line>To grace in captive bonds his chariot-wheels?</line>
            <line>You blocks, you stones, you worse than senseless things!</line>
            <line>O you hard hearts, you cruel men of Rome,</line>
            <line>Knew you not Pompey? Many a time and oft</line>
            <line>Have you climb'd up to walls and battlements,</line>
            <line>To towers and windows, yea, to chimney-tops,</line>
            <line>Your infants in your arms, and there have sat</line>
            <line>The livelong day, with patient expectation,</line>
            <line>To see great Pompey pass the streets of Rome:</line>
            <line>And when you saw his chariot but appear,</line>
            <line>Have you not made an universal shout,</line>
            <line>That Tiber trembled underneath her banks,</line>
            <line>To hear the replication of your sounds</line>
            <line>Made in her concave shores?</line>
            <line>And do you now put on your best attire?</line>
            <line>And do you now cull out a holiday?</line>
            <line>And do you now strew flowers in his way</line>
            <line>That comes in triumph over Pompey's blood? Be gone!</line>
            <line>Run to your houses, fall upon your knees,</line>
            <line>Pray to the gods to intermit the plague</line>
            <line>That needs must light on this ingratitude.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLAVIUS</speaker>
            <line>Go, go, good countrymen, and, for this fault,</line>
            <line>Assemble all the poor men of your sort;</line>
            <line>Draw them to Tiber banks, and weep your tears</line>
            <line>Into the channel, till the lowest stream</line>
            <line>Do kiss the most exalted shores of all.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt all the Commoners</stagedir>
            <line>See whether their basest metal be not moved;</line>
            <line>They vanish tongue-tied in their guiltiness.</line>
            <line>Go you down that way towards the Capitol;</line>
            <line>This way will I disrobe the images,</line>
            <line>If you do find them deck'd with ceremonies.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARULLUS</speaker>
            <line>May we do so?</line>
            <line>You know it is the feast of Lupercal.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLAVIUS</speaker>
            <line>It is no matter; let no images</line>
            <line>Be hung with Caesar's trophies. I'll about,</line>
            <line>And drive away the vulgar from the streets:</line>
            <line>So do you too, where you perceive them thick.</line>
            <line>These growing feathers pluck'd from Caesar's wing</line>
            <line>Will make him fly an ordinary pitch,</line>
            <line>Who else would soar above the view of men</line>
            <line>And keep us all in servile fearfulness.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  A public place.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Flourish. Enter CAESAR; ANTONY, for the course;
CALPURNIA, PORTIA, DECIUS BRUTUS, CICERO, BRUTUS,
CASSIUS, and CASCA; a great crowd following, among
them a Soothsayer</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAESAR</speaker>
            <line>Calpurnia!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASCA</speaker>
            <line>Peace, ho! Caesar speaks.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAESAR</speaker>
            <line>Calpurnia!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CALPURNIA</speaker>
            <line>Here, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAESAR</speaker>
            <line>Stand you directly in Antonius' way,</line>
            <line>When he doth run his course. Antonius!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONY</speaker>
            <line>Caesar, my lord?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAESAR</speaker>
            <line>Forget not, in your speed, Antonius,</line>
            <line>To touch Calpurnia; for our elders say,</line>
            <line>The barren, touched in this holy chase,</line>
            <line>Shake off their sterile curse.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONY</speaker>
            <line>I shall remember:</line>
            <line>When Caesar says 'do this,' it is perform'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAESAR</speaker>
            <line>Set on; and leave no ceremony out.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Flourish</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Soothsayer</speaker>
            <line>Caesar!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAESAR</speaker>
            <line>Ha! who calls?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASCA</speaker>
            <line>Bid every noise be still: peace yet again!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAESAR</speaker>
            <line>Who is it in the press that calls on me?</line>
            <line>I hear a tongue, shriller than all the music,</line>
            <line>Cry 'Caesar!' Speak; Caesar is turn'd to hear.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Soothsayer</speaker>
            <line>Beware the ides of March.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAESAR</speaker>
            <line>What man is that?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>A soothsayer bids you beware the ides of March.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAESAR</speaker>
            <line>Set him before me; let me see his face.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIUS</speaker>
            <line>Fellow, come from the throng; look upon Caesar.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAESAR</speaker>
            <line>What say'st thou to me now? speak once again.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Soothsayer</speaker>
            <line>Beware the ides of March.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAESAR</speaker>
            <line>He is a dreamer; let us leave him: pass.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Sennet. Exeunt all except BRUTUS and CASSIUS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIUS</speaker>
            <line>Will you go see the order of the course?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>Not I.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIUS</speaker>
            <line>I pray you, do.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>I am not gamesome: I do lack some part</line>
            <line>Of that quick spirit that is in Antony.</line>
            <line>Let me not hinder, Cassius, your desires;</line>
            <line>I'll leave you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIUS</speaker>
            <line>Brutus, I do observe you now of late:</line>
            <line>I have not from your eyes that gentleness</line>
            <line>And show of love as I was wont to have:</line>
            <line>You bear too stubborn and too strange a hand</line>
            <line>Over your friend that loves you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>Cassius,</line>
            <line>Be not deceived: if I have veil'd my look,</line>
            <line>I turn the trouble of my countenance</line>
            <line>Merely upon myself. Vexed I am</line>
            <line>Of late with passions of some difference,</line>
            <line>Conceptions only proper to myself,</line>
            <line>Which give some soil perhaps to my behaviors;</line>
            <line>But let not therefore my good friends be grieved--</line>
            <line>Among which number, Cassius, be you one--</line>
            <line>Nor construe any further my neglect,</line>
            <line>Than that poor Brutus, with himself at war,</line>
            <line>Forgets the shows of love to other men.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIUS</speaker>
            <line>Then, Brutus, I have much mistook your passion;</line>
            <line>By means whereof this breast of mine hath buried</line>
            <line>Thoughts of great value, worthy cogitations.</line>
            <line>Tell me, good Brutus, can you see your face?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>No, Cassius; for the eye sees not itself,</line>
            <line>But by reflection, by some other things.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIUS</speaker>
            <line>'Tis just:</line>
            <line>And it is very much lamented, Brutus,</line>
            <line>That you have no such mirrors as will turn</line>
            <line>Your hidden worthiness into your eye,</line>
            <line>That you might see your shadow. I have heard,</line>
            <line>Where many of the best respect in Rome,</line>
            <line>Except immortal Caesar, speaking of Brutus</line>
            <line>And groaning underneath this age's yoke,</line>
            <line>Have wish'd that noble Brutus had his eyes.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>Into what dangers would you lead me, Cassius,</line>
            <line>That you would have me seek into myself</line>
            <line>For that which is not in me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIUS</speaker>
            <line>Therefore, good Brutus, be prepared to hear:</line>
            <line>And since you know you cannot see yourself</line>
            <line>So well as by reflection, I, your glass,</line>
            <line>Will modestly discover to yourself</line>
            <line>That of yourself which you yet know not of.</line>
            <line>And be not jealous on me, gentle Brutus:</line>
            <line>Were I a common laugher, or did use</line>
            <line>To stale with ordinary oaths my love</line>
            <line>To every new protester; if you know</line>
            <line>That I do fawn on men and hug them hard</line>
            <line>And after scandal them, or if you know</line>
            <line>That I profess myself in banqueting</line>
            <line>To all the rout, then hold me dangerous.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Flourish, and shout</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>What means this shouting? I do fear, the people</line>
            <line>Choose Caesar for their king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIUS</speaker>
            <line>Ay, do you fear it?</line>
            <line>Then must I think you would not have it so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>I would not, Cassius; yet I love him well.</line>
            <line>But wherefore do you hold me here so long?</line>
            <line>What is it that you would impart to me?</line>
            <line>If it be aught toward the general good,</line>
            <line>Set honour in one eye and death i' the other,</line>
            <line>And I will look on both indifferently,</line>
            <line>For let the gods so speed me as I love</line>
            <line>The name of honour more than I fear death.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIUS</speaker>
            <line>I know that virtue to be in you, Brutus,</line>
            <line>As well as I do know your outward favour.</line>
            <line>Well, honour is the subject of my story.</line>
            <line>I cannot tell what you and other men</line>
            <line>Think of this life; but, for my single self,</line>
            <line>I had as lief not be as live to be</line>
            <line>In awe of such a thing as I myself.</line>
            <line>I was born free as Caesar; so were you:</line>
            <line>We both have fed as well, and we can both</line>
            <line>Endure the winter's cold as well as he:</line>
            <line>For once, upon a raw and gusty day,</line>
            <line>The troubled Tiber chafing with her shores,</line>
            <line>Caesar said to me 'Darest thou, Cassius, now</line>
            <line>Leap in with me into this angry flood,</line>
            <line>And swim to yonder point?' Upon the word,</line>
            <line>Accoutred as I was, I plunged in</line>
            <line>And bade him follow; so indeed he did.</line>
            <line>The torrent roar'd, and we did buffet it</line>
            <line>With lusty sinews, throwing it aside</line>
            <line>And stemming it with hearts of controversy;</line>
            <line>But ere we could arrive the point proposed,</line>
            <line>Caesar cried 'Help me, Cassius, or I sink!'</line>
            <line>I, as Aeneas, our great ancestor,</line>
            <line>Did from the flames of Troy upon his shoulder</line>
            <line>The old Anchises bear, so from the waves of Tiber</line>
            <line>Did I the tired Caesar. And this man</line>
            <line>Is now become a god, and Cassius is</line>
            <line>A wretched creature and must bend his body,</line>
            <line>If Caesar carelessly but nod on him.</line>
            <line>He had a fever when he was in Spain,</line>
            <line>And when the fit was on him, I did mark</line>
            <line>How he did shake: 'tis true, this god did shake;</line>
            <line>His coward lips did from their colour fly,</line>
            <line>And that same eye whose bend doth awe the world</line>
            <line>Did lose his lustre: I did hear him groan:</line>
            <line>Ay, and that tongue of his that bade the Romans</line>
            <line>Mark him and write his speeches in their books,</line>
            <line>Alas, it cried 'Give me some drink, Titinius,'</line>
            <line>As a sick girl. Ye gods, it doth amaze me</line>
            <line>A man of such a feeble temper should</line>
            <line>So get the start of the majestic world</line>
            <line>And bear the palm alone.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Shout. Flourish</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>Another general shout!</line>
            <line>I do believe that these applauses are</line>
            <line>For some new honours that are heap'd on Caesar.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIUS</speaker>
            <line>Why, man, he doth bestride the narrow world</line>
            <line>Like a Colossus, and we petty men</line>
            <line>Walk under his huge legs and peep about</line>
            <line>To find ourselves dishonourable graves.</line>
            <line>Men at some time are masters of their fates:</line>
            <line>The fault, dear Brutus, is not in our stars,</line>
            <line>But in ourselves, that we are underlings.</line>
            <line>Brutus and Caesar: what should be in that 'Caesar'?</line>
            <line>Why should that name be sounded more than yours?</line>
            <line>Write them together, yours is as fair a name;</line>
            <line>Sound them, it doth become the mouth as well;</line>
            <line>Weigh them, it is as heavy; conjure with 'em,</line>
            <line>Brutus will start a spirit as soon as Caesar.</line>
            <line>Now, in the names of all the gods at once,</line>
            <line>Upon what meat doth this our Caesar feed,</line>
            <line>That he is grown so great? Age, thou art shamed!</line>
            <line>Rome, thou hast lost the breed of noble bloods!</line>
            <line>When went there by an age, since the great flood,</line>
            <line>But it was famed with more than with one man?</line>
            <line>When could they say till now, that talk'd of Rome,</line>
            <line>That her wide walls encompass'd but one man?</line>
            <line>Now is it Rome indeed and room enough,</line>
            <line>When there is in it but one only man.</line>
            <line>O, you and I have heard our fathers say,</line>
            <line>There was a Brutus once that would have brook'd</line>
            <line>The eternal devil to keep his state in Rome</line>
            <line>As easily as a king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>That you do love me, I am nothing jealous;</line>
            <line>What you would work me to, I have some aim:</line>
            <line>How I have thought of this and of these times,</line>
            <line>I shall recount hereafter; for this present,</line>
            <line>I would not, so with love I might entreat you,</line>
            <line>Be any further moved. What you have said</line>
            <line>I will consider; what you have to say</line>
            <line>I will with patience hear, and find a time</line>
            <line>Both meet to hear and answer such high things.</line>
            <line>Till then, my noble friend, chew upon this:</line>
            <line>Brutus had rather be a villager</line>
            <line>Than to repute himself a son of Rome</line>
            <line>Under these hard conditions as this time</line>
            <line>Is like to lay upon us.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIUS</speaker>
            <line>I am glad that my weak words</line>
            <line>Have struck but thus much show of fire from Brutus.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>The games are done and Caesar is returning.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIUS</speaker>
            <line>As they pass by, pluck Casca by the sleeve;</line>
            <line>And he will, after his sour fashion, tell you</line>
            <line>What hath proceeded worthy note to-day.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter CAESAR and his Train</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>I will do so. But, look you, Cassius,</line>
            <line>The angry spot doth glow on Caesar's brow,</line>
            <line>And all the rest look like a chidden train:</line>
            <line>Calpurnia's cheek is pale; and Cicero</line>
            <line>Looks with such ferret and such fiery eyes</line>
            <line>As we have seen him in the Capitol,</line>
            <line>Being cross'd in conference by some senators.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIUS</speaker>
            <line>Casca will tell us what the matter is.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAESAR</speaker>
            <line>Antonius!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONY</speaker>
            <line>Caesar?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAESAR</speaker>
            <line>Let me have men about me that are fat;</line>
            <line>Sleek-headed men and such as sleep o' nights:</line>
            <line>Yond Cassius has a lean and hungry look;</line>
            <line>He thinks too much: such men are dangerous.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONY</speaker>
            <line>Fear him not, Caesar; he's not dangerous;</line>
            <line>He is a noble Roman and well given.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAESAR</speaker>
            <line>Would he were fatter! But I fear him not:</line>
            <line>Yet if my name were liable to fear,</line>
            <line>I do not know the man I should avoid</line>
            <line>So soon as that spare Cassius. He reads much;</line>
            <line>He is a great observer and he looks</line>
            <line>Quite through the deeds of men: he loves no plays,</line>
            <line>As thou dost, Antony; he hears no music;</line>
            <line>Seldom he smiles, and smiles in such a sort</line>
            <line>As if he mock'd himself and scorn'd his spirit</line>
            <line>That could be moved to smile at any thing.</line>
            <line>Such men as he be never at heart's ease</line>
            <line>Whiles they behold a greater than themselves,</line>
            <line>And therefore are they very dangerous.</line>
            <line>I rather tell thee what is to be fear'd</line>
            <line>Than what I fear; for always I am Caesar.</line>
            <line>Come on my right hand, for this ear is deaf,</line>
            <line>And tell me truly what thou think'st of him.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Sennet. Exeunt CAESAR and all his Train, but CASCA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASCA</speaker>
            <line>You pull'd me by the cloak; would you speak with me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>Ay, Casca; tell us what hath chanced to-day,</line>
            <line>That Caesar looks so sad.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASCA</speaker>
            <line>Why, you were with him, were you not?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>I should not then ask Casca what had chanced.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASCA</speaker>
            <line>Why, there was a crown offered him: and being</line>
            <line>offered him, he put it by with the back of his hand,</line>
            <line>thus; and then the people fell a-shouting.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>What was the second noise for?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASCA</speaker>
            <line>Why, for that too.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIUS</speaker>
            <line>They shouted thrice: what was the last cry for?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASCA</speaker>
            <line>Why, for that too.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>Was the crown offered him thrice?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASCA</speaker>
            <line>Ay, marry, was't, and he put it by thrice, every</line>
            <line>time gentler than other, and at every putting-by</line>
            <line>mine honest neighbours shouted.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIUS</speaker>
            <line>Who offered him the crown?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASCA</speaker>
            <line>Why, Antony.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>Tell us the manner of it, gentle Casca.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASCA</speaker>
            <line>I can as well be hanged as tell the manner of it:</line>
            <line>it was mere foolery; I did not mark it. I saw Mark</line>
            <line>Antony offer him a crown;--yet 'twas not a crown</line>
            <line>neither, 'twas one of these coronets;--and, as I told</line>
            <line>you, he put it by once: but, for all that, to my</line>
            <line>thinking, he would fain have had it. Then he</line>
            <line>offered it to him again; then he put it by again:</line>
            <line>but, to my thinking, he was very loath to lay his</line>
            <line>fingers off it. And then he offered it the third</line>
            <line>time; he put it the third time by: and still as he</line>
            <line>refused it, the rabblement hooted and clapped their</line>
            <line>chapped hands and threw up their sweaty night-caps</line>
            <line>and uttered such a deal of stinking breath because</line>
            <line>Caesar refused the crown that it had almost choked</line>
            <line>Caesar; for he swounded and fell down at it: and</line>
            <line>for mine own part, I durst not laugh, for fear of</line>
            <line>opening my lips and receiving the bad air.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIUS</speaker>
            <line>But, soft, I pray you: what, did Caesar swound?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASCA</speaker>
            <line>He fell down in the market-place, and foamed at</line>
            <line>mouth, and was speechless.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>'Tis very like: he hath the failing sickness.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIUS</speaker>
            <line>No, Caesar hath it not; but you and I,</line>
            <line>And honest Casca, we have the falling sickness.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASCA</speaker>
            <line>I know not what you mean by that; but, I am sure,</line>
            <line>Caesar fell down. If the tag-rag people did not</line>
            <line>clap him and hiss him, according as he pleased and</line>
            <line>displeased them, as they use to do the players in</line>
            <line>the theatre, I am no true man.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>What said he when he came unto himself?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASCA</speaker>
            <line>Marry, before he fell down, when he perceived the</line>
            <line>common herd was glad he refused the crown, he</line>
            <line>plucked me ope his doublet and offered them his</line>
            <line>throat to cut. An I had been a man of any</line>
            <line>occupation, if I would not have taken him at a word,</line>
            <line>I would I might go to hell among the rogues. And so</line>
            <line>he fell. When he came to himself again, he said,</line>
            <line>If he had done or said any thing amiss, he desired</line>
            <line>their worships to think it was his infirmity. Three</line>
            <line>or four wenches, where I stood, cried 'Alas, good</line>
            <line>soul!' and forgave him with all their hearts: but</line>
            <line>there's no heed to be taken of them; if Caesar had</line>
            <line>stabbed their mothers, they would have done no less.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>And after that, he came, thus sad, away?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASCA</speaker>
            <line>Ay.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIUS</speaker>
            <line>Did Cicero say any thing?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASCA</speaker>
            <line>Ay, he spoke Greek.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIUS</speaker>
            <line>To what effect?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASCA</speaker>
            <line>Nay, an I tell you that, Ill ne'er look you i' the</line>
            <line>face again: but those that understood him smiled at</line>
            <line>one another and shook their heads; but, for mine own</line>
            <line>part, it was Greek to me. I could tell you more</line>
            <line>news too: Marullus and Flavius, for pulling scarfs</line>
            <line>off Caesar's images, are put to silence. Fare you</line>
            <line>well. There was more foolery yet, if I could</line>
            <line>remember it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIUS</speaker>
            <line>Will you sup with me to-night, Casca?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASCA</speaker>
            <line>No, I am promised forth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIUS</speaker>
            <line>Will you dine with me to-morrow?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASCA</speaker>
            <line>Ay, if I be alive and your mind hold and your dinner</line>
            <line>worth the eating.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIUS</speaker>
            <line>Good: I will expect you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASCA</speaker>
            <line>Do so. Farewell, both.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>What a blunt fellow is this grown to be!</line>
            <line>He was quick mettle when he went to school.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIUS</speaker>
            <line>So is he now in execution</line>
            <line>Of any bold or noble enterprise,</line>
            <line>However he puts on this tardy form.</line>
            <line>This rudeness is a sauce to his good wit,</line>
            <line>Which gives men stomach to digest his words</line>
            <line>With better appetite.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>And so it is. For this time I will leave you:</line>
            <line>To-morrow, if you please to speak with me,</line>
            <line>I will come home to you; or, if you will,</line>
            <line>Come home to me, and I will wait for you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIUS</speaker>
            <line>I will do so: till then, think of the world.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit BRUTUS</stagedir>
            <line>Well, Brutus, thou art noble; yet, I see,</line>
            <line>Thy honourable metal may be wrought</line>
            <line>From that it is disposed: therefore it is meet</line>
            <line>That noble minds keep ever with their likes;</line>
            <line>For who so firm that cannot be seduced?</line>
            <line>Caesar doth bear me hard; but he loves Brutus:</line>
            <line>If I were Brutus now and he were Cassius,</line>
            <line>He should not humour me. I will this night,</line>
            <line>In several hands, in at his windows throw,</line>
            <line>As if they came from several citizens,</line>
            <line>Writings all tending to the great opinion</line>
            <line>That Rome holds of his name; wherein obscurely</line>
            <line>Caesar's ambition shall be glanced at:</line>
            <line>And after this let Caesar seat him sure;</line>
            <line>For we will shake him, or worse days endure.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  The same. A street.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Thunder and lightning. Enter from opposite sides,
CASCA, with his sword drawn, and CICERO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CICERO</speaker>
            <line>Good even, Casca: brought you Caesar home?</line>
            <line>Why are you breathless? and why stare you so?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASCA</speaker>
            <line>Are not you moved, when all the sway of earth</line>
            <line>Shakes like a thing unfirm? O Cicero,</line>
            <line>I have seen tempests, when the scolding winds</line>
            <line>Have rived the knotty oaks, and I have seen</line>
            <line>The ambitious ocean swell and rage and foam,</line>
            <line>To be exalted with the threatening clouds:</line>
            <line>But never till to-night, never till now,</line>
            <line>Did I go through a tempest dropping fire.</line>
            <line>Either there is a civil strife in heaven,</line>
            <line>Or else the world, too saucy with the gods,</line>
            <line>Incenses them to send destruction.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CICERO</speaker>
            <line>Why, saw you any thing more wonderful?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASCA</speaker>
            <line>A common slave--you know him well by sight--</line>
            <line>Held up his left hand, which did flame and burn</line>
            <line>Like twenty torches join'd, and yet his hand,</line>
            <line>Not sensible of fire, remain'd unscorch'd.</line>
            <line>Besides--I ha' not since put up my sword--</line>
            <line>Against the Capitol I met a lion,</line>
            <line>Who glared upon me, and went surly by,</line>
            <line>Without annoying me: and there were drawn</line>
            <line>Upon a heap a hundred ghastly women,</line>
            <line>Transformed with their fear; who swore they saw</line>
            <line>Men all in fire walk up and down the streets.</line>
            <line>And yesterday the bird of night did sit</line>
            <line>Even at noon-day upon the market-place,</line>
            <line>Hooting and shrieking. When these prodigies</line>
            <line>Do so conjointly meet, let not men say</line>
            <line>'These are their reasons; they are natural;'</line>
            <line>For, I believe, they are portentous things</line>
            <line>Unto the climate that they point upon.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CICERO</speaker>
            <line>Indeed, it is a strange-disposed time:</line>
            <line>But men may construe things after their fashion,</line>
            <line>Clean from the purpose of the things themselves.</line>
            <line>Come Caesar to the Capitol to-morrow?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASCA</speaker>
            <line>He doth; for he did bid Antonius</line>
            <line>Send word to you he would be there to-morrow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CICERO</speaker>
            <line>Good night then, Casca: this disturbed sky</line>
            <line>Is not to walk in.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASCA</speaker>
            <line>Farewell, Cicero.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit CICERO</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Enter CASSIUS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIUS</speaker>
            <line>Who's there?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASCA</speaker>
            <line>A Roman.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIUS</speaker>
            <line>Casca, by your voice.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASCA</speaker>
            <line>Your ear is good. Cassius, what night is this!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIUS</speaker>
            <line>A very pleasing night to honest men.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASCA</speaker>
            <line>Who ever knew the heavens menace so?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIUS</speaker>
            <line>Those that have known the earth so full of faults.</line>
            <line>For my part, I have walk'd about the streets,</line>
            <line>Submitting me unto the perilous night,</line>
            <line>And, thus unbraced, Casca, as you see,</line>
            <line>Have bared my bosom to the thunder-stone;</line>
            <line>And when the cross blue lightning seem'd to open</line>
            <line>The breast of heaven, I did present myself</line>
            <line>Even in the aim and very flash of it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASCA</speaker>
            <line>But wherefore did you so much tempt the heavens?</line>
            <line>It is the part of men to fear and tremble,</line>
            <line>When the most mighty gods by tokens send</line>
            <line>Such dreadful heralds to astonish us.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIUS</speaker>
            <line>You are dull, Casca, and those sparks of life</line>
            <line>That should be in a Roman you do want,</line>
            <line>Or else you use not. You look pale and gaze</line>
            <line>And put on fear and cast yourself in wonder,</line>
            <line>To see the strange impatience of the heavens:</line>
            <line>But if you would consider the true cause</line>
            <line>Why all these fires, why all these gliding ghosts,</line>
            <line>Why birds and beasts from quality and kind,</line>
            <line>Why old men fool and children calculate,</line>
            <line>Why all these things change from their ordinance</line>
            <line>Their natures and preformed faculties</line>
            <line>To monstrous quality,--why, you shall find</line>
            <line>That heaven hath infused them with these spirits,</line>
            <line>To make them instruments of fear and warning</line>
            <line>Unto some monstrous state.</line>
            <line>Now could I, Casca, name to thee a man</line>
            <line>Most like this dreadful night,</line>
            <line>That thunders, lightens, opens graves, and roars</line>
            <line>As doth the lion in the Capitol,</line>
            <line>A man no mightier than thyself or me</line>
            <line>In personal action, yet prodigious grown</line>
            <line>And fearful, as these strange eruptions are.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASCA</speaker>
            <line>'Tis Caesar that you mean; is it not, Cassius?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIUS</speaker>
            <line>Let it be who it is: for Romans now</line>
            <line>Have thews and limbs like to their ancestors;</line>
            <line>But, woe the while! our fathers' minds are dead,</line>
            <line>And we are govern'd with our mothers' spirits;</line>
            <line>Our yoke and sufferance show us womanish.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASCA</speaker>
            <line>Indeed, they say the senators tomorrow</line>
            <line>Mean to establish Caesar as a king;</line>
            <line>And he shall wear his crown by sea and land,</line>
            <line>In every place, save here in Italy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIUS</speaker>
            <line>I know where I will wear this dagger then;</line>
            <line>Cassius from bondage will deliver Cassius:</line>
            <line>Therein, ye gods, you make the weak most strong;</line>
            <line>Therein, ye gods, you tyrants do defeat:</line>
            <line>Nor stony tower, nor walls of beaten brass,</line>
            <line>Nor airless dungeon, nor strong links of iron,</line>
            <line>Can be retentive to the strength of spirit;</line>
            <line>But life, being weary of these worldly bars,</line>
            <line>Never lacks power to dismiss itself.</line>
            <line>If I know this, know all the world besides,</line>
            <line>That part of tyranny that I do bear</line>
            <line>I can shake off at pleasure.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Thunder still</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASCA</speaker>
            <line>So can I:</line>
            <line>So every bondman in his own hand bears</line>
            <line>The power to cancel his captivity.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIUS</speaker>
            <line>And why should Caesar be a tyrant then?</line>
            <line>Poor man! I know he would not be a wolf,</line>
            <line>But that he sees the Romans are but sheep:</line>
            <line>He were no lion, were not Romans hinds.</line>
            <line>Those that with haste will make a mighty fire</line>
            <line>Begin it with weak straws: what trash is Rome,</line>
            <line>What rubbish and what offal, when it serves</line>
            <line>For the base matter to illuminate</line>
            <line>So vile a thing as Caesar! But, O grief,</line>
            <line>Where hast thou led me? I perhaps speak this</line>
            <line>Before a willing bondman; then I know</line>
            <line>My answer must be made. But I am arm'd,</line>
            <line>And dangers are to me indifferent.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASCA</speaker>
            <line>You speak to Casca, and to such a man</line>
            <line>That is no fleering tell-tale. Hold, my hand:</line>
            <line>Be factious for redress of all these griefs,</line>
            <line>And I will set this foot of mine as far</line>
            <line>As who goes farthest.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIUS</speaker>
            <line>There's a bargain made.</line>
            <line>Now know you, Casca, I have moved already</line>
            <line>Some certain of the noblest-minded Romans</line>
            <line>To undergo with me an enterprise</line>
            <line>Of honourable-dangerous consequence;</line>
            <line>And I do know, by this, they stay for me</line>
            <line>In Pompey's porch: for now, this fearful night,</line>
            <line>There is no stir or walking in the streets;</line>
            <line>And the complexion of the element</line>
            <line>In favour's like the work we have in hand,</line>
            <line>Most bloody, fiery, and most terrible.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASCA</speaker>
            <line>Stand close awhile, for here comes one in haste.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIUS</speaker>
            <line>'Tis Cinna; I do know him by his gait;</line>
            <line>He is a friend.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter CINNA</stagedir>
            <line>Cinna, where haste you so?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CINNA</speaker>
            <line>To find out you. Who's that? Metellus Cimber?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIUS</speaker>
            <line>No, it is Casca; one incorporate</line>
            <line>To our attempts. Am I not stay'd for, Cinna?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CINNA</speaker>
            <line>I am glad on 't. What a fearful night is this!</line>
            <line>There's two or three of us have seen strange sights.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIUS</speaker>
            <line>Am I not stay'd for? tell me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CINNA</speaker>
            <line>Yes, you are.</line>
            <line>O Cassius, if you could</line>
            <line>But win the noble Brutus to our party--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIUS</speaker>
            <line>Be you content: good Cinna, take this paper,</line>
            <line>And look you lay it in the praetor's chair,</line>
            <line>Where Brutus may but find it; and throw this</line>
            <line>In at his window; set this up with wax</line>
            <line>Upon old Brutus' statue: all this done,</line>
            <line>Repair to Pompey's porch, where you shall find us.</line>
            <line>Is Decius Brutus and Trebonius there?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CINNA</speaker>
            <line>All but Metellus Cimber; and he's gone</line>
            <line>To seek you at your house. Well, I will hie,</line>
            <line>And so bestow these papers as you bade me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIUS</speaker>
            <line>That done, repair to Pompey's theatre.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit CINNA</stagedir>
            <line>Come, Casca, you and I will yet ere day</line>
            <line>See Brutus at his house: three parts of him</line>
            <line>Is ours already, and the man entire</line>
            <line>Upon the next encounter yields him ours.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASCA</speaker>
            <line>O, he sits high in all the people's hearts:</line>
            <line>And that which would appear offence in us,</line>
            <line>His countenance, like richest alchemy,</line>
            <line>Will change to virtue and to worthiness.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIUS</speaker>
            <line>Him and his worth and our great need of him</line>
            <line>You have right well conceited. Let us go,</line>
            <line>For it is after midnight; and ere day</line>
            <line>We will awake him and be sure of him.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>