<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:shakespear:dtd:act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-3">
   <title>ACT III</title>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  Rome. Before the Capitol; the Senate sitting above.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>A crowd of people; among them ARTEMIDORUS and the
Soothsayer. Flourish. Enter CAESAR, BRUTUS,
CASSIUS, CASCA, DECIUS BRUTUS, METELLUS CIMBER,
TREBONIUS, CINNA, ANTONY, LEPIDUS, POPILIUS,
PUBLIUS, and others</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAESAR</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>To the Soothsayer</stagedir>  The ides of March are come.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Soothsayer</speaker>
            <line>Ay, Caesar; but not gone.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARTEMIDORUS</speaker>
            <line>Hail, Caesar! read this schedule.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DECIUS BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>Trebonius doth desire you to o'erread,</line>
            <line>At your best leisure, this his humble suit.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARTEMIDORUS</speaker>
            <line>O Caesar, read mine first; for mine's a suit</line>
            <line>That touches Caesar nearer: read it, great Caesar.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAESAR</speaker>
            <line>What touches us ourself shall be last served.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARTEMIDORUS</speaker>
            <line>Delay not, Caesar; read it instantly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAESAR</speaker>
            <line>What, is the fellow mad?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PUBLIUS</speaker>
            <line>Sirrah, give place.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIUS</speaker>
            <line>What, urge you your petitions in the street?</line>
            <line>Come to the Capitol.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>CAESAR goes up to the Senate-House, the rest
following</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POPILIUS</speaker>
            <line>I wish your enterprise to-day may thrive.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIUS</speaker>
            <line>What enterprise, Popilius?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POPILIUS</speaker>
            <line>Fare you well.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Advances to CAESAR</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>What said Popilius Lena?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIUS</speaker>
            <line>He wish'd to-day our enterprise might thrive.</line>
            <line>I fear our purpose is discovered.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>Look, how he makes to Caesar; mark him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIUS</speaker>
            <line>Casca, be sudden, for we fear prevention.</line>
            <line>Brutus, what shall be done? If this be known,</line>
            <line>Cassius or Caesar never shall turn back,</line>
            <line>For I will slay myself.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>Cassius, be constant:</line>
            <line>Popilius Lena speaks not of our purposes;</line>
            <line>For, look, he smiles, and Caesar doth not change.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIUS</speaker>
            <line>Trebonius knows his time; for, look you, Brutus.</line>
            <line>He draws Mark Antony out of the way.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt ANTONY and TREBONIUS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DECIUS BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>Where is Metellus Cimber? Let him go,</line>
            <line>And presently prefer his suit to Caesar.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>He is address'd: press near and second him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CINNA</speaker>
            <line>Casca, you are the first that rears your hand.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAESAR</speaker>
            <line>Are we all ready? What is now amiss</line>
            <line>That Caesar and his senate must redress?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>METELLUS CIMBER</speaker>
            <line>Most high, most mighty, and most puissant Caesar,</line>
            <line>Metellus Cimber throws before thy seat</line>
            <line>An humble heart,--</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Kneeling</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAESAR</speaker>
            <line>I must prevent thee, Cimber.</line>
            <line>These couchings and these lowly courtesies</line>
            <line>Might fire the blood of ordinary men,</line>
            <line>And turn pre-ordinance and first decree</line>
            <line>Into the law of children. Be not fond,</line>
            <line>To think that Caesar bears such rebel blood</line>
            <line>That will be thaw'd from the true quality</line>
            <line>With that which melteth fools; I mean, sweet words,</line>
            <line>Low-crooked court'sies and base spaniel-fawning.</line>
            <line>Thy brother by decree is banished:</line>
            <line>If thou dost bend and pray and fawn for him,</line>
            <line>I spurn thee like a cur out of my way.</line>
            <line>Know, Caesar doth not wrong, nor without cause</line>
            <line>Will he be satisfied.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>METELLUS CIMBER</speaker>
            <line>Is there no voice more worthy than my own</line>
            <line>To sound more sweetly in great Caesar's ear</line>
            <line>For the repealing of my banish'd brother?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>I kiss thy hand, but not in flattery, Caesar;</line>
            <line>Desiring thee that Publius Cimber may</line>
            <line>Have an immediate freedom of repeal.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAESAR</speaker>
            <line>What, Brutus!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIUS</speaker>
            <line>Pardon, Caesar; Caesar, pardon:</line>
            <line>As low as to thy foot doth Cassius fall,</line>
            <line>To beg enfranchisement for Publius Cimber.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIUS</speaker>
            <line>I could be well moved, if I were as you:</line>
            <line>If I could pray to move, prayers would move me:</line>
            <line>But I am constant as the northern star,</line>
            <line>Of whose true-fix'd and resting quality</line>
            <line>There is no fellow in the firmament.</line>
            <line>The skies are painted with unnumber'd sparks,</line>
            <line>They are all fire and every one doth shine,</line>
            <line>But there's but one in all doth hold his place:</line>
            <line>So in the world; 'tis furnish'd well with men,</line>
            <line>And men are flesh and blood, and apprehensive;</line>
            <line>Yet in the number I do know but one</line>
            <line>That unassailable holds on his rank,</line>
            <line>Unshaked of motion: and that I am he,</line>
            <line>Let me a little show it, even in this;</line>
            <line>That I was constant Cimber should be banish'd,</line>
            <line>And constant do remain to keep him so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CINNA</speaker>
            <line>O Caesar,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAESAR</speaker>
            <line>Hence! wilt thou lift up Olympus?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DECIUS BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>Great Caesar,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAESAR</speaker>
            <line>Doth not Brutus bootless kneel?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASCA</speaker>
            <line>Speak, hands for me!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>CASCA first, then the other Conspirators and
BRUTUS stab CAESAR</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAESAR</speaker>
            <line>Et tu, Brute! Then fall, Caesar.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Dies</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CINNA</speaker>
            <line>Liberty! Freedom! Tyranny is dead!</line>
            <line>Run hence, proclaim, cry it about the streets.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIUS</speaker>
            <line>Some to the common pulpits, and cry out</line>
            <line>'Liberty, freedom, and enfranchisement!'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>People and senators, be not affrighted;</line>
            <line>Fly not; stand stiff: ambition's debt is paid.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASCA</speaker>
            <line>Go to the pulpit, Brutus.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DECIUS BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>And Cassius too.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>Where's Publius?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CINNA</speaker>
            <line>Here, quite confounded with this mutiny.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>METELLUS CIMBER</speaker>
            <line>Stand fast together, lest some friend of Caesar's</line>
            <line>Should chance--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>Talk not of standing. Publius, good cheer;</line>
            <line>There is no harm intended to your person,</line>
            <line>Nor to no Roman else: so tell them, Publius.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIUS</speaker>
            <line>And leave us, Publius; lest that the people,</line>
            <line>Rushing on us, should do your age some mischief.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>Do so: and let no man abide this deed,</line>
            <line>But we the doers.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter TREBONIUS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIUS</speaker>
            <line>Where is Antony?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TREBONIUS</speaker>
            <line>Fled to his house amazed:</line>
            <line>Men, wives and children stare, cry out and run</line>
            <line>As it were doomsday.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>Fates, we will know your pleasures:</line>
            <line>That we shall die, we know; 'tis but the time</line>
            <line>And drawing days out, that men stand upon.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIUS</speaker>
            <line>Why, he that cuts off twenty years of life</line>
            <line>Cuts off so many years of fearing death.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>Grant that, and then is death a benefit:</line>
            <line>So are we Caesar's friends, that have abridged</line>
            <line>His time of fearing death. Stoop, Romans, stoop,</line>
            <line>And let us bathe our hands in Caesar's blood</line>
            <line>Up to the elbows, and besmear our swords:</line>
            <line>Then walk we forth, even to the market-place,</line>
            <line>And, waving our red weapons o'er our heads,</line>
            <line>Let's all cry 'Peace, freedom and liberty!'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIUS</speaker>
            <line>Stoop, then, and wash. How many ages hence</line>
            <line>Shall this our lofty scene be acted over</line>
            <line>In states unborn and accents yet unknown!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>How many times shall Caesar bleed in sport,</line>
            <line>That now on Pompey's basis lies along</line>
            <line>No worthier than the dust!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIUS</speaker>
            <line>So oft as that shall be,</line>
            <line>So often shall the knot of us be call'd</line>
            <line>The men that gave their country liberty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DECIUS BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>What, shall we forth?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIUS</speaker>
            <line>Ay, every man away:</line>
            <line>Brutus shall lead; and we will grace his heels</line>
            <line>With the most boldest and best hearts of Rome.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter a Servant</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>Soft! who comes here? A friend of Antony's.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>Thus, Brutus, did my master bid me kneel:</line>
            <line>Thus did Mark Antony bid me fall down;</line>
            <line>And, being prostrate, thus he bade me say:</line>
            <line>Brutus is noble, wise, valiant, and honest;</line>
            <line>Caesar was mighty, bold, royal, and loving:</line>
            <line>Say I love Brutus, and I honour him;</line>
            <line>Say I fear'd Caesar, honour'd him and loved him.</line>
            <line>If Brutus will vouchsafe that Antony</line>
            <line>May safely come to him, and be resolved</line>
            <line>How Caesar hath deserved to lie in death,</line>
            <line>Mark Antony shall not love Caesar dead</line>
            <line>So well as Brutus living; but will follow</line>
            <line>The fortunes and affairs of noble Brutus</line>
            <line>Thorough the hazards of this untrod state</line>
            <line>With all true faith. So says my master Antony.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>Thy master is a wise and valiant Roman;</line>
            <line>I never thought him worse.</line>
            <line>Tell him, so please him come unto this place,</line>
            <line>He shall be satisfied; and, by my honour,</line>
            <line>Depart untouch'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>I'll fetch him presently.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>I know that we shall have him well to friend.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIUS</speaker>
            <line>I wish we may: but yet have I a mind</line>
            <line>That fears him much; and my misgiving still</line>
            <line>Falls shrewdly to the purpose.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>But here comes Antony.</line>
            <stagedir>Re-enter ANTONY</stagedir>
            <line>Welcome, Mark Antony.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONY</speaker>
            <line>O mighty Caesar! dost thou lie so low?</line>
            <line>Are all thy conquests, glories, triumphs, spoils,</line>
            <line>Shrunk to this little measure? Fare thee well.</line>
            <line>I know not, gentlemen, what you intend,</line>
            <line>Who else must be let blood, who else is rank:</line>
            <line>If I myself, there is no hour so fit</line>
            <line>As Caesar's death hour, nor no instrument</line>
            <line>Of half that worth as those your swords, made rich</line>
            <line>With the most noble blood of all this world.</line>
            <line>I do beseech ye, if you bear me hard,</line>
            <line>Now, whilst your purpled hands do reek and smoke,</line>
            <line>Fulfil your pleasure. Live a thousand years,</line>
            <line>I shall not find myself so apt to die:</line>
            <line>No place will please me so, no mean of death,</line>
            <line>As here by Caesar, and by you cut off,</line>
            <line>The choice and master spirits of this age.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>O Antony, beg not your death of us.</line>
            <line>Though now we must appear bloody and cruel,</line>
            <line>As, by our hands and this our present act,</line>
            <line>You see we do, yet see you but our hands</line>
            <line>And this the bleeding business they have done:</line>
            <line>Our hearts you see not; they are pitiful;</line>
            <line>And pity to the general wrong of Rome--</line>
            <line>As fire drives out fire, so pity pity--</line>
            <line>Hath done this deed on Caesar. For your part,</line>
            <line>To you our swords have leaden points, Mark Antony:</line>
            <line>Our arms, in strength of malice, and our hearts</line>
            <line>Of brothers' temper, do receive you in</line>
            <line>With all kind love, good thoughts, and reverence.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIUS</speaker>
            <line>Your voice shall be as strong as any man's</line>
            <line>In the disposing of new dignities.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>Only be patient till we have appeased</line>
            <line>The multitude, beside themselves with fear,</line>
            <line>And then we will deliver you the cause,</line>
            <line>Why I, that did love Caesar when I struck him,</line>
            <line>Have thus proceeded.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONY</speaker>
            <line>I doubt not of your wisdom.</line>
            <line>Let each man render me his bloody hand:</line>
            <line>First, Marcus Brutus, will I shake with you;</line>
            <line>Next, Caius Cassius, do I take your hand;</line>
            <line>Now, Decius Brutus, yours: now yours, Metellus;</line>
            <line>Yours, Cinna; and, my valiant Casca, yours;</line>
            <line>Though last, not last in love, yours, good Trebonius.</line>
            <line>Gentlemen all,--alas, what shall I say?</line>
            <line>My credit now stands on such slippery ground,</line>
            <line>That one of two bad ways you must conceit me,</line>
            <line>Either a coward or a flatterer.</line>
            <line>That I did love thee, Caesar, O, 'tis true:</line>
            <line>If then thy spirit look upon us now,</line>
            <line>Shall it not grieve thee dearer than thy death,</line>
            <line>To see thy thy Anthony making his peace,</line>
            <line>Shaking the bloody fingers of thy foes,</line>
            <line>Most noble! in the presence of thy corse?</line>
            <line>Had I as many eyes as thou hast wounds,</line>
            <line>Weeping as fast as they stream forth thy blood,</line>
            <line>It would become me better than to close</line>
            <line>In terms of friendship with thine enemies.</line>
            <line>Pardon me, Julius! Here wast thou bay'd, brave hart;</line>
            <line>Here didst thou fall; and here thy hunters stand,</line>
            <line>Sign'd in thy spoil, and crimson'd in thy lethe.</line>
            <line>O world, thou wast the forest to this hart;</line>
            <line>And this, indeed, O world, the heart of thee.</line>
            <line>How like a deer, strucken by many princes,</line>
            <line>Dost thou here lie!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIUS</speaker>
            <line>Mark Antony,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONY</speaker>
            <line>Pardon me, Caius Cassius:</line>
            <line>The enemies of Caesar shall say this;</line>
            <line>Then, in a friend, it is cold modesty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIUS</speaker>
            <line>I blame you not for praising Caesar so;</line>
            <line>But what compact mean you to have with us?</line>
            <line>Will you be prick'd in number of our friends;</line>
            <line>Or shall we on, and not depend on you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONY</speaker>
            <line>Therefore I took your hands, but was, indeed,</line>
            <line>Sway'd from the point, by looking down on Caesar.</line>
            <line>Friends am I with you all and love you all,</line>
            <line>Upon this hope, that you shall give me reasons</line>
            <line>Why and wherein Caesar was dangerous.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>Or else were this a savage spectacle:</line>
            <line>Our reasons are so full of good regard</line>
            <line>That were you, Antony, the son of Caesar,</line>
            <line>You should be satisfied.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONY</speaker>
            <line>That's all I seek:</line>
            <line>And am moreover suitor that I may</line>
            <line>Produce his body to the market-place;</line>
            <line>And in the pulpit, as becomes a friend,</line>
            <line>Speak in the order of his funeral.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>You shall, Mark Antony.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIUS</speaker>
            <line>Brutus, a word with you.</line>
            <stagedir>Aside to BRUTUS</stagedir>
            <line>You know not what you do: do not consent</line>
            <line>That Antony speak in his funeral:</line>
            <line>Know you how much the people may be moved</line>
            <line>By that which he will utter?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>By your pardon;</line>
            <line>I will myself into the pulpit first,</line>
            <line>And show the reason of our Caesar's death:</line>
            <line>What Antony shall speak, I will protest</line>
            <line>He speaks by leave and by permission,</line>
            <line>And that we are contented Caesar shall</line>
            <line>Have all true rites and lawful ceremonies.</line>
            <line>It shall advantage more than do us wrong.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIUS</speaker>
            <line>I know not what may fall; I like it not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>Mark Antony, here, take you Caesar's body.</line>
            <line>You shall not in your funeral speech blame us,</line>
            <line>But speak all good you can devise of Caesar,</line>
            <line>And say you do't by our permission;</line>
            <line>Else shall you not have any hand at all</line>
            <line>About his funeral: and you shall speak</line>
            <line>In the same pulpit whereto I am going,</line>
            <line>After my speech is ended.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONY</speaker>
            <line>Be it so.</line>
            <line>I do desire no more.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>Prepare the body then, and follow us.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt all but ANTONY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONY</speaker>
            <line>O, pardon me, thou bleeding piece of earth,</line>
            <line>That I am meek and gentle with these butchers!</line>
            <line>Thou art the ruins of the noblest man</line>
            <line>That ever lived in the tide of times.</line>
            <line>Woe to the hand that shed this costly blood!</line>
            <line>Over thy wounds now do I prophesy,--</line>
            <line>Which, like dumb mouths, do ope their ruby lips,</line>
            <line>To beg the voice and utterance of my tongue--</line>
            <line>A curse shall light upon the limbs of men;</line>
            <line>Domestic fury and fierce civil strife</line>
            <line>Shall cumber all the parts of Italy;</line>
            <line>Blood and destruction shall be so in use</line>
            <line>And dreadful objects so familiar</line>
            <line>That mothers shall but smile when they behold</line>
            <line>Their infants quarter'd with the hands of war;</line>
            <line>All pity choked with custom of fell deeds:</line>
            <line>And Caesar's spirit, ranging for revenge,</line>
            <line>With Ate by his side come hot from hell,</line>
            <line>Shall in these confines with a monarch's voice</line>
            <line>Cry  'Havoc,' and let slip the dogs of war;</line>
            <line>That this foul deed shall smell above the earth</line>
            <line>With carrion men, groaning for burial.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter a Servant</stagedir>
            <line>You serve Octavius Caesar, do you not?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>I do, Mark Antony.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONY</speaker>
            <line>Caesar did write for him to come to Rome.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>He did receive his letters, and is coming;</line>
            <line>And bid me say to you by word of mouth--</line>
            <line>O Caesar!--</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Seeing the body</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONY</speaker>
            <line>Thy heart is big, get thee apart and weep.</line>
            <line>Passion, I see, is catching; for mine eyes,</line>
            <line>Seeing those beads of sorrow stand in thine,</line>
            <line>Began to water. Is thy master coming?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>He lies to-night within seven leagues of Rome.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONY</speaker>
            <line>Post back with speed, and tell him what hath chanced:</line>
            <line>Here is a mourning Rome, a dangerous Rome,</line>
            <line>No Rome of safety for Octavius yet;</line>
            <line>Hie hence, and tell him so. Yet, stay awhile;</line>
            <line>Thou shalt not back till I have borne this corse</line>
            <line>Into the market-place: there shall I try</line>
            <line>In my oration, how the people take</line>
            <line>The cruel issue of these bloody men;</line>
            <line>According to the which, thou shalt discourse</line>
            <line>To young Octavius of the state of things.</line>
            <line>Lend me your hand.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt with CAESAR's body</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  The Forum.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter BRUTUS and CASSIUS, and a throng of Citizens</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Citizens</speaker>
            <line>We will be satisfied; let us be satisfied.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>Then follow me, and give me audience, friends.</line>
            <line>Cassius, go you into the other street,</line>
            <line>And part the numbers.</line>
            <line>Those that will hear me speak, let 'em stay here;</line>
            <line>Those that will follow Cassius, go with him;</line>
            <line>And public reasons shall be rendered</line>
            <line>Of Caesar's death.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>I will hear Brutus speak.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Citizen</speaker>
            <line>I will hear Cassius; and compare their reasons,</line>
            <line>When severally we hear them rendered.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit CASSIUS, with some of the Citizens. BRUTUS
goes into the pulpit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Citizen</speaker>
            <line>The noble Brutus is ascended: silence!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>Be patient till the last.</line>
            <line>Romans, countrymen, and lovers! hear me for my</line>
            <line>cause, and be silent, that you may hear: believe me</line>
            <line>for mine honour, and have respect to mine honour, that</line>
            <line>you may believe: censure me in your wisdom, and</line>
            <line>awake your senses, that you may the better judge.</line>
            <line>If there be any in this assembly, any dear friend of</line>
            <line>Caesar's, to him I say, that Brutus' love to Caesar</line>
            <line>was no less than his. If then that friend demand</line>
            <line>why Brutus rose against Caesar, this is my answer:</line>
            <line>--Not that I loved Caesar less, but that I loved</line>
            <line>Rome more. Had you rather Caesar were living and</line>
            <line>die all slaves, than that Caesar were dead, to live</line>
            <line>all free men? As Caesar loved me, I weep for him;</line>
            <line>as he was fortunate, I rejoice at it; as he was</line>
            <line>valiant, I honour him: but, as he was ambitious, I</line>
            <line>slew him. There is tears for his love; joy for his</line>
            <line>fortune; honour for his valour; and death for his</line>
            <line>ambition. Who is here so base that would be a</line>
            <line>bondman? If any, speak; for him have I offended.</line>
            <line>Who is here so rude that would not be a Roman? If</line>
            <line>any, speak; for him have I offended. Who is here so</line>
            <line>vile that will not love his country? If any, speak;</line>
            <line>for him have I offended. I pause for a reply.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>All</speaker>
            <line>None, Brutus, none.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>Then none have I offended. I have done no more to</line>
            <line>Caesar than you shall do to Brutus. The question of</line>
            <line>his death is enrolled in the Capitol; his glory not</line>
            <line>extenuated, wherein he was worthy, nor his offences</line>
            <line>enforced, for which he suffered death.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter ANTONY and others, with CAESAR's body</stagedir>
            <line>Here comes his body, mourned by Mark Antony: who,</line>
            <line>though he had no hand in his death, shall receive</line>
            <line>the benefit of his dying, a place in the</line>
            <line>commonwealth; as which of you shall not? With this</line>
            <line>I depart,--that, as I slew my best lover for the</line>
            <line>good of Rome, I have the same dagger for myself,</line>
            <line>when it shall please my country to need my death.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>All</speaker>
            <line>Live, Brutus! live, live!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Bring him with triumph home unto his house.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Give him a statue with his ancestors.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Let him be Caesar.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fourth Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Caesar's better parts</line>
            <line>Shall be crown'd in Brutus.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>We'll bring him to his house</line>
            <line>With shouts and clamours.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>My countrymen,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Peace, silence! Brutus speaks.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Peace, ho!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRUTUS</speaker>
            <line>Good countrymen, let me depart alone,</line>
            <line>And, for my sake, stay here with Antony:</line>
            <line>Do grace to Caesar's corpse, and grace his speech</line>
            <line>Tending to Caesar's glories; which Mark Antony,</line>
            <line>By our permission, is allow'd to make.</line>
            <line>I do entreat you, not a man depart,</line>
            <line>Save I alone, till Antony have spoke.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Stay, ho! and let us hear Mark Antony.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Let him go up into the public chair;</line>
            <line>We'll hear him. Noble Antony, go up.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONY</speaker>
            <line>For Brutus' sake, I am beholding to you.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Goes into the pulpit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fourth Citizen</speaker>
            <line>What does he say of Brutus?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Citizen</speaker>
            <line>He says, for Brutus' sake,</line>
            <line>He finds himself beholding to us all.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fourth Citizen</speaker>
            <line>'Twere best he speak no harm of Brutus here.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>This Caesar was a tyrant.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Nay, that's certain:</line>
            <line>We are blest that Rome is rid of him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Peace! let us hear what Antony can say.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONY</speaker>
            <line>You gentle Romans,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Citizens</speaker>
            <line>Peace, ho! let us hear him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONY</speaker>
            <line>Friends, Romans, countrymen, lend me your ears;</line>
            <line>I come to bury Caesar, not to praise him.</line>
            <line>The evil that men do lives after them;</line>
            <line>The good is oft interred with their bones;</line>
            <line>So let it be with Caesar. The noble Brutus</line>
            <line>Hath told you Caesar was ambitious:</line>
            <line>If it were so, it was a grievous fault,</line>
            <line>And grievously hath Caesar answer'd it.</line>
            <line>Here, under leave of Brutus and the rest--</line>
            <line>For Brutus is an honourable man;</line>
            <line>So are they all, all honourable men--</line>
            <line>Come I to speak in Caesar's funeral.</line>
            <line>He was my friend, faithful and just to me:</line>
            <line>But Brutus says he was ambitious;</line>
            <line>And Brutus is an honourable man.</line>
            <line>He hath brought many captives home to Rome</line>
            <line>Whose ransoms did the general coffers fill:</line>
            <line>Did this in Caesar seem ambitious?</line>
            <line>When that the poor have cried, Caesar hath wept:</line>
            <line>Ambition should be made of sterner stuff:</line>
            <line>Yet Brutus says he was ambitious;</line>
            <line>And Brutus is an honourable man.</line>
            <line>You all did see that on the Lupercal</line>
            <line>I thrice presented him a kingly crown,</line>
            <line>Which he did thrice refuse: was this ambition?</line>
            <line>Yet Brutus says he was ambitious;</line>
            <line>And, sure, he is an honourable man.</line>
            <line>I speak not to disprove what Brutus spoke,</line>
            <line>But here I am to speak what I do know.</line>
            <line>You all did love him once, not without cause:</line>
            <line>What cause withholds you then, to mourn for him?</line>
            <line>O judgment! thou art fled to brutish beasts,</line>
            <line>And men have lost their reason. Bear with me;</line>
            <line>My heart is in the coffin there with Caesar,</line>
            <line>And I must pause till it come back to me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Methinks there is much reason in his sayings.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Citizen</speaker>
            <line>If thou consider rightly of the matter,</line>
            <line>Caesar has had great wrong.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Has he, masters?</line>
            <line>I fear there will a worse come in his place.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fourth Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Mark'd ye his words? He would not take the crown;</line>
            <line>Therefore 'tis certain he was not ambitious.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>If it be found so, some will dear abide it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Poor soul! his eyes are red as fire with weeping.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Citizen</speaker>
            <line>There's not a nobler man in Rome than Antony.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fourth Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Now mark him, he begins again to speak.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONY</speaker>
            <line>But yesterday the word of Caesar might</line>
            <line>Have stood against the world; now lies he there.</line>
            <line>And none so poor to do him reverence.</line>
            <line>O masters, if I were disposed to stir</line>
            <line>Your hearts and minds to mutiny and rage,</line>
            <line>I should do Brutus wrong, and Cassius wrong,</line>
            <line>Who, you all know, are honourable men:</line>
            <line>I will not do them wrong; I rather choose</line>
            <line>To wrong the dead, to wrong myself and you,</line>
            <line>Than I will wrong such honourable men.</line>
            <line>But here's a parchment with the seal of Caesar;</line>
            <line>I found it in his closet, 'tis his will:</line>
            <line>Let but the commons hear this testament--</line>
            <line>Which, pardon me, I do not mean to read--</line>
            <line>And they would go and kiss dead Caesar's wounds</line>
            <line>And dip their napkins in his sacred blood,</line>
            <line>Yea, beg a hair of him for memory,</line>
            <line>And, dying, mention it within their wills,</line>
            <line>Bequeathing it as a rich legacy</line>
            <line>Unto their issue.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fourth Citizen</speaker>
            <line>We'll hear the will: read it, Mark Antony.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>All</speaker>
            <line>The will, the will! we will hear Caesar's will.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONY</speaker>
            <line>Have patience, gentle friends, I must not read it;</line>
            <line>It is not meet you know how Caesar loved you.</line>
            <line>You are not wood, you are not stones, but men;</line>
            <line>And, being men, bearing the will of Caesar,</line>
            <line>It will inflame you, it will make you mad:</line>
            <line>'Tis good you know not that you are his heirs;</line>
            <line>For, if you should, O, what would come of it!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fourth Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Read the will; we'll hear it, Antony;</line>
            <line>You shall read us the will, Caesar's will.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONY</speaker>
            <line>Will you be patient? will you stay awhile?</line>
            <line>I have o'ershot myself to tell you of it:</line>
            <line>I fear I wrong the honourable men</line>
            <line>Whose daggers have stabb'd Caesar; I do fear it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fourth Citizen</speaker>
            <line>They were traitors: honourable men!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>All</speaker>
            <line>The will! the testament!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Citizen</speaker>
            <line>They were villains, murderers: the will! read the will.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONY</speaker>
            <line>You will compel me, then, to read the will?</line>
            <line>Then make a ring about the corpse of Caesar,</line>
            <line>And let me show you him that made the will.</line>
            <line>Shall I descend? and will you give me leave?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Several Citizens</speaker>
            <line>Come down.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Descend.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Citizen</speaker>
            <line>You shall have leave.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>ANTONY comes down</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fourth Citizen</speaker>
            <line>A ring; stand round.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Stand from the hearse, stand from the body.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Room for Antony, most noble Antony.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONY</speaker>
            <line>Nay, press not so upon me; stand far off.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Several Citizens</speaker>
            <line>Stand back; room; bear back.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONY</speaker>
            <line>If you have tears, prepare to shed them now.</line>
            <line>You all do know this mantle: I remember</line>
            <line>The first time ever Caesar put it on;</line>
            <line>'Twas on a summer's evening, in his tent,</line>
            <line>That day he overcame the Nervii:</line>
            <line>Look, in this place ran Cassius' dagger through:</line>
            <line>See what a rent the envious Casca made:</line>
            <line>Through this the well-beloved Brutus stabb'd;</line>
            <line>And as he pluck'd his cursed steel away,</line>
            <line>Mark how the blood of Caesar follow'd it,</line>
            <line>As rushing out of doors, to be resolved</line>
            <line>If Brutus so unkindly knock'd, or no;</line>
            <line>For Brutus, as you know, was Caesar's angel:</line>
            <line>Judge, O you gods, how dearly Caesar loved him!</line>
            <line>This was the most unkindest cut of all;</line>
            <line>For when the noble Caesar saw him stab,</line>
            <line>Ingratitude, more strong than traitors' arms,</line>
            <line>Quite vanquish'd him: then burst his mighty heart;</line>
            <line>And, in his mantle muffling up his face,</line>
            <line>Even at the base of Pompey's statua,</line>
            <line>Which all the while ran blood, great Caesar fell.</line>
            <line>O, what a fall was there, my countrymen!</line>
            <line>Then I, and you, and all of us fell down,</line>
            <line>Whilst bloody treason flourish'd over us.</line>
            <line>O, now you weep; and, I perceive, you feel</line>
            <line>The dint of pity: these are gracious drops.</line>
            <line>Kind souls, what, weep you when you but behold</line>
            <line>Our Caesar's vesture wounded? Look you here,</line>
            <line>Here is himself, marr'd, as you see, with traitors.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>O piteous spectacle!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Citizen</speaker>
            <line>O noble Caesar!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Citizen</speaker>
            <line>O woful day!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fourth Citizen</speaker>
            <line>O traitors, villains!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>O most bloody sight!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Citizen</speaker>
            <line>We will be revenged.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>All</speaker>
            <line>Revenge! About! Seek! Burn! Fire! Kill! Slay!</line>
            <line>Let not a traitor live!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONY</speaker>
            <line>Stay, countrymen.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Peace there! hear the noble Antony.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Citizen</speaker>
            <line>We'll hear him, we'll follow him, we'll die with him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONY</speaker>
            <line>Good friends, sweet friends, let me not stir you up</line>
            <line>To such a sudden flood of mutiny.</line>
            <line>They that have done this deed are honourable:</line>
            <line>What private griefs they have, alas, I know not,</line>
            <line>That made them do it: they are wise and honourable,</line>
            <line>And will, no doubt, with reasons answer you.</line>
            <line>I come not, friends, to steal away your hearts:</line>
            <line>I am no orator, as Brutus is;</line>
            <line>But, as you know me all, a plain blunt man,</line>
            <line>That love my friend; and that they know full well</line>
            <line>That gave me public leave to speak of him:</line>
            <line>For I have neither wit, nor words, nor worth,</line>
            <line>Action, nor utterance, nor the power of speech,</line>
            <line>To stir men's blood: I only speak right on;</line>
            <line>I tell you that which you yourselves do know;</line>
            <line>Show you sweet Caesar's wounds, poor poor dumb mouths,</line>
            <line>And bid them speak for me: but were I Brutus,</line>
            <line>And Brutus Antony, there were an Antony</line>
            <line>Would ruffle up your spirits and put a tongue</line>
            <line>In every wound of Caesar that should move</line>
            <line>The stones of Rome to rise and mutiny.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>All</speaker>
            <line>We'll mutiny.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>We'll burn the house of Brutus.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Away, then! come, seek the conspirators.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONY</speaker>
            <line>Yet hear me, countrymen; yet hear me speak.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>All</speaker>
            <line>Peace, ho! Hear Antony. Most noble Antony!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONY</speaker>
            <line>Why, friends, you go to do you know not what:</line>
            <line>Wherein hath Caesar thus deserved your loves?</line>
            <line>Alas, you know not: I must tell you then:</line>
            <line>You have forgot the will I told you of.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>All</speaker>
            <line>Most true. The will! Let's stay and hear the will.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONY</speaker>
            <line>Here is the will, and under Caesar's seal.</line>
            <line>To every Roman citizen he gives,</line>
            <line>To every several man, seventy-five drachmas.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Most noble Caesar! We'll revenge his death.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Citizen</speaker>
            <line>O royal Caesar!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONY</speaker>
            <line>Hear me with patience.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>All</speaker>
            <line>Peace, ho!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONY</speaker>
            <line>Moreover, he hath left you all his walks,</line>
            <line>His private arbours and new-planted orchards,</line>
            <line>On this side Tiber; he hath left them you,</line>
            <line>And to your heirs for ever, common pleasures,</line>
            <line>To walk abroad, and recreate yourselves.</line>
            <line>Here was a Caesar! when comes such another?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Never, never. Come, away, away!</line>
            <line>We'll burn his body in the holy place,</line>
            <line>And with the brands fire the traitors' houses.</line>
            <line>Take up the body.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Go fetch fire.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Pluck down benches.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fourth Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Pluck down forms, windows, any thing.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt Citizens with the body</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONY</speaker>
            <line>Now let it work. Mischief, thou art afoot,</line>
            <line>Take thou what course thou wilt!</line>
            <stagedir>Enter a Servant</stagedir>
            <line>How now, fellow!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>Sir, Octavius is already come to Rome.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONY</speaker>
            <line>Where is he?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>He and Lepidus are at Caesar's house.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONY</speaker>
            <line>And thither will I straight to visit him:</line>
            <line>He comes upon a wish. Fortune is merry,</line>
            <line>And in this mood will give us any thing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>I heard him say, Brutus and Cassius</line>
            <line>Are rid like madmen through the gates of Rome.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONY</speaker>
            <line>Belike they had some notice of the people,</line>
            <line>How I had moved them. Bring me to Octavius.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  A street.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter CINNA the poet</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CINNA THE POET</speaker>
            <line>I dreamt to-night that I did feast with Caesar,</line>
            <line>And things unlucky charge my fantasy:</line>
            <line>I have no will to wander forth of doors,</line>
            <line>Yet something leads me forth.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter Citizens</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>What is your name?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Whither are you going?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Where do you dwell?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fourth Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Are you a married man or a bachelor?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Answer every man directly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Ay, and briefly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fourth Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Ay, and wisely.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Ay, and truly, you were best.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CINNA THE POET</speaker>
            <line>What is my name? Whither am I going? Where do I</line>
            <line>dwell? Am I a married man or a bachelor? Then, to</line>
            <line>answer every man directly and briefly, wisely and</line>
            <line>truly: wisely I say, I am a bachelor.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Citizen</speaker>
            <line>That's as much as to say, they are fools that marry:</line>
            <line>you'll bear me a bang for that, I fear. Proceed; directly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CINNA THE POET</speaker>
            <line>Directly, I am going to Caesar's funeral.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>As a friend or an enemy?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CINNA THE POET</speaker>
            <line>As a friend.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Citizen</speaker>
            <line>That matter is answered directly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fourth Citizen</speaker>
            <line>For your dwelling,--briefly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CINNA THE POET</speaker>
            <line>Briefly, I dwell by the Capitol.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Your name, sir, truly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CINNA THE POET</speaker>
            <line>Truly, my name is Cinna.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Tear him to pieces; he's a conspirator.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CINNA THE POET</speaker>
            <line>I am Cinna the poet, I am Cinna the poet.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fourth Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Tear him for his bad verses, tear him for his bad verses.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CINNA THE POET</speaker>
            <line>I am not Cinna the conspirator.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fourth Citizen</speaker>
            <line>It is no matter, his name's Cinna; pluck but his</line>
            <line>name out of his heart, and turn him going.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Tear him, tear him! Come, brands ho! fire-brands:</line>
            <line>to Brutus', to Cassius'; burn all: some to Decius'</line>
            <line>house, and some to Casca's; some to Ligarius': away, go!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>