<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<chapter id="d5e2"><title>Commenting and Connecting with Users</title><prolog/><body><p><image href="../images/chapter05.png" id="image_ecd21818-dc5f-474d-b0ac-c989b7db7115" width="5in" placement="inline"/></p><epigram>The biggest mistake is believing there is one right way to listen, <br/>to talk, to
      have a conversation - or a relationship. <br/>—Deborah Tannen</epigram><epigram>It was impossible to get a conversation going, <br/>everybody was talking too much.<br/>—Yogi Berra</epigram><p>There are new social computing tools being invented all the time, and traditional websites
      are also finding ways to incorporate tagging, sharing, and other collaboration helpers in
      their content. <indexterm>conversations<indexterm>blogs</indexterm></indexterm>Blogs have led
      the way. <indexterm>blogs<indexterm>description of</indexterm></indexterm>Blogs, short for
      weblogs, are websites with reverse chronological entries (listing them from newest to oldest).
      Topics range from personal to professional, offering galleries of photography or comics, and
      can be written, audio, or video entries. </p><p>When <indexterm>content<indexterm>blogs</indexterm></indexterm>blogging, realize first and
      foremost that a conversation doesn’t have to be a direct connection between writer and
      customer. You can blog about your area of expertise which shows the customer your passion for
      your work, which translates into high quality products or services from you when representing
      your company on a blog. A blog entry can offer a link opportunity for a customer to connect to
      you. </p><p>Also think about how you can help customers connect with each other in comments or in
      trackbacks, which notify the original blog author that you have linked to a particular entry.
      This section discusses ideas for starting conversations, building on the stages of listening,
      participating, and offering a platform. </p></body></chapter>
