<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE learningContent
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Learning Content//EN" "learningContent.dtd">
<learningContent id="SEC006_003">
   <title>6.3 Anisotropies in the Universe itself</title>
   <learningContentbody>
      <section>
          
          <p>Having subtracted the dipolar anisotropy due to the motion of the Earth
            relative to the 3 K radiation, we are left with radiation that is exceedingly isotropic.
            So, we have to ask whether there are any residual variations that would point to a
            departure from isotropy of the radiation <i>itself</i>? This is a crucial question.
            Although it was gratifying to have the radiation so isotropic that there could be little
            doubt of its cosmic origins, nevertheless a <i>completely</i> isotropic distribution
            would bring troubles of its own.</p>
          <p>The reason for this is that, although the <i>matter</i> distribution is
            isotropic on a large enough scale, it is clearly not so on smaller scales. It is clumped
            together in galaxies, the galaxies are preferentially to be found in clusters of
            galaxies, and even the clusters are loosely associated in superclusters. In fact, the
            matter distribution somewhat resembles a gigantic sponge; it has enormous holes in it,
            with the superclusters arranged around the boundaries of these voids. Presumably this
            distribution came about as a result of inhomogeneities in the original distribution of
            matter coming from the big bang. If a particular region happened to have by chance a
            somewhat greater density of matter than its neighbours, its increased gravity would tend
            to attract matter away from the less densely populated regions and towards itself. This
            would enhance the inhomogeneity, leading to this particular region gaining an even
            stronger pulling power, and attracting yet more material to itself. The initial
            inhomogeneities, which in themselves may have been slight, would over the course of time
            have become magnified.</p>
          <p>That is thought to be the process whereby we have our present-day distribution.
            Having said that, it is not at all clear yet in what order the hierarchy of structures
            formed. Perhaps the matter first assembled to form superclusters; these then broke down
            into their component clusters, which in their turn later separated out into galaxies.
            Finally, the individual stars condensed. Alternatively it could all have happened the
            opposite way round, with stars forming first, these being attracted into galaxies, which
            later gathered into clusters and superclusters. Or indeed it could have been some other
            mix of aspects drawn from both these scenarios. But whichever was the correct sequence
            of events, one thing is clear: there had to be density inhomogeneities on some scale or
            other.</p>
          <p>From this we infer that there should also be anisotropies in the 3 K radiation.
            The reason is that when gas collects together and is squashed down by its mutual
            gravity, potential energy is converted into kinetic energy leading to a temperature
            rise. It is such temperature increases that can ignite nuclear reactions and result in
            the birth of a new star (assuming sufficient gas has been collected originally). Gas
            collecting to form a primordial galaxy or a cluster of galaxies will similarly undergo a
            temperature rise, this rise being reflected in the type of radiation it emits. The
            angular distribution of this radiation, as we receive it today, should show a degree of
            anisotropy because it originates in matter that was not itself entirely homogeneous.
            Inhomogeneities must have already been present in matter when it was emitting what is
            now the 3 K radiation. Thus we should expect the 3 K radiation to manifest some degree
            of anisotropy; it should <i>not</i> be wholly uniform.</p>
          <p>This is not to say that we should necessarily expect to detect ‘hot
            spots’. The situation is somewhat more subtle than that. We have to recall that
            when we are dealing with galaxies or with clusters, a great deal of matter is involved.
            The gravitational potential energies are enormous. Radiation emitted from the depths of
            one of these conglomerations of matter has to escape the gravitational field of the
            matter producing it. This will lead to a
            gravitational redshift, i.e. a cooling of the radiation. The interesting question then
            becomes whether the hot radiation from the interior is still ‘hot’ when it
            escapes, or whether it will now have lost so much energy through redshift that it
            emerges <i>cooler</i> than the ambient temperature of the surrounding matter. We might
            therefore observe ‘cold spots’ rather than ‘hot
            spots’.</p>
          <p>So, although the theoretical analysis is complicated, there have to be
            anisotropies of one kind or another in the 3 K radiation at some level of sensitivity,
            and definite predictions have long been made about the angular scale on which such
            anisotropies ought to appear. The refinement of these predictions and the effort to
            detect the anisotropies observationally have become major themes in the recent
            development of cosmology.</p>
          <p>There was a great stir, which even the popular press recognised, when in 1992,
            the COBE satellite succeeded in detecting the anisotropies, albeit at the extremely low
            level of 1 part in 100 000. <xref href="#FIG001_026">Figure 29</xref> shows a picture of the measured intensity
            distribution across the sky.</p>
          <fig>
            <title>
              <b>Figure 29</b>: Departures from isotropy in the 3 K radiation (COBE
              satellite)</title>
            <image href="../../media/S357_1_026i.jpg"/>
            <p outputclass="SourceReference">Source: courtesy of NASA Goddard Space Flight Center, Greenbelt, Maryland
                <data name="ItemRights">
                  <data name="OwnerRef"/>
                  <data name="ItemRef"/>
                  <data name="ItemAcknowledgement">courtesy of NASA Goddard Space Flight Center, Greenbelt,
                  Maryland</data>
              </data>
            </p>
            <p/>
         </fig>
          <p>This first detection of the intrinsic anisotropies in the cosmic microwave
            background had to be interpreted with great care since the signal being detected was of
            the same order of magnitude as the background noise fluctuations. However, since that
            first detection many other studies have been carried out and the angular distribution of
            the anisotropies has been characterised with greatly increased precision.</p>
          
          <p>The characterisation of the angular distribution of anisotropies is usually
            expressed through a plot of the <i>angular power spectrum</i> of the observed radiation.
            Such a plot indicates the relative strength of intensity (or temperature) fluctuations
            as a function of the angular scale of those fluctuations. A recent determination of this
            angular power spectrum, based on results obtained by COBE's successor, the Wilkinson
            Microwave Anisotropy Probe (WMAP), is shown in <xref href="#FIG001_027">Figure 30</xref>.</p>
          <fig>
            <title>
              <b>Figure 30</b>: The angular power spectrum of the cosmic microwave background
              radiation as determined by the WMAP satellite (based on Bennett et al.,
              2003)</title>
            <image href="../../media/S357_1_027i.jpg"/>
            <p outputclass="SourceReference">Source: based on C.L. Bennett <i>et al.</i>, (2003) <i>The Astrophys. J.
                Supp.</i>, 148(1), 1–27 <data name="ItemRights">
                  <data name="OwnerRef"/>
                  <data name="ItemRef"/>
                  <data name="ItemAcknowledgement">based on C.L. Bennett <i>et al.</i>, (2003) <i>The Astrophys.
                    J. Supp.</i>, 148(1), 1–27 </data>
              </data>
            </p>
            <p/>
         </fig>
          <p>The details of the angular power spectrum need not concern us here, but the
            following points should be noted.</p>
          <ol>
            <li>
              <p>The points and vertical ‘error bars’ represent the results of
                observation. The smooth line represents a ‘best fit’ to the data based
                on specific theoretical assumptions.</p>
            </li>
            <li>
              <p>The shaded band represents the unavoidable uncertainty (known as <i>cosmic
                  variance</i> in this case) associated with trying to determine a
                ‘cosmic’ quantity from observations made at one (typical) point in the
                Universe, i.e. from the neighbourhood of the Earth.</p>
            </li>
            <li>
              <p>The COBE data were limited to angular scales of 10° or more. The WMAP
                data reveal anisotropies on much finer scales and tell us much about the angular
                distribution of those anisotropies.</p>
            </li>
            <li>
              <p>The anisotropies are particularly powerful on a scale of about 1°.
                This is just the angular scale at which the inhomogeneities associated with the
                formation of superclusters are expected to leave their imprint on the 3 K
                radiation.</p>
            </li>
            <li>
              <p>Theoretical explanations for the peaks and troughs seen in the data depend
                on the assumed values of various cosmological parameters such as the current value
                of the Hubble parameter. Thus the process of ‘fitting’ predictions to
                the data provides a method of determining the values of those cosmological
                parameters. We shall return to this point later.</p>
            </li>
          </ol>
          <p>In conclusion, we can say that the extreme degree of isotropy of the 3 K
            radiation points to its cosmic origin in the big bang, and justifies us in regarding it
            as powerful confirmatory evidence that there was indeed a big bang. Nevertheless, it is
            perhaps the exceedingly weak inhomogeneities that will ultimately prove to be of the
            most lasting value for cosmology. These give us what may be a unique snapshot of a stage
            in the early development of galaxies/clusters/superclusters – the stage reached
            at the time of decoupling, 4 × 10<sup>5</sup> years after the big
            bang.</p>
        </section>
   </learningContentbody>
</learningContent>