<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE learningContent
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Learning Content//EN" "learningContent.dtd">
<learningContent id="SEC006_002_003">
   <title>6.2.3 Measurement of the angular distribution of the 3 K radiation</title>
   <learningContentbody>
      <section>
            
            <p>How are such angular distributions to be measured? One way, of course, is to
              take a radio telescope and swing it round the sky, taking readings in different
              directions. But as is clear from <xref href="#FIG001_017">Figure 20</xref>(a), the atmosphere itself emits microwaves.
              There is therefore a grave danger, with this method, of picking up different
              contributions of atmospheric emission from different directions – more as you
              point your telescope close to the ground, with a long path through the atmosphere,
              less when it is vertical with the minimum path through the atmosphere. A better, and
              indeed simpler, way with a ground-based telescope is to leave the telescope in a fixed
              direction with respect to the Earth, say vertical, and let the Earth's rotation carry
              it round. In 24 hours, the telescope will be carried round a whole circle, allowing
              the measured intensity to be plotted against angle of observation as indicated in <xref href="#FIG001_024">Figure 27</xref>.</p>
            <p>Thus a practical prescription for looking for the translational motion of the
              Earth, relative to the frame in which the 3 K radiation is isotropic, is to look for a
              variation with a 24-hour period in the radiation detected by a fixed radio telescope.
              Such a search, for a variation of <i>known period</i>, can be carried out very
              sensitively. That is why we have looked at the data in two stages, first asking if the
              data look isotropic, and now asking more specifically for the magnitude of any 24-hour
              variation.</p>
            <p>A further nice experimental feature is that the component being sought is of
              period 24 <i>sidereal</i> hours. Human interference, on the other hand, will tend to
              have a period of 24 <i>solar</i> hours. This small distinction (explained below) often
              allows a radio astronomer to sort out the pure astronomical signal from the strong
              terrestrial noise.</p>
            <p>
            <b>Sidereal Day</b>
         </p>
            <p>Looking at the Earth from outside the Solar System, one sees it revolving
              366¼ times a year, not 365¼. From our position on the Earth, we see only
              365¼ days, because one turn is taken up in the revolution round the Sun. A
              sidereal day is (1/366¼) of a year and a solar day is (1/365¼) of a
              year.</p>
            
            <sectiondiv outputclass="SAQ">
              <p outputclass="Heading">
               <b>Question 14</b>
            </p>
              <sectiondiv outputclass="saq.question">
                <p>How large a change in apparent temperature of the 3 K radiation is
                  expected due to the Earth's motion round the Sun? How large is it due to the Solar
                  System's motion of 230 km s<sup>−1</sup> round the Galaxy? (The <xref href="http://openlearn.open.ac.uk/file.php/3639/S357Datasheets.pdf"
                        scope="external"
                        format="html">data sheet</xref> gives information you may need to answer this
                  question.)</p>
              </sectiondiv>
              <sectiondiv outputclass="saq.answer">
                <p>The mean speed of the Earth round the Sun can be obtained by taking the
                  orbit as a circle of radius 1.5 × 10<sup>11</sup> m. The speed <ph outputclass="InlineEquation">
                     <image href="../../media/S357_1_ie00italvi.gif"/>
                     <ph outputclass="inlineequation-description"/>
                  </ph> is
                  then</p>
                <fig outputclass="Equation">
                  <image href="../../media/S357_1_ue047i.gif"/>
                  <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
               </fig>
                <p>(Strictly, the orbit is not quite circular, so the speed varies somewhat
                  above and below this value.)</p>
                <p>From Equation 12 in <xref href="#SEC006_002">Section 6.2</xref>, the maximum change in apparent
                  temperature, Δ<i>T</i>, which this motion can cause at low frequencies
                  arises when cos<i>θ</i> = 1. Δ<i>T</i>/<i>T</i> is then a
                  fraction</p>
                <fig outputclass="Equation">
                  <image href="../../media/S357_1_ue048i.gif"/>
                  <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
               </fig>
                <p>The speed of the Solar System round the Galaxy about 230 km
                    s<sup>−1</sup>, gives a Δ<i>T</i>/<i>T</i> of about
                    (2.3 × 10<sup>5</sup>)/(3 × 10<sup>8</sup>)
                  ≈ 10<sup>−3</sup>.</p>
              </sectiondiv>
            </sectiondiv>
          </section>
   </learningContentbody>
</learningContent>