<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE learningContent
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Learning Content//EN" "learningContent.dtd">
<learningContent id="SEC006_002_001">
   <title>6.2.1 The need for a reference frame for describing the Universe</title>
   <learningContentbody>
      <section>
            
            <p>The speed of the Earth in its orbit round the Sun is 29.8 km
                s<sup>−1</sup>, in a heliocentric frame. But to specify the velocity vector,
              it is not sufficient to specify the Sun as the origin of the coordinate system; fixed
              directions must also be identified.</p>
            
            <sectiondiv outputclass="SAQ">
              <p outputclass="Heading">
               <b>Question 13</b>
            </p>
              <sectiondiv outputclass="saq.question">
                <p>Here are two possible rules for fixing an
                  <i>x</i>
                  <sup>1</sup>-direction:</p>
                <p>(i) The <i>x</i>
                  <sup>1</sup>-axis is taken as the line from the Sun to
                  the nearest star (Proxima Centauri);</p>
                <p>(ii) The <i>x</i>
                  <sup>1</sup>-axis is taken as pointing in the direction
                  from the centre of the Galaxy to the nearest large galaxy (the Andromeda
                  galaxy).</p>
                <p>Are these two methods equally acceptable? If not, which is preferable,
                  and is it completely satisfactory?</p>
              </sectiondiv>
              <sectiondiv outputclass="saq.answer">
                <p>Proxima Centauri is the nearest star, and so is undoubtedly in our
                  Galaxy. Our Galaxy is rotating, as is suggested independently of all frames of
                  reference by its disc-like
                  shape.
                  So the line to Proxima Centauri is <i>not</i> a good x<sup>1</sup>-axis, because
                  of the relative motion of the Sun and Proxima Centauri within the
                  Galaxy.</p>
                <p>The Andromeda galaxy is the nearest galaxy to ours (apart from satellite
                  galaxies and the Magellanic Clouds). It is gravitationally bound to our Galaxy and
                  moving relative to us. The period of the mutual ‘orbit’ of our
                  Galaxy and the Andromeda galaxy is certainly longer than the period of the Sun (or
                  Proxima Centauri) round our Galaxy, because the distance from our Galaxy to the
                  Andromeda galaxy is about a hundred times bigger than the distance of the Sun (or
                  Proxima Centauri) from the centre of our Galaxy. Nevertheless, the line connecting
                  our Galaxy to the Andromeda galaxy cannot be taken as fixed because of their
                  motions within the Local Group.</p>
                <p>Thus methods (i) and (ii) are not equally acceptable; (ii) is preferable
                  to (i), but is still not fully satisfactory.</p>
              </sectiondiv>
            </sectiondiv>
            <p>The considerations of <xref href="#SAQ001_013">Question 13</xref> force one to look at bigger and bigger
              aggregates of matter in the search for reference bodies with respect to which a system
              of coordinates can be defined independently of the motion caused by the gravitational
              effects of nearby matter in our local region of the Universe. We assume that the
              clusters of galaxies fulfil this role. But clusters may be loosely associated (though
              not bound) in superclusters.</p>
            <p>For this reason, we would like to have an alternative way of establishing a
              reference frame. The 3 K radiation provides such a means.</p>
            <p>If the 3 K radiation filled the Universe at early times and has not
              interacted appreciably with matter since decoupling, then this radiation defines a
              system in which matter and energy in the early Universe are assumed to have been
              distributed homogeneously. So if we were to find that the 3 K radiation is
                <i>completely</i> isotropic when observed on Earth, we could conclude that we are
                <i>at rest</i> with respect to the average distribution of matter and energy in the
              Universe. In that sense, the radiation can be said to define a ‘rest
              frame’ of the Universe. But if we find that the radiation is not isotropic, and
              moreover, that it varies in a characteristically systematic fashion according to
              direction, then we can conclude that we are moving in a particular direction with
              respect to the frame in which the radiation is isotropic.</p>
            <p>It is a matter of great interest to know the velocities of the Earth, the
              Sun, our Galaxy and our Local Group with respect to the system defined by the 3 K
              radiation. It might, for example, provide support for the idea that gravitational
              effects within a supercluster must be taken into account in mapping out the
              Universe.</p>
          </section>
   </learningContentbody>
</learningContent>