<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net/doctypes/dita/shakespear/dtd/act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-3">
   <title>ACT III</title>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  Before the house of ANTIPHOLUS of Ephesus.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter ANTIPHOLUS of Ephesus, DROMIO of Ephesus,
ANGELO, and BALTHAZAR</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>Good Signior Angelo, you must excuse us all;</line>
            <line>My wife is shrewish when I keep not hours:</line>
            <line>Say that I linger'd with you at your shop</line>
            <line>To see the making of her carcanet,</line>
            <line>And that to-morrow you will bring it home.</line>
            <line>But here's a villain that would face me down</line>
            <line>He met me on the mart, and that I beat him,</line>
            <line>And charged him with a thousand marks in gold,</line>
            <line>And that I did deny my wife and house.</line>
            <line>Thou drunkard, thou, what didst thou mean by this?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>Say what you will, sir, but I know what I know;</line>
            <line>That you beat me at the mart, I have your hand to show:</line>
            <line>If the skin were parchment, and the blows you gave were ink,</line>
            <line>Your own handwriting would tell you what I think.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>I think thou art an ass.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>Marry, so it doth appear</line>
            <line>By the wrongs I suffer and the blows I bear.</line>
            <line>I should kick, being kick'd; and, being at that pass,</line>
            <line>You would keep from my heels and beware of an ass.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>You're sad, Signior Balthazar: pray God our cheer</line>
            <line>May answer my good will and your good welcome here.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BALTHAZAR</speaker>
            <line>I hold your dainties cheap, sir, and your</line>
            <line>welcome dear.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>O, Signior Balthazar, either at flesh or fish,</line>
            <line>A table full of welcome make scarce one dainty dish.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BALTHAZAR</speaker>
            <line>Good meat, sir, is common; that every churl affords.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>And welcome more common; for that's nothing but words.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BALTHAZAR</speaker>
            <line>Small cheer and great welcome makes a merry feast.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>Ay, to a niggardly host, and more sparing guest:</line>
            <line>But though my cates be mean, take them in good part;</line>
            <line>Better cheer may you have, but not with better heart.</line>
            <line>But, soft! my door is lock'd. Go bid them let us in.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>Maud, Bridget, Marian, Cicel, Gillian, Ginn!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Within</stagedir>  Mome, malt-horse, capon, coxcomb,</line>
            <line>idiot, patch!</line>
            <line>Either get thee from the door, or sit down at the hatch.</line>
            <line>Dost thou conjure for wenches, that thou call'st</line>
            <line>for such store,</line>
            <line>When one is one too many? Go, get thee from the door.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>What patch is made our porter? My master stays in</line>
            <line>the street.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Within</stagedir>  Let him walk from whence he came, lest he</line>
            <line>catch cold on's feet.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>Who talks within there? ho, open the door!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Within</stagedir>  Right, sir; I'll tell you when, an you tell</line>
            <line>me wherefore.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>Wherefore? for my dinner: I have not dined to-day.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Within</stagedir>  Nor to-day here you must not; come again</line>
            <line>when you may.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>What art thou that keepest me out from the house I owe?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Within</stagedir>  The porter for this time, sir, and my name</line>
            <line>is Dromio.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>O villain! thou hast stolen both mine office and my name.</line>
            <line>The one ne'er got me credit, the other mickle blame.</line>
            <line>If thou hadst been Dromio to-day in my place,</line>
            <line>Thou wouldst have changed thy face for a name or thy</line>
            <line>name for an ass.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCE</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Within</stagedir>  What a coil is there, Dromio? who are those</line>
            <line>at the gate?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>Let my master in, Luce.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCE</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Within</stagedir>  Faith, no; he comes too late;</line>
            <line>And so tell your master.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>O Lord, I must laugh!</line>
            <line>Have at you with a proverb--Shall I set in my staff?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCE</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Within</stagedir>  Have at you with another; that's--When?</line>
            <line>can you tell?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Within</stagedir>  If thy name be call'd Luce--Luce, thou hast</line>
            <line>answered him well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>Do you hear, you minion? you'll let us in, I hope?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCE</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Within</stagedir>  I thought to have asked you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Within</stagedir>  And you said no.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>So, come, help: well struck! there was blow for blow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>Thou baggage, let me in.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCE</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Within</stagedir>  Can you tell for whose sake?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>Master, knock the door hard.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCE</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Within</stagedir>  Let him knock till it ache.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>You'll cry for this, minion, if I beat the door down.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCE</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Within</stagedir>  What needs all that, and a pair of stocks in the town?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ADRIANA</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Within</stagedir>  Who is that at the door that keeps all</line>
            <line>this noise?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Within</stagedir>  By my troth, your town is troubled with</line>
            <line>unruly boys.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>Are you there, wife? you might have come before.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ADRIANA</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Within</stagedir>  Your wife, sir knave! go get you from the door.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>If you went in pain, master, this 'knave' would go sore.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>Here is neither cheer, sir, nor welcome: we would</line>
            <line>fain have either.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BALTHAZAR</speaker>
            <line>In debating which was best, we shall part with neither.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>They stand at the door, master; bid them welcome hither.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>There is something in the wind, that we cannot get in.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>You would say so, master, if your garments were thin.</line>
            <line>Your cake there is warm within; you stand here in the cold:</line>
            <line>It would make a man mad as a buck, to be so bought and sold.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>Go fetch me something: I'll break ope the gate.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Within</stagedir>  Break any breaking here, and I'll break your</line>
            <line>knave's pate.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>A man may break a word with you, sir, and words are but wind,</line>
            <line>Ay, and break it in your face, so he break it not behind.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Within</stagedir>  It seems thou want'st breaking: out upon</line>
            <line>thee, hind!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>Here's too much 'out upon thee!' I pray thee,</line>
            <line>let me in.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Within</stagedir>  Ay, when fowls have no feathers and fish have no fin.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>Well, I'll break in: go borrow me a crow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>A crow without feather? Master, mean you so?</line>
            <line>For a fish without a fin, there's a fowl without a feather;</line>
            <line>If a crow help us in, sirrah, we'll pluck a crow together.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>Go get thee gone; fetch me an iron crow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BALTHAZAR</speaker>
            <line>Have patience, sir; O, let it not be so!</line>
            <line>Herein you war against your reputation</line>
            <line>And draw within the compass of suspect</line>
            <line>The unviolated honour of your wife.</line>
            <line>Once this,--your long experience of her wisdom,</line>
            <line>Her sober virtue, years and modesty,</line>
            <line>Plead on her part some cause to you unknown:</line>
            <line>And doubt not, sir, but she will well excuse</line>
            <line>Why at this time the doors are made against you.</line>
            <line>Be ruled by me: depart in patience,</line>
            <line>And let us to the Tiger all to dinner,</line>
            <line>And about evening come yourself alone</line>
            <line>To know the reason of this strange restraint.</line>
            <line>If by strong hand you offer to break in</line>
            <line>Now in the stirring passage of the day,</line>
            <line>A vulgar comment will be made of it,</line>
            <line>And that supposed by the common rout</line>
            <line>Against your yet ungalled estimation</line>
            <line>That may with foul intrusion enter in</line>
            <line>And dwell upon your grave when you are dead;</line>
            <line>For slander lives upon succession,</line>
            <line>For ever housed where it gets possession.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>You have prevailed: I will depart in quiet,</line>
            <line>And, in despite of mirth, mean to be merry.</line>
            <line>I know a wench of excellent discourse,</line>
            <line>Pretty and witty; wild, and yet, too, gentle:</line>
            <line>There will we dine. This woman that I mean,</line>
            <line>My wife--but, I protest, without desert--</line>
            <line>Hath oftentimes upbraided me withal:</line>
            <line>To her will we to dinner.</line>
            <stagedir>To Angelo</stagedir>
            <line>Get you home</line>
            <line>And fetch the chain; by this I know 'tis made:</line>
            <line>Bring it, I pray you, to the Porpentine;</line>
            <line>For there's the house: that chain will I bestow--</line>
            <line>Be it for nothing but to spite my wife--</line>
            <line>Upon mine hostess there: good sir, make haste.</line>
            <line>Since mine own doors refuse to entertain me,</line>
            <line>I'll knock elsewhere, to see if they'll disdain me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>I'll meet you at that place some hour hence.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>Do so. This jest shall cost me some expense.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  The same.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter LUCIANA and ANTIPHOLUS of Syracuse</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIANA</speaker>
            <line>And may it be that you have quite forgot</line>
            <line>A husband's office? shall, Antipholus.</line>
            <line>Even in the spring of love, thy love-springs rot?</line>
            <line>Shall love, in building, grow so ruinous?</line>
            <line>If you did wed my sister for her wealth,</line>
            <line>Then for her wealth's sake use her with more kindness:</line>
            <line>Or if you like elsewhere, do it by stealth;</line>
            <line>Muffle your false love with some show of blindness:</line>
            <line>Let not my sister read it in your eye;</line>
            <line>Be not thy tongue thy own shame's orator;</line>
            <line>Look sweet, be fair, become disloyalty;</line>
            <line>Apparel vice like virtue's harbinger;</line>
            <line>Bear a fair presence, though your heart be tainted;</line>
            <line>Teach sin the carriage of a holy saint;</line>
            <line>Be secret-false: what need she be acquainted?</line>
            <line>What simple thief brags of his own attaint?</line>
            <line>'Tis double wrong, to truant with your bed</line>
            <line>And let her read it in thy looks at board:</line>
            <line>Shame hath a bastard fame, well managed;</line>
            <line>Ill deeds are doubled with an evil word.</line>
            <line>Alas, poor women! make us but believe,</line>
            <line>Being compact of credit, that you love us;</line>
            <line>Though others have the arm, show us the sleeve;</line>
            <line>We in your motion turn and you may move us.</line>
            <line>Then, gentle brother, get you in again;</line>
            <line>Comfort my sister, cheer her, call her wife:</line>
            <line>'Tis holy sport to be a little vain,</line>
            <line>When the sweet breath of flattery conquers strife.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>Sweet mistress--what your name is else, I know not,</line>
            <line>Nor by what wonder you do hit of mine,--</line>
            <line>Less in your knowledge and your grace you show not</line>
            <line>Than our earth's wonder, more than earth divine.</line>
            <line>Teach me, dear creature, how to think and speak;</line>
            <line>Lay open to my earthy-gross conceit,</line>
            <line>Smother'd in errors, feeble, shallow, weak,</line>
            <line>The folded meaning of your words' deceit.</line>
            <line>Against my soul's pure truth why labour you</line>
            <line>To make it wander in an unknown field?</line>
            <line>Are you a god? would you create me new?</line>
            <line>Transform me then, and to your power I'll yield.</line>
            <line>But if that I am I, then well I know</line>
            <line>Your weeping sister is no wife of mine,</line>
            <line>Nor to her bed no homage do I owe</line>
            <line>Far more, far more to you do I decline.</line>
            <line>O, train me not, sweet mermaid, with thy note,</line>
            <line>To drown me in thy sister's flood of tears:</line>
            <line>Sing, siren, for thyself and I will dote:</line>
            <line>Spread o'er the silver waves thy golden hairs,</line>
            <line>And as a bed I'll take them and there lie,</line>
            <line>And in that glorious supposition think</line>
            <line>He gains by death that hath such means to die:</line>
            <line>Let Love, being light, be drowned if she sink!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIANA</speaker>
            <line>What, are you mad, that you do reason so?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>Not mad, but mated; how, I do not know.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIANA</speaker>
            <line>It is a fault that springeth from your eye.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>For gazing on your beams, fair sun, being by.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIANA</speaker>
            <line>Gaze where you should, and that will clear your sight.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>As good to wink, sweet love, as look on night.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIANA</speaker>
            <line>Why call you me love? call my sister so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>Thy sister's sister.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIANA</speaker>
            <line>That's my sister.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>No;</line>
            <line>It is thyself, mine own self's better part,</line>
            <line>Mine eye's clear eye, my dear heart's dearer heart,</line>
            <line>My food, my fortune and my sweet hope's aim,</line>
            <line>My sole earth's heaven and my heaven's claim.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIANA</speaker>
            <line>All this my sister is, or else should be.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>Call thyself sister, sweet, for I am thee.</line>
            <line>Thee will I love and with thee lead my life:</line>
            <line>Thou hast no husband yet nor I no wife.</line>
            <line>Give me thy hand.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIANA</speaker>
            <line>O, soft, air! hold you still:</line>
            <line>I'll fetch my sister, to get her good will.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Enter DROMIO of Syracuse</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>Why, how now, Dromio! where runn'st thou so fast?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>Do you know me, sir? am I Dromio? am I your man?</line>
            <line>am I myself?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>Thou art Dromio, thou art my man, thou art thyself.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>I am an ass, I am a woman's man and besides myself.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>Marry, sir, besides myself, I am due to a woman; one</line>
            <line>that claims me, one that haunts me, one that will have me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>What claim lays she to thee?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>Marry sir, such claim as you would lay to your</line>
            <line>horse; and she would have me as a beast: not that, I</line>
            <line>being a beast, she would have me; but that she,</line>
            <line>being a very beastly creature, lays claim to me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>What is she?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>A very reverent body; ay, such a one as a man may</line>
            <line>not speak of without he say 'Sir-reverence.' I have</line>
            <line>but lean luck in the match, and yet is she a</line>
            <line>wondrous fat marriage.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>How dost thou mean a fat marriage?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>Marry, sir, she's the kitchen wench and all grease;</line>
            <line>and I know not what use to put her to but to make a</line>
            <line>lamp of her and run from her by her own light. I</line>
            <line>warrant, her rags and the tallow in them will burn a</line>
            <line>Poland winter: if she lives till doomsday,</line>
            <line>she'll burn a week longer than the whole world.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>What complexion is she of?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>Swart, like my shoe, but her face nothing half so</line>
            <line>clean kept: for why, she sweats; a man may go over</line>
            <line>shoes in the grime of it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>That's a fault that water will mend.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>No, sir, 'tis in grain; Noah's flood could not do it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>What's her name?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>Nell, sir; but her name and three quarters, that's</line>
            <line>an ell and three quarters, will not measure her from</line>
            <line>hip to hip.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>Then she bears some breadth?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>No longer from head to foot than from hip to hip:</line>
            <line>she is spherical, like a globe; I could find out</line>
            <line>countries in her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>In what part of her body stands Ireland?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>Marry, in her buttocks: I found it out by the bogs.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>Where Scotland?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>I found it by the barrenness; hard in the palm of the hand.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>Where France?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>In her forehead; armed and reverted, making war</line>
            <line>against her heir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>Where England?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>I looked for the chalky cliffs, but I could find no</line>
            <line>whiteness in them; but I guess it stood in her chin,</line>
            <line>by the salt rheum that ran between France and it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>Where Spain?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>Faith, I saw it not; but I felt it hot in her breath.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>Where America, the Indies?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>Oh, sir, upon her nose all o'er embellished with</line>
            <line>rubies, carbuncles, sapphires, declining their rich</line>
            <line>aspect to the hot breath of Spain; who sent whole</line>
            <line>armadoes of caracks to be ballast at her nose.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>Where stood Belgia, the Netherlands?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>Oh, sir, I did not look so low. To conclude, this</line>
            <line>drudge, or diviner, laid claim to me, call'd me</line>
            <line>Dromio; swore I was assured to her; told me what</line>
            <line>privy marks I had about me, as, the mark of my</line>
            <line>shoulder, the mole in my neck, the great wart on my</line>
            <line>left arm, that I amazed ran from her as a witch:</line>
            <line>And, I think, if my breast had not been made of</line>
            <line>faith and my heart of steel,</line>
            <line>She had transform'd me to a curtal dog and made</line>
            <line>me turn i' the wheel.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>Go hie thee presently, post to the road:</line>
            <line>An if the wind blow any way from shore,</line>
            <line>I will not harbour in this town to-night:</line>
            <line>If any bark put forth, come to the mart,</line>
            <line>Where I will walk till thou return to me.</line>
            <line>If every one knows us and we know none,</line>
            <line>'Tis time, I think, to trudge, pack and be gone.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>As from a bear a man would run for life,</line>
            <line>So fly I from her that would be my wife.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>There's none but witches do inhabit here;</line>
            <line>And therefore 'tis high time that I were hence.</line>
            <line>She that doth call me husband, even my soul</line>
            <line>Doth for a wife abhor. But her fair sister,</line>
            <line>Possess'd with such a gentle sovereign grace,</line>
            <line>Of such enchanting presence and discourse,</line>
            <line>Hath almost made me traitor to myself:</line>
            <line>But, lest myself be guilty to self-wrong,</line>
            <line>I'll stop mine ears against the mermaid's song.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter ANGELO with the chain</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>Master Antipholus,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>Ay, that's my name.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>I know it well, sir, lo, here is the chain.</line>
            <line>I thought to have ta'en you at the Porpentine:</line>
            <line>The chain unfinish'd made me stay thus long.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>What is your will that I shall do with this?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>What please yourself, sir: I have made it for you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>Made it for me, sir! I bespoke it not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>Not once, nor twice, but twenty times you have.</line>
            <line>Go home with it and please your wife withal;</line>
            <line>And soon at supper-time I'll visit you</line>
            <line>And then receive my money for the chain.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>I pray you, sir, receive the money now,</line>
            <line>For fear you ne'er see chain nor money more.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>You are a merry man, sir: fare you well.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>What I should think of this, I cannot tell:</line>
            <line>But this I think, there's no man is so vain</line>
            <line>That would refuse so fair an offer'd chain.</line>
            <line>I see a man here needs not live by shifts,</line>
            <line>When in the streets he meets such golden gifts.</line>
            <line>I'll to the mart, and there for Dromio stay</line>
            <line>If any ship put out, then straight away.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>