<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:shakespear:dtd:act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-4">
   <title>ACT IV</title>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  A public place.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter Second Merchant, ANGELO, and an Officer</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Merchant</speaker>
            <line>You know since Pentecost the sum is due,</line>
            <line>And since I have not much importuned you;</line>
            <line>Nor now I had not, but that I am bound</line>
            <line>To Persia, and want guilders for my voyage:</line>
            <line>Therefore make present satisfaction,</line>
            <line>Or I'll attach you by this officer.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>Even just the sum that I do owe to you</line>
            <line>Is growing to me by Antipholus,</line>
            <line>And in the instant that I met with you</line>
            <line>He had of me a chain: at five o'clock</line>
            <line>I shall receive the money for the same.</line>
            <line>Pleaseth you walk with me down to his house,</line>
            <line>I will discharge my bond and thank you too.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter ANTIPHOLUS of Ephesus and DROMIO of Ephesus
from the courtezan's</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Officer</speaker>
            <line>That labour may you save: see where he comes.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>While I go to the goldsmith's house, go thou</line>
            <line>And buy a rope's end: that will I bestow</line>
            <line>Among my wife and her confederates,</line>
            <line>For locking me out of my doors by day.</line>
            <line>But, soft! I see the goldsmith. Get thee gone;</line>
            <line>Buy thou a rope and bring it home to me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>I buy a thousand pound a year: I buy a rope.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>A man is well holp up that trusts to you:</line>
            <line>I promised your presence and the chain;</line>
            <line>But neither chain nor goldsmith came to me.</line>
            <line>Belike you thought our love would last too long,</line>
            <line>If it were chain'd together, and therefore came not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>Saving your merry humour, here's the note</line>
            <line>How much your chain weighs to the utmost carat,</line>
            <line>The fineness of the gold and chargeful fashion.</line>
            <line>Which doth amount to three odd ducats more</line>
            <line>Than I stand debted to this gentleman:</line>
            <line>I pray you, see him presently discharged,</line>
            <line>For he is bound to sea and stays but for it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>I am not furnish'd with the present money;</line>
            <line>Besides, I have some business in the town.</line>
            <line>Good signior, take the stranger to my house</line>
            <line>And with you take the chain and bid my wife</line>
            <line>Disburse the sum on the receipt thereof:</line>
            <line>Perchance I will be there as soon as you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>Then you will bring the chain to her yourself?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>No; bear it with you, lest I come not time enough.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>Well, sir, I will. Have you the chain about you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>An if I have not, sir, I hope you have;</line>
            <line>Or else you may return without your money.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>Nay, come, I pray you, sir, give me the chain:</line>
            <line>Both wind and tide stays for this gentleman,</line>
            <line>And I, to blame, have held him here too long.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>Good Lord! you use this dalliance to excuse</line>
            <line>Your breach of promise to the Porpentine.</line>
            <line>I should have chid you for not bringing it,</line>
            <line>But, like a shrew, you first begin to brawl.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Merchant</speaker>
            <line>The hour steals on; I pray you, sir, dispatch.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>You hear how he importunes me;--the chain!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>Why, give it to my wife and fetch your money.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>Come, come, you know I gave it you even now.</line>
            <line>Either send the chain or send me by some token.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>Fie, now you run this humour out of breath,</line>
            <line>where's the chain? I pray you, let me see it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Merchant</speaker>
            <line>My business cannot brook this dalliance.</line>
            <line>Good sir, say whether you'll answer me or no:</line>
            <line>If not, I'll leave him to the officer.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>I answer you! what should I answer you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>The money that you owe me for the chain.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>I owe you none till I receive the chain.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>You know I gave it you half an hour since.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>You gave me none: you wrong me much to say so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>You wrong me more, sir, in denying it:</line>
            <line>Consider how it stands upon my credit.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Merchant</speaker>
            <line>Well, officer, arrest him at my suit.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Officer</speaker>
            <line>I do; and charge you in the duke's name to obey me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>This touches me in reputation.</line>
            <line>Either consent to pay this sum for me</line>
            <line>Or I attach you by this officer.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>Consent to pay thee that I never had!</line>
            <line>Arrest me, foolish fellow, if thou darest.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>Here is thy fee; arrest him, officer,</line>
            <line>I would not spare my brother in this case,</line>
            <line>If he should scorn me so apparently.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Officer</speaker>
            <line>I do arrest you, sir: you hear the suit.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>I do obey thee till I give thee bail.</line>
            <line>But, sirrah, you shall buy this sport as dear</line>
            <line>As all the metal in your shop will answer.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>Sir, sir, I will have law in Ephesus,</line>
            <line>To your notorious shame; I doubt it not.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter DROMIO of Syracuse, from the bay</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>Master, there is a bark of Epidamnum</line>
            <line>That stays but till her owner comes aboard,</line>
            <line>And then, sir, she bears away. Our fraughtage, sir,</line>
            <line>I have convey'd aboard; and I have bought</line>
            <line>The oil, the balsamum and aqua-vitae.</line>
            <line>The ship is in her trim; the merry wind</line>
            <line>Blows fair from land: they stay for nought at all</line>
            <line>But for their owner, master, and yourself.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>How now! a madman! Why, thou peevish sheep,</line>
            <line>What ship of Epidamnum stays for me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>A ship you sent me to, to hire waftage.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>Thou drunken slave, I sent thee for a rope;</line>
            <line>And told thee to what purpose and what end.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>You sent me for a rope's end as soon:</line>
            <line>You sent me to the bay, sir, for a bark.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>I will debate this matter at more leisure</line>
            <line>And teach your ears to list me with more heed.</line>
            <line>To Adriana, villain, hie thee straight:</line>
            <line>Give her this key, and tell her, in the desk</line>
            <line>That's cover'd o'er with Turkish tapestry,</line>
            <line>There is a purse of ducats; let her send it:</line>
            <line>Tell her I am arrested in the street</line>
            <line>And that shall bail me; hie thee, slave, be gone!</line>
            <line>On, officer, to prison till it come.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt Second Merchant, Angelo, Officer, and
Antipholus of Ephesus</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>To Adriana! that is where we dined,</line>
            <line>Where Dowsabel did claim me for her husband:</line>
            <line>She is too big, I hope, for me to compass.</line>
            <line>Thither I must, although against my will,</line>
            <line>For servants must their masters' minds fulfil.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  The house of ANTIPHOLUS of Ephesus.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter ADRIANA and LUCIANA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ADRIANA</speaker>
            <line>Ah, Luciana, did he tempt thee so?</line>
            <line>Mightst thou perceive austerely in his eye</line>
            <line>That he did plead in earnest? yea or no?</line>
            <line>Look'd he or red or pale, or sad or merrily?</line>
            <line>What observation madest thou in this case</line>
            <line>Of his heart's meteors tilting in his face?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIANA</speaker>
            <line>First he denied you had in him no right.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ADRIANA</speaker>
            <line>He meant he did me none; the more my spite.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIANA</speaker>
            <line>Then swore he that he was a stranger here.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ADRIANA</speaker>
            <line>And true he swore, though yet forsworn he were.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIANA</speaker>
            <line>Then pleaded I for you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ADRIANA</speaker>
            <line>And what said he?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIANA</speaker>
            <line>That love I begg'd for you he begg'd of me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ADRIANA</speaker>
            <line>With what persuasion did he tempt thy love?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIANA</speaker>
            <line>With words that in an honest suit might move.</line>
            <line>First he did praise my beauty, then my speech.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ADRIANA</speaker>
            <line>Didst speak him fair?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIANA</speaker>
            <line>Have patience, I beseech.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ADRIANA</speaker>
            <line>I cannot, nor I will not, hold me still;</line>
            <line>My tongue, though not my heart, shall have his will.</line>
            <line>He is deformed, crooked, old and sere,</line>
            <line>Ill-faced, worse bodied, shapeless everywhere;</line>
            <line>Vicious, ungentle, foolish, blunt, unkind;</line>
            <line>Stigmatical in making, worse in mind.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIANA</speaker>
            <line>Who would be jealous then of such a one?</line>
            <line>No evil lost is wail'd when it is gone.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ADRIANA</speaker>
            <line>Ah, but I think him better than I say,</line>
            <line>And yet would herein others' eyes were worse.</line>
            <line>Far from her nest the lapwing cries away:</line>
            <line>My heart prays for him, though my tongue do curse.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter DROMIO of Syracuse</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>Here! go; the desk, the purse! sweet, now, make haste.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIANA</speaker>
            <line>How hast thou lost thy breath?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>By running fast.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ADRIANA</speaker>
            <line>Where is thy master, Dromio? is he well?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>No, he's in Tartar limbo, worse than hell.</line>
            <line>A devil in an everlasting garment hath him;</line>
            <line>One whose hard heart is button'd up with steel;</line>
            <line>A fiend, a fury, pitiless and rough;</line>
            <line>A wolf, nay, worse, a fellow all in buff;</line>
            <line>A back-friend, a shoulder-clapper, one that</line>
            <line>countermands</line>
            <line>The passages of alleys, creeks and narrow lands;</line>
            <line>A hound that runs counter and yet draws dryfoot well;</line>
            <line>One that before the judgement carries poor souls to hell.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ADRIANA</speaker>
            <line>Why, man, what is the matter?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>I do not know the matter: he is 'rested on the case.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ADRIANA</speaker>
            <line>What, is he arrested? Tell me at whose suit.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>I know not at whose suit he is arrested well;</line>
            <line>But he's in a suit of buff which 'rested him, that can I tell.</line>
            <line>Will you send him, mistress, redemption, the money in his desk?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ADRIANA</speaker>
            <line>Go fetch it, sister.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit Luciana</stagedir>
            <line>This I wonder at,</line>
            <line>That he, unknown to me, should be in debt.</line>
            <line>Tell me, was he arrested on a band?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>Not on a band, but on a stronger thing;</line>
            <line>A chain, a chain! Do you not hear it ring?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ADRIANA</speaker>
            <line>What, the chain?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>No, no, the bell: 'tis time that I were gone:</line>
            <line>It was two ere I left him, and now the clock</line>
            <line>strikes one.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ADRIANA</speaker>
            <line>The hours come back! that did I never hear.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>O, yes; if any hour meet a sergeant, a' turns back for</line>
            <line>very fear.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ADRIANA</speaker>
            <line>As if Time were in debt! how fondly dost thou reason!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>Time is a very bankrupt, and owes more than he's</line>
            <line>worth, to season.</line>
            <line>Nay, he's a thief too: have you not heard men say</line>
            <line>That Time comes stealing on by night and day?</line>
            <line>If Time be in debt and theft, and a sergeant in the way,</line>
            <line>Hath he not reason to turn back an hour in a day?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter LUCIANA with a purse</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ADRIANA</speaker>
            <line>Go, Dromio; there's the money, bear it straight;</line>
            <line>And bring thy master home immediately.</line>
            <line>Come, sister: I am press'd down with conceit--</line>
            <line>Conceit, my comfort and my injury.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  A public place.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter ANTIPHOLUS of Syracuse</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>There's not a man I meet but doth salute me</line>
            <line>As if I were their well-acquainted friend;</line>
            <line>And every one doth call me by my name.</line>
            <line>Some tender money to me; some invite me;</line>
            <line>Some other give me thanks for kindnesses;</line>
            <line>Some offer me commodities to buy:</line>
            <line>Even now a tailor call'd me in his shop</line>
            <line>And show'd me silks that he had bought for me,</line>
            <line>And therewithal took measure of my body.</line>
            <line>Sure, these are but imaginary wiles</line>
            <line>And Lapland sorcerers inhabit here.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter DROMIO OF SYRACUSE</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>Master, here's the gold you sent me for. What, have</line>
            <line>you got the picture of old Adam new-apparelled?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>What gold is this? what Adam dost thou mean?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>Not that Adam that kept the Paradise but that Adam</line>
            <line>that keeps the prison: he that goes in the calf's</line>
            <line>skin that was killed for the Prodigal; he that came</line>
            <line>behind you, sir, like an evil angel, and bid you</line>
            <line>forsake your liberty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>I understand thee not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>No? why, 'tis a plain case: he that went, like a</line>
            <line>bass-viol, in a case of leather; the man, sir,</line>
            <line>that, when gentlemen are tired, gives them a sob</line>
            <line>and 'rests them; he, sir, that takes pity on decayed</line>
            <line>men and gives them suits of durance; he that sets up</line>
            <line>his rest to do more exploits with his mace than a</line>
            <line>morris-pike.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>What, thou meanest an officer?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>Ay, sir, the sergeant of the band, he that brings</line>
            <line>any man to answer it that breaks his band; one that</line>
            <line>thinks a man always going to bed, and says, 'God</line>
            <line>give you good rest!'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>Well, sir, there rest in your foolery. Is there any</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>Why, sir, I brought you word an hour since that the</line>
            <line>bark Expedition put forth to-night; and then were</line>
            <line>you hindered by the sergeant, to tarry for the hoy</line>
            <line>Delay. Here are the angels that you sent for to</line>
            <line>deliver you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>The fellow is distract, and so am I;</line>
            <line>And here we wander in illusions:</line>
            <line>Some blessed power deliver us from hence!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter a Courtezan</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Courtezan</speaker>
            <line>Well met, well met, Master Antipholus.</line>
            <line>I see, sir, you have found the goldsmith now:</line>
            <line>Is that the chain you promised me to-day?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>Satan, avoid! I charge thee, tempt me not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>Master, is this Mistress Satan?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>It is the devil.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>Nay, she is worse, she is the devil's dam; and here</line>
            <line>she comes in the habit of a light wench: and thereof</line>
            <line>comes that the wenches say 'God damn me;' that's as</line>
            <line>much to say 'God make me a light wench.' It is</line>
            <line>written, they appear to men like angels of light:</line>
            <line>light is an effect of fire, and fire will burn;</line>
            <line>ergo, light wenches will burn. Come not near her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Courtezan</speaker>
            <line>Your man and you are marvellous merry, sir.</line>
            <line>Will you go with me? We'll mend our dinner here?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>Master, if you do, expect spoon-meat; or bespeak a</line>
            <line>long spoon.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>Why, Dromio?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>Marry, he must have a long spoon that must eat with</line>
            <line>the devil.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>Avoid then, fiend! what tell'st thou me of supping?</line>
            <line>Thou art, as you are all, a sorceress:</line>
            <line>I conjure thee to leave me and be gone.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Courtezan</speaker>
            <line>Give me the ring of mine you had at dinner,</line>
            <line>Or, for my diamond, the chain you promised,</line>
            <line>And I'll be gone, sir, and not trouble you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>Some devils ask but the parings of one's nail,</line>
            <line>A rush, a hair, a drop of blood, a pin,</line>
            <line>A nut, a cherry-stone;</line>
            <line>But she, more covetous, would have a chain.</line>
            <line>Master, be wise: an if you give it her,</line>
            <line>The devil will shake her chain and fright us with it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Courtezan</speaker>
            <line>I pray you, sir, my ring, or else the chain:</line>
            <line>I hope you do not mean to cheat me so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>Avaunt, thou witch! Come, Dromio, let us go.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>'Fly pride,' says the peacock: mistress, that you know.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt Antipholus of Syracuse and Dromio of Syracuse</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Courtezan</speaker>
            <line>Now, out of doubt Antipholus is mad,</line>
            <line>Else would he never so demean himself.</line>
            <line>A ring he hath of mine worth forty ducats,</line>
            <line>And for the same he promised me a chain:</line>
            <line>Both one and other he denies me now.</line>
            <line>The reason that I gather he is mad,</line>
            <line>Besides this present instance of his rage,</line>
            <line>Is a mad tale he told to-day at dinner,</line>
            <line>Of his own doors being shut against his entrance.</line>
            <line>Belike his wife, acquainted with his fits,</line>
            <line>On purpose shut the doors against his way.</line>
            <line>My way is now to hie home to his house,</line>
            <line>And tell his wife that, being lunatic,</line>
            <line>He rush'd into my house and took perforce</line>
            <line>My ring away. This course I fittest choose;</line>
            <line>For forty ducats is too much to lose.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-4">
      <title>SCENE IV.  A street.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter ANTIPHOLUS of Ephesus and the Officer</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>Fear me not, man; I will not break away:</line>
            <line>I'll give thee, ere I leave thee, so much money,</line>
            <line>To warrant thee, as I am 'rested for.</line>
            <line>My wife is in a wayward mood to-day,</line>
            <line>And will not lightly trust the messenger</line>
            <line>That I should be attach'd in Ephesus,</line>
            <line>I tell you, 'twill sound harshly in her ears.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter DROMIO of Ephesus with a rope's-end</stagedir>
            <line>Here comes my man; I think he brings the money.</line>
            <line>How now, sir! have you that I sent you for?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>Here's that, I warrant you, will pay them all.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>But where's the money?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>Why, sir, I gave the money for the rope.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>Five hundred ducats, villain, for a rope?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>I'll serve you, sir, five hundred at the rate.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>To what end did I bid thee hie thee home?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>To a rope's-end, sir; and to that end am I returned.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>And to that end, sir, I will welcome you.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Beating him</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Officer</speaker>
            <line>Good sir, be patient.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>Nay, 'tis for me to be patient; I am in adversity.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Officer</speaker>
            <line>Good, now, hold thy tongue.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>Nay, rather persuade him to hold his hands.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>Thou whoreson, senseless villain!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>I would I were senseless, sir, that I might not feel</line>
            <line>your blows.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>I am an ass, indeed; you may prove it by my long</line>
            <line>ears. I have served him from the hour of my</line>
            <line>nativity to this instant, and have nothing at his</line>
            <line>hands for my service but blows. When I am cold, he</line>
            <line>heats me with beating; when I am warm, he cools me</line>
            <line>with beating; I am waked with it when I sleep;</line>
            <line>raised with it when I sit; driven out of doors with</line>
            <line>it when I go from home; welcomed home with it when</line>
            <line>I return; nay, I bear it on my shoulders, as a</line>
            <line>beggar wont her brat; and, I think when he hath</line>
            <line>lamed me, I shall beg with it from door to door.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>Come, go along; my wife is coming yonder.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter ADRIANA, LUCIANA, the Courtezan, and PINCH</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>Mistress, 'respice finem,' respect your end; or</line>
            <line>rather, the prophecy like the parrot, 'beware the</line>
            <line>rope's-end.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>Wilt thou still talk?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Beating him</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Courtezan</speaker>
            <line>How say you now? is not your husband mad?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ADRIANA</speaker>
            <line>His incivility confirms no less.</line>
            <line>Good Doctor Pinch, you are a conjurer;</line>
            <line>Establish him in his true sense again,</line>
            <line>And I will please you what you will demand.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIANA</speaker>
            <line>Alas, how fiery and how sharp he looks!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Courtezan</speaker>
            <line>Mark how he trembles in his ecstasy!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PINCH</speaker>
            <line>Give me your hand and let me feel your pulse.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>There is my hand, and let it feel your ear.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Striking him</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PINCH</speaker>
            <line>I charge thee, Satan, housed within this man,</line>
            <line>To yield possession to my holy prayers</line>
            <line>And to thy state of darkness hie thee straight:</line>
            <line>I conjure thee by all the saints in heaven!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>Peace, doting wizard, peace! I am not mad.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ADRIANA</speaker>
            <line>O, that thou wert not, poor distressed soul!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>You minion, you, are these your customers?</line>
            <line>Did this companion with the saffron face</line>
            <line>Revel and feast it at my house to-day,</line>
            <line>Whilst upon me the guilty doors were shut</line>
            <line>And I denied to enter in my house?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ADRIANA</speaker>
            <line>O husband, God doth know you dined at home;</line>
            <line>Where would you had remain'd until this time,</line>
            <line>Free from these slanders and this open shame!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>Dined at home! Thou villain, what sayest thou?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>Sir, sooth to say, you did not dine at home.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>Were not my doors lock'd up and I shut out?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>Perdie, your doors were lock'd and you shut out.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>And did not she herself revile me there?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>Sans fable, she herself reviled you there.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>Did not her kitchen-maid rail, taunt, and scorn me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>Certes, she did; the kitchen-vestal scorn'd you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>And did not I in rage depart from thence?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>In verity you did; my bones bear witness,</line>
            <line>That since have felt the vigour of his rage.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ADRIANA</speaker>
            <line>Is't good to soothe him in these contraries?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PINCH</speaker>
            <line>It is no shame: the fellow finds his vein,</line>
            <line>And yielding to him humours well his frenzy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>Thou hast suborn'd the goldsmith to arrest me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ADRIANA</speaker>
            <line>Alas, I sent you money to redeem you,</line>
            <line>By Dromio here, who came in haste for it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>Money by me! heart and goodwill you might;</line>
            <line>But surely master, not a rag of money.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>Went'st not thou to her for a purse of ducats?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ADRIANA</speaker>
            <line>He came to me and I deliver'd it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIANA</speaker>
            <line>And I am witness with her that she did.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>God and the rope-maker bear me witness</line>
            <line>That I was sent for nothing but a rope!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PINCH</speaker>
            <line>Mistress, both man and master is possess'd;</line>
            <line>I know it by their pale and deadly looks:</line>
            <line>They must be bound and laid in some dark room.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>Say, wherefore didst thou lock me forth to-day?</line>
            <line>And why dost thou deny the bag of gold?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ADRIANA</speaker>
            <line>I did not, gentle husband, lock thee forth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>And, gentle master, I received no gold;</line>
            <line>But I confess, sir, that we were lock'd out.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ADRIANA</speaker>
            <line>Dissembling villain, thou speak'st false in both.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>Dissembling harlot, thou art false in all;</line>
            <line>And art confederate with a damned pack</line>
            <line>To make a loathsome abject scorn of me:</line>
            <line>But with these nails I'll pluck out these false eyes</line>
            <line>That would behold in me this shameful sport.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter three or four, and offer to bind him.
He strives</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ADRIANA</speaker>
            <line>O, bind him, bind him! let him not come near me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PINCH</speaker>
            <line>More company! The fiend is strong within him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIANA</speaker>
            <line>Ay me, poor man, how pale and wan he looks!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>What, will you murder me? Thou gaoler, thou,</line>
            <line>I am thy prisoner: wilt thou suffer them</line>
            <line>To make a rescue?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Officer</speaker>
            <line>Masters, let him go</line>
            <line>He is my prisoner, and you shall not have him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PINCH</speaker>
            <line>Go bind this man, for he is frantic too.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>They offer to bind Dromio of Ephesus</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ADRIANA</speaker>
            <line>What wilt thou do, thou peevish officer?</line>
            <line>Hast thou delight to see a wretched man</line>
            <line>Do outrage and displeasure to himself?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Officer</speaker>
            <line>He is my prisoner: if I let him go,</line>
            <line>The debt he owes will be required of me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ADRIANA</speaker>
            <line>I will discharge thee ere I go from thee:</line>
            <line>Bear me forthwith unto his creditor,</line>
            <line>And, knowing how the debt grows, I will pay it.</line>
            <line>Good master doctor, see him safe convey'd</line>
            <line>Home to my house. O most unhappy day!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>O most unhappy strumpet!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>Master, I am here entered in bond for you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>Out on thee, villain! wherefore dost thou mad me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>Will you be bound for nothing? be mad, good master:</line>
            <line>cry 'The devil!'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIANA</speaker>
            <line>God help, poor souls, how idly do they talk!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ADRIANA</speaker>
            <line>Go bear him hence. Sister, go you with me.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt all but Adriana, Luciana, Officer and
Courtezan</stagedir>
            <line>Say now, whose suit is he arrested at?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Officer</speaker>
            <line>One Angelo, a goldsmith: do you know him?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ADRIANA</speaker>
            <line>I know the man. What is the sum he owes?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Officer</speaker>
            <line>Two hundred ducats.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ADRIANA</speaker>
            <line>Say, how grows it due?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Officer</speaker>
            <line>Due for a chain your husband had of him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ADRIANA</speaker>
            <line>He did bespeak a chain for me, but had it not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Courtezan</speaker>
            <line>When as your husband all in rage to-day</line>
            <line>Came to my house and took away my ring--</line>
            <line>The ring I saw upon his finger now--</line>
            <line>Straight after did I meet him with a chain.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ADRIANA</speaker>
            <line>It may be so, but I did never see it.</line>
            <line>Come, gaoler, bring me where the goldsmith is:</line>
            <line>I long to know the truth hereof at large.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter ANTIPHOLUS of Syracuse with his rapier drawn,
and DROMIO of Syracuse</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIANA</speaker>
            <line>God, for thy mercy! they are loose again.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ADRIANA</speaker>
            <line>And come with naked swords.</line>
            <line>Let's call more help to have them bound again.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Officer</speaker>
            <line>Away! they'll kill us.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt all but Antipholus of Syracuse and Dromio
of Syracuse</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>I see these witches are afraid of swords.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>She that would be your wife now ran from you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>Come to the Centaur; fetch our stuff from thence:</line>
            <line>I long that we were safe and sound aboard.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>Faith, stay here this night; they will surely do us</line>
            <line>no harm: you saw they speak us fair, give us gold:</line>
            <line>methinks they are such a gentle nation that, but for</line>
            <line>the mountain of mad flesh that claims marriage of</line>
            <line>me, I could find in my heart to stay here still and</line>
            <line>turn witch.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>I will not stay to-night for all the town;</line>
            <line>Therefore away, to get our stuff aboard.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>