<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:shakespear:dtd:act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-1">
   <title>ACT I</title>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  A hall in DUKE SOLINUS'S palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter DUKE SOLINUS, AEGEON, Gaoler, Officers, and other
Attendants</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AEGEON</speaker>
            <line>Proceed, Solinus, to procure my fall</line>
            <line>And by the doom of death end woes and all.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE SOLINUS</speaker>
            <line>Merchant of Syracuse, plead no more;</line>
            <line>I am not partial to infringe our laws:</line>
            <line>The enmity and discord which of late</line>
            <line>Sprung from the rancorous outrage of your duke</line>
            <line>To merchants, our well-dealing countrymen,</line>
            <line>Who wanting guilders to redeem their lives</line>
            <line>Have seal'd his rigorous statutes with their bloods,</line>
            <line>Excludes all pity from our threatening looks.</line>
            <line>For, since the mortal and intestine jars</line>
            <line>'Twixt thy seditious countrymen and us,</line>
            <line>It hath in solemn synods been decreed</line>
            <line>Both by the Syracusians and ourselves,</line>
            <line>To admit no traffic to our adverse towns Nay, more,</line>
            <line>If any born at Ephesus be seen</line>
            <line>At any Syracusian marts and fairs;</line>
            <line>Again: if any Syracusian born</line>
            <line>Come to the bay of Ephesus, he dies,</line>
            <line>His goods confiscate to the duke's dispose,</line>
            <line>Unless a thousand marks be levied,</line>
            <line>To quit the penalty and to ransom him.</line>
            <line>Thy substance, valued at the highest rate,</line>
            <line>Cannot amount unto a hundred marks;</line>
            <line>Therefore by law thou art condemned to die.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AEGEON</speaker>
            <line>Yet this my comfort: when your words are done,</line>
            <line>My woes end likewise with the evening sun.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE SOLINUS</speaker>
            <line>Well, Syracusian, say in brief the cause</line>
            <line>Why thou departed'st from thy native home</line>
            <line>And for what cause thou camest to Ephesus.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AEGEON</speaker>
            <line>A heavier task could not have been imposed</line>
            <line>Than I to speak my griefs unspeakable:</line>
            <line>Yet, that the world may witness that my end</line>
            <line>Was wrought by nature, not by vile offence,</line>
            <line>I'll utter what my sorrows give me leave.</line>
            <line>In Syracusa was I born, and wed</line>
            <line>Unto a woman, happy but for me,</line>
            <line>And by me, had not our hap been bad.</line>
            <line>With her I lived in joy; our wealth increased</line>
            <line>By prosperous voyages I often made</line>
            <line>To Epidamnum; till my factor's death</line>
            <line>And the great care of goods at random left</line>
            <line>Drew me from kind embracements of my spouse:</line>
            <line>From whom my absence was not six months old</line>
            <line>Before herself, almost at fainting under</line>
            <line>The pleasing punishment that women bear,</line>
            <line>Had made provision for her following me</line>
            <line>And soon and safe arrived where I was.</line>
            <line>There had she not been long, but she became</line>
            <line>A joyful mother of two goodly sons;</line>
            <line>And, which was strange, the one so like the other,</line>
            <line>As could not be distinguish'd but by names.</line>
            <line>That very hour, and in the self-same inn,</line>
            <line>A meaner woman was delivered</line>
            <line>Of such a burden, male twins, both alike:</line>
            <line>Those,--for their parents were exceeding poor,--</line>
            <line>I bought and brought up to attend my sons.</line>
            <line>My wife, not meanly proud of two such boys,</line>
            <line>Made daily motions for our home return:</line>
            <line>Unwilling I agreed. Alas! too soon,</line>
            <line>We came aboard.</line>
            <line>A league from Epidamnum had we sail'd,</line>
            <line>Before the always wind-obeying deep</line>
            <line>Gave any tragic instance of our harm:</line>
            <line>But longer did we not retain much hope;</line>
            <line>For what obscured light the heavens did grant</line>
            <line>Did but convey unto our fearful minds</line>
            <line>A doubtful warrant of immediate death;</line>
            <line>Which though myself would gladly have embraced,</line>
            <line>Yet the incessant weepings of my wife,</line>
            <line>Weeping before for what she saw must come,</line>
            <line>And piteous plainings of the pretty babes,</line>
            <line>That mourn'd for fashion, ignorant what to fear,</line>
            <line>Forced me to seek delays for them and me.</line>
            <line>And this it was, for other means was none:</line>
            <line>The sailors sought for safety by our boat,</line>
            <line>And left the ship, then sinking-ripe, to us:</line>
            <line>My wife, more careful for the latter-born,</line>
            <line>Had fasten'd him unto a small spare mast,</line>
            <line>Such as seafaring men provide for storms;</line>
            <line>To him one of the other twins was bound,</line>
            <line>Whilst I had been like heedful of the other:</line>
            <line>The children thus disposed, my wife and I,</line>
            <line>Fixing our eyes on whom our care was fix'd,</line>
            <line>Fasten'd ourselves at either end the mast;</line>
            <line>And floating straight, obedient to the stream,</line>
            <line>Was carried towards Corinth, as we thought.</line>
            <line>At length the sun, gazing upon the earth,</line>
            <line>Dispersed those vapours that offended us;</line>
            <line>And by the benefit of his wished light,</line>
            <line>The seas wax'd calm, and we discovered</line>
            <line>Two ships from far making amain to us,</line>
            <line>Of Corinth that, of Epidaurus this:</line>
            <line>But ere they came,--O, let me say no more!</line>
            <line>Gather the sequel by that went before.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE SOLINUS</speaker>
            <line>Nay, forward, old man; do not break off so;</line>
            <line>For we may pity, though not pardon thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AEGEON</speaker>
            <line>O, had the gods done so, I had not now</line>
            <line>Worthily term'd them merciless to us!</line>
            <line>For, ere the ships could meet by twice five leagues,</line>
            <line>We were encounterd by a mighty rock;</line>
            <line>Which being violently borne upon,</line>
            <line>Our helpful ship was splitted in the midst;</line>
            <line>So that, in this unjust divorce of us,</line>
            <line>Fortune had left to both of us alike</line>
            <line>What to delight in, what to sorrow for.</line>
            <line>Her part, poor soul! seeming as burdened</line>
            <line>With lesser weight but not with lesser woe,</line>
            <line>Was carried with more speed before the wind;</line>
            <line>And in our sight they three were taken up</line>
            <line>By fishermen of Corinth, as we thought.</line>
            <line>At length, another ship had seized on us;</line>
            <line>And, knowing whom it was their hap to save,</line>
            <line>Gave healthful welcome to their shipwreck'd guests;</line>
            <line>And would have reft the fishers of their prey,</line>
            <line>Had not their bark been very slow of sail;</line>
            <line>And therefore homeward did they bend their course.</line>
            <line>Thus have you heard me sever'd from my bliss;</line>
            <line>That by misfortunes was my life prolong'd,</line>
            <line>To tell sad stories of my own mishaps.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE SOLINUS</speaker>
            <line>And for the sake of them thou sorrowest for,</line>
            <line>Do me the favour to dilate at full</line>
            <line>What hath befall'n of them and thee till now.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AEGEON</speaker>
            <line>My youngest boy, and yet my eldest care,</line>
            <line>At eighteen years became inquisitive</line>
            <line>After his brother: and importuned me</line>
            <line>That his attendant--so his case was like,</line>
            <line>Reft of his brother, but retain'd his name--</line>
            <line>Might bear him company in the quest of him:</line>
            <line>Whom whilst I labour'd of a love to see,</line>
            <line>I hazarded the loss of whom I loved.</line>
            <line>Five summers have I spent in furthest Greece,</line>
            <line>Roaming clean through the bounds of Asia,</line>
            <line>And, coasting homeward, came to Ephesus;</line>
            <line>Hopeless to find, yet loath to leave unsought</line>
            <line>Or that or any place that harbours men.</line>
            <line>But here must end the story of my life;</line>
            <line>And happy were I in my timely death,</line>
            <line>Could all my travels warrant me they live.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE SOLINUS</speaker>
            <line>Hapless AEgeon, whom the fates have mark'd</line>
            <line>To bear the extremity of dire mishap!</line>
            <line>Now, trust me, were it not against our laws,</line>
            <line>Against my crown, my oath, my dignity,</line>
            <line>Which princes, would they, may not disannul,</line>
            <line>My soul would sue as advocate for thee.</line>
            <line>But, though thou art adjudged to the death</line>
            <line>And passed sentence may not be recall'd</line>
            <line>But to our honour's great disparagement,</line>
            <line>Yet I will favour thee in what I can.</line>
            <line>Therefore, merchant, I'll limit thee this day</line>
            <line>To seek thy life by beneficial help:</line>
            <line>Try all the friends thou hast in Ephesus;</line>
            <line>Beg thou, or borrow, to make up the sum,</line>
            <line>And live; if no, then thou art doom'd to die.</line>
            <line>Gaoler, take him to thy custody.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Gaoler</speaker>
            <line>I will, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AEGEON</speaker>
            <line>Hopeless and helpless doth AEgeon wend,</line>
            <line>But to procrastinate his lifeless end.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  The Mart.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter ANTIPHOLUS of Syracuse, DROMIO of Syracuse,
and First Merchant</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Merchant</speaker>
            <line>Therefore give out you are of Epidamnum,</line>
            <line>Lest that your goods too soon be confiscate.</line>
            <line>This very day a Syracusian merchant</line>
            <line>Is apprehended for arrival here;</line>
            <line>And not being able to buy out his life</line>
            <line>According to the statute of the town,</line>
            <line>Dies ere the weary sun set in the west.</line>
            <line>There is your money that I had to keep.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>Go bear it to the Centaur, where we host,</line>
            <line>And stay there, Dromio, till I come to thee.</line>
            <line>Within this hour it will be dinner-time:</line>
            <line>Till that, I'll view the manners of the town,</line>
            <line>Peruse the traders, gaze upon the buildings,</line>
            <line>And then return and sleep within mine inn,</line>
            <line>For with long travel I am stiff and weary.</line>
            <line>Get thee away.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>Many a man would take you at your word,</line>
            <line>And go indeed, having so good a mean.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>A trusty villain, sir, that very oft,</line>
            <line>When I am dull with care and melancholy,</line>
            <line>Lightens my humour with his merry jests.</line>
            <line>What, will you walk with me about the town,</line>
            <line>And then go to my inn and dine with me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Merchant</speaker>
            <line>I am invited, sir, to certain merchants,</line>
            <line>Of whom I hope to make much benefit;</line>
            <line>I crave your pardon. Soon at five o'clock,</line>
            <line>Please you, I'll meet with you upon the mart</line>
            <line>And afterward consort you till bed-time:</line>
            <line>My present business calls me from you now.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>Farewell till then: I will go lose myself</line>
            <line>And wander up and down to view the city.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Merchant</speaker>
            <line>Sir, I commend you to your own content.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>He that commends me to mine own content</line>
            <line>Commends me to the thing I cannot get.</line>
            <line>I to the world am like a drop of water</line>
            <line>That in the ocean seeks another drop,</line>
            <line>Who, falling there to find his fellow forth,</line>
            <line>Unseen, inquisitive, confounds himself:</line>
            <line>So I, to find a mother and a brother,</line>
            <line>In quest of them, unhappy, lose myself.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter DROMIO of Ephesus</stagedir>
            <line>Here comes the almanac of my true date.</line>
            <line>What now? how chance thou art return'd so soon?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>Return'd so soon! rather approach'd too late:</line>
            <line>The capon burns, the pig falls from the spit,</line>
            <line>The clock hath strucken twelve upon the bell;</line>
            <line>My mistress made it one upon my cheek:</line>
            <line>She is so hot because the meat is cold;</line>
            <line>The meat is cold because you come not home;</line>
            <line>You come not home because you have no stomach;</line>
            <line>You have no stomach having broke your fast;</line>
            <line>But we that know what 'tis to fast and pray</line>
            <line>Are penitent for your default to-day.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>Stop in your wind, sir: tell me this, I pray:</line>
            <line>Where have you left the money that I gave you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>O,--sixpence, that I had o' Wednesday last</line>
            <line>To pay the saddler for my mistress' crupper?</line>
            <line>The saddler had it, sir; I kept it not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>I am not in a sportive humour now:</line>
            <line>Tell me, and dally not, where is the money?</line>
            <line>We being strangers here, how darest thou trust</line>
            <line>So great a charge from thine own custody?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>I pray you, air, as you sit at dinner:</line>
            <line>I from my mistress come to you in post;</line>
            <line>If I return, I shall be post indeed,</line>
            <line>For she will score your fault upon my pate.</line>
            <line>Methinks your maw, like mine, should be your clock,</line>
            <line>And strike you home without a messenger.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>Come, Dromio, come, these jests are out of season;</line>
            <line>Reserve them till a merrier hour than this.</line>
            <line>Where is the gold I gave in charge to thee?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>To me, sir? why, you gave no gold to me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>Come on, sir knave, have done your foolishness,</line>
            <line>And tell me how thou hast disposed thy charge.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>My charge was but to fetch you from the mart</line>
            <line>Home to your house, the Phoenix, sir, to dinner:</line>
            <line>My mistress and her sister stays for you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>In what safe place you have bestow'd my money,</line>
            <line>Or I shall break that merry sconce of yours</line>
            <line>That stands on tricks when I am undisposed:</line>
            <line>Where is the thousand marks thou hadst of me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>I have some marks of yours upon my pate,</line>
            <line>Some of my mistress' marks upon my shoulders,</line>
            <line>But not a thousand marks between you both.</line>
            <line>If I should pay your worship those again,</line>
            <line>Perchance you will not bear them patiently.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>Thy mistress' marks? what mistress, slave, hast thou?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>Your worship's wife, my mistress at the Phoenix;</line>
            <line>She that doth fast till you come home to dinner,</line>
            <line>And prays that you will hie you home to dinner.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>What, wilt thou flout me thus unto my face,</line>
            <line>Being forbid? There, take you that, sir knave.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DROMIO OF EPHESUS</speaker>
            <line>What mean you, sir? for God's sake, hold your hands!</line>
            <line>Nay, and you will not, sir, I'll take my heels.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIPHOLUS OF SYRACUSE</speaker>
            <line>Upon my life, by some device or other</line>
            <line>The villain is o'er-raught of all my money.</line>
            <line>They say this town is full of cozenage,</line>
            <line>As, nimble jugglers that deceive the eye,</line>
            <line>Dark-working sorcerers that change the mind,</line>
            <line>Soul-killing witches that deform the body,</line>
            <line>Disguised cheaters, prating mountebanks,</line>
            <line>And many such-like liberties of sin:</line>
            <line>If it prove so, I will be gone the sooner.</line>
            <line>I'll to the Centaur, to go seek this slave:</line>
            <line>I greatly fear my money is not safe.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>