<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE prologue
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:shakespear:dtd:prologue" "prologue.dtd">
<prologue id="prologue">
   <title>THE PROLOGUE</title>
   <prologue-body>
      <speech>
         <speaker/>
         <line>I come no more to make you laugh: things now,</line>
         <line>That bear a weighty and a serious brow,</line>
         <line>Sad, high, and working, full of state and woe,</line>
         <line>Such noble scenes as draw the eye to flow,</line>
         <line>We now present. Those that can pity, here</line>
         <line>May, if they think it well, let fall a tear;</line>
         <line>The subject will deserve it. Such as give</line>
         <line>Their money out of hope they may believe,</line>
         <line>May here find truth too. Those that come to see</line>
         <line>Only a show or two, and so agree</line>
         <line>The play may pass, if they be still and willing,</line>
         <line>I'll undertake may see away their shilling</line>
         <line>Richly in two short hours. Only they</line>
         <line>That come to hear a merry bawdy play,</line>
         <line>A noise of targets, or to see a fellow</line>
         <line>In a long motley coat guarded with yellow,</line>
         <line>Will be deceived; for, gentle hearers, know,</line>
         <line>To rank our chosen truth with such a show</line>
         <line>As fool and fight is, beside forfeiting</line>
         <line>Our own brains, and the opinion that we bring,</line>
         <line>To make that only true we now intend,</line>
         <line>Will leave us never an understanding friend.</line>
         <line>Therefore, for goodness' sake, and as you are known</line>
         <line>The first and happiest hearers of the town,</line>
         <line>Be sad, as we would make ye: think ye see</line>
         <line>The very persons of our noble story</line>
         <line>As they were living; think you see them great,</line>
         <line>And follow'd with the general throng and sweat</line>
         <line>Of thousand friends; then in a moment, see</line>
         <line>How soon this mightiness meets misery:</line>
         <line>And, if you can be merry then, I'll say</line>
         <line>A man may weep upon his wedding-day.</line>
      </speech>
   </prologue-body>
</prologue>