<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE learningContent
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Learning Content//EN" "learningContent.dtd">
<learningContent id="SEC002">
   <title>2 Radiation from the galaxies</title>
   <learningContentbody>
      <section>
        
        
        <p>Stars occur in great collections called <i>galaxies</i>. The distribution and
          motion of galaxies provide us with the first important experimental information on which
          we shall build our understanding of the type of universe we inhabit. So, what do we know
          about galaxies?</p>
        <p>All the stars that can be distinguished by the naked eye – a few thousand
          in number – belong to one galaxy: our own Milky Way Galaxy. Sometimes it is just
          written Galaxy, with a capital G, to distinguish it from all the billions of other
          galaxies in the observable Universe.</p>
        <p>Our Galaxy has the overall shape of a flattened spiral. As shown in <xref href="#FIG001_001">Figure 1</xref>, we are halfway inside the Galaxy so the spiral
          form is not obvious to us as we look at the sky. In fact it has only been revealed by
          detailed radio mapping. This is because there are large sections of the
           Galaxy that are obscured from optical
          observations by the intervening <i>dust</i> and gas which scatter and absorb visible
          light. (However, they are essentially transparent to radio waves.) If there were an
          unobscured view through telescopes, we would be able to see to the far side of the Galaxy,
          and in doing so we would record about 10<sup>11</sup> stars within it.</p>
        <fig>
            <title>
               <b>Figure 1</b>: The Solar System is about halfway out from the centre of the Milky Way
            galaxy. We have a relatively clear view outwards from the disc to other
            galaxies</title>
            <image href="../../media/S357_1_001i.jpg"/>
            <p/>
         </fig>
        <p>Fortunately for astronomers, the stars, though vast in number, display a degree
          of uniformity which makes their classification and study possible. Their masses are
          broadly similar – most are contained within a couple of orders of magnitude, with
          our Sun having a typical average mass. They do differ considerably in size and therefore
          in density (since their masses are similar), but these differences are thought principally
          to relate to different <i>stages</i> in the life of a star rather than to different
            <i>types</i> of star. These various stages correspond to different types of nuclei
          taking part in the nuclear reactions that provide the energy output. It is one of the
          features of astrophysics that one is able to take nuclear data obtained in the laboratory
          and use them to understand the various stages of evolution seen in different stars. The
          main process in young stars is a sequence of reactions leading to the fusion of hydrogen
          nuclei to make helium nuclei. Later, helium fuses to form carbon, then carbon undergoes
          reactions which build up heavier nuclei. This can continue up to iron. The different
          reactions take place at different temperatures and pressures, so this progression of
          reactions governs the sequence in which a star changes its size and
          appearance.</p>
        
        
        <p>Stellar evolution is too slow a process for us to see any particular star undergo
          change in one human lifetime, apart from a few exceptionally young stars, and some very
          old stars undergoing gravitational collapse leading to supernova explosions. But by
          observing different stars at their respective different stages of development, it is
          possible to piece together the whole of a typical stellar life cycle.</p>
        <p>The general idea of an evolutionary sequence – one that can be
          reconstructed on a computer – is of concern in this unit for the following reason:
          when astronomers look at a very distant galaxy, they are receiving radiation that left its
          source long ago. The galaxy will, therefore, seem <i>younger</i> than it actually is now.
          The travel time for the light may have been hundreds or thousands of millions of years. To
          interpret the observations, one needs to know how the power output of the galaxy evolves
          with time.</p>
        <p>The light from a typical galaxy derives mostly from the stars it contains, with
          only a small amount from interstellar matter. So, to understand the power output of a
          galaxy one has to add together the light from about 10<sup>11</sup> stars at various
          stages of development. We cannot assume that the stars of the distant galaxy will be
          emitting the same amount of light as those of our own Galaxy today; the distant stars will
          be seen at an earlier stage in their development when perhaps their power output was
          different from what it actually is now. Indeed, there is an added complication. The
          evolution of a star depends critically on its <i>mass</i>. A very massive star will shine
          much more brightly than a less massive one, but over a much shorter time period. It could
          be that when we look at a young galaxy, we see many more massive stars living out their
          brief active lives than we observe today in our own Galaxy. So the mass distribution of
          active stars in our Galaxy might not be representative of what we see happening in the
          distant younger galaxy. It is difficult to know how to compensate for this. The mass
          distribution of the stars in a galaxy depends on the way the galaxy was formed, and
          unfortunately, the formation and growth of galaxies remains an unsolved, or at least
          poorly understood, problem.</p>
        <p>In summary, we know little about the way the power output of a galaxy changes
          with time, and this represents a severe limitation on the cosmologist's use and
          interpretation of astronomical data on power output. The frustration this causes will
          become apparent later.</p>
        <p>The light from a galaxy can tell us more than just its overall power output.
          Additional information comes from the analysis of its <i>spectrum</i>. Let us assume that
          light comes mainly from the stars and that we can ignore interstellar matter. The majority
          of galaxies are too far away for it to be possible to resolve individual stars, and
          therefore the best one can do is to take the spectrum of the galaxy as a whole:
            10<sup>11</sup> stars summed together. How can we relate this to a stellar
          spectrum?</p>
        <p>The light from a star comes from the hot layers of gas near its surface. This
          light filters out through the dilute layers above. As it does so, characteristic patterns
          of absorption lines are imprinted on the spectrum.</p>
        
        
        <p>
            <xref href="#FIG001_002">Figure 2</xref> shows part of the <i>absorption spectrum</i> of
          the Sun, compared to an <i>emission spectrum</i> produced in the laboratory.</p>
        <fig>
            <title>
               <b>Figure 2</b>: The absorption spectrum of light from the Sun, for wavelengths between
            390 nm and 450 nm. It is complicated because of the many elements involved. The bright
            lines above and below the absorption spectrum belong to the emission spectrum of a
            laboratory reference source</title>
            <image href="../../media/S357_1_002i.jpg"/>
            <p outputclass="SourceReference">Source: Hale Observatories <data name="ItemRights">
                  <data name="OwnerRef"/>
                  <data name="ItemRef"/>
                  <data name="ItemAcknowledgement">Hale Observatories</data>
               </data>
            </p>
            <p/>
         </fig>
        
        <sectiondiv outputclass="SAQ">
            <p outputclass="Heading">
               <b>Question 1</b>
            </p>
            <sectiondiv outputclass="saq.question">
               <p>A beam of white light is passed through a bulb containing calcium vapour.
              Explain, in broad terms, with the aid of diagrams, the nature of the light
              transmitted, (a) in the direction of the beam, and (b) at an angle to it.</p>
            </sectiondiv>
            <sectiondiv outputclass="saq.answer">
               <p>
                  <b>(a)</b> At position A (<xref href="#FIG001_032">Figure 3</xref>), the spectrum of the observed light consists
              of a flat continuum with absorption lines (corresponding to the transitions between
              the ground state and other states) as in <xref href="#FIG001_033">Figure 4</xref>(a).</p>
               <p>
                  <b>(b)</b> At position B, no direct light is seen. The light that is observed
              comes from calcium atoms that have been excited, and is therefore an emission spectrum
              of lines on a dark background, with the wavelengths of the lines the same as those of
              the absorption lines seen at position A. This is shown in <xref href="#FIG001_033">Figure 4</xref>(b).</p>
               <fig>
                  <title>
                     <b>Figure 3</b>: White light is passed through a bulb containing calcium vapour and
                observed at A (in the direction of the beam) and at B (at an angle to the
                beam)</title>
                  <image href="../../media/S357_1_032i.jpg"/>
                  <p/>
               </fig>
               <fig>
                  <title>
                     <b>Figure 4</b>: The spectra observed at the points A and B of Figure 3</title>
                  <image href="../../media/S357_1_033i.jpg"/>
                  <p outputclass="SourceReference">Source: 
                <data name="ItemRights">
                        <data name="OwnerRef"/>
                        <data name="ItemRef"/>
                        <data name="ItemAcknowledgement"/>
                     </data>
                  </p>
                  <p/>
               </fig>
            </sectiondiv>
        </sectiondiv>
        
        
        
        <p>The spectral lines in the light from a galaxy enable the astronomer to identify
          the elements emitting the light. Any of the ninety or so stable elements may be present,
          but the lighter elements, especially hydrogen, are usually the more abundant. Because some
          elements are common to most stars, the absorption lines of these particular elements will
          be visible in the light of the galaxy as a whole. Also, the absorption lines of magnesium,
          sodium, calcium and iron are often easy to distinguish, even though other elements, such
          as hydrogen and helium, are more abundant than these.</p>
        <p>Usually the absorption lines are sharp and identifiable, despite several effects
          which can broaden them. One of these effects is a <i>Doppler shift</i> caused by the
          rotation of the source. For example, the spectral lines of calcium atoms moving towards us
          would have their apparent frequencies systematically increased (blueshifted) according to
          the equation</p>
        <fig outputclass="Equation">
            <image href="../../media/S357_1_ue018i.gif"/>
            <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
         </fig>
        <p>where <i>f</i>
            <sub>0</sub> is the observed frequency, <i>f</i>
            <sub>1</sub> is the
          emitted frequency and <ph outputclass="InlineEquation">
               <image href="../../media/S357_1_ie00italvi.gif"/>
               <ph outputclass="inlineequation-description"/>
            </ph> is the speed of appoach.
          The spectral lines of atoms moving away from us would be correspondingly redshifted. This
          Doppler shift causes the width of a given spectral line to <i>broaden</i> if we are
          viewing the rotating galaxy along the plane of its disc so that the light-absorbing atoms
          belonging to stars on one side are moving away from us, while those on the opposite side
          are moving towards us (refer back to <xref href="#FIG001_001">Figure 1</xref>). In addition, the star itself might be rotating
          so that different parts of the star would have different components of velocity towards or
          away from us, thereby increasing the broadening. Random motions of stars can also cause
          line broadening in a similar way.</p>
        <p>The shifts and broadenings of the lines are not usually bad enough to mask the
          spectrum. Therefore, although a galaxy is a very complicated light source, its light is
          not just a meaningless jumble of fuzzy lines. There are some features, such as the calcium
          lines, which stand out sharply.</p>
        
        <sectiondiv outputclass="SAQ">
            <p outputclass="Heading">
               <b>Question 2</b>
            </p>
            <sectiondiv outputclass="saq.question">
            
               <p>(a) It can be shown that when radiation rises a height <i>H</i> near the
              Earth's surface, there is a shift in frequency towards the red end of the spectrum
              given by Δ<i>f</i>/<i>f</i> = −<i>gH/c</i>
                  <sup>2</sup>, where
                <i>g</i> is the acceleration due to gravity. When radiation starting from the
              surface of a body of mass <i>M</i> and radius <i>R</i> escapes to a large distance, it
              suffers a fractional frequency shift
                Δ<i>f</i>/<i>f</i> = −<i>GM/Rc</i>
                  <sup>2</sup>, where
                <i>G</i> is the gravitational constant. Outline the steps you would need to take to
              establish the connection between these two statements <i>without</i> necessarily
              giving the derivation. (<i>Hint:</i> Bear in mind that
                <i>g</i> = <i>GM/R</i>
                  <sup>2</sup>.)</p>
            
               <p>(b) Imagine a star with a mass
                <i>M</i> = 2 × 10<sup>30</sup> kg, a radius
                <i>R</i> = 7 × 10<sup>8</sup> m and a period of rotation
                <i>T</i> = 2 × 10<sup>6</sup> s (similar to the Sun).
              Suppose also that the typical speed of turbulent motion in the atmosphere of the star
              is 6000 m s<sup>−1</sup>. How is the frequency of the hydrogen line whose
              wavelength in the laboratory is 656 nm, affected by:</p>
            
               <p>(i) gravitational redshift;</p>
            
               <p>(ii) Doppler shift due to rotation;</p>
            
               <p>(iii) Doppler shift due to turbulence?</p>
            
               <p>(The values of <i>G</i> and <i>c</i> are given in the <xref href="http://openlearn.open.ac.uk/file.php/3639/S357Datasheets.pdf"
                        scope="external"
                        format="html">data sheet</xref>, and the formula for the Doppler shift of light is
              given in the equation above.)</p>
            
            </sectiondiv>
            <sectiondiv outputclass="saq.answer">
               <p>
                  <b>(a)</b> The result
                  Δ<i>f</i>/<i>f</i> = −<i>gH/c<sup>2</sup>
                  </i>
              applies only to small changes in height, <i>H</i>. For a large change, one must take
              account of the fact that <i>g</i> changes with height. The value of <i>g</i> is given
              by equating the weight of a body, <i>mg</i>, to the gravitational attraction. Thus at
              the surface of the Earth</p>
               <fig outputclass="Equation">
                  <image href="../../media/S357_1_ue009i.gif"/>
                  <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
               </fig>
               <p>where <i>M</i> and <i>R</i> are the mass and radius of the Earth
              respectively. At any distance <i>r</i> (greater than <i>R</i>), we may write more
              generally</p>
               <fig outputclass="Equation">
                  <image href="../../media/S357_1_ue010i.gif"/>
                  <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
               </fig>
               <p>At each distance <i>r</i>, the frequency shift caused by rising to <i>r</i> +
                <i>dr</i> is given by the formula .</p>
               <fig outputclass="Equation">
                  <image href="../../media/S357_1_ue011i.gif"/>
                  <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
               </fig>
               <p>where we write <i>dr</i> in place of <i>H</i>. Thus the total frequency shift
              suffered in escaping to a very large distance (‘infinity’) is determined
              by:</p>
               <fig outputclass="Equation">
                  <image href="../../media/S357_1_ue012i.gif"/>
                  <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
               </fig>
               <p>where <i>f</i>
                  <sub>1</sub> is the emitted frequency and <i>f</i>
                  <sub>0</sub>
              is the observed frequency. This gives the method asked for in the
              Question.</p>
               <p>Performing the integration (which the Question did <i>not</i> ask for) gives
              the stated result. In fact,</p>
               <fig outputclass="Equation">
                  <image href="../../media/S357_1_ue013i.gif"/>
                  <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
               </fig>
               <p>Provided the magnitude of Δ<i>f</i> = <i>f</i>
                  <sub>0</sub>
              −
              <i>f</i>
                  <sub>1</sub> ≪
              <i>f</i>
                  <sub>1</sub>, we can approximate the left-hand side of this equation
              by</p>
               <fig outputclass="Equation">
                  <image href="../../media/S357_1_ue014i.gif"/>
                  <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
               </fig>
               <p>and conclude that, for any emitted frequency <i>f</i>.</p>
               <fig outputclass="Equation">
                  <image href="../../media/S357_1_ue015i.gif"/>
                  <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
               </fig>
               <p>
                  <b>(b) (i)</b> Using the result of part (a), we can find the effect of the
              gravitational redshift on light leaving the star as follows:</p>
               <fig outputclass="Equation">
                  <image href="../../media/S357_1_ue016i.gif"/>
                  <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
               </fig>
               <p>All the radiation leaving the star has been ‘redshifted’ by
              this amount by the time it reaches the Earth, which we may certainly regard as at an
              ‘infinite’ distance from the star.</p>
               <p>
                  <b>(ii)</b> The speed at the edge of the star is</p>
               <fig outputclass="Equation">
                  <image href="../../media/S357_1_ue017i.gif"/>
                  <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
               </fig>
               <p>The Doppler shift is</p>
               <fig outputclass="Equation">
                  <image href="../../media/S357_1_ue018i.gif"/>
                  <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
               </fig>
               <p>
                  <i/> when <ph outputclass="InlineEquation">
                     <image href="../../media/S357_1_ie00italvi.gif"/>
                     <ph outputclass="inlineequation-description"/>
                  </ph> is a speed of
              approach. Here,</p>
               <fig outputclass="Equation">
                  <image href="../../media/S357_1_ue019i.gif"/>
                  <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
               </fig>
               <p>This could be used directly in the formula but since <ph outputclass="InlineEquation">
                     <image href="../../media/S357_1_ie00italvi.gif"/>
                     <ph outputclass="inlineequation-description"/>
                  </ph>/<i>c</i> is so small,
              we can use the approximation</p>
               <fig outputclass="Equation">
                  <image href="../../media/S357_1_ue020i.gif"/>
                  <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
               </fig>
               <p>so the fractional change in frequency, Δ<i>f</i>/<i>f</i>, is
              simply:</p>
               <fig outputclass="Equation">
                  <image href="../../media/S357_1_ue021i.gif"/>
                  <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
               </fig>
               <p>Light from the advancing limb is blueshifted by this amount, and from the
              receding limb is redshifted by this amount. The width imparted to lines is thus the
              fraction 14.7 ×10<sup>−6</sup> of their central frequency.</p>
               <p>
                  <b>(iii)</b> The turbulent motion again produces both blueshifts and
              redshifts, of amount ±6000 m
                s<sup>−1</sup>/<i>c</i> = ±20 × 10<sup>−6</sup>.</p>
               <p>The frequency of the 656 nm line is given by</p>
               <fig outputclass="Equation">
                  <image href="../../media/S357_1_ue022i.gif"/>
                  <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
               </fig>
               <p>The frequency shifts are therefore as shown in <xref href="#TBL003">Table 1</xref>.</p>
               <table>
                  <title>Table 1</title>
                  <tgroup cols="5">
                     <tbody>
                        <row>
                           <entry outputclass="th">
                              <b/>
                           </entry>
                           <entry outputclass="th">
                              <b/>
                           </entry>
                           <entry outputclass="th">
                              <b>Δ<i>f</i>/<i>f</i>
                              </b>
                           </entry>
                           <entry outputclass="th">
                              <b/>
                           </entry>
                           <entry outputclass="th">
                              <b>Δ<i>f/</i>MHz</b>
                           </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <entry>gravitation</entry>
                           <entry outputclass="th">
                              <b/>
                           </entry>
                           <entry>−2.12 × 10<sup>−6</sup>
                           </entry>
                           <entry outputclass="th">
                              <b/>
                           </entry>
                           <entry>−970</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <entry>rotation</entry>
                           <entry outputclass="th">
                              <b/>
                           </entry>
                           <entry>±7.33 × 10<sup>−6</sup>
                           </entry>
                           <entry outputclass="th">
                              <b/>
                           </entry>
                           <entry>±3350</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <entry>turbulence</entry>
                           <entry outputclass="th">
                              <b/>
                           </entry>
                           <entry>±20 × 10<sup>−6</sup>
                           </entry>
                           <entry outputclass="th">
                              <b/>
                           </entry>
                           <entry>±9150</entry>
                        </row>
                     </tbody>
                  </tgroup>
               </table>
               <p outputclass="SourceReference">Source: </p>
            </sectiondiv>
        </sectiondiv>
        <p> </p>
        <p>In many galaxies, spectral lines have been observed whose <i>relative</i>
          positions correspond exactly with those of a known element (so that the spectrum is
          confidently identified), but whose <i>absolute</i> frequencies are all noticeably shifted.
          This can have nothing to do with the random motions of the stars within the galaxy, or the
          rotations of either the individual stars or of the galaxy as a whole; all these motions
          (being as often towards us as away from us) would merely broaden the line. A net shift of
          all the lines in a spectrum seems to suggest that the galaxy itself has a line-of-sight
          motion (i.e. a component of velocity towards or away from us). The shift is nearly always
          to longer wavelengths, i.e. towards the red end of the visible spectrum, so it is referred
          to as the ‘redshift’. If the redshift is interpreted as a Doppler shift (an
          interpretation we shall reconsider later) due to the motion of the galaxies, then it
          follows that most of the galaxies are receding from us. In other words, <i>the Universe is
            expanding</i>.</p>
        <p>The term ‘redshift’ has a precise definition: it is equal to
          Δλ/λ, where Δλ is the shift in wavelength of a line whose
          emitted wavelength is λ. The value of Δλ/λ is the same for all the
          lines in the spectrum of an object receding at a given speed, and is normally denoted by
            <i>z:</i>
         </p>
        <fig outputclass="Equation">
            <image href="../../media/S357_1_e001i.gif"/>
            <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
         </fig>
        <p>where λ<sub>0</sub> is the observed wavelength now, and λ<sub>1</sub>
          is the wavelength at emission. These redshifts in the spectra of galaxies are generally
            <i>far</i> larger than the stellar effects considered in <xref href="#SAQ001_002">Question 2</xref>, as can be judged from <xref href="#FIG001_003">Figure 5</xref>.</p>
        <fig>
            <title>
               <b>Figure 5</b>: The absorption spectra of five different galaxies. Only the most
            strongly absorbed lines, common to the bulk of the stars, are visible, but this is
            enough to give a recognisable pattern</title>
            <image href="../../media/S357_1_003i.jpg"/>
            <p outputclass="SourceReference">Source: Hale Observatories <data name="ItemRights">
                  <data name="OwnerRef"/>
                  <data name="ItemRef"/>
                  <data name="ItemAcknowledgement">Hale Observatories</data>
               </data>
            </p>
            <p/>
         </fig>
        
        <p>In summary then, when dealing with light from stars, there are three ways in
          which the frequency can be shifted:</p>
        <p>(i) The Doppler shift due to motion – whether that arises through the
          rotation of the star, its bodily motion along the line of sight, or turbulence in its
          atmosphere. This type of shift, which can be red or blue, is accounted for by special
          relativity.</p>
        <p>(ii) The gravitational redshift, arising from general relativity.</p>
        <p>(iii) A new type of redshift due to the recession of the galaxies,
          which is also a consequence of general
          relativity.</p>
        <p>(Note that it is customary to reserve the suffix, 0, for the values of quantities
          as they are at the present time, <i>t</i>
            <sub>0</sub>. Values at other times must carry
          some other suffix. In this way, we end up with the rather counterintuitive situation where
            λ<sub>1</sub> applies to an <i>earlier</i> time, <i>t</i>
            <sub>1</sub>, than
            λ<sub>0</sub>.)</p>
        
        <sectiondiv outputclass="SAQ">
            <p outputclass="Heading">
               <b>Question 3</b>
            </p>
            <sectiondiv outputclass="saq.question">
               <p>Hydrogen has emission lines at 434, 486 and 656 nm. A galaxy is observed to
              have these three lines redshifted in wavelength by 2% (i.e.
              <i>z</i> = Δλ/λ = 0.02). What wavelengths will
              be observed? What is the frequency shift Δ<i>f</i>/<i>f</i> ?</p>
            </sectiondiv>
            <sectiondiv outputclass="saq.answer">
               <p>If λ<sub>1</sub> is the emitted wavelength and λ<sub>0</sub> is
              the observed wavelength, then</p>
               <fig outputclass="Equation">
                  <image href="../../media/S357_1_ue023i.gif"/>
                  <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
               </fig>
               <p>Therefore</p>
               <fig outputclass="Equation">
                  <image href="../../media/S357_1_ue024i.gif"/>
                  <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
               </fig>
               <p>Thus the observed wavelengths are:</p>
               <fig outputclass="Equation">
                  <image href="../../media/S357_1_ue025i.gif"/>
                  <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
               </fig>
               <p>The relative frequency shift is given by</p>
               <fig outputclass="Equation">
                  <image href="../../media/S357_1_ue026i.gif"/>
                  <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
               </fig>
               <p>But</p>
               <fig outputclass="Equation">
                  <image href="../../media/S357_1_ue027i.gif"/>
                  <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
               </fig>
               <p>Therefore</p>
               <fig outputclass="Equation">
                  <image href="../../media/S357_1_ue028i.gif"/>
                  <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
               </fig>
               <p>and</p>
               <fig outputclass="Equation">
                  <image href="../../media/S357_1_ue029i.gif"/>
                  <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
               </fig>
               <p>Note that the shift in frequency is the same for all lines of the spectrum,
              but differs from the shift in wavelength, which is <i>z</i>.</p>
            </sectiondiv>
        </sectiondiv>
        
        <p>As we shall see later in this unit, the redshift in galactic light has provided
          one of the main clues to the nature of the large-scale structure of spacetime. But to
          discover how the pattern of the redshifts observed in different galaxies reveals this
          structure, we need further information about the distances of galaxies.</p>
      </section>
   </learningContentbody>
</learningContent>