<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:shakespear:dtd:act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-2">
   <title>ACT II</title>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  Belmont. A room in PORTIA'S house.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Flourish of cornets. Enter the PRINCE OF MOROCCO
and his train; PORTIA, NERISSA, and others
attending</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOROCCO</speaker>
            <line>Mislike me not for my complexion,</line>
            <line>The shadow'd livery of the burnish'd sun,</line>
            <line>To whom I am a neighbour and near bred.</line>
            <line>Bring me the fairest creature northward born,</line>
            <line>Where Phoebus' fire scarce thaws the icicles,</line>
            <line>And let us make incision for your love,</line>
            <line>To prove whose blood is reddest, his or mine.</line>
            <line>I tell thee, lady, this aspect of mine</line>
            <line>Hath fear'd the valiant: by my love I swear</line>
            <line>The best-regarded virgins of our clime</line>
            <line>Have loved it too: I would not change this hue,</line>
            <line>Except to steal your thoughts, my gentle queen.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PORTIA</speaker>
            <line>In terms of choice I am not solely led</line>
            <line>By nice direction of a maiden's eyes;</line>
            <line>Besides, the lottery of my destiny</line>
            <line>Bars me the right of voluntary choosing:</line>
            <line>But if my father had not scanted me</line>
            <line>And hedged me by his wit, to yield myself</line>
            <line>His wife who wins me by that means I told you,</line>
            <line>Yourself, renowned prince, then stood as fair</line>
            <line>As any comer I have look'd on yet</line>
            <line>For my affection.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOROCCO</speaker>
            <line>Even for that I thank you:</line>
            <line>Therefore, I pray you, lead me to the caskets</line>
            <line>To try my fortune. By this scimitar</line>
            <line>That slew the Sophy and a Persian prince</line>
            <line>That won three fields of Sultan Solyman,</line>
            <line>I would outstare the sternest eyes that look,</line>
            <line>Outbrave the heart most daring on the earth,</line>
            <line>Pluck the young sucking cubs from the she-bear,</line>
            <line>Yea, mock the lion when he roars for prey,</line>
            <line>To win thee, lady. But, alas the while!</line>
            <line>If Hercules and Lichas play at dice</line>
            <line>Which is the better man, the greater throw</line>
            <line>May turn by fortune from the weaker hand:</line>
            <line>So is Alcides beaten by his page;</line>
            <line>And so may I, blind fortune leading me,</line>
            <line>Miss that which one unworthier may attain,</line>
            <line>And die with grieving.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PORTIA</speaker>
            <line>You must take your chance,</line>
            <line>And either not attempt to choose at all</line>
            <line>Or swear before you choose, if you choose wrong</line>
            <line>Never to speak to lady afterward</line>
            <line>In way of marriage: therefore be advised.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOROCCO</speaker>
            <line>Nor will not. Come, bring me unto my chance.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PORTIA</speaker>
            <line>First, forward to the temple: after dinner</line>
            <line>Your hazard shall be made.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOROCCO</speaker>
            <line>Good fortune then!</line>
            <line>To make me blest or cursed'st among men.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Cornets, and exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  Venice. A street.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter LAUNCELOT</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAUNCELOT</speaker>
            <line>Certainly my conscience will serve me to run from</line>
            <line>this Jew my master. The fiend is at mine elbow and</line>
            <line>tempts me saying to me 'Gobbo, Launcelot Gobbo, good</line>
            <line>Launcelot,' or 'good Gobbo,' or good Launcelot</line>
            <line>Gobbo, use your legs, take the start, run away. My</line>
            <line>conscience says 'No; take heed,' honest Launcelot;</line>
            <line>take heed, honest Gobbo, or, as aforesaid, 'honest</line>
            <line>Launcelot Gobbo; do not run; scorn running with thy</line>
            <line>heels.' Well, the most courageous fiend bids me</line>
            <line>pack: 'Via!' says the fiend; 'away!' says the</line>
            <line>fiend; 'for the heavens, rouse up a brave mind,'</line>
            <line>says the fiend, 'and run.' Well, my conscience,</line>
            <line>hanging about the neck of my heart, says very wisely</line>
            <line>to me 'My honest friend Launcelot, being an honest</line>
            <line>man's son,' or rather an honest woman's son; for,</line>
            <line>indeed, my father did something smack, something</line>
            <line>grow to, he had a kind of taste; well, my conscience</line>
            <line>says 'Launcelot, budge not.' 'Budge,' says the</line>
            <line>fiend. 'Budge not,' says my conscience.</line>
            <line>'Conscience,' say I, 'you counsel well;' ' Fiend,'</line>
            <line>say I, 'you counsel well:' to be ruled by my</line>
            <line>conscience, I should stay with the Jew my master,</line>
            <line>who, God bless the mark, is a kind of devil; and, to</line>
            <line>run away from the Jew, I should be ruled by the</line>
            <line>fiend, who, saving your reverence, is the devil</line>
            <line>himself. Certainly the Jew is the very devil</line>
            <line>incarnal; and, in my conscience, my conscience is</line>
            <line>but a kind of hard conscience, to offer to counsel</line>
            <line>me to stay with the Jew. The fiend gives the more</line>
            <line>friendly counsel: I will run, fiend; my heels are</line>
            <line>at your command; I will run.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter Old GOBBO, with a basket</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GOBBO</speaker>
            <line>Master young man, you, I pray you, which is the way</line>
            <line>to master Jew's?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAUNCELOT</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  O heavens, this is my true-begotten father!</line>
            <line>who, being more than sand-blind, high-gravel blind,</line>
            <line>knows me not: I will try confusions with him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GOBBO</speaker>
            <line>Master young gentleman, I pray you, which is the way</line>
            <line>to master Jew's?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAUNCELOT</speaker>
            <line>Turn up on your right hand at the next turning, but,</line>
            <line>at the next turning of all, on your left; marry, at</line>
            <line>the very next turning, turn of no hand, but turn</line>
            <line>down indirectly to the Jew's house.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GOBBO</speaker>
            <line>By God's sonties, 'twill be a hard way to hit. Can</line>
            <line>you tell me whether one Launcelot,</line>
            <line>that dwells with him, dwell with him or no?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAUNCELOT</speaker>
            <line>Talk you of young Master Launcelot?</line>
            <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>
            <line>Mark me now; now will I raise the waters. Talk you</line>
            <line>of young Master Launcelot?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GOBBO</speaker>
            <line>No master, sir, but a poor man's son: his father,</line>
            <line>though I say it, is an honest exceeding poor man</line>
            <line>and, God be thanked, well to live.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAUNCELOT</speaker>
            <line>Well, let his father be what a' will, we talk of</line>
            <line>young Master Launcelot.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GOBBO</speaker>
            <line>Your worship's friend and Launcelot, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAUNCELOT</speaker>
            <line>But I pray you, ergo, old man, ergo, I beseech you,</line>
            <line>talk you of young Master Launcelot?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GOBBO</speaker>
            <line>Of Launcelot, an't please your mastership.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAUNCELOT</speaker>
            <line>Ergo, Master Launcelot. Talk not of Master</line>
            <line>Launcelot, father; for the young gentleman,</line>
            <line>according to Fates and Destinies and such odd</line>
            <line>sayings, the Sisters Three and such branches of</line>
            <line>learning, is indeed deceased, or, as you would say</line>
            <line>in plain terms, gone to heaven.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GOBBO</speaker>
            <line>Marry, God forbid! the boy was the very staff of my</line>
            <line>age, my very prop.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAUNCELOT</speaker>
            <line>Do I look like a cudgel or a hovel-post, a staff or</line>
            <line>a prop? Do you know me, father?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GOBBO</speaker>
            <line>Alack the day, I know you not, young gentleman:</line>
            <line>but, I pray you, tell me, is my boy, God rest his</line>
            <line>soul, alive or dead?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAUNCELOT</speaker>
            <line>Do you not know me, father?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GOBBO</speaker>
            <line>Alack, sir, I am sand-blind; I know you not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAUNCELOT</speaker>
            <line>Nay, indeed, if you had your eyes, you might fail of</line>
            <line>the knowing me: it is a wise father that knows his</line>
            <line>own child. Well, old man, I will tell you news of</line>
            <line>your son: give me your blessing: truth will come</line>
            <line>to light; murder cannot be hid long; a man's son</line>
            <line>may, but at the length truth will out.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GOBBO</speaker>
            <line>Pray you, sir, stand up: I am sure you are not</line>
            <line>Launcelot, my boy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAUNCELOT</speaker>
            <line>Pray you, let's have no more fooling about it, but</line>
            <line>give me your blessing: I am Launcelot, your boy</line>
            <line>that was, your son that is, your child that shall</line>
            <line>be.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GOBBO</speaker>
            <line>I cannot think you are my son.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAUNCELOT</speaker>
            <line>I know not what I shall think of that: but I am</line>
            <line>Launcelot, the Jew's man, and I am sure Margery your</line>
            <line>wife is my mother.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GOBBO</speaker>
            <line>Her name is Margery, indeed: I'll be sworn, if thou</line>
            <line>be Launcelot, thou art mine own flesh and blood.</line>
            <line>Lord worshipped might he be! what a beard hast thou</line>
            <line>got! thou hast got more hair on thy chin than</line>
            <line>Dobbin my fill-horse has on his tail.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAUNCELOT</speaker>
            <line>It should seem, then, that Dobbin's tail grows</line>
            <line>backward: I am sure he had more hair of his tail</line>
            <line>than I have of my face when I last saw him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GOBBO</speaker>
            <line>Lord, how art thou changed! How dost thou and thy</line>
            <line>master agree? I have brought him a present. How</line>
            <line>'gree you now?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAUNCELOT</speaker>
            <line>Well, well: but, for mine own part, as I have set</line>
            <line>up my rest to run away, so I will not rest till I</line>
            <line>have run some ground. My master's a very Jew: give</line>
            <line>him a present! give him a halter: I am famished in</line>
            <line>his service; you may tell every finger I have with</line>
            <line>my ribs. Father, I am glad you are come: give me</line>
            <line>your present to one Master Bassanio, who, indeed,</line>
            <line>gives rare new liveries: if I serve not him, I</line>
            <line>will run as far as God has any ground. O rare</line>
            <line>fortune! here comes the man: to him, father; for I</line>
            <line>am a Jew, if I serve the Jew any longer.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter BASSANIO, with LEONARDO and other followers</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSANIO</speaker>
            <line>You may do so; but let it be so hasted that supper</line>
            <line>be ready at the farthest by five of the clock. See</line>
            <line>these letters delivered; put the liveries to making,</line>
            <line>and desire Gratiano to come anon to my lodging.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit a Servant</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAUNCELOT</speaker>
            <line>To him, father.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GOBBO</speaker>
            <line>God bless your worship!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSANIO</speaker>
            <line>Gramercy! wouldst thou aught with me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GOBBO</speaker>
            <line>Here's my son, sir, a poor boy,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAUNCELOT</speaker>
            <line>Not a poor boy, sir, but the rich Jew's man; that</line>
            <line>would, sir, as my father shall specify--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GOBBO</speaker>
            <line>He hath a great infection, sir, as one would say, to serve--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAUNCELOT</speaker>
            <line>Indeed, the short and the long is, I serve the Jew,</line>
            <line>and have a desire, as my father shall specify--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GOBBO</speaker>
            <line>His master and he, saving your worship's reverence,</line>
            <line>are scarce cater-cousins--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAUNCELOT</speaker>
            <line>To be brief, the very truth is that the Jew, having</line>
            <line>done me wrong, doth cause me, as my father, being, I</line>
            <line>hope, an old man, shall frutify unto you--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GOBBO</speaker>
            <line>I have here a dish of doves that I would bestow upon</line>
            <line>your worship, and my suit is--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAUNCELOT</speaker>
            <line>In very brief, the suit is impertinent to myself, as</line>
            <line>your worship shall know by this honest old man; and,</line>
            <line>though I say it, though old man, yet poor man, my father.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSANIO</speaker>
            <line>One speak for both. What would you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAUNCELOT</speaker>
            <line>Serve you, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GOBBO</speaker>
            <line>That is the very defect of the matter, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSANIO</speaker>
            <line>I know thee well; thou hast obtain'd thy suit:</line>
            <line>Shylock thy master spoke with me this day,</line>
            <line>And hath preferr'd thee, if it be preferment</line>
            <line>To leave a rich Jew's service, to become</line>
            <line>The follower of so poor a gentleman.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAUNCELOT</speaker>
            <line>The old proverb is very well parted between my</line>
            <line>master Shylock and you, sir: you have the grace of</line>
            <line>God, sir, and he hath enough.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSANIO</speaker>
            <line>Thou speak'st it well. Go, father, with thy son.</line>
            <line>Take leave of thy old master and inquire</line>
            <line>My lodging out. Give him a livery</line>
            <line>More guarded than his fellows': see it done.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAUNCELOT</speaker>
            <line>Father, in. I cannot get a service, no; I have</line>
            <line>ne'er a tongue in my head. Well, if any man in</line>
            <line>Italy have a fairer table which doth offer to swear</line>
            <line>upon a book, I shall have good fortune. Go to,</line>
            <line>here's a simple line of life: here's a small trifle</line>
            <line>of wives: alas, fifteen wives is nothing! eleven</line>
            <line>widows and nine maids is a simple coming-in for one</line>
            <line>man: and then to 'scape drowning thrice, and to be</line>
            <line>in peril of my life with the edge of a feather-bed;</line>
            <line>here are simple scapes. Well, if Fortune be a</line>
            <line>woman, she's a good wench for this gear. Father,</line>
            <line>come; I'll take my leave of the Jew in the twinkling of an eye.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt Launcelot and Old Gobbo</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSANIO</speaker>
            <line>I pray thee, good Leonardo, think on this:</line>
            <line>These things being bought and orderly bestow'd,</line>
            <line>Return in haste, for I do feast to-night</line>
            <line>My best-esteem'd acquaintance: hie thee, go.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONARDO</speaker>
            <line>My best endeavours shall be done herein.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter GRATIANO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRATIANO</speaker>
            <line>Where is your master?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONARDO</speaker>
            <line>Yonder, sir, he walks.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRATIANO</speaker>
            <line>Signior Bassanio!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSANIO</speaker>
            <line>Gratiano!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRATIANO</speaker>
            <line>I have a suit to you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSANIO</speaker>
            <line>You have obtain'd it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRATIANO</speaker>
            <line>You must not deny me: I must go with you to Belmont.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSANIO</speaker>
            <line>Why then you must. But hear thee, Gratiano;</line>
            <line>Thou art too wild, too rude and bold of voice;</line>
            <line>Parts that become thee happily enough</line>
            <line>And in such eyes as ours appear not faults;</line>
            <line>But where thou art not known, why, there they show</line>
            <line>Something too liberal. Pray thee, take pain</line>
            <line>To allay with some cold drops of modesty</line>
            <line>Thy skipping spirit, lest through thy wild behavior</line>
            <line>I be misconstrued in the place I go to,</line>
            <line>And lose my hopes.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRATIANO</speaker>
            <line>Signior Bassanio, hear me:</line>
            <line>If I do not put on a sober habit,</line>
            <line>Talk with respect and swear but now and then,</line>
            <line>Wear prayer-books in my pocket, look demurely,</line>
            <line>Nay more, while grace is saying, hood mine eyes</line>
            <line>Thus with my hat, and sigh and say 'amen,'</line>
            <line>Use all the observance of civility,</line>
            <line>Like one well studied in a sad ostent</line>
            <line>To please his grandam, never trust me more.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSANIO</speaker>
            <line>Well, we shall see your bearing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRATIANO</speaker>
            <line>Nay, but I bar to-night: you shall not gauge me</line>
            <line>By what we do to-night.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSANIO</speaker>
            <line>No, that were pity:</line>
            <line>I would entreat you rather to put on</line>
            <line>Your boldest suit of mirth, for we have friends</line>
            <line>That purpose merriment. But fare you well:</line>
            <line>I have some business.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRATIANO</speaker>
            <line>And I must to Lorenzo and the rest:</line>
            <line>But we will visit you at supper-time.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  The same. A room in SHYLOCK'S house.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter JESSICA and LAUNCELOT</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JESSICA</speaker>
            <line>I am sorry thou wilt leave my father so:</line>
            <line>Our house is hell, and thou, a merry devil,</line>
            <line>Didst rob it of some taste of tediousness.</line>
            <line>But fare thee well, there is a ducat for thee:</line>
            <line>And, Launcelot, soon at supper shalt thou see</line>
            <line>Lorenzo, who is thy new master's guest:</line>
            <line>Give him this letter; do it secretly;</line>
            <line>And so farewell: I would not have my father</line>
            <line>See me in talk with thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAUNCELOT</speaker>
            <line>Adieu! tears exhibit my tongue. Most beautiful</line>
            <line>pagan, most sweet Jew! if a Christian did not play</line>
            <line>the knave and get thee, I am much deceived. But,</line>
            <line>adieu: these foolish drops do something drown my</line>
            <line>manly spirit: adieu.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JESSICA</speaker>
            <line>Farewell, good Launcelot.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit Launcelot</stagedir>
            <line>Alack, what heinous sin is it in me</line>
            <line>To be ashamed to be my father's child!</line>
            <line>But though I am a daughter to his blood,</line>
            <line>I am not to his manners. O Lorenzo,</line>
            <line>If thou keep promise, I shall end this strife,</line>
            <line>Become a Christian and thy loving wife.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-4">
      <title>SCENE IV.  The same. A street.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter GRATIANO, LORENZO, SALARINO, and SALANIO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORENZO</speaker>
            <line>Nay, we will slink away in supper-time,</line>
            <line>Disguise us at my lodging and return,</line>
            <line>All in an hour.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRATIANO</speaker>
            <line>We have not made good preparation.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALARINO</speaker>
            <line>We have not spoke us yet of torchbearers.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALANIO</speaker>
            <line>'Tis vile, unless it may be quaintly order'd,</line>
            <line>And better in my mind not undertook.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORENZO</speaker>
            <line>'Tis now but four o'clock: we have two hours</line>
            <line>To furnish us.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter LAUNCELOT, with a letter</stagedir>
            <line>Friend Launcelot, what's the news?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAUNCELOT</speaker>
            <line>An it shall please you to break up</line>
            <line>this, it shall seem to signify.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORENZO</speaker>
            <line>I know the hand: in faith, 'tis a fair hand;</line>
            <line>And whiter than the paper it writ on</line>
            <line>Is the fair hand that writ.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRATIANO</speaker>
            <line>Love-news, in faith.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAUNCELOT</speaker>
            <line>By your leave, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORENZO</speaker>
            <line>Whither goest thou?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAUNCELOT</speaker>
            <line>Marry, sir, to bid my old master the</line>
            <line>Jew to sup to-night with my new master the Christian.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORENZO</speaker>
            <line>Hold here, take this: tell gentle Jessica</line>
            <line>I will not fail her; speak it privately.</line>
            <line>Go, gentlemen,</line>
            <stagedir>Exit Launcelot</stagedir>
            <line>Will you prepare you for this masque tonight?</line>
            <line>I am provided of a torch-bearer.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALANIO</speaker>
            <line>Ay, marry, I'll be gone about it straight.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALANIO</speaker>
            <line>And so will I.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORENZO</speaker>
            <line>Meet me and Gratiano</line>
            <line>At Gratiano's lodging some hour hence.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALARINO</speaker>
            <line>'Tis good we do so.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt SALARINO and SALANIO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRATIANO</speaker>
            <line>Was not that letter from fair Jessica?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORENZO</speaker>
            <line>I must needs tell thee all. She hath directed</line>
            <line>How I shall take her from her father's house,</line>
            <line>What gold and jewels she is furnish'd with,</line>
            <line>What page's suit she hath in readiness.</line>
            <line>If e'er the Jew her father come to heaven,</line>
            <line>It will be for his gentle daughter's sake:</line>
            <line>And never dare misfortune cross her foot,</line>
            <line>Unless she do it under this excuse,</line>
            <line>That she is issue to a faithless Jew.</line>
            <line>Come, go with me; peruse this as thou goest:</line>
            <line>Fair Jessica shall be my torch-bearer.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-5">
      <title>SCENE V.  The same. Before SHYLOCK'S house.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter SHYLOCK and LAUNCELOT</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>
            <line>Well, thou shalt see, thy eyes shall be thy judge,</line>
            <line>The difference of old Shylock and Bassanio:--</line>
            <line>What, Jessica!--thou shalt not gormandise,</line>
            <line>As thou hast done with me:--What, Jessica!--</line>
            <line>And sleep and snore, and rend apparel out;--</line>
            <line>Why, Jessica, I say!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAUNCELOT</speaker>
            <line>Why, Jessica!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>
            <line>Who bids thee call? I do not bid thee call.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAUNCELOT</speaker>
            <line>Your worship was wont to tell me that</line>
            <line>I could do nothing without bidding.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter Jessica</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JESSICA</speaker>
            <line>Call you? what is your will?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>
            <line>I am bid forth to supper, Jessica:</line>
            <line>There are my keys. But wherefore should I go?</line>
            <line>I am not bid for love; they flatter me:</line>
            <line>But yet I'll go in hate, to feed upon</line>
            <line>The prodigal Christian. Jessica, my girl,</line>
            <line>Look to my house. I am right loath to go:</line>
            <line>There is some ill a-brewing towards my rest,</line>
            <line>For I did dream of money-bags to-night.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAUNCELOT</speaker>
            <line>I beseech you, sir, go: my young master doth expect</line>
            <line>your reproach.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>
            <line>So do I his.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAUNCELOT</speaker>
            <line>An they have conspired together, I will not say you</line>
            <line>shall see a masque; but if you do, then it was not</line>
            <line>for nothing that my nose fell a-bleeding on</line>
            <line>Black-Monday last at six o'clock i' the morning,</line>
            <line>falling out that year on Ash-Wednesday was four</line>
            <line>year, in the afternoon.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>
            <line>What, are there masques? Hear you me, Jessica:</line>
            <line>Lock up my doors; and when you hear the drum</line>
            <line>And the vile squealing of the wry-neck'd fife,</line>
            <line>Clamber not you up to the casements then,</line>
            <line>Nor thrust your head into the public street</line>
            <line>To gaze on Christian fools with varnish'd faces,</line>
            <line>But stop my house's ears, I mean my casements:</line>
            <line>Let not the sound of shallow foppery enter</line>
            <line>My sober house. By Jacob's staff, I swear,</line>
            <line>I have no mind of feasting forth to-night:</line>
            <line>But I will go. Go you before me, sirrah;</line>
            <line>Say I will come.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAUNCELOT</speaker>
            <line>I will go before, sir. Mistress, look out at</line>
            <line>window, for all this, There will come a Christian</line>
            <line>boy, will be worth a Jewess' eye.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>
            <line>What says that fool of Hagar's offspring, ha?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JESSICA</speaker>
            <line>His words were 'Farewell mistress;' nothing else.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>
            <line>The patch is kind enough, but a huge feeder;</line>
            <line>Snail-slow in profit, and he sleeps by day</line>
            <line>More than the wild-cat: drones hive not with me;</line>
            <line>Therefore I part with him, and part with him</line>
            <line>To one that would have him help to waste</line>
            <line>His borrow'd purse. Well, Jessica, go in;</line>
            <line>Perhaps I will return immediately:</line>
            <line>Do as I bid you; shut doors after you:</line>
            <line>Fast bind, fast find;</line>
            <line>A proverb never stale in thrifty mind.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JESSICA</speaker>
            <line>Farewell; and if my fortune be not crost,</line>
            <line>I have a father, you a daughter, lost.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-6">
      <title>SCENE VI.  The same.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter GRATIANO and SALARINO, masqued</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRATIANO</speaker>
            <line>This is the pent-house under which Lorenzo</line>
            <line>Desired us to make stand.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALARINO</speaker>
            <line>His hour is almost past.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRATIANO</speaker>
            <line>And it is marvel he out-dwells his hour,</line>
            <line>For lovers ever run before the clock.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALARINO</speaker>
            <line>O, ten times faster Venus' pigeons fly</line>
            <line>To seal love's bonds new-made, than they are wont</line>
            <line>To keep obliged faith unforfeited!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRATIANO</speaker>
            <line>That ever holds: who riseth from a feast</line>
            <line>With that keen appetite that he sits down?</line>
            <line>Where is the horse that doth untread again</line>
            <line>His tedious measures with the unbated fire</line>
            <line>That he did pace them first? All things that are,</line>
            <line>Are with more spirit chased than enjoy'd.</line>
            <line>How like a younker or a prodigal</line>
            <line>The scarfed bark puts from her native bay,</line>
            <line>Hugg'd and embraced by the strumpet wind!</line>
            <line>How like the prodigal doth she return,</line>
            <line>With over-weather'd ribs and ragged sails,</line>
            <line>Lean, rent and beggar'd by the strumpet wind!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALARINO</speaker>
            <line>Here comes Lorenzo: more of this hereafter.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter LORENZO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORENZO</speaker>
            <line>Sweet friends, your patience for my long abode;</line>
            <line>Not I, but my affairs, have made you wait:</line>
            <line>When you shall please to play the thieves for wives,</line>
            <line>I'll watch as long for you then. Approach;</line>
            <line>Here dwells my father Jew. Ho! who's within?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter JESSICA, above, in boy's clothes</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JESSICA</speaker>
            <line>Who are you? Tell me, for more certainty,</line>
            <line>Albeit I'll swear that I do know your tongue.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORENZO</speaker>
            <line>Lorenzo, and thy love.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JESSICA</speaker>
            <line>Lorenzo, certain, and my love indeed,</line>
            <line>For who love I so much? And now who knows</line>
            <line>But you, Lorenzo, whether I am yours?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORENZO</speaker>
            <line>Heaven and thy thoughts are witness that thou art.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JESSICA</speaker>
            <line>Here, catch this casket; it is worth the pains.</line>
            <line>I am glad 'tis night, you do not look on me,</line>
            <line>For I am much ashamed of my exchange:</line>
            <line>But love is blind and lovers cannot see</line>
            <line>The pretty follies that themselves commit;</line>
            <line>For if they could, Cupid himself would blush</line>
            <line>To see me thus transformed to a boy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORENZO</speaker>
            <line>Descend, for you must be my torchbearer.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JESSICA</speaker>
            <line>What, must I hold a candle to my shames?</line>
            <line>They in themselves, good-sooth, are too too light.</line>
            <line>Why, 'tis an office of discovery, love;</line>
            <line>And I should be obscured.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORENZO</speaker>
            <line>So are you, sweet,</line>
            <line>Even in the lovely garnish of a boy.</line>
            <line>But come at once;</line>
            <line>For the close night doth play the runaway,</line>
            <line>And we are stay'd for at Bassanio's feast.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JESSICA</speaker>
            <line>I will make fast the doors, and gild myself</line>
            <line>With some more ducats, and be with you straight.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit above</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRATIANO</speaker>
            <line>Now, by my hood, a Gentile and no Jew.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORENZO</speaker>
            <line>Beshrew me but I love her heartily;</line>
            <line>For she is wise, if I can judge of her,</line>
            <line>And fair she is, if that mine eyes be true,</line>
            <line>And true she is, as she hath proved herself,</line>
            <line>And therefore, like herself, wise, fair and true,</line>
            <line>Shall she be placed in my constant soul.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter JESSICA, below</stagedir>
            <line>What, art thou come? On, gentlemen; away!</line>
            <line>Our masquing mates by this time for us stay.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit with Jessica and Salarino</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Enter ANTONIO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>Who's there?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRATIANO</speaker>
            <line>Signior Antonio!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>Fie, fie, Gratiano! where are all the rest?</line>
            <line>'Tis nine o'clock: our friends all stay for you.</line>
            <line>No masque to-night: the wind is come about;</line>
            <line>Bassanio presently will go aboard:</line>
            <line>I have sent twenty out to seek for you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRATIANO</speaker>
            <line>I am glad on't: I desire no more delight</line>
            <line>Than to be under sail and gone to-night.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-7">
      <title>SCENE VII.  Belmont. A room in PORTIA'S house.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Flourish of cornets. Enter PORTIA, with the
PRINCE OF MOROCCO, and their trains</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PORTIA</speaker>
            <line>Go draw aside the curtains and discover</line>
            <line>The several caskets to this noble prince.</line>
            <line>Now make your choice.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOROCCO</speaker>
            <line>The first, of gold, who this inscription bears,</line>
            <line>'Who chooseth me shall gain what many men desire;'</line>
            <line>The second, silver, which this promise carries,</line>
            <line>'Who chooseth me shall get as much as he deserves;'</line>
            <line>This third, dull lead, with warning all as blunt,</line>
            <line>'Who chooseth me must give and hazard all he hath.'</line>
            <line>How shall I know if I do choose the right?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PORTIA</speaker>
            <line>The one of them contains my picture, prince:</line>
            <line>If you choose that, then I am yours withal.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOROCCO</speaker>
            <line>Some god direct my judgment! Let me see;</line>
            <line>I will survey the inscriptions back again.</line>
            <line>What says this leaden casket?</line>
            <line>'Who chooseth me must give and hazard all he hath.'</line>
            <line>Must give: for what? for lead? hazard for lead?</line>
            <line>This casket threatens. Men that hazard all</line>
            <line>Do it in hope of fair advantages:</line>
            <line>A golden mind stoops not to shows of dross;</line>
            <line>I'll then nor give nor hazard aught for lead.</line>
            <line>What says the silver with her virgin hue?</line>
            <line>'Who chooseth me shall get as much as he deserves.'</line>
            <line>As much as he deserves! Pause there, Morocco,</line>
            <line>And weigh thy value with an even hand:</line>
            <line>If thou be'st rated by thy estimation,</line>
            <line>Thou dost deserve enough; and yet enough</line>
            <line>May not extend so far as to the lady:</line>
            <line>And yet to be afeard of my deserving</line>
            <line>Were but a weak disabling of myself.</line>
            <line>As much as I deserve! Why, that's the lady:</line>
            <line>I do in birth deserve her, and in fortunes,</line>
            <line>In graces and in qualities of breeding;</line>
            <line>But more than these, in love I do deserve.</line>
            <line>What if I stray'd no further, but chose here?</line>
            <line>Let's see once more this saying graved in gold</line>
            <line>'Who chooseth me shall gain what many men desire.'</line>
            <line>Why, that's the lady; all the world desires her;</line>
            <line>From the four corners of the earth they come,</line>
            <line>To kiss this shrine, this mortal-breathing saint:</line>
            <line>The Hyrcanian deserts and the vasty wilds</line>
            <line>Of wide Arabia are as thoroughfares now</line>
            <line>For princes to come view fair Portia:</line>
            <line>The watery kingdom, whose ambitious head</line>
            <line>Spits in the face of heaven, is no bar</line>
            <line>To stop the foreign spirits, but they come,</line>
            <line>As o'er a brook, to see fair Portia.</line>
            <line>One of these three contains her heavenly picture.</line>
            <line>Is't like that lead contains her? 'Twere damnation</line>
            <line>To think so base a thought: it were too gross</line>
            <line>To rib her cerecloth in the obscure grave.</line>
            <line>Or shall I think in silver she's immured,</line>
            <line>Being ten times undervalued to tried gold?</line>
            <line>O sinful thought! Never so rich a gem</line>
            <line>Was set in worse than gold. They have in England</line>
            <line>A coin that bears the figure of an angel</line>
            <line>Stamped in gold, but that's insculp'd upon;</line>
            <line>But here an angel in a golden bed</line>
            <line>Lies all within. Deliver me the key:</line>
            <line>Here do I choose, and thrive I as I may!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PORTIA</speaker>
            <line>There, take it, prince; and if my form lie there,</line>
            <line>Then I am yours.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>He unlocks the golden casket</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOROCCO</speaker>
            <line>O hell! what have we here?</line>
            <line>A carrion Death, within whose empty eye</line>
            <line>There is a written scroll! I'll read the writing.</line>
            <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>
            <line>All that glitters is not gold;</line>
            <line>Often have you heard that told:</line>
            <line>Many a man his life hath sold</line>
            <line>But my outside to behold:</line>
            <line>Gilded tombs do worms enfold.</line>
            <line>Had you been as wise as bold,</line>
            <line>Young in limbs, in judgment old,</line>
            <line>Your answer had not been inscroll'd:</line>
            <line>Fare you well; your suit is cold.</line>
            <line>Cold, indeed; and labour lost:</line>
            <line>Then, farewell, heat, and welcome, frost!</line>
            <line>Portia, adieu. I have too grieved a heart</line>
            <line>To take a tedious leave: thus losers part.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit with his train. Flourish of cornets</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PORTIA</speaker>
            <line>A gentle riddance. Draw the curtains, go.</line>
            <line>Let all of his complexion choose me so.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-8">
      <title>SCENE VIII.  Venice. A street.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter SALARINO and SALANIO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALARINO</speaker>
            <line>Why, man, I saw Bassanio under sail:</line>
            <line>With him is Gratiano gone along;</line>
            <line>And in their ship I am sure Lorenzo is not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALANIO</speaker>
            <line>The villain Jew with outcries raised the duke,</line>
            <line>Who went with him to search Bassanio's ship.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALARINO</speaker>
            <line>He came too late, the ship was under sail:</line>
            <line>But there the duke was given to understand</line>
            <line>That in a gondola were seen together</line>
            <line>Lorenzo and his amorous Jessica:</line>
            <line>Besides, Antonio certified the duke</line>
            <line>They were not with Bassanio in his ship.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALANIO</speaker>
            <line>I never heard a passion so confused,</line>
            <line>So strange, outrageous, and so variable,</line>
            <line>As the dog Jew did utter in the streets:</line>
            <line>'My daughter! O my ducats! O my daughter!</line>
            <line>Fled with a Christian! O my Christian ducats!</line>
            <line>Justice! the law! my ducats, and my daughter!</line>
            <line>A sealed bag, two sealed bags of ducats,</line>
            <line>Of double ducats, stolen from me by my daughter!</line>
            <line>And jewels, two stones, two rich and precious stones,</line>
            <line>Stolen by my daughter! Justice! find the girl;</line>
            <line>She hath the stones upon her, and the ducats.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALARINO</speaker>
            <line>Why, all the boys in Venice follow him,</line>
            <line>Crying, his stones, his daughter, and his ducats.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALANIO</speaker>
            <line>Let good Antonio look he keep his day,</line>
            <line>Or he shall pay for this.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALARINO</speaker>
            <line>Marry, well remember'd.</line>
            <line>I reason'd with a Frenchman yesterday,</line>
            <line>Who told me, in the narrow seas that part</line>
            <line>The French and English, there miscarried</line>
            <line>A vessel of our country richly fraught:</line>
            <line>I thought upon Antonio when he told me;</line>
            <line>And wish'd in silence that it were not his.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALANIO</speaker>
            <line>You were best to tell Antonio what you hear;</line>
            <line>Yet do not suddenly, for it may grieve him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALARINO</speaker>
            <line>A kinder gentleman treads not the earth.</line>
            <line>I saw Bassanio and Antonio part:</line>
            <line>Bassanio told him he would make some speed</line>
            <line>Of his return: he answer'd, 'Do not so;</line>
            <line>Slubber not business for my sake, Bassanio</line>
            <line>But stay the very riping of the time;</line>
            <line>And for the Jew's bond which he hath of me,</line>
            <line>Let it not enter in your mind of love:</line>
            <line>Be merry, and employ your chiefest thoughts</line>
            <line>To courtship and such fair ostents of love</line>
            <line>As shall conveniently become you there:'</line>
            <line>And even there, his eye being big with tears,</line>
            <line>Turning his face, he put his hand behind him,</line>
            <line>And with affection wondrous sensible</line>
            <line>He wrung Bassanio's hand; and so they parted.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALANIO</speaker>
            <line>I think he only loves the world for him.</line>
            <line>I pray thee, let us go and find him out</line>
            <line>And quicken his embraced heaviness</line>
            <line>With some delight or other.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALARINO</speaker>
            <line>Do we so.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-9">
      <title>SCENE IX.  Belmont. A room in PORTIA'S house.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter NERISSA with a Servitor</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NERISSA</speaker>
            <line>Quick, quick, I pray thee; draw the curtain straight:</line>
            <line>The Prince of Arragon hath ta'en his oath,</line>
            <line>And comes to his election presently.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Flourish of cornets. Enter the PRINCE OF ARRAGON,
PORTIA, and their trains</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PORTIA</speaker>
            <line>Behold, there stand the caskets, noble prince:</line>
            <line>If you choose that wherein I am contain'd,</line>
            <line>Straight shall our nuptial rites be solemnized:</line>
            <line>But if you fail, without more speech, my lord,</line>
            <line>You must be gone from hence immediately.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARRAGON</speaker>
            <line>I am enjoin'd by oath to observe three things:</line>
            <line>First, never to unfold to any one</line>
            <line>Which casket 'twas I chose; next, if I fail</line>
            <line>Of the right casket, never in my life</line>
            <line>To woo a maid in way of marriage: Lastly,</line>
            <line>If I do fail in fortune of my choice,</line>
            <line>Immediately to leave you and be gone.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PORTIA</speaker>
            <line>To these injunctions every one doth swear</line>
            <line>That comes to hazard for my worthless self.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARRAGON</speaker>
            <line>And so have I address'd me. Fortune now</line>
            <line>To my heart's hope! Gold; silver; and base lead.</line>
            <line>'Who chooseth me must give and hazard all he hath.'</line>
            <line>You shall look fairer, ere I give or hazard.</line>
            <line>What says the golden chest? ha! let me see:</line>
            <line>'Who chooseth me shall gain what many men desire.'</line>
            <line>What many men desire! that 'many' may be meant</line>
            <line>By the fool multitude, that choose by show,</line>
            <line>Not learning more than the fond eye doth teach;</line>
            <line>Which pries not to the interior, but, like the martlet,</line>
            <line>Builds in the weather on the outward wall,</line>
            <line>Even in the force and road of casualty.</line>
            <line>I will not choose what many men desire,</line>
            <line>Because I will not jump with common spirits</line>
            <line>And rank me with the barbarous multitudes.</line>
            <line>Why, then to thee, thou silver treasure-house;</line>
            <line>Tell me once more what title thou dost bear:</line>
            <line>'Who chooseth me shall get as much as he deserves:'</line>
            <line>And well said too; for who shall go about</line>
            <line>To cozen fortune and be honourable</line>
            <line>Without the stamp of merit? Let none presume</line>
            <line>To wear an undeserved dignity.</line>
            <line>O, that estates, degrees and offices</line>
            <line>Were not derived corruptly, and that clear honour</line>
            <line>Were purchased by the merit of the wearer!</line>
            <line>How many then should cover that stand bare!</line>
            <line>How many be commanded that command!</line>
            <line>How much low peasantry would then be glean'd</line>
            <line>From the true seed of honour! and how much honour</line>
            <line>Pick'd from the chaff and ruin of the times</line>
            <line>To be new-varnish'd! Well, but to my choice:</line>
            <line>'Who chooseth me shall get as much as he deserves.'</line>
            <line>I will assume desert. Give me a key for this,</line>
            <line>And instantly unlock my fortunes here.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>He opens the silver casket</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PORTIA</speaker>
            <line>Too long a pause for that which you find there.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARRAGON</speaker>
            <line>What's here? the portrait of a blinking idiot,</line>
            <line>Presenting me a schedule! I will read it.</line>
            <line>How much unlike art thou to Portia!</line>
            <line>How much unlike my hopes and my deservings!</line>
            <line>'Who chooseth me shall have as much as he deserves.'</line>
            <line>Did I deserve no more than a fool's head?</line>
            <line>Is that my prize? are my deserts no better?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PORTIA</speaker>
            <line>To offend, and judge, are distinct offices</line>
            <line>And of opposed natures.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARRAGON</speaker>
            <line>What is here?</line>
            <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>
            <line>The fire seven times tried this:</line>
            <line>Seven times tried that judgment is,</line>
            <line>That did never choose amiss.</line>
            <line>Some there be that shadows kiss;</line>
            <line>Such have but a shadow's bliss:</line>
            <line>There be fools alive, I wis,</line>
            <line>Silver'd o'er; and so was this.</line>
            <line>Take what wife you will to bed,</line>
            <line>I will ever be your head:</line>
            <line>So be gone: you are sped.</line>
            <line>Still more fool I shall appear</line>
            <line>By the time I linger here</line>
            <line>With one fool's head I came to woo,</line>
            <line>But I go away with two.</line>
            <line>Sweet, adieu. I'll keep my oath,</line>
            <line>Patiently to bear my wroth.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt Arragon and train</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PORTIA</speaker>
            <line>Thus hath the candle singed the moth.</line>
            <line>O, these deliberate fools! when they do choose,</line>
            <line>They have the wisdom by their wit to lose.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NERISSA</speaker>
            <line>The ancient saying is no heresy,</line>
            <line>Hanging and wiving goes by destiny.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PORTIA</speaker>
            <line>Come, draw the curtain, Nerissa.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter a Servant</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>Where is my lady?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PORTIA</speaker>
            <line>Here: what would my lord?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>Madam, there is alighted at your gate</line>
            <line>A young Venetian, one that comes before</line>
            <line>To signify the approaching of his lord;</line>
            <line>From whom he bringeth sensible regreets,</line>
            <line>To wit, besides commends and courteous breath,</line>
            <line>Gifts of rich value. Yet I have not seen</line>
            <line>So likely an ambassador of love:</line>
            <line>A day in April never came so sweet,</line>
            <line>To show how costly summer was at hand,</line>
            <line>As this fore-spurrer comes before his lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PORTIA</speaker>
            <line>No more, I pray thee: I am half afeard</line>
            <line>Thou wilt say anon he is some kin to thee,</line>
            <line>Thou spend'st such high-day wit in praising him.</line>
            <line>Come, come, Nerissa; for I long to see</line>
            <line>Quick Cupid's post that comes so mannerly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NERISSA</speaker>
            <line>Bassanio, lord Love, if thy will it be!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>