<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net/doctypes/dita/shakespear/dtd/act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-3">
   <title>ACT III</title>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  Venice. A street.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter SALANIO and SALARINO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALANIO</speaker>
            <line>Now, what news on the Rialto?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALARINO</speaker>
            <line>Why, yet it lives there uncheck'd that Antonio hath</line>
            <line>a ship of rich lading wrecked on the narrow seas;</line>
            <line>the Goodwins, I think they call the place; a very</line>
            <line>dangerous flat and fatal, where the carcasses of many</line>
            <line>a tall ship lie buried, as they say, if my gossip</line>
            <line>Report be an honest woman of her word.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALANIO</speaker>
            <line>I would she were as lying a gossip in that as ever</line>
            <line>knapped ginger or made her neighbours believe she</line>
            <line>wept for the death of a third husband. But it is</line>
            <line>true, without any slips of prolixity or crossing the</line>
            <line>plain highway of talk, that the good Antonio, the</line>
            <line>honest Antonio,--O that I had a title good enough</line>
            <line>to keep his name company!--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALARINO</speaker>
            <line>Come, the full stop.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALANIO</speaker>
            <line>Ha! what sayest thou? Why, the end is, he hath</line>
            <line>lost a ship.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALARINO</speaker>
            <line>I would it might prove the end of his losses.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALANIO</speaker>
            <line>Let me say 'amen' betimes, lest the devil cross my</line>
            <line>prayer, for here he comes in the likeness of a Jew.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter SHYLOCK</stagedir>
            <line>How now, Shylock! what news among the merchants?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>
            <line>You know, none so well, none so well as you, of my</line>
            <line>daughter's flight.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALARINO</speaker>
            <line>That's certain: I, for my part, knew the tailor</line>
            <line>that made the wings she flew withal.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALANIO</speaker>
            <line>And Shylock, for his own part, knew the bird was</line>
            <line>fledged; and then it is the complexion of them all</line>
            <line>to leave the dam.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>
            <line>She is damned for it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALANIO</speaker>
            <line>That's certain, if the devil may be her judge.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>
            <line>My own flesh and blood to rebel!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALANIO</speaker>
            <line>Out upon it, old carrion! rebels it at these years?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>
            <line>I say, my daughter is my flesh and blood.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALARINO</speaker>
            <line>There is more difference between thy flesh and hers</line>
            <line>than between jet and ivory; more between your bloods</line>
            <line>than there is between red wine and rhenish. But</line>
            <line>tell us, do you hear whether Antonio have had any</line>
            <line>loss at sea or no?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>
            <line>There I have another bad match: a bankrupt, a</line>
            <line>prodigal, who dare scarce show his head on the</line>
            <line>Rialto; a beggar, that was used to come so smug upon</line>
            <line>the mart; let him look to his bond: he was wont to</line>
            <line>call me usurer; let him look to his bond: he was</line>
            <line>wont to lend money for a Christian courtesy; let him</line>
            <line>look to his bond.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALARINO</speaker>
            <line>Why, I am sure, if he forfeit, thou wilt not take</line>
            <line>his flesh: what's that good for?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>
            <line>To bait fish withal: if it will feed nothing else,</line>
            <line>it will feed my revenge. He hath disgraced me, and</line>
            <line>hindered me half a million; laughed at my losses,</line>
            <line>mocked at my gains, scorned my nation, thwarted my</line>
            <line>bargains, cooled my friends, heated mine</line>
            <line>enemies; and what's his reason? I am a Jew. Hath</line>
            <line>not a Jew eyes? hath not a Jew hands, organs,</line>
            <line>dimensions, senses, affections, passions? fed with</line>
            <line>the same food, hurt with the same weapons, subject</line>
            <line>to the same diseases, healed by the same means,</line>
            <line>warmed and cooled by the same winter and summer, as</line>
            <line>a Christian is? If you prick us, do we not bleed?</line>
            <line>if you tickle us, do we not laugh? if you poison</line>
            <line>us, do we not die? and if you wrong us, shall we not</line>
            <line>revenge? If we are like you in the rest, we will</line>
            <line>resemble you in that. If a Jew wrong a Christian,</line>
            <line>what is his humility? Revenge. If a Christian</line>
            <line>wrong a Jew, what should his sufferance be by</line>
            <line>Christian example? Why, revenge. The villany you</line>
            <line>teach me, I will execute, and it shall go hard but I</line>
            <line>will better the instruction.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter a Servant</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>Gentlemen, my master Antonio is at his house and</line>
            <line>desires to speak with you both.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALARINO</speaker>
            <line>We have been up and down to seek him.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter TUBAL</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALANIO</speaker>
            <line>Here comes another of the tribe: a third cannot be</line>
            <line>matched, unless the devil himself turn Jew.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt SALANIO, SALARINO, and Servant</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>
            <line>How now, Tubal! what news from Genoa? hast thou</line>
            <line>found my daughter?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TUBAL</speaker>
            <line>I often came where I did hear of her, but cannot find her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>
            <line>Why, there, there, there, there! a diamond gone,</line>
            <line>cost me two thousand ducats in Frankfort! The curse</line>
            <line>never fell upon our nation till now; I never felt it</line>
            <line>till now: two thousand ducats in that; and other</line>
            <line>precious, precious jewels. I would my daughter</line>
            <line>were dead at my foot, and the jewels in her ear!</line>
            <line>would she were hearsed at my foot, and the ducats in</line>
            <line>her coffin! No news of them? Why, so: and I know</line>
            <line>not what's spent in the search: why, thou loss upon</line>
            <line>loss! the thief gone with so much, and so much to</line>
            <line>find the thief; and no satisfaction, no revenge:</line>
            <line>nor no in luck stirring but what lights on my</line>
            <line>shoulders; no sighs but of my breathing; no tears</line>
            <line>but of my shedding.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TUBAL</speaker>
            <line>Yes, other men have ill luck too: Antonio, as I</line>
            <line>heard in Genoa,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>
            <line>What, what, what? ill luck, ill luck?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TUBAL</speaker>
            <line>Hath an argosy cast away, coming from Tripolis.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>
            <line>I thank God, I thank God. Is't true, is't true?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TUBAL</speaker>
            <line>I spoke with some of the sailors that escaped the wreck.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>
            <line>I thank thee, good Tubal: good news, good news!</line>
            <line>ha, ha! where? in Genoa?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TUBAL</speaker>
            <line>Your daughter spent in Genoa, as I heard, in one</line>
            <line>night fourscore ducats.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>
            <line>Thou stickest a dagger in me: I shall never see my</line>
            <line>gold again: fourscore ducats at a sitting!</line>
            <line>fourscore ducats!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TUBAL</speaker>
            <line>There came divers of Antonio's creditors in my</line>
            <line>company to Venice, that swear he cannot choose but break.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>
            <line>I am very glad of it: I'll plague him; I'll torture</line>
            <line>him: I am glad of it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TUBAL</speaker>
            <line>One of them showed me a ring that he had of your</line>
            <line>daughter for a monkey.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>
            <line>Out upon her! Thou torturest me, Tubal: it was my</line>
            <line>turquoise; I had it of Leah when I was a bachelor:</line>
            <line>I would not have given it for a wilderness of monkeys.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TUBAL</speaker>
            <line>But Antonio is certainly undone.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>
            <line>Nay, that's true, that's very true. Go, Tubal, fee</line>
            <line>me an officer; bespeak him a fortnight before. I</line>
            <line>will have the heart of him, if he forfeit; for, were</line>
            <line>he out of Venice, I can make what merchandise I</line>
            <line>will. Go, go, Tubal, and meet me at our synagogue;</line>
            <line>go, good Tubal; at our synagogue, Tubal.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  Belmont. A room in PORTIA'S house.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter BASSANIO, PORTIA, GRATIANO, NERISSA, and
Attendants</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PORTIA</speaker>
            <line>I pray you, tarry: pause a day or two</line>
            <line>Before you hazard; for, in choosing wrong,</line>
            <line>I lose your company: therefore forbear awhile.</line>
            <line>There's something tells me, but it is not love,</line>
            <line>I would not lose you; and you know yourself,</line>
            <line>Hate counsels not in such a quality.</line>
            <line>But lest you should not understand me well,--</line>
            <line>And yet a maiden hath no tongue but thought,--</line>
            <line>I would detain you here some month or two</line>
            <line>Before you venture for me. I could teach you</line>
            <line>How to choose right, but I am then forsworn;</line>
            <line>So will I never be: so may you miss me;</line>
            <line>But if you do, you'll make me wish a sin,</line>
            <line>That I had been forsworn. Beshrew your eyes,</line>
            <line>They have o'erlook'd me and divided me;</line>
            <line>One half of me is yours, the other half yours,</line>
            <line>Mine own, I would say; but if mine, then yours,</line>
            <line>And so all yours. O, these naughty times</line>
            <line>Put bars between the owners and their rights!</line>
            <line>And so, though yours, not yours. Prove it so,</line>
            <line>Let fortune go to hell for it, not I.</line>
            <line>I speak too long; but 'tis to peize the time,</line>
            <line>To eke it and to draw it out in length,</line>
            <line>To stay you from election.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSANIO</speaker>
            <line>Let me choose</line>
            <line>For as I am, I live upon the rack.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PORTIA</speaker>
            <line>Upon the rack, Bassanio! then confess</line>
            <line>What treason there is mingled with your love.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSANIO</speaker>
            <line>None but that ugly treason of mistrust,</line>
            <line>Which makes me fear the enjoying of my love:</line>
            <line>There may as well be amity and life</line>
            <line>'Tween snow and fire, as treason and my love.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PORTIA</speaker>
            <line>Ay, but I fear you speak upon the rack,</line>
            <line>Where men enforced do speak anything.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSANIO</speaker>
            <line>Promise me life, and I'll confess the truth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PORTIA</speaker>
            <line>Well then, confess and live.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSANIO</speaker>
            <line>'Confess' and 'love'</line>
            <line>Had been the very sum of my confession:</line>
            <line>O happy torment, when my torturer</line>
            <line>Doth teach me answers for deliverance!</line>
            <line>But let me to my fortune and the caskets.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PORTIA</speaker>
            <line>Away, then! I am lock'd in one of them:</line>
            <line>If you do love me, you will find me out.</line>
            <line>Nerissa and the rest, stand all aloof.</line>
            <line>Let music sound while he doth make his choice;</line>
            <line>Then, if he lose, he makes a swan-like end,</line>
            <line>Fading in music: that the comparison</line>
            <line>May stand more proper, my eye shall be the stream</line>
            <line>And watery death-bed for him. He may win;</line>
            <line>And what is music then? Then music is</line>
            <line>Even as the flourish when true subjects bow</line>
            <line>To a new-crowned monarch: such it is</line>
            <line>As are those dulcet sounds in break of day</line>
            <line>That creep into the dreaming bridegroom's ear,</line>
            <line>And summon him to marriage. Now he goes,</line>
            <line>With no less presence, but with much more love,</line>
            <line>Than young Alcides, when he did redeem</line>
            <line>The virgin tribute paid by howling Troy</line>
            <line>To the sea-monster: I stand for sacrifice</line>
            <line>The rest aloof are the Dardanian wives,</line>
            <line>With bleared visages, come forth to view</line>
            <line>The issue of the exploit. Go, Hercules!</line>
            <line>Live thou, I live: with much, much more dismay</line>
            <line>I view the fight than thou that makest the fray.</line>
            <stagedir>Music, whilst BASSANIO comments on the caskets to himself</stagedir>
            <subhead>SONG.</subhead>
            <line>Tell me where is fancy bred,</line>
            <line>Or in the heart, or in the head?</line>
            <line>How begot, how nourished?</line>
            <line>Reply, reply.</line>
            <line>It is engender'd in the eyes,</line>
            <line>With gazing fed; and fancy dies</line>
            <line>In the cradle where it lies.</line>
            <line>Let us all ring fancy's knell</line>
            <line>I'll begin it,--Ding, dong, bell.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALL</speaker>
            <line>Ding, dong, bell.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSANIO</speaker>
            <line>So may the outward shows be least themselves:</line>
            <line>The world is still deceived with ornament.</line>
            <line>In law, what plea so tainted and corrupt,</line>
            <line>But, being seasoned with a gracious voice,</line>
            <line>Obscures the show of evil? In religion,</line>
            <line>What damned error, but some sober brow</line>
            <line>Will bless it and approve it with a text,</line>
            <line>Hiding the grossness with fair ornament?</line>
            <line>There is no vice so simple but assumes</line>
            <line>Some mark of virtue on his outward parts:</line>
            <line>How many cowards, whose hearts are all as false</line>
            <line>As stairs of sand, wear yet upon their chins</line>
            <line>The beards of Hercules and frowning Mars;</line>
            <line>Who, inward search'd, have livers white as milk;</line>
            <line>And these assume but valour's excrement</line>
            <line>To render them redoubted! Look on beauty,</line>
            <line>And you shall see 'tis purchased by the weight;</line>
            <line>Which therein works a miracle in nature,</line>
            <line>Making them lightest that wear most of it:</line>
            <line>So are those crisped snaky golden locks</line>
            <line>Which make such wanton gambols with the wind,</line>
            <line>Upon supposed fairness, often known</line>
            <line>To be the dowry of a second head,</line>
            <line>The skull that bred them in the sepulchre.</line>
            <line>Thus ornament is but the guiled shore</line>
            <line>To a most dangerous sea; the beauteous scarf</line>
            <line>Veiling an Indian beauty; in a word,</line>
            <line>The seeming truth which cunning times put on</line>
            <line>To entrap the wisest. Therefore, thou gaudy gold,</line>
            <line>Hard food for Midas, I will none of thee;</line>
            <line>Nor none of thee, thou pale and common drudge</line>
            <line>'Tween man and man: but thou, thou meagre lead,</line>
            <line>Which rather threatenest than dost promise aught,</line>
            <line>Thy paleness moves me more than eloquence;</line>
            <line>And here choose I; joy be the consequence!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PORTIA</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  How all the other passions fleet to air,</line>
            <line>As doubtful thoughts, and rash-embraced despair,</line>
            <line>And shuddering fear, and green-eyed jealousy! O love,</line>
            <line>Be moderate; allay thy ecstasy,</line>
            <line>In measure rein thy joy; scant this excess.</line>
            <line>I feel too much thy blessing: make it less,</line>
            <line>For fear I surfeit.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSANIO</speaker>
            <line>What find I here?</line>
            <stagedir>Opening the leaden casket</stagedir>
            <line>Fair Portia's counterfeit! What demi-god</line>
            <line>Hath come so near creation? Move these eyes?</line>
            <line>Or whether, riding on the balls of mine,</line>
            <line>Seem they in motion? Here are sever'd lips,</line>
            <line>Parted with sugar breath: so sweet a bar</line>
            <line>Should sunder such sweet friends. Here in her hairs</line>
            <line>The painter plays the spider and hath woven</line>
            <line>A golden mesh to entrap the hearts of men,</line>
            <line>Faster than gnats in cobwebs; but her eyes,--</line>
            <line>How could he see to do them? having made one,</line>
            <line>Methinks it should have power to steal both his</line>
            <line>And leave itself unfurnish'd. Yet look, how far</line>
            <line>The substance of my praise doth wrong this shadow</line>
            <line>In underprizing it, so far this shadow</line>
            <line>Doth limp behind the substance. Here's the scroll,</line>
            <line>The continent and summary of my fortune.</line>
            <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>
            <line>You that choose not by the view,</line>
            <line>Chance as fair and choose as true!</line>
            <line>Since this fortune falls to you,</line>
            <line>Be content and seek no new,</line>
            <line>If you be well pleased with this</line>
            <line>And hold your fortune for your bliss,</line>
            <line>Turn you where your lady is</line>
            <line>And claim her with a loving kiss.</line>
            <line>A gentle scroll. Fair lady, by your leave;</line>
            <line>I come by note, to give and to receive.</line>
            <line>Like one of two contending in a prize,</line>
            <line>That thinks he hath done well in people's eyes,</line>
            <line>Hearing applause and universal shout,</line>
            <line>Giddy in spirit, still gazing in a doubt</line>
            <line>Whether these pearls of praise be his or no;</line>
            <line>So, thrice fair lady, stand I, even so;</line>
            <line>As doubtful whether what I see be true,</line>
            <line>Until confirm'd, sign'd, ratified by you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PORTIA</speaker>
            <line>You see me, Lord Bassanio, where I stand,</line>
            <line>Such as I am: though for myself alone</line>
            <line>I would not be ambitious in my wish,</line>
            <line>To wish myself much better; yet, for you</line>
            <line>I would be trebled twenty times myself;</line>
            <line>A thousand times more fair, ten thousand times more rich;</line>
            <line>That only to stand high in your account,</line>
            <line>I might in virtue, beauties, livings, friends,</line>
            <line>Exceed account; but the full sum of me</line>
            <line>Is sum of something, which, to term in gross,</line>
            <line>Is an unlesson'd girl, unschool'd, unpractised;</line>
            <line>Happy in this, she is not yet so old</line>
            <line>But she may learn; happier than this,</line>
            <line>She is not bred so dull but she can learn;</line>
            <line>Happiest of all is that her gentle spirit</line>
            <line>Commits itself to yours to be directed,</line>
            <line>As from her lord, her governor, her king.</line>
            <line>Myself and what is mine to you and yours</line>
            <line>Is now converted: but now I was the lord</line>
            <line>Of this fair mansion, master of my servants,</line>
            <line>Queen o'er myself: and even now, but now,</line>
            <line>This house, these servants and this same myself</line>
            <line>Are yours, my lord: I give them with this ring;</line>
            <line>Which when you part from, lose, or give away,</line>
            <line>Let it presage the ruin of your love</line>
            <line>And be my vantage to exclaim on you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSANIO</speaker>
            <line>Madam, you have bereft me of all words,</line>
            <line>Only my blood speaks to you in my veins;</line>
            <line>And there is such confusion in my powers,</line>
            <line>As after some oration fairly spoke</line>
            <line>By a beloved prince, there doth appear</line>
            <line>Among the buzzing pleased multitude;</line>
            <line>Where every something, being blent together,</line>
            <line>Turns to a wild of nothing, save of joy,</line>
            <line>Express'd and not express'd. But when this ring</line>
            <line>Parts from this finger, then parts life from hence:</line>
            <line>O, then be bold to say Bassanio's dead!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NERISSA</speaker>
            <line>My lord and lady, it is now our time,</line>
            <line>That have stood by and seen our wishes prosper,</line>
            <line>To cry, good joy: good joy, my lord and lady!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRATIANO</speaker>
            <line>My lord Bassanio and my gentle lady,</line>
            <line>I wish you all the joy that you can wish;</line>
            <line>For I am sure you can wish none from me:</line>
            <line>And when your honours mean to solemnize</line>
            <line>The bargain of your faith, I do beseech you,</line>
            <line>Even at that time I may be married too.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSANIO</speaker>
            <line>With all my heart, so thou canst get a wife.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRATIANO</speaker>
            <line>I thank your lordship, you have got me one.</line>
            <line>My eyes, my lord, can look as swift as yours:</line>
            <line>You saw the mistress, I beheld the maid;</line>
            <line>You loved, I loved for intermission.</line>
            <line>No more pertains to me, my lord, than you.</line>
            <line>Your fortune stood upon the casket there,</line>
            <line>And so did mine too, as the matter falls;</line>
            <line>For wooing here until I sweat again,</line>
            <line>And sweating until my very roof was dry</line>
            <line>With oaths of love, at last, if promise last,</line>
            <line>I got a promise of this fair one here</line>
            <line>To have her love, provided that your fortune</line>
            <line>Achieved her mistress.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PORTIA</speaker>
            <line>Is this true, Nerissa?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NERISSA</speaker>
            <line>Madam, it is, so you stand pleased withal.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSANIO</speaker>
            <line>And do you, Gratiano, mean good faith?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRATIANO</speaker>
            <line>Yes, faith, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSANIO</speaker>
            <line>Our feast shall be much honour'd in your marriage.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRATIANO</speaker>
            <line>We'll play with them the first boy for a thousand ducats.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NERISSA</speaker>
            <line>What, and stake down?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRATIANO</speaker>
            <line>No; we shall ne'er win at that sport, and stake down.</line>
            <line>But who comes here? Lorenzo and his infidel? What,</line>
            <line>and my old Venetian friend Salerio?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter LORENZO, JESSICA, and SALERIO, a Messenger
from Venice</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSANIO</speaker>
            <line>Lorenzo and Salerio, welcome hither;</line>
            <line>If that the youth of my new interest here</line>
            <line>Have power to bid you welcome. By your leave,</line>
            <line>I bid my very friends and countrymen,</line>
            <line>Sweet Portia, welcome.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PORTIA</speaker>
            <line>So do I, my lord:</line>
            <line>They are entirely welcome.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORENZO</speaker>
            <line>I thank your honour. For my part, my lord,</line>
            <line>My purpose was not to have seen you here;</line>
            <line>But meeting with Salerio by the way,</line>
            <line>He did entreat me, past all saying nay,</line>
            <line>To come with him along.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALERIO</speaker>
            <line>I did, my lord;</line>
            <line>And I have reason for it. Signior Antonio</line>
            <line>Commends him to you.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Gives Bassanio a letter</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSANIO</speaker>
            <line>Ere I ope his letter,</line>
            <line>I pray you, tell me how my good friend doth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALERIO</speaker>
            <line>Not sick, my lord, unless it be in mind;</line>
            <line>Nor well, unless in mind: his letter there</line>
            <line>Will show you his estate.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRATIANO</speaker>
            <line>Nerissa, cheer yon stranger; bid her welcome.</line>
            <line>Your hand, Salerio: what's the news from Venice?</line>
            <line>How doth that royal merchant, good Antonio?</line>
            <line>I know he will be glad of our success;</line>
            <line>We are the Jasons, we have won the fleece.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALERIO</speaker>
            <line>I would you had won the fleece that he hath lost.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PORTIA</speaker>
            <line>There are some shrewd contents in yon same paper,</line>
            <line>That steals the colour from Bassanio's cheek:</line>
            <line>Some dear friend dead; else nothing in the world</line>
            <line>Could turn so much the constitution</line>
            <line>Of any constant man. What, worse and worse!</line>
            <line>With leave, Bassanio: I am half yourself,</line>
            <line>And I must freely have the half of anything</line>
            <line>That this same paper brings you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSANIO</speaker>
            <line>O sweet Portia,</line>
            <line>Here are a few of the unpleasant'st words</line>
            <line>That ever blotted paper! Gentle lady,</line>
            <line>When I did first impart my love to you,</line>
            <line>I freely told you, all the wealth I had</line>
            <line>Ran in my veins, I was a gentleman;</line>
            <line>And then I told you true: and yet, dear lady,</line>
            <line>Rating myself at nothing, you shall see</line>
            <line>How much I was a braggart. When I told you</line>
            <line>My state was nothing, I should then have told you</line>
            <line>That I was worse than nothing; for, indeed,</line>
            <line>I have engaged myself to a dear friend,</line>
            <line>Engaged my friend to his mere enemy,</line>
            <line>To feed my means. Here is a letter, lady;</line>
            <line>The paper as the body of my friend,</line>
            <line>And every word in it a gaping wound,</line>
            <line>Issuing life-blood. But is it true, Salerio?</line>
            <line>Have all his ventures fail'd? What, not one hit?</line>
            <line>From Tripolis, from Mexico and England,</line>
            <line>From Lisbon, Barbary and India?</line>
            <line>And not one vessel 'scape the dreadful touch</line>
            <line>Of merchant-marring rocks?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALERIO</speaker>
            <line>Not one, my lord.</line>
            <line>Besides, it should appear, that if he had</line>
            <line>The present money to discharge the Jew,</line>
            <line>He would not take it. Never did I know</line>
            <line>A creature, that did bear the shape of man,</line>
            <line>So keen and greedy to confound a man:</line>
            <line>He plies the duke at morning and at night,</line>
            <line>And doth impeach the freedom of the state,</line>
            <line>If they deny him justice: twenty merchants,</line>
            <line>The duke himself, and the magnificoes</line>
            <line>Of greatest port, have all persuaded with him;</line>
            <line>But none can drive him from the envious plea</line>
            <line>Of forfeiture, of justice and his bond.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JESSICA</speaker>
            <line>When I was with him I have heard him swear</line>
            <line>To Tubal and to Chus, his countrymen,</line>
            <line>That he would rather have Antonio's flesh</line>
            <line>Than twenty times the value of the sum</line>
            <line>That he did owe him: and I know, my lord,</line>
            <line>If law, authority and power deny not,</line>
            <line>It will go hard with poor Antonio.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PORTIA</speaker>
            <line>Is it your dear friend that is thus in trouble?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSANIO</speaker>
            <line>The dearest friend to me, the kindest man,</line>
            <line>The best-condition'd and unwearied spirit</line>
            <line>In doing courtesies, and one in whom</line>
            <line>The ancient Roman honour more appears</line>
            <line>Than any that draws breath in Italy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PORTIA</speaker>
            <line>What sum owes he the Jew?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSANIO</speaker>
            <line>For me three thousand ducats.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PORTIA</speaker>
            <line>What, no more?</line>
            <line>Pay him six thousand, and deface the bond;</line>
            <line>Double six thousand, and then treble that,</line>
            <line>Before a friend of this description</line>
            <line>Shall lose a hair through Bassanio's fault.</line>
            <line>First go with me to church and call me wife,</line>
            <line>And then away to Venice to your friend;</line>
            <line>For never shall you lie by Portia's side</line>
            <line>With an unquiet soul. You shall have gold</line>
            <line>To pay the petty debt twenty times over:</line>
            <line>When it is paid, bring your true friend along.</line>
            <line>My maid Nerissa and myself meantime</line>
            <line>Will live as maids and widows. Come, away!</line>
            <line>For you shall hence upon your wedding-day:</line>
            <line>Bid your friends welcome, show a merry cheer:</line>
            <line>Since you are dear bought, I will love you dear.</line>
            <line>But let me hear the letter of your friend.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSANIO</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>  Sweet Bassanio, my ships have all</line>
            <line>miscarried, my creditors grow cruel, my estate is</line>
            <line>very low, my bond to the Jew is forfeit; and since</line>
            <line>in paying it, it is impossible I should live, all</line>
            <line>debts are cleared between you and I, if I might but</line>
            <line>see you at my death. Notwithstanding, use your</line>
            <line>pleasure: if your love do not persuade you to come,</line>
            <line>let not my letter.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PORTIA</speaker>
            <line>O love, dispatch all business, and be gone!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSANIO</speaker>
            <line>Since I have your good leave to go away,</line>
            <line>I will make haste: but, till I come again,</line>
            <line>No bed shall e'er be guilty of my stay,</line>
            <line>No rest be interposer 'twixt us twain.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  Venice. A street.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter SHYLOCK, SALARINO, ANTONIO, and Gaoler</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>
            <line>Gaoler, look to him: tell not me of mercy;</line>
            <line>This is the fool that lent out money gratis:</line>
            <line>Gaoler, look to him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>Hear me yet, good Shylock.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>
            <line>I'll have my bond; speak not against my bond:</line>
            <line>I have sworn an oath that I will have my bond.</line>
            <line>Thou call'dst me dog before thou hadst a cause;</line>
            <line>But, since I am a dog, beware my fangs:</line>
            <line>The duke shall grant me justice. I do wonder,</line>
            <line>Thou naughty gaoler, that thou art so fond</line>
            <line>To come abroad with him at his request.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>I pray thee, hear me speak.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>
            <line>I'll have my bond; I will not hear thee speak:</line>
            <line>I'll have my bond; and therefore speak no more.</line>
            <line>I'll not be made a soft and dull-eyed fool,</line>
            <line>To shake the head, relent, and sigh, and yield</line>
            <line>To Christian intercessors. Follow not;</line>
            <line>I'll have no speaking: I will have my bond.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALARINO</speaker>
            <line>It is the most impenetrable cur</line>
            <line>That ever kept with men.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>Let him alone:</line>
            <line>I'll follow him no more with bootless prayers.</line>
            <line>He seeks my life; his reason well I know:</line>
            <line>I oft deliver'd from his forfeitures</line>
            <line>Many that have at times made moan to me;</line>
            <line>Therefore he hates me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALARINO</speaker>
            <line>I am sure the duke</line>
            <line>Will never grant this forfeiture to hold.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>The duke cannot deny the course of law:</line>
            <line>For the commodity that strangers have</line>
            <line>With us in Venice, if it be denied,</line>
            <line>Will much impeach the justice of his state;</line>
            <line>Since that the trade and profit of the city</line>
            <line>Consisteth of all nations. Therefore, go:</line>
            <line>These griefs and losses have so bated me,</line>
            <line>That I shall hardly spare a pound of flesh</line>
            <line>To-morrow to my bloody creditor.</line>
            <line>Well, gaoler, on. Pray God, Bassanio come</line>
            <line>To see me pay his debt, and then I care not!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-4">
      <title>SCENE IV.  Belmont. A room in PORTIA'S house.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter PORTIA, NERISSA, LORENZO, JESSICA, and
BALTHASAR</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORENZO</speaker>
            <line>Madam, although I speak it in your presence,</line>
            <line>You have a noble and a true conceit</line>
            <line>Of godlike amity; which appears most strongly</line>
            <line>In bearing thus the absence of your lord.</line>
            <line>But if you knew to whom you show this honour,</line>
            <line>How true a gentleman you send relief,</line>
            <line>How dear a lover of my lord your husband,</line>
            <line>I know you would be prouder of the work</line>
            <line>Than customary bounty can enforce you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PORTIA</speaker>
            <line>I never did repent for doing good,</line>
            <line>Nor shall not now: for in companions</line>
            <line>That do converse and waste the time together,</line>
            <line>Whose souls do bear an equal yoke Of love,</line>
            <line>There must be needs a like proportion</line>
            <line>Of lineaments, of manners and of spirit;</line>
            <line>Which makes me think that this Antonio,</line>
            <line>Being the bosom lover of my lord,</line>
            <line>Must needs be like my lord. If it be so,</line>
            <line>How little is the cost I have bestow'd</line>
            <line>In purchasing the semblance of my soul</line>
            <line>From out the state of hellish misery!</line>
            <line>This comes too near the praising of myself;</line>
            <line>Therefore no more of it: hear other things.</line>
            <line>Lorenzo, I commit into your hands</line>
            <line>The husbandry and manage of my house</line>
            <line>Until my lord's return: for mine own part,</line>
            <line>I have toward heaven breathed a secret vow</line>
            <line>To live in prayer and contemplation,</line>
            <line>Only attended by Nerissa here,</line>
            <line>Until her husband and my lord's return:</line>
            <line>There is a monastery two miles off;</line>
            <line>And there will we abide. I do desire you</line>
            <line>Not to deny this imposition;</line>
            <line>The which my love and some necessity</line>
            <line>Now lays upon you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORENZO</speaker>
            <line>Madam, with all my heart;</line>
            <line>I shall obey you in all fair commands.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PORTIA</speaker>
            <line>My people do already know my mind,</line>
            <line>And will acknowledge you and Jessica</line>
            <line>In place of Lord Bassanio and myself.</line>
            <line>And so farewell, till we shall meet again.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORENZO</speaker>
            <line>Fair thoughts and happy hours attend on you!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JESSICA</speaker>
            <line>I wish your ladyship all heart's content.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PORTIA</speaker>
            <line>I thank you for your wish, and am well pleased</line>
            <line>To wish it back on you: fare you well Jessica.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt JESSICA and LORENZO</stagedir>
            <line>Now, Balthasar,</line>
            <line>As I have ever found thee honest-true,</line>
            <line>So let me find thee still. Take this same letter,</line>
            <line>And use thou all the endeavour of a man</line>
            <line>In speed to Padua: see thou render this</line>
            <line>Into my cousin's hand, Doctor Bellario;</line>
            <line>And, look, what notes and garments he doth give thee,</line>
            <line>Bring them, I pray thee, with imagined speed</line>
            <line>Unto the tranect, to the common ferry</line>
            <line>Which trades to Venice. Waste no time in words,</line>
            <line>But get thee gone: I shall be there before thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BALTHASAR</speaker>
            <line>Madam, I go with all convenient speed.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PORTIA</speaker>
            <line>Come on, Nerissa; I have work in hand</line>
            <line>That you yet know not of: we'll see our husbands</line>
            <line>Before they think of us.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NERISSA</speaker>
            <line>Shall they see us?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PORTIA</speaker>
            <line>They shall, Nerissa; but in such a habit,</line>
            <line>That they shall think we are accomplished</line>
            <line>With that we lack. I'll hold thee any wager,</line>
            <line>When we are both accoutred like young men,</line>
            <line>I'll prove the prettier fellow of the two,</line>
            <line>And wear my dagger with the braver grace,</line>
            <line>And speak between the change of man and boy</line>
            <line>With a reed voice, and turn two mincing steps</line>
            <line>Into a manly stride, and speak of frays</line>
            <line>Like a fine bragging youth, and tell quaint lies,</line>
            <line>How honourable ladies sought my love,</line>
            <line>Which I denying, they fell sick and died;</line>
            <line>I could not do withal; then I'll repent,</line>
            <line>And wish for all that, that I had not killed them;</line>
            <line>And twenty of these puny lies I'll tell,</line>
            <line>That men shall swear I have discontinued school</line>
            <line>Above a twelvemonth. I have within my mind</line>
            <line>A thousand raw tricks of these bragging Jacks,</line>
            <line>Which I will practise.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NERISSA</speaker>
            <line>Why, shall we turn to men?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PORTIA</speaker>
            <line>Fie, what a question's that,</line>
            <line>If thou wert near a lewd interpreter!</line>
            <line>But come, I'll tell thee all my whole device</line>
            <line>When I am in my coach, which stays for us</line>
            <line>At the park gate; and therefore haste away,</line>
            <line>For we must measure twenty miles to-day.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-5">
      <title>SCENE V.  The same. A garden.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter LAUNCELOT and JESSICA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAUNCELOT</speaker>
            <line>Yes, truly; for, look you, the sins of the father</line>
            <line>are to be laid upon the children: therefore, I</line>
            <line>promise ye, I fear you. I was always plain with</line>
            <line>you, and so now I speak my agitation of the matter:</line>
            <line>therefore be of good cheer, for truly I think you</line>
            <line>are damned. There is but one hope in it that can do</line>
            <line>you any good; and that is but a kind of bastard</line>
            <line>hope neither.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JESSICA</speaker>
            <line>And what hope is that, I pray thee?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAUNCELOT</speaker>
            <line>Marry, you may partly hope that your father got you</line>
            <line>not, that you are not the Jew's daughter.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JESSICA</speaker>
            <line>That were a kind of bastard hope, indeed: so the</line>
            <line>sins of my mother should be visited upon me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAUNCELOT</speaker>
            <line>Truly then I fear you are damned both by father and</line>
            <line>mother: thus when I shun Scylla, your father, I</line>
            <line>fall into Charybdis, your mother: well, you are</line>
            <line>gone both ways.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JESSICA</speaker>
            <line>I shall be saved by my husband; he hath made me a</line>
            <line>Christian.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAUNCELOT</speaker>
            <line>Truly, the more to blame he: we were Christians</line>
            <line>enow before; e'en as many as could well live, one by</line>
            <line>another. This making Christians will raise the</line>
            <line>price of hogs: if we grow all to be pork-eaters, we</line>
            <line>shall not shortly have a rasher on the coals for money.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter LORENZO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JESSICA</speaker>
            <line>I'll tell my husband, Launcelot, what you say: here he comes.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORENZO</speaker>
            <line>I shall grow jealous of you shortly, Launcelot, if</line>
            <line>you thus get my wife into corners.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JESSICA</speaker>
            <line>Nay, you need not fear us, Lorenzo: Launcelot and I</line>
            <line>are out. He tells me flatly, there is no mercy for</line>
            <line>me in heaven, because I am a Jew's daughter: and he</line>
            <line>says, you are no good member of the commonwealth,</line>
            <line>for in converting Jews to Christians, you raise the</line>
            <line>price of pork.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORENZO</speaker>
            <line>I shall answer that better to the commonwealth than</line>
            <line>you can the getting up of the negro's belly: the</line>
            <line>Moor is with child by you, Launcelot.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAUNCELOT</speaker>
            <line>It is much that the Moor should be more than reason:</line>
            <line>but if she be less than an honest woman, she is</line>
            <line>indeed more than I took her for.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORENZO</speaker>
            <line>How every fool can play upon the word! I think the</line>
            <line>best grace of wit will shortly turn into silence,</line>
            <line>and discourse grow commendable in none only but</line>
            <line>parrots. Go in, sirrah; bid them prepare for dinner.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAUNCELOT</speaker>
            <line>That is done, sir; they have all stomachs.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORENZO</speaker>
            <line>Goodly Lord, what a wit-snapper are you! then bid</line>
            <line>them prepare dinner.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAUNCELOT</speaker>
            <line>That is done too, sir; only 'cover' is the word.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORENZO</speaker>
            <line>Will you cover then, sir?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAUNCELOT</speaker>
            <line>Not so, sir, neither; I know my duty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORENZO</speaker>
            <line>Yet more quarrelling with occasion! Wilt thou show</line>
            <line>the whole wealth of thy wit in an instant? I pray</line>
            <line>tree, understand a plain man in his plain meaning:</line>
            <line>go to thy fellows; bid them cover the table, serve</line>
            <line>in the meat, and we will come in to dinner.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAUNCELOT</speaker>
            <line>For the table, sir, it shall be served in; for the</line>
            <line>meat, sir, it shall be covered; for your coming in</line>
            <line>to dinner, sir, why, let it be as humours and</line>
            <line>conceits shall govern.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORENZO</speaker>
            <line>O dear discretion, how his words are suited!</line>
            <line>The fool hath planted in his memory</line>
            <line>An army of good words; and I do know</line>
            <line>A many fools, that stand in better place,</line>
            <line>Garnish'd like him, that for a tricksy word</line>
            <line>Defy the matter. How cheerest thou, Jessica?</line>
            <line>And now, good sweet, say thy opinion,</line>
            <line>How dost thou like the Lord Bassanio's wife?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JESSICA</speaker>
            <line>Past all expressing. It is very meet</line>
            <line>The Lord Bassanio live an upright life;</line>
            <line>For, having such a blessing in his lady,</line>
            <line>He finds the joys of heaven here on earth;</line>
            <line>And if on earth he do not mean it, then</line>
            <line>In reason he should never come to heaven</line>
            <line>Why, if two gods should play some heavenly match</line>
            <line>And on the wager lay two earthly women,</line>
            <line>And Portia one, there must be something else</line>
            <line>Pawn'd with the other, for the poor rude world</line>
            <line>Hath not her fellow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORENZO</speaker>
            <line>Even such a husband</line>
            <line>Hast thou of me as she is for a wife.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JESSICA</speaker>
            <line>Nay, but ask my opinion too of that.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORENZO</speaker>
            <line>I will anon: first, let us go to dinner.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JESSICA</speaker>
            <line>Nay, let me praise you while I have a stomach.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORENZO</speaker>
            <line>No, pray thee, let it serve for table-talk;</line>
            <line>' Then, howso'er thou speak'st, 'mong other things</line>
            <line>I shall digest it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JESSICA</speaker>
            <line>Well, I'll set you forth.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>