<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net/doctypes/dita/shakespear/dtd/act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-1">
   <title>ACT I</title>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  Venice. A street.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter ANTONIO, SALARINO, and SALANIO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>In sooth, I know not why I am so sad:</line>
            <line>It wearies me; you say it wearies you;</line>
            <line>But how I caught it, found it, or came by it,</line>
            <line>What stuff 'tis made of, whereof it is born,</line>
            <line>I am to learn;</line>
            <line>And such a want-wit sadness makes of me,</line>
            <line>That I have much ado to know myself.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALARINO</speaker>
            <line>Your mind is tossing on the ocean;</line>
            <line>There, where your argosies with portly sail,</line>
            <line>Like signiors and rich burghers on the flood,</line>
            <line>Or, as it were, the pageants of the sea,</line>
            <line>Do overpeer the petty traffickers,</line>
            <line>That curtsy to them, do them reverence,</line>
            <line>As they fly by them with their woven wings.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALANIO</speaker>
            <line>Believe me, sir, had I such venture forth,</line>
            <line>The better part of my affections would</line>
            <line>Be with my hopes abroad. I should be still</line>
            <line>Plucking the grass, to know where sits the wind,</line>
            <line>Peering in maps for ports and piers and roads;</line>
            <line>And every object that might make me fear</line>
            <line>Misfortune to my ventures, out of doubt</line>
            <line>Would make me sad.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALARINO</speaker>
            <line>My wind cooling my broth</line>
            <line>Would blow me to an ague, when I thought</line>
            <line>What harm a wind too great at sea might do.</line>
            <line>I should not see the sandy hour-glass run,</line>
            <line>But I should think of shallows and of flats,</line>
            <line>And see my wealthy Andrew dock'd in sand,</line>
            <line>Vailing her high-top lower than her ribs</line>
            <line>To kiss her burial. Should I go to church</line>
            <line>And see the holy edifice of stone,</line>
            <line>And not bethink me straight of dangerous rocks,</line>
            <line>Which touching but my gentle vessel's side,</line>
            <line>Would scatter all her spices on the stream,</line>
            <line>Enrobe the roaring waters with my silks,</line>
            <line>And, in a word, but even now worth this,</line>
            <line>And now worth nothing? Shall I have the thought</line>
            <line>To think on this, and shall I lack the thought</line>
            <line>That such a thing bechanced would make me sad?</line>
            <line>But tell not me; I know, Antonio</line>
            <line>Is sad to think upon his merchandise.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>Believe me, no: I thank my fortune for it,</line>
            <line>My ventures are not in one bottom trusted,</line>
            <line>Nor to one place; nor is my whole estate</line>
            <line>Upon the fortune of this present year:</line>
            <line>Therefore my merchandise makes me not sad.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALARINO</speaker>
            <line>Why, then you are in love.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>Fie, fie!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALARINO</speaker>
            <line>Not in love neither? Then let us say you are sad,</line>
            <line>Because you are not merry: and 'twere as easy</line>
            <line>For you to laugh and leap and say you are merry,</line>
            <line>Because you are not sad. Now, by two-headed Janus,</line>
            <line>Nature hath framed strange fellows in her time:</line>
            <line>Some that will evermore peep through their eyes</line>
            <line>And laugh like parrots at a bag-piper,</line>
            <line>And other of such vinegar aspect</line>
            <line>That they'll not show their teeth in way of smile,</line>
            <line>Though Nestor swear the jest be laughable.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter BASSANIO, LORENZO, and GRATIANO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALANIO</speaker>
            <line>Here comes Bassanio, your most noble kinsman,</line>
            <line>Gratiano and Lorenzo. Fare ye well:</line>
            <line>We leave you now with better company.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALARINO</speaker>
            <line>I would have stay'd till I had made you merry,</line>
            <line>If worthier friends had not prevented me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>Your worth is very dear in my regard.</line>
            <line>I take it, your own business calls on you</line>
            <line>And you embrace the occasion to depart.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALARINO</speaker>
            <line>Good morrow, my good lords.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSANIO</speaker>
            <line>Good signiors both, when shall we laugh? say, when?</line>
            <line>You grow exceeding strange: must it be so?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALARINO</speaker>
            <line>We'll make our leisures to attend on yours.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt Salarino and Salanio</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORENZO</speaker>
            <line>My Lord Bassanio, since you have found Antonio,</line>
            <line>We two will leave you: but at dinner-time,</line>
            <line>I pray you, have in mind where we must meet.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSANIO</speaker>
            <line>I will not fail you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRATIANO</speaker>
            <line>You look not well, Signior Antonio;</line>
            <line>You have too much respect upon the world:</line>
            <line>They lose it that do buy it with much care:</line>
            <line>Believe me, you are marvellously changed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>I hold the world but as the world, Gratiano;</line>
            <line>A stage where every man must play a part,</line>
            <line>And mine a sad one.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRATIANO</speaker>
            <line>Let me play the fool:</line>
            <line>With mirth and laughter let old wrinkles come,</line>
            <line>And let my liver rather heat with wine</line>
            <line>Than my heart cool with mortifying groans.</line>
            <line>Why should a man, whose blood is warm within,</line>
            <line>Sit like his grandsire cut in alabaster?</line>
            <line>Sleep when he wakes and creep into the jaundice</line>
            <line>By being peevish? I tell thee what, Antonio--</line>
            <line>I love thee, and it is my love that speaks--</line>
            <line>There are a sort of men whose visages</line>
            <line>Do cream and mantle like a standing pond,</line>
            <line>And do a wilful stillness entertain,</line>
            <line>With purpose to be dress'd in an opinion</line>
            <line>Of wisdom, gravity, profound conceit,</line>
            <line>As who should say 'I am Sir Oracle,</line>
            <line>And when I ope my lips let no dog bark!'</line>
            <line>O my Antonio, I do know of these</line>
            <line>That therefore only are reputed wise</line>
            <line>For saying nothing; when, I am very sure,</line>
            <line>If they should speak, would almost damn those ears,</line>
            <line>Which, hearing them, would call their brothers fools.</line>
            <line>I'll tell thee more of this another time:</line>
            <line>But fish not, with this melancholy bait,</line>
            <line>For this fool gudgeon, this opinion.</line>
            <line>Come, good Lorenzo. Fare ye well awhile:</line>
            <line>I'll end my exhortation after dinner.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORENZO</speaker>
            <line>Well, we will leave you then till dinner-time:</line>
            <line>I must be one of these same dumb wise men,</line>
            <line>For Gratiano never lets me speak.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRATIANO</speaker>
            <line>Well, keep me company but two years moe,</line>
            <line>Thou shalt not know the sound of thine own tongue.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>Farewell: I'll grow a talker for this gear.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRATIANO</speaker>
            <line>Thanks, i' faith, for silence is only commendable</line>
            <line>In a neat's tongue dried and a maid not vendible.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt GRATIANO and LORENZO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>Is that any thing now?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSANIO</speaker>
            <line>Gratiano speaks an infinite deal of nothing, more</line>
            <line>than any man in all Venice. His reasons are as two</line>
            <line>grains of wheat hid in two bushels of chaff: you</line>
            <line>shall seek all day ere you find them, and when you</line>
            <line>have them, they are not worth the search.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>Well, tell me now what lady is the same</line>
            <line>To whom you swore a secret pilgrimage,</line>
            <line>That you to-day promised to tell me of?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSANIO</speaker>
            <line>'Tis not unknown to you, Antonio,</line>
            <line>How much I have disabled mine estate,</line>
            <line>By something showing a more swelling port</line>
            <line>Than my faint means would grant continuance:</line>
            <line>Nor do I now make moan to be abridged</line>
            <line>From such a noble rate; but my chief care</line>
            <line>Is to come fairly off from the great debts</line>
            <line>Wherein my time something too prodigal</line>
            <line>Hath left me gaged. To you, Antonio,</line>
            <line>I owe the most, in money and in love,</line>
            <line>And from your love I have a warranty</line>
            <line>To unburden all my plots and purposes</line>
            <line>How to get clear of all the debts I owe.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>I pray you, good Bassanio, let me know it;</line>
            <line>And if it stand, as you yourself still do,</line>
            <line>Within the eye of honour, be assured,</line>
            <line>My purse, my person, my extremest means,</line>
            <line>Lie all unlock'd to your occasions.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSANIO</speaker>
            <line>In my school-days, when I had lost one shaft,</line>
            <line>I shot his fellow of the self-same flight</line>
            <line>The self-same way with more advised watch,</line>
            <line>To find the other forth, and by adventuring both</line>
            <line>I oft found both: I urge this childhood proof,</line>
            <line>Because what follows is pure innocence.</line>
            <line>I owe you much, and, like a wilful youth,</line>
            <line>That which I owe is lost; but if you please</line>
            <line>To shoot another arrow that self way</line>
            <line>Which you did shoot the first, I do not doubt,</line>
            <line>As I will watch the aim, or to find both</line>
            <line>Or bring your latter hazard back again</line>
            <line>And thankfully rest debtor for the first.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>You know me well, and herein spend but time</line>
            <line>To wind about my love with circumstance;</line>
            <line>And out of doubt you do me now more wrong</line>
            <line>In making question of my uttermost</line>
            <line>Than if you had made waste of all I have:</line>
            <line>Then do but say to me what I should do</line>
            <line>That in your knowledge may by me be done,</line>
            <line>And I am prest unto it: therefore, speak.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSANIO</speaker>
            <line>In Belmont is a lady richly left;</line>
            <line>And she is fair, and, fairer than that word,</line>
            <line>Of wondrous virtues: sometimes from her eyes</line>
            <line>I did receive fair speechless messages:</line>
            <line>Her name is Portia, nothing undervalued</line>
            <line>To Cato's daughter, Brutus' Portia:</line>
            <line>Nor is the wide world ignorant of her worth,</line>
            <line>For the four winds blow in from every coast</line>
            <line>Renowned suitors, and her sunny locks</line>
            <line>Hang on her temples like a golden fleece;</line>
            <line>Which makes her seat of Belmont Colchos' strand,</line>
            <line>And many Jasons come in quest of her.</line>
            <line>O my Antonio, had I but the means</line>
            <line>To hold a rival place with one of them,</line>
            <line>I have a mind presages me such thrift,</line>
            <line>That I should questionless be fortunate!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>Thou know'st that all my fortunes are at sea;</line>
            <line>Neither have I money nor commodity</line>
            <line>To raise a present sum: therefore go forth;</line>
            <line>Try what my credit can in Venice do:</line>
            <line>That shall be rack'd, even to the uttermost,</line>
            <line>To furnish thee to Belmont, to fair Portia.</line>
            <line>Go, presently inquire, and so will I,</line>
            <line>Where money is, and I no question make</line>
            <line>To have it of my trust or for my sake.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II: Belmont. A room in PORTIA'S house.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter PORTIA and NERISSA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PORTIA</speaker>
            <line>By my troth, Nerissa, my little body is aweary of</line>
            <line>this great world.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NERISSA</speaker>
            <line>You would be, sweet madam, if your miseries were in</line>
            <line>the same abundance as your good fortunes are: and</line>
            <line>yet, for aught I see, they are as sick that surfeit</line>
            <line>with too much as they that starve with nothing. It</line>
            <line>is no mean happiness therefore, to be seated in the</line>
            <line>mean: superfluity comes sooner by white hairs, but</line>
            <line>competency lives longer.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PORTIA</speaker>
            <line>Good sentences and well pronounced.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NERISSA</speaker>
            <line>They would be better, if well followed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PORTIA</speaker>
            <line>If to do were as easy as to know what were good to</line>
            <line>do, chapels had been churches and poor men's</line>
            <line>cottages princes' palaces. It is a good divine that</line>
            <line>follows his own instructions: I can easier teach</line>
            <line>twenty what were good to be done, than be one of the</line>
            <line>twenty to follow mine own teaching. The brain may</line>
            <line>devise laws for the blood, but a hot temper leaps</line>
            <line>o'er a cold decree: such a hare is madness the</line>
            <line>youth, to skip o'er the meshes of good counsel the</line>
            <line>cripple. But this reasoning is not in the fashion to</line>
            <line>choose me a husband. O me, the word 'choose!' I may</line>
            <line>neither choose whom I would nor refuse whom I</line>
            <line>dislike; so is the will of a living daughter curbed</line>
            <line>by the will of a dead father. Is it not hard,</line>
            <line>Nerissa, that I cannot choose one nor refuse none?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NERISSA</speaker>
            <line>Your father was ever virtuous; and holy men at their</line>
            <line>death have good inspirations: therefore the lottery,</line>
            <line>that he hath devised in these three chests of gold,</line>
            <line>silver and lead, whereof who chooses his meaning</line>
            <line>chooses you, will, no doubt, never be chosen by any</line>
            <line>rightly but one who shall rightly love. But what</line>
            <line>warmth is there in your affection towards any of</line>
            <line>these princely suitors that are already come?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PORTIA</speaker>
            <line>I pray thee, over-name them; and as thou namest</line>
            <line>them, I will describe them; and, according to my</line>
            <line>description, level at my affection.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NERISSA</speaker>
            <line>First, there is the Neapolitan prince.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PORTIA</speaker>
            <line>Ay, that's a colt indeed, for he doth nothing but</line>
            <line>talk of his horse; and he makes it a great</line>
            <line>appropriation to his own good parts, that he can</line>
            <line>shoe him himself. I am much afeard my lady his</line>
            <line>mother played false with a smith.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NERISSA</speaker>
            <line>Then there is the County Palatine.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PORTIA</speaker>
            <line>He doth nothing but frown, as who should say 'If you</line>
            <line>will not have me, choose:' he hears merry tales and</line>
            <line>smiles not: I fear he will prove the weeping</line>
            <line>philosopher when he grows old, being so full of</line>
            <line>unmannerly sadness in his youth. I had rather be</line>
            <line>married to a death's-head with a bone in his mouth</line>
            <line>than to either of these. God defend me from these</line>
            <line>two!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NERISSA</speaker>
            <line>How say you by the French lord, Monsieur Le Bon?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PORTIA</speaker>
            <line>God made him, and therefore let him pass for a man.</line>
            <line>In truth, I know it is a sin to be a mocker: but,</line>
            <line>he! why, he hath a horse better than the</line>
            <line>Neapolitan's, a better bad habit of frowning than</line>
            <line>the Count Palatine; he is every man in no man; if a</line>
            <line>throstle sing, he falls straight a capering: he will</line>
            <line>fence with his own shadow: if I should marry him, I</line>
            <line>should marry twenty husbands. If he would despise me</line>
            <line>I would forgive him, for if he love me to madness, I</line>
            <line>shall never requite him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NERISSA</speaker>
            <line>What say you, then, to Falconbridge, the young baron</line>
            <line>of England?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PORTIA</speaker>
            <line>You know I say nothing to him, for he understands</line>
            <line>not me, nor I him: he hath neither Latin, French,</line>
            <line>nor Italian, and you will come into the court and</line>
            <line>swear that I have a poor pennyworth in the English.</line>
            <line>He is a proper man's picture, but, alas, who can</line>
            <line>converse with a dumb-show? How oddly he is suited!</line>
            <line>I think he bought his doublet in Italy, his round</line>
            <line>hose in France, his bonnet in Germany and his</line>
            <line>behavior every where.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NERISSA</speaker>
            <line>What think you of the Scottish lord, his neighbour?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PORTIA</speaker>
            <line>That he hath a neighbourly charity in him, for he</line>
            <line>borrowed a box of the ear of the Englishman and</line>
            <line>swore he would pay him again when he was able: I</line>
            <line>think the Frenchman became his surety and sealed</line>
            <line>under for another.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NERISSA</speaker>
            <line>How like you the young German, the Duke of Saxony's nephew?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PORTIA</speaker>
            <line>Very vilely in the morning, when he is sober, and</line>
            <line>most vilely in the afternoon, when he is drunk: when</line>
            <line>he is best, he is a little worse than a man, and</line>
            <line>when he is worst, he is little better than a beast:</line>
            <line>and the worst fall that ever fell, I hope I shall</line>
            <line>make shift to go without him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NERISSA</speaker>
            <line>If he should offer to choose, and choose the right</line>
            <line>casket, you should refuse to perform your father's</line>
            <line>will, if you should refuse to accept him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PORTIA</speaker>
            <line>Therefore, for fear of the worst, I pray thee, set a</line>
            <line>deep glass of rhenish wine on the contrary casket,</line>
            <line>for if the devil be within and that temptation</line>
            <line>without, I know he will choose it. I will do any</line>
            <line>thing, Nerissa, ere I'll be married to a sponge.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NERISSA</speaker>
            <line>You need not fear, lady, the having any of these</line>
            <line>lords: they have acquainted me with their</line>
            <line>determinations; which is, indeed, to return to their</line>
            <line>home and to trouble you with no more suit, unless</line>
            <line>you may be won by some other sort than your father's</line>
            <line>imposition depending on the caskets.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PORTIA</speaker>
            <line>If I live to be as old as Sibylla, I will die as</line>
            <line>chaste as Diana, unless I be obtained by the manner</line>
            <line>of my father's will. I am glad this parcel of wooers</line>
            <line>are so reasonable, for there is not one among them</line>
            <line>but I dote on his very absence, and I pray God grant</line>
            <line>them a fair departure.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NERISSA</speaker>
            <line>Do you not remember, lady, in your father's time, a</line>
            <line>Venetian, a scholar and a soldier, that came hither</line>
            <line>in company of the Marquis of Montferrat?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PORTIA</speaker>
            <line>Yes, yes, it was Bassanio; as I think, he was so called.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NERISSA</speaker>
            <line>True, madam: he, of all the men that ever my foolish</line>
            <line>eyes looked upon, was the best deserving a fair lady.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PORTIA</speaker>
            <line>I remember him well, and I remember him worthy of</line>
            <line>thy praise.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter a Serving-man</stagedir>
            <line>How now! what news?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>The four strangers seek for you, madam, to take</line>
            <line>their leave: and there is a forerunner come from a</line>
            <line>fifth, the Prince of Morocco, who brings word the</line>
            <line>prince his master will be here to-night.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PORTIA</speaker>
            <line>If I could bid the fifth welcome with so good a</line>
            <line>heart as I can bid the other four farewell, I should</line>
            <line>be glad of his approach: if he have the condition</line>
            <line>of a saint and the complexion of a devil, I had</line>
            <line>rather he should shrive me than wive me. Come,</line>
            <line>Nerissa. Sirrah, go before.</line>
            <line>Whiles we shut the gates</line>
            <line>upon one wooer, another knocks at the door.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  Venice. A public place.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter BASSANIO and SHYLOCK</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>
            <line>Three thousand ducats; well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSANIO</speaker>
            <line>Ay, sir, for three months.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>
            <line>For three months; well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSANIO</speaker>
            <line>For the which, as I told you, Antonio shall be bound.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>
            <line>Antonio shall become bound; well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSANIO</speaker>
            <line>May you stead me? will you pleasure me? shall I</line>
            <line>know your answer?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>
            <line>Three thousand ducats for three months and Antonio bound.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSANIO</speaker>
            <line>Your answer to that.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>
            <line>Antonio is a good man.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSANIO</speaker>
            <line>Have you heard any imputation to the contrary?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>
            <line>Oh, no, no, no, no: my meaning in saying he is a</line>
            <line>good man is to have you understand me that he is</line>
            <line>sufficient. Yet his means are in supposition: he</line>
            <line>hath an argosy bound to Tripolis, another to the</line>
            <line>Indies; I understand moreover, upon the Rialto, he</line>
            <line>hath a third at Mexico, a fourth for England, and</line>
            <line>other ventures he hath, squandered abroad. But ships</line>
            <line>are but boards, sailors but men: there be land-rats</line>
            <line>and water-rats, water-thieves and land-thieves, I</line>
            <line>mean pirates, and then there is the peril of waters,</line>
            <line>winds and rocks. The man is, notwithstanding,</line>
            <line>sufficient. Three thousand ducats; I think I may</line>
            <line>take his bond.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSANIO</speaker>
            <line>Be assured you may.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>
            <line>I will be assured I may; and, that I may be assured,</line>
            <line>I will bethink me. May I speak with Antonio?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSANIO</speaker>
            <line>If it please you to dine with us.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>
            <line>Yes, to smell pork; to eat of the habitation which</line>
            <line>your prophet the Nazarite conjured the devil into. I</line>
            <line>will buy with you, sell with you, talk with you,</line>
            <line>walk with you, and so following, but I will not eat</line>
            <line>with you, drink with you, nor pray with you. What</line>
            <line>news on the Rialto? Who is he comes here?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter ANTONIO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSANIO</speaker>
            <line>This is Signior Antonio.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  How like a fawning publican he looks!</line>
            <line>I hate him for he is a Christian,</line>
            <line>But more for that in low simplicity</line>
            <line>He lends out money gratis and brings down</line>
            <line>The rate of usance here with us in Venice.</line>
            <line>If I can catch him once upon the hip,</line>
            <line>I will feed fat the ancient grudge I bear him.</line>
            <line>He hates our sacred nation, and he rails,</line>
            <line>Even there where merchants most do congregate,</line>
            <line>On me, my bargains and my well-won thrift,</line>
            <line>Which he calls interest. Cursed be my tribe,</line>
            <line>If I forgive him!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSANIO</speaker>
            <line>Shylock, do you hear?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>
            <line>I am debating of my present store,</line>
            <line>And, by the near guess of my memory,</line>
            <line>I cannot instantly raise up the gross</line>
            <line>Of full three thousand ducats. What of that?</line>
            <line>Tubal, a wealthy Hebrew of my tribe,</line>
            <line>Will furnish me. But soft! how many months</line>
            <line>Do you desire?</line>
            <stagedir>To ANTONIO</stagedir>
            <line>Rest you fair, good signior;</line>
            <line>Your worship was the last man in our mouths.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>Shylock, although I neither lend nor borrow</line>
            <line>By taking nor by giving of excess,</line>
            <line>Yet, to supply the ripe wants of my friend,</line>
            <line>I'll break a custom. Is he yet possess'd</line>
            <line>How much ye would?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>
            <line>Ay, ay, three thousand ducats.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>And for three months.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>
            <line>I had forgot; three months; you told me so.</line>
            <line>Well then, your bond; and let me see; but hear you;</line>
            <line>Methought you said you neither lend nor borrow</line>
            <line>Upon advantage.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>I do never use it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>
            <line>When Jacob grazed his uncle Laban's sheep--</line>
            <line>This Jacob from our holy Abram was,</line>
            <line>As his wise mother wrought in his behalf,</line>
            <line>The third possessor; ay, he was the third--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>And what of him? did he take interest?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>
            <line>No, not take interest, not, as you would say,</line>
            <line>Directly interest: mark what Jacob did.</line>
            <line>When Laban and himself were compromised</line>
            <line>That all the eanlings which were streak'd and pied</line>
            <line>Should fall as Jacob's hire, the ewes, being rank,</line>
            <line>In the end of autumn turned to the rams,</line>
            <line>And, when the work of generation was</line>
            <line>Between these woolly breeders in the act,</line>
            <line>The skilful shepherd peel'd me certain wands,</line>
            <line>And, in the doing of the deed of kind,</line>
            <line>He stuck them up before the fulsome ewes,</line>
            <line>Who then conceiving did in eaning time</line>
            <line>Fall parti-colour'd lambs, and those were Jacob's.</line>
            <line>This was a way to thrive, and he was blest:</line>
            <line>And thrift is blessing, if men steal it not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>This was a venture, sir, that Jacob served for;</line>
            <line>A thing not in his power to bring to pass,</line>
            <line>But sway'd and fashion'd by the hand of heaven.</line>
            <line>Was this inserted to make interest good?</line>
            <line>Or is your gold and silver ewes and rams?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>
            <line>I cannot tell; I make it breed as fast:</line>
            <line>But note me, signior.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>Mark you this, Bassanio,</line>
            <line>The devil can cite Scripture for his purpose.</line>
            <line>An evil soul producing holy witness</line>
            <line>Is like a villain with a smiling cheek,</line>
            <line>A goodly apple rotten at the heart:</line>
            <line>O, what a goodly outside falsehood hath!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>
            <line>Three thousand ducats; 'tis a good round sum.</line>
            <line>Three months from twelve; then, let me see; the rate--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>Well, Shylock, shall we be beholding to you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>
            <line>Signior Antonio, many a time and oft</line>
            <line>In the Rialto you have rated me</line>
            <line>About my moneys and my usances:</line>
            <line>Still have I borne it with a patient shrug,</line>
            <line>For sufferance is the badge of all our tribe.</line>
            <line>You call me misbeliever, cut-throat dog,</line>
            <line>And spit upon my Jewish gaberdine,</line>
            <line>And all for use of that which is mine own.</line>
            <line>Well then, it now appears you need my help:</line>
            <line>Go to, then; you come to me, and you say</line>
            <line>'Shylock, we would have moneys:' you say so;</line>
            <line>You, that did void your rheum upon my beard</line>
            <line>And foot me as you spurn a stranger cur</line>
            <line>Over your threshold: moneys is your suit</line>
            <line>What should I say to you? Should I not say</line>
            <line>'Hath a dog money? is it possible</line>
            <line>A cur can lend three thousand ducats?' Or</line>
            <line>Shall I bend low and in a bondman's key,</line>
            <line>With bated breath and whispering humbleness, Say this;</line>
            <line>'Fair sir, you spit on me on Wednesday last;</line>
            <line>You spurn'd me such a day; another time</line>
            <line>You call'd me dog; and for these courtesies</line>
            <line>I'll lend you thus much moneys'?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>I am as like to call thee so again,</line>
            <line>To spit on thee again, to spurn thee too.</line>
            <line>If thou wilt lend this money, lend it not</line>
            <line>As to thy friends; for when did friendship take</line>
            <line>A breed for barren metal of his friend?</line>
            <line>But lend it rather to thine enemy,</line>
            <line>Who, if he break, thou mayst with better face</line>
            <line>Exact the penalty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>
            <line>Why, look you, how you storm!</line>
            <line>I would be friends with you and have your love,</line>
            <line>Forget the shames that you have stain'd me with,</line>
            <line>Supply your present wants and take no doit</line>
            <line>Of usance for my moneys, and you'll not hear me:</line>
            <line>This is kind I offer.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSANIO</speaker>
            <line>This were kindness.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>
            <line>This kindness will I show.</line>
            <line>Go with me to a notary, seal me there</line>
            <line>Your single bond; and, in a merry sport,</line>
            <line>If you repay me not on such a day,</line>
            <line>In such a place, such sum or sums as are</line>
            <line>Express'd in the condition, let the forfeit</line>
            <line>Be nominated for an equal pound</line>
            <line>Of your fair flesh, to be cut off and taken</line>
            <line>In what part of your body pleaseth me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>Content, i' faith: I'll seal to such a bond</line>
            <line>And say there is much kindness in the Jew.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSANIO</speaker>
            <line>You shall not seal to such a bond for me:</line>
            <line>I'll rather dwell in my necessity.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>Why, fear not, man; I will not forfeit it:</line>
            <line>Within these two months, that's a month before</line>
            <line>This bond expires, I do expect return</line>
            <line>Of thrice three times the value of this bond.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>
            <line>O father Abram, what these Christians are,</line>
            <line>Whose own hard dealings teaches them suspect</line>
            <line>The thoughts of others! Pray you, tell me this;</line>
            <line>If he should break his day, what should I gain</line>
            <line>By the exaction of the forfeiture?</line>
            <line>A pound of man's flesh taken from a man</line>
            <line>Is not so estimable, profitable neither,</line>
            <line>As flesh of muttons, beefs, or goats. I say,</line>
            <line>To buy his favour, I extend this friendship:</line>
            <line>If he will take it, so; if not, adieu;</line>
            <line>And, for my love, I pray you wrong me not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>Yes Shylock, I will seal unto this bond.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHYLOCK</speaker>
            <line>Then meet me forthwith at the notary's;</line>
            <line>Give him direction for this merry bond,</line>
            <line>And I will go and purse the ducats straight,</line>
            <line>See to my house, left in the fearful guard</line>
            <line>Of an unthrifty knave, and presently</line>
            <line>I will be with you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>Hie thee, gentle Jew.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit Shylock</stagedir>
            <line>The Hebrew will turn Christian: he grows kind.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSANIO</speaker>
            <line>I like not fair terms and a villain's mind.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>Come on: in this there can be no dismay;</line>
            <line>My ships come home a month before the day.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>