<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:shakespear:dtd:act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-3">
   <title>ACT III</title>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  Forres. The palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter BANQUO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BANQUO</speaker>
            <line>Thou hast it now: king, Cawdor, Glamis, all,</line>
            <line>As the weird women promised, and, I fear,</line>
            <line>Thou play'dst most foully for't: yet it was said</line>
            <line>It should not stand in thy posterity,</line>
            <line>But that myself should be the root and father</line>
            <line>Of many kings. If there come truth from them--</line>
            <line>As upon thee, Macbeth, their speeches shine--</line>
            <line>Why, by the verities on thee made good,</line>
            <line>May they not be my oracles as well,</line>
            <line>And set me up in hope? But hush! no more.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Sennet sounded. Enter MACBETH, as king, LADY
MACBETH, as queen, LENNOX, ROSS, Lords, Ladies, and
Attendants</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>Here's our chief guest.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>If he had been forgotten,</line>
            <line>It had been as a gap in our great feast,</line>
            <line>And all-thing unbecoming.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>To-night we hold a solemn supper sir,</line>
            <line>And I'll request your presence.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BANQUO</speaker>
            <line>Let your highness</line>
            <line>Command upon me; to the which my duties</line>
            <line>Are with a most indissoluble tie</line>
            <line>For ever knit.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>Ride you this afternoon?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BANQUO</speaker>
            <line>Ay, my good lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>We should have else desired your good advice,</line>
            <line>Which still hath been both grave and prosperous,</line>
            <line>In this day's council; but we'll take to-morrow.</line>
            <line>Is't far you ride?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BANQUO</speaker>
            <line>As far, my lord, as will fill up the time</line>
            <line>'Twixt this and supper: go not my horse the better,</line>
            <line>I must become a borrower of the night</line>
            <line>For a dark hour or twain.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>Fail not our feast.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BANQUO</speaker>
            <line>My lord, I will not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>We hear, our bloody cousins are bestow'd</line>
            <line>In England and in Ireland, not confessing</line>
            <line>Their cruel parricide, filling their hearers</line>
            <line>With strange invention: but of that to-morrow,</line>
            <line>When therewithal we shall have cause of state</line>
            <line>Craving us jointly. Hie you to horse: adieu,</line>
            <line>Till you return at night. Goes Fleance with you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BANQUO</speaker>
            <line>Ay, my good lord: our time does call upon 's.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>I wish your horses swift and sure of foot;</line>
            <line>And so I do commend you to their backs. Farewell.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit BANQUO</stagedir>
            <line>Let every man be master of his time</line>
            <line>Till seven at night: to make society</line>
            <line>The sweeter welcome, we will keep ourself</line>
            <line>Till supper-time alone: while then, God be with you!</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt all but MACBETH, and an attendant</stagedir>
            <line>Sirrah, a word with you: attend those men</line>
            <line>Our pleasure?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ATTENDANT</speaker>
            <line>They are, my lord, without the palace gate.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>Bring them before us.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit Attendant</stagedir>
            <line>To be thus is nothing;</line>
            <line>But to be safely thus.--Our fears in Banquo</line>
            <line>Stick deep; and in his royalty of nature</line>
            <line>Reigns that which would be fear'd: 'tis much he dares;</line>
            <line>And, to that dauntless temper of his mind,</line>
            <line>He hath a wisdom that doth guide his valour</line>
            <line>To act in safety. There is none but he</line>
            <line>Whose being I do fear: and, under him,</line>
            <line>My Genius is rebuked; as, it is said,</line>
            <line>Mark Antony's was by Caesar. He chid the sisters</line>
            <line>When first they put the name of king upon me,</line>
            <line>And bade them speak to him: then prophet-like</line>
            <line>They hail'd him father to a line of kings:</line>
            <line>Upon my head they placed a fruitless crown,</line>
            <line>And put a barren sceptre in my gripe,</line>
            <line>Thence to be wrench'd with an unlineal hand,</line>
            <line>No son of mine succeeding. If 't be so,</line>
            <line>For Banquo's issue have I filed my mind;</line>
            <line>For them the gracious Duncan have I murder'd;</line>
            <line>Put rancours in the vessel of my peace</line>
            <line>Only for them; and mine eternal jewel</line>
            <line>Given to the common enemy of man,</line>
            <line>To make them kings, the seed of Banquo kings!</line>
            <line>Rather than so, come fate into the list.</line>
            <line>And champion me to the utterance! Who's there!</line>
            <stagedir>Re-enter Attendant, with two Murderers</stagedir>
            <line>Now go to the door, and stay there till we call.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit Attendant</stagedir>
            <line>Was it not yesterday we spoke together?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Murderer</speaker>
            <line>It was, so please your highness.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>Well then, now</line>
            <line>Have you consider'd of my speeches? Know</line>
            <line>That it was he in the times past which held you</line>
            <line>So under fortune, which you thought had been</line>
            <line>Our innocent self: this I made good to you</line>
            <line>In our last conference, pass'd in probation with you,</line>
            <line>How you were borne in hand, how cross'd,</line>
            <line>the instruments,</line>
            <line>Who wrought with them, and all things else that might</line>
            <line>To half a soul and to a notion crazed</line>
            <line>Say 'Thus did Banquo.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Murderer</speaker>
            <line>You made it known to us.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>I did so, and went further, which is now</line>
            <line>Our point of second meeting. Do you find</line>
            <line>Your patience so predominant in your nature</line>
            <line>That you can let this go? Are you so gospell'd</line>
            <line>To pray for this good man and for his issue,</line>
            <line>Whose heavy hand hath bow'd you to the grave</line>
            <line>And beggar'd yours for ever?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Murderer</speaker>
            <line>We are men, my liege.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>Ay, in the catalogue ye go for men;</line>
            <line>As hounds and greyhounds, mongrels, spaniels, curs,</line>
            <line>Shoughs, water-rugs and demi-wolves, are clept</line>
            <line>All by the name of dogs: the valued file</line>
            <line>Distinguishes the swift, the slow, the subtle,</line>
            <line>The housekeeper, the hunter, every one</line>
            <line>According to the gift which bounteous nature</line>
            <line>Hath in him closed; whereby he does receive</line>
            <line>Particular addition. from the bill</line>
            <line>That writes them all alike: and so of men.</line>
            <line>Now, if you have a station in the file,</line>
            <line>Not i' the worst rank of manhood, say 't;</line>
            <line>And I will put that business in your bosoms,</line>
            <line>Whose execution takes your enemy off,</line>
            <line>Grapples you to the heart and love of us,</line>
            <line>Who wear our health but sickly in his life,</line>
            <line>Which in his death were perfect.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Murderer</speaker>
            <line>I am one, my liege,</line>
            <line>Whom the vile blows and buffets of the world</line>
            <line>Have so incensed that I am reckless what</line>
            <line>I do to spite the world.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Murderer</speaker>
            <line>And I another</line>
            <line>So weary with disasters, tugg'd with fortune,</line>
            <line>That I would set my lie on any chance,</line>
            <line>To mend it, or be rid on't.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>Both of you</line>
            <line>Know Banquo was your enemy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Both Murderers</speaker>
            <line>True, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>So is he mine; and in such bloody distance,</line>
            <line>That every minute of his being thrusts</line>
            <line>Against my near'st of life: and though I could</line>
            <line>With barefaced power sweep him from my sight</line>
            <line>And bid my will avouch it, yet I must not,</line>
            <line>For certain friends that are both his and mine,</line>
            <line>Whose loves I may not drop, but wail his fall</line>
            <line>Who I myself struck down; and thence it is,</line>
            <line>That I to your assistance do make love,</line>
            <line>Masking the business from the common eye</line>
            <line>For sundry weighty reasons.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Murderer</speaker>
            <line>We shall, my lord,</line>
            <line>Perform what you command us.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Murderer</speaker>
            <line>Though our lives--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>Your spirits shine through you. Within this hour at most</line>
            <line>I will advise you where to plant yourselves;</line>
            <line>Acquaint you with the perfect spy o' the time,</line>
            <line>The moment on't; for't must be done to-night,</line>
            <line>And something from the palace; always thought</line>
            <line>That I require a clearness: and with him--</line>
            <line>To leave no rubs nor botches in the work--</line>
            <line>Fleance his son, that keeps him company,</line>
            <line>Whose absence is no less material to me</line>
            <line>Than is his father's, must embrace the fate</line>
            <line>Of that dark hour. Resolve yourselves apart:</line>
            <line>I'll come to you anon.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Both Murderers</speaker>
            <line>We are resolved, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>I'll call upon you straight: abide within.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt Murderers</stagedir>
            <line>It is concluded. Banquo, thy soul's flight,</line>
            <line>If it find heaven, must find it out to-night.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  The palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter LADY MACBETH and a Servant</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>Is Banquo gone from court?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>Ay, madam, but returns again to-night.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>Say to the king, I would attend his leisure</line>
            <line>For a few words.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>Madam, I will.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>Nought's had, all's spent,</line>
            <line>Where our desire is got without content:</line>
            <line>'Tis safer to be that which we destroy</line>
            <line>Than by destruction dwell in doubtful joy.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter MACBETH</stagedir>
            <line>How now, my lord! why do you keep alone,</line>
            <line>Of sorriest fancies your companions making,</line>
            <line>Using those thoughts which should indeed have died</line>
            <line>With them they think on? Things without all remedy</line>
            <line>Should be without regard: what's done is done.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>We have scotch'd the snake, not kill'd it:</line>
            <line>She'll close and be herself, whilst our poor malice</line>
            <line>Remains in danger of her former tooth.</line>
            <line>But let the frame of things disjoint, both the</line>
            <line>worlds suffer,</line>
            <line>Ere we will eat our meal in fear and sleep</line>
            <line>In the affliction of these terrible dreams</line>
            <line>That shake us nightly: better be with the dead,</line>
            <line>Whom we, to gain our peace, have sent to peace,</line>
            <line>Than on the torture of the mind to lie</line>
            <line>In restless ecstasy. Duncan is in his grave;</line>
            <line>After life's fitful fever he sleeps well;</line>
            <line>Treason has done his worst: nor steel, nor poison,</line>
            <line>Malice domestic, foreign levy, nothing,</line>
            <line>Can touch him further.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>Come on;</line>
            <line>Gentle my lord, sleek o'er your rugged looks;</line>
            <line>Be bright and jovial among your guests to-night.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>So shall I, love; and so, I pray, be you:</line>
            <line>Let your remembrance apply to Banquo;</line>
            <line>Present him eminence, both with eye and tongue:</line>
            <line>Unsafe the while, that we</line>
            <line>Must lave our honours in these flattering streams,</line>
            <line>And make our faces vizards to our hearts,</line>
            <line>Disguising what they are.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>You must leave this.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>O, full of scorpions is my mind, dear wife!</line>
            <line>Thou know'st that Banquo, and his Fleance, lives.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>But in them nature's copy's not eterne.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>There's comfort yet; they are assailable;</line>
            <line>Then be thou jocund: ere the bat hath flown</line>
            <line>His cloister'd flight, ere to black Hecate's summons</line>
            <line>The shard-borne beetle with his drowsy hums</line>
            <line>Hath rung night's yawning peal, there shall be done</line>
            <line>A deed of dreadful note.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>What's to be done?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>Be innocent of the knowledge, dearest chuck,</line>
            <line>Till thou applaud the deed. Come, seeling night,</line>
            <line>Scarf up the tender eye of pitiful day;</line>
            <line>And with thy bloody and invisible hand</line>
            <line>Cancel and tear to pieces that great bond</line>
            <line>Which keeps me pale! Light thickens; and the crow</line>
            <line>Makes wing to the rooky wood:</line>
            <line>Good things of day begin to droop and drowse;</line>
            <line>While night's black agents to their preys do rouse.</line>
            <line>Thou marvell'st at my words: but hold thee still;</line>
            <line>Things bad begun make strong themselves by ill.</line>
            <line>So, prithee, go with me.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  A park near the palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter three Murderers</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Murderer</speaker>
            <line>But who did bid thee join with us?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Murderer</speaker>
            <line>Macbeth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Murderer</speaker>
            <line>He needs not our mistrust, since he delivers</line>
            <line>Our offices and what we have to do</line>
            <line>To the direction just.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Murderer</speaker>
            <line>Then stand with us.</line>
            <line>The west yet glimmers with some streaks of day:</line>
            <line>Now spurs the lated traveller apace</line>
            <line>To gain the timely inn; and near approaches</line>
            <line>The subject of our watch.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Murderer</speaker>
            <line>Hark! I hear horses.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BANQUO</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Within</stagedir>  Give us a light there, ho!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Murderer</speaker>
            <line>Then 'tis he: the rest</line>
            <line>That are within the note of expectation</line>
            <line>Already are i' the court.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Murderer</speaker>
            <line>His horses go about.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Murderer</speaker>
            <line>Almost a mile: but he does usually,</line>
            <line>So all men do, from hence to the palace gate</line>
            <line>Make it their walk.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Murderer</speaker>
            <line>A light, a light!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter BANQUO, and FLEANCE with a torch</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Murderer</speaker>
            <line>'Tis he.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Murderer</speaker>
            <line>Stand to't.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BANQUO</speaker>
            <line>It will be rain to-night.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Murderer</speaker>
            <line>Let it come down.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>They set upon BANQUO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BANQUO</speaker>
            <line>O, treachery! Fly, good Fleance, fly, fly, fly!</line>
            <line>Thou mayst revenge. O slave!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Dies. FLEANCE escapes</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Murderer</speaker>
            <line>Who did strike out the light?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Murderer</speaker>
            <line>Wast not the way?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Murderer</speaker>
            <line>There's but one down; the son is fled.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Murderer</speaker>
            <line>We have lost</line>
            <line>Best half of our affair.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Murderer</speaker>
            <line>Well, let's away, and say how much is done.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-4">
      <title>SCENE IV.  The same. Hall in the palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>A banquet prepared. Enter MACBETH, LADY MACBETH,
ROSS, LENNOX, Lords, and Attendants</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>You know your own degrees; sit down: at first</line>
            <line>And last the hearty welcome.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lords</speaker>
            <line>Thanks to your majesty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>Ourself will mingle with society,</line>
            <line>And play the humble host.</line>
            <line>Our hostess keeps her state, but in best time</line>
            <line>We will require her welcome.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>Pronounce it for me, sir, to all our friends;</line>
            <line>For my heart speaks they are welcome.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>First Murderer appears at the door</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>See, they encounter thee with their hearts' thanks.</line>
            <line>Both sides are even: here I'll sit i' the midst:</line>
            <line>Be large in mirth; anon we'll drink a measure</line>
            <line>The table round.</line>
            <stagedir>Approaching the door</stagedir>
            <line>There's blood on thy face.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Murderer</speaker>
            <line>'Tis Banquo's then.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>'Tis better thee without than he within.</line>
            <line>Is he dispatch'd?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Murderer</speaker>
            <line>My lord, his throat is cut; that I did for him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>Thou art the best o' the cut-throats: yet he's good</line>
            <line>That did the like for Fleance: if thou didst it,</line>
            <line>Thou art the nonpareil.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Murderer</speaker>
            <line>Most royal sir,</line>
            <line>Fleance is 'scaped.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>Then comes my fit again: I had else been perfect,</line>
            <line>Whole as the marble, founded as the rock,</line>
            <line>As broad and general as the casing air:</line>
            <line>But now I am cabin'd, cribb'd, confined, bound in</line>
            <line>To saucy doubts and fears. But Banquo's safe?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Murderer</speaker>
            <line>Ay, my good lord: safe in a ditch he bides,</line>
            <line>With twenty trenched gashes on his head;</line>
            <line>The least a death to nature.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>Thanks for that:</line>
            <line>There the grown serpent lies; the worm that's fled</line>
            <line>Hath nature that in time will venom breed,</line>
            <line>No teeth for the present. Get thee gone: to-morrow</line>
            <line>We'll hear, ourselves, again.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit Murderer</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>My royal lord,</line>
            <line>You do not give the cheer: the feast is sold</line>
            <line>That is not often vouch'd, while 'tis a-making,</line>
            <line>'Tis given with welcome: to feed were best at home;</line>
            <line>From thence the sauce to meat is ceremony;</line>
            <line>Meeting were bare without it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>Sweet remembrancer!</line>
            <line>Now, good digestion wait on appetite,</line>
            <line>And health on both!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LENNOX</speaker>
            <line>May't please your highness sit.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>The GHOST OF BANQUO enters, and sits in
MACBETH's place</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>Here had we now our country's honour roof'd,</line>
            <line>Were the graced person of our Banquo present;</line>
            <line>Who may I rather challenge for unkindness</line>
            <line>Than pity for mischance!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSS</speaker>
            <line>His absence, sir,</line>
            <line>Lays blame upon his promise. Please't your highness</line>
            <line>To grace us with your royal company.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>The table's full.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LENNOX</speaker>
            <line>Here is a place reserved, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>Where?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LENNOX</speaker>
            <line>Here, my good lord. What is't that moves your highness?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>Which of you have done this?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lords</speaker>
            <line>What, my good lord?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>Thou canst not say I did it: never shake</line>
            <line>Thy gory locks at me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSS</speaker>
            <line>Gentlemen, rise: his highness is not well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>Sit, worthy friends: my lord is often thus,</line>
            <line>And hath been from his youth: pray you, keep seat;</line>
            <line>The fit is momentary; upon a thought</line>
            <line>He will again be well: if much you note him,</line>
            <line>You shall offend him and extend his passion:</line>
            <line>Feed, and regard him not. Are you a man?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>Ay, and a bold one, that dare look on that</line>
            <line>Which might appal the devil.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>O proper stuff!</line>
            <line>This is the very painting of your fear:</line>
            <line>This is the air-drawn dagger which, you said,</line>
            <line>Led you to Duncan. O, these flaws and starts,</line>
            <line>Impostors to true fear, would well become</line>
            <line>A woman's story at a winter's fire,</line>
            <line>Authorized by her grandam. Shame itself!</line>
            <line>Why do you make such faces? When all's done,</line>
            <line>You look but on a stool.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>Prithee, see there! behold! look! lo!</line>
            <line>how say you?</line>
            <line>Why, what care I? If thou canst nod, speak too.</line>
            <line>If charnel-houses and our graves must send</line>
            <line>Those that we bury back, our monuments</line>
            <line>Shall be the maws of kites.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>GHOST OF BANQUO vanishes</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>What, quite unmann'd in folly?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>If I stand here, I saw him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>Fie, for shame!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>Blood hath been shed ere now, i' the olden time,</line>
            <line>Ere human statute purged the gentle weal;</line>
            <line>Ay, and since too, murders have been perform'd</line>
            <line>Too terrible for the ear: the times have been,</line>
            <line>That, when the brains were out, the man would die,</line>
            <line>And there an end; but now they rise again,</line>
            <line>With twenty mortal murders on their crowns,</line>
            <line>And push us from our stools: this is more strange</line>
            <line>Than such a murder is.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>My worthy lord,</line>
            <line>Your noble friends do lack you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>I do forget.</line>
            <line>Do not muse at me, my most worthy friends,</line>
            <line>I have a strange infirmity, which is nothing</line>
            <line>To those that know me. Come, love and health to all;</line>
            <line>Then I'll sit down. Give me some wine; fill full.</line>
            <line>I drink to the general joy o' the whole table,</line>
            <line>And to our dear friend Banquo, whom we miss;</line>
            <line>Would he were here! to all, and him, we thirst,</line>
            <line>And all to all.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lords</speaker>
            <line>Our duties, and the pledge.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter GHOST OF BANQUO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>Avaunt! and quit my sight! let the earth hide thee!</line>
            <line>Thy bones are marrowless, thy blood is cold;</line>
            <line>Thou hast no speculation in those eyes</line>
            <line>Which thou dost glare with!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>Think of this, good peers,</line>
            <line>But as a thing of custom: 'tis no other;</line>
            <line>Only it spoils the pleasure of the time.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>What man dare, I dare:</line>
            <line>Approach thou like the rugged Russian bear,</line>
            <line>The arm'd rhinoceros, or the Hyrcan tiger;</line>
            <line>Take any shape but that, and my firm nerves</line>
            <line>Shall never tremble: or be alive again,</line>
            <line>And dare me to the desert with thy sword;</line>
            <line>If trembling I inhabit then, protest me</line>
            <line>The baby of a girl. Hence, horrible shadow!</line>
            <line>Unreal mockery, hence!</line>
            <stagedir>GHOST OF BANQUO vanishes</stagedir>
            <line>Why, so: being gone,</line>
            <line>I am a man again. Pray you, sit still.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>You have displaced the mirth, broke the good meeting,</line>
            <line>With most admired disorder.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>Can such things be,</line>
            <line>And overcome us like a summer's cloud,</line>
            <line>Without our special wonder? You make me strange</line>
            <line>Even to the disposition that I owe,</line>
            <line>When now I think you can behold such sights,</line>
            <line>And keep the natural ruby of your cheeks,</line>
            <line>When mine is blanched with fear.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSS</speaker>
            <line>What sights, my lord?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>I pray you, speak not; he grows worse and worse;</line>
            <line>Question enrages him. At once, good night:</line>
            <line>Stand not upon the order of your going,</line>
            <line>But go at once.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LENNOX</speaker>
            <line>Good night; and better health</line>
            <line>Attend his majesty!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>A kind good night to all!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt all but MACBETH and LADY MACBETH</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>It will have blood; they say, blood will have blood:</line>
            <line>Stones have been known to move and trees to speak;</line>
            <line>Augurs and understood relations have</line>
            <line>By magot-pies and choughs and rooks brought forth</line>
            <line>The secret'st man of blood. What is the night?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>Almost at odds with morning, which is which.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>How say'st thou, that Macduff denies his person</line>
            <line>At our great bidding?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>Did you send to him, sir?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>I hear it by the way; but I will send:</line>
            <line>There's not a one of them but in his house</line>
            <line>I keep a servant fee'd. I will to-morrow,</line>
            <line>And betimes I will, to the weird sisters:</line>
            <line>More shall they speak; for now I am bent to know,</line>
            <line>By the worst means, the worst. For mine own good,</line>
            <line>All causes shall give way: I am in blood</line>
            <line>Stepp'd in so far that, should I wade no more,</line>
            <line>Returning were as tedious as go o'er:</line>
            <line>Strange things I have in head, that will to hand;</line>
            <line>Which must be acted ere they may be scann'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>You lack the season of all natures, sleep.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MACBETH</speaker>
            <line>Come, we'll to sleep. My strange and self-abuse</line>
            <line>Is the initiate fear that wants hard use:</line>
            <line>We are yet but young in deed.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-5">
      <title>SCENE V.  A Heath.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Thunder. Enter the three Witches meeting HECATE</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Witch</speaker>
            <line>Why, how now, Hecate! you look angerly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HECATE</speaker>
            <line>Have I not reason, beldams as you are,</line>
            <line>Saucy and overbold? How did you dare</line>
            <line>To trade and traffic with Macbeth</line>
            <line>In riddles and affairs of death;</line>
            <line>And I, the mistress of your charms,</line>
            <line>The close contriver of all harms,</line>
            <line>Was never call'd to bear my part,</line>
            <line>Or show the glory of our art?</line>
            <line>And, which is worse, all you have done</line>
            <line>Hath been but for a wayward son,</line>
            <line>Spiteful and wrathful, who, as others do,</line>
            <line>Loves for his own ends, not for you.</line>
            <line>But make amends now: get you gone,</line>
            <line>And at the pit of Acheron</line>
            <line>Meet me i' the morning: thither he</line>
            <line>Will come to know his destiny:</line>
            <line>Your vessels and your spells provide,</line>
            <line>Your charms and every thing beside.</line>
            <line>I am for the air; this night I'll spend</line>
            <line>Unto a dismal and a fatal end:</line>
            <line>Great business must be wrought ere noon:</line>
            <line>Upon the corner of the moon</line>
            <line>There hangs a vaporous drop profound;</line>
            <line>I'll catch it ere it come to ground:</line>
            <line>And that distill'd by magic sleights</line>
            <line>Shall raise such artificial sprites</line>
            <line>As by the strength of their illusion</line>
            <line>Shall draw him on to his confusion:</line>
            <line>He shall spurn fate, scorn death, and bear</line>
            <line>He hopes 'bove wisdom, grace and fear:</line>
            <line>And you all know, security</line>
            <line>Is mortals' chiefest enemy.</line>
            <stagedir>Music and a song within: 'Come away, come
away,' &amp;c</stagedir>
            <line>Hark! I am call'd; my little spirit, see,</line>
            <line>Sits in a foggy cloud, and stays for me.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Witch</speaker>
            <line>Come, let's make haste; she'll soon be back again.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-6">
      <title>SCENE VI.  Forres. The palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter LENNOX and another Lord</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LENNOX</speaker>
            <line>My former speeches have but hit your thoughts,</line>
            <line>Which can interpret further: only, I say,</line>
            <line>Things have been strangely borne. The</line>
            <line>gracious Duncan</line>
            <line>Was pitied of Macbeth: marry, he was dead:</line>
            <line>And the right-valiant Banquo walk'd too late;</line>
            <line>Whom, you may say, if't please you, Fleance kill'd,</line>
            <line>For Fleance fled: men must not walk too late.</line>
            <line>Who cannot want the thought how monstrous</line>
            <line>It was for Malcolm and for Donalbain</line>
            <line>To kill their gracious father? damned fact!</line>
            <line>How it did grieve Macbeth! did he not straight</line>
            <line>In pious rage the two delinquents tear,</line>
            <line>That were the slaves of drink and thralls of sleep?</line>
            <line>Was not that nobly done? Ay, and wisely too;</line>
            <line>For 'twould have anger'd any heart alive</line>
            <line>To hear the men deny't. So that, I say,</line>
            <line>He has borne all things well: and I do think</line>
            <line>That had he Duncan's sons under his key--</line>
            <line>As, an't please heaven, he shall not--they</line>
            <line>should find</line>
            <line>What 'twere to kill a father; so should Fleance.</line>
            <line>But, peace! for from broad words and 'cause he fail'd</line>
            <line>His presence at the tyrant's feast, I hear</line>
            <line>Macduff lives in disgrace: sir, can you tell</line>
            <line>Where he bestows himself?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord</speaker>
            <line>The son of Duncan,</line>
            <line>From whom this tyrant holds the due of birth</line>
            <line>Lives in the English court, and is received</line>
            <line>Of the most pious Edward with such grace</line>
            <line>That the malevolence of fortune nothing</line>
            <line>Takes from his high respect: thither Macduff</line>
            <line>Is gone to pray the holy king, upon his aid</line>
            <line>To wake Northumberland and warlike Siward:</line>
            <line>That, by the help of these--with Him above</line>
            <line>To ratify the work--we may again</line>
            <line>Give to our tables meat, sleep to our nights,</line>
            <line>Free from our feasts and banquets bloody knives,</line>
            <line>Do faithful homage and receive free honours:</line>
            <line>All which we pine for now: and this report</line>
            <line>Hath so exasperate the king that he</line>
            <line>Prepares for some attempt of war.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LENNOX</speaker>
            <line>Sent he to Macduff?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord</speaker>
            <line>He did: and with an absolute 'Sir, not I,'</line>
            <line>The cloudy messenger turns me his back,</line>
            <line>And hums, as who should say 'You'll rue the time</line>
            <line>That clogs me with this answer.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LENNOX</speaker>
            <line>And that well might</line>
            <line>Advise him to a caution, to hold what distance</line>
            <line>His wisdom can provide. Some holy angel</line>
            <line>Fly to the court of England and unfold</line>
            <line>His message ere he come, that a swift blessing</line>
            <line>May soon return to this our suffering country</line>
            <line>Under a hand accursed!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord</speaker>
            <line>I'll send my prayers with him.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>