<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net/doctypes/dita/topic" "topic.dtd">
<topic
  id="topic-id">
  <title>Sample Publications: Shakespear Plays</title>
  <body>
    <p>The Shakespear Plays sample demonstrates how to create publication-specific specializations
      for data that is more structured than just paragraphs and lists.</p>
    <p>The DITA source is based on Jon Bosak's XML Shakespear data set, which he had created as an
      exercise in markup design and with the goal of producing interesting XML content for
      transforming, searching, and so on.</p>
    <p>With Jon's approval, I have created a DITA specialization that emulates Jon's original markup
      design as closely as possible within the constraints and requirements of DITA. The materials
      are provided via a <xref
        href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/us/"
        format="html"
        scope="external">Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike</xref> license.</p>
    <p><xref
        href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/us/"
        format="html"
        scope="external"><image
          href="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-sa/3.0/us/88x31.png">
          <alt>Creative Commons License</alt>
        </image></xref></p>
    <p>In the original XML data set, each play is provided as a single-file XML document. While it
      would have been possible to create a topic specialization that allowed an analogous
      single-file representation of the whole play, it seemed to make more sense to represent the
      whole play as a map and organize the top-level components into separate topics.</p>
    <p>Thus, the specializations for the plays are:<dl>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>playmap</dt>
          <dd>Represents the play as whole. Holds the play-level metadata. Provides specialized
            topicrefs for grouping the play components and linking to them: <xmlelem>invoc</xmlelem>
            (invocation), <xmlelem>prologue</xmlelem>, <xmlelem>epilogue</xmlelem>, and <xmlelem
              >act</xmlelem>, with the initial assumption being that these top-level play components
            would be managed as single files (that is, the scenes within an act would not be broken
            out into separate files).</dd>
        </dlentry>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>play-component</dt>
          <dd>An "abstract" base topic type that establishes the common components needed by the
            concrete topic types (act, scene, etc.). Looking at Jon's markup design, it was clear
            that each of the different major play components shared many of the same structural
            components and structural rules. In that case, it is necessary, or at least, convenient
            to have a common base topic type from which concrete types are derived. Defines
            specialized elements for representing speeches as sets of lines and stage
            directions.</dd>
        </dlentry>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>act</dt>
          <dd>Topic type for holding an entire act. An act consists of one or more <xmlelem
              >scene</xmlelem> topics. May also include a <xmlelem>prologue</xmlelem> or <xmlelem
              >epilogue</xmlelem> topic.</dd>
        </dlentry>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>scene</dt>
          <dd>Topic type for holding an individual scene within an act. Scene topics have no nested
            topics by default (but, for example, it could make sense to allow nested commentary
            topics if it was useful to allow authoring of commentary within the scene source
            document, rather than linking it to the scene using normal DITA linking
            mechanisms).</dd>
        </dlentry>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>induct</dt>
          <dd>Topic type for the "induction" part of the play, if there is one (e.g., <cite>Henry
              IV, Part 2</cite>).</dd>
        </dlentry>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>personae</dt>
          <dd>Topic type for the "dramatis personae" for the play, that is, a list of characters.
            Defines specialized elements for identifying the characters and grouping sets of
            characters together.</dd>
        </dlentry>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>prologue</dt>
          <dd>Topic type for a prologue for the entire play or for an individual act.</dd>
        </dlentry>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>epilogue</dt>
          <dd>Topic type for an epilogue for the entire play or for an individual act.</dd>
        </dlentry>
      </dl></p>
    <p>The <xmlelem>scene</xmlelem> topic type can be literally nested within the other
      scene-containing topic types or managed as separate topic files.</p>
    <p>The Shakespear plays materials includes a Toolkit plugin that extends the XHTML transform to
      render the play-specific elements appropriately. Using this plugin, you can then generate both
      HTML and EPub renderings of the plays that look like plays.</p>
  </body>
</topic>
