<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net/doctypes/dita/topic" "topic.dtd">
<topic
  id="topic-1">
  <title>DITA for Publishers Specialization Modules Overview</title>
  <body>
    <p>The DITA for Publishers project provides map, topic, and domain specializations for
      constructs needed by typical publishing documents.</p>
    <p>The map specializations are:<dl>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>pubmap</dt>
          <dd>Publication map. Similar to the DITA 1.1 bookmap, but less constrained. Represents a
            single publication, nominally as presented in print (although may be adapted for other
            media formats as well). Includes publishing-specific metadata not available from
            bookmap, such as both 10- and 13-digit ISBNs and ISSNs. Includes the ability to
            represent arbitrary single pages, such as often occur in fiction books before the main
            content. Also includes facilities for including cover components.</dd>
        </dlentry>
      </dl></p>
    <p>The topic specializations are:<dl>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>article</dt>
          <dd>For articles within periodicals or article-based books. Allows nested subsection and
            sidebar topic types in the default shell configuration. Enables authoring of complete
            articles as single files.</dd>
        </dlentry>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>chapter</dt>
          <dd>For chapters within books. Allows nested subsection and sidebar topic types in the
            default shell configuration. Enables authoring of complete chapters as single
            files.</dd>
        </dlentry>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>part</dt>
          <dd>For parts within books. Provides the part title and, optionally, introductory body
            content. Can be configured to allow nested chapter or subsection topics but does not in
            the default shell configuration.</dd>
        </dlentry>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>subsection</dt>
          <dd>Generic subsection within articles and chapters. Enables creation of arbitrary
            hierarchies of titled divisions, e.g., within chapters and articles. Base for more
            specialized subsection types.</dd>
        </dlentry>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>sidebar</dt>
          <dd>Generic out-of-line topic. May contain nested subsections in the default shell
            configuration. Base for more specialized sidebar types.</dd>
        </dlentry>
      </dl></p>
    <p>The domain specializations are:<dl>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>formatting</dt>
          <dd>Provides elements that request or capture specific formatting effects, including line
            breaks, tabs, and mathematical equations represented using any combination of MathML,
            InDesign data, or graphics.</dd>
        </dlentry>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>XML</dt>
          <dd>Provides elements for identifying mentions of XML constructs.</dd>
        </dlentry>
      </dl></p>
  </body>
</topic>
