<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE subsection PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:subsection" "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:subsection">
<subsection
  id="subsection-id">
  <title>Publication Maps</title>
  <shortdesc>Publications are represented by maps that capture the publication metadata and the organizational structure of the publication content.</shortdesc>
  <prolog>
    <metadata>
      <keywords>
        <indexterm>publication<indexterm>maps for</indexterm></indexterm>
      </keywords>
    </metadata>
  </prolog>
  <body>
    <p>The DITA standard does not formally define the notion of a "publication". In DITA terms, a publication is simply a map that is used as the input to a process that is intended to create a complete unit of delivery, such as a complete EPUB or PDF or whatever.</p>
    <p>In DITA for Publishers, by "publication" is meant a primary unit of publishing business, that is a title or issue, something that probably has an ISBN or ISSN and is sold as a separate SKU. Publications are distinguished by having meta that describes the publication as a whole: publication identifiers (ISBNs, etc.), authorship, ownership, license statements (copyright or some other form of license), descriptive and classifying metadata, and so on.</p>
    <p>The D4P materials include two sample map document types that integrate the various D4P map domains and serve as an example of hwo to create your own use-case-specific publication maps. As for DITA generally, you should always create your own document type shells so that you are prepared for future customization and extension. For example, you can copy the D4P-provided "pubmap" map type, assign it a new public identifier in your copy, and you're ready to go.</p>
    <p>The two map document types are:<ul>
      <li>map<p>An otherwise generic <xmlelem>map</xmlelem> document with the pubmap, pubmeta, and D4P enumeration domains integrated. This integration allows you maximum flexibility but isn't really intended as an example of good production practice. It mostly shows how to simply integrate the various domains in the simplest possible way.</p></li>
      <li>pubmap<p>Integrates the pubmap domain and defines a more specific publication structure, but one that is still generic enough to represent most publications in a useful and satisfying way. Demonstrates how to use the pubmap domain to define a more title-specific publication structure. Also integrates the pubmeta and enumeration domains, making it consistent with the more generic map document type.</p></li>
      </ul></p>
    <p/>
  </body>
</subsection>
