<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net/doctypes/dita/shakespear/dtd/act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-3">
   <title>ACT III</title>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  Westminster. The palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter KING HENRY IV in his nightgown, with a Page</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>Go call the Earls of Surrey and of Warwick;</line>
            <line>But, ere they come, bid them o'er-read these letters,</line>
            <line>And well consider of them; make good speed.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit Page</stagedir>
            <line>How many thousand of my poorest subjects</line>
            <line>Are at this hour asleep! O sleep, O gentle sleep,</line>
            <line>Nature's soft nurse, how have I frighted thee,</line>
            <line>That thou no more wilt weigh my eyelids down</line>
            <line>And steep my senses in forgetfulness?</line>
            <line>Why rather, sleep, liest thou in smoky cribs,</line>
            <line>Upon uneasy pallets stretching thee</line>
            <line>And hush'd with buzzing night-flies to thy slumber,</line>
            <line>Than in the perfumed chambers of the great,</line>
            <line>Under the canopies of costly state,</line>
            <line>And lull'd with sound of sweetest melody?</line>
            <line>O thou dull god, why liest thou with the vile</line>
            <line>In loathsome beds, and leavest the kingly couch</line>
            <line>A watch-case or a common 'larum-bell?</line>
            <line>Wilt thou upon the high and giddy mast</line>
            <line>Seal up the ship-boy's eyes, and rock his brains</line>
            <line>In cradle of the rude imperious surge</line>
            <line>And in the visitation of the winds,</line>
            <line>Who take the ruffian billows by the top,</line>
            <line>Curling their monstrous heads and hanging them</line>
            <line>With deafening clamour in the slippery clouds,</line>
            <line>That, with the hurly, death itself awakes?</line>
            <line>Canst thou, O partial sleep, give thy repose</line>
            <line>To the wet sea-boy in an hour so rude,</line>
            <line>And in the calmest and most stillest night,</line>
            <line>With all appliances and means to boot,</line>
            <line>Deny it to a king? Then happy low, lie down!</line>
            <line>Uneasy lies the head that wears a crown.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter WARWICK and SURREY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Many good morrows to your majesty!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>Is it good morrow, lords?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>'Tis one o'clock, and past.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>Why, then, good morrow to you all, my lords.</line>
            <line>Have you read o'er the letters that I sent you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>We have, my liege.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>Then you perceive the body of our kingdom</line>
            <line>How foul it is; what rank diseases grow</line>
            <line>And with what danger, near the heart of it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>It is but as a body yet distemper'd;</line>
            <line>Which to his former strength may be restored</line>
            <line>With good advice and little medicine:</line>
            <line>My Lord Northumberland will soon be cool'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>O God! that one might read the book of fate,</line>
            <line>And see the revolution of the times</line>
            <line>Make mountains level, and the continent,</line>
            <line>Weary of solid firmness, melt itself</line>
            <line>Into the sea! and, other times, to see</line>
            <line>The beachy girdle of the ocean</line>
            <line>Too wide for Neptune's hips; how chances mock,</line>
            <line>And changes fill the cup of alteration</line>
            <line>With divers liquors! O, if this were seen,</line>
            <line>The happiest youth, viewing his progress through,</line>
            <line>What perils past, what crosses to ensue,</line>
            <line>Would shut the book, and sit him down and die.</line>
            <line>'Tis not 'ten years gone</line>
            <line>Since Richard and Northumberland, great friends,</line>
            <line>Did feast together, and in two years after</line>
            <line>Were they at wars: it is but eight years since</line>
            <line>This Percy was the man nearest my soul,</line>
            <line>Who like a brother toil'd in my affairs</line>
            <line>And laid his love and life under my foot,</line>
            <line>Yea, for my sake, even to the eyes of Richard</line>
            <line>Gave him defiance. But which of you was by--</line>
            <line>You, cousin Nevil, as I may remember--</line>
            <stagedir>To WARWICK</stagedir>
            <line>When Richard, with his eye brimful of tears,</line>
            <line>Then cheque'd and rated by Northumberland,</line>
            <line>Did speak these words, now proved a prophecy?</line>
            <line>'Northumberland, thou ladder by the which</line>
            <line>My cousin Bolingbroke ascends my throne;'</line>
            <line>Though then, God knows, I had no such intent,</line>
            <line>But that necessity so bow'd the state</line>
            <line>That I and greatness were compell'd to kiss:</line>
            <line>'The time shall come,' thus did he follow it,</line>
            <line>'The time will come, that foul sin, gathering head,</line>
            <line>Shall break into corruption:' so went on,</line>
            <line>Foretelling this same time's condition</line>
            <line>And the division of our amity.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>There is a history in all men's lives,</line>
            <line>Figuring the nature of the times deceased;</line>
            <line>The which observed, a man may prophesy,</line>
            <line>With a near aim, of the main chance of things</line>
            <line>As yet not come to life, which in their seeds</line>
            <line>And weak beginnings lie intreasured.</line>
            <line>Such things become the hatch and brood of time;</line>
            <line>And by the necessary form of this</line>
            <line>King Richard might create a perfect guess</line>
            <line>That great Northumberland, then false to him,</line>
            <line>Would of that seed grow to a greater falseness;</line>
            <line>Which should not find a ground to root upon,</line>
            <line>Unless on you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>Are these things then necessities?</line>
            <line>Then let us meet them like necessities:</line>
            <line>And that same word even now cries out on us:</line>
            <line>They say the bishop and Northumberland</line>
            <line>Are fifty thousand strong.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>It cannot be, my lord;</line>
            <line>Rumour doth double, like the voice and echo,</line>
            <line>The numbers of the fear'd. Please it your grace</line>
            <line>To go to bed. Upon my soul, my lord,</line>
            <line>The powers that you already have sent forth</line>
            <line>Shall bring this prize in very easily.</line>
            <line>To comfort you the more, I have received</line>
            <line>A certain instance that Glendower is dead.</line>
            <line>Your majesty hath been this fortnight ill,</line>
            <line>And these unseason'd hours perforce must add</line>
            <line>Unto your sickness.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>I will take your counsel:</line>
            <line>And were these inward wars once out of hand,</line>
            <line>We would, dear lords, unto the Holy Land.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  Gloucestershire. Before SHALLOW'S house.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter SHALLOW and SILENCE, meeting; MOULDY,
SHADOW, WART, FEEBLE, BULLCALF, a Servant or two
with them</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>Come on, come on, come on, sir; give me your hand,</line>
            <line>sir, give me your hand, sir: an early stirrer, by</line>
            <line>the rood! And how doth my good cousin Silence?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SILENCE</speaker>
            <line>Good morrow, good cousin Shallow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>And how doth my cousin, your bedfellow? and your</line>
            <line>fairest daughter and mine, my god-daughter Ellen?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SILENCE</speaker>
            <line>Alas, a black ousel, cousin Shallow!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>By yea and nay, sir, I dare say my cousin William is</line>
            <line>become a good scholar: he is at Oxford still, is he not?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SILENCE</speaker>
            <line>Indeed, sir, to my cost.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>A' must, then, to the inns o' court shortly. I was</line>
            <line>once of Clement's Inn, where I think they will</line>
            <line>talk of mad Shallow yet.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SILENCE</speaker>
            <line>You were called 'lusty Shallow' then, cousin.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>By the mass, I was called any thing; and I would</line>
            <line>have done any thing indeed too, and roundly too.</line>
            <line>There was I, and little John Doit of Staffordshire,</line>
            <line>and black George Barnes, and Francis Pickbone, and</line>
            <line>Will Squele, a Cotswold man; you had not four such</line>
            <line>swinge-bucklers in all the inns o' court again: and</line>
            <line>I may say to you, we knew where the bona-robas were</line>
            <line>and had the best of them all at commandment. Then</line>
            <line>was Jack Falstaff, now Sir John, a boy, and page to</line>
            <line>Thomas Mowbray, Duke of Norfolk.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SILENCE</speaker>
            <line>This Sir John, cousin, that comes hither anon about soldiers?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>The same Sir John, the very same. I  see him break</line>
            <line>Skogan's head at the court-gate, when a' was a</line>
            <line>crack not thus high: and the very same day did I</line>
            <line>fight with one Sampson Stockfish, a fruiterer,</line>
            <line>behind Gray's Inn. Jesu, Jesu, the mad days that I</line>
            <line>have spent! and to see how many of my old</line>
            <line>acquaintance are dead!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SILENCE</speaker>
            <line>We shall all follow, cousin.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHADOW</speaker>
            <line>Certain, 'tis certain; very sure, very sure: death,</line>
            <line>as the Psalmist saith, is certain to all; all shall</line>
            <line>die. How a good yoke of bullocks at Stamford fair?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SILENCE</speaker>
            <line>By my troth, I was not there.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>Death is certain. Is old Double of your town living</line>
            <line>yet?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SILENCE</speaker>
            <line>Dead, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>Jesu, Jesu, dead! a' drew a good bow; and dead! a'</line>
            <line>shot a fine shoot: John a Gaunt loved him well, and</line>
            <line>betted much money on his head. Dead! a' would have</line>
            <line>clapped i' the clout at twelve score; and carried</line>
            <line>you a forehand shaft a fourteen and fourteen and a</line>
            <line>half, that it would have done a man's heart good to</line>
            <line>see. How a score of ewes now?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SILENCE</speaker>
            <line>Thereafter as they be: a score of good ewes may be</line>
            <line>worth ten pounds.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>And is old Double dead?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SILENCE</speaker>
            <line>Here come two of Sir John Falstaff's men, as I think.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter BARDOLPH and one with him</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BARDOLPH</speaker>
            <line>Good morrow, honest gentlemen: I beseech you, which</line>
            <line>is Justice Shallow?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>I am Robert Shallow, sir; a poor esquire of this</line>
            <line>county, and one of the king's justices of the peace:</line>
            <line>What is your good pleasure with me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BARDOLPH</speaker>
            <line>My captain, sir, commends him to you; my captain,</line>
            <line>Sir John Falstaff, a tall gentleman, by heaven, and</line>
            <line>a most gallant leader.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>He greets me well, sir. I knew him a good backsword</line>
            <line>man. How doth the good knight? may I ask how my</line>
            <line>lady his wife doth?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BARDOLPH</speaker>
            <line>Sir, pardon; a soldier is better accommodated than</line>
            <line>with a wife.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>It is well said, in faith, sir; and it is well said</line>
            <line>indeed too. Better accommodated! it is good; yea,</line>
            <line>indeed, is it: good phrases are surely, and ever</line>
            <line>were, very commendable. Accommodated! it comes of</line>
            <line>'accommodo' very good; a good phrase.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BARDOLPH</speaker>
            <line>Pardon me, sir; I have heard the word. Phrase call</line>
            <line>you it? by this good day, I know not the phrase;</line>
            <line>but I will maintain the word with my sword to be a</line>
            <line>soldier-like word, and a word of exceeding good</line>
            <line>command, by heaven. Accommodated; that is, when a</line>
            <line>man is, as they say, accommodated; or when a man is,</line>
            <line>being, whereby a' may be thought to be accommodated;</line>
            <line>which is an excellent thing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>It is very just.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter FALSTAFF</stagedir>
            <line>Look, here comes good Sir John. Give me your good</line>
            <line>hand, give me your worship's good hand: by my</line>
            <line>troth, you like well and bear your years very well:</line>
            <line>welcome, good Sir John.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>I am glad to see you well, good Master Robert</line>
            <line>Shallow: Master Surecard, as I think?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>No, Sir John; it is my cousin Silence, in commission with me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Good Master Silence, it well befits you should be of</line>
            <line>the peace.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SILENCE</speaker>
            <line>Your good-worship is welcome.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Fie! this is hot weather, gentlemen. Have you</line>
            <line>provided me here half a dozen sufficient men?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>Marry, have we, sir. Will you sit?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Let me see them, I beseech you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>Where's the roll? where's the roll? where's the</line>
            <line>roll? Let me see, let me see, let me see. So, so:</line>
            <line>yea, marry, sir: Ralph Mouldy! Let them appear as</line>
            <line>I call; let them do so, let them do so. Let me</line>
            <line>see; where is Mouldy?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOULDY</speaker>
            <line>Here, an't please you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>What think you, Sir John? a good-limbed fellow;</line>
            <line>young, strong, and of good friends.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Is thy name Mouldy?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOULDY</speaker>
            <line>Yea, an't please you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>'Tis the more time thou wert used.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>Ha, ha, ha! most excellent, i' faith! Things that</line>
            <line>are mouldy lack use: very singular good! in faith,</line>
            <line>well said, Sir John, very well said.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Prick him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOULDY</speaker>
            <line>I was pricked well enough before, an you could have</line>
            <line>let me alone: my old dame will be undone now for</line>
            <line>one to do her husbandry and her drudgery: you need</line>
            <line>not to have pricked me; there are other men fitter</line>
            <line>to go out than I.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Go to: peace, Mouldy; you shall go. Mouldy, it is</line>
            <line>time you were spent.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOULDY</speaker>
            <line>Spent!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>Peace, fellow, peace; stand aside: know you where</line>
            <line>you are? For the other, Sir John: let me see:</line>
            <line>Simon Shadow!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Yea, marry, let me have him to sit under: he's like</line>
            <line>to be a cold soldier.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>Where's Shadow?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHADOW</speaker>
            <line>Here, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Shadow, whose son art thou?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHADOW</speaker>
            <line>My mother's son, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Thy mother's son! like enough, and thy father's</line>
            <line>shadow: so the son of the female is the shadow of</line>
            <line>the male: it is often so, indeed; but much of the</line>
            <line>father's substance!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>Do you like him, Sir John?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Shadow will serve for summer; prick him, for we have</line>
            <line>a number of shadows to fill up the muster-book.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>Thomas Wart!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Where's he?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WART</speaker>
            <line>Here, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Is thy name Wart?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WART</speaker>
            <line>Yea, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Thou art a very ragged wart.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>Shall I prick him down, Sir John?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>It were superfluous; for his apparel is built upon</line>
            <line>his back and the whole frame stands upon pins:</line>
            <line>prick him no more.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>Ha, ha, ha! you can do it, sir; you can do it: I</line>
            <line>commend you well. Francis Feeble!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FEEBLE</speaker>
            <line>Here, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>What trade art thou, Feeble?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FEEBLE</speaker>
            <line>A woman's tailor, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>Shall I prick him, sir?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>You may: but if he had been a man's tailor, he'ld</line>
            <line>ha' pricked you. Wilt thou make as many holes in</line>
            <line>an enemy's battle as thou hast done in a woman's petticoat?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FEEBLE</speaker>
            <line>I will do my good will, sir; you can have no more.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Well said, good woman's tailor! well said,</line>
            <line>courageous Feeble! thou wilt be as valiant as the</line>
            <line>wrathful dove or most magnanimous mouse. Prick the</line>
            <line>woman's tailor: well, Master Shallow; deep, Master Shallow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FEEBLE</speaker>
            <line>I would Wart might have gone, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>I would thou wert a man's tailor, that thou mightst</line>
            <line>mend him and make him fit to go. I cannot put him</line>
            <line>to a private soldier that is the leader of so many</line>
            <line>thousands: let that suffice, most forcible Feeble.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FEEBLE</speaker>
            <line>It shall suffice, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>I am bound to thee, reverend Feeble. Who is next?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>Peter Bullcalf o' the green!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Yea, marry, let's see Bullcalf.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BULLCALF</speaker>
            <line>Here, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>'Fore God, a likely fellow! Come, prick me Bullcalf</line>
            <line>till he roar again.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BULLCALF</speaker>
            <line>O Lord! good my lord captain,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>What, dost thou roar before thou art pricked?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BULLCALF</speaker>
            <line>O Lord, sir! I am a diseased man.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>What disease hast thou?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BULLCALF</speaker>
            <line>A whoreson cold, sir, a cough, sir, which I caught</line>
            <line>with ringing in the king's affairs upon his</line>
            <line>coronation-day, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Come, thou shalt go to the wars in a gown; we wilt</line>
            <line>have away thy cold; and I will take such order that</line>
            <line>my friends shall ring for thee. Is here all?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>Here is two more called than your number, you must</line>
            <line>have but four here, sir: and so, I pray you, go in</line>
            <line>with me to dinner.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Come, I will go drink with you, but I cannot tarry</line>
            <line>dinner. I am glad to see you, by my troth, Master Shallow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>O, Sir John, do you remember since we lay all night</line>
            <line>in the windmill in Saint George's field?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>No more of that, good Master Shallow, no more of that.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>Ha! 'twas a merry night. And is Jane Nightwork alive?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>She lives, Master Shallow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>She never could away with me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Never, never; she would always say she could not</line>
            <line>abide Master Shallow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>By the mass, I could anger her to the heart. She</line>
            <line>was then a bona-roba. Doth she hold her own well?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Old, old, Master Shallow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>Nay, she must be old; she cannot choose but be old;</line>
            <line>certain she's old; and had Robin Nightwork by old</line>
            <line>Nightwork before I came to Clement's Inn.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SILENCE</speaker>
            <line>That's fifty-five year ago.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>Ha, cousin Silence, that thou hadst seen that that</line>
            <line>this knight and I have seen! Ha, Sir John, said I well?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>We have heard the chimes at midnight, Master Shallow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>That we have, that we have, that we have; in faith,</line>
            <line>Sir John, we have: our watch-word was 'Hem boys!'</line>
            <line>Come, let's to dinner; come, let's to dinner:</line>
            <line>Jesus, the days that we have seen! Come, come.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt FALSTAFF and Justices</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BULLCALF</speaker>
            <line>Good Master Corporate Bardolph, stand my friend;</line>
            <line>and here's four Harry ten shillings in French crowns</line>
            <line>for you. In very truth, sir, I had as lief be</line>
            <line>hanged, sir, as go: and yet, for mine own part, sir,</line>
            <line>I do not care; but rather, because I am unwilling,</line>
            <line>and, for mine own part, have a desire to stay with</line>
            <line>my friends; else, sir, I did not care, for mine own</line>
            <line>part, so much.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BARDOLPH</speaker>
            <line>Go to; stand aside.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOULDY</speaker>
            <line>And, good master corporal captain, for my old</line>
            <line>dame's sake, stand my friend: she has nobody to do</line>
            <line>any thing about her when I am gone; and she is old,</line>
            <line>and cannot help herself: You shall have forty, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BARDOLPH</speaker>
            <line>Go to; stand aside.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FEEBLE</speaker>
            <line>By my troth, I care not; a man can die but once: we</line>
            <line>owe God a death: I'll ne'er bear a base mind:</line>
            <line>an't be my destiny, so; an't be not, so: no man is</line>
            <line>too good to serve's prince; and let it go which way</line>
            <line>it will, he that dies this year is quit for the next.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BARDOLPH</speaker>
            <line>Well said; thou'rt a good fellow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FEEBLE</speaker>
            <line>Faith, I'll bear no base mind.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter FALSTAFF and the Justices</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Come, sir, which men shall I have?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>Four of which you please.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BARDOLPH</speaker>
            <line>Sir, a word with you: I have three pound to free</line>
            <line>Mouldy and Bullcalf.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Go to; well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>Come, Sir John, which four will you have?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Do you choose for me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>Marry, then, Mouldy, Bullcalf, Feeble and Shadow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Mouldy and Bullcalf: for you, Mouldy, stay at home</line>
            <line>till you are past service: and for your part,</line>
            <line>Bullcalf, grow till you come unto it: I will none of you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>Sir John, Sir John, do not yourself wrong: they are</line>
            <line>your likeliest men, and I would have you served with the best.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Will you tell me, Master Shallow, how to choose a</line>
            <line>man? Care I for the limb, the thewes, the stature,</line>
            <line>bulk, and big assemblance of a man! Give me the</line>
            <line>spirit, Master Shallow. Here's Wart; you see what a</line>
            <line>ragged appearance it is; a' shall charge you and</line>
            <line>discharge you with the motion of a pewterer's</line>
            <line>hammer, come off and on swifter than he that gibbets</line>
            <line>on the brewer's bucket. And this same half-faced</line>
            <line>fellow, Shadow; give me this man: he presents no</line>
            <line>mark to the enemy; the foeman may with as great aim</line>
            <line>level at the edge of a penknife. And for a retreat;</line>
            <line>how swiftly will this Feeble the woman's tailor run</line>
            <line>off! O, give me the spare men, and spare me the</line>
            <line>great ones. Put me a caliver into Wart's hand, Bardolph.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BARDOLPH</speaker>
            <line>Hold, Wart, traverse; thus, thus, thus.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Come, manage me your caliver. So: very well: go</line>
            <line>to: very good, exceeding good. O, give me always a</line>
            <line>little, lean, old, chapt, bald shot. Well said, i'</line>
            <line>faith, Wart; thou'rt a good scab: hold, there's a</line>
            <line>tester for thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>He is not his craft's master; he doth not do it</line>
            <line>right. I remember at Mile-end Green, when I lay at</line>
            <line>Clement's Inn--I was then Sir Dagonet in Arthur's</line>
            <line>show,--there was a little quiver fellow, and a'</line>
            <line>would manage you his piece thus; and a' would about</line>
            <line>and about, and come you in and come you in: 'rah,</line>
            <line>tah, tah,' would a' say; 'bounce' would a' say; and</line>
            <line>away again would a' go, and again would a' come: I</line>
            <line>shall ne'er see such a fellow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>These fellows will do well, Master Shallow. God</line>
            <line>keep you, Master Silence: I will not use many words</line>
            <line>with you. Fare you well, gentlemen both: I thank</line>
            <line>you: I must a dozen mile to-night. Bardolph, give</line>
            <line>the soldiers coats.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>Sir John, the Lord bless you! God prosper your</line>
            <line>affairs! God send us peace! At your return visit</line>
            <line>our house; let our old acquaintance be renewed;</line>
            <line>peradventure I will with ye to the court.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>'Fore God, I would you would, Master Shallow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>Go to; I have spoke at a word. God keep you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Fare you well, gentle gentlemen.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt Justices</stagedir>
            <line>On, Bardolph; lead the men away.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt BARDOLPH, Recruits, &amp;c</stagedir>
            <line>As I return, I will fetch off these justices: I do</line>
            <line>see the bottom of Justice Shallow. Lord, Lord, how</line>
            <line>subject we old men are to this vice of lying! This</line>
            <line>same starved justice hath done nothing but prate to</line>
            <line>me of the wildness of his youth, and the feats he</line>
            <line>hath done about Turnbull Street: and every third</line>
            <line>word a lie, duer paid to the hearer than the Turk's</line>
            <line>tribute. I do remember him at Clement's Inn like a</line>
            <line>man made after supper of a cheese-paring: when a'</line>
            <line>was naked, he was, for all the world, like a forked</line>
            <line>radish, with a head fantastically carved upon it</line>
            <line>with a knife: a' was so forlorn, that his</line>
            <line>dimensions to any thick sight were invincible: a'</line>
            <line>was the very genius of famine; yet lecherous as a</line>
            <line>monkey, and the whores called him mandrake: a' came</line>
            <line>ever in the rearward of the fashion, and sung those</line>
            <line>tunes to the overscutched huswives that he heard the</line>
            <line>carmen whistle, and swear they were his fancies or</line>
            <line>his good-nights. And now is this Vice's dagger</line>
            <line>become a squire, and talks as familiarly of John a</line>
            <line>Gaunt as if he had been sworn brother to him; and</line>
            <line>I'll be sworn a' ne'er saw him but once in the</line>
            <line>Tilt-yard; and then he burst his head for crowding</line>
            <line>among the marshal's men. I saw it, and told John a</line>
            <line>Gaunt he beat his own name; for you might have</line>
            <line>thrust him and all his apparel into an eel-skin; the</line>
            <line>case of a treble hautboy was a mansion for him, a</line>
            <line>court: and now has he land and beefs. Well, I'll</line>
            <line>be acquainted with him, if I return; and it shall</line>
            <line>go hard but I will make him a philosopher's two</line>
            <line>stones to me: if the young dace be a bait for the</line>
            <line>old pike, I see no reason in the law of nature but I</line>
            <line>may snap at him. Let time shape, and there an end.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>