<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:shakespear:dtd:act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-5">
   <title>ACT V</title>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  Gloucestershire. SHALLOW'S house.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter SHALLOW, FALSTAFF, BARDOLPH, and Page</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>By cock and pie, sir, you shall not away to-night.</line>
            <line>What, Davy, I say!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>You must excuse me, Master Robert Shallow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>I will not excuse you; you shall not be excused;</line>
            <line>excuses shall not be admitted; there is no excuse</line>
            <line>shall serve; you shall not be excused. Why, Davy!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter DAVY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DAVY</speaker>
            <line>Here, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>Davy, Davy, Davy, Davy, let me see, Davy; let me</line>
            <line>see, Davy; let me see: yea, marry, William cook,</line>
            <line>bid him come hither. Sir John, you shall not be excused.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DAVY</speaker>
            <line>Marry, sir, thus; those precepts cannot be served:</line>
            <line>and, again, sir, shall we sow the headland with wheat?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>With red wheat, Davy. But for William cook: are</line>
            <line>there no young pigeons?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DAVY</speaker>
            <line>Yes, sir. Here is now the smith's note for shoeing</line>
            <line>and plough-irons.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>Let it be cast and paid. Sir John, you shall not be excused.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DAVY</speaker>
            <line>Now, sir, a new link to the bucket must need be</line>
            <line>had: and, sir, do you mean to stop any of William's</line>
            <line>wages, about the sack he lost the other day at</line>
            <line>Hinckley fair?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>A' shall answer it. Some pigeons, Davy, a couple</line>
            <line>of short-legged hens, a joint of mutton, and any</line>
            <line>pretty little tiny kickshaws, tell William cook.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DAVY</speaker>
            <line>Doth the man of war stay all night, sir?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>Yea, Davy. I will use him well: a friend i' the</line>
            <line>court is better than a penny in purse. Use his men</line>
            <line>well, Davy; for they are arrant knaves, and will backbite.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DAVY</speaker>
            <line>No worse than they are backbitten, sir; for they</line>
            <line>have marvellous foul linen.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>Well conceited, Davy: about thy business, Davy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DAVY</speaker>
            <line>I beseech you, sir, to countenance William Visor of</line>
            <line>Woncot against Clement Perkes of the hill.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>There is many complaints, Davy, against that Visor:</line>
            <line>that Visor is an arrant knave, on my knowledge.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DAVY</speaker>
            <line>I grant your worship that he is a knave, sir; but</line>
            <line>yet, God forbid, sir, but a knave should have some</line>
            <line>countenance at his friend's request. An honest</line>
            <line>man, sir, is able to speak for himself, when a knave</line>
            <line>is not. I have served your worship truly, sir,</line>
            <line>this eight years; and if I cannot once or twice in</line>
            <line>a quarter bear out a knave against an honest man, I</line>
            <line>have but a very little credit with your worship. The</line>
            <line>knave is mine honest friend, sir; therefore, I</line>
            <line>beseech your worship, let him be countenanced.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>Go to; I say he shall have no wrong. Look about, Davy.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit DAVY</stagedir>
            <line>Where are you, Sir John? Come, come, come, off</line>
            <line>with your boots. Give me your hand, Master Bardolph.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BARDOLPH</speaker>
            <line>I am glad to see your worship.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>I thank thee with all my heart, kind</line>
            <line>Master Bardolph: and welcome, my tall fellow.</line>
            <stagedir>To the Page</stagedir>
            <line>Come, Sir John.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>I'll follow you, good Master Robert Shallow.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit SHALLOW</stagedir>
            <line>Bardolph, look to our horses.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt BARDOLPH and Page</stagedir>
            <line>If I were sawed into quantities, I should make four</line>
            <line>dozen of such bearded hermits' staves as Master</line>
            <line>Shallow. It is a wonderful thing to see the</line>
            <line>semblable coherence of his men's spirits and his:</line>
            <line>they, by observing of him, do bear themselves like</line>
            <line>foolish justices; he, by conversing with them, is</line>
            <line>turned into a justice-like serving-man: their</line>
            <line>spirits are so married in conjunction with the</line>
            <line>participation of society that they flock together in</line>
            <line>consent, like so many wild-geese. If I had a suit</line>
            <line>to Master Shallow, I would humour his men with the</line>
            <line>imputation of being near their master: if to his</line>
            <line>men, I would curry with Master Shallow that no man</line>
            <line>could better command his servants. It is certain</line>
            <line>that either wise bearing or ignorant carriage is</line>
            <line>caught, as men take diseases, one of another:</line>
            <line>therefore let men take heed of their company. I</line>
            <line>will devise matter enough out of this Shallow to</line>
            <line>keep Prince Harry in continual laughter the wearing</line>
            <line>out of six fashions, which is four terms, or two</line>
            <line>actions, and a' shall laugh without intervallums. O,</line>
            <line>it is much that a lie with a slight oath and a jest</line>
            <line>with a sad brow will do with a fellow that never</line>
            <line>had the ache in his shoulders! O, you shall see him</line>
            <line>laugh till his face be like a wet cloak ill laid up!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Within</stagedir>  Sir John!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>I come, Master Shallow; I come, Master Shallow.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  Westminster. The palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter WARWICK and the Lord Chief-Justice, meeting</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>How now, my lord chief-justice! whither away?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord Chief-Justice</speaker>
            <line>How doth the king?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Exceeding well; his cares are now all ended.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord Chief-Justice</speaker>
            <line>I hope, not dead.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>He's walk'd the way of nature;</line>
            <line>And to our purposes he lives no more.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord Chief-Justice</speaker>
            <line>I would his majesty had call'd me with him:</line>
            <line>The service that I truly did his life</line>
            <line>Hath left me open to all injuries.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Indeed I think the young king loves you not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord Chief-Justice</speaker>
            <line>I know he doth not, and do arm myself</line>
            <line>To welcome the condition of the time,</line>
            <line>Which cannot look more hideously upon me</line>
            <line>Than I have drawn it in my fantasy.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter LANCASTER, CLARENCE, GLOUCESTER,
WESTMORELAND, and others</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Here come the heavy issue of dead Harry:</line>
            <line>O that the living Harry had the temper</line>
            <line>Of him, the worst of these three gentlemen!</line>
            <line>How many nobles then should hold their places</line>
            <line>That must strike sail to spirits of vile sort!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord Chief-Justice</speaker>
            <line>O God, I fear all will be overturn'd!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LANCASTER</speaker>
            <line>Good morrow, cousin Warwick, good morrow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>Good morrow, cousin.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LANCASTER</speaker>
            <line>We meet like men that had forgot to speak.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>We do remember; but our argument</line>
            <line>Is all too heavy to admit much talk.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LANCASTER</speaker>
            <line>Well, peace be with him that hath made us heavy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord Chief-Justice</speaker>
            <line>Peace be with us, lest we be heavier!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>O, good my lord, you have lost a friend indeed;</line>
            <line>And I dare swear you borrow not that face</line>
            <line>Of seeming sorrow, it is sure your own.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LANCASTER</speaker>
            <line>Though no man be assured what grace to find,</line>
            <line>You stand in coldest expectation:</line>
            <line>I am the sorrier; would 'twere otherwise.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>Well, you must now speak Sir John Falstaff fair;</line>
            <line>Which swims against your stream of quality.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord Chief-Justice</speaker>
            <line>Sweet princes, what I did, I did in honour,</line>
            <line>Led by the impartial conduct of my soul:</line>
            <line>And never shall you see that I will beg</line>
            <line>A ragged and forestall'd remission.</line>
            <line>If truth and upright innocency fail me,</line>
            <line>I'll to the king my master that is dead,</line>
            <line>And tell him who hath sent me after him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Here comes the prince.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter KING HENRY V, attended</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord Chief-Justice</speaker>
            <line>Good morrow; and God save your majesty!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>This new and gorgeous garment, majesty,</line>
            <line>Sits not so easy on me as you think.</line>
            <line>Brothers, you mix your sadness with some fear:</line>
            <line>This is the English, not the Turkish court;</line>
            <line>Not Amurath an Amurath succeeds,</line>
            <line>But Harry Harry. Yet be sad, good brothers,</line>
            <line>For, by my faith, it very well becomes you:</line>
            <line>Sorrow so royally in you appears</line>
            <line>That I will deeply put the fashion on</line>
            <line>And wear it in my heart: why then, be sad;</line>
            <line>But entertain no more of it, good brothers,</line>
            <line>Than a joint burden laid upon us all.</line>
            <line>For me, by heaven, I bid you be assured,</line>
            <line>I'll be your father and your brother too;</line>
            <line>Let me but bear your love, I 'll bear your cares:</line>
            <line>Yet weep that Harry's dead; and so will I;</line>
            <line>But Harry lives, that shall convert those tears</line>
            <line>By number into hours of happiness.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Princes</speaker>
            <line>We hope no other from your majesty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>You all look strangely on me: and you most;</line>
            <line>You are, I think, assured I love you not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord Chief-Justice</speaker>
            <line>I am assured, if I be measured rightly,</line>
            <line>Your majesty hath no just cause to hate me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>No!</line>
            <line>How might a prince of my great hopes forget</line>
            <line>So great indignities you laid upon me?</line>
            <line>What! rate, rebuke, and roughly send to prison</line>
            <line>The immediate heir of England! Was this easy?</line>
            <line>May this be wash'd in Lethe, and forgotten?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord Chief-Justice</speaker>
            <line>I then did use the person of your father;</line>
            <line>The image of his power lay then in me:</line>
            <line>And, in the administration of his law,</line>
            <line>Whiles I was busy for the commonwealth,</line>
            <line>Your highness pleased to forget my place,</line>
            <line>The majesty and power of law and justice,</line>
            <line>The image of the king whom I presented,</line>
            <line>And struck me in my very seat of judgment;</line>
            <line>Whereon, as an offender to your father,</line>
            <line>I gave bold way to my authority</line>
            <line>And did commit you. If the deed were ill,</line>
            <line>Be you contented, wearing now the garland,</line>
            <line>To have a son set your decrees at nought,</line>
            <line>To pluck down justice from your awful bench,</line>
            <line>To trip the course of law and blunt the sword</line>
            <line>That guards the peace and safety of your person;</line>
            <line>Nay, more, to spurn at your most royal image</line>
            <line>And mock your workings in a second body.</line>
            <line>Question your royal thoughts, make the case yours;</line>
            <line>Be now the father and propose a son,</line>
            <line>Hear your own dignity so much profaned,</line>
            <line>See your most dreadful laws so loosely slighted,</line>
            <line>Behold yourself so by a son disdain'd;</line>
            <line>And then imagine me taking your part</line>
            <line>And in your power soft silencing your son:</line>
            <line>After this cold considerance, sentence me;</line>
            <line>And, as you are a king, speak in your state</line>
            <line>What I have done that misbecame my place,</line>
            <line>My person, or my liege's sovereignty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY V</speaker>
            <line>You are right, justice, and you weigh this well;</line>
            <line>Therefore still bear the balance and the sword:</line>
            <line>And I do wish your honours may increase,</line>
            <line>Till you do live to see a son of mine</line>
            <line>Offend you and obey you, as I did.</line>
            <line>So shall I live to speak my father's words:</line>
            <line>'Happy am I, that have a man so bold,</line>
            <line>That dares do justice on my proper son;</line>
            <line>And not less happy, having such a son,</line>
            <line>That would deliver up his greatness so</line>
            <line>Into the hands of justice.' You did commit me:</line>
            <line>For which, I do commit into your hand</line>
            <line>The unstained sword that you have used to bear;</line>
            <line>With this remembrance, that you use the same</line>
            <line>With the like bold, just and impartial spirit</line>
            <line>As you have done 'gainst me. There is my hand.</line>
            <line>You shall be as a father to my youth:</line>
            <line>My voice shall sound as you do prompt mine ear,</line>
            <line>And I will stoop and humble my intents</line>
            <line>To your well-practised wise directions.</line>
            <line>And, princes all, believe me, I beseech you;</line>
            <line>My father is gone wild into his grave,</line>
            <line>For in his tomb lie my affections;</line>
            <line>And with his spirit sadly I survive,</line>
            <line>To mock the expectation of the world,</line>
            <line>To frustrate prophecies and to raze out</line>
            <line>Rotten opinion, who hath writ me down</line>
            <line>After my seeming. The tide of blood in me</line>
            <line>Hath proudly flow'd in vanity till now:</line>
            <line>Now doth it turn and ebb back to the sea,</line>
            <line>Where it shall mingle with the state of floods</line>
            <line>And flow henceforth in formal majesty.</line>
            <line>Now call we our high court of parliament:</line>
            <line>And let us choose such limbs of noble counsel,</line>
            <line>That the great body of our state may go</line>
            <line>In equal rank with the best govern'd nation;</line>
            <line>That war, or peace, or both at once, may be</line>
            <line>As things acquainted and familiar to us;</line>
            <line>In which you, father, shall have foremost hand.</line>
            <line>Our coronation done, we will accite,</line>
            <line>As I before remember'd, all our state:</line>
            <line>And, God consigning to my good intents,</line>
            <line>No prince nor peer shall have just cause to say,</line>
            <line>God shorten Harry's happy life one day!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  Gloucestershire. SHALLOW'S orchard.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter FALSTAFF, SHALLOW, SILENCE, DAVY, BARDOLPH,
and the Page</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>Nay, you shall see my orchard, where, in an arbour,</line>
            <line>we will eat a last year's pippin of my own graffing,</line>
            <line>with a dish of caraways, and so forth: come,</line>
            <line>cousin Silence: and then to bed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>'Fore God, you have here a goodly dwelling and a rich.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>Barren, barren, barren; beggars all, beggars all,</line>
            <line>Sir John: marry, good air. Spread, Davy; spread,</line>
            <line>Davy; well said, Davy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>This Davy serves you for good uses; he is your</line>
            <line>serving-man and your husband.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>A good varlet, a good varlet, a very good varlet,</line>
            <line>Sir John: by the mass, I have drunk too much sack</line>
            <line>at supper: a good varlet. Now sit down, now sit</line>
            <line>down: come, cousin.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SILENCE</speaker>
            <line>Ah, sirrah! quoth-a, we shall</line>
            <line>Do nothing but eat, and make good cheer,</line>
            <stagedir>Singing</stagedir>
            <line>And praise God for the merry year;</line>
            <line>When flesh is cheap and females dear,</line>
            <line>And lusty lads roam here and there</line>
            <line>So merrily,</line>
            <line>And ever among so merrily.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>There's a merry heart! Good Master Silence, I'll</line>
            <line>give you a health for that anon.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>Give Master Bardolph some wine, Davy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DAVY</speaker>
            <line>Sweet sir, sit; I'll be with you anon. most sweet</line>
            <line>sir, sit. Master page, good master page, sit.</line>
            <line>Proface! What you want in meat, we'll have in drink:</line>
            <line>but you must bear; the heart's all.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>Be merry, Master Bardolph; and, my little soldier</line>
            <line>there, be merry.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SILENCE</speaker>
            <line>Be merry, be merry, my wife has all;</line>
            <stagedir>Singing</stagedir>
            <line>For women are shrews, both short and tall:</line>
            <line>'Tis merry in hall when beards wag all,</line>
            <line>And welcome merry Shrove-tide.</line>
            <line>Be merry, be merry.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>I did not think Master Silence had been a man of</line>
            <line>this mettle.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SILENCE</speaker>
            <line>Who, I? I have been merry twice and once ere now.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter DAVY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DAVY</speaker>
            <line>There's a dish of leather-coats for you.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>To BARDOLPH</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>Davy!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DAVY</speaker>
            <line>Your worship! I'll be with you straight.</line>
            <stagedir>To BARDOLPH</stagedir>
            <line>A cup of wine, sir?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SILENCE</speaker>
            <line>A cup of wine that's brisk and fine,</line>
            <stagedir>Singing</stagedir>
            <line>And drink unto the leman mine;</line>
            <line>And a merry heart lives long-a.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Well said, Master Silence.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SILENCE</speaker>
            <line>An we shall be merry, now comes in the sweet o' the night.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Health and long life to you, Master Silence.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SILENCE</speaker>
            <line>Fill the cup, and let it come;</line>
            <stagedir>Singing</stagedir>
            <line>I'll pledge you a mile to the bottom.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>Honest Bardolph, welcome: if thou wantest any</line>
            <line>thing, and wilt not call, beshrew thy heart.</line>
            <line>Welcome, my little tiny thief.</line>
            <stagedir>To the Page</stagedir>
            <line>And welcome indeed too. I'll drink to Master</line>
            <line>Bardolph, and to all the cavaleros about London.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DAVY</speaker>
            <line>I hove to see London once ere I die.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BARDOLPH</speaker>
            <line>An I might see you there, Davy,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>By the mass, you'll crack a quart together, ha!</line>
            <line>Will you not, Master Bardolph?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BARDOLPH</speaker>
            <line>Yea, sir, in a pottle-pot.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>By God's liggens, I thank thee: the knave will</line>
            <line>stick by thee, I can assure thee that. A' will not</line>
            <line>out; he is true bred.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BARDOLPH</speaker>
            <line>And I'll stick by him, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>Why, there spoke a king. Lack nothing: be merry.</line>
            <stagedir>Knocking within</stagedir>
            <line>Look who's at door there, ho! who knocks?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit DAVY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Why, now you have done me right.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>To SILENCE, seeing him take off a bumper</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SILENCE</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Singing</stagedir>
            </line>
            <line>Do me right,</line>
            <line>And dub me knight: Samingo.</line>
            <line>Is't not so?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>'Tis so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SILENCE</speaker>
            <line>Is't so? Why then, say an old man can do somewhat.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter DAVY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DAVY</speaker>
            <line>An't please your worship, there's one Pistol come</line>
            <line>from the court with news.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>From the court! let him come in.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter PISTOL</stagedir>
            <line>How now, Pistol!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>Sir John, God save you!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>What wind blew you hither, Pistol?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>Not the ill wind which blows no man to good. Sweet</line>
            <line>knight, thou art now one of the greatest men in this realm.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SILENCE</speaker>
            <line>By'r lady, I think a' be, but goodman Puff of Barson.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>Puff!</line>
            <line>Puff in thy teeth, most recreant coward base!</line>
            <line>Sir John, I am thy Pistol and thy friend,</line>
            <line>And helter-skelter have I rode to thee,</line>
            <line>And tidings do I bring and lucky joys</line>
            <line>And golden times and happy news of price.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>I pray thee now, deliver them like a man of this world.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>A foutre for the world and worldlings base!</line>
            <line>I speak of Africa and golden joys.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>O base Assyrian knight, what is thy news?</line>
            <line>Let King Cophetua know the truth thereof.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SILENCE</speaker>
            <line>And Robin Hood, Scarlet, and John.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Singing</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>Shall dunghill curs confront the Helicons?</line>
            <line>And shall good news be baffled?</line>
            <line>Then, Pistol, lay thy head in Furies' lap.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SILENCE</speaker>
            <line>Honest gentleman, I know not your breeding.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>Why then, lament therefore.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>Give me pardon, sir: if, sir, you come with news</line>
            <line>from the court, I take it there's but two ways,</line>
            <line>either to utter them, or to conceal them. I am,</line>
            <line>sir, under the king, in some authority.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>Under which king, Besonian? speak, or die.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>Under King Harry.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>Harry the Fourth? or Fifth?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>Harry the Fourth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>A foutre for thine office!</line>
            <line>Sir John, thy tender lambkin now is king;</line>
            <line>Harry the Fifth's the man. I speak the truth:</line>
            <line>When Pistol lies, do this; and fig me, like</line>
            <line>The bragging Spaniard.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>What, is the old king dead?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>As nail in door: the things I speak are just.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Away, Bardolph! saddle my horse. Master Robert</line>
            <line>Shallow, choose what office thou wilt in the land,</line>
            <line>'tis thine. Pistol, I will double-charge thee with dignities.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BARDOLPH</speaker>
            <line>O joyful day!</line>
            <line>I would not take a knighthood for my fortune.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>What! I do bring good news.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Carry Master Silence to bed. Master Shallow, my</line>
            <line>Lord Shallow,--be what thou wilt; I am fortune's</line>
            <line>steward--get on thy boots: we'll ride all night.</line>
            <line>O sweet Pistol! Away, Bardolph!</line>
            <stagedir>Exit BARDOLPH</stagedir>
            <line>Come, Pistol, utter more to me; and withal devise</line>
            <line>something to do thyself good. Boot, boot, Master</line>
            <line>Shallow: I know the young king is sick for me. Let</line>
            <line>us take any man's horses; the laws of England are at</line>
            <line>my commandment. Blessed are they that have been my</line>
            <line>friends; and woe to my lord chief-justice!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>Let vultures vile seize on his lungs also!</line>
            <line>'Where is the life that late I led?' say they:</line>
            <line>Why, here it is; welcome these pleasant days!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-4">
      <title>SCENE IV.  London. A street.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter Beadles, dragging in HOSTESS QUICKLY
and DOLL TEARSHEET</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS QUICKLY</speaker>
            <line>No, thou arrant knave; I would to God that I might</line>
            <line>die, that I might have thee hanged: thou hast</line>
            <line>drawn my shoulder out of joint.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Beadle</speaker>
            <line>The constables have delivered her over to me; and</line>
            <line>she shall have whipping-cheer enough, I warrant</line>
            <line>her: there hath been a man or two lately killed about her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOLL TEARSHEET</speaker>
            <line>Nut-hook, nut-hook, you lie. Come on; I 'll tell</line>
            <line>thee what, thou damned tripe-visaged rascal, an</line>
            <line>the child I now go with do miscarry, thou wert</line>
            <line>better thou hadst struck thy mother, thou</line>
            <line>paper-faced villain.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS QUICKLY</speaker>
            <line>O the Lord, that Sir John were come! he would make</line>
            <line>this a bloody day to somebody. But I pray God the</line>
            <line>fruit of her womb miscarry!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Beadle</speaker>
            <line>If it do, you shall have a dozen of cushions again;</line>
            <line>you have but eleven now. Come, I charge you both go</line>
            <line>with me; for the man is dead that you and Pistol</line>
            <line>beat amongst you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOLL TEARSHEET</speaker>
            <line>I'll tell you what, you thin man in a censer, I</line>
            <line>will have you as soundly swinged for this,--you</line>
            <line>blue-bottle rogue, you filthy famished correctioner,</line>
            <line>if you be not swinged, I'll forswear half-kirtles.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Beadle</speaker>
            <line>Come, come, you she knight-errant, come.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS QUICKLY</speaker>
            <line>O God, that right should thus overcome might!</line>
            <line>Well, of sufferance comes ease.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOLL TEARSHEET</speaker>
            <line>Come, you rogue, come; bring me to a justice.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS QUICKLY</speaker>
            <line>Ay, come, you starved blood-hound.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOLL TEARSHEET</speaker>
            <line>Goodman death, goodman bones!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS QUICKLY</speaker>
            <line>Thou atomy, thou!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOLL TEARSHEET</speaker>
            <line>Come, you thin thing; come you rascal.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Beadle</speaker>
            <line>Very well.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-5">
      <title>SCENE V.  A public place near Westminster Abbey.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter two Grooms, strewing rushes</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Groom</speaker>
            <line>More rushes, more rushes.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Groom</speaker>
            <line>The trumpets have sounded twice.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Groom</speaker>
            <line>'Twill be two o'clock ere they come from the</line>
            <line>coronation: dispatch, dispatch.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Enter FALSTAFF, SHALLOW, PISTOL,
BARDOLPH, and Page</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Stand here by me, Master Robert Shallow; I will</line>
            <line>make the king do you grace: I will leer upon him as</line>
            <line>a' comes by; and do but mark the countenance that he</line>
            <line>will give me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>God bless thy lungs, good knight.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Come here, Pistol; stand behind me. O, if I had had</line>
            <line>time to have made new liveries, I would have</line>
            <line>bestowed the thousand pound I borrowed of you. But</line>
            <line>'tis no matter; this poor show doth better: this</line>
            <line>doth infer the zeal I had to see him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>It doth so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>It shows my earnestness of affection,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>It doth so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>My devotion,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>It doth, it doth, it doth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>As it were, to ride day and night; and not to</line>
            <line>deliberate, not to remember, not to have patience</line>
            <line>to shift me,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>It is best, certain.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>But to stand stained with travel, and sweating with</line>
            <line>desire to see him; thinking of nothing else,</line>
            <line>putting all affairs else in oblivion, as if there</line>
            <line>were nothing else to be done but to see him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>'Tis 'semper idem,' for 'obsque hoc nihil est:'</line>
            <line>'tis all in every part.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>'Tis so, indeed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>My knight, I will inflame thy noble liver,</line>
            <line>And make thee rage.</line>
            <line>Thy Doll, and Helen of thy noble thoughts,</line>
            <line>Is in base durance and contagious prison;</line>
            <line>Haled thither</line>
            <line>By most mechanical and dirty hand:</line>
            <line>Rouse up revenge from ebon den with fell</line>
            <line>Alecto's snake,</line>
            <line>For Doll is in. Pistol speaks nought but truth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>I will deliver her.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Shouts within, and the trumpets sound</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>There roar'd the sea, and trumpet-clangor sounds.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter KING HENRY V and his train, the Lord Chief-
Justice among them</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>God save thy grace, King Hal! my royal Hal!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>The heavens thee guard and keep, most royal imp of fame!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>God save thee, my sweet boy!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>My lord chief-justice, speak to that vain man.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord Chief-Justice</speaker>
            <line>Have you your wits? know you what 'tis to speak?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>My king! my Jove! I speak to thee, my heart!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>I know thee not, old man: fall to thy prayers;</line>
            <line>How ill white hairs become a fool and jester!</line>
            <line>I have long dream'd of such a kind of man,</line>
            <line>So surfeit-swell'd, so old and so profane;</line>
            <line>But, being awaked, I do despise my dream.</line>
            <line>Make less thy body hence, and more thy grace;</line>
            <line>Leave gormandizing; know the grave doth gape</line>
            <line>For thee thrice wider than for other men.</line>
            <line>Reply not to me with a fool-born jest:</line>
            <line>Presume not that I am the thing I was;</line>
            <line>For God doth know, so shall the world perceive,</line>
            <line>That I have turn'd away my former self;</line>
            <line>So will I those that kept me company.</line>
            <line>When thou dost hear I am as I have been,</line>
            <line>Approach me, and thou shalt be as thou wast,</line>
            <line>The tutor and the feeder of my riots:</line>
            <line>Till then, I banish thee, on pain of death,</line>
            <line>As I have done the rest of my misleaders,</line>
            <line>Not to come near our person by ten mile.</line>
            <line>For competence of life I will allow you,</line>
            <line>That lack of means enforce you not to evil:</line>
            <line>And, as we hear you do reform yourselves,</line>
            <line>We will, according to your strengths and qualities,</line>
            <line>Give you advancement. Be it your charge, my lord,</line>
            <line>To see perform'd the tenor of our word. Set on.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt KING HENRY V, &amp;c</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Master Shallow, I owe you a thousand pound.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>Yea, marry, Sir John; which I beseech you to let me</line>
            <line>have home with me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>That can hardly be, Master Shallow. Do not you</line>
            <line>grieve at this; I shall be sent for in private to</line>
            <line>him: look you, he must seem thus to the world:</line>
            <line>fear not your advancements; I will be the man yet</line>
            <line>that shall make you great.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>I cannot well perceive how, unless you should give</line>
            <line>me your doublet and stuff me out with straw. I</line>
            <line>beseech you, good Sir John, let me have five hundred</line>
            <line>of my thousand.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Sir, I will be as good as my word: this that you</line>
            <line>heard was but a colour.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SHALLOW</speaker>
            <line>A colour that I fear you will die in, Sir John.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Fear no colours: go with me to dinner: come,</line>
            <line>Lieutenant Pistol; come, Bardolph: I shall be sent</line>
            <line>for soon at night.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter Prince John of LANCASTER, the Lord
Chief-Justice; Officers with them</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord Chief-Justice</speaker>
            <line>Go, carry Sir John Falstaff to the Fleet:</line>
            <line>Take all his company along with him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>My lord, my lord,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord Chief-Justice</speaker>
            <line>I cannot now speak: I will hear you soon.</line>
            <line>Take them away.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISTOL</speaker>
            <line>Si fortune me tormenta, spero contenta.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt all but PRINCE JOHN and the Lord
Chief-Justice</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LANCASTER</speaker>
            <line>I like this fair proceeding of the king's:</line>
            <line>He hath intent his wonted followers</line>
            <line>Shall all be very well provided for;</line>
            <line>But all are banish'd till their conversations</line>
            <line>Appear more wise and modest to the world.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord Chief-Justice</speaker>
            <line>And so they are.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LANCASTER</speaker>
            <line>The king hath call'd his parliament, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord Chief-Justice</speaker>
            <line>He hath.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LANCASTER</speaker>
            <line>I will lay odds that, ere this year expire,</line>
            <line>We bear our civil swords and native fire</line>
            <line>As far as France: I heard a bird so sing,</line>
            <line>Whose music, to my thinking, pleased the king.</line>
            <line>Come, will you hence?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <epilogue id="act-5-epilog">
      <title>EPILOGUE</title>
      <epilogue-body>
         <stagedir>Spoken by a Dancer</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker/>
            <line>First my fear; then my courtesy; last my speech.</line>
            <line>My fear is, your displeasure; my courtesy, my duty;</line>
            <line>and my speech, to beg your pardons. If you look</line>
            <line>for a good speech now, you undo me: for what I have</line>
            <line>to say is of mine own making; and what indeed I</line>
            <line>should say will, I doubt, prove mine own marring.</line>
            <line>But to the purpose, and so to the venture. Be it</line>
            <line>known to you, as it is very well, I was lately here</line>
            <line>in the end of a displeasing play, to pray your</line>
            <line>patience for it and to promise you a better. I</line>
            <line>meant indeed to pay you with this; which, if like an</line>
            <line>ill venture it come unluckily home, I break, and</line>
            <line>you, my gentle creditors, lose. Here I promised you</line>
            <line>I would be and here I commit my body to your</line>
            <line>mercies: bate me some and I will pay you some and,</line>
            <line>as most debtors do, promise you infinitely.</line>
            <line>If my tongue cannot entreat you to acquit me, will</line>
            <line>you command me to use my legs? and yet that were but</line>
            <line>light payment, to dance out of your debt. But a</line>
            <line>good conscience will make any possible satisfaction,</line>
            <line>and so would I. All the gentlewomen here have</line>
            <line>forgiven me: if the gentlemen will not, then the</line>
            <line>gentlemen do not agree with the gentlewomen, which</line>
            <line>was never seen before in such an assembly.</line>
            <line>One word more, I beseech you. If you be not too</line>
            <line>much cloyed with fat meat, our humble author will</line>
            <line>continue the story, with Sir John in it, and make</line>
            <line>you merry with fair Katharine of France: where, for</line>
            <line>any thing I know, Falstaff shall die of a sweat,</line>
            <line>unless already a' be killed with your hard</line>
            <line>opinions; for Oldcastle died a martyr, and this is</line>
            <line>not the man. My tongue is weary; when my legs are</line>
            <line>too, I will bid you good night: and so kneel down</line>
            <line>before you; but, indeed, to pray for the queen.</line>
         </speech>
      </epilogue-body>
   </epilogue>
</act>