<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net/doctypes/dita/shakespear/dtd/act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-4">
   <title>ACT IV</title>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  Yorkshire. Gaultree Forest.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter the ARCHBISHOP OF YORK, MOWBRAY, LORD
HASTINGS, and others</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARCHBISHOP OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>What is this forest call'd?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>'Tis Gaultree Forest, an't shall please your grace.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARCHBISHOP OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Here stand, my lords; and send discoverers forth</line>
            <line>To know the numbers of our enemies.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>We have sent forth already.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARCHBISHOP OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>'Tis well done.</line>
            <line>My friends and brethren in these great affairs,</line>
            <line>I must acquaint you that I have received</line>
            <line>New-dated letters from Northumberland;</line>
            <line>Their cold intent, tenor and substance, thus:</line>
            <line>Here doth he wish his person, with such powers</line>
            <line>As might hold sortance with his quality,</line>
            <line>The which he could not levy; whereupon</line>
            <line>He is retired, to ripe his growing fortunes,</line>
            <line>To Scotland: and concludes in hearty prayers</line>
            <line>That your attempts may overlive the hazard</line>
            <line>And fearful melting of their opposite.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOWBRAY</speaker>
            <line>Thus do the hopes we have in him touch ground</line>
            <line>And dash themselves to pieces.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter a Messenger</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>Now, what news?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>West of this forest, scarcely off a mile,</line>
            <line>In goodly form comes on the enemy;</line>
            <line>And, by the ground they hide, I judge their number</line>
            <line>Upon or near the rate of thirty thousand.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOWBRAY</speaker>
            <line>The just proportion that we gave them out</line>
            <line>Let us sway on and face them in the field.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARCHBISHOP OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>What well-appointed leader fronts us here?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter WESTMORELAND</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOWBRAY</speaker>
            <line>I think it is my Lord of Westmoreland.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WESTMORELAND</speaker>
            <line>Health and fair greeting from our general,</line>
            <line>The prince, Lord John and Duke of Lancaster.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARCHBISHOP OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Say on, my Lord of Westmoreland, in peace:</line>
            <line>What doth concern your coming?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WESTMORELAND</speaker>
            <line>Then, my lord,</line>
            <line>Unto your grace do I in chief address</line>
            <line>The substance of my speech. If that rebellion</line>
            <line>Came like itself, in base and abject routs,</line>
            <line>Led on by bloody youth, guarded with rags,</line>
            <line>And countenanced by boys and beggary,</line>
            <line>I say, if damn'd commotion so appear'd,</line>
            <line>In his true, native and most proper shape,</line>
            <line>You, reverend father, and these noble lords</line>
            <line>Had not been here, to dress the ugly form</line>
            <line>Of base and bloody insurrection</line>
            <line>With your fair honours. You, lord archbishop,</line>
            <line>Whose see is by a civil peace maintained,</line>
            <line>Whose beard the silver hand of peace hath touch'd,</line>
            <line>Whose learning and good letters peace hath tutor'd,</line>
            <line>Whose white investments figure innocence,</line>
            <line>The dove and very blessed spirit of peace,</line>
            <line>Wherefore do you so ill translate ourself</line>
            <line>Out of the speech of peace that bears such grace,</line>
            <line>Into the harsh and boisterous tongue of war;</line>
            <line>Turning your books to graves, your ink to blood,</line>
            <line>Your pens to lances and your tongue divine</line>
            <line>To a trumpet and a point of war?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARCHBISHOP OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Wherefore do I this? so the question stands.</line>
            <line>Briefly to this end: we are all diseased,</line>
            <line>And with our surfeiting and wanton hours</line>
            <line>Have brought ourselves into a burning fever,</line>
            <line>And we must bleed for it; of which disease</line>
            <line>Our late king, Richard, being infected, died.</line>
            <line>But, my most noble Lord of Westmoreland,</line>
            <line>I take not on me here as a physician,</line>
            <line>Nor do I as an enemy to peace</line>
            <line>Troop in the throngs of military men;</line>
            <line>But rather show awhile like fearful war,</line>
            <line>To diet rank minds sick of happiness</line>
            <line>And purge the obstructions which begin to stop</line>
            <line>Our very veins of life. Hear me more plainly.</line>
            <line>I have in equal balance justly weigh'd</line>
            <line>What wrongs our arms may do, what wrongs we suffer,</line>
            <line>And find our griefs heavier than our offences.</line>
            <line>We see which way the stream of time doth run,</line>
            <line>And are enforced from our most quiet there</line>
            <line>By the rough torrent of occasion;</line>
            <line>And have the summary of all our griefs,</line>
            <line>When time shall serve, to show in articles;</line>
            <line>Which long ere this we offer'd to the king,</line>
            <line>And might by no suit gain our audience:</line>
            <line>When we are wrong'd and would unfold our griefs,</line>
            <line>We are denied access unto his person</line>
            <line>Even by those men that most have done us wrong.</line>
            <line>The dangers of the days but newly gone,</line>
            <line>Whose memory is written on the earth</line>
            <line>With yet appearing blood, and the examples</line>
            <line>Of every minute's instance, present now,</line>
            <line>Hath put us in these ill-beseeming arms,</line>
            <line>Not to break peace or any branch of it,</line>
            <line>But to establish here a peace indeed,</line>
            <line>Concurring both in name and quality.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WESTMORELAND</speaker>
            <line>When ever yet was your appeal denied?</line>
            <line>Wherein have you been galled by the king?</line>
            <line>What peer hath been suborn'd to grate on you,</line>
            <line>That you should seal this lawless bloody book</line>
            <line>Of forged rebellion with a seal divine</line>
            <line>And consecrate commotion's bitter edge?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARCHBISHOP OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>My brother general, the commonwealth,</line>
            <line>To brother born an household cruelty,</line>
            <line>I make my quarrel in particular.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WESTMORELAND</speaker>
            <line>There is no need of any such redress;</line>
            <line>Or if there were, it not belongs to you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOWBRAY</speaker>
            <line>Why not to him in part, and to us all</line>
            <line>That feel the bruises of the days before,</line>
            <line>And suffer the condition of these times</line>
            <line>To lay a heavy and unequal hand</line>
            <line>Upon our honours?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WESTMORELAND</speaker>
            <line>O, my good Lord Mowbray,</line>
            <line>Construe the times to their necessities,</line>
            <line>And you shall say indeed, it is the time,</line>
            <line>And not the king, that doth you injuries.</line>
            <line>Yet for your part, it not appears to me</line>
            <line>Either from the king or in the present time</line>
            <line>That you should have an inch of any ground</line>
            <line>To build a grief on: were you not restored</line>
            <line>To all the Duke of Norfolk's signories,</line>
            <line>Your noble and right well remember'd father's?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOWBRAY</speaker>
            <line>What thing, in honour, had my father lost,</line>
            <line>That need to be revived and breathed in me?</line>
            <line>The king that loved him, as the state stood then,</line>
            <line>Was force perforce compell'd to banish him:</line>
            <line>And then that Harry Bolingbroke and he,</line>
            <line>Being mounted and both roused in their seats,</line>
            <line>Their neighing coursers daring of the spur,</line>
            <line>Their armed staves in charge, their beavers down,</line>
            <line>Their eyes of fire sparking through sights of steel</line>
            <line>And the loud trumpet blowing them together,</line>
            <line>Then, then, when there was nothing could have stay'd</line>
            <line>My father from the breast of Bolingbroke,</line>
            <line>O when the king did throw his warder down,</line>
            <line>His own life hung upon the staff he threw;</line>
            <line>Then threw he down himself and all their lives</line>
            <line>That by indictment and by dint of sword</line>
            <line>Have since miscarried under Bolingbroke.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WESTMORELAND</speaker>
            <line>You speak, Lord Mowbray, now you know not what.</line>
            <line>The Earl of Hereford was reputed then</line>
            <line>In England the most valiant gentlemen:</line>
            <line>Who knows on whom fortune would then have smiled?</line>
            <line>But if your father had been victor there,</line>
            <line>He ne'er had borne it out of Coventry:</line>
            <line>For all the country in a general voice</line>
            <line>Cried hate upon him; and all their prayers and love</line>
            <line>Were set on Hereford, whom they doted on</line>
            <line>And bless'd and graced indeed, more than the king.</line>
            <line>But this is mere digression from my purpose.</line>
            <line>Here come I from our princely general</line>
            <line>To know your griefs; to tell you from his grace</line>
            <line>That he will give you audience; and wherein</line>
            <line>It shall appear that your demands are just,</line>
            <line>You shall enjoy them, every thing set off</line>
            <line>That might so much as think you enemies.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOWBRAY</speaker>
            <line>But he hath forced us to compel this offer;</line>
            <line>And it proceeds from policy, not love.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WESTMORELAND</speaker>
            <line>Mowbray, you overween to take it so;</line>
            <line>This offer comes from mercy, not from fear:</line>
            <line>For, lo! within a ken our army lies,</line>
            <line>Upon mine honour, all too confident</line>
            <line>To give admittance to a thought of fear.</line>
            <line>Our battle is more full of names than yours,</line>
            <line>Our men more perfect in the use of arms,</line>
            <line>Our armour all as strong, our cause the best;</line>
            <line>Then reason will our heart should be as good</line>
            <line>Say you not then our offer is compell'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOWBRAY</speaker>
            <line>Well, by my will we shall admit no parley.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WESTMORELAND</speaker>
            <line>That argues but the shame of your offence:</line>
            <line>A rotten case abides no handling.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>Hath the Prince John a full commission,</line>
            <line>In very ample virtue of his father,</line>
            <line>To hear and absolutely to determine</line>
            <line>Of what conditions we shall stand upon?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WESTMORELAND</speaker>
            <line>That is intended in the general's name:</line>
            <line>I muse you make so slight a question.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARCHBISHOP OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Then take, my Lord of Westmoreland, this schedule,</line>
            <line>For this contains our general grievances:</line>
            <line>Each several article herein redress'd,</line>
            <line>All members of our cause, both here and hence,</line>
            <line>That are insinew'd to this action,</line>
            <line>Acquitted by a true substantial form</line>
            <line>And present execution of our wills</line>
            <line>To us and to our purposes confined,</line>
            <line>We come within our awful banks again</line>
            <line>And knit our powers to the arm of peace.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WESTMORELAND</speaker>
            <line>This will I show the general. Please you, lords,</line>
            <line>In sight of both our battles we may meet;</line>
            <line>And either end in peace, which God so frame!</line>
            <line>Or to the place of difference call the swords</line>
            <line>Which must decide it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARCHBISHOP OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>My lord, we will do so.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit WESTMORELAND</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOWBRAY</speaker>
            <line>There is a thing within my bosom tells me</line>
            <line>That no conditions of our peace can stand.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>Fear you not that: if we can make our peace</line>
            <line>Upon such large terms and so absolute</line>
            <line>As our conditions shall consist upon,</line>
            <line>Our peace shall stand as firm as rocky mountains.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOWBRAY</speaker>
            <line>Yea, but our valuation shall be such</line>
            <line>That every slight and false-derived cause,</line>
            <line>Yea, every idle, nice and wanton reason</line>
            <line>Shall to the king taste of this action;</line>
            <line>That, were our royal faiths martyrs in love,</line>
            <line>We shall be winnow'd with so rough a wind</line>
            <line>That even our corn shall seem as light as chaff</line>
            <line>And good from bad find no partition.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARCHBISHOP OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>No, no, my lord. Note this; the king is weary</line>
            <line>Of dainty and such picking grievances:</line>
            <line>For he hath found to end one doubt by death</line>
            <line>Revives two greater in the heirs of life,</line>
            <line>And therefore will he wipe his tables clean</line>
            <line>And keep no tell-tale to his memory</line>
            <line>That may repeat and history his loss</line>
            <line>To new remembrance; for full well he knows</line>
            <line>He cannot so precisely weed this land</line>
            <line>As his misdoubts present occasion:</line>
            <line>His foes are so enrooted with his friends</line>
            <line>That, plucking to unfix an enemy,</line>
            <line>He doth unfasten so and shake a friend:</line>
            <line>So that this land, like an offensive wife</line>
            <line>That hath enraged him on to offer strokes,</line>
            <line>As he is striking, holds his infant up</line>
            <line>And hangs resolved correction in the arm</line>
            <line>That was uprear'd to execution.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>Besides, the king hath wasted all his rods</line>
            <line>On late offenders, that he now doth lack</line>
            <line>The very instruments of chastisement:</line>
            <line>So that his power, like to a fangless lion,</line>
            <line>May offer, but not hold.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARCHBISHOP OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>'Tis very true:</line>
            <line>And therefore be assured, my good lord marshal,</line>
            <line>If we do now make our atonement well,</line>
            <line>Our peace will, like a broken limb united,</line>
            <line>Grow stronger for the breaking.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOWBRAY</speaker>
            <line>Be it so.</line>
            <line>Here is return'd my Lord of Westmoreland.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter WESTMORELAND</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WESTMORELAND</speaker>
            <line>The prince is here at hand: pleaseth your lordship</line>
            <line>To meet his grace just distance 'tween our armies.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOWBRAY</speaker>
            <line>Your grace of York, in God's name then, set forward.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARCHBISHOP OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Before, and greet his grace: my lord, we come.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  Another part of the forest.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter, from one side, MOWBRAY, attended; afterwards
the ARCHBISHOP OF YORK, HASTINGS, and others: from
the other side, Prince John of LANCASTER, and
WESTMORELAND; Officers, and others with them</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LANCASTER</speaker>
            <line>You are well encounter'd here, my cousin Mowbray:</line>
            <line>Good day to you, gentle lord archbishop;</line>
            <line>And so to you, Lord Hastings, and to all.</line>
            <line>My Lord of York, it better show'd with you</line>
            <line>When that your flock, assembled by the bell,</line>
            <line>Encircled you to hear with reverence</line>
            <line>Your exposition on the holy text</line>
            <line>Than now to see you here an iron man,</line>
            <line>Cheering a rout of rebels with your drum,</line>
            <line>Turning the word to sword and life to death.</line>
            <line>That man that sits within a monarch's heart,</line>
            <line>And ripens in the sunshine of his favour,</line>
            <line>Would he abuse the countenance of the king,</line>
            <line>Alack, what mischiefs might he set abrooch</line>
            <line>In shadow of such greatness! With you, lord bishop,</line>
            <line>It is even so. Who hath not heard it spoken</line>
            <line>How deep you were within the books of God?</line>
            <line>To us the speaker in his parliament;</line>
            <line>To us the imagined voice of God himself;</line>
            <line>The very opener and intelligencer</line>
            <line>Between the grace, the sanctities of heaven</line>
            <line>And our dull workings. O, who shall believe</line>
            <line>But you misuse the reverence of your place,</line>
            <line>Employ the countenance and grace of heaven,</line>
            <line>As a false favourite doth his prince's name,</line>
            <line>In deeds dishonourable? You have ta'en up,</line>
            <line>Under the counterfeited zeal of God,</line>
            <line>The subjects of his substitute, my father,</line>
            <line>And both against the peace of heaven and him</line>
            <line>Have here up-swarm'd them.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARCHBISHOP OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Good my Lord of Lancaster,</line>
            <line>I am not here against your father's peace;</line>
            <line>But, as I told my lord of Westmoreland,</line>
            <line>The time misorder'd doth, in common sense,</line>
            <line>Crowd us and crush us to this monstrous form,</line>
            <line>To hold our safety up. I sent your grace</line>
            <line>The parcels and particulars of our grief,</line>
            <line>The which hath been with scorn shoved from the court,</line>
            <line>Whereon this Hydra son of war is born;</line>
            <line>Whose dangerous eyes may well be charm'd asleep</line>
            <line>With grant of our most just and right desires,</line>
            <line>And true obedience, of this madness cured,</line>
            <line>Stoop tamely to the foot of majesty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOWBRAY</speaker>
            <line>If not, we ready are to try our fortunes</line>
            <line>To the last man.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>And though we here fall down,</line>
            <line>We have supplies to second our attempt:</line>
            <line>If they miscarry, theirs shall second them;</line>
            <line>And so success of mischief shall be born</line>
            <line>And heir from heir shall hold this quarrel up</line>
            <line>Whiles England shall have generation.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LANCASTER</speaker>
            <line>You are too shallow, Hastings, much too shallow,</line>
            <line>To sound the bottom of the after-times.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WESTMORELAND</speaker>
            <line>Pleaseth your grace to answer them directly</line>
            <line>How far forth you do like their articles.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LANCASTER</speaker>
            <line>I like them all, and do allow them well,</line>
            <line>And swear here, by the honour of my blood,</line>
            <line>My father's purposes have been mistook,</line>
            <line>And some about him have too lavishly</line>
            <line>Wrested his meaning and authority.</line>
            <line>My lord, these griefs shall be with speed redress'd;</line>
            <line>Upon my soul, they shall. If this may please you,</line>
            <line>Discharge your powers unto their several counties,</line>
            <line>As we will ours: and here between the armies</line>
            <line>Let's drink together friendly and embrace,</line>
            <line>That all their eyes may bear those tokens home</line>
            <line>Of our restored love and amity.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARCHBISHOP OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>I take your princely word for these redresses.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LANCASTER</speaker>
            <line>I give it you, and will maintain my word:</line>
            <line>And thereupon I drink unto your grace.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>Go, captain, and deliver to the army</line>
            <line>This news of peace: let them have pay, and part:</line>
            <line>I know it will well please them. Hie thee, captain.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit Officer</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARCHBISHOP OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>To you, my noble Lord of Westmoreland.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WESTMORELAND</speaker>
            <line>I pledge your grace; and, if you knew what pains</line>
            <line>I have bestow'd to breed this present peace,</line>
            <line>You would drink freely: but my love to ye</line>
            <line>Shall show itself more openly hereafter.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARCHBISHOP OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>I do not doubt you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WESTMORELAND</speaker>
            <line>I am glad of it.</line>
            <line>Health to my lord and gentle cousin, Mowbray.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOWBRAY</speaker>
            <line>You wish me health in very happy season;</line>
            <line>For I am, on the sudden, something ill.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARCHBISHOP OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Against ill chances men are ever merry;</line>
            <line>But heaviness foreruns the good event.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WESTMORELAND</speaker>
            <line>Therefore be merry, coz; since sudden sorrow</line>
            <line>Serves to say thus, 'some good thing comes</line>
            <line>to-morrow.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARCHBISHOP OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Believe me, I am passing light in spirit.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOWBRAY</speaker>
            <line>So much the worse, if your own rule be true.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Shouts within</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LANCASTER</speaker>
            <line>The word of peace is render'd: hark, how they shout!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOWBRAY</speaker>
            <line>This had been cheerful after victory.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARCHBISHOP OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>A peace is of the nature of a conquest;</line>
            <line>For then both parties nobly are subdued,</line>
            <line>And neither party loser.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LANCASTER</speaker>
            <line>Go, my lord,</line>
            <line>And let our army be discharged too.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit WESTMORELAND</stagedir>
            <line>And, good my lord, so please you, let our trains</line>
            <line>March, by us, that we may peruse the men</line>
            <line>We should have coped withal.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARCHBISHOP OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Go, good Lord Hastings,</line>
            <line>And, ere they be dismissed, let them march by.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit HASTINGS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LANCASTER</speaker>
            <line>I trust, lords, we shall lie to-night together.</line>
            <stagedir>Re-enter WESTMORELAND</stagedir>
            <line>Now, cousin, wherefore stands our army still?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WESTMORELAND</speaker>
            <line>The leaders, having charge from you to stand,</line>
            <line>Will not go off until they hear you speak.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LANCASTER</speaker>
            <line>They know their duties.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter HASTINGS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>My lord, our army is dispersed already;</line>
            <line>Like youthful steers unyoked, they take their courses</line>
            <line>East, west, north, south; or, like a school broke up,</line>
            <line>Each hurries toward his home and sporting-place.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WESTMORELAND</speaker>
            <line>Good tidings, my Lord Hastings; for the which</line>
            <line>I do arrest thee, traitor, of high treason:</line>
            <line>And you, lord archbishop, and you, Lord Mowbray,</line>
            <line>Of capitol treason I attach you both.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOWBRAY</speaker>
            <line>Is this proceeding just and honourable?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WESTMORELAND</speaker>
            <line>Is your assembly so?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARCHBISHOP OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Will you thus break your faith?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LANCASTER</speaker>
            <line>I pawn'd thee none:</line>
            <line>I promised you redress of these same grievances</line>
            <line>Whereof you did complain; which, by mine honour,</line>
            <line>I will perform with a most Christian care.</line>
            <line>But for you, rebels, look to taste the due</line>
            <line>Meet for rebellion and such acts as yours.</line>
            <line>Most shallowly did you these arms commence,</line>
            <line>Fondly brought here and foolishly sent hence.</line>
            <line>Strike up our drums, pursue the scatter'd stray:</line>
            <line>God, and not we, hath safely fought to-day.</line>
            <line>Some guard these traitors to the block of death,</line>
            <line>Treason's true bed and yielder up of breath.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  Another part of the forest.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Alarum. Excursions. Enter FALSTAFF and COLEVILE, meeting</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>What's your name, sir? of what condition are you,</line>
            <line>and of what place, I pray?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COLEVILE</speaker>
            <line>I am a knight, sir, and my name is Colevile of the dale.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Well, then, Colevile is your name, a knight is your</line>
            <line>degree, and your place the dale: Colevile shall be</line>
            <line>still your name, a traitor your degree, and the</line>
            <line>dungeon your place, a place deep enough; so shall</line>
            <line>you be still Colevile of the dale.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COLEVILE</speaker>
            <line>Are not you Sir John Falstaff?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>As good a man as he, sir, whoe'er I am. Do ye</line>
            <line>yield, sir? or shall I sweat for you? if I do</line>
            <line>sweat, they are the drops of thy lovers, and they</line>
            <line>weep for thy death: therefore rouse up fear and</line>
            <line>trembling, and do observance to my mercy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COLEVILE</speaker>
            <line>I think you are Sir John Falstaff, and in that</line>
            <line>thought yield me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>I have a whole school of tongues in this belly of</line>
            <line>mine, and not a tongue of them all speaks any other</line>
            <line>word but my name. An I had but a belly of any</line>
            <line>indifference, I were simply the most active fellow</line>
            <line>in Europe: my womb, my womb, my womb, undoes me.</line>
            <line>Here comes our general.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter PRINCE JOHN OF LANCASTER, WESTMORELAND,
BLUNT, and others</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LANCASTER</speaker>
            <line>The heat is past; follow no further now:</line>
            <line>Call in the powers, good cousin Westmoreland.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit WESTMORELAND</stagedir>
            <line>Now, Falstaff, where have you been all this while?</line>
            <line>When every thing is ended, then you come:</line>
            <line>These tardy tricks of yours will, on my life,</line>
            <line>One time or other break some gallows' back.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>I would be sorry, my lord, but it should be thus: I</line>
            <line>never knew yet but rebuke and cheque was the reward</line>
            <line>of valour. Do you think me a swallow, an arrow, or a</line>
            <line>bullet? have I, in my poor and old motion, the</line>
            <line>expedition of thought? I have speeded hither with</line>
            <line>the very extremest inch of possibility; I have</line>
            <line>foundered nine score and odd posts: and here,</line>
            <line>travel-tainted as I am, have in my pure and</line>
            <line>immaculate valour, taken Sir John Colevile of the</line>
            <line>dale, a most furious knight and valorous enemy.</line>
            <line>But what of that? he saw me, and yielded; that I</line>
            <line>may justly say, with the hook-nosed fellow of Rome,</line>
            <line>'I came, saw, and overcame.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LANCASTER</speaker>
            <line>It was more of his courtesy than your deserving.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>I know not: here he is, and here I yield him: and</line>
            <line>I beseech your grace, let it be booked with the</line>
            <line>rest of this day's deeds; or, by the Lord, I will</line>
            <line>have it in a particular ballad else, with mine own</line>
            <line>picture on the top on't, Colevile kissing my foot:</line>
            <line>to the which course if I be enforced, if you do not</line>
            <line>all show like gilt twopences to me, and I in the</line>
            <line>clear sky of fame o'ershine you as much as the full</line>
            <line>moon doth the cinders of the element, which show</line>
            <line>like pins' heads to her, believe not the word of</line>
            <line>the noble: therefore let me have right, and let</line>
            <line>desert mount.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LANCASTER</speaker>
            <line>Thine's too heavy to mount.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Let it shine, then.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LANCASTER</speaker>
            <line>Thine's too thick to shine.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Let it do something, my good lord, that may do me</line>
            <line>good, and call it what you will.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LANCASTER</speaker>
            <line>Is thy name Colevile?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COLEVILE</speaker>
            <line>It is, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LANCASTER</speaker>
            <line>A famous rebel art thou, Colevile.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>And a famous true subject took him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COLEVILE</speaker>
            <line>I am, my lord, but as my betters are</line>
            <line>That led me hither: had they been ruled by me,</line>
            <line>You should have won them dearer than you have.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>I know not how they sold themselves: but thou, like</line>
            <line>a kind fellow, gavest thyself away gratis; and I</line>
            <line>thank thee for thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter WESTMORELAND</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LANCASTER</speaker>
            <line>Now, have you left pursuit?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WESTMORELAND</speaker>
            <line>Retreat is made and execution stay'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LANCASTER</speaker>
            <line>Send Colevile with his confederates</line>
            <line>To York, to present execution:</line>
            <line>Blunt, lead him hence; and see you guard him sure.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt BLUNT and others with COLEVILE</stagedir>
            <line>And now dispatch we toward the court, my lords:</line>
            <line>I hear the king my father is sore sick:</line>
            <line>Our news shall go before us to his majesty,</line>
            <line>Which, cousin, you shall bear to comfort him,</line>
            <line>And we with sober speed will follow you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>My lord, I beseech you, give me leave to go</line>
            <line>Through Gloucestershire: and, when you come to court,</line>
            <line>Stand my good lord, pray, in your good report.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LANCASTER</speaker>
            <line>Fare you well, Falstaff: I, in my condition,</line>
            <line>Shall better speak of you than you deserve.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt all but Falstaff</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>I would you had but the wit: 'twere better than</line>
            <line>your dukedom. Good faith, this same young sober-</line>
            <line>blooded boy doth not love me; nor a man cannot make</line>
            <line>him laugh; but that's no marvel, he drinks no wine.</line>
            <line>There's never none of these demure boys come to any</line>
            <line>proof; for thin drink doth so over-cool their blood,</line>
            <line>and making many fish-meals, that they fall into a</line>
            <line>kind of male green-sickness; and then when they</line>
            <line>marry, they get wenches: they are generally fools</line>
            <line>and cowards; which some of us should be too, but for</line>
            <line>inflammation. A good sherris sack hath a two-fold</line>
            <line>operation in it. It ascends me into the brain;</line>
            <line>dries me there all the foolish and dull and curdy</line>
            <line>vapours which environ it; makes it apprehensive,</line>
            <line>quick, forgetive, full of nimble fiery and</line>
            <line>delectable shapes, which, delivered o'er to the</line>
            <line>voice, the tongue, which is the birth, becomes</line>
            <line>excellent wit. The second property of your</line>
            <line>excellent sherris is, the warming of the blood;</line>
            <line>which, before cold and settled, left the liver</line>
            <line>white and pale, which is the badge of pusillanimity</line>
            <line>and cowardice; but the sherris warms it and makes</line>
            <line>it course from the inwards to the parts extreme:</line>
            <line>it illumineth the face, which as a beacon gives</line>
            <line>warning to all the rest of this little kingdom,</line>
            <line>man, to arm; and then the vital commoners and</line>
            <line>inland petty spirits muster me all to their captain,</line>
            <line>the heart, who, great and puffed up with this</line>
            <line>retinue, doth any deed of courage; and this valour</line>
            <line>comes of sherris. So that skill in the weapon is</line>
            <line>nothing without sack, for that sets it a-work; and</line>
            <line>learning a mere hoard of gold kept by a devil, till</line>
            <line>sack commences it and sets it in act and use.</line>
            <line>Hereof comes it that Prince Harry is valiant; for</line>
            <line>the cold blood he did naturally inherit of his</line>
            <line>father, he hath, like lean, sterile and bare land,</line>
            <line>manured, husbanded and tilled with excellent</line>
            <line>endeavour of drinking good and good store of fertile</line>
            <line>sherris, that he is become very hot and valiant. If</line>
            <line>I had a thousand sons, the first humane principle I</line>
            <line>would teach them should be, to forswear thin</line>
            <line>potations and to addict themselves to sack.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter BARDOLPH</stagedir>
            <line>How now Bardolph?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BARDOLPH</speaker>
            <line>The army is discharged all and gone.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Let them go. I'll through Gloucestershire; and</line>
            <line>there will I visit Master Robert Shallow, esquire:</line>
            <line>I have him already tempering between my finger and</line>
            <line>my thumb, and shortly will I seal with him. Come away.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-4">
      <title>SCENE IV.  Westminster. The Jerusalem Chamber.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter KING HENRY IV, the Princes Thomas of CLARENCE
and Humphrey of GLOUCESTER, WARWICK, and others</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>Now, lords, if God doth give successful end</line>
            <line>To this debate that bleedeth at our doors,</line>
            <line>We will our youth lead on to higher fields</line>
            <line>And draw no swords but what are sanctified.</line>
            <line>Our navy is address'd, our power collected,</line>
            <line>Our substitutes in absence well invested,</line>
            <line>And every thing lies level to our wish:</line>
            <line>Only, we want a little personal strength;</line>
            <line>And pause us, till these rebels, now afoot,</line>
            <line>Come underneath the yoke of government.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Both which we doubt not but your majesty</line>
            <line>Shall soon enjoy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>Humphrey, my son of Gloucester,</line>
            <line>Where is the prince your brother?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>I think he's gone to hunt, my lord, at Windsor.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>And how accompanied?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>I do not know, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>Is not his brother, Thomas of Clarence, with him?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>No, my good lord; he is in presence here.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>What would my lord and father?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>Nothing but well to thee, Thomas of Clarence.</line>
            <line>How chance thou art not with the prince thy brother?</line>
            <line>He loves thee, and thou dost neglect him, Thomas;</line>
            <line>Thou hast a better place in his affection</line>
            <line>Than all thy brothers: cherish it, my boy,</line>
            <line>And noble offices thou mayst effect</line>
            <line>Of mediation, after I am dead,</line>
            <line>Between his greatness and thy other brethren:</line>
            <line>Therefore omit him not; blunt not his love,</line>
            <line>Nor lose the good advantage of his grace</line>
            <line>By seeming cold or careless of his will;</line>
            <line>For he is gracious, if he be observed:</line>
            <line>He hath a tear for pity and a hand</line>
            <line>Open as day for melting charity:</line>
            <line>Yet notwithstanding, being incensed, he's flint,</line>
            <line>As humorous as winter and as sudden</line>
            <line>As flaws congealed in the spring of day.</line>
            <line>His temper, therefore, must be well observed:</line>
            <line>Chide him for faults, and do it reverently,</line>
            <line>When thou perceive his blood inclined to mirth;</line>
            <line>But, being moody, give him line and scope,</line>
            <line>Till that his passions, like a whale on ground,</line>
            <line>Confound themselves with working. Learn this, Thomas,</line>
            <line>And thou shalt prove a shelter to thy friends,</line>
            <line>A hoop of gold to bind thy brothers in,</line>
            <line>That the united vessel of their blood,</line>
            <line>Mingled with venom of suggestion--</line>
            <line>As, force perforce, the age will pour it in--</line>
            <line>Shall never leak, though it do work as strong</line>
            <line>As aconitum or rash gunpowder.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>I shall observe him with all care and love.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>Why art thou not at Windsor with him, Thomas?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>He is not there to-day; he dines in London.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>And how accompanied? canst thou tell that?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>With Poins, and other his continual followers.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>Most subject is the fattest soil to weeds;</line>
            <line>And he, the noble image of my youth,</line>
            <line>Is overspread with them: therefore my grief</line>
            <line>Stretches itself beyond the hour of death:</line>
            <line>The blood weeps from my heart when I do shape</line>
            <line>In forms imaginary the unguided days</line>
            <line>And rotten times that you shall look upon</line>
            <line>When I am sleeping with my ancestors.</line>
            <line>For when his headstrong riot hath no curb,</line>
            <line>When rage and hot blood are his counsellors,</line>
            <line>When means and lavish manners meet together,</line>
            <line>O, with what wings shall his affections fly</line>
            <line>Towards fronting peril and opposed decay!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>My gracious lord, you look beyond him quite:</line>
            <line>The prince but studies his companions</line>
            <line>Like a strange tongue, wherein, to gain the language,</line>
            <line>'Tis needful that the most immodest word</line>
            <line>Be look'd upon and learn'd; which once attain'd,</line>
            <line>Your highness knows, comes to no further use</line>
            <line>But to be known and hated. So, like gross terms,</line>
            <line>The prince will in the perfectness of time</line>
            <line>Cast off his followers; and their memory</line>
            <line>Shall as a pattern or a measure live,</line>
            <line>By which his grace must mete the lives of others,</line>
            <line>Turning past evils to advantages.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>'Tis seldom when the bee doth leave her comb</line>
            <line>In the dead carrion.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter WESTMORELAND</stagedir>
            <line>Who's here? Westmoreland?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WESTMORELAND</speaker>
            <line>Health to my sovereign, and new happiness</line>
            <line>Added to that that I am to deliver!</line>
            <line>Prince John your son doth kiss your grace's hand:</line>
            <line>Mowbray, the Bishop Scroop, Hastings and all</line>
            <line>Are brought to the correction of your law;</line>
            <line>There is not now a rebel's sword unsheath'd</line>
            <line>But peace puts forth her olive every where.</line>
            <line>The manner how this action hath been borne</line>
            <line>Here at more leisure may your highness read,</line>
            <line>With every course in his particular.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>O Westmoreland, thou art a summer bird,</line>
            <line>Which ever in the haunch of winter sings</line>
            <line>The lifting up of day.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter HARCOURT</stagedir>
            <line>Look, here's more news.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HARCOURT</speaker>
            <line>From enemies heaven keep your majesty;</line>
            <line>And, when they stand against you, may they fall</line>
            <line>As those that I am come to tell you of!</line>
            <line>The Earl Northumberland and the Lord Bardolph,</line>
            <line>With a great power of English and of Scots</line>
            <line>Are by the sheriff of Yorkshire overthrown:</line>
            <line>The manner and true order of the fight</line>
            <line>This packet, please it you, contains at large.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>And wherefore should these good news make me sick?</line>
            <line>Will fortune never come with both hands full,</line>
            <line>But write her fair words still in foulest letters?</line>
            <line>She either gives a stomach and no food;</line>
            <line>Such are the poor, in health; or else a feast</line>
            <line>And takes away the stomach; such are the rich,</line>
            <line>That have abundance and enjoy it not.</line>
            <line>I should rejoice now at this happy news;</line>
            <line>And now my sight fails, and my brain is giddy:</line>
            <line>O me! come near me; now I am much ill.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Comfort, your majesty!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>O my royal father!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WESTMORELAND</speaker>
            <line>My sovereign lord, cheer up yourself, look up.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Be patient, princes; you do know, these fits</line>
            <line>Are with his highness very ordinary.</line>
            <line>Stand from him. Give him air; he'll straight be well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>No, no, he cannot long hold out these pangs:</line>
            <line>The incessant care and labour of his mind</line>
            <line>Hath wrought the mure that should confine it in</line>
            <line>So thin that life looks through and will break out.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>The people fear me; for they do observe</line>
            <line>Unfather'd heirs and loathly births of nature:</line>
            <line>The seasons change their manners, as the year</line>
            <line>Had found some months asleep and leap'd them over.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>The river hath thrice flow'd, no ebb between;</line>
            <line>And the old folk, time's doting chronicles,</line>
            <line>Say it did so a little time before</line>
            <line>That our great-grandsire, Edward, sick'd and died.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Speak lower, princes, for the king recovers.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>This apoplexy will certain be his end.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>I pray you, take me up, and bear me hence</line>
            <line>Into some other chamber: softly, pray.</line>
         </speech>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-5">
      <title>SCENE V.  Another chamber.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>KING HENRY IV lying on a bed: CLARENCE,
GLOUCESTER, WARWICK, and others in attendance</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>Let there be no noise made, my gentle friends;</line>
            <line>Unless some dull and favourable hand</line>
            <line>Will whisper music to my weary spirit.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Call for the music in the other room.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>Set me the crown upon my pillow here.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>His eye is hollow, and he changes much.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Less noise, less noise!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter PRINCE HENRY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>Who saw the Duke of Clarence?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>I am here, brother, full of heaviness.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>How now! rain within doors, and none abroad!</line>
            <line>How doth the king?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Exceeding ill.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>Heard he the good news yet?</line>
            <line>Tell it him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>He alter'd much upon the hearing it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>If he be sick with joy, he'll recover without physic.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Not so much noise, my lords: sweet prince,</line>
            <line>speak low;</line>
            <line>The king your father is disposed to sleep.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>Let us withdraw into the other room.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Will't please your grace to go along with us?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>No; I will sit and watch here by the king.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt all but PRINCE HENRY</stagedir>
            <line>Why doth the crown lie there upon his pillow,</line>
            <line>Being so troublesome a bedfellow?</line>
            <line>O polish'd perturbation! golden care!</line>
            <line>That keep'st the ports of slumber open wide</line>
            <line>To many a watchful night! sleep with it now!</line>
            <line>Yet not so sound and half so deeply sweet</line>
            <line>As he whose brow with homely biggen bound</line>
            <line>Snores out the watch of night. O majesty!</line>
            <line>When thou dost pinch thy bearer, thou dost sit</line>
            <line>Like a rich armour worn in heat of day,</line>
            <line>That scalds with safety. By his gates of breath</line>
            <line>There lies a downy feather which stirs not:</line>
            <line>Did he suspire, that light and weightless down</line>
            <line>Perforce must move. My gracious lord! my father!</line>
            <line>This sleep is sound indeed, this is a sleep</line>
            <line>That from this golden rigol hath divorced</line>
            <line>So many English kings. Thy due from me</line>
            <line>Is tears and heavy sorrows of the blood,</line>
            <line>Which nature, love, and filial tenderness,</line>
            <line>Shall, O dear father, pay thee plenteously:</line>
            <line>My due from thee is this imperial crown,</line>
            <line>Which, as immediate as thy place and blood,</line>
            <line>Derives itself to me. Lo, here it sits,</line>
            <line>Which God shall guard: and put the world's whole strength</line>
            <line>Into one giant arm, it shall not force</line>
            <line>This lineal honour from me: this from thee</line>
            <line>Will I to mine leave, as 'tis left to me.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>Warwick! Gloucester! Clarence!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter WARWICK, GLOUCESTER, CLARENCE, and the rest</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>Doth the king call?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>What would your majesty? How fares your grace?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>Why did you leave me here alone, my lords?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>We left the prince my brother here, my liege,</line>
            <line>Who undertook to sit and watch by you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>The Prince of Wales! Where is he? let me see him:</line>
            <line>He is not here.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>This door is open; he is gone this way.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>He came not through the chamber where we stay'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>Where is the crown? who took it from my pillow?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>When we withdrew, my liege, we left it here.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>The prince hath ta'en it hence: go, seek him out.</line>
            <line>Is he so hasty that he doth suppose</line>
            <line>My sleep my death?</line>
            <line>Find him, my Lord of Warwick; chide him hither.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit WARWICK</stagedir>
            <line>This part of his conjoins with my disease,</line>
            <line>And helps to end me. See, sons, what things you are!</line>
            <line>How quickly nature falls into revolt</line>
            <line>When gold becomes her object!</line>
            <line>For this the foolish over-careful fathers</line>
            <line>Have broke their sleep with thoughts, their brains with care,</line>
            <line>Their bones with industry;</line>
            <line>For this they have engrossed and piled up</line>
            <line>The canker'd heaps of strange-achieved gold;</line>
            <line>For this they have been thoughtful to invest</line>
            <line>Their sons with arts and martial exercises:</line>
            <line>When, like the bee, culling from every flower</line>
            <line>The virtuous sweets,</line>
            <line>Our thighs pack'd with wax, our mouths with honey,</line>
            <line>We bring it to the hive, and, like the bees,</line>
            <line>Are murdered for our pains. This bitter taste</line>
            <line>Yield his engrossments to the ending father.</line>
            <stagedir>Re-enter WARWICK</stagedir>
            <line>Now, where is he that will not stay so long</line>
            <line>Till his friend sickness hath determined me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>My lord, I found the prince in the next room,</line>
            <line>Washing with kindly tears his gentle cheeks,</line>
            <line>With such a deep demeanor in great sorrow</line>
            <line>That tyranny, which never quaff'd but blood,</line>
            <line>Would, by beholding him, have wash'd his knife</line>
            <line>With gentle eye-drops. He is coming hither.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>But wherefore did he take away the crown?</line>
            <stagedir>Re-enter PRINCE HENRY</stagedir>
            <line>Lo, where he comes. Come hither to me, Harry.</line>
            <line>Depart the chamber, leave us here alone.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt WARWICK and the rest</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>I never thought to hear you speak again.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>Thy wish was father, Harry, to that thought:</line>
            <line>I stay too long by thee, I weary thee.</line>
            <line>Dost thou so hunger for mine empty chair</line>
            <line>That thou wilt needs invest thee with my honours</line>
            <line>Before thy hour be ripe? O foolish youth!</line>
            <line>Thou seek'st the greatness that will o'erwhelm thee.</line>
            <line>Stay but a little; for my cloud of dignity</line>
            <line>Is held from falling with so weak a wind</line>
            <line>That it will quickly drop: my day is dim.</line>
            <line>Thou hast stolen that which after some few hours</line>
            <line>Were thine without offence; and at my death</line>
            <line>Thou hast seal'd up my expectation:</line>
            <line>Thy life did manifest thou lovedst me not,</line>
            <line>And thou wilt have me die assured of it.</line>
            <line>Thou hidest a thousand daggers in thy thoughts,</line>
            <line>Which thou hast whetted on thy stony heart,</line>
            <line>To stab at half an hour of my life.</line>
            <line>What! canst thou not forbear me half an hour?</line>
            <line>Then get thee gone and dig my grave thyself,</line>
            <line>And bid the merry bells ring to thine ear</line>
            <line>That thou art crowned, not that I am dead.</line>
            <line>Let all the tears that should bedew my hearse</line>
            <line>Be drops of balm to sanctify thy head:</line>
            <line>Only compound me with forgotten dust</line>
            <line>Give that which gave thee life unto the worms.</line>
            <line>Pluck down my officers, break my decrees;</line>
            <line>For now a time is come to mock at form:</line>
            <line>Harry the Fifth is crown'd: up, vanity!</line>
            <line>Down, royal state! all you sage counsellors, hence!</line>
            <line>And to the English court assemble now,</line>
            <line>From every region, apes of idleness!</line>
            <line>Now, neighbour confines, purge you of your scum:</line>
            <line>Have you a ruffian that will swear, drink, dance,</line>
            <line>Revel the night, rob, murder, and commit</line>
            <line>The oldest sins the newest kind of ways?</line>
            <line>Be happy, he will trouble you no more;</line>
            <line>England shall double gild his treble guilt,</line>
            <line>England shall give him office, honour, might;</line>
            <line>For the fifth Harry from curb'd licence plucks</line>
            <line>The muzzle of restraint, and the wild dog</line>
            <line>Shall flesh his tooth on every innocent.</line>
            <line>O my poor kingdom, sick with civil blows!</line>
            <line>When that my care could not withhold thy riots,</line>
            <line>What wilt thou do when riot is thy care?</line>
            <line>O, thou wilt be a wilderness again,</line>
            <line>Peopled with wolves, thy old inhabitants!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>O, pardon me, my liege! but for my tears,</line>
            <line>The moist impediments unto my speech,</line>
            <line>I had forestall'd this dear and deep rebuke</line>
            <line>Ere you with grief had spoke and I had heard</line>
            <line>The course of it so far. There is your crown;</line>
            <line>And He that wears the crown immortally</line>
            <line>Long guard it yours! If I affect it more</line>
            <line>Than as your honour and as your renown,</line>
            <line>Let me no more from this obedience rise,</line>
            <line>Which my most inward true and duteous spirit</line>
            <line>Teacheth, this prostrate and exterior bending.</line>
            <line>God witness with me, when I here came in,</line>
            <line>And found no course of breath within your majesty,</line>
            <line>How cold it struck my heart! If I do feign,</line>
            <line>O, let me in my present wildness die</line>
            <line>And never live to show the incredulous world</line>
            <line>The noble change that I have purposed!</line>
            <line>Coming to look on you, thinking you dead,</line>
            <line>And dead almost, my liege, to think you were,</line>
            <line>I spake unto this crown as having sense,</line>
            <line>And thus upbraided it: 'The care on thee depending</line>
            <line>Hath fed upon the body of my father;</line>
            <line>Therefore, thou best of gold art worst of gold:</line>
            <line>Other, less fine in carat, is more precious,</line>
            <line>Preserving life in medicine potable;</line>
            <line>But thou, most fine, most honour'd: most renown'd,</line>
            <line>Hast eat thy bearer up.' Thus, my most royal liege,</line>
            <line>Accusing it, I put it on my head,</line>
            <line>To try with it, as with an enemy</line>
            <line>That had before my face murder'd my father,</line>
            <line>The quarrel of a true inheritor.</line>
            <line>But if it did infect my blood with joy,</line>
            <line>Or swell my thoughts to any strain of pride;</line>
            <line>If any rebel or vain spirit of mine</line>
            <line>Did with the least affection of a welcome</line>
            <line>Give entertainment to the might of it,</line>
            <line>Let God for ever keep it from my head</line>
            <line>And make me as the poorest vassal is</line>
            <line>That doth with awe and terror kneel to it!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>O my son,</line>
            <line>God put it in thy mind to take it hence,</line>
            <line>That thou mightst win the more thy father's love,</line>
            <line>Pleading so wisely in excuse of it!</line>
            <line>Come hither, Harry, sit thou by my bed;</line>
            <line>And hear, I think, the very latest counsel</line>
            <line>That ever I shall breathe. God knows, my son,</line>
            <line>By what by-paths and indirect crook'd ways</line>
            <line>I met this crown; and I myself know well</line>
            <line>How troublesome it sat upon my head.</line>
            <line>To thee it shall descend with bitter quiet,</line>
            <line>Better opinion, better confirmation;</line>
            <line>For all the soil of the achievement goes</line>
            <line>With me into the earth. It seem'd in me</line>
            <line>But as an honour snatch'd with boisterous hand,</line>
            <line>And I had many living to upbraid</line>
            <line>My gain of it by their assistances;</line>
            <line>Which daily grew to quarrel and to bloodshed,</line>
            <line>Wounding supposed peace: all these bold fears</line>
            <line>Thou see'st with peril I have answered;</line>
            <line>For all my reign hath been but as a scene</line>
            <line>Acting that argument: and now my death</line>
            <line>Changes the mode; for what in me was purchased,</line>
            <line>Falls upon thee in a more fairer sort;</line>
            <line>So thou the garland wear'st successively.</line>
            <line>Yet, though thou stand'st more sure than I could do,</line>
            <line>Thou art not firm enough, since griefs are green;</line>
            <line>And all my friends, which thou must make thy friends,</line>
            <line>Have but their stings and teeth newly ta'en out;</line>
            <line>By whose fell working I was first advanced</line>
            <line>And by whose power I well might lodge a fear</line>
            <line>To be again displaced: which to avoid,</line>
            <line>I cut them off; and had a purpose now</line>
            <line>To lead out many to the Holy Land,</line>
            <line>Lest rest and lying still might make them look</line>
            <line>Too near unto my state. Therefore, my Harry,</line>
            <line>Be it thy course to busy giddy minds</line>
            <line>With foreign quarrels; that action, hence borne out,</line>
            <line>May waste the memory of the former days.</line>
            <line>More would I, but my lungs are wasted so</line>
            <line>That strength of speech is utterly denied me.</line>
            <line>How I came by the crown, O God forgive;</line>
            <line>And grant it may with thee in true peace live!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>My gracious liege,</line>
            <line>You won it, wore it, kept it, gave it me;</line>
            <line>Then plain and right must my possession be:</line>
            <line>Which I with more than with a common pain</line>
            <line>'Gainst all the world will rightfully maintain.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter Lord John of LANCASTER</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>Look, look, here comes my John of Lancaster.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LANCASTER</speaker>
            <line>Health, peace, and happiness to my royal father!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>Thou bring'st me happiness and peace, son John;</line>
            <line>But health, alack, with youthful wings is flown</line>
            <line>From this bare wither'd trunk: upon thy sight</line>
            <line>My worldly business makes a period.</line>
            <line>Where is my Lord of Warwick?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>My Lord of Warwick!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter WARWICK, and others</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>Doth any name particular belong</line>
            <line>Unto the lodging where I first did swoon?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>'Tis call'd Jerusalem, my noble lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>Laud be to God! even there my life must end.</line>
            <line>It hath been prophesied to me many years,</line>
            <line>I should not die but in Jerusalem;</line>
            <line>Which vainly I supposed the Holy Land:</line>
            <line>But bear me to that chamber; there I'll lie;</line>
            <line>In that Jerusalem shall Harry die.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>