<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net/doctypes/dita/shakespear/dtd/act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-1">
   <title>ACT I</title>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  The same.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter LORD BARDOLPH</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD BARDOLPH</speaker>
            <line>Who keeps the gate here, ho?</line>
            <stagedir>The Porter opens the gate</stagedir>
            <line>Where is the earl?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Porter</speaker>
            <line>What shall I say you are?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD BARDOLPH</speaker>
            <line>Tell thou the earl</line>
            <line>That the Lord Bardolph doth attend him here.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Porter</speaker>
            <line>His lordship is walk'd forth into the orchard;</line>
            <line>Please it your honour, knock but at the gate,</line>
            <line>And he himself wilt answer.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter NORTHUMBERLAND</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD BARDOLPH</speaker>
            <line>Here comes the earl.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit Porter</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>What news, Lord Bardolph? every minute now</line>
            <line>Should be the father of some stratagem:</line>
            <line>The times are wild: contention, like a horse</line>
            <line>Full of high feeding, madly hath broke loose</line>
            <line>And bears down all before him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD BARDOLPH</speaker>
            <line>Noble earl,</line>
            <line>I bring you certain news from Shrewsbury.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>Good, an God will!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD BARDOLPH</speaker>
            <line>As good as heart can wish:</line>
            <line>The king is almost wounded to the death;</line>
            <line>And, in the fortune of my lord your son,</line>
            <line>Prince Harry slain outright; and both the Blunts</line>
            <line>Kill'd by the hand of Douglas; young Prince John</line>
            <line>And Westmoreland and Stafford fled the field;</line>
            <line>And Harry Monmouth's brawn, the hulk Sir John,</line>
            <line>Is prisoner to your son: O, such a day,</line>
            <line>So fought, so follow'd and so fairly won,</line>
            <line>Came not till now to dignify the times,</line>
            <line>Since Caesar's fortunes!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>How is this derived?</line>
            <line>Saw you the field? came you from Shrewsbury?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD BARDOLPH</speaker>
            <line>I spake with one, my lord, that came from thence,</line>
            <line>A gentleman well bred and of good name,</line>
            <line>That freely render'd me these news for true.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>Here comes my servant Travers, whom I sent</line>
            <line>On Tuesday last to listen after news.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter TRAVERS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD BARDOLPH</speaker>
            <line>My lord, I over-rode him on the way;</line>
            <line>And he is furnish'd with no certainties</line>
            <line>More than he haply may retail from me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>Now, Travers, what good tidings comes with you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRAVERS</speaker>
            <line>My lord, Sir John Umfrevile turn'd me back</line>
            <line>With joyful tidings; and, being better horsed,</line>
            <line>Out-rode me. After him came spurring hard</line>
            <line>A gentleman, almost forspent with speed,</line>
            <line>That stopp'd by me to breathe his bloodied horse.</line>
            <line>He ask'd the way to Chester; and of him</line>
            <line>I did demand what news from Shrewsbury:</line>
            <line>He told me that rebellion had bad luck</line>
            <line>And that young Harry Percy's spur was cold.</line>
            <line>With that, he gave his able horse the head,</line>
            <line>And bending forward struck his armed heels</line>
            <line>Against the panting sides of his poor jade</line>
            <line>Up to the rowel-head, and starting so</line>
            <line>He seem'd in running to devour the way,</line>
            <line>Staying no longer question.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>Ha! Again:</line>
            <line>Said he young Harry Percy's spur was cold?</line>
            <line>Of Hotspur Coldspur? that rebellion</line>
            <line>Had met ill luck?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD BARDOLPH</speaker>
            <line>My lord, I'll tell you what;</line>
            <line>If my young lord your son have not the day,</line>
            <line>Upon mine honour, for a silken point</line>
            <line>I'll give my barony: never talk of it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>Why should that gentleman that rode by Travers</line>
            <line>Give then such instances of loss?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD BARDOLPH</speaker>
            <line>Who, he?</line>
            <line>He was some hilding fellow that had stolen</line>
            <line>The horse he rode on, and, upon my life,</line>
            <line>Spoke at a venture. Look, here comes more news.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter MORTON</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>Yea, this man's brow, like to a title-leaf,</line>
            <line>Foretells the nature of a tragic volume:</line>
            <line>So looks the strand whereon the imperious flood</line>
            <line>Hath left a witness'd usurpation.</line>
            <line>Say, Morton, didst thou come from Shrewsbury?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MORTON</speaker>
            <line>I ran from Shrewsbury, my noble lord;</line>
            <line>Where hateful death put on his ugliest mask</line>
            <line>To fright our party.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>How doth my son and brother?</line>
            <line>Thou tremblest; and the whiteness in thy cheek</line>
            <line>Is apter than thy tongue to tell thy errand.</line>
            <line>Even such a man, so faint, so spiritless,</line>
            <line>So dull, so dead in look, so woe-begone,</line>
            <line>Drew Priam's curtain in the dead of night,</line>
            <line>And would have told him half his Troy was burnt;</line>
            <line>But Priam found the fire ere he his tongue,</line>
            <line>And I my Percy's death ere thou report'st it.</line>
            <line>This thou wouldst say, 'Your son did thus and thus;</line>
            <line>Your brother thus: so fought the noble Douglas:'</line>
            <line>Stopping my greedy ear with their bold deeds:</line>
            <line>But in the end, to stop my ear indeed,</line>
            <line>Thou hast a sigh to blow away this praise,</line>
            <line>Ending with 'Brother, son, and all are dead.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MORTON</speaker>
            <line>Douglas is living, and your brother, yet;</line>
            <line>But, for my lord your son--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>Why, he is dead.</line>
            <line>See what a ready tongue suspicion hath!</line>
            <line>He that but fears the thing he would not know</line>
            <line>Hath by instinct knowledge from others' eyes</line>
            <line>That what he fear'd is chanced. Yet speak, Morton;</line>
            <line>Tell thou an earl his divination lies,</line>
            <line>And I will take it as a sweet disgrace</line>
            <line>And make thee rich for doing me such wrong.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MORTON</speaker>
            <line>You are too great to be by me gainsaid:</line>
            <line>Your spirit is too true, your fears too certain.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>Yet, for all this, say not that Percy's dead.</line>
            <line>I see a strange confession in thine eye:</line>
            <line>Thou shakest thy head and hold'st it fear or sin</line>
            <line>To speak a truth. If he be slain, say so;</line>
            <line>The tongue offends not that reports his death:</line>
            <line>And he doth sin that doth belie the dead,</line>
            <line>Not he which says the dead is not alive.</line>
            <line>Yet the first bringer of unwelcome news</line>
            <line>Hath but a losing office, and his tongue</line>
            <line>Sounds ever after as a sullen bell,</line>
            <line>Remember'd tolling a departing friend.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD BARDOLPH</speaker>
            <line>I cannot think, my lord, your son is dead.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MORTON</speaker>
            <line>I am sorry I should force you to believe</line>
            <line>That which I would to God I had not seen;</line>
            <line>But these mine eyes saw him in bloody state,</line>
            <line>Rendering faint quittance, wearied and out-breathed,</line>
            <line>To Harry Monmouth; whose swift wrath beat down</line>
            <line>The never-daunted Percy to the earth,</line>
            <line>From whence with life he never more sprung up.</line>
            <line>In few, his death, whose spirit lent a fire</line>
            <line>Even to the dullest peasant in his camp,</line>
            <line>Being bruited once, took fire and heat away</line>
            <line>From the best temper'd courage in his troops;</line>
            <line>For from his metal was his party steel'd;</line>
            <line>Which once in him abated, all the rest</line>
            <line>Turn'd on themselves, like dull and heavy lead:</line>
            <line>And as the thing that's heavy in itself,</line>
            <line>Upon enforcement flies with greatest speed,</line>
            <line>So did our men, heavy in Hotspur's loss,</line>
            <line>Lend to this weight such lightness with their fear</line>
            <line>That arrows fled not swifter toward their aim</line>
            <line>Than did our soldiers, aiming at their safety,</line>
            <line>Fly from the field. Then was the noble Worcester</line>
            <line>Too soon ta'en prisoner; and that furious Scot,</line>
            <line>The bloody Douglas, whose well-labouring sword</line>
            <line>Had three times slain the appearance of the king,</line>
            <line>'Gan vail his stomach and did grace the shame</line>
            <line>Of those that turn'd their backs, and in his flight,</line>
            <line>Stumbling in fear, was took. The sum of all</line>
            <line>Is that the king hath won, and hath sent out</line>
            <line>A speedy power to encounter you, my lord,</line>
            <line>Under the conduct of young Lancaster</line>
            <line>And Westmoreland. This is the news at full.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>For this I shall have time enough to mourn.</line>
            <line>In poison there is physic; and these news,</line>
            <line>Having been well, that would have made me sick,</line>
            <line>Being sick, have in some measure made me well:</line>
            <line>And as the wretch, whose fever-weaken'd joints,</line>
            <line>Like strengthless hinges, buckle under life,</line>
            <line>Impatient of his fit, breaks like a fire</line>
            <line>Out of his keeper's arms, even so my limbs,</line>
            <line>Weaken'd with grief, being now enraged with grief,</line>
            <line>Are thrice themselves. Hence, therefore, thou nice crutch!</line>
            <line>A scaly gauntlet now with joints of steel</line>
            <line>Must glove this hand: and hence, thou sickly quoif!</line>
            <line>Thou art a guard too wanton for the head</line>
            <line>Which princes, flesh'd with conquest, aim to hit.</line>
            <line>Now bind my brows with iron; and approach</line>
            <line>The ragged'st hour that time and spite dare bring</line>
            <line>To frown upon the enraged Northumberland!</line>
            <line>Let heaven kiss earth! now let not Nature's hand</line>
            <line>Keep the wild flood confined! let order die!</line>
            <line>And let this world no longer be a stage</line>
            <line>To feed contention in a lingering act;</line>
            <line>But let one spirit of the first-born Cain</line>
            <line>Reign in all bosoms, that, each heart being set</line>
            <line>On bloody courses, the rude scene may end,</line>
            <line>And darkness be the burier of the dead!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRAVERS</speaker>
            <line>This strained passion doth you wrong, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD BARDOLPH</speaker>
            <line>Sweet earl, divorce not wisdom from your honour.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MORTON</speaker>
            <line>The lives of all your loving complices</line>
            <line>Lean on your health; the which, if you give o'er</line>
            <line>To stormy passion, must perforce decay.</line>
            <line>You cast the event of war, my noble lord,</line>
            <line>And summ'd the account of chance, before you said</line>
            <line>'Let us make head.' It was your presurmise,</line>
            <line>That, in the dole of blows, your son might drop:</line>
            <line>You knew he walk'd o'er perils, on an edge,</line>
            <line>More likely to fall in than to get o'er;</line>
            <line>You were advised his flesh was capable</line>
            <line>Of wounds and scars and that his forward spirit</line>
            <line>Would lift him where most trade of danger ranged:</line>
            <line>Yet did you say 'Go forth;' and none of this,</line>
            <line>Though strongly apprehended, could restrain</line>
            <line>The stiff-borne action: what hath then befallen,</line>
            <line>Or what hath this bold enterprise brought forth,</line>
            <line>More than that being which was like to be?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD BARDOLPH</speaker>
            <line>We all that are engaged to this loss</line>
            <line>Knew that we ventured on such dangerous seas</line>
            <line>That if we wrought our life 'twas ten to one;</line>
            <line>And yet we ventured, for the gain proposed</line>
            <line>Choked the respect of likely peril fear'd;</line>
            <line>And since we are o'erset, venture again.</line>
            <line>Come, we will all put forth, body and goods.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MORTON</speaker>
            <line>'Tis more than time: and, my most noble lord,</line>
            <line>I hear for certain, and do speak the truth,</line>
            <line>The gentle Archbishop of York is up</line>
            <line>With well-appointed powers: he is a man</line>
            <line>Who with a double surety binds his followers.</line>
            <line>My lord your son had only but the corpse,</line>
            <line>But shadows and the shows of men, to fight;</line>
            <line>For that same word, rebellion, did divide</line>
            <line>The action of their bodies from their souls;</line>
            <line>And they did fight with queasiness, constrain'd,</line>
            <line>As men drink potions, that their weapons only</line>
            <line>Seem'd on our side; but, for their spirits and souls,</line>
            <line>This word, rebellion, it had froze them up,</line>
            <line>As fish are in a pond. But now the bishop</line>
            <line>Turns insurrection to religion:</line>
            <line>Supposed sincere and holy in his thoughts,</line>
            <line>He's followed both with body and with mind;</line>
            <line>And doth enlarge his rising with the blood</line>
            <line>Of fair King Richard, scraped from Pomfret stones;</line>
            <line>Derives from heaven his quarrel and his cause;</line>
            <line>Tells them he doth bestride a bleeding land,</line>
            <line>Gasping for life under great Bolingbroke;</line>
            <line>And more and less do flock to follow him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>I knew of this before; but, to speak truth,</line>
            <line>This present grief had wiped it from my mind.</line>
            <line>Go in with me; and counsel every man</line>
            <line>The aptest way for safety and revenge:</line>
            <line>Get posts and letters, and make friends with speed:</line>
            <line>Never so few, and never yet more need.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  London. A street.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter FALSTAFF, with his Page bearing his sword
and buckler</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Sirrah, you giant, what says the doctor to my water?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <line>He said, sir, the water itself was a good healthy</line>
            <line>water; but, for the party that owed it, he might</line>
            <line>have more diseases than he knew for.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Men of all sorts take a pride to gird at me: the</line>
            <line>brain of this foolish-compounded clay, man, is not</line>
            <line>able to invent anything that tends to laughter, more</line>
            <line>than I invent or is invented on me: I am not only</line>
            <line>witty in myself, but the cause that wit is in other</line>
            <line>men. I do here walk before thee like a sow that</line>
            <line>hath overwhelmed all her litter but one. If the</line>
            <line>prince put thee into my service for any other reason</line>
            <line>than to set me off, why then I have no judgment.</line>
            <line>Thou whoreson mandrake, thou art fitter to be worn</line>
            <line>in my cap than to wait at my heels. I was never</line>
            <line>manned with an agate till now: but I will inset you</line>
            <line>neither in gold nor silver, but in vile apparel, and</line>
            <line>send you back again to your master, for a jewel,--</line>
            <line>the juvenal, the prince your master, whose chin is</line>
            <line>not yet fledged. I will sooner have a beard grow in</line>
            <line>the palm of my hand than he shall get one on his</line>
            <line>cheek; and yet he will not stick to say his face is</line>
            <line>a face-royal: God may finish it when he will, 'tis</line>
            <line>not a hair amiss yet: he may keep it still at a</line>
            <line>face-royal, for a barber shall never earn sixpence</line>
            <line>out of it; and yet he'll be crowing as if he had</line>
            <line>writ man ever since his father was a bachelor. He</line>
            <line>may keep his own grace, but he's almost out of mine,</line>
            <line>I can assure him. What said Master Dombledon about</line>
            <line>the satin for my short cloak and my slops?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <line>He said, sir, you should procure him better</line>
            <line>assurance than Bardolph: he would not take his</line>
            <line>band and yours; he liked not the security.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Let him be damned, like the glutton! pray God his</line>
            <line>tongue be hotter! A whoreson Achitophel! a rascally</line>
            <line>yea-forsooth knave! to bear a gentleman in hand,</line>
            <line>and then stand upon security! The whoreson</line>
            <line>smooth-pates do now wear nothing but high shoes, and</line>
            <line>bunches of keys at their girdles; and if a man is</line>
            <line>through with them in honest taking up, then they</line>
            <line>must stand upon security. I had as lief they would</line>
            <line>put ratsbane in my mouth as offer to stop it with</line>
            <line>security. I looked a' should have sent me two and</line>
            <line>twenty yards of satin, as I am a true knight, and he</line>
            <line>sends me security. Well, he may sleep in security;</line>
            <line>for he hath the horn of abundance, and the lightness</line>
            <line>of his wife shines through it: and yet cannot he</line>
            <line>see, though he have his own lanthorn to light him.</line>
            <line>Where's Bardolph?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <line>He's gone into Smithfield to buy your worship a horse.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>I bought him in Paul's, and he'll buy me a horse in</line>
            <line>Smithfield: an I could get me but a wife in the</line>
            <line>stews, I were manned, horsed, and wived.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter the Lord Chief-Justice and Servant</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <line>Sir, here comes the nobleman that committed the</line>
            <line>Prince for striking him about Bardolph.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Wait, close; I will not see him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord Chief-Justice</speaker>
            <line>What's he that goes there?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>Falstaff, an't please your lordship.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord Chief-Justice</speaker>
            <line>He that was in question for the robbery?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>He, my lord: but he hath since done good service at</line>
            <line>Shrewsbury; and, as I hear, is now going with some</line>
            <line>charge to the Lord John of Lancaster.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord Chief-Justice</speaker>
            <line>What, to York? Call him back again.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>Sir John Falstaff!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Boy, tell him I am deaf.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <line>You must speak louder; my master is deaf.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord Chief-Justice</speaker>
            <line>I am sure he is, to the hearing of any thing good.</line>
            <line>Go, pluck him by the elbow; I must speak with him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>Sir John!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>What! a young knave, and begging! Is there not</line>
            <line>wars? is there not employment? doth not the king</line>
            <line>lack subjects? do not the rebels need soldiers?</line>
            <line>Though it be a shame to be on any side but one, it</line>
            <line>is worse shame to beg than to be on the worst side,</line>
            <line>were it worse than the name of rebellion can tell</line>
            <line>how to make it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>You mistake me, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Why, sir, did I say you were an honest man? setting</line>
            <line>my knighthood and my soldiership aside, I had lied</line>
            <line>in my throat, if I had said so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>I pray you, sir, then set your knighthood and our</line>
            <line>soldiership aside; and give me leave to tell you,</line>
            <line>you lie in your throat, if you say I am any other</line>
            <line>than an honest man.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>I give thee leave to tell me so! I lay aside that</line>
            <line>which grows to me! if thou gettest any leave of me,</line>
            <line>hang me; if thou takest leave, thou wert better be</line>
            <line>hanged. You hunt counter: hence! avaunt!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>Sir, my lord would speak with you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord Chief-Justice</speaker>
            <line>Sir John Falstaff, a word with you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>My good lord! God give your lordship good time of</line>
            <line>day. I am glad to see your lordship abroad: I heard</line>
            <line>say your lordship was sick: I hope your lordship</line>
            <line>goes abroad by advice. Your lordship, though not</line>
            <line>clean past your youth, hath yet some smack of age in</line>
            <line>you, some relish of the saltness of time; and I must</line>
            <line>humbly beseech your lordship to have a reverent care</line>
            <line>of your health.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord Chief-Justice</speaker>
            <line>Sir John, I sent for you before your expedition to</line>
            <line>Shrewsbury.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>An't please your lordship, I hear his majesty is</line>
            <line>returned with some discomfort from Wales.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord Chief-Justice</speaker>
            <line>I talk not of his majesty: you would not come when</line>
            <line>I sent for you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>And I hear, moreover, his highness is fallen into</line>
            <line>this same whoreson apoplexy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord Chief-Justice</speaker>
            <line>Well, God mend him! I pray you, let me speak with</line>
            <line>you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>This apoplexy is, as I take it, a kind of lethargy,</line>
            <line>an't please your lordship; a kind of sleeping in the</line>
            <line>blood, a whoreson tingling.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord Chief-Justice</speaker>
            <line>What tell you me of it? be it as it is.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>It hath its original from much grief, from study and</line>
            <line>perturbation of the brain: I have read the cause of</line>
            <line>his effects in Galen: it is a kind of deafness.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord Chief-Justice</speaker>
            <line>I think you are fallen into the disease; for you</line>
            <line>hear not what I say to you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Very well, my lord, very well: rather, an't please</line>
            <line>you, it is the disease of not listening, the malady</line>
            <line>of not marking, that I am troubled withal.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord Chief-Justice</speaker>
            <line>To punish you by the heels would amend the</line>
            <line>attention of your ears; and I care not if I do</line>
            <line>become your physician.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>I am as poor as Job, my lord, but not so patient:</line>
            <line>your lordship may minister the potion of</line>
            <line>imprisonment to me in respect of poverty; but how</line>
            <line>should I be your patient to follow your</line>
            <line>prescriptions, the wise may make some dram of a</line>
            <line>scruple, or indeed a scruple itself.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord Chief-Justice</speaker>
            <line>I sent for you, when there were matters against you</line>
            <line>for your life, to come speak with me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>As I was then advised by my learned counsel in the</line>
            <line>laws of this land-service, I did not come.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord Chief-Justice</speaker>
            <line>Well, the truth is, Sir John, you live in great infamy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>He that buckles him in my belt cannot live in less.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord Chief-Justice</speaker>
            <line>Your means are very slender, and your waste is great.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>I would it were otherwise; I would my means were</line>
            <line>greater, and my waist slenderer.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord Chief-Justice</speaker>
            <line>You have misled the youthful prince.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>The young prince hath misled me: I am the fellow</line>
            <line>with the great belly, and he my dog.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord Chief-Justice</speaker>
            <line>Well, I am loath to gall a new-healed wound: your</line>
            <line>day's service at Shrewsbury hath a little gilded</line>
            <line>over your night's exploit on Gad's-hill: you may</line>
            <line>thank the unquiet time for your quiet o'er-posting</line>
            <line>that action.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>My lord?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord Chief-Justice</speaker>
            <line>But since all is well, keep it so: wake not a</line>
            <line>sleeping wolf.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>To wake a wolf is as bad as to smell a fox.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord Chief-Justice</speaker>
            <line>What! you are as a candle, the better part burnt</line>
            <line>out.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>A wassail candle, my lord, all tallow: if I did say</line>
            <line>of wax, my growth would approve the truth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord Chief-Justice</speaker>
            <line>There is not a white hair on your face but should</line>
            <line>have his effect of gravity.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>His effect of gravy, gravy, gravy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord Chief-Justice</speaker>
            <line>You follow the young prince up and down, like his</line>
            <line>ill angel.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Not so, my lord; your ill angel is light; but I hope</line>
            <line>he that looks upon me will take me without weighing:</line>
            <line>and yet, in some respects, I grant, I cannot go: I</line>
            <line>cannot tell. Virtue is of so little regard in these</line>
            <line>costermonger times that true valour is turned</line>
            <line>bear-herd: pregnancy is made a tapster, and hath</line>
            <line>his quick wit wasted in giving reckonings: all the</line>
            <line>other gifts appertinent to man, as the malice of</line>
            <line>this age shapes them, are not worth a gooseberry.</line>
            <line>You that are old consider not the capacities of us</line>
            <line>that are young; you do measure the heat of our</line>
            <line>livers with the bitterness of your galls: and we</line>
            <line>that are in the vaward of our youth, I must confess,</line>
            <line>are wags too.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord Chief-Justice</speaker>
            <line>Do you set down your name in the scroll of youth,</line>
            <line>that are written down old with all the characters of</line>
            <line>age? Have you not a moist eye? a dry hand? a</line>
            <line>yellow cheek? a white beard? a decreasing leg? an</line>
            <line>increasing belly? is not your voice broken? your</line>
            <line>wind short? your chin double? your wit single? and</line>
            <line>every part about you blasted with antiquity? and</line>
            <line>will you yet call yourself young? Fie, fie, fie, Sir John!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>My lord, I was born about three of the clock in the</line>
            <line>afternoon, with a white head and something a round</line>
            <line>belly. For my voice, I have lost it with halloing</line>
            <line>and singing of anthems. To approve my youth</line>
            <line>further, I will not: the truth is, I am only old in</line>
            <line>judgment and understanding; and he that will caper</line>
            <line>with me for a thousand marks, let him lend me the</line>
            <line>money, and have at him! For the box of the ear that</line>
            <line>the prince gave you, he gave it like a rude prince,</line>
            <line>and you took it like a sensible lord. I have</line>
            <line>chequed him for it, and the young lion repents;</line>
            <line>marry, not in ashes and sackcloth, but in new silk</line>
            <line>and old sack.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord Chief-Justice</speaker>
            <line>Well, God send the prince a better companion!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>God send the companion a better prince! I cannot</line>
            <line>rid my hands of him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord Chief-Justice</speaker>
            <line>Well, the king hath severed you and Prince Harry: I</line>
            <line>hear you are going with Lord John of Lancaster</line>
            <line>against the Archbishop and the Earl of</line>
            <line>Northumberland.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Yea; I thank your pretty sweet wit for it. But look</line>
            <line>you pray, all you that kiss my lady Peace at home,</line>
            <line>that our armies join not in a hot day; for, by the</line>
            <line>Lord, I take but two shirts out with me, and I mean</line>
            <line>not to sweat extraordinarily: if it be a hot day,</line>
            <line>and I brandish any thing but a bottle, I would I</line>
            <line>might never spit white again. There is not a</line>
            <line>dangerous action can peep out his head but I am</line>
            <line>thrust upon it: well, I cannot last ever: but it</line>
            <line>was alway yet the trick of our English nation, if</line>
            <line>they have a good thing, to make it too common. If</line>
            <line>ye will needs say I am an old man, you should give</line>
            <line>me rest. I would to God my name were not so</line>
            <line>terrible to the enemy as it is: I were better to be</line>
            <line>eaten to death with a rust than to be scoured to</line>
            <line>nothing with perpetual motion.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord Chief-Justice</speaker>
            <line>Well, be honest, be honest; and God bless your</line>
            <line>expedition!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Will your lordship lend me a thousand pound to</line>
            <line>furnish me forth?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord Chief-Justice</speaker>
            <line>Not a penny, not a penny; you are too impatient to</line>
            <line>bear crosses. Fare you well: commend me to my</line>
            <line>cousin Westmoreland.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt Chief-Justice and Servant</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>If I do, fillip me with a three-man beetle. A man</line>
            <line>can no more separate age and covetousness than a'</line>
            <line>can part young limbs and lechery: but the gout</line>
            <line>galls the one, and the pox pinches the other; and</line>
            <line>so both the degrees prevent my curses. Boy!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <line>Sir?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>What money is in my purse?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <line>Seven groats and two pence.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>I can get no remedy against this consumption of the</line>
            <line>purse: borrowing only lingers and lingers it out,</line>
            <line>but the disease is incurable. Go bear this letter</line>
            <line>to my Lord of Lancaster; this to the prince; this</line>
            <line>to the Earl of Westmoreland; and this to old</line>
            <line>Mistress Ursula, whom I have weekly sworn to marry</line>
            <line>since I perceived the first white hair on my chin.</line>
            <line>About it: you know where to find me.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit Page</stagedir>
            <line>A pox of this gout! or, a gout of this pox! for</line>
            <line>the one or the other plays the rogue with my great</line>
            <line>toe. 'Tis no matter if I do halt; I have the wars</line>
            <line>for my colour, and my pension shall seem the more</line>
            <line>reasonable. A good wit will make use of any thing:</line>
            <line>I will turn diseases to commodity.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  York. The Archbishop's palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter the ARCHBISHOP OF YORK, the Lords HASTINGS,
MOWBRAY, and BARDOLPH</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARCHBISHOP OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Thus have you heard our cause and known our means;</line>
            <line>And, my most noble friends, I pray you all,</line>
            <line>Speak plainly your opinions of our hopes:</line>
            <line>And first, lord marshal, what say you to it?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOWBRAY</speaker>
            <line>I well allow the occasion of our arms;</line>
            <line>But gladly would be better satisfied</line>
            <line>How in our means we should advance ourselves</line>
            <line>To look with forehead bold and big enough</line>
            <line>Upon the power and puissance of the king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>Our present musters grow upon the file</line>
            <line>To five and twenty thousand men of choice;</line>
            <line>And our supplies live largely in the hope</line>
            <line>Of great Northumberland, whose bosom burns</line>
            <line>With an incensed fire of injuries.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD BARDOLPH</speaker>
            <line>The question then, Lord Hastings, standeth thus;</line>
            <line>Whether our present five and twenty thousand</line>
            <line>May hold up head without Northumberland?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>With him, we may.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD BARDOLPH</speaker>
            <line>Yea, marry, there's the point:</line>
            <line>But if without him we be thought too feeble,</line>
            <line>My judgment is, we should not step too far</line>
            <line>Till we had his assistance by the hand;</line>
            <line>For in a theme so bloody-faced as this</line>
            <line>Conjecture, expectation, and surmise</line>
            <line>Of aids incertain should not be admitted.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARCHBISHOP OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>'Tis very true, Lord Bardolph; for indeed</line>
            <line>It was young Hotspur's case at Shrewsbury.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD BARDOLPH</speaker>
            <line>It was, my lord; who lined himself with hope,</line>
            <line>Eating the air on promise of supply,</line>
            <line>Flattering himself in project of a power</line>
            <line>Much smaller than the smallest of his thoughts:</line>
            <line>And so, with great imagination</line>
            <line>Proper to madmen, led his powers to death</line>
            <line>And winking leap'd into destruction.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>But, by your leave, it never yet did hurt</line>
            <line>To lay down likelihoods and forms of hope.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD BARDOLPH</speaker>
            <line>Yes, if this present quality of war,</line>
            <line>Indeed the instant action: a cause on foot</line>
            <line>Lives so in hope as in an early spring</line>
            <line>We see the appearing buds; which to prove fruit,</line>
            <line>Hope gives not so much warrant as despair</line>
            <line>That frosts will bite them. When we mean to build,</line>
            <line>We first survey the plot, then draw the model;</line>
            <line>And when we see the figure of the house,</line>
            <line>Then must we rate the cost of the erection;</line>
            <line>Which if we find outweighs ability,</line>
            <line>What do we then but draw anew the model</line>
            <line>In fewer offices, or at last desist</line>
            <line>To build at all? Much more, in this great work,</line>
            <line>Which is almost to pluck a kingdom down</line>
            <line>And set another up, should we survey</line>
            <line>The plot of situation and the model,</line>
            <line>Consent upon a sure foundation,</line>
            <line>Question surveyors, know our own estate,</line>
            <line>How able such a work to undergo,</line>
            <line>To weigh against his opposite; or else</line>
            <line>We fortify in paper and in figures,</line>
            <line>Using the names of men instead of men:</line>
            <line>Like one that draws the model of a house</line>
            <line>Beyond his power to build it; who, half through,</line>
            <line>Gives o'er and leaves his part-created cost</line>
            <line>A naked subject to the weeping clouds</line>
            <line>And waste for churlish winter's tyranny.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>Grant that our hopes, yet likely of fair birth,</line>
            <line>Should be still-born, and that we now possess'd</line>
            <line>The utmost man of expectation,</line>
            <line>I think we are a body strong enough,</line>
            <line>Even as we are, to equal with the king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD BARDOLPH</speaker>
            <line>What, is the king but five and twenty thousand?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>To us no more; nay, not so much, Lord Bardolph.</line>
            <line>For his divisions, as the times do brawl,</line>
            <line>Are in three heads: one power against the French,</line>
            <line>And one against Glendower; perforce a third</line>
            <line>Must take up us: so is the unfirm king</line>
            <line>In three divided; and his coffers sound</line>
            <line>With hollow poverty and emptiness.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARCHBISHOP OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>That he should draw his several strengths together</line>
            <line>And come against us in full puissance,</line>
            <line>Need not be dreaded.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>If he should do so,</line>
            <line>He leaves his back unarm'd, the French and Welsh</line>
            <line>Baying him at the heels: never fear that.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD BARDOLPH</speaker>
            <line>Who is it like should lead his forces hither?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>The Duke of Lancaster and Westmoreland;</line>
            <line>Against the Welsh, himself and Harry Monmouth:</line>
            <line>But who is substituted 'gainst the French,</line>
            <line>I have no certain notice.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARCHBISHOP OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Let us on,</line>
            <line>And publish the occasion of our arms.</line>
            <line>The commonwealth is sick of their own choice;</line>
            <line>Their over-greedy love hath surfeited:</line>
            <line>An habitation giddy and unsure</line>
            <line>Hath he that buildeth on the vulgar heart.</line>
            <line>O thou fond many, with what loud applause</line>
            <line>Didst thou beat heaven with blessing Bolingbroke,</line>
            <line>Before he was what thou wouldst have him be!</line>
            <line>And being now trimm'd in thine own desires,</line>
            <line>Thou, beastly feeder, art so full of him,</line>
            <line>That thou provokest thyself to cast him up.</line>
            <line>So, so, thou common dog, didst thou disgorge</line>
            <line>Thy glutton bosom of the royal Richard;</line>
            <line>And now thou wouldst eat thy dead vomit up,</line>
            <line>And howl'st to find it. What trust is in</line>
            <line>these times?</line>
            <line>They that, when Richard lived, would have him die,</line>
            <line>Are now become enamour'd on his grave:</line>
            <line>Thou, that threw'st dust upon his goodly head</line>
            <line>When through proud London he came sighing on</line>
            <line>After the admired heels of Bolingbroke,</line>
            <line>Criest now 'O earth, yield us that king again,</line>
            <line>And take thou this!' O thoughts of men accursed!</line>
            <line>Past and to come seems best; things present worst.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOWBRAY</speaker>
            <line>Shall we go draw our numbers and set on?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>We are time's subjects, and time bids be gone.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>