<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE induct
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:shakespear:dtd:induct" "induct.dtd">
<induct id="induct">
   <title>INDUCTION</title>
   <induct-body>
      <stagedir>Warkworth. Before the castle</stagedir>
      <stagedir>Enter RUMOUR, painted full of tongues</stagedir>
      <speech>
         <speaker>RUMOUR</speaker>
         <line>Open your ears; for which of you will stop</line>
         <line>The vent of hearing when loud Rumour speaks?</line>
         <line>I, from the orient to the drooping west,</line>
         <line>Making the wind my post-horse, still unfold</line>
         <line>The acts commenced on this ball of earth:</line>
         <line>Upon my tongues continual slanders ride,</line>
         <line>The which in every language I pronounce,</line>
         <line>Stuffing the ears of men with false reports.</line>
         <line>I speak of peace, while covert enmity</line>
         <line>Under the smile of safety wounds the world:</line>
         <line>And who but Rumour, who but only I,</line>
         <line>Make fearful musters and prepared defence,</line>
         <line>Whiles the big year, swoln with some other grief,</line>
         <line>Is thought with child by the stern tyrant war,</line>
         <line>And no such matter? Rumour is a pipe</line>
         <line>Blown by surmises, jealousies, conjectures</line>
         <line>And of so easy and so plain a stop</line>
         <line>That the blunt monster with uncounted heads,</line>
         <line>The still-discordant wavering multitude,</line>
         <line>Can play upon it. But what need I thus</line>
         <line>My well-known body to anatomize</line>
         <line>Among my household? Why is Rumour here?</line>
         <line>I run before King Harry's victory;</line>
         <line>Who in a bloody field by Shrewsbury</line>
         <line>Hath beaten down young Hotspur and his troops,</line>
         <line>Quenching the flame of bold rebellion</line>
         <line>Even with the rebel's blood. But what mean I</line>
         <line>To speak so true at first? my office is</line>
         <line>To noise abroad that Harry Monmouth fell</line>
         <line>Under the wrath of noble Hotspur's sword,</line>
         <line>And that the king before the Douglas' rage</line>
         <line>Stoop'd his anointed head as low as death.</line>
         <line>This have I rumour'd through the peasant towns</line>
         <line>Between that royal field of Shrewsbury</line>
         <line>And this worm-eaten hold of ragged stone,</line>
         <line>Where Hotspur's father, old Northumberland,</line>
         <line>Lies crafty-sick: the posts come tiring on,</line>
         <line>And not a man of them brings other news</line>
         <line>Than they have learn'd of me: from Rumour's tongues</line>
         <line>They bring smooth comforts false, worse than</line>
         <line>true wrongs.</line>
      </speech>
      <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
   </induct-body>
</induct>