<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net/doctypes/dita/shakespear/dtd/act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-1">
   <title>ACT I</title>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  King Lear's palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter KENT, GLOUCESTER, and EDMUND</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KENT</speaker>
            <line>I thought the king had more affected the Duke of</line>
            <line>Albany than Cornwall.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>It did always seem so to us: but now, in the</line>
            <line>division of the kingdom, it appears not which of</line>
            <line>the dukes he values most; for equalities are so</line>
            <line>weighed, that curiosity in neither can make choice</line>
            <line>of either's moiety.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KENT</speaker>
            <line>Is not this your son, my lord?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>His breeding, sir, hath been at my charge: I have</line>
            <line>so often blushed to acknowledge him, that now I am</line>
            <line>brazed to it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KENT</speaker>
            <line>I cannot conceive you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Sir, this young fellow's mother could: whereupon</line>
            <line>she grew round-wombed, and had, indeed, sir, a son</line>
            <line>for her cradle ere she had a husband for her bed.</line>
            <line>Do you smell a fault?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KENT</speaker>
            <line>I cannot wish the fault undone, the issue of it</line>
            <line>being so proper.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>But I have, sir, a son by order of law, some year</line>
            <line>elder than this, who yet is no dearer in my account:</line>
            <line>though this knave came something saucily into the</line>
            <line>world before he was sent for, yet was his mother</line>
            <line>fair; there was good sport at his making, and the</line>
            <line>whoreson must be acknowledged. Do you know this</line>
            <line>noble gentleman, Edmund?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDMUND</speaker>
            <line>No, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>My lord of Kent: remember him hereafter as my</line>
            <line>honourable friend.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDMUND</speaker>
            <line>My services to your lordship.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KENT</speaker>
            <line>I must love you, and sue to know you better.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDMUND</speaker>
            <line>Sir, I shall study deserving.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>He hath been out nine years, and away he shall</line>
            <line>again. The king is coming.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Sennet. Enter KING LEAR, CORNWALL, ALBANY,
GONERIL, REGAN, CORDELIA, and Attendants</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Attend the lords of France and Burgundy, Gloucester.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>I shall, my liege.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt GLOUCESTER and EDMUND</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Meantime we shall express our darker purpose.</line>
            <line>Give me the map there. Know that we have divided</line>
            <line>In three our kingdom: and 'tis our fast intent</line>
            <line>To shake all cares and business from our age;</line>
            <line>Conferring them on younger strengths, while we</line>
            <line>Unburthen'd crawl toward death. Our son of Cornwall,</line>
            <line>And you, our no less loving son of Albany,</line>
            <line>We have this hour a constant will to publish</line>
            <line>Our daughters' several dowers, that future strife</line>
            <line>May be prevented now. The princes, France and Burgundy,</line>
            <line>Great rivals in our youngest daughter's love,</line>
            <line>Long in our court have made their amorous sojourn,</line>
            <line>And here are to be answer'd. Tell me, my daughters,--</line>
            <line>Since now we will divest us both of rule,</line>
            <line>Interest of territory, cares of state,--</line>
            <line>Which of you shall we say doth love us most?</line>
            <line>That we our largest bounty may extend</line>
            <line>Where nature doth with merit challenge. Goneril,</line>
            <line>Our eldest-born, speak first.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GONERIL</speaker>
            <line>Sir, I love you more than words can wield the matter;</line>
            <line>Dearer than eye-sight, space, and liberty;</line>
            <line>Beyond what can be valued, rich or rare;</line>
            <line>No less than life, with grace, health, beauty, honour;</line>
            <line>As much as child e'er loved, or father found;</line>
            <line>A love that makes breath poor, and speech unable;</line>
            <line>Beyond all manner of so much I love you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORDELIA</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  What shall Cordelia do?</line>
            <line>Love, and be silent.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Of all these bounds, even from this line to this,</line>
            <line>With shadowy forests and with champains rich'd,</line>
            <line>With plenteous rivers and wide-skirted meads,</line>
            <line>We make thee lady: to thine and Albany's issue</line>
            <line>Be this perpetual. What says our second daughter,</line>
            <line>Our dearest Regan, wife to Cornwall? Speak.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>REGAN</speaker>
            <line>Sir, I am made</line>
            <line>Of the self-same metal that my sister is,</line>
            <line>And prize me at her worth. In my true heart</line>
            <line>I find she names my very deed of love;</line>
            <line>Only she comes too short: that I profess</line>
            <line>Myself an enemy to all other joys,</line>
            <line>Which the most precious square of sense possesses;</line>
            <line>And find I am alone felicitate</line>
            <line>In your dear highness' love.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORDELIA</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir> Then poor Cordelia!</line>
            <line>And yet not so; since, I am sure, my love's</line>
            <line>More richer than my tongue.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>To thee and thine hereditary ever</line>
            <line>Remain this ample third of our fair kingdom;</line>
            <line>No less in space, validity, and pleasure,</line>
            <line>Than that conferr'd on Goneril. Now, our joy,</line>
            <line>Although the last, not least; to whose young love</line>
            <line>The vines of France and milk of Burgundy</line>
            <line>Strive to be interess'd; what can you say to draw</line>
            <line>A third more opulent than your sisters? Speak.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORDELIA</speaker>
            <line>Nothing, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Nothing!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORDELIA</speaker>
            <line>Nothing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Nothing will come of nothing: speak again.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORDELIA</speaker>
            <line>Unhappy that I am, I cannot heave</line>
            <line>My heart into my mouth: I love your majesty</line>
            <line>According to my bond; nor more nor less.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>How, how, Cordelia! mend your speech a little,</line>
            <line>Lest it may mar your fortunes.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORDELIA</speaker>
            <line>Good my lord,</line>
            <line>You have begot me, bred me, loved me: I</line>
            <line>Return those duties back as are right fit,</line>
            <line>Obey you, love you, and most honour you.</line>
            <line>Why have my sisters husbands, if they say</line>
            <line>They love you all? Haply, when I shall wed,</line>
            <line>That lord whose hand must take my plight shall carry</line>
            <line>Half my love with him, half my care and duty:</line>
            <line>Sure, I shall never marry like my sisters,</line>
            <line>To love my father all.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>But goes thy heart with this?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORDELIA</speaker>
            <line>Ay, good my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>So young, and so untender?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORDELIA</speaker>
            <line>So young, my lord, and true.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Let it be so; thy truth, then, be thy dower:</line>
            <line>For, by the sacred radiance of the sun,</line>
            <line>The mysteries of Hecate, and the night;</line>
            <line>By all the operation of the orbs</line>
            <line>From whom we do exist, and cease to be;</line>
            <line>Here I disclaim all my paternal care,</line>
            <line>Propinquity and property of blood,</line>
            <line>And as a stranger to my heart and me</line>
            <line>Hold thee, from this, for ever. The barbarous Scythian,</line>
            <line>Or he that makes his generation messes</line>
            <line>To gorge his appetite, shall to my bosom</line>
            <line>Be as well neighbour'd, pitied, and relieved,</line>
            <line>As thou my sometime daughter.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KENT</speaker>
            <line>Good my liege,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Peace, Kent!</line>
            <line>Come not between the dragon and his wrath.</line>
            <line>I loved her most, and thought to set my rest</line>
            <line>On her kind nursery. Hence, and avoid my sight!</line>
            <line>So be my grave my peace, as here I give</line>
            <line>Her father's heart from her! Call France; who stirs?</line>
            <line>Call Burgundy. Cornwall and Albany,</line>
            <line>With my two daughters' dowers digest this third:</line>
            <line>Let pride, which she calls plainness, marry her.</line>
            <line>I do invest you jointly with my power,</line>
            <line>Pre-eminence, and all the large effects</line>
            <line>That troop with majesty. Ourself, by monthly course,</line>
            <line>With reservation of an hundred knights,</line>
            <line>By you to be sustain'd, shall our abode</line>
            <line>Make with you by due turns. Only we still retain</line>
            <line>The name, and all the additions to a king;</line>
            <line>The sway, revenue, execution of the rest,</line>
            <line>Beloved sons, be yours: which to confirm,</line>
            <line>This coronet part betwixt you.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Giving the crown</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KENT</speaker>
            <line>Royal Lear,</line>
            <line>Whom I have ever honour'd as my king,</line>
            <line>Loved as my father, as my master follow'd,</line>
            <line>As my great patron thought on in my prayers,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>The bow is bent and drawn, make from the shaft.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KENT</speaker>
            <line>Let it fall rather, though the fork invade</line>
            <line>The region of my heart: be Kent unmannerly,</line>
            <line>When Lear is mad. What wilt thou do, old man?</line>
            <line>Think'st thou that duty shall have dread to speak,</line>
            <line>When power to flattery bows? To plainness honour's bound,</line>
            <line>When majesty stoops to folly. Reverse thy doom;</line>
            <line>And, in thy best consideration, cheque</line>
            <line>This hideous rashness: answer my life my judgment,</line>
            <line>Thy youngest daughter does not love thee least;</line>
            <line>Nor are those empty-hearted whose low sound</line>
            <line>Reverbs no hollowness.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Kent, on thy life, no more.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KENT</speaker>
            <line>My life I never held but as a pawn</line>
            <line>To wage against thy enemies; nor fear to lose it,</line>
            <line>Thy safety being the motive.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Out of my sight!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KENT</speaker>
            <line>See better, Lear; and let me still remain</line>
            <line>The true blank of thine eye.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Now, by Apollo,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KENT</speaker>
            <line>Now, by Apollo, king,</line>
            <line>Thou swear'st thy gods in vain.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>O, vassal! miscreant!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Laying his hand on his sword</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALBANY</speaker>
            <speaker>CORNWALL</speaker>
            <line>Dear sir, forbear.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KENT</speaker>
            <line>Do:</line>
            <line>Kill thy physician, and the fee bestow</line>
            <line>Upon thy foul disease. Revoke thy doom;</line>
            <line>Or, whilst I can vent clamour from my throat,</line>
            <line>I'll tell thee thou dost evil.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Hear me, recreant!</line>
            <line>On thine allegiance, hear me!</line>
            <line>Since thou hast sought to make us break our vow,</line>
            <line>Which we durst never yet, and with strain'd pride</line>
            <line>To come between our sentence and our power,</line>
            <line>Which nor our nature nor our place can bear,</line>
            <line>Our potency made good, take thy reward.</line>
            <line>Five days we do allot thee, for provision</line>
            <line>To shield thee from diseases of the world;</line>
            <line>And on the sixth to turn thy hated back</line>
            <line>Upon our kingdom: if, on the tenth day following,</line>
            <line>Thy banish'd trunk be found in our dominions,</line>
            <line>The moment is thy death. Away! by Jupiter,</line>
            <line>This shall not be revoked.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KENT</speaker>
            <line>Fare thee well, king: sith thus thou wilt appear,</line>
            <line>Freedom lives hence, and banishment is here.</line>
            <stagedir>To CORDELIA</stagedir>
            <line>The gods to their dear shelter take thee, maid,</line>
            <line>That justly think'st, and hast most rightly said!</line>
            <stagedir>To REGAN and GONERIL</stagedir>
            <line>And your large speeches may your deeds approve,</line>
            <line>That good effects may spring from words of love.</line>
            <line>Thus Kent, O princes, bids you all adieu;</line>
            <line>He'll shape his old course in a country new.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Flourish. Re-enter GLOUCESTER, with KING OF FRANCE,
BURGUNDY, and Attendants</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Here's France and Burgundy, my noble lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>My lord of Burgundy.</line>
            <line>We first address towards you, who with this king</line>
            <line>Hath rivall'd for our daughter: what, in the least,</line>
            <line>Will you require in present dower with her,</line>
            <line>Or cease your quest of love?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BURGUNDY</speaker>
            <line>Most royal majesty,</line>
            <line>I crave no more than what your highness offer'd,</line>
            <line>Nor will you tender less.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Right noble Burgundy,</line>
            <line>When she was dear to us, we did hold her so;</line>
            <line>But now her price is fall'n. Sir, there she stands:</line>
            <line>If aught within that little seeming substance,</line>
            <line>Or all of it, with our displeasure pieced,</line>
            <line>And nothing more, may fitly like your grace,</line>
            <line>She's there, and she is yours.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BURGUNDY</speaker>
            <line>I know no answer.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Will you, with those infirmities she owes,</line>
            <line>Unfriended, new-adopted to our hate,</line>
            <line>Dower'd with our curse, and stranger'd with our oath,</line>
            <line>Take her, or leave her?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BURGUNDY</speaker>
            <line>Pardon me, royal sir;</line>
            <line>Election makes not up on such conditions.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Then leave her, sir; for, by the power that made me,</line>
            <line>I tell you all her wealth.</line>
            <stagedir>To KING OF FRANCE</stagedir>
            <line>For you, great king,</line>
            <line>I would not from your love make such a stray,</line>
            <line>To match you where I hate; therefore beseech you</line>
            <line>To avert your liking a more worthier way</line>
            <line>Than on a wretch whom nature is ashamed</line>
            <line>Almost to acknowledge hers.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING OF FRANCE</speaker>
            <line>This is most strange,</line>
            <line>That she, that even but now was your best object,</line>
            <line>The argument of your praise, balm of your age,</line>
            <line>Most best, most dearest, should in this trice of time</line>
            <line>Commit a thing so monstrous, to dismantle</line>
            <line>So many folds of favour. Sure, her offence</line>
            <line>Must be of such unnatural degree,</line>
            <line>That monsters it, or your fore-vouch'd affection</line>
            <line>Fall'n into taint: which to believe of her,</line>
            <line>Must be a faith that reason without miracle</line>
            <line>Could never plant in me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORDELIA</speaker>
            <line>I yet beseech your majesty,--</line>
            <line>If for I want that glib and oily art,</line>
            <line>To speak and purpose not; since what I well intend,</line>
            <line>I'll do't before I speak,--that you make known</line>
            <line>It is no vicious blot, murder, or foulness,</line>
            <line>No unchaste action, or dishonour'd step,</line>
            <line>That hath deprived me of your grace and favour;</line>
            <line>But even for want of that for which I am richer,</line>
            <line>A still-soliciting eye, and such a tongue</line>
            <line>As I am glad I have not, though not to have it</line>
            <line>Hath lost me in your liking.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Better thou</line>
            <line>Hadst not been born than not to have pleased me better.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING OF FRANCE</speaker>
            <line>Is it but this,--a tardiness in nature</line>
            <line>Which often leaves the history unspoke</line>
            <line>That it intends to do? My lord of Burgundy,</line>
            <line>What say you to the lady? Love's not love</line>
            <line>When it is mingled with regards that stand</line>
            <line>Aloof from the entire point. Will you have her?</line>
            <line>She is herself a dowry.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BURGUNDY</speaker>
            <line>Royal Lear,</line>
            <line>Give but that portion which yourself proposed,</line>
            <line>And here I take Cordelia by the hand,</line>
            <line>Duchess of Burgundy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Nothing: I have sworn; I am firm.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BURGUNDY</speaker>
            <line>I am sorry, then, you have so lost a father</line>
            <line>That you must lose a husband.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORDELIA</speaker>
            <line>Peace be with Burgundy!</line>
            <line>Since that respects of fortune are his love,</line>
            <line>I shall not be his wife.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING OF FRANCE</speaker>
            <line>Fairest Cordelia, that art most rich, being poor;</line>
            <line>Most choice, forsaken; and most loved, despised!</line>
            <line>Thee and thy virtues here I seize upon:</line>
            <line>Be it lawful I take up what's cast away.</line>
            <line>Gods, gods! 'tis strange that from their cold'st neglect</line>
            <line>My love should kindle to inflamed respect.</line>
            <line>Thy dowerless daughter, king, thrown to my chance,</line>
            <line>Is queen of us, of ours, and our fair France:</line>
            <line>Not all the dukes of waterish Burgundy</line>
            <line>Can buy this unprized precious maid of me.</line>
            <line>Bid them farewell, Cordelia, though unkind:</line>
            <line>Thou losest here, a better where to find.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Thou hast her, France: let her be thine; for we</line>
            <line>Have no such daughter, nor shall ever see</line>
            <line>That face of hers again. Therefore be gone</line>
            <line>Without our grace, our love, our benison.</line>
            <line>Come, noble Burgundy.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Flourish. Exeunt all but KING OF FRANCE, GONERIL,
REGAN, and CORDELIA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING OF FRANCE</speaker>
            <line>Bid farewell to your sisters.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORDELIA</speaker>
            <line>The jewels of our father, with wash'd eyes</line>
            <line>Cordelia leaves you: I know you what you are;</line>
            <line>And like a sister am most loath to call</line>
            <line>Your faults as they are named. Use well our father:</line>
            <line>To your professed bosoms I commit him</line>
            <line>But yet, alas, stood I within his grace,</line>
            <line>I would prefer him to a better place.</line>
            <line>So, farewell to you both.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>REGAN</speaker>
            <line>Prescribe not us our duties.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GONERIL</speaker>
            <line>Let your study</line>
            <line>Be to content your lord, who hath received you</line>
            <line>At fortune's alms. You have obedience scanted,</line>
            <line>And well are worth the want that you have wanted.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORDELIA</speaker>
            <line>Time shall unfold what plaited cunning hides:</line>
            <line>Who cover faults, at last shame them derides.</line>
            <line>Well may you prosper!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING OF FRANCE</speaker>
            <line>Come, my fair Cordelia.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt KING OF FRANCE and CORDELIA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GONERIL</speaker>
            <line>Sister, it is not a little I have to say of what</line>
            <line>most nearly appertains to us both. I think our</line>
            <line>father will hence to-night.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>REGAN</speaker>
            <line>That's most certain, and with you; next month with us.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GONERIL</speaker>
            <line>You see how full of changes his age is; the</line>
            <line>observation we have made of it hath not been</line>
            <line>little: he always loved our sister most; and</line>
            <line>with what poor judgment he hath now cast her off</line>
            <line>appears too grossly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>REGAN</speaker>
            <line>'Tis the infirmity of his age: yet he hath ever</line>
            <line>but slenderly known himself.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GONERIL</speaker>
            <line>The best and soundest of his time hath been but</line>
            <line>rash; then must we look to receive from his age,</line>
            <line>not alone the imperfections of long-engraffed</line>
            <line>condition, but therewithal the unruly waywardness</line>
            <line>that infirm and choleric years bring with them.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>REGAN</speaker>
            <line>Such unconstant starts are we like to have from</line>
            <line>him as this of Kent's banishment.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GONERIL</speaker>
            <line>There is further compliment of leavetaking</line>
            <line>between France and him. Pray you, let's hit</line>
            <line>together: if our father carry authority with</line>
            <line>such dispositions as he bears, this last</line>
            <line>surrender of his will but offend us.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>REGAN</speaker>
            <line>We shall further think on't.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GONERIL</speaker>
            <line>We must do something, and i' the heat.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  The Earl of Gloucester's castle.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter EDMUND, with a letter</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDMUND</speaker>
            <line>Thou, nature, art my goddess; to thy law</line>
            <line>My services are bound. Wherefore should I</line>
            <line>Stand in the plague of custom, and permit</line>
            <line>The curiosity of nations to deprive me,</line>
            <line>For that I am some twelve or fourteen moon-shines</line>
            <line>Lag of a brother? Why bastard? wherefore base?</line>
            <line>When my dimensions are as well compact,</line>
            <line>My mind as generous, and my shape as true,</line>
            <line>As honest madam's issue? Why brand they us</line>
            <line>With base? with baseness? bastardy? base, base?</line>
            <line>Who, in the lusty stealth of nature, take</line>
            <line>More composition and fierce quality</line>
            <line>Than doth, within a dull, stale, tired bed,</line>
            <line>Go to the creating a whole tribe of fops,</line>
            <line>Got 'tween asleep and wake? Well, then,</line>
            <line>Legitimate Edgar, I must have your land:</line>
            <line>Our father's love is to the bastard Edmund</line>
            <line>As to the legitimate: fine word,--legitimate!</line>
            <line>Well, my legitimate, if this letter speed,</line>
            <line>And my invention thrive, Edmund the base</line>
            <line>Shall top the legitimate. I grow; I prosper:</line>
            <line>Now, gods, stand up for bastards!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter GLOUCESTER</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Kent banish'd thus! and France in choler parted!</line>
            <line>And the king gone to-night! subscribed his power!</line>
            <line>Confined to exhibition! All this done</line>
            <line>Upon the gad! Edmund, how now! what news?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDMUND</speaker>
            <line>So please your lordship, none.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Putting up the letter</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Why so earnestly seek you to put up that letter?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDMUND</speaker>
            <line>I know no news, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>What paper were you reading?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDMUND</speaker>
            <line>Nothing, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>No? What needed, then, that terrible dispatch of</line>
            <line>it into your pocket? the quality of nothing hath</line>
            <line>not such need to hide itself. Let's see: come,</line>
            <line>if it be nothing, I shall not need spectacles.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDMUND</speaker>
            <line>I beseech you, sir, pardon me: it is a letter</line>
            <line>from my brother, that I have not all o'er-read;</line>
            <line>and for so much as I have perused, I find it not</line>
            <line>fit for your o'er-looking.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Give me the letter, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDMUND</speaker>
            <line>I shall offend, either to detain or give it. The</line>
            <line>contents, as in part I understand them, are to blame.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Let's see, let's see.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDMUND</speaker>
            <line>I hope, for my brother's justification, he wrote</line>
            <line>this but as an essay or taste of my virtue.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>  'This policy and reverence of age makes</line>
            <line>the world bitter to the best of our times; keeps</line>
            <line>our fortunes from us till our oldness cannot relish</line>
            <line>them. I begin to find an idle and fond bondage</line>
            <line>in the oppression of aged tyranny; who sways, not</line>
            <line>as it hath power, but as it is suffered. Come to</line>
            <line>me, that of this I may speak more. If our father</line>
            <line>would sleep till I waked him, you should half his</line>
            <line>revenue for ever, and live the beloved of your</line>
            <line>brother, EDGAR.'</line>
            <line>Hum--conspiracy!--'Sleep till I waked him,--you</line>
            <line>should enjoy half his revenue,'--My son Edgar!</line>
            <line>Had he a hand to write this? a heart and brain</line>
            <line>to breed it in?--When came this to you? who</line>
            <line>brought it?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDMUND</speaker>
            <line>It was not brought me, my lord; there's the</line>
            <line>cunning of it; I found it thrown in at the</line>
            <line>casement of my closet.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>You know the character to be your brother's?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDMUND</speaker>
            <line>If the matter were good, my lord, I durst swear</line>
            <line>it were his; but, in respect of that, I would</line>
            <line>fain think it were not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>It is his.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDMUND</speaker>
            <line>It is his hand, my lord; but I hope his heart is</line>
            <line>not in the contents.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Hath he never heretofore sounded you in this business?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDMUND</speaker>
            <line>Never, my lord: but I have heard him oft</line>
            <line>maintain it to be fit, that, sons at perfect age,</line>
            <line>and fathers declining, the father should be as</line>
            <line>ward to the son, and the son manage his revenue.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>O villain, villain! His very opinion in the</line>
            <line>letter! Abhorred villain! Unnatural, detested,</line>
            <line>brutish villain! worse than brutish! Go, sirrah,</line>
            <line>seek him; I'll apprehend him: abominable villain!</line>
            <line>Where is he?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDMUND</speaker>
            <line>I do not well know, my lord. If it shall please</line>
            <line>you to suspend your indignation against my</line>
            <line>brother till you can derive from him better</line>
            <line>testimony of his intent, you shall run a certain</line>
            <line>course; where, if you violently proceed against</line>
            <line>him, mistaking his purpose, it would make a great</line>
            <line>gap in your own honour, and shake in pieces the</line>
            <line>heart of his obedience. I dare pawn down my life</line>
            <line>for him, that he hath wrote this to feel my</line>
            <line>affection to your honour, and to no further</line>
            <line>pretence of danger.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Think you so?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDMUND</speaker>
            <line>If your honour judge it meet, I will place you</line>
            <line>where you shall hear us confer of this, and by an</line>
            <line>auricular assurance have your satisfaction; and</line>
            <line>that without any further delay than this very evening.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>He cannot be such a monster--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDMUND</speaker>
            <line>Nor is not, sure.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>To his father, that so tenderly and entirely</line>
            <line>loves him. Heaven and earth! Edmund, seek him</line>
            <line>out: wind me into him, I pray you: frame the</line>
            <line>business after your own wisdom. I would unstate</line>
            <line>myself, to be in a due resolution.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDMUND</speaker>
            <line>I will seek him, sir, presently: convey the</line>
            <line>business as I shall find means and acquaint you withal.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>These late eclipses in the sun and moon portend</line>
            <line>no good to us: though the wisdom of nature can</line>
            <line>reason it thus and thus, yet nature finds itself</line>
            <line>scourged by the sequent effects: love cools,</line>
            <line>friendship falls off, brothers divide: in</line>
            <line>cities, mutinies; in countries, discord; in</line>
            <line>palaces, treason; and the bond cracked 'twixt son</line>
            <line>and father. This villain of mine comes under the</line>
            <line>prediction; there's son against father: the king</line>
            <line>falls from bias of nature; there's father against</line>
            <line>child. We have seen the best of our time:</line>
            <line>machinations, hollowness, treachery, and all</line>
            <line>ruinous disorders, follow us disquietly to our</line>
            <line>graves. Find out this villain, Edmund; it shall</line>
            <line>lose thee nothing; do it carefully. And the</line>
            <line>noble and true-hearted Kent banished! his</line>
            <line>offence, honesty! 'Tis strange.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDMUND</speaker>
            <line>This is the excellent foppery of the world, that,</line>
            <line>when we are sick in fortune,--often the surfeit</line>
            <line>of our own behavior,--we make guilty of our</line>
            <line>disasters the sun, the moon, and the stars: as</line>
            <line>if we were villains by necessity; fools by</line>
            <line>heavenly compulsion; knaves, thieves, and</line>
            <line>treachers, by spherical predominance; drunkards,</line>
            <line>liars, and adulterers, by an enforced obedience of</line>
            <line>planetary influence; and all that we are evil in,</line>
            <line>by a divine thrusting on: an admirable evasion</line>
            <line>of whoremaster man, to lay his goatish</line>
            <line>disposition to the charge of a star! My</line>
            <line>father compounded with my mother under the</line>
            <line>dragon's tail; and my nativity was under Ursa</line>
            <line>major; so that it follows, I am rough and</line>
            <line>lecherous. Tut, I should have been that I am,</line>
            <line>had the maidenliest star in the firmament</line>
            <line>twinkled on my bastardizing. Edgar--</line>
            <stagedir>Enter EDGAR</stagedir>
            <line>And pat he comes like the catastrophe of the old</line>
            <line>comedy: my cue is villanous melancholy, with a</line>
            <line>sigh like Tom o' Bedlam. O, these eclipses do</line>
            <line>portend these divisions! fa, sol, la, mi.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDGAR</speaker>
            <line>How now, brother Edmund! what serious</line>
            <line>contemplation are you in?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDMUND</speaker>
            <line>I am thinking, brother, of a prediction I read</line>
            <line>this other day, what should follow these eclipses.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDGAR</speaker>
            <line>Do you busy yourself about that?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDMUND</speaker>
            <line>I promise you, the effects he writes of succeed</line>
            <line>unhappily; as of unnaturalness between the child</line>
            <line>and the parent; death, dearth, dissolutions of</line>
            <line>ancient amities; divisions in state, menaces and</line>
            <line>maledictions against king and nobles; needless</line>
            <line>diffidences, banishment of friends, dissipation</line>
            <line>of cohorts, nuptial breaches, and I know not what.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDGAR</speaker>
            <line>How long have you been a sectary astronomical?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDMUND</speaker>
            <line>Come, come; when saw you my father last?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDGAR</speaker>
            <line>Why, the night gone by.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDMUND</speaker>
            <line>Spake you with him?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDGAR</speaker>
            <line>Ay, two hours together.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDMUND</speaker>
            <line>Parted you in good terms? Found you no</line>
            <line>displeasure in him by word or countenance?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDGAR</speaker>
            <line>None at all.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDMUND</speaker>
            <line>Bethink yourself wherein you may have offended</line>
            <line>him: and at my entreaty forbear his presence</line>
            <line>till some little time hath qualified the heat of</line>
            <line>his displeasure; which at this instant so rageth</line>
            <line>in him, that with the mischief of your person it</line>
            <line>would scarcely allay.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDGAR</speaker>
            <line>Some villain hath done me wrong.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDMUND</speaker>
            <line>That's my fear. I pray you, have a continent</line>
            <line>forbearance till the spied of his rage goes</line>
            <line>slower; and, as I say, retire with me to my</line>
            <line>lodging, from whence I will fitly bring you to</line>
            <line>hear my lord speak: pray ye, go; there's my key:</line>
            <line>if you do stir abroad, go armed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDGAR</speaker>
            <line>Armed, brother!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDMUND</speaker>
            <line>Brother, I advise you to the best; go armed: I</line>
            <line>am no honest man if there be any good meaning</line>
            <line>towards you: I have told you what I have seen</line>
            <line>and heard; but faintly, nothing like the image</line>
            <line>and horror of it: pray you, away.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDGAR</speaker>
            <line>Shall I hear from you anon?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDMUND</speaker>
            <line>I do serve you in this business.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit EDGAR</stagedir>
            <line>A credulous father! and a brother noble,</line>
            <line>Whose nature is so far from doing harms,</line>
            <line>That he suspects none: on whose foolish honesty</line>
            <line>My practises ride easy! I see the business.</line>
            <line>Let me, if not by birth, have lands by wit:</line>
            <line>All with me's meet that I can fashion fit.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  The Duke of Albany's palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter GONERIL, and OSWALD, her steward</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GONERIL</speaker>
            <line>Did my father strike my gentleman for chiding of his fool?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OSWALD</speaker>
            <line>Yes, madam.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GONERIL</speaker>
            <line>By day and night he wrongs me; every hour</line>
            <line>He flashes into one gross crime or other,</line>
            <line>That sets us all at odds: I'll not endure it:</line>
            <line>His knights grow riotous, and himself upbraids us</line>
            <line>On every trifle. When he returns from hunting,</line>
            <line>I will not speak with him; say I am sick:</line>
            <line>If you come slack of former services,</line>
            <line>You shall do well; the fault of it I'll answer.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OSWALD</speaker>
            <line>He's coming, madam; I hear him.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Horns within</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GONERIL</speaker>
            <line>Put on what weary negligence you please,</line>
            <line>You and your fellows; I'll have it come to question:</line>
            <line>If he dislike it, let him to our sister,</line>
            <line>Whose mind and mine, I know, in that are one,</line>
            <line>Not to be over-ruled. Idle old man,</line>
            <line>That still would manage those authorities</line>
            <line>That he hath given away! Now, by my life,</line>
            <line>Old fools are babes again; and must be used</line>
            <line>With cheques as flatteries,--when they are seen abused.</line>
            <line>Remember what I tell you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OSWALD</speaker>
            <line>Well, madam.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GONERIL</speaker>
            <line>And let his knights have colder looks among you;</line>
            <line>What grows of it, no matter; advise your fellows so:</line>
            <line>I would breed from hence occasions, and I shall,</line>
            <line>That I may speak: I'll write straight to my sister,</line>
            <line>To hold my very course. Prepare for dinner.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-4">
      <title>SCENE IV.  A hall in the same.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter KENT, disguised</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KENT</speaker>
            <line>If but as well I other accents borrow,</line>
            <line>That can my speech defuse, my good intent</line>
            <line>May carry through itself to that full issue</line>
            <line>For which I razed my likeness. Now, banish'd Kent,</line>
            <line>If thou canst serve where thou dost stand condemn'd,</line>
            <line>So may it come, thy master, whom thou lovest,</line>
            <line>Shall find thee full of labours.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Horns within. Enter KING LEAR, Knights, and
Attendants</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Let me not stay a jot for dinner; go get it ready.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit an Attendant</stagedir>
            <line>How now! what art thou?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KENT</speaker>
            <line>A man, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>What dost thou profess? what wouldst thou with us?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KENT</speaker>
            <line>I do profess to be no less than I seem; to serve</line>
            <line>him truly that will put me in trust: to love him</line>
            <line>that is honest; to converse with him that is wise,</line>
            <line>and says little; to fear judgment; to fight when I</line>
            <line>cannot choose; and to eat no fish.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>What art thou?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KENT</speaker>
            <line>A very honest-hearted fellow, and as poor as the king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>If thou be as poor for a subject as he is for a</line>
            <line>king, thou art poor enough. What wouldst thou?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KENT</speaker>
            <line>Service.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Who wouldst thou serve?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KENT</speaker>
            <line>You.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Dost thou know me, fellow?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KENT</speaker>
            <line>No, sir; but you have that in your countenance</line>
            <line>which I would fain call master.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>What's that?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KENT</speaker>
            <line>Authority.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>What services canst thou do?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KENT</speaker>
            <line>I can keep honest counsel, ride, run, mar a curious</line>
            <line>tale in telling it, and deliver a plain message</line>
            <line>bluntly: that which ordinary men are fit for, I am</line>
            <line>qualified in; and the best of me is diligence.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>How old art thou?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KENT</speaker>
            <line>Not so young, sir, to love a woman for singing, nor</line>
            <line>so old to dote on her for any thing: I have years</line>
            <line>on my back forty eight.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Follow me; thou shalt serve me: if I like thee no</line>
            <line>worse after dinner, I will not part from thee yet.</line>
            <line>Dinner, ho, dinner! Where's my knave? my fool?</line>
            <line>Go you, and call my fool hither.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit an Attendant</stagedir>
            <stagedir>Enter OSWALD</stagedir>
            <line>You, you, sirrah, where's my daughter?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OSWALD</speaker>
            <line>So please you,--</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>What says the fellow there? Call the clotpoll back.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit a Knight</stagedir>
            <line>Where's my fool, ho? I think the world's asleep.</line>
            <stagedir>Re-enter Knight</stagedir>
            <line>How now! where's that mongrel?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Knight</speaker>
            <line>He says, my lord, your daughter is not well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Why came not the slave back to me when I called him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Knight</speaker>
            <line>Sir, he answered me in the roundest manner, he would</line>
            <line>not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>He would not!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Knight</speaker>
            <line>My lord, I know not what the matter is; but, to my</line>
            <line>judgment, your highness is not entertained with that</line>
            <line>ceremonious affection as you were wont; there's a</line>
            <line>great abatement of kindness appears as well in the</line>
            <line>general dependants as in the duke himself also and</line>
            <line>your daughter.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Ha! sayest thou so?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Knight</speaker>
            <line>I beseech you, pardon me, my lord, if I be mistaken;</line>
            <line>for my duty cannot be silent when I think your</line>
            <line>highness wronged.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Thou but rememberest me of mine own conception: I</line>
            <line>have perceived a most faint neglect of late; which I</line>
            <line>have rather blamed as mine own jealous curiosity</line>
            <line>than as a very pretence and purpose of unkindness:</line>
            <line>I will look further into't. But where's my fool? I</line>
            <line>have not seen him this two days.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Knight</speaker>
            <line>Since my young lady's going into France, sir, the</line>
            <line>fool hath much pined away.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>No more of that; I have noted it well. Go you, and</line>
            <line>tell my daughter I would speak with her.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit an Attendant</stagedir>
            <line>Go you, call hither my fool.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit an Attendant</stagedir>
            <stagedir>Re-enter OSWALD</stagedir>
            <line>O, you sir, you, come you hither, sir: who am I,</line>
            <line>sir?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OSWALD</speaker>
            <line>My lady's father.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>'My lady's father'! my lord's knave: your</line>
            <line>whoreson dog! you slave! you cur!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OSWALD</speaker>
            <line>I am none of these, my lord; I beseech your pardon.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Do you bandy looks with me, you rascal?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Striking him</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OSWALD</speaker>
            <line>I'll not be struck, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KENT</speaker>
            <line>Nor tripped neither, you base football player.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Tripping up his heels</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>I thank thee, fellow; thou servest me, and I'll</line>
            <line>love thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KENT</speaker>
            <line>Come, sir, arise, away! I'll teach you differences:</line>
            <line>away, away! if you will measure your lubber's</line>
            <line>length again, tarry: but away! go to; have you</line>
            <line>wisdom? so.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Pushes OSWALD out</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Now, my friendly knave, I thank thee: there's</line>
            <line>earnest of thy service.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Giving KENT money</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Enter Fool</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fool</speaker>
            <line>Let me hire him too: here's my coxcomb.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Offering KENT his cap</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>How now, my pretty knave! how dost thou?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fool</speaker>
            <line>Sirrah, you were best take my coxcomb.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KENT</speaker>
            <line>Why, fool?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fool</speaker>
            <line>Why, for taking one's part that's out of favour:</line>
            <line>nay, an thou canst not smile as the wind sits,</line>
            <line>thou'lt catch cold shortly: there, take my coxcomb:</line>
            <line>why, this fellow has banished two on's daughters,</line>
            <line>and did the third a blessing against his will; if</line>
            <line>thou follow him, thou must needs wear my coxcomb.</line>
            <line>How now, nuncle! Would I had two coxcombs and two daughters!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Why, my boy?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fool</speaker>
            <line>If I gave them all my living, I'ld keep my coxcombs</line>
            <line>myself. There's mine; beg another of thy daughters.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Take heed, sirrah; the whip.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fool</speaker>
            <line>Truth's a dog must to kennel; he must be whipped</line>
            <line>out, when Lady the brach may stand by the fire and stink.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>A pestilent gall to me!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fool</speaker>
            <line>Sirrah, I'll teach thee a speech.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Do.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fool</speaker>
            <line>Mark it, nuncle:</line>
            <line>Have more than thou showest,</line>
            <line>Speak less than thou knowest,</line>
            <line>Lend less than thou owest,</line>
            <line>Ride more than thou goest,</line>
            <line>Learn more than thou trowest,</line>
            <line>Set less than thou throwest;</line>
            <line>Leave thy drink and thy whore,</line>
            <line>And keep in-a-door,</line>
            <line>And thou shalt have more</line>
            <line>Than two tens to a score.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KENT</speaker>
            <line>This is nothing, fool.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fool</speaker>
            <line>Then 'tis like the breath of an unfee'd lawyer; you</line>
            <line>gave me nothing for't. Can you make no use of</line>
            <line>nothing, nuncle?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Why, no, boy; nothing can be made out of nothing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fool</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>To KENT</stagedir>  Prithee, tell him, so much the rent of</line>
            <line>his land comes to: he will not believe a fool.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>A bitter fool!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fool</speaker>
            <line>Dost thou know the difference, my boy, between a</line>
            <line>bitter fool and a sweet fool?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>No, lad; teach me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fool</speaker>
            <line>That lord that counsell'd thee</line>
            <line>To give away thy land,</line>
            <line>Come place him here by me,</line>
            <line>Do thou for him stand:</line>
            <line>The sweet and bitter fool</line>
            <line>Will presently appear;</line>
            <line>The one in motley here,</line>
            <line>The other found out there.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Dost thou call me fool, boy?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fool</speaker>
            <line>All thy other titles thou hast given away; that</line>
            <line>thou wast born with.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KENT</speaker>
            <line>This is not altogether fool, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fool</speaker>
            <line>No, faith, lords and great men will not let me; if</line>
            <line>I had a monopoly out, they would have part on't:</line>
            <line>and ladies too, they will not let me have all fool</line>
            <line>to myself; they'll be snatching. Give me an egg,</line>
            <line>nuncle, and I'll give thee two crowns.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>What two crowns shall they be?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fool</speaker>
            <line>Why, after I have cut the egg i' the middle, and eat</line>
            <line>up the meat, the two crowns of the egg. When thou</line>
            <line>clovest thy crown i' the middle, and gavest away</line>
            <line>both parts, thou borest thy ass on thy back o'er</line>
            <line>the dirt: thou hadst little wit in thy bald crown,</line>
            <line>when thou gavest thy golden one away. If I speak</line>
            <line>like myself in this, let him be whipped that first</line>
            <line>finds it so.</line>
            <stagedir>Singing</stagedir>
            <line>Fools had ne'er less wit in a year;</line>
            <line>For wise men are grown foppish,</line>
            <line>They know not how their wits to wear,</line>
            <line>Their manners are so apish.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>When were you wont to be so full of songs, sirrah?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fool</speaker>
            <line>I have used it, nuncle, ever since thou madest thy</line>
            <line>daughters thy mothers: for when thou gavest them</line>
            <line>the rod, and put'st down thine own breeches,</line>
            <stagedir>Singing</stagedir>
            <line>Then they for sudden joy did weep,</line>
            <line>And I for sorrow sung,</line>
            <line>That such a king should play bo-peep,</line>
            <line>And go the fools among.</line>
            <line>Prithee, nuncle, keep a schoolmaster that can teach</line>
            <line>thy fool to lie: I would fain learn to lie.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>An you lie, sirrah, we'll have you whipped.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fool</speaker>
            <line>I marvel what kin thou and thy daughters are:</line>
            <line>they'll have me whipped for speaking true, thou'lt</line>
            <line>have me whipped for lying; and sometimes I am</line>
            <line>whipped for holding my peace. I had rather be any</line>
            <line>kind o' thing than a fool: and yet I would not be</line>
            <line>thee, nuncle; thou hast pared thy wit o' both sides,</line>
            <line>and left nothing i' the middle: here comes one o'</line>
            <line>the parings.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter GONERIL</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>How now, daughter! what makes that frontlet on?</line>
            <line>Methinks you are too much of late i' the frown.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fool</speaker>
            <line>Thou wast a pretty fellow when thou hadst no need to</line>
            <line>care for her frowning; now thou art an O without a</line>
            <line>figure: I am better than thou art now; I am a fool,</line>
            <line>thou art nothing.</line>
            <stagedir>To GONERIL</stagedir>
            <line>Yes, forsooth, I will hold my tongue; so your face</line>
            <line>bids me, though you say nothing. Mum, mum,</line>
            <line>He that keeps nor crust nor crum,</line>
            <line>Weary of all, shall want some.</line>
            <stagedir>Pointing to KING LEAR</stagedir>
            <line>That's a shealed peascod.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GONERIL</speaker>
            <line>Not only, sir, this your all-licensed fool,</line>
            <line>But other of your insolent retinue</line>
            <line>Do hourly carp and quarrel; breaking forth</line>
            <line>In rank and not-to-be endured riots. Sir,</line>
            <line>I had thought, by making this well known unto you,</line>
            <line>To have found a safe redress; but now grow fearful,</line>
            <line>By what yourself too late have spoke and done.</line>
            <line>That you protect this course, and put it on</line>
            <line>By your allowance; which if you should, the fault</line>
            <line>Would not 'scape censure, nor the redresses sleep,</line>
            <line>Which, in the tender of a wholesome weal,</line>
            <line>Might in their working do you that offence,</line>
            <line>Which else were shame, that then necessity</line>
            <line>Will call discreet proceeding.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fool</speaker>
            <line>For, you trow, nuncle,</line>
            <line>The hedge-sparrow fed the cuckoo so long,</line>
            <line>That it's had it head bit off by it young.</line>
            <line>So, out went the candle, and we were left darkling.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Are you our daughter?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GONERIL</speaker>
            <line>Come, sir,</line>
            <line>I would you would make use of that good wisdom,</line>
            <line>Whereof I know you are fraught; and put away</line>
            <line>These dispositions, that of late transform you</line>
            <line>From what you rightly are.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fool</speaker>
            <line>May not an ass know when the cart</line>
            <line>draws the horse? Whoop, Jug! I love thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Doth any here know me? This is not Lear:</line>
            <line>Doth Lear walk thus? speak thus? Where are his eyes?</line>
            <line>Either his notion weakens, his discernings</line>
            <line>Are lethargied--Ha! waking? 'tis not so.</line>
            <line>Who is it that can tell me who I am?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fool</speaker>
            <line>Lear's shadow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>I would learn that; for, by the</line>
            <line>marks of sovereignty, knowledge, and reason,</line>
            <line>I should be false persuaded I had daughters.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fool</speaker>
            <line>Which they will make an obedient father.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Your name, fair gentlewoman?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GONERIL</speaker>
            <line>This admiration, sir, is much o' the savour</line>
            <line>Of other your new pranks. I do beseech you</line>
            <line>To understand my purposes aright:</line>
            <line>As you are old and reverend, you should be wise.</line>
            <line>Here do you keep a hundred knights and squires;</line>
            <line>Men so disorder'd, so debosh'd and bold,</line>
            <line>That this our court, infected with their manners,</line>
            <line>Shows like a riotous inn: epicurism and lust</line>
            <line>Make it more like a tavern or a brothel</line>
            <line>Than a graced palace. The shame itself doth speak</line>
            <line>For instant remedy: be then desired</line>
            <line>By her, that else will take the thing she begs,</line>
            <line>A little to disquantity your train;</line>
            <line>And the remainder, that shall still depend,</line>
            <line>To be such men as may besort your age,</line>
            <line>And know themselves and you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Darkness and devils!</line>
            <line>Saddle my horses; call my train together:</line>
            <line>Degenerate bastard! I'll not trouble thee.</line>
            <line>Yet have I left a daughter.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GONERIL</speaker>
            <line>You strike my people; and your disorder'd rabble</line>
            <line>Make servants of their betters.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter ALBANY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Woe, that too late repents,--</line>
            <stagedir>To ALBANY</stagedir>
            <line>O, sir, are you come?</line>
            <line>Is it your will? Speak, sir. Prepare my horses.</line>
            <line>Ingratitude, thou marble-hearted fiend,</line>
            <line>More hideous when thou show'st thee in a child</line>
            <line>Than the sea-monster!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALBANY</speaker>
            <line>Pray, sir, be patient.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>To GONERIL</stagedir>  Detested kite! thou liest.</line>
            <line>My train are men of choice and rarest parts,</line>
            <line>That all particulars of duty know,</line>
            <line>And in the most exact regard support</line>
            <line>The worships of their name. O most small fault,</line>
            <line>How ugly didst thou in Cordelia show!</line>
            <line>That, like an engine, wrench'd my frame of nature</line>
            <line>From the fix'd place; drew from heart all love,</line>
            <line>And added to the gall. O Lear, Lear, Lear!</line>
            <line>Beat at this gate, that let thy folly in,</line>
            <stagedir>Striking his head</stagedir>
            <line>And thy dear judgment out! Go, go, my people.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALBANY</speaker>
            <line>My lord, I am guiltless, as I am ignorant</line>
            <line>Of what hath moved you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>It may be so, my lord.</line>
            <line>Hear, nature, hear; dear goddess, hear!</line>
            <line>Suspend thy purpose, if thou didst intend</line>
            <line>To make this creature fruitful!</line>
            <line>Into her womb convey sterility!</line>
            <line>Dry up in her the organs of increase;</line>
            <line>And from her derogate body never spring</line>
            <line>A babe to honour her! If she must teem,</line>
            <line>Create her child of spleen; that it may live,</line>
            <line>And be a thwart disnatured torment to her!</line>
            <line>Let it stamp wrinkles in her brow of youth;</line>
            <line>With cadent tears fret channels in her cheeks;</line>
            <line>Turn all her mother's pains and benefits</line>
            <line>To laughter and contempt; that she may feel</line>
            <line>How sharper than a serpent's tooth it is</line>
            <line>To have a thankless child! Away, away!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALBANY</speaker>
            <line>Now, gods that we adore, whereof comes this?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GONERIL</speaker>
            <line>Never afflict yourself to know the cause;</line>
            <line>But let his disposition have that scope</line>
            <line>That dotage gives it.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter KING LEAR</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>What, fifty of my followers at a clap!</line>
            <line>Within a fortnight!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALBANY</speaker>
            <line>What's the matter, sir?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>I'll tell thee:</line>
            <stagedir>To GONERIL</stagedir>
            <line>Life and death! I am ashamed</line>
            <line>That thou hast power to shake my manhood thus;</line>
            <line>That these hot tears, which break from me perforce,</line>
            <line>Should make thee worth them. Blasts and fogs upon thee!</line>
            <line>The untented woundings of a father's curse</line>
            <line>Pierce every sense about thee! Old fond eyes,</line>
            <line>Beweep this cause again, I'll pluck ye out,</line>
            <line>And cast you, with the waters that you lose,</line>
            <line>To temper clay. Yea, it is come to this?</line>
            <line>Let is be so: yet have I left a daughter,</line>
            <line>Who, I am sure, is kind and comfortable:</line>
            <line>When she shall hear this of thee, with her nails</line>
            <line>She'll flay thy wolvish visage. Thou shalt find</line>
            <line>That I'll resume the shape which thou dost think</line>
            <line>I have cast off for ever: thou shalt,</line>
            <line>I warrant thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt KING LEAR, KENT, and Attendants</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GONERIL</speaker>
            <line>Do you mark that, my lord?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALBANY</speaker>
            <line>I cannot be so partial, Goneril,</line>
            <line>To the great love I bear you,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GONERIL</speaker>
            <line>Pray you, content. What, Oswald, ho!</line>
            <stagedir>To the Fool</stagedir>
            <line>You, sir, more knave than fool, after your master.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fool</speaker>
            <line>Nuncle Lear, nuncle Lear, tarry and take the fool</line>
            <line>with thee.</line>
            <line>A fox, when one has caught her,</line>
            <line>And such a daughter,</line>
            <line>Should sure to the slaughter,</line>
            <line>If my cap would buy a halter:</line>
            <line>So the fool follows after.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GONERIL</speaker>
            <line>This man hath had good counsel:--a hundred knights!</line>
            <line>'Tis politic and safe to let him keep</line>
            <line>At point a hundred knights: yes, that, on every dream,</line>
            <line>Each buzz, each fancy, each complaint, dislike,</line>
            <line>He may enguard his dotage with their powers,</line>
            <line>And hold our lives in mercy. Oswald, I say!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALBANY</speaker>
            <line>Well, you may fear too far.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GONERIL</speaker>
            <line>Safer than trust too far:</line>
            <line>Let me still take away the harms I fear,</line>
            <line>Not fear still to be taken: I know his heart.</line>
            <line>What he hath utter'd I have writ my sister</line>
            <line>If she sustain him and his hundred knights</line>
            <line>When I have show'd the unfitness,--</line>
            <stagedir>Re-enter OSWALD</stagedir>
            <line>How now, Oswald!</line>
            <line>What, have you writ that letter to my sister?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OSWALD</speaker>
            <line>Yes, madam.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GONERIL</speaker>
            <line>Take you some company, and away to horse:</line>
            <line>Inform her full of my particular fear;</line>
            <line>And thereto add such reasons of your own</line>
            <line>As may compact it more. Get you gone;</line>
            <line>And hasten your return.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit OSWALD</stagedir>
            <line>No, no, my lord,</line>
            <line>This milky gentleness and course of yours</line>
            <line>Though I condemn not, yet, under pardon,</line>
            <line>You are much more attask'd for want of wisdom</line>
            <line>Than praised for harmful mildness.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALBANY</speaker>
            <line>How far your eyes may pierce I can not tell:</line>
            <line>Striving to better, oft we mar what's well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GONERIL</speaker>
            <line>Nay, then--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALBANY</speaker>
            <line>Well, well; the event.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-5">
      <title>SCENE V.  Court before the same.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter KING LEAR, KENT, and Fool</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Go you before to Gloucester with these letters.</line>
            <line>Acquaint my daughter no further with any thing you</line>
            <line>know than comes from her demand out of the letter.</line>
            <line>If your diligence be not speedy, I shall be there afore you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KENT</speaker>
            <line>I will not sleep, my lord, till I have delivered</line>
            <line>your letter.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fool</speaker>
            <line>If a man's brains were in's heels, were't not in</line>
            <line>danger of kibes?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Ay, boy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fool</speaker>
            <line>Then, I prithee, be merry; thy wit shall ne'er go</line>
            <line>slip-shod.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Ha, ha, ha!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fool</speaker>
            <line>Shalt see thy other daughter will use thee kindly;</line>
            <line>for though she's as like this as a crab's like an</line>
            <line>apple, yet I can tell what I can tell.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Why, what canst thou tell, my boy?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fool</speaker>
            <line>She will taste as like this as a crab does to a</line>
            <line>crab. Thou canst tell why one's nose stands i'</line>
            <line>the middle on's face?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>No.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fool</speaker>
            <line>Why, to keep one's eyes of either side's nose; that</line>
            <line>what a man cannot smell out, he may spy into.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>I did her wrong--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fool</speaker>
            <line>Canst tell how an oyster makes his shell?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>No.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fool</speaker>
            <line>Nor I neither; but I can tell why a snail has a house.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Why?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fool</speaker>
            <line>Why, to put his head in; not to give it away to his</line>
            <line>daughters, and leave his horns without a case.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>I will forget my nature. So kind a father! Be my</line>
            <line>horses ready?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fool</speaker>
            <line>Thy asses are gone about 'em. The reason why the</line>
            <line>seven stars are no more than seven is a pretty reason.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Because they are not eight?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fool</speaker>
            <line>Yes, indeed: thou wouldst make a good fool.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>To take 't again perforce! Monster ingratitude!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fool</speaker>
            <line>If thou wert my fool, nuncle, I'ld have thee beaten</line>
            <line>for being old before thy time.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>How's that?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fool</speaker>
            <line>Thou shouldst not have been old till thou hadst</line>
            <line>been wise.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>O, let me not be mad, not mad, sweet heaven</line>
            <line>Keep me in temper: I would not be mad!</line>
            <stagedir>Enter Gentleman</stagedir>
            <line>How now! are the horses ready?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Gentleman</speaker>
            <line>Ready, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Come, boy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fool</speaker>
            <line>She that's a maid now, and laughs at my departure,</line>
            <line>Shall not be a maid long, unless things be cut shorter.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>