<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:shakespear:dtd:act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-3">
   <title>ACT III</title>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  A heath.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Storm still. Enter KENT and a Gentleman, meeting</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KENT</speaker>
            <line>Who's there, besides foul weather?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Gentleman</speaker>
            <line>One minded like the weather, most unquietly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KENT</speaker>
            <line>I know you. Where's the king?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Gentleman</speaker>
            <line>Contending with the fretful element:</line>
            <line>Bids the winds blow the earth into the sea,</line>
            <line>Or swell the curled water 'bove the main,</line>
            <line>That things might change or cease; tears his white hair,</line>
            <line>Which the impetuous blasts, with eyeless rage,</line>
            <line>Catch in their fury, and make nothing of;</line>
            <line>Strives in his little world of man to out-scorn</line>
            <line>The to-and-fro-conflicting wind and rain.</line>
            <line>This night, wherein the cub-drawn bear would couch,</line>
            <line>The lion and the belly-pinched wolf</line>
            <line>Keep their fur dry, unbonneted he runs,</line>
            <line>And bids what will take all.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KENT</speaker>
            <line>But who is with him?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Gentleman</speaker>
            <line>None but the fool; who labours to out-jest</line>
            <line>His heart-struck injuries.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KENT</speaker>
            <line>Sir, I do know you;</line>
            <line>And dare, upon the warrant of my note,</line>
            <line>Commend a dear thing to you. There is division,</line>
            <line>Although as yet the face of it be cover'd</line>
            <line>With mutual cunning, 'twixt Albany and Cornwall;</line>
            <line>Who have--as who have not, that their great stars</line>
            <line>Throned and set high?--servants, who seem no less,</line>
            <line>Which are to France the spies and speculations</line>
            <line>Intelligent of our state; what hath been seen,</line>
            <line>Either in snuffs and packings of the dukes,</line>
            <line>Or the hard rein which both of them have borne</line>
            <line>Against the old kind king; or something deeper,</line>
            <line>Whereof perchance these are but furnishings;</line>
            <line>But, true it is, from France there comes a power</line>
            <line>Into this scatter'd kingdom; who already,</line>
            <line>Wise in our negligence, have secret feet</line>
            <line>In some of our best ports, and are at point</line>
            <line>To show their open banner. Now to you:</line>
            <line>If on my credit you dare build so far</line>
            <line>To make your speed to Dover, you shall find</line>
            <line>Some that will thank you, making just report</line>
            <line>Of how unnatural and bemadding sorrow</line>
            <line>The king hath cause to plain.</line>
            <line>I am a gentleman of blood and breeding;</line>
            <line>And, from some knowledge and assurance, offer</line>
            <line>This office to you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Gentleman</speaker>
            <line>I will talk further with you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KENT</speaker>
            <line>No, do not.</line>
            <line>For confirmation that I am much more</line>
            <line>Than my out-wall, open this purse, and take</line>
            <line>What it contains. If you shall see Cordelia,--</line>
            <line>As fear not but you shall,--show her this ring;</line>
            <line>And she will tell you who your fellow is</line>
            <line>That yet you do not know. Fie on this storm!</line>
            <line>I will go seek the king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Gentleman</speaker>
            <line>Give me your hand: have you no more to say?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KENT</speaker>
            <line>Few words, but, to effect, more than all yet;</line>
            <line>That, when we have found the king,--in which your pain</line>
            <line>That way, I'll this,--he that first lights on him</line>
            <line>Holla the other.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt severally</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  Another part of the heath. Storm still.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter KING LEAR and Fool</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Blow, winds, and crack your cheeks! rage! blow!</line>
            <line>You cataracts and hurricanoes, spout</line>
            <line>Till you have drench'd our steeples, drown'd the cocks!</line>
            <line>You sulphurous and thought-executing fires,</line>
            <line>Vaunt-couriers to oak-cleaving thunderbolts,</line>
            <line>Singe my white head! And thou, all-shaking thunder,</line>
            <line>Smite flat the thick rotundity o' the world!</line>
            <line>Crack nature's moulds, an germens spill at once,</line>
            <line>That make ingrateful man!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fool</speaker>
            <line>O nuncle, court holy-water in a dry</line>
            <line>house is better than this rain-water out o' door.</line>
            <line>Good nuncle, in, and ask thy daughters' blessing:</line>
            <line>here's a night pities neither wise man nor fool.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Rumble thy bellyful! Spit, fire! spout, rain!</line>
            <line>Nor rain, wind, thunder, fire, are my daughters:</line>
            <line>I tax not you, you elements, with unkindness;</line>
            <line>I never gave you kingdom, call'd you children,</line>
            <line>You owe me no subscription: then let fall</line>
            <line>Your horrible pleasure: here I stand, your slave,</line>
            <line>A poor, infirm, weak, and despised old man:</line>
            <line>But yet I call you servile ministers,</line>
            <line>That have with two pernicious daughters join'd</line>
            <line>Your high engender'd battles 'gainst a head</line>
            <line>So old and white as this. O! O! 'tis foul!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fool</speaker>
            <line>He that has a house to put's head in has a good</line>
            <line>head-piece.</line>
            <line>The cod-piece that will house</line>
            <line>Before the head has any,</line>
            <line>The head and he shall louse;</line>
            <line>So beggars marry many.</line>
            <line>The man that makes his toe</line>
            <line>What he his heart should make</line>
            <line>Shall of a corn cry woe,</line>
            <line>And turn his sleep to wake.</line>
            <line>For there was never yet fair woman but she made</line>
            <line>mouths in a glass.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>No, I will be the pattern of all patience;</line>
            <line>I will say nothing.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter KENT</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KENT</speaker>
            <line>Who's there?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fool</speaker>
            <line>Marry, here's grace and a cod-piece; that's a wise</line>
            <line>man and a fool.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KENT</speaker>
            <line>Alas, sir, are you here? things that love night</line>
            <line>Love not such nights as these; the wrathful skies</line>
            <line>Gallow the very wanderers of the dark,</line>
            <line>And make them keep their caves: since I was man,</line>
            <line>Such sheets of fire, such bursts of horrid thunder,</line>
            <line>Such groans of roaring wind and rain, I never</line>
            <line>Remember to have heard: man's nature cannot carry</line>
            <line>The affliction nor the fear.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Let the great gods,</line>
            <line>That keep this dreadful pother o'er our heads,</line>
            <line>Find out their enemies now. Tremble, thou wretch,</line>
            <line>That hast within thee undivulged crimes,</line>
            <line>Unwhipp'd of justice: hide thee, thou bloody hand;</line>
            <line>Thou perjured, and thou simular man of virtue</line>
            <line>That art incestuous: caitiff, to pieces shake,</line>
            <line>That under covert and convenient seeming</line>
            <line>Hast practised on man's life: close pent-up guilts,</line>
            <line>Rive your concealing continents, and cry</line>
            <line>These dreadful summoners grace. I am a man</line>
            <line>More sinn'd against than sinning.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KENT</speaker>
            <line>Alack, bare-headed!</line>
            <line>Gracious my lord, hard by here is a hovel;</line>
            <line>Some friendship will it lend you 'gainst the tempest:</line>
            <line>Repose you there; while I to this hard house--</line>
            <line>More harder than the stones whereof 'tis raised;</line>
            <line>Which even but now, demanding after you,</line>
            <line>Denied me to come in--return, and force</line>
            <line>Their scanted courtesy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>My wits begin to turn.</line>
            <line>Come on, my boy: how dost, my boy? art cold?</line>
            <line>I am cold myself. Where is this straw, my fellow?</line>
            <line>The art of our necessities is strange,</line>
            <line>That can make vile things precious. Come,</line>
            <line>your hovel.</line>
            <line>Poor fool and knave, I have one part in my heart</line>
            <line>That's sorry yet for thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fool</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Singing</stagedir>
            </line>
            <line>He that has and a little tiny wit--</line>
            <line>With hey, ho, the wind and the rain,--</line>
            <line>Must make content with his fortunes fit,</line>
            <line>For the rain it raineth every day.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>True, my good boy. Come, bring us to this hovel.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt KING LEAR and KENT</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fool</speaker>
            <line>This is a brave night to cool a courtezan.</line>
            <line>I'll speak a prophecy ere I go:</line>
            <line>When priests are more in word than matter;</line>
            <line>When brewers mar their malt with water;</line>
            <line>When nobles are their tailors' tutors;</line>
            <line>No heretics burn'd, but wenches' suitors;</line>
            <line>When every case in law is right;</line>
            <line>No squire in debt, nor no poor knight;</line>
            <line>When slanders do not live in tongues;</line>
            <line>Nor cutpurses come not to throngs;</line>
            <line>When usurers tell their gold i' the field;</line>
            <line>And bawds and whores do churches build;</line>
            <line>Then shall the realm of Albion</line>
            <line>Come to great confusion:</line>
            <line>Then comes the time, who lives to see't,</line>
            <line>That going shall be used with feet.</line>
            <line>This prophecy Merlin shall make; for I live before his time.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  Gloucester's castle.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter GLOUCESTER and EDMUND</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Alack, alack, Edmund, I like not this unnatural</line>
            <line>dealing. When I desire their leave that I might</line>
            <line>pity him, they took from me the use of mine own</line>
            <line>house; charged me, on pain of their perpetual</line>
            <line>displeasure, neither to speak of him, entreat for</line>
            <line>him, nor any way sustain him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDMUND</speaker>
            <line>Most savage and unnatural!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Go to; say you nothing. There's a division betwixt</line>
            <line>the dukes; and a worse matter than that: I have</line>
            <line>received a letter this night; 'tis dangerous to be</line>
            <line>spoken; I have locked the letter in my closet:</line>
            <line>these injuries the king now bears will be revenged</line>
            <line>home; there's part of a power already footed: we</line>
            <line>must incline to the king. I will seek him, and</line>
            <line>privily relieve him: go you and maintain talk with</line>
            <line>the duke, that my charity be not of him perceived:</line>
            <line>if he ask for me. I am ill, and gone to bed.</line>
            <line>Though I die for it, as no less is threatened me,</line>
            <line>the king my old master must be relieved. There is</line>
            <line>some strange thing toward, Edmund; pray you, be careful.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDMUND</speaker>
            <line>This courtesy, forbid thee, shall the duke</line>
            <line>Instantly know; and of that letter too:</line>
            <line>This seems a fair deserving, and must draw me</line>
            <line>That which my father loses; no less than all:</line>
            <line>The younger rises when the old doth fall.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-4">
      <title>SCENE IV.  The heath. Before a hovel.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter KING LEAR, KENT, and Fool</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KENT</speaker>
            <line>Here is the place, my lord; good my lord, enter:</line>
            <line>The tyranny of the open night's too rough</line>
            <line>For nature to endure.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Storm still</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Let me alone.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KENT</speaker>
            <line>Good my lord, enter here.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Wilt break my heart?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KENT</speaker>
            <line>I had rather break mine own. Good my lord, enter.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Thou think'st 'tis much that this contentious storm</line>
            <line>Invades us to the skin: so 'tis to thee;</line>
            <line>But where the greater malady is fix'd,</line>
            <line>The lesser is scarce felt. Thou'ldst shun a bear;</line>
            <line>But if thy flight lay toward the raging sea,</line>
            <line>Thou'ldst meet the bear i' the mouth. When the</line>
            <line>mind's free,</line>
            <line>The body's delicate: the tempest in my mind</line>
            <line>Doth from my senses take all feeling else</line>
            <line>Save what beats there. Filial ingratitude!</line>
            <line>Is it not as this mouth should tear this hand</line>
            <line>For lifting food to't? But I will punish home:</line>
            <line>No, I will weep no more. In such a night</line>
            <line>To shut me out! Pour on; I will endure.</line>
            <line>In such a night as this! O Regan, Goneril!</line>
            <line>Your old kind father, whose frank heart gave all,--</line>
            <line>O, that way madness lies; let me shun that;</line>
            <line>No more of that.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KENT</speaker>
            <line>Good my lord, enter here.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Prithee, go in thyself: seek thine own ease:</line>
            <line>This tempest will not give me leave to ponder</line>
            <line>On things would hurt me more. But I'll go in.</line>
            <stagedir>To the Fool</stagedir>
            <line>In, boy; go first. You houseless poverty,--</line>
            <line>Nay, get thee in. I'll pray, and then I'll sleep.</line>
            <stagedir>Fool goes in</stagedir>
            <line>Poor naked wretches, whereso'er you are,</line>
            <line>That bide the pelting of this pitiless storm,</line>
            <line>How shall your houseless heads and unfed sides,</line>
            <line>Your loop'd and window'd raggedness, defend you</line>
            <line>From seasons such as these? O, I have ta'en</line>
            <line>Too little care of this! Take physic, pomp;</line>
            <line>Expose thyself to feel what wretches feel,</line>
            <line>That thou mayst shake the superflux to them,</line>
            <line>And show the heavens more just.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDGAR</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Within</stagedir>  Fathom and half, fathom and half! Poor Tom!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>The Fool runs out from the hovel</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fool</speaker>
            <line>Come not in here, nuncle, here's a spirit</line>
            <line>Help me, help me!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KENT</speaker>
            <line>Give me thy hand. Who's there?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fool</speaker>
            <line>A spirit, a spirit: he says his name's poor Tom.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KENT</speaker>
            <line>What art thou that dost grumble there i' the straw?</line>
            <line>Come forth.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter EDGAR disguised as a mad man</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDGAR</speaker>
            <line>Away! the foul fiend follows me!</line>
            <line>Through the sharp hawthorn blows the cold wind.</line>
            <line>Hum! go to thy cold bed, and warm thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Hast thou given all to thy two daughters?</line>
            <line>And art thou come to this?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDGAR</speaker>
            <line>Who gives any thing to poor Tom? whom the foul</line>
            <line>fiend hath led through fire and through flame, and</line>
            <line>through ford and whirlipool e'er bog and quagmire;</line>
            <line>that hath laid knives under his pillow, and halters</line>
            <line>in his pew; set ratsbane by his porridge; made film</line>
            <line>proud of heart, to ride on a bay trotting-horse over</line>
            <line>four-inched bridges, to course his own shadow for a</line>
            <line>traitor. Bless thy five wits! Tom's a-cold,--O, do</line>
            <line>de, do de, do de. Bless thee from whirlwinds,</line>
            <line>star-blasting, and taking! Do poor Tom some</line>
            <line>charity, whom the foul fiend vexes: there could I</line>
            <line>have him now,--and there,--and there again, and there.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Storm still</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>What, have his daughters brought him to this pass?</line>
            <line>Couldst thou save nothing? Didst thou give them all?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fool</speaker>
            <line>Nay, he reserved a blanket, else we had been all shamed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Now, all the plagues that in the pendulous air</line>
            <line>Hang fated o'er men's faults light on thy daughters!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KENT</speaker>
            <line>He hath no daughters, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Death, traitor! nothing could have subdued nature</line>
            <line>To such a lowness but his unkind daughters.</line>
            <line>Is it the fashion, that discarded fathers</line>
            <line>Should have thus little mercy on their flesh?</line>
            <line>Judicious punishment! 'twas this flesh begot</line>
            <line>Those pelican daughters.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDGAR</speaker>
            <line>Pillicock sat on Pillicock-hill:</line>
            <line>Halloo, halloo, loo, loo!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fool</speaker>
            <line>This cold night will turn us all to fools and madmen.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDGAR</speaker>
            <line>Take heed o' the foul fiend: obey thy parents;</line>
            <line>keep thy word justly; swear not; commit not with</line>
            <line>man's sworn spouse; set not thy sweet heart on proud</line>
            <line>array. Tom's a-cold.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>What hast thou been?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDGAR</speaker>
            <line>A serving-man, proud in heart and mind; that curled</line>
            <line>my hair; wore gloves in my cap; served the lust of</line>
            <line>my mistress' heart, and did the act of darkness with</line>
            <line>her; swore as many oaths as I spake words, and</line>
            <line>broke them in the sweet face of heaven: one that</line>
            <line>slept in the contriving of lust, and waked to do it:</line>
            <line>wine loved I deeply, dice dearly: and in woman</line>
            <line>out-paramoured the Turk: false of heart, light of</line>
            <line>ear, bloody of hand; hog in sloth, fox in stealth,</line>
            <line>wolf in greediness, dog in madness, lion in prey.</line>
            <line>Let not the creaking of shoes nor the rustling of</line>
            <line>silks betray thy poor heart to woman: keep thy foot</line>
            <line>out of brothels, thy hand out of plackets, thy pen</line>
            <line>from lenders' books, and defy the foul fiend.</line>
            <line>Still through the hawthorn blows the cold wind:</line>
            <line>Says suum, mun, ha, no, nonny.</line>
            <line>Dolphin my boy, my boy, sessa! let him trot by.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Storm still</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Why, thou wert better in thy grave than to answer</line>
            <line>with thy uncovered body this extremity of the skies.</line>
            <line>Is man no more than this? Consider him well. Thou</line>
            <line>owest the worm no silk, the beast no hide, the sheep</line>
            <line>no wool, the cat no perfume. Ha! here's three on</line>
            <line>'s are sophisticated! Thou art the thing itself:</line>
            <line>unaccommodated man is no more but such a poor bare,</line>
            <line>forked animal as thou art. Off, off, you lendings!</line>
            <line>come unbutton here.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Tearing off his clothes</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fool</speaker>
            <line>Prithee, nuncle, be contented; 'tis a naughty night</line>
            <line>to swim in. Now a little fire in a wild field were</line>
            <line>like an old lecher's heart; a small spark, all the</line>
            <line>rest on's body cold. Look, here comes a walking fire.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter GLOUCESTER, with a torch</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDGAR</speaker>
            <line>This is the foul fiend Flibbertigibbet: he begins</line>
            <line>at curfew, and walks till the first cock; he gives</line>
            <line>the web and the pin, squints the eye, and makes the</line>
            <line>hare-lip; mildews the white wheat, and hurts the</line>
            <line>poor creature of earth.</line>
            <line>S. Withold footed thrice the old;</line>
            <line>He met the night-mare, and her nine-fold;</line>
            <line>Bid her alight,</line>
            <line>And her troth plight,</line>
            <line>And, aroint thee, witch, aroint thee!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KENT</speaker>
            <line>How fares your grace?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>What's he?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KENT</speaker>
            <line>Who's there? What is't you seek?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>What are you there? Your names?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDGAR</speaker>
            <line>Poor Tom; that eats the swimming frog, the toad,</line>
            <line>the tadpole, the wall-newt and the water; that in</line>
            <line>the fury of his heart, when the foul fiend rages,</line>
            <line>eats cow-dung for sallets; swallows the old rat and</line>
            <line>the ditch-dog; drinks the green mantle of the</line>
            <line>standing pool; who is whipped from tithing to</line>
            <line>tithing, and stock- punished, and imprisoned; who</line>
            <line>hath had three suits to his back, six shirts to his</line>
            <line>body, horse to ride, and weapon to wear;</line>
            <line>But mice and rats, and such small deer,</line>
            <line>Have been Tom's food for seven long year.</line>
            <line>Beware my follower. Peace, Smulkin; peace, thou fiend!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>What, hath your grace no better company?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDGAR</speaker>
            <line>The prince of darkness is a gentleman:</line>
            <line>Modo he's call'd, and Mahu.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Our flesh and blood is grown so vile, my lord,</line>
            <line>That it doth hate what gets it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDGAR</speaker>
            <line>Poor Tom's a-cold.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Go in with me: my duty cannot suffer</line>
            <line>To obey in all your daughters' hard commands:</line>
            <line>Though their injunction be to bar my doors,</line>
            <line>And let this tyrannous night take hold upon you,</line>
            <line>Yet have I ventured to come seek you out,</line>
            <line>And bring you where both fire and food is ready.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>First let me talk with this philosopher.</line>
            <line>What is the cause of thunder?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KENT</speaker>
            <line>Good my lord, take his offer; go into the house.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>I'll talk a word with this same learned Theban.</line>
            <line>What is your study?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDGAR</speaker>
            <line>How to prevent the fiend, and to kill vermin.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Let me ask you one word in private.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KENT</speaker>
            <line>Importune him once more to go, my lord;</line>
            <line>His wits begin to unsettle.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Canst thou blame him?</line>
            <stagedir>Storm still</stagedir>
            <line>His daughters seek his death: ah, that good Kent!</line>
            <line>He said it would be thus, poor banish'd man!</line>
            <line>Thou say'st the king grows mad; I'll tell thee, friend,</line>
            <line>I am almost mad myself: I had a son,</line>
            <line>Now outlaw'd from my blood; he sought my life,</line>
            <line>But lately, very late: I loved him, friend;</line>
            <line>No father his son dearer: truth to tell thee,</line>
            <line>The grief hath crazed my wits. What a night's this!</line>
            <line>I do beseech your grace,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>O, cry your mercy, sir.</line>
            <line>Noble philosopher, your company.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDGAR</speaker>
            <line>Tom's a-cold.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>In, fellow, there, into the hovel: keep thee warm.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Come let's in all.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KENT</speaker>
            <line>This way, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>With him;</line>
            <line>I will keep still with my philosopher.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KENT</speaker>
            <line>Good my lord, soothe him; let him take the fellow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Take him you on.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KENT</speaker>
            <line>Sirrah, come on; go along with us.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Come, good Athenian.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>No words, no words: hush.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDGAR</speaker>
            <line>Child Rowland to the dark tower came,</line>
            <line>His word was still,--Fie, foh, and fum,</line>
            <line>I smell the blood of a British man.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-5">
      <title>SCENE V.  Gloucester's castle.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter CORNWALL and EDMUND</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORNWALL</speaker>
            <line>I will have my revenge ere I depart his house.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDMUND</speaker>
            <line>How, my lord, I may be censured, that nature thus</line>
            <line>gives way to loyalty, something fears me to think</line>
            <line>of.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORNWALL</speaker>
            <line>I now perceive, it was not altogether your</line>
            <line>brother's evil disposition made him seek his death;</line>
            <line>but a provoking merit, set a-work by a reprovable</line>
            <line>badness in himself.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDMUND</speaker>
            <line>How malicious is my fortune, that I must repent to</line>
            <line>be just! This is the letter he spoke of, which</line>
            <line>approves him an intelligent party to the advantages</line>
            <line>of France: O heavens! that this treason were not,</line>
            <line>or not I the detector!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORNWALL</speaker>
            <line>o with me to the duchess.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDMUND</speaker>
            <line>If the matter of this paper be certain, you have</line>
            <line>mighty business in hand.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORNWALL</speaker>
            <line>True or false, it hath made thee earl of</line>
            <line>Gloucester. Seek out where thy father is, that he</line>
            <line>may be ready for our apprehension.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDMUND</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  If I find him comforting the king, it will</line>
            <line>stuff his suspicion more fully.--I will persevere in</line>
            <line>my course of loyalty, though the conflict be sore</line>
            <line>between that and my blood.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORNWALL</speaker>
            <line>I will lay trust upon thee; and thou shalt find a</line>
            <line>dearer father in my love.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-6">
      <title>SCENE VI.  A chamber in a farmhouse adjoining the castle.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter GLOUCESTER, KING LEAR, KENT, Fool, and EDGAR</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Here is better than the open air; take it</line>
            <line>thankfully. I will piece out the comfort with what</line>
            <line>addition I can: I will not be long from you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KENT</speaker>
            <line>All the power of his wits have given way to his</line>
            <line>impatience: the gods reward your kindness!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit GLOUCESTER</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDGAR</speaker>
            <line>Frateretto calls me; and tells me</line>
            <line>Nero is an angler in the lake of darkness.</line>
            <line>Pray, innocent, and beware the foul fiend.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fool</speaker>
            <line>Prithee, nuncle, tell me whether a madman be a</line>
            <line>gentleman or a yeoman?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>A king, a king!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fool</speaker>
            <line>No, he's a yeoman that has a gentleman to his son;</line>
            <line>for he's a mad yeoman that sees his son a gentleman</line>
            <line>before him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>To have a thousand with red burning spits</line>
            <line>Come hissing in upon 'em,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDGAR</speaker>
            <line>The foul fiend bites my back.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fool</speaker>
            <line>He's mad that trusts in the tameness of a wolf, a</line>
            <line>horse's health, a boy's love, or a whore's oath.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>It shall be done; I will arraign them straight.</line>
            <stagedir>To EDGAR</stagedir>
            <line>Come, sit thou here, most learned justicer;</line>
            <stagedir>To the Fool</stagedir>
            <line>Thou, sapient sir, sit here. Now, you she foxes!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDGAR</speaker>
            <line>Look, where he stands and glares!</line>
            <line>Wantest thou eyes at trial, madam?</line>
            <line>Come o'er the bourn, Bessy, to me,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fool</speaker>
            <line>Her boat hath a leak,</line>
            <line>And she must not speak</line>
            <line>Why she dares not come over to thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDGAR</speaker>
            <line>The foul fiend haunts poor Tom in the voice of a</line>
            <line>nightingale. Hopdance cries in Tom's belly for two</line>
            <line>white herring. Croak not, black angel; I have no</line>
            <line>food for thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KENT</speaker>
            <line>How do you, sir? Stand you not so amazed:</line>
            <line>Will you lie down and rest upon the cushions?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>I'll see their trial first. Bring in the evidence.</line>
            <stagedir>To EDGAR</stagedir>
            <line>Thou robed man of justice, take thy place;</line>
            <stagedir>To the Fool</stagedir>
            <line>And thou, his yoke-fellow of equity,</line>
            <line>Bench by his side:</line>
            <stagedir>To KENT</stagedir>
            <line>you are o' the commission,</line>
            <line>Sit you too.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDGAR</speaker>
            <line>Let us deal justly.</line>
            <line>Sleepest or wakest thou, jolly shepherd?</line>
            <line>Thy sheep be in the corn;</line>
            <line>And for one blast of thy minikin mouth,</line>
            <line>Thy sheep shall take no harm.</line>
            <line>Pur! the cat is gray.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Arraign her first; 'tis Goneril. I here take my</line>
            <line>oath before this honourable assembly, she kicked the</line>
            <line>poor king her father.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fool</speaker>
            <line>Come hither, mistress. Is your name Goneril?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>She cannot deny it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fool</speaker>
            <line>Cry you mercy, I took you for a joint-stool.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>And here's another, whose warp'd looks proclaim</line>
            <line>What store her heart is made on. Stop her there!</line>
            <line>Arms, arms, sword, fire! Corruption in the place!</line>
            <line>False justicer, why hast thou let her 'scape?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDGAR</speaker>
            <line>Bless thy five wits!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KENT</speaker>
            <line>O pity! Sir, where is the patience now,</line>
            <line>That thou so oft have boasted to retain?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDGAR</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  My tears begin to take his part so much,</line>
            <line>They'll mar my counterfeiting.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>The little dogs and all, Tray, Blanch, and</line>
            <line>Sweet-heart, see, they bark at me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDGAR</speaker>
            <line>Tom will throw his head at them. Avaunt, you curs!</line>
            <line>Be thy mouth or black or white,</line>
            <line>Tooth that poisons if it bite;</line>
            <line>Mastiff, grey-hound, mongrel grim,</line>
            <line>Hound or spaniel, brach or lym,</line>
            <line>Or bobtail tike or trundle-tail,</line>
            <line>Tom will make them weep and wail:</line>
            <line>For, with throwing thus my head,</line>
            <line>Dogs leap the hatch, and all are fled.</line>
            <line>Do de, de, de. Sessa! Come, march to wakes and</line>
            <line>fairs and market-towns. Poor Tom, thy horn is dry.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Then let them anatomize Regan; see what breeds</line>
            <line>about her heart. Is there any cause in nature that</line>
            <line>makes these hard hearts?</line>
            <stagedir>To EDGAR</stagedir>
            <line>You, sir, I entertain for one of my hundred; only I</line>
            <line>do not like the fashion of your garments: you will</line>
            <line>say they are Persian attire: but let them be changed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KENT</speaker>
            <line>Now, good my lord, lie here and rest awhile.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING LEAR</speaker>
            <line>Make no noise, make no noise; draw the curtains:</line>
            <line>so, so, so. We'll go to supper i' he morning. So, so, so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fool</speaker>
            <line>And I'll go to bed at noon.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter GLOUCESTER</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Come hither, friend: where is the king my master?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KENT</speaker>
            <line>Here, sir; but trouble him not, his wits are gone.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Good friend, I prithee, take him in thy arms;</line>
            <line>I have o'erheard a plot of death upon him:</line>
            <line>There is a litter ready; lay him in 't,</line>
            <line>And drive towards Dover, friend, where thou shalt meet</line>
            <line>Both welcome and protection. Take up thy master:</line>
            <line>If thou shouldst dally half an hour, his life,</line>
            <line>With thine, and all that offer to defend him,</line>
            <line>Stand in assured loss: take up, take up;</line>
            <line>And follow me, that will to some provision</line>
            <line>Give thee quick conduct.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KENT</speaker>
            <line>Oppressed nature sleeps:</line>
            <line>This rest might yet have balm'd thy broken senses,</line>
            <line>Which, if convenience will not allow,</line>
            <line>Stand in hard cure.</line>
            <stagedir>To the Fool</stagedir>
            <line>Come, help to bear thy master;</line>
            <line>Thou must not stay behind.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Come, come, away.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt all but EDGAR</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDGAR</speaker>
            <line>When we our betters see bearing our woes,</line>
            <line>We scarcely think our miseries our foes.</line>
            <line>Who alone suffers suffers most i' the mind,</line>
            <line>Leaving free things and happy shows behind:</line>
            <line>But then the mind much sufferance doth o'er skip,</line>
            <line>When grief hath mates, and bearing fellowship.</line>
            <line>How light and portable my pain seems now,</line>
            <line>When that which makes me bend makes the king bow,</line>
            <line>He childed as I father'd! Tom, away!</line>
            <line>Mark the high noises; and thyself bewray,</line>
            <line>When false opinion, whose wrong thought defiles thee,</line>
            <line>In thy just proof, repeals and reconciles thee.</line>
            <line>What will hap more to-night, safe 'scape the king!</line>
            <line>Lurk, lurk.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-7">
      <title>SCENE VII.  Gloucester's castle.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter CORNWALL, REGAN, GONERIL, EDMUND, and Servants</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORNWALL</speaker>
            <line>Post speedily to my lord your husband; show him</line>
            <line>this letter: the army of France is landed. Seek</line>
            <line>out the villain Gloucester.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt some of the Servants</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>REGAN</speaker>
            <line>Hang him instantly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GONERIL</speaker>
            <line>Pluck out his eyes.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORNWALL</speaker>
            <line>Leave him to my displeasure. Edmund, keep you our</line>
            <line>sister company: the revenges we are bound to take</line>
            <line>upon your traitorous father are not fit for your</line>
            <line>beholding. Advise the duke, where you are going, to</line>
            <line>a most festinate preparation: we are bound to the</line>
            <line>like. Our posts shall be swift and intelligent</line>
            <line>betwixt us. Farewell, dear sister: farewell, my</line>
            <line>lord of Gloucester.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter OSWALD</stagedir>
            <line>How now! where's the king?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OSWALD</speaker>
            <line>My lord of Gloucester hath convey'd him hence:</line>
            <line>Some five or six and thirty of his knights,</line>
            <line>Hot questrists after him, met him at gate;</line>
            <line>Who, with some other of the lords dependants,</line>
            <line>Are gone with him towards Dover; where they boast</line>
            <line>To have well-armed friends.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORNWALL</speaker>
            <line>Get horses for your mistress.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GONERIL</speaker>
            <line>Farewell, sweet lord, and sister.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORNWALL</speaker>
            <line>Edmund, farewell.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt GONERIL, EDMUND, and OSWALD</stagedir>
            <line>Go seek the traitor Gloucester,</line>
            <line>Pinion him like a thief, bring him before us.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt other Servants</stagedir>
            <line>Though well we may not pass upon his life</line>
            <line>Without the form of justice, yet our power</line>
            <line>Shall do a courtesy to our wrath, which men</line>
            <line>May blame, but not control. Who's there? the traitor?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter GLOUCESTER, brought in by two or three</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>REGAN</speaker>
            <line>Ingrateful fox! 'tis he.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORNWALL</speaker>
            <line>Bind fast his corky arms.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>What mean your graces? Good my friends, consider</line>
            <line>You are my guests: do me no foul play, friends.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORNWALL</speaker>
            <line>Bind him, I say.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Servants bind him</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>REGAN</speaker>
            <line>Hard, hard. O filthy traitor!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Unmerciful lady as you are, I'm none.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORNWALL</speaker>
            <line>To this chair bind him. Villain, thou shalt find--</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>REGAN plucks his beard</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>By the kind gods, 'tis most ignobly done</line>
            <line>To pluck me by the beard.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>REGAN</speaker>
            <line>So white, and such a traitor!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Naughty lady,</line>
            <line>These hairs, which thou dost ravish from my chin,</line>
            <line>Will quicken, and accuse thee: I am your host:</line>
            <line>With robbers' hands my hospitable favours</line>
            <line>You should not ruffle thus. What will you do?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORNWALL</speaker>
            <line>Come, sir, what letters had you late from France?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>REGAN</speaker>
            <line>Be simple answerer, for we know the truth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORNWALL</speaker>
            <line>And what confederacy have you with the traitors</line>
            <line>Late footed in the kingdom?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>REGAN</speaker>
            <line>To whose hands have you sent the lunatic king? Speak.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>I have a letter guessingly set down,</line>
            <line>Which came from one that's of a neutral heart,</line>
            <line>And not from one opposed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORNWALL</speaker>
            <line>Cunning.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>REGAN</speaker>
            <line>And false.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORNWALL</speaker>
            <line>Where hast thou sent the king?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>To Dover.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>REGAN</speaker>
            <line>Wherefore to Dover? Wast thou not charged at peril--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORNWALL</speaker>
            <line>Wherefore to Dover? Let him first answer that.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>I am tied to the stake, and I must stand the course.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>REGAN</speaker>
            <line>Wherefore to Dover, sir?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Because I would not see thy cruel nails</line>
            <line>Pluck out his poor old eyes; nor thy fierce sister</line>
            <line>In his anointed flesh stick boarish fangs.</line>
            <line>The sea, with such a storm as his bare head</line>
            <line>In hell-black night endured, would have buoy'd up,</line>
            <line>And quench'd the stelled fires:</line>
            <line>Yet, poor old heart, he holp the heavens to rain.</line>
            <line>If wolves had at thy gate howl'd that stern time,</line>
            <line>Thou shouldst have said 'Good porter, turn the key,'</line>
            <line>All cruels else subscribed: but I shall see</line>
            <line>The winged vengeance overtake such children.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORNWALL</speaker>
            <line>See't shalt thou never. Fellows, hold the chair.</line>
            <line>Upon these eyes of thine I'll set my foot.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>He that will think to live till he be old,</line>
            <line>Give me some help! O cruel! O you gods!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>REGAN</speaker>
            <line>One side will mock another; the other too.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORNWALL</speaker>
            <line>If you see vengeance,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Servant</speaker>
            <line>Hold your hand, my lord:</line>
            <line>I have served you ever since I was a child;</line>
            <line>But better service have I never done you</line>
            <line>Than now to bid you hold.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>REGAN</speaker>
            <line>How now, you dog!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Servant</speaker>
            <line>If you did wear a beard upon your chin,</line>
            <line>I'd shake it on this quarrel. What do you mean?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORNWALL</speaker>
            <line>My villain!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>They draw and fight</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Servant</speaker>
            <line>Nay, then, come on, and take the chance of anger.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>REGAN</speaker>
            <line>Give me thy sword. A peasant stand up thus!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Takes a sword, and runs at him behind</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Servant</speaker>
            <line>O, I am slain! My lord, you have one eye left</line>
            <line>To see some mischief on him. O!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Dies</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORNWALL</speaker>
            <line>Lest it see more, prevent it. Out, vile jelly!</line>
            <line>Where is thy lustre now?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>All dark and comfortless. Where's my son Edmund?</line>
            <line>Edmund, enkindle all the sparks of nature,</line>
            <line>To quit this horrid act.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>REGAN</speaker>
            <line>Out, treacherous villain!</line>
            <line>Thou call'st on him that hates thee: it was he</line>
            <line>That made the overture of thy treasons to us;</line>
            <line>Who is too good to pity thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>O my follies! then Edgar was abused.</line>
            <line>Kind gods, forgive me that, and prosper him!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>REGAN</speaker>
            <line>Go thrust him out at gates, and let him smell</line>
            <line>His way to Dover.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit one with GLOUCESTER</stagedir>
            <line>How is't, my lord? how look you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORNWALL</speaker>
            <line>I have received a hurt: follow me, lady.</line>
            <line>Turn out that eyeless villain; throw this slave</line>
            <line>Upon the dunghill. Regan, I bleed apace:</line>
            <line>Untimely comes this hurt: give me your arm.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit CORNWALL, led by REGAN</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Servant</speaker>
            <line>I'll never care what wickedness I do,</line>
            <line>If this man come to good.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Servant</speaker>
            <line>If she live long,</line>
            <line>And in the end meet the old course of death,</line>
            <line>Women will all turn monsters.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Servant</speaker>
            <line>Let's follow the old earl, and get the Bedlam</line>
            <line>To lead him where he would: his roguish madness</line>
            <line>Allows itself to any thing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Servant</speaker>
            <line>Go thou: I'll fetch some flax and whites of eggs</line>
            <line>To apply to his bleeding face. Now, heaven help him!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt severally</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>