<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:concept" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="conceptId">
 <title>Data Collection Processing Phase</title>
 <shortdesc>Overview of map-driven-processing data collection phase </shortdesc>
  <prolog>
    <metadata>
      <keywords>
        <indexterm>map-driven processing<indexterm>data
          collection</indexterm></indexterm>
        <indexterm>data collection<indexterm>overview</indexterm></indexterm>
        <indexterm></indexterm>
      </keywords>
    </metadata>
  </prolog>
 <conbody>
    <p>The data collection process can be extended in several
      ways:<indexterm>extension points<indexterm>data
      collection</indexterm></indexterm><ul
      id="ul_ifb_52d_rh">
      <li>You can extend the default enumeration data set to add or remove
        things you do or don't want to number by adding templates in the mode
        <keyword>construct-enumerable-structure</keyword>.<p>By default the
        enumeration data reflects all elements with titles: topics, figures,
        tables, sections, examples, bodydiv, sectiondiv, and div. </p><p>If you
        wanted to number notes, for example, you could add a template that
        matches on "topic/note" in the mode construct-enumerable-structure and
        call the template <keyword>construct-enumerated-element</keyword> with
        the appropriate content.</p></li>
      <li>You can extend or modify the index and glossary grouping and sorting
        behavior, although there should be no need unless you need to apply
        specific grouping or sorting rules for some reason. Note that as of
        0.9.19, the grouping and sorting is only tested for English, so getting
        correct grouping and sorting for other languages, locales, and writing
        systems will likely require customization or, in the worst case, XSLT
        extensions that implement appropriate collation.</li>
      <li> Add your own data collection for whatever purpose by implementing
        templates in the mode <keyword>data-collection-extensions</keyword>. You
        can generate whatever XML structures you want through this mode.<p>For
        example, if you needed specific data to support some interaction feature
        of your generated output, you could gather that data in the
        data-collection-extensions mode.</p></li>
      </ul></p>
    <p>The collected data is not normally written out—it is simply held in
      memory as an XSLT variable. However, if you turn debugging on using the
      <parmname>debug</parmname> parameter the collected data will be written to
      the output directory as the file
      <filepath>collected-data.xml</filepath>.</p>
  </conbody>
</concept>
