<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net/doctypes/dita/shakespear/dtd/act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-2">
   <title>ACT II</title>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  A room in POLONIUS' house.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter POLONIUS and REYNALDO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD POLONIUS</speaker>
            <line>Give him this money and these notes, Reynaldo.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>REYNALDO</speaker>
            <line>I will, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD POLONIUS</speaker>
            <line>You shall do marvellous wisely, good Reynaldo,</line>
            <line>Before you visit him, to make inquire</line>
            <line>Of his behavior.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>REYNALDO</speaker>
            <line>My lord, I did intend it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD POLONIUS</speaker>
            <line>Marry, well said; very well said. Look you, sir,</line>
            <line>Inquire me first what Danskers are in Paris;</line>
            <line>And how, and who, what means, and where they keep,</line>
            <line>What company, at what expense; and finding</line>
            <line>By this encompassment and drift of question</line>
            <line>That they do know my son, come you more nearer</line>
            <line>Than your particular demands will touch it:</line>
            <line>Take you, as 'twere, some distant knowledge of him;</line>
            <line>As thus, 'I know his father and his friends,</line>
            <line>And in part him: ' do you mark this, Reynaldo?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>REYNALDO</speaker>
            <line>Ay, very well, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD POLONIUS</speaker>
            <line>'And in part him; but' you may say 'not well:</line>
            <line>But, if't be he I mean, he's very wild;</line>
            <line>Addicted so and so:' and there put on him</line>
            <line>What forgeries you please; marry, none so rank</line>
            <line>As may dishonour him; take heed of that;</line>
            <line>But, sir, such wanton, wild and usual slips</line>
            <line>As are companions noted and most known</line>
            <line>To youth and liberty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>REYNALDO</speaker>
            <line>As gaming, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD POLONIUS</speaker>
            <line>Ay, or drinking, fencing, swearing, quarrelling,</line>
            <line>Drabbing: you may go so far.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>REYNALDO</speaker>
            <line>My lord, that would dishonour him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD POLONIUS</speaker>
            <line>'Faith, no; as you may season it in the charge</line>
            <line>You must not put another scandal on him,</line>
            <line>That he is open to incontinency;</line>
            <line>That's not my meaning: but breathe his faults so quaintly</line>
            <line>That they may seem the taints of liberty,</line>
            <line>The flash and outbreak of a fiery mind,</line>
            <line>A savageness in unreclaimed blood,</line>
            <line>Of general assault.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>REYNALDO</speaker>
            <line>But, my good lord,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD POLONIUS</speaker>
            <line>Wherefore should you do this?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>REYNALDO</speaker>
            <line>Ay, my lord,</line>
            <line>I would know that.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD POLONIUS</speaker>
            <line>Marry, sir, here's my drift;</line>
            <line>And I believe, it is a fetch of wit:</line>
            <line>You laying these slight sullies on my son,</line>
            <line>As 'twere a thing a little soil'd i' the working, Mark you,</line>
            <line>Your party in converse, him you would sound,</line>
            <line>Having ever seen in the prenominate crimes</line>
            <line>The youth you breathe of guilty, be assured</line>
            <line>He closes with you in this consequence;</line>
            <line>'Good sir,' or so, or 'friend,' or 'gentleman,'</line>
            <line>According to the phrase or the addition</line>
            <line>Of man and country.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>REYNALDO</speaker>
            <line>Very good, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD POLONIUS</speaker>
            <line>And then, sir, does he this--he does--what was I</line>
            <line>about to say? By the mass, I was about to say</line>
            <line>something: where did I leave?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>REYNALDO</speaker>
            <line>At 'closes in the consequence,' at 'friend or so,'</line>
            <line>and 'gentleman.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD POLONIUS</speaker>
            <line>At 'closes in the consequence,' ay, marry;</line>
            <line>He closes thus: 'I know the gentleman;</line>
            <line>I saw him yesterday, or t' other day,</line>
            <line>Or then, or then; with such, or such; and, as you say,</line>
            <line>There was a' gaming; there o'ertook in's rouse;</line>
            <line>There falling out at tennis:' or perchance,</line>
            <line>'I saw him enter such a house of sale,'</line>
            <line>Videlicet, a brothel, or so forth.</line>
            <line>See you now;</line>
            <line>Your bait of falsehood takes this carp of truth:</line>
            <line>And thus do we of wisdom and of reach,</line>
            <line>With windlasses and with assays of bias,</line>
            <line>By indirections find directions out:</line>
            <line>So by my former lecture and advice,</line>
            <line>Shall you my son. You have me, have you not?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>REYNALDO</speaker>
            <line>My lord, I have.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD POLONIUS</speaker>
            <line>God be wi' you; fare you well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>REYNALDO</speaker>
            <line>Good my lord!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD POLONIUS</speaker>
            <line>Observe his inclination in yourself.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>REYNALDO</speaker>
            <line>I shall, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD POLONIUS</speaker>
            <line>And let him ply his music.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>REYNALDO</speaker>
            <line>Well, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD POLONIUS</speaker>
            <line>Farewell!</line>
            <stagedir>Exit REYNALDO</stagedir>
            <stagedir>Enter OPHELIA</stagedir>
            <line>How now, Ophelia! what's the matter?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OPHELIA</speaker>
            <line>O, my lord, my lord, I have been so affrighted!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD POLONIUS</speaker>
            <line>With what, i' the name of God?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OPHELIA</speaker>
            <line>My lord, as I was sewing in my closet,</line>
            <line>Lord Hamlet, with his doublet all unbraced;</line>
            <line>No hat upon his head; his stockings foul'd,</line>
            <line>Ungarter'd, and down-gyved to his ancle;</line>
            <line>Pale as his shirt; his knees knocking each other;</line>
            <line>And with a look so piteous in purport</line>
            <line>As if he had been loosed out of hell</line>
            <line>To speak of horrors,--he comes before me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD POLONIUS</speaker>
            <line>Mad for thy love?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OPHELIA</speaker>
            <line>My lord, I do not know;</line>
            <line>But truly, I do fear it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD POLONIUS</speaker>
            <line>What said he?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OPHELIA</speaker>
            <line>He took me by the wrist and held me hard;</line>
            <line>Then goes he to the length of all his arm;</line>
            <line>And, with his other hand thus o'er his brow,</line>
            <line>He falls to such perusal of my face</line>
            <line>As he would draw it. Long stay'd he so;</line>
            <line>At last, a little shaking of mine arm</line>
            <line>And thrice his head thus waving up and down,</line>
            <line>He raised a sigh so piteous and profound</line>
            <line>As it did seem to shatter all his bulk</line>
            <line>And end his being: that done, he lets me go:</line>
            <line>And, with his head over his shoulder turn'd,</line>
            <line>He seem'd to find his way without his eyes;</line>
            <line>For out o' doors he went without their helps,</line>
            <line>And, to the last, bended their light on me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD POLONIUS</speaker>
            <line>Come, go with me: I will go seek the king.</line>
            <line>This is the very ecstasy of love,</line>
            <line>Whose violent property fordoes itself</line>
            <line>And leads the will to desperate undertakings</line>
            <line>As oft as any passion under heaven</line>
            <line>That does afflict our natures. I am sorry.</line>
            <line>What, have you given him any hard words of late?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OPHELIA</speaker>
            <line>No, my good lord, but, as you did command,</line>
            <line>I did repel his fetters and denied</line>
            <line>His access to me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD POLONIUS</speaker>
            <line>That hath made him mad.</line>
            <line>I am sorry that with better heed and judgment</line>
            <line>I had not quoted him: I fear'd he did but trifle,</line>
            <line>And meant to wreck thee; but, beshrew my jealousy!</line>
            <line>By heaven, it is as proper to our age</line>
            <line>To cast beyond ourselves in our opinions</line>
            <line>As it is common for the younger sort</line>
            <line>To lack discretion. Come, go we to the king:</line>
            <line>This must be known; which, being kept close, might</line>
            <line>move</line>
            <line>More grief to hide than hate to utter love.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  A room in the castle.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter KING CLAUDIUS, QUEEN GERTRUDE, ROSENCRANTZ,
GUILDENSTERN, and Attendants</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING CLAUDIUS</speaker>
            <line>Welcome, dear Rosencrantz and Guildenstern!</line>
            <line>Moreover that we much did long to see you,</line>
            <line>The need we have to use you did provoke</line>
            <line>Our hasty sending. Something have you heard</line>
            <line>Of Hamlet's transformation; so call it,</line>
            <line>Sith nor the exterior nor the inward man</line>
            <line>Resembles that it was. What it should be,</line>
            <line>More than his father's death, that thus hath put him</line>
            <line>So much from the understanding of himself,</line>
            <line>I cannot dream of: I entreat you both,</line>
            <line>That, being of so young days brought up with him,</line>
            <line>And sith so neighbour'd to his youth and havior,</line>
            <line>That you vouchsafe your rest here in our court</line>
            <line>Some little time: so by your companies</line>
            <line>To draw him on to pleasures, and to gather,</line>
            <line>So much as from occasion you may glean,</line>
            <line>Whether aught, to us unknown, afflicts him thus,</line>
            <line>That, open'd, lies within our remedy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN GERTRUDE</speaker>
            <line>Good gentlemen, he hath much talk'd of you;</line>
            <line>And sure I am two men there are not living</line>
            <line>To whom he more adheres. If it will please you</line>
            <line>To show us so much gentry and good will</line>
            <line>As to expend your time with us awhile,</line>
            <line>For the supply and profit of our hope,</line>
            <line>Your visitation shall receive such thanks</line>
            <line>As fits a king's remembrance.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSENCRANTZ</speaker>
            <line>Both your majesties</line>
            <line>Might, by the sovereign power you have of us,</line>
            <line>Put your dread pleasures more into command</line>
            <line>Than to entreaty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GUILDENSTERN</speaker>
            <line>But we both obey,</line>
            <line>And here give up ourselves, in the full bent</line>
            <line>To lay our service freely at your feet,</line>
            <line>To be commanded.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING CLAUDIUS</speaker>
            <line>Thanks, Rosencrantz and gentle Guildenstern.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN GERTRUDE</speaker>
            <line>Thanks, Guildenstern and gentle Rosencrantz:</line>
            <line>And I beseech you instantly to visit</line>
            <line>My too much changed son. Go, some of you,</line>
            <line>And bring these gentlemen where Hamlet is.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GUILDENSTERN</speaker>
            <line>Heavens make our presence and our practises</line>
            <line>Pleasant and helpful to him!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN GERTRUDE</speaker>
            <line>Ay, amen!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt ROSENCRANTZ, GUILDENSTERN, and some
Attendants</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Enter POLONIUS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD POLONIUS</speaker>
            <line>The ambassadors from Norway, my good lord,</line>
            <line>Are joyfully return'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING CLAUDIUS</speaker>
            <line>Thou still hast been the father of good news.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD POLONIUS</speaker>
            <line>Have I, my lord? I assure my good liege,</line>
            <line>I hold my duty, as I hold my soul,</line>
            <line>Both to my God and to my gracious king:</line>
            <line>And I do think, or else this brain of mine</line>
            <line>Hunts not the trail of policy so sure</line>
            <line>As it hath used to do, that I have found</line>
            <line>The very cause of Hamlet's lunacy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING CLAUDIUS</speaker>
            <line>O, speak of that; that do I long to hear.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD POLONIUS</speaker>
            <line>Give first admittance to the ambassadors;</line>
            <line>My news shall be the fruit to that great feast.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING CLAUDIUS</speaker>
            <line>Thyself do grace to them, and bring them in.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit POLONIUS</stagedir>
            <line>He tells me, my dear Gertrude, he hath found</line>
            <line>The head and source of all your son's distemper.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN GERTRUDE</speaker>
            <line>I doubt it is no other but the main;</line>
            <line>His father's death, and our o'erhasty marriage.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING CLAUDIUS</speaker>
            <line>Well, we shall sift him.</line>
            <stagedir>Re-enter POLONIUS, with VOLTIMAND and CORNELIUS</stagedir>
            <line>Welcome, my good friends!</line>
            <line>Say, Voltimand, what from our brother Norway?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VOLTIMAND</speaker>
            <line>Most fair return of greetings and desires.</line>
            <line>Upon our first, he sent out to suppress</line>
            <line>His nephew's levies; which to him appear'd</line>
            <line>To be a preparation 'gainst the Polack;</line>
            <line>But, better look'd into, he truly found</line>
            <line>It was against your highness: whereat grieved,</line>
            <line>That so his sickness, age and impotence</line>
            <line>Was falsely borne in hand, sends out arrests</line>
            <line>On Fortinbras; which he, in brief, obeys;</line>
            <line>Receives rebuke from Norway, and in fine</line>
            <line>Makes vow before his uncle never more</line>
            <line>To give the assay of arms against your majesty.</line>
            <line>Whereon old Norway, overcome with joy,</line>
            <line>Gives him three thousand crowns in annual fee,</line>
            <line>And his commission to employ those soldiers,</line>
            <line>So levied as before, against the Polack:</line>
            <line>With an entreaty, herein further shown,</line>
            <stagedir>Giving a paper</stagedir>
            <line>That it might please you to give quiet pass</line>
            <line>Through your dominions for this enterprise,</line>
            <line>On such regards of safety and allowance</line>
            <line>As therein are set down.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING CLAUDIUS</speaker>
            <line>It likes us well;</line>
            <line>And at our more consider'd time well read,</line>
            <line>Answer, and think upon this business.</line>
            <line>Meantime we thank you for your well-took labour:</line>
            <line>Go to your rest; at night we'll feast together:</line>
            <line>Most welcome home!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt VOLTIMAND and CORNELIUS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD POLONIUS</speaker>
            <line>This business is well ended.</line>
            <line>My liege, and madam, to expostulate</line>
            <line>What majesty should be, what duty is,</line>
            <line>Why day is day, night night, and time is time,</line>
            <line>Were nothing but to waste night, day and time.</line>
            <line>Therefore, since brevity is the soul of wit,</line>
            <line>And tediousness the limbs and outward flourishes,</line>
            <line>I will be brief: your noble son is mad:</line>
            <line>Mad call I it; for, to define true madness,</line>
            <line>What is't but to be nothing else but mad?</line>
            <line>But let that go.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN GERTRUDE</speaker>
            <line>More matter, with less art.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD POLONIUS</speaker>
            <line>Madam, I swear I use no art at all.</line>
            <line>That he is mad, 'tis true: 'tis true 'tis pity;</line>
            <line>And pity 'tis 'tis true: a foolish figure;</line>
            <line>But farewell it, for I will use no art.</line>
            <line>Mad let us grant him, then: and now remains</line>
            <line>That we find out the cause of this effect,</line>
            <line>Or rather say, the cause of this defect,</line>
            <line>For this effect defective comes by cause:</line>
            <line>Thus it remains, and the remainder thus. Perpend.</line>
            <line>I have a daughter--have while she is mine--</line>
            <line>Who, in her duty and obedience, mark,</line>
            <line>Hath given me this: now gather, and surmise.</line>
            <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>
            <line>'To the celestial and my soul's idol, the most</line>
            <line>beautified Ophelia,'--</line>
            <line>That's an ill phrase, a vile phrase; 'beautified' is</line>
            <line>a vile phrase: but you shall hear. Thus:</line>
            <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>
            <line>'In her excellent white bosom, these, &amp;c.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN GERTRUDE</speaker>
            <line>Came this from Hamlet to her?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD POLONIUS</speaker>
            <line>Good madam, stay awhile; I will be faithful.</line>
            <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>
            <line>'Doubt thou the stars are fire;</line>
            <line>Doubt that the sun doth move;</line>
            <line>Doubt truth to be a liar;</line>
            <line>But never doubt I love.</line>
            <line>'O dear Ophelia, I am ill at these numbers;</line>
            <line>I have not art to reckon my groans: but that</line>
            <line>I love thee best, O most best, believe it. Adieu.</line>
            <line>'Thine evermore most dear lady, whilst</line>
            <line>this machine is to him, HAMLET.'</line>
            <line>This, in obedience, hath my daughter shown me,</line>
            <line>And more above, hath his solicitings,</line>
            <line>As they fell out by time, by means and place,</line>
            <line>All given to mine ear.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING CLAUDIUS</speaker>
            <line>But how hath she</line>
            <line>Received his love?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD POLONIUS</speaker>
            <line>What do you think of me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING CLAUDIUS</speaker>
            <line>As of a man faithful and honourable.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD POLONIUS</speaker>
            <line>I would fain prove so. But what might you think,</line>
            <line>When I had seen this hot love on the wing--</line>
            <line>As I perceived it, I must tell you that,</line>
            <line>Before my daughter told me--what might you,</line>
            <line>Or my dear majesty your queen here, think,</line>
            <line>If I had play'd the desk or table-book,</line>
            <line>Or given my heart a winking, mute and dumb,</line>
            <line>Or look'd upon this love with idle sight;</line>
            <line>What might you think? No, I went round to work,</line>
            <line>And my young mistress thus I did bespeak:</line>
            <line>'Lord Hamlet is a prince, out of thy star;</line>
            <line>This must not be:' and then I precepts gave her,</line>
            <line>That she should lock herself from his resort,</line>
            <line>Admit no messengers, receive no tokens.</line>
            <line>Which done, she took the fruits of my advice;</line>
            <line>And he, repulsed--a short tale to make--</line>
            <line>Fell into a sadness, then into a fast,</line>
            <line>Thence to a watch, thence into a weakness,</line>
            <line>Thence to a lightness, and, by this declension,</line>
            <line>Into the madness wherein now he raves,</line>
            <line>And all we mourn for.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING CLAUDIUS</speaker>
            <line>Do you think 'tis this?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN GERTRUDE</speaker>
            <line>It may be, very likely.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD POLONIUS</speaker>
            <line>Hath there been such a time--I'd fain know that--</line>
            <line>That I have positively said 'Tis so,'</line>
            <line>When it proved otherwise?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING CLAUDIUS</speaker>
            <line>Not that I know.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD POLONIUS</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Pointing to his head and shoulder</stagedir>
            </line>
            <line>Take this from this, if this be otherwise:</line>
            <line>If circumstances lead me, I will find</line>
            <line>Where truth is hid, though it were hid indeed</line>
            <line>Within the centre.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING CLAUDIUS</speaker>
            <line>How may we try it further?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD POLONIUS</speaker>
            <line>You know, sometimes he walks four hours together</line>
            <line>Here in the lobby.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN GERTRUDE</speaker>
            <line>So he does indeed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD POLONIUS</speaker>
            <line>At such a time I'll loose my daughter to him:</line>
            <line>Be you and I behind an arras then;</line>
            <line>Mark the encounter: if he love her not</line>
            <line>And be not from his reason fall'n thereon,</line>
            <line>Let me be no assistant for a state,</line>
            <line>But keep a farm and carters.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING CLAUDIUS</speaker>
            <line>We will try it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN GERTRUDE</speaker>
            <line>But, look, where sadly the poor wretch comes reading.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD POLONIUS</speaker>
            <line>Away, I do beseech you, both away:</line>
            <line>I'll board him presently.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt KING CLAUDIUS, QUEEN GERTRUDE, and
Attendants</stagedir>
            <stagedir>Enter HAMLET, reading</stagedir>
            <line>O, give me leave:</line>
            <line>How does my good Lord Hamlet?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HAMLET</speaker>
            <line>Well, God-a-mercy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD POLONIUS</speaker>
            <line>Do you know me, my lord?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HAMLET</speaker>
            <line>Excellent well; you are a fishmonger.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD POLONIUS</speaker>
            <line>Not I, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HAMLET</speaker>
            <line>Then I would you were so honest a man.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD POLONIUS</speaker>
            <line>Honest, my lord!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HAMLET</speaker>
            <line>Ay, sir; to be honest, as this world goes, is to be</line>
            <line>one man picked out of ten thousand.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD POLONIUS</speaker>
            <line>That's very true, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HAMLET</speaker>
            <line>For if the sun breed maggots in a dead dog, being a</line>
            <line>god kissing carrion,--Have you a daughter?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD POLONIUS</speaker>
            <line>I have, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HAMLET</speaker>
            <line>Let her not walk i' the sun: conception is a</line>
            <line>blessing: but not as your daughter may conceive.</line>
            <line>Friend, look to 't.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD POLONIUS</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  How say you by that? Still harping on my</line>
            <line>daughter: yet he knew me not at first; he said I</line>
            <line>was a fishmonger: he is far gone, far gone: and</line>
            <line>truly in my youth I suffered much extremity for</line>
            <line>love; very near this. I'll speak to him again.</line>
            <line>What do you read, my lord?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HAMLET</speaker>
            <line>Words, words, words.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD POLONIUS</speaker>
            <line>What is the matter, my lord?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HAMLET</speaker>
            <line>Between who?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD POLONIUS</speaker>
            <line>I mean, the matter that you read, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HAMLET</speaker>
            <line>Slanders, sir: for the satirical rogue says here</line>
            <line>that old men have grey beards, that their faces are</line>
            <line>wrinkled, their eyes purging thick amber and</line>
            <line>plum-tree gum and that they have a plentiful lack of</line>
            <line>wit, together with most weak hams: all which, sir,</line>
            <line>though I most powerfully and potently believe, yet</line>
            <line>I hold it not honesty to have it thus set down, for</line>
            <line>yourself, sir, should be old as I am, if like a crab</line>
            <line>you could go backward.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD POLONIUS</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  Though this be madness, yet there is method</line>
            <line>in 't. Will you walk out of the air, my lord?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HAMLET</speaker>
            <line>Into my grave.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD POLONIUS</speaker>
            <line>Indeed, that is out o' the air.</line>
            <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>
            <line>How pregnant sometimes his replies are! a happiness</line>
            <line>that often madness hits on, which reason and sanity</line>
            <line>could not so prosperously be delivered of. I will</line>
            <line>leave him, and suddenly contrive the means of</line>
            <line>meeting between him and my daughter.--My honourable</line>
            <line>lord, I will most humbly take my leave of you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HAMLET</speaker>
            <line>You cannot, sir, take from me any thing that I will</line>
            <line>more willingly part withal: except my life, except</line>
            <line>my life, except my life.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD POLONIUS</speaker>
            <line>Fare you well, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HAMLET</speaker>
            <line>These tedious old fools!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter ROSENCRANTZ and GUILDENSTERN</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD POLONIUS</speaker>
            <line>You go to seek the Lord Hamlet; there he is.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSENCRANTZ</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>To POLONIUS</stagedir>  God save you, sir!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit POLONIUS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GUILDENSTERN</speaker>
            <line>My honoured lord!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSENCRANTZ</speaker>
            <line>My most dear lord!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HAMLET</speaker>
            <line>My excellent good friends! How dost thou,</line>
            <line>Guildenstern? Ah, Rosencrantz! Good lads, how do ye both?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSENCRANTZ</speaker>
            <line>As the indifferent children of the earth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GUILDENSTERN</speaker>
            <line>Happy, in that we are not over-happy;</line>
            <line>On fortune's cap we are not the very button.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HAMLET</speaker>
            <line>Nor the soles of her shoe?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSENCRANTZ</speaker>
            <line>Neither, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HAMLET</speaker>
            <line>Then you live about her waist, or in the middle of</line>
            <line>her favours?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GUILDENSTERN</speaker>
            <line>'Faith, her privates we.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HAMLET</speaker>
            <line>In the secret parts of fortune? O, most true; she</line>
            <line>is a strumpet. What's the news?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSENCRANTZ</speaker>
            <line>None, my lord, but that the world's grown honest.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HAMLET</speaker>
            <line>Then is doomsday near: but your news is not true.</line>
            <line>Let me question more in particular: what have you,</line>
            <line>my good friends, deserved at the hands of fortune,</line>
            <line>that she sends you to prison hither?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GUILDENSTERN</speaker>
            <line>Prison, my lord!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HAMLET</speaker>
            <line>Denmark's a prison.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSENCRANTZ</speaker>
            <line>Then is the world one.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HAMLET</speaker>
            <line>A goodly one; in which there are many confines,</line>
            <line>wards and dungeons, Denmark being one o' the worst.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSENCRANTZ</speaker>
            <line>We think not so, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HAMLET</speaker>
            <line>Why, then, 'tis none to you; for there is nothing</line>
            <line>either good or bad, but thinking makes it so: to me</line>
            <line>it is a prison.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSENCRANTZ</speaker>
            <line>Why then, your ambition makes it one; 'tis too</line>
            <line>narrow for your mind.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HAMLET</speaker>
            <line>O God, I could be bounded in a nut shell and count</line>
            <line>myself a king of infinite space, were it not that I</line>
            <line>have bad dreams.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GUILDENSTERN</speaker>
            <line>Which dreams indeed are ambition, for the very</line>
            <line>substance of the ambitious is merely the shadow of a dream.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HAMLET</speaker>
            <line>A dream itself is but a shadow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSENCRANTZ</speaker>
            <line>Truly, and I hold ambition of so airy and light a</line>
            <line>quality that it is but a shadow's shadow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HAMLET</speaker>
            <line>Then are our beggars bodies, and our monarchs and</line>
            <line>outstretched heroes the beggars' shadows. Shall we</line>
            <line>to the court? for, by my fay, I cannot reason.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSENCRANTZ</speaker>
            <speaker>GUILDENSTERN</speaker>
            <line>We'll wait upon you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HAMLET</speaker>
            <line>No such matter: I will not sort you with the rest</line>
            <line>of my servants, for, to speak to you like an honest</line>
            <line>man, I am most dreadfully attended. But, in the</line>
            <line>beaten way of friendship, what make you at Elsinore?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSENCRANTZ</speaker>
            <line>To visit you, my lord; no other occasion.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HAMLET</speaker>
            <line>Beggar that I am, I am even poor in thanks; but I</line>
            <line>thank you: and sure, dear friends, my thanks are</line>
            <line>too dear a halfpenny. Were you not sent for? Is it</line>
            <line>your own inclining? Is it a free visitation? Come,</line>
            <line>deal justly with me: come, come; nay, speak.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GUILDENSTERN</speaker>
            <line>What should we say, my lord?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HAMLET</speaker>
            <line>Why, any thing, but to the purpose. You were sent</line>
            <line>for; and there is a kind of confession in your looks</line>
            <line>which your modesties have not craft enough to colour:</line>
            <line>I know the good king and queen have sent for you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSENCRANTZ</speaker>
            <line>To what end, my lord?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HAMLET</speaker>
            <line>That you must teach me. But let me conjure you, by</line>
            <line>the rights of our fellowship, by the consonancy of</line>
            <line>our youth, by the obligation of our ever-preserved</line>
            <line>love, and by what more dear a better proposer could</line>
            <line>charge you withal, be even and direct with me,</line>
            <line>whether you were sent for, or no?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSENCRANTZ</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside to GUILDENSTERN</stagedir>  What say you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HAMLET</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  Nay, then, I have an eye of you.--If you</line>
            <line>love me, hold not off.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GUILDENSTERN</speaker>
            <line>My lord, we were sent for.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HAMLET</speaker>
            <line>I will tell you why; so shall my anticipation</line>
            <line>prevent your discovery, and your secrecy to the king</line>
            <line>and queen moult no feather. I have of late--but</line>
            <line>wherefore I know not--lost all my mirth, forgone all</line>
            <line>custom of exercises; and indeed it goes so heavily</line>
            <line>with my disposition that this goodly frame, the</line>
            <line>earth, seems to me a sterile promontory, this most</line>
            <line>excellent canopy, the air, look you, this brave</line>
            <line>o'erhanging firmament, this majestical roof fretted</line>
            <line>with golden fire, why, it appears no other thing to</line>
            <line>me than a foul and pestilent congregation of vapours.</line>
            <line>What a piece of work is a man! how noble in reason!</line>
            <line>how infinite in faculty! in form and moving how</line>
            <line>express and admirable! in action how like an angel!</line>
            <line>in apprehension how like a god! the beauty of the</line>
            <line>world! the paragon of animals! And yet, to me,</line>
            <line>what is this quintessence of dust? man delights not</line>
            <line>me: no, nor woman neither, though by your smiling</line>
            <line>you seem to say so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSENCRANTZ</speaker>
            <line>My lord, there was no such stuff in my thoughts.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HAMLET</speaker>
            <line>Why did you laugh then, when I said 'man delights not me'?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSENCRANTZ</speaker>
            <line>To think, my lord, if you delight not in man, what</line>
            <line>lenten entertainment the players shall receive from</line>
            <line>you: we coted them on the way; and hither are they</line>
            <line>coming, to offer you service.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HAMLET</speaker>
            <line>He that plays the king shall be welcome; his majesty</line>
            <line>shall have tribute of me; the adventurous knight</line>
            <line>shall use his foil and target; the lover shall not</line>
            <line>sigh gratis; the humourous man shall end his part</line>
            <line>in peace; the clown shall make those laugh whose</line>
            <line>lungs are tickled o' the sere; and the lady shall</line>
            <line>say her mind freely, or the blank verse shall halt</line>
            <line>for't. What players are they?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSENCRANTZ</speaker>
            <line>Even those you were wont to take delight in, the</line>
            <line>tragedians of the city.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HAMLET</speaker>
            <line>How chances it they travel? their residence, both</line>
            <line>in reputation and profit, was better both ways.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSENCRANTZ</speaker>
            <line>I think their inhibition comes by the means of the</line>
            <line>late innovation.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HAMLET</speaker>
            <line>Do they hold the same estimation they did when I was</line>
            <line>in the city? are they so followed?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSENCRANTZ</speaker>
            <line>No, indeed, are they not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HAMLET</speaker>
            <line>How comes it? do they grow rusty?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSENCRANTZ</speaker>
            <line>Nay, their endeavour keeps in the wonted pace: but</line>
            <line>there is, sir, an aery of children, little eyases,</line>
            <line>that cry out on the top of question, and are most</line>
            <line>tyrannically clapped for't: these are now the</line>
            <line>fashion, and so berattle the common stages--so they</line>
            <line>call them--that many wearing rapiers are afraid of</line>
            <line>goose-quills and dare scarce come thither.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HAMLET</speaker>
            <line>What, are they children? who maintains 'em? how are</line>
            <line>they escoted? Will they pursue the quality no</line>
            <line>longer than they can sing? will they not say</line>
            <line>afterwards, if they should grow themselves to common</line>
            <line>players--as it is most like, if their means are no</line>
            <line>better--their writers do them wrong, to make them</line>
            <line>exclaim against their own succession?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSENCRANTZ</speaker>
            <line>'Faith, there has been much to do on both sides; and</line>
            <line>the nation holds it no sin to tarre them to</line>
            <line>controversy: there was, for a while, no money bid</line>
            <line>for argument, unless the poet and the player went to</line>
            <line>cuffs in the question.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HAMLET</speaker>
            <line>Is't possible?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GUILDENSTERN</speaker>
            <line>O, there has been much throwing about of brains.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HAMLET</speaker>
            <line>Do the boys carry it away?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSENCRANTZ</speaker>
            <line>Ay, that they do, my lord; Hercules and his load too.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HAMLET</speaker>
            <line>It is not very strange; for mine uncle is king of</line>
            <line>Denmark, and those that would make mows at him while</line>
            <line>my father lived, give twenty, forty, fifty, an</line>
            <line>hundred ducats a-piece for his picture in little.</line>
            <line>'Sblood, there is something in this more than</line>
            <line>natural, if philosophy could find it out.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Flourish of trumpets within</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GUILDENSTERN</speaker>
            <line>There are the players.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HAMLET</speaker>
            <line>Gentlemen, you are welcome to Elsinore. Your hands,</line>
            <line>come then: the appurtenance of welcome is fashion</line>
            <line>and ceremony: let me comply with you in this garb,</line>
            <line>lest my extent to the players, which, I tell you,</line>
            <line>must show fairly outward, should more appear like</line>
            <line>entertainment than yours. You are welcome: but my</line>
            <line>uncle-father and aunt-mother are deceived.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GUILDENSTERN</speaker>
            <line>In what, my dear lord?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HAMLET</speaker>
            <line>I am but mad north-north-west: when the wind is</line>
            <line>southerly I know a hawk from a handsaw.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter POLONIUS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD POLONIUS</speaker>
            <line>Well be with you, gentlemen!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HAMLET</speaker>
            <line>Hark you, Guildenstern; and you too: at each ear a</line>
            <line>hearer: that great baby you see there is not yet</line>
            <line>out of his swaddling-clouts.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSENCRANTZ</speaker>
            <line>Happily he's the second time come to them; for they</line>
            <line>say an old man is twice a child.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HAMLET</speaker>
            <line>I will prophesy he comes to tell me of the players;</line>
            <line>mark it. You say right, sir: o' Monday morning;</line>
            <line>'twas so indeed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD POLONIUS</speaker>
            <line>My lord, I have news to tell you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HAMLET</speaker>
            <line>My lord, I have news to tell you.</line>
            <line>When Roscius was an actor in Rome,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD POLONIUS</speaker>
            <line>The actors are come hither, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HAMLET</speaker>
            <line>Buz, buz!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD POLONIUS</speaker>
            <line>Upon mine honour,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HAMLET</speaker>
            <line>Then came each actor on his ass,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD POLONIUS</speaker>
            <line>The best actors in the world, either for tragedy,</line>
            <line>comedy, history, pastoral, pastoral-comical,</line>
            <line>historical-pastoral, tragical-historical, tragical-</line>
            <line>comical-historical-pastoral, scene individable, or</line>
            <line>poem unlimited: Seneca cannot be too heavy, nor</line>
            <line>Plautus too light. For the law of writ and the</line>
            <line>liberty, these are the only men.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HAMLET</speaker>
            <line>O Jephthah, judge of Israel, what a treasure hadst thou!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD POLONIUS</speaker>
            <line>What a treasure had he, my lord?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HAMLET</speaker>
            <line>Why,</line>
            <line>'One fair daughter and no more,</line>
            <line>The which he loved passing well.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD POLONIUS</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  Still on my daughter.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HAMLET</speaker>
            <line>Am I not i' the right, old Jephthah?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD POLONIUS</speaker>
            <line>If you call me Jephthah, my lord, I have a daughter</line>
            <line>that I love passing well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HAMLET</speaker>
            <line>Nay, that follows not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD POLONIUS</speaker>
            <line>What follows, then, my lord?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HAMLET</speaker>
            <line>Why,</line>
            <line>'As by lot, God wot,'</line>
            <line>and then, you know,</line>
            <line>'It came to pass, as most like it was,'--</line>
            <line>the first row of the pious chanson will show you</line>
            <line>more; for look, where my abridgement comes.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter four or five Players</stagedir>
            <line>You are welcome, masters; welcome, all. I am glad</line>
            <line>to see thee well. Welcome, good friends. O, my old</line>
            <line>friend! thy face is valenced since I saw thee last:</line>
            <line>comest thou to beard me in Denmark? What, my young</line>
            <line>lady and mistress! By'r lady, your ladyship is</line>
            <line>nearer to heaven than when I saw you last, by the</line>
            <line>altitude of a chopine. Pray God, your voice, like</line>
            <line>apiece of uncurrent gold, be not cracked within the</line>
            <line>ring. Masters, you are all welcome. We'll e'en</line>
            <line>to't like French falconers, fly at any thing we see:</line>
            <line>we'll have a speech straight: come, give us a taste</line>
            <line>of your quality; come, a passionate speech.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Player</speaker>
            <line>What speech, my lord?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HAMLET</speaker>
            <line>I heard thee speak me a speech once, but it was</line>
            <line>never acted; or, if it was, not above once; for the</line>
            <line>play, I remember, pleased not the million; 'twas</line>
            <line>caviare to the general: but it was--as I received</line>
            <line>it, and others, whose judgments in such matters</line>
            <line>cried in the top of mine--an excellent play, well</line>
            <line>digested in the scenes, set down with as much</line>
            <line>modesty as cunning. I remember, one said there</line>
            <line>were no sallets in the lines to make the matter</line>
            <line>savoury, nor no matter in the phrase that might</line>
            <line>indict the author of affectation; but called it an</line>
            <line>honest method, as wholesome as sweet, and by very</line>
            <line>much more handsome than fine. One speech in it I</line>
            <line>chiefly loved: 'twas Aeneas' tale to Dido; and</line>
            <line>thereabout of it especially, where he speaks of</line>
            <line>Priam's slaughter: if it live in your memory, begin</line>
            <line>at this line: let me see, let me see--</line>
            <line>'The rugged Pyrrhus, like the Hyrcanian beast,'--</line>
            <line>it is not so:--it begins with Pyrrhus:--</line>
            <line>'The rugged Pyrrhus, he whose sable arms,</line>
            <line>Black as his purpose, did the night resemble</line>
            <line>When he lay couched in the ominous horse,</line>
            <line>Hath now this dread and black complexion smear'd</line>
            <line>With heraldry more dismal; head to foot</line>
            <line>Now is he total gules; horridly trick'd</line>
            <line>With blood of fathers, mothers, daughters, sons,</line>
            <line>Baked and impasted with the parching streets,</line>
            <line>That lend a tyrannous and damned light</line>
            <line>To their lord's murder: roasted in wrath and fire,</line>
            <line>And thus o'er-sized with coagulate gore,</line>
            <line>With eyes like carbuncles, the hellish Pyrrhus</line>
            <line>Old grandsire Priam seeks.'</line>
            <line>So, proceed you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD POLONIUS</speaker>
            <line>'Fore God, my lord, well spoken, with good accent and</line>
            <line>good discretion.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Player</speaker>
            <line>'Anon he finds him</line>
            <line>Striking too short at Greeks; his antique sword,</line>
            <line>Rebellious to his arm, lies where it falls,</line>
            <line>Repugnant to command: unequal match'd,</line>
            <line>Pyrrhus at Priam drives; in rage strikes wide;</line>
            <line>But with the whiff and wind of his fell sword</line>
            <line>The unnerved father falls. Then senseless Ilium,</line>
            <line>Seeming to feel this blow, with flaming top</line>
            <line>Stoops to his base, and with a hideous crash</line>
            <line>Takes prisoner Pyrrhus' ear: for, lo! his sword,</line>
            <line>Which was declining on the milky head</line>
            <line>Of reverend Priam, seem'd i' the air to stick:</line>
            <line>So, as a painted tyrant, Pyrrhus stood,</line>
            <line>And like a neutral to his will and matter,</line>
            <line>Did nothing.</line>
            <line>But, as we often see, against some storm,</line>
            <line>A silence in the heavens, the rack stand still,</line>
            <line>The bold winds speechless and the orb below</line>
            <line>As hush as death, anon the dreadful thunder</line>
            <line>Doth rend the region, so, after Pyrrhus' pause,</line>
            <line>Aroused vengeance sets him new a-work;</line>
            <line>And never did the Cyclops' hammers fall</line>
            <line>On Mars's armour forged for proof eterne</line>
            <line>With less remorse than Pyrrhus' bleeding sword</line>
            <line>Now falls on Priam.</line>
            <line>Out, out, thou strumpet, Fortune! All you gods,</line>
            <line>In general synod 'take away her power;</line>
            <line>Break all the spokes and fellies from her wheel,</line>
            <line>And bowl the round nave down the hill of heaven,</line>
            <line>As low as to the fiends!'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD POLONIUS</speaker>
            <line>This is too long.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HAMLET</speaker>
            <line>It shall to the barber's, with your beard. Prithee,</line>
            <line>say on: he's for a jig or a tale of bawdry, or he</line>
            <line>sleeps: say on: come to Hecuba.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Player</speaker>
            <line>'But who, O, who had seen the mobled queen--'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HAMLET</speaker>
            <line>'The mobled queen?'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD POLONIUS</speaker>
            <line>That's good; 'mobled queen' is good.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Player</speaker>
            <line>'Run barefoot up and down, threatening the flames</line>
            <line>With bisson rheum; a clout upon that head</line>
            <line>Where late the diadem stood, and for a robe,</line>
            <line>About her lank and all o'er-teemed loins,</line>
            <line>A blanket, in the alarm of fear caught up;</line>
            <line>Who this had seen, with tongue in venom steep'd,</line>
            <line>'Gainst Fortune's state would treason have</line>
            <line>pronounced:</line>
            <line>But if the gods themselves did see her then</line>
            <line>When she saw Pyrrhus make malicious sport</line>
            <line>In mincing with his sword her husband's limbs,</line>
            <line>The instant burst of clamour that she made,</line>
            <line>Unless things mortal move them not at all,</line>
            <line>Would have made milch the burning eyes of heaven,</line>
            <line>And passion in the gods.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD POLONIUS</speaker>
            <line>Look, whether he has not turned his colour and has</line>
            <line>tears in's eyes. Pray you, no more.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HAMLET</speaker>
            <line>'Tis well: I'll have thee speak out the rest soon.</line>
            <line>Good my lord, will you see the players well</line>
            <line>bestowed? Do you hear, let them be well used; for</line>
            <line>they are the abstract and brief chronicles of the</line>
            <line>time: after your death you were better have a bad</line>
            <line>epitaph than their ill report while you live.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD POLONIUS</speaker>
            <line>My lord, I will use them according to their desert.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HAMLET</speaker>
            <line>God's bodykins, man, much better: use every man</line>
            <line>after his desert, and who should 'scape whipping?</line>
            <line>Use them after your own honour and dignity: the less</line>
            <line>they deserve, the more merit is in your bounty.</line>
            <line>Take them in.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD POLONIUS</speaker>
            <line>Come, sirs.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HAMLET</speaker>
            <line>Follow him, friends: we'll hear a play to-morrow.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit POLONIUS with all the Players but the First</stagedir>
            <line>Dost thou hear me, old friend; can you play the</line>
            <line>Murder of Gonzago?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Player</speaker>
            <line>Ay, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HAMLET</speaker>
            <line>We'll ha't to-morrow night. You could, for a need,</line>
            <line>study a speech of some dozen or sixteen lines, which</line>
            <line>I would set down and insert in't, could you not?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Player</speaker>
            <line>Ay, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HAMLET</speaker>
            <line>Very well. Follow that lord; and look you mock him</line>
            <line>not.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit First Player</stagedir>
            <line>My good friends, I'll leave you till night: you are</line>
            <line>welcome to Elsinore.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROSENCRANTZ</speaker>
            <line>Good my lord!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HAMLET</speaker>
            <line>Ay, so, God be wi' ye;</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt ROSENCRANTZ and GUILDENSTERN</stagedir>
            <line>Now I am alone.</line>
            <line>O, what a rogue and peasant slave am I!</line>
            <line>Is it not monstrous that this player here,</line>
            <line>But in a fiction, in a dream of passion,</line>
            <line>Could force his soul so to his own conceit</line>
            <line>That from her working all his visage wann'd,</line>
            <line>Tears in his eyes, distraction in's aspect,</line>
            <line>A broken voice, and his whole function suiting</line>
            <line>With forms to his conceit? and all for nothing!</line>
            <line>For Hecuba!</line>
            <line>What's Hecuba to him, or he to Hecuba,</line>
            <line>That he should weep for her? What would he do,</line>
            <line>Had he the motive and the cue for passion</line>
            <line>That I have? He would drown the stage with tears</line>
            <line>And cleave the general ear with horrid speech,</line>
            <line>Make mad the guilty and appal the free,</line>
            <line>Confound the ignorant, and amaze indeed</line>
            <line>The very faculties of eyes and ears. Yet I,</line>
            <line>A dull and muddy-mettled rascal, peak,</line>
            <line>Like John-a-dreams, unpregnant of my cause,</line>
            <line>And can say nothing; no, not for a king,</line>
            <line>Upon whose property and most dear life</line>
            <line>A damn'd defeat was made. Am I a coward?</line>
            <line>Who calls me villain? breaks my pate across?</line>
            <line>Plucks off my beard, and blows it in my face?</line>
            <line>Tweaks me by the nose? gives me the lie i' the throat,</line>
            <line>As deep as to the lungs? who does me this?</line>
            <line>Ha!</line>
            <line>'Swounds, I should take it: for it cannot be</line>
            <line>But I am pigeon-liver'd and lack gall</line>
            <line>To make oppression bitter, or ere this</line>
            <line>I should have fatted all the region kites</line>
            <line>With this slave's offal: bloody, bawdy villain!</line>
            <line>Remorseless, treacherous, lecherous, kindless villain!</line>
            <line>O, vengeance!</line>
            <line>Why, what an ass am I! This is most brave,</line>
            <line>That I, the son of a dear father murder'd,</line>
            <line>Prompted to my revenge by heaven and hell,</line>
            <line>Must, like a whore, unpack my heart with words,</line>
            <line>And fall a-cursing, like a very drab,</line>
            <line>A scullion!</line>
            <line>Fie upon't! foh! About, my brain! I have heard</line>
            <line>That guilty creatures sitting at a play</line>
            <line>Have by the very cunning of the scene</line>
            <line>Been struck so to the soul that presently</line>
            <line>They have proclaim'd their malefactions;</line>
            <line>For murder, though it have no tongue, will speak</line>
            <line>With most miraculous organ. I'll have these players</line>
            <line>Play something like the murder of my father</line>
            <line>Before mine uncle: I'll observe his looks;</line>
            <line>I'll tent him to the quick: if he but blench,</line>
            <line>I know my course. The spirit that I have seen</line>
            <line>May be the devil: and the devil hath power</line>
            <line>To assume a pleasing shape; yea, and perhaps</line>
            <line>Out of my weakness and my melancholy,</line>
            <line>As he is very potent with such spirits,</line>
            <line>Abuses me to damn me: I'll have grounds</line>
            <line>More relative than this: the play 's the thing</line>
            <line>Wherein I'll catch the conscience of the king.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>