<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE learningContent
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Learning Content//EN" "learningContent.dtd">
<learningContent id="SEC005_001">
   <title>5.1 A second major discovery</title>
   <learningContentbody>
      <section>
          
          <p>In the introduction to this unit, we said that there were three pillars of
            evidence for the big bang. We now turn to the second. It rests on a discovery that ranks
            in importance with that of Hubble's law. It came about when observations in a new region
            of the electromagnetic spectrum – the microwave region – became possible.
            This was due to the invention of new detectors, working at frequencies as high as 30 000
            MHz. In 1965, two Bell Telephone scientists, A. Penzias and R. Wilson, were
            investigating the radio noise found at wavelengths between a few millimetres and a few
            centimetres. These wavelengths were, at the time, a relatively untapped field for
            communications. (They are now very useful for satellites because even small antennae
            give narrow beams at these wavelengths. Penzias and Wilson were working on the
            Telstar/Echo satellite project at that time.)</p>
          <p>They found that, once all known sources of noise had been accounted for, they
            were left with a residual signal which was coming equally from all directions. It was
            soon realised that because of this isotropy, it could not originate on the Earth, or in
            the Solar System. Nor could it be coming even from the Galaxy – the Galaxy being
            a thin disc, with us not at its centre.</p>
          
          <sectiondiv outputclass="SAQ">
            <p outputclass="Heading">
               <b>Question 9</b>
            </p>
            <sectiondiv outputclass="saq.question">
              <p>Consider our Galaxy to be a uniform disc which is generating radio waves
                uniformly throughout its volume (<xref href="#FIG001_016">Figure 19</xref>). Assume for the purposes of this question
                that all other radio sources are negligible. Also assume that the Earth is in the
                central plane of the disc but off centre (nearer the edge than the centre) and that
                it is at rest in the Galaxy. <i>Sketch</i> graphs showing the way the signal picked
                up by a radio telescope on Earth will vary when the telescope rotates:</p>
              <p>(a) in the plane of the
                Galaxy;</p>
               <p>(b) in a plane
                perpendicular to the Galaxy.</p>
              <fig>
                  <title>
                     <b>Figure 19</b>: The Earth inside the Galaxy, shown schematically as a
                  disc</title>
                  <image href="../../media/S357_1_016i.jpg"/>
                  <p/>
               </fig>
            </sectiondiv>
            <sectiondiv outputclass="saq.answer">
              <p>
                  <b>(a)</b> If <i>φ</i> is the angle between the direction of the
                telescope and the line from the centre of the Galaxy to the telescope, with
                  <i>φ</i> = 0 corresponding to looking directly away from the
                centre of the Galaxy, then, if the telescope is swept round in the plane of the
                Galaxy, the variation of intensity <i>W</i> of radio waves with φ will be that
                shown in <xref href="#FIG001_034">Figure 18</xref>(a).</p>
              <p>
                  <b>(b)</b> If <i>θ</i> is the angle between the direction of the
                telescope and a line drawn perpendicular to the plane of the Galaxy at the
                telescope, with <i>θ</i> = 0 corresponding to looking directly
                ‘upwards’ through the disc, then the variation of intensity <i>W</i>
                of radio waves with <i>θ</i> will be as shown in <xref href="#FIG001_034">Figure 18</xref> (b).</p>
              <fig>
                  <title>
                     <b>Figure 18</b>: Variation of intensity of radio waves with angle (a) in the
                  plane of the Galaxy, and (b) in a plane perpendicular to the Galaxy</title>
                  <image href="../../media/S357_1_034i.jpg"/>
                  <p/>
               </fig>
            </sectiondiv>
          </sectiondiv>
          <p>Having separated out these other sources of background noise, it was concluded
            that the isotropic component had to be of cosmic origin. It is called the <i>cosmic
              microwave background radiation</i>.</p>
          
          <p>
            <xref href="#FIG001_017">Figure 20</xref>(a) shows how complicated the overall microwave
            spectrum is, due largely to a set of lines generated in the Earth's atmosphere. <xref href="#FIG001_017">Figure 20</xref>(b) focuses on the region at the left-hand side
            of <xref href="#FIG001_017">Figure 20</xref>(a). This region is of interest because it is
            at lower frequencies than most of the atmospheric lines. The atmospheric interference
            varies with the thickness of the atmosphere, and hence with the angle of observation.
            This noise can therefore be separated out from the cosmic signal in which we are
            interested. <xref href="#FIG001_017">Figure 20</xref>(b) shows the microwave spectrum after
            correcting for the effects of the atmosphere.</p>
          <fig>
            <title>
              <b>Figure 20</b>: (a) The overall ground-based microwave spectrum. (b) Ground-based
              measurements by Penzias and Wilson, and by other observers, of the microwave intensity
              at various frequencies; an enlargement of the spectrum shown at the left-hand side of
              (a), corrected to remove the effects of the atmosphere. The shaded area represents the
              limits given by measurements made with a detector that covered a wide band of
              frequencies. (The solid line shows a thermal spectrum corresponding to a temperature
              of 2.8 K. The term ‘thermal spectrum’ is explained a little later in the
              text.)</title>
            <image href="../../media/S357_1_017i.jpg"/>
            <p outputclass="SourceReference">Source: (a) based on D.P. Woody <i>et al.</i> (1975) in <i>Phys. Rev.
              Lett.</i>, 34, 1036–9; (b) based on R.A. Muller (1978) in <i>Scientific
                American</i>, 238, 64–74 <data name="ItemRights">
                  <data name="OwnerRef"/>
                  <data name="ItemRef"/>
                  <data name="ItemAcknowledgement">(a) based on D.P. Woody <i>et al.</i> (1975) in <i>Phys. Rev.
                    Lett.</i>, 34, 1036–9; (b) based on R.A. Muller (1978) in <i>Scientific
                    American</i>, 238, 64–74</data>
              </data>
            </p>
            <p/>
         </fig>
          <p>In 1989, the COBE satellite was launched. It was able to make measurements from
            above the Earth's atmosphere and was therefore not subject to some of the problems
            encountered by Penzias and Wilson, and by other ground-based observers. However, a major
            contaminant – radiation originating from within the Galaxy – remained. The
            COBE results, after correction for this effect, are shown in <xref href="#FIG001_018">Figure 21</xref>.</p>
          <p>The shape revealed by this closer look is identical to that found for the
            spectrum inside a hot cavity – for example the spectrum in an oven or furnace (<xref href="#FIG001_019">Figure 22</xref>). It is called a ‘black body’
            spectrum (because it is that which is given out by an idealised heated black surface),
            or simply a <i>‘thermal’ spectrum</i>.</p>
          
          <fig>
            <title>
              <b>Figure 21</b>: Data on the microwave background radiation taken by the COBE
              satellite. The curve through the data points is that of a thermal spectrum of 2.73 K.
              Note that Figure 20(b) had a logarithmic frequency scale, while this one is
              linear</title>
            <image href="../../media/S357_1_018i.jpg"/>
            <p outputclass="SourceReference">Source: courtesy of NASA/CSFC and COBE Science Working Group <data name="ItemRights">
                  <data name="OwnerRef"/>
                  <data name="ItemRef"/>
                  <data name="ItemAcknowledgement">courtesy of NASA/CSFC and COBE Science Working
                  Group</data>
              </data>
            </p>
            <p/>
         </fig>
          <fig>
            <title>
              <b>Figure 22</b>: Thermal spectra for various temperatures, <i>T</i>, based on
              laboratory measurements of relative intensity, <i>W</i>, of radiation with frequency
                <i>f</i>
            </title>
            <image href="../../media/S357_1_019i.jpg"/>
            <p/>
         </fig>
          <p>One of the basic features of thermal radiation is that, regardless of the
            temperature of the surface or enclosure generating it, the <i>shape</i> of the spectrum
            is always the same. The <i>peak</i> of the spectrum moves up to higher frequencies as
            the temperature rises (it might glow red hot or white hot). But the basic shape remains
            the same. What this means is that if the spectra for two different temperatures are
            drawn on two graphs, we can always choose scales – linear but different –
            so that the graphs can be superimposed (<xref href="#FIG001_020">Figures 23</xref> and <xref href="#FIG001_021">24</xref>). This single, characteristic shape arises from, and
            is an indicator of, the equilibrium conditions inside the oven. The rescaling in <xref href="#FIG001_020">Figure 23</xref> works <i>only</i> for thermal spectra, and so
            is a true indicator of equilibrium.</p>
          <p>As an example of the opposite extreme, take the line spectra from a hydrogen
            lamp and a sodium lamp. No amount of rescaling would fit these two together; they are
            quite distinct.</p>
          <fig>
            <title>
              <b>Figure 23</b>: What is meant by the shapes of thermal spectra being independent of
              temperature: (a) is the measured spectrum at 998 K (from Figure 22); (b) is obtained
              from (a) by expanding the vertical scale by a factor of
                (1646﻿/﻿998)﻿<sup>3</sup>; (c) is obtained from (b) by
              expanding the horizontal scale by a factor of (1646/998); (d) is the measured spectrum
              at 1646 K (from Figure 22) plotted using the same scales as those in (a), and is the
              same curve as (c).</title>
            <image href="../../media/S357_1_020i.jpg"/>
            <p/>
         </fig>
          <fig>
            <title>
              <b>Figure 24</b>: As suggested by Figure 23, a plot of <i>W/T</i>
               <sup>3</sup> as a
              function of <i>f/T</i> is a single curve, for all temperatures; that is, if
                <i>W/T</i>
               <sup>3</sup> is plotted against <i>f</i>/<i>T</i> for a number of
              frequencies and temperatures, the plotted points for all frequencies and temperatures
              lie on one and the same curve</title>
            <image href="../../media/S357_1_021i.jpg"/>
            <p/>
         </fig>
          
          <p>Since the cosmic microwave spectrum has a thermal shape; the conclusion is that
            it was generated in equilibrium conditions – in some sort of cavity. But the
            radiation fills the Universe: the ‘cavity’ is the Universe itself, a
            cavity with no walls.</p>
          <p>The word ‘equilibrium’ is used here with some reservations. The
            Universe has not reached overall equilibrium, and strictly speaking never will. This is
            because of the expansion of the Universe. We saw in <xref href="#SEC004_001">Section 4.1</xref> how the wavelength of light from distant
            galaxies is redshifted due to the expansion of the Universe. It turns out that the same
            thing happens to the microwave background radiation; its wavelength is also increased.
            The peak frequency of the spectrum is reduced, and this means the radiation is
            progressively cooling. Hence the radiation has not strictly speaking reached
            equilibrium. However, the processes which transferred energy between radiation and
            matter in the early Universe were so rapid that it is meaningful to think of a
            quasi-equilibrium state having been attained at an early time, with the temperature
            gradually falling subsequently because of the expansion of the Universe.</p>
          <p>A second feature of the thermal spectrum is that if the detector is situated
            within the ‘oven’ generating it (as distinct from looking at a distant
            black surface or opening to an oven), the intensity of the radiation at any particular
            frequency uniquely identifies the thermal curve to which it belongs, i.e. what the
            temperature of the ‘oven’ is. So, if <xref href="#FIG001_019">Figure 22</xref> referred to thermal spectra picked up by a
            detector situated <i>inside</i> an oven, the ordinate of the graph could be expressed in
            terms of <i>absolute</i>, rather than <i>relative</i> intensities. Under these
            circumstances, a measurement of intensity at a single frequency, say
              60 × 10<sup>12</sup> Hz, would be sufficient to identify which curve
            that data point belonged to, and hence what the temperature of the oven was.</p>
          
          <p>Inasmuch as the Universe can be regarded as an ‘oven’, and we are
            in it, Penzias and Wilson were able to estimate from the intensity of the radiation at
            the single frequency they were detecting that the temperature was about 3 K. For this
            reason, the cosmic microwave background radiation is often called the <i>3 K
              radiation</i>. The spectrum observed by COBE allowed a more precise estimate of the
            temperature, namely 2.73 K. This is based on the results presented in <xref href="#FIG001_018">Figure 21</xref>, where it should be noted that the data points
            do not deviate from the thermal curve by more than 0.03%, this being consistent with
            measurement precision.</p>
          <p>In the 1940s, some theoreticians already had an inkling that this radiation
            should exist, from the predictions of their cosmological models. The Abbe Georges
            Lemaitre, a Belgian cosmologist, was the first to see clearly (around 1927) that the
            expansion of the Universe pointed back to a ‘big bang’. But he could not
            get much further because not enough was known about nuclear physics at that time. It was
            George Gamow and his colleagues, in 1948, who first saw that very high temperatures must
            be involved at early times in an expanding Universe. They sketched out some nuclear
            reactions that must therefore have taken place. By 1953, their reconstruction had been
            refined and gave definite predictions for nuclear abundances – and radiation
            intensity. It was at this stage they realised that radiation had been a vital component
            in the early Universe and that this same radiation, albeit substantially redshifted and
            cooled, should still be around today (there being no other place for it to go!). In the
            1950s, radio equipment already existed which was sensitive enough to detect this
            radiation. Indeed, radio astronomy was developing fast, based at first on the technology
            of military radar in World War II. So by 1953 the stage was set for this radiation to be
            discovered. But as it so happened, the two groups, theoretical and experimental, did not
            stumble into each other for another 12 years. Despite conferences and journals,
            scientific communication with New Jersey was not as effective as communication over
              10<sup>10</sup> light-years! When theory and observation finally came together, the
            question of priority took some sorting out, as indicated in Gamow's letter, reproduced
            as <xref href="#FIG001_022">Figure 25</xref>.</p>
          <fig>
            <title>
              <b>Figure 25</b>: A letter from George Gamow to Arno Penzias</title>
            <image href="../../media/S357_1_022i.jpg"/>
            <p outputclass="SourceReference">Source: courtesy of Dr A.A. Penzias <data name="ItemRights">
                  <data name="OwnerRef"/>
                  <data name="ItemRef"/>
                  <data name="ItemAcknowledgement">courtesy of Dr A.A. Penzias</data>
              </data>
            </p>
            <p/>
         </fig>
          <p>The reference to ‘almighty Dicke’ at the end of this letter
            concerns R. H. Dicke, the leader of a group at Princeton University (also in New Jersey)
            which was pursuing both theoretical and observational research into the background
            radiation in the 1960s. The paper by Penzias and Wilson announcing their discovery, and
            a paper by Dicke's group providing a possible cosmological interpretation, were
            published back to back in volume 142 of the <i>Astrophysical Journal</i> in
            1965.</p>
          <p>The spectrum of thermal radiation at a given temperature <i>T</i> can be
            expressed in terms of a function <i>W</i>(<i>f</i>, <i>T</i>) which gives the intensity
            of radiation of frequency <i>f</i>. The energy density of that part of the radiation
            with frequencies lying between <i>f</i> and <i>f</i> + Δ<i>f</i> is given by
              <i>W</i>(<i>f</i>, <i>T</i>) Δ<i>f</i>. The formula for <i>W</i>(<i>f</i>,
              <i>T</i>) was derived by Max Planck in 1900:</p>
          <fig outputclass="Equation">
            <image href="../../media/S357_1_e007i.gif"/>
            <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
         </fig>
          <p>where <i>A</i> and <i>B</i> are constants. At low frequencies (<i>f</i>
            ≪
            <i>T</i>/<i>B</i>), one can use a simpler approximate formula:</p>
          <fig outputclass="Equation">
            <image href="../../media/S357_1_e008i.gif"/>
            <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
         </fig>
          <sectiondiv outputclass="Activity">
            <p outputclass="Heading">
               <b>Study comment</b>
            </p>
            <sectiondiv outputclass="activity.question">
              <p>We suggest that you do not omit
                <xref href="#SAQ001_010">Question 10</xref> as it contains information that will be
                needed later.</p>
            </sectiondiv>
          </sectiondiv>
          
          <sectiondiv outputclass="SAQ">
            <p outputclass="Heading">
               <b>Question 10</b>
            </p>
            <sectiondiv outputclass="saq.question">
              
              <p>(a) Verify the result represented by <xref href="#FIG001_021">Figure 24</xref>, that <i>W/T</i>
                  <sup>3</sup> is a function
                of <i>f/T</i> only, which applies for all frequencies and temperatures.</p>
              
              <p>(b) Use the result of (a) to show that maximum intensity occurs at a
                frequency, <i>f</i>
                  <sub>max</sub>, which is proportional to the
                temperature.</p>
              
              <p>(c) Imagine that you receive a radio message from a very distant galaxy,
                informing you about measurements of the cosmic background radiation at various
                frequencies (defined in terms of fractions of the frequency of a standard spectral
                line). These results do not agree with your own measurements of the radiation. In
                particular, you find that the quoted value of the maximum intensity is <i>eight</i>
                times your value and occurs at a frequency that is <i>twice</i> your frequency for
                maximum intensity. You find that the quoted intensities at low frequencies are
                  <i>twice</i> your values at the same frequencies. How can you explain these
                discrepancies? (You may assume that the discrepancy is not due to calibration or
                other errors.)</p>
              
            </sectiondiv>
            <sectiondiv outputclass="saq.answer">
              <p>
                  <b>(a)</b> Let <i>y</i> = <i>W</i>/<i>T</i>
                  <sup>3</sup> and
                  <i>x</i> = <i>f</i>/<i>T</i>. Then</p>
              <fig outputclass="Equation">
                  <image href="../../media/S357_1_ue039i.gif"/>
                  <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
               </fig>
              <p>which shows that <i>W</i>/<i>T</i>
                  <sup>3</sup> is a function of
                  <i>f</i>/<i>T</i> only.</p>
              <p>
                  <b>(b)</b> From the above expression for <i>y</i>, we see there must be a
                universal value of <i>x</i> which gives a maximum value of <i>y</i>. But a maximum
                value of <i>y</i> implies a maximum value of <i>W</i> at a given temperature. If we
                denote this value of <i>x</i> by the constant <i>x</i>
                  <sub>max</sub>, it follows
                that</p>
              <fig outputclass="Equation">
                  <image href="../../media/S357_1_ue040i.gif"/>
                  <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
               </fig>
              <p>and hence that</p>
              <fig outputclass="Equation">
                  <image href="../../media/S357_1_ue041i.gif"/>
                  <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
               </fig>
              <p>Thus the frequency, <i>f</i>
                  <sub>max</sub> which gives maximum intensity is
                proportional to the temperature <i>T</i>. (You might have heard of this relation
                referred to as Wien's displacement law.)</p>
              <p>
                  <b>(c)</b> The explanation is that the cosmic background radiation has
                cooled during the time it took for the radio message to reach you. The discrepancies
                between their results and yours can all be explained by this difference in
                temperature of the radiation.</p>
              <p>In part (b), it was shown that the frequency, <i>f</i>
                  <sub>max</sub>,
                corresponding to maximum intensity, is proportional to <i>T</i>. Since their value
                of <i>f</i>
                  <sub>max</sub> is twice yours, the temperature of the cosmic background
                radiation then must have been twice what it is here and now, i.e. it must have been
                just under 6 K.</p>
              <p>In part (a), it was shown that:</p>
              <fig outputclass="Equation">
                  <image href="../../media/S357_1_ue042i.gif"/>
                  <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
               </fig>
              <p>If the maximum intensity is <i>W</i>
                  <sub>max</sub>, it follows
                that</p>
              <fig outputclass="Equation">
                  <image href="../../media/S357_1_ue043i.gif"/>
                  <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
               </fig>
              <p>which is independent of <i>T</i> since <i>x</i>
                  <sub>max</sub> is a
                universal constant from part (b). Hence</p>
              <fig outputclass="Equation">
                  <image href="../../media/S357_1_ue044i.gif"/>
                  <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
               </fig>
              <p>which is why their value of <i>W</i>
                  <sub>max</sub> is
                2<sup>3</sup> = 8 times yours.</p>
              <p>Finally, Equation 8 shows that the intensity at a given low frequency is
                proportional to the temperature and hence will be twice what you measure now at the
                  <i>same</i> low frequency.</p>
            </sectiondiv>
          </sectiondiv>
          
          <sectiondiv outputclass="SAQ">
            <p outputclass="Heading">
               <b>Question 11</b>
            </p>
            <sectiondiv outputclass="saq.question">
              
              <p>(a) On the basis of your solutions to parts (a) and (b) of <xref href="#SAQ001_010">Question 10</xref>, which would be hotter, a red star or a
                yellow star?</p>
              
              <p>(b) The curves of <xref href="#FIG001_019">Figure 22</xref> can be used to extrapolate results to
                lower temperatures. By taking a measurement off the figure, and using the result of <xref href="#SAQ001_010">Question 10</xref>(b), estimate the frequency of the
                intensity maximum for radiation emitted by a body at room temperature. What is the
                term used to describe electromagnetic radiation in this frequency range?</p>
              
            </sectiondiv>
            <sectiondiv outputclass="saq.answer">
              <p>
                  <b>(a)</b> We have already established (in part (b) of the previous
                question) that the frequency of maximum intensity increases proportionately with
                temperature. As yellow light has a higher frequency than red light we would expect
                the yellow star to be the hotter.</p>
              <p>
                  <b>(b)</b> From <xref href="#FIG001_019">Figure 22</xref>, we see that the maximum intensity for a
                temperature of, say, 1646 K occurs at a frequency of about
                  92 × 10<sup>12</sup> Hz. The maximum for room temperature, taken to
                be 300 K, is then given by
                  (300/1646) × 92 × 10<sup>12</sup> Hz = 16.8 × 10<sup>12</sup> Hz.</p>
              <p>Radiation of this frequency occurs in the infrared part of the
                spectrum.</p>
            </sectiondiv>
          </sectiondiv>
        </section>
   </learningContentbody>
</learningContent>