<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:concept" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="conceptId">
 <title>Graph Visualization of DITA Content Using GraphViz</title>
 <shortdesc>The net.sf.dita4publishers.graphviz transform type provides a general framework for using the GraphViz tool to generate different node-and-arc graph visualizations of DITA content.</shortdesc>
  <prolog>
    <metadata>
      <keywords>
        <indexterm>graph</indexterm>
        <indexterm>visualization</indexterm>
        <indexterm>GraphViz</indexterm>
      </keywords>
    </metadata>
  </prolog>
 <conbody>
   <p>The GraphViz tool (<xref
      href="http://graphviz.org"
      format="html"
      scope="external">http://graphviz.org</xref>) is an open-source node-and-arc graph layout and rendering tool that uses a simple data format ("DOT") as input. This data format is easy to generate from DITA content (or anything else from which a node-and-arc representation can be generated). For example, the back-of-the-book index graph for this publication is in <xref
      href="#conceptId/fig-gv-01"
      format="dita"/>.</p>
    <fig
      id="fig-gv-01">
      <title>Generated index graph for the DITA for Publishers Users Guide</title>
      <image
        href="graphics/d4p-users-guide.png"/>
    </fig>
    <p>The net.sf.dita4publishers.graphviz Toolkit Plugin provides an XLST function package for creating the DOT data file and two graph generation options: a navigation tree graph and an index graph.</p>
    <p>The graphviz transform type can be used as the base for other visualizations. Interesting visualizations might include task-to-task dependency graphs, relationship-table relationships, topic-to-topic dependencies based on cross references or content references, and so on.</p>
    <p>The graphviz transformation type includes the Ant code needed to run the graphviz <cmdname>dot</cmdname> command-line tool to generate graphics from DOT data sets.</p>
 </conbody>
</concept>
