<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:shakespear:dtd:act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-4">
   <title>ACT IV</title>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  PETRUCHIO'S country house.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter GRUMIO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>Fie, fie on all tired jades, on all mad masters, and</line>
            <line>all foul ways! Was ever man so beaten? was ever</line>
            <line>man so rayed? was ever man so weary? I am sent</line>
            <line>before to make a fire, and they are coming after to</line>
            <line>warm them. Now, were not I a little pot and soon</line>
            <line>hot, my very lips might freeze to my teeth, my</line>
            <line>tongue to the roof of my mouth, my heart in my</line>
            <line>belly, ere I should come by a fire to thaw me: but</line>
            <line>I, with blowing the fire, shall warm myself; for,</line>
            <line>considering the weather, a taller man than I will</line>
            <line>take cold. Holla, ho! Curtis.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter CURTIS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CURTIS</speaker>
            <line>Who is that calls so coldly?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>A piece of ice: if thou doubt it, thou mayst slide</line>
            <line>from my shoulder to my heel with no greater a run</line>
            <line>but my head and my neck. A fire good Curtis.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CURTIS</speaker>
            <line>Is my master and his wife coming, Grumio?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>O, ay, Curtis, ay: and therefore fire, fire; cast</line>
            <line>on no water.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CURTIS</speaker>
            <line>Is she so hot a shrew as she's reported?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>She was, good Curtis, before this frost: but, thou</line>
            <line>knowest, winter tames man, woman and beast; for it</line>
            <line>hath tamed my old master and my new mistress and</line>
            <line>myself, fellow Curtis.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CURTIS</speaker>
            <line>Away, you three-inch fool! I am no beast.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>Am I but three inches? why, thy horn is a foot; and</line>
            <line>so long am I at the least. But wilt thou make a</line>
            <line>fire, or shall I complain on thee to our mistress,</line>
            <line>whose hand, she being now at hand, thou shalt soon</line>
            <line>feel, to thy cold comfort, for being slow in thy hot office?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CURTIS</speaker>
            <line>I prithee, good Grumio, tell me, how goes the world?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>A cold world, Curtis, in every office but thine; and</line>
            <line>therefore fire: do thy duty, and have thy duty; for</line>
            <line>my master and mistress are almost frozen to death.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CURTIS</speaker>
            <line>There's fire ready; and therefore, good Grumio, the news.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>Why, 'Jack, boy! ho! boy!' and as much news as</line>
            <line>will thaw.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CURTIS</speaker>
            <line>Come, you are so full of cony-catching!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>Why, therefore fire; for I have caught extreme cold.</line>
            <line>Where's the cook? is supper ready, the house</line>
            <line>trimmed, rushes strewed, cobwebs swept; the</line>
            <line>serving-men in their new fustian, their white</line>
            <line>stockings, and every officer his wedding-garment on?</line>
            <line>Be the jacks fair within, the jills fair without,</line>
            <line>the carpets laid, and every thing in order?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CURTIS</speaker>
            <line>All ready; and therefore, I pray thee, news.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>First, know, my horse is tired; my master and</line>
            <line>mistress fallen out.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CURTIS</speaker>
            <line>How?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>Out of their saddles into the dirt; and thereby</line>
            <line>hangs a tale.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CURTIS</speaker>
            <line>Let's ha't, good Grumio.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>Lend thine ear.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CURTIS</speaker>
            <line>Here.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>There.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Strikes him</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CURTIS</speaker>
            <line>This is to feel a tale, not to hear a tale.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>And therefore 'tis called a sensible tale: and this</line>
            <line>cuff was but to knock at your ear, and beseech</line>
            <line>listening. Now I begin: Imprimis, we came down a</line>
            <line>foul hill, my master riding behind my mistress,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CURTIS</speaker>
            <line>Both of one horse?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>What's that to thee?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CURTIS</speaker>
            <line>Why, a horse.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>Tell thou the tale: but hadst thou not crossed me,</line>
            <line>thou shouldst have heard how her horse fell and she</line>
            <line>under her horse; thou shouldst have heard in how</line>
            <line>miry a place, how she was bemoiled, how he left her</line>
            <line>with the horse upon her, how he beat me because</line>
            <line>her horse stumbled, how she waded through the dirt</line>
            <line>to pluck him off me, how he swore, how she prayed,</line>
            <line>that never prayed before, how I cried, how the</line>
            <line>horses ran away, how her bridle was burst, how I</line>
            <line>lost my crupper, with many things of worthy memory,</line>
            <line>which now shall die in oblivion and thou return</line>
            <line>unexperienced to thy grave.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CURTIS</speaker>
            <line>By this reckoning he is more shrew than she.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>Ay; and that thou and the proudest of you all shall</line>
            <line>find when he comes home. But what talk I of this?</line>
            <line>Call forth Nathaniel, Joseph, Nicholas, Philip,</line>
            <line>Walter, Sugarsop and the rest: let their heads be</line>
            <line>sleekly combed their blue coats brushed and their</line>
            <line>garters of an indifferent knit: let them curtsy</line>
            <line>with their left legs and not presume to touch a hair</line>
            <line>of my master's horse-tail till they kiss their</line>
            <line>hands. Are they all ready?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CURTIS</speaker>
            <line>They are.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>Call them forth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CURTIS</speaker>
            <line>Do you hear, ho? you must meet my master to</line>
            <line>countenance my mistress.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>Why, she hath a face of her own.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CURTIS</speaker>
            <line>Who knows not that?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>Thou, it seems, that calls for company to</line>
            <line>countenance her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CURTIS</speaker>
            <line>I call them forth to credit her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>Why, she comes to borrow nothing of them.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter four or five Serving-men</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NATHANIEL</speaker>
            <line>Welcome home, Grumio!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PHILIP</speaker>
            <line>How now, Grumio!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOSEPH</speaker>
            <line>What, Grumio!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NICHOLAS</speaker>
            <line>Fellow Grumio!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NATHANIEL</speaker>
            <line>How now, old lad?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>Welcome, you;--how now, you;-- what, you;--fellow,</line>
            <line>you;--and thus much for greeting. Now, my spruce</line>
            <line>companions, is all ready, and all things neat?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NATHANIEL</speaker>
            <line>All things is ready. How near is our master?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>E'en at hand, alighted by this; and therefore be</line>
            <line>not--Cock's passion, silence! I hear my master.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter PETRUCHIO and KATHARINA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>Where be these knaves? What, no man at door</line>
            <line>To hold my stirrup nor to take my horse!</line>
            <line>Where is Nathaniel, Gregory, Philip?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALL SERVING-MEN</speaker>
            <line>Here, here, sir; here, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>Here, sir! here, sir! here, sir! here, sir!</line>
            <line>You logger-headed and unpolish'd grooms!</line>
            <line>What, no attendance? no regard? no duty?</line>
            <line>Where is the foolish knave I sent before?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>Here, sir; as foolish as I was before.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>You peasant swain! you whoreson malt-horse drudge!</line>
            <line>Did I not bid thee meet me in the park,</line>
            <line>And bring along these rascal knaves with thee?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>Nathaniel's coat, sir, was not fully made,</line>
            <line>And Gabriel's pumps were all unpink'd i' the heel;</line>
            <line>There was no link to colour Peter's hat,</line>
            <line>And Walter's dagger was not come from sheathing:</line>
            <line>There were none fine but Adam, Ralph, and Gregory;</line>
            <line>The rest were ragged, old, and beggarly;</line>
            <line>Yet, as they are, here are they come to meet you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>Go, rascals, go, and fetch my supper in.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt Servants</stagedir>
            <stagedir>Singing</stagedir>
            <line>Where is the life that late I led--</line>
            <line>Where are those--Sit down, Kate, and welcome.--</line>
            <line>Sound, sound, sound, sound!</line>
            <stagedir>Re-enter Servants with supper</stagedir>
            <line>Why, when, I say? Nay, good sweet Kate, be merry.</line>
            <line>Off with my boots, you rogues! you villains, when?</line>
            <stagedir>Sings</stagedir>
            <line>It was the friar of orders grey,</line>
            <line>As he forth walked on his way:--</line>
            <line>Out, you rogue! you pluck my foot awry:</line>
            <line>Take that, and mend the plucking off the other.</line>
            <stagedir>Strikes him</stagedir>
            <line>Be merry, Kate. Some water, here; what, ho!</line>
            <line>Where's my spaniel Troilus? Sirrah, get you hence,</line>
            <line>And bid my cousin Ferdinand come hither:</line>
            <line>One, Kate, that you must kiss, and be acquainted with.</line>
            <line>Where are my slippers? Shall I have some water?</line>
            <stagedir>Enter one with water</stagedir>
            <line>Come, Kate, and wash, and welcome heartily.</line>
            <line>You whoreson villain! will you let it fall?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Strikes him</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KATHARINA</speaker>
            <line>Patience, I pray you; 'twas a fault unwilling.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>A whoreson beetle-headed, flap-ear'd knave!</line>
            <line>Come, Kate, sit down; I know you have a stomach.</line>
            <line>Will you give thanks, sweet Kate; or else shall I?</line>
            <line>What's this? mutton?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Servant</speaker>
            <line>Ay.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>Who brought it?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETER</speaker>
            <line>I.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>'Tis burnt; and so is all the meat.</line>
            <line>What dogs are these! Where is the rascal cook?</line>
            <line>How durst you, villains, bring it from the dresser,</line>
            <line>And serve it thus to me that love it not?</line>
            <line>Theretake it to you, trenchers, cups, and all;</line>
            <stagedir>Throws the meat, &amp;c. about the stage</stagedir>
            <line>You heedless joltheads and unmanner'd slaves!</line>
            <line>What, do you grumble? I'll be with you straight.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KATHARINA</speaker>
            <line>I pray you, husband, be not so disquiet:</line>
            <line>The meat was well, if you were so contented.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>I tell thee, Kate, 'twas burnt and dried away;</line>
            <line>And I expressly am forbid to touch it,</line>
            <line>For it engenders choler, planteth anger;</line>
            <line>And better 'twere that both of us did fast,</line>
            <line>Since, of ourselves, ourselves are choleric,</line>
            <line>Than feed it with such over-roasted flesh.</line>
            <line>Be patient; to-morrow 't shall be mended,</line>
            <line>And, for this night, we'll fast for company:</line>
            <line>Come, I will bring thee to thy bridal chamber.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Re-enter Servants severally</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NATHANIEL</speaker>
            <line>Peter, didst ever see the like?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETER</speaker>
            <line>He kills her in her own humour.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter CURTIS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>Where is he?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CURTIS</speaker>
            <line>In her chamber, making a sermon of continency to her;</line>
            <line>And rails, and swears, and rates, that she, poor soul,</line>
            <line>Knows not which way to stand, to look, to speak,</line>
            <line>And sits as one new-risen from a dream.</line>
            <line>Away, away! for he is coming hither.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Re-enter PETRUCHIO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>Thus have I politicly begun my reign,</line>
            <line>And 'tis my hope to end successfully.</line>
            <line>My falcon now is sharp and passing empty;</line>
            <line>And till she stoop she must not be full-gorged,</line>
            <line>For then she never looks upon her lure.</line>
            <line>Another way I have to man my haggard,</line>
            <line>To make her come and know her keeper's call,</line>
            <line>That is, to watch her, as we watch these kites</line>
            <line>That bate and beat and will not be obedient.</line>
            <line>She eat no meat to-day, nor none shall eat;</line>
            <line>Last night she slept not, nor to-night she shall not;</line>
            <line>As with the meat, some undeserved fault</line>
            <line>I'll find about the making of the bed;</line>
            <line>And here I'll fling the pillow, there the bolster,</line>
            <line>This way the coverlet, another way the sheets:</line>
            <line>Ay, and amid this hurly I intend</line>
            <line>That all is done in reverend care of her;</line>
            <line>And in conclusion she shall watch all night:</line>
            <line>And if she chance to nod I'll rail and brawl</line>
            <line>And with the clamour keep her still awake.</line>
            <line>This is a way to kill a wife with kindness;</line>
            <line>And thus I'll curb her mad and headstrong humour.</line>
            <line>He that knows better how to tame a shrew,</line>
            <line>Now let him speak: 'tis charity to show.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  Padua. Before BAPTISTA'S house.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter TRANIO and HORTENSIO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRANIO</speaker>
            <line>Is't possible, friend Licio, that Mistress Bianca</line>
            <line>Doth fancy any other but Lucentio?</line>
            <line>I tell you, sir, she bears me fair in hand.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HORTENSIO</speaker>
            <line>Sir, to satisfy you in what I have said,</line>
            <line>Stand by and mark the manner of his teaching.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter BIANCA and LUCENTIO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>Now, mistress, profit you in what you read?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIANCA</speaker>
            <line>What, master, read you? first resolve me that.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>I read that I profess, the Art to Love.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIANCA</speaker>
            <line>And may you prove, sir, master of your art!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>While you, sweet dear, prove mistress of my heart!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HORTENSIO</speaker>
            <line>Quick proceeders, marry! Now, tell me, I pray,</line>
            <line>You that durst swear at your mistress Bianca</line>
            <line>Loved none in the world so well as Lucentio.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRANIO</speaker>
            <line>O despiteful love! unconstant womankind!</line>
            <line>I tell thee, Licio, this is wonderful.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HORTENSIO</speaker>
            <line>Mistake no more: I am not Licio,</line>
            <line>Nor a musician, as I seem to be;</line>
            <line>But one that scorn to live in this disguise,</line>
            <line>For such a one as leaves a gentleman,</line>
            <line>And makes a god of such a cullion:</line>
            <line>Know, sir, that I am call'd Hortensio.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRANIO</speaker>
            <line>Signior Hortensio, I have often heard</line>
            <line>Of your entire affection to Bianca;</line>
            <line>And since mine eyes are witness of her lightness,</line>
            <line>I will with you, if you be so contented,</line>
            <line>Forswear Bianca and her love for ever.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HORTENSIO</speaker>
            <line>See, how they kiss and court! Signior Lucentio,</line>
            <line>Here is my hand, and here I firmly vow</line>
            <line>Never to woo her no more, but do forswear her,</line>
            <line>As one unworthy all the former favours</line>
            <line>That I have fondly flatter'd her withal.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRANIO</speaker>
            <line>And here I take the unfeigned oath,</line>
            <line>Never to marry with her though she would entreat:</line>
            <line>Fie on her! see, how beastly she doth court him!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HORTENSIO</speaker>
            <line>Would all the world but he had quite forsworn!</line>
            <line>For me, that I may surely keep mine oath,</line>
            <line>I will be married to a wealthy widow,</line>
            <line>Ere three days pass, which hath as long loved me</line>
            <line>As I have loved this proud disdainful haggard.</line>
            <line>And so farewell, Signior Lucentio.</line>
            <line>Kindness in women, not their beauteous looks,</line>
            <line>Shall win my love: and so I take my leave,</line>
            <line>In resolution as I swore before.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRANIO</speaker>
            <line>Mistress Bianca, bless you with such grace</line>
            <line>As 'longeth to a lover's blessed case!</line>
            <line>Nay, I have ta'en you napping, gentle love,</line>
            <line>And have forsworn you with Hortensio.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIANCA</speaker>
            <line>Tranio, you jest: but have you both forsworn me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRANIO</speaker>
            <line>Mistress, we have.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>Then we are rid of Licio.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRANIO</speaker>
            <line>I' faith, he'll have a lusty widow now,</line>
            <line>That shall be wood and wedded in a day.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIANCA</speaker>
            <line>God give him joy!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRANIO</speaker>
            <line>Ay, and he'll tame her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIANCA</speaker>
            <line>He says so, Tranio.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRANIO</speaker>
            <line>Faith, he is gone unto the taming-school.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIANCA</speaker>
            <line>The taming-school! what, is there such a place?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRANIO</speaker>
            <line>Ay, mistress, and Petruchio is the master;</line>
            <line>That teacheth tricks eleven and twenty long,</line>
            <line>To tame a shrew and charm her chattering tongue.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter BIONDELLO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIONDELLO</speaker>
            <line>O master, master, I have watch'd so long</line>
            <line>That I am dog-weary: but at last I spied</line>
            <line>An ancient angel coming down the hill,</line>
            <line>Will serve the turn.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRANIO</speaker>
            <line>What is he, Biondello?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIONDELLO</speaker>
            <line>Master, a mercatante, or a pedant,</line>
            <line>I know not what; but format in apparel,</line>
            <line>In gait and countenance surely like a father.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>And what of him, Tranio?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRANIO</speaker>
            <line>If he be credulous and trust my tale,</line>
            <line>I'll make him glad to seem Vincentio,</line>
            <line>And give assurance to Baptista Minola,</line>
            <line>As if he were the right Vincentio</line>
            <line>Take in your love, and then let me alone.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt LUCENTIO and BIANCA</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Enter a Pedant</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Pedant</speaker>
            <line>God save you, sir!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRANIO</speaker>
            <line>And you, sir! you are welcome.</line>
            <line>Travel you far on, or are you at the farthest?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Pedant</speaker>
            <line>Sir, at the farthest for a week or two:</line>
            <line>But then up farther, and as for as Rome;</line>
            <line>And so to Tripoli, if God lend me life.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRANIO</speaker>
            <line>What countryman, I pray?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Pedant</speaker>
            <line>Of Mantua.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRANIO</speaker>
            <line>Of Mantua, sir? marry, God forbid!</line>
            <line>And come to Padua, careless of your life?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Pedant</speaker>
            <line>My life, sir! how, I pray? for that goes hard.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRANIO</speaker>
            <line>'Tis death for any one in Mantua</line>
            <line>To come to Padua. Know you not the cause?</line>
            <line>Your ships are stay'd at Venice, and the duke,</line>
            <line>For private quarrel 'twixt your duke and him,</line>
            <line>Hath publish'd and proclaim'd it openly:</line>
            <line>'Tis, marvel, but that you are but newly come,</line>
            <line>You might have heard it else proclaim'd about.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Pedant</speaker>
            <line>Alas! sir, it is worse for me than so;</line>
            <line>For I have bills for money by exchange</line>
            <line>From Florence and must here deliver them.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRANIO</speaker>
            <line>Well, sir, to do you courtesy,</line>
            <line>This will I do, and this I will advise you:</line>
            <line>First, tell me, have you ever been at Pisa?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Pedant</speaker>
            <line>Ay, sir, in Pisa have I often been,</line>
            <line>Pisa renowned for grave citizens.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRANIO</speaker>
            <line>Among them know you one Vincentio?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Pedant</speaker>
            <line>I know him not, but I have heard of him;</line>
            <line>A merchant of incomparable wealth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRANIO</speaker>
            <line>He is my father, sir; and, sooth to say,</line>
            <line>In countenance somewhat doth resemble you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIONDELLO</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  As much as an apple doth an oyster,</line>
            <line>and all one.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRANIO</speaker>
            <line>To save your life in this extremity,</line>
            <line>This favour will I do you for his sake;</line>
            <line>And think it not the worst of an your fortunes</line>
            <line>That you are like to Sir Vincentio.</line>
            <line>His name and credit shall you undertake,</line>
            <line>And in my house you shall be friendly lodged:</line>
            <line>Look that you take upon you as you should;</line>
            <line>You understand me, sir: so shall you stay</line>
            <line>Till you have done your business in the city:</line>
            <line>If this be courtesy, sir, accept of it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Pedant</speaker>
            <line>O sir, I do; and will repute you ever</line>
            <line>The patron of my life and liberty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRANIO</speaker>
            <line>Then go with me to make the matter good.</line>
            <line>This, by the way, I let you understand;</line>
            <line>my father is here look'd for every day,</line>
            <line>To pass assurance of a dower in marriage</line>
            <line>'Twixt me and one Baptista's daughter here:</line>
            <line>In all these circumstances I'll instruct you:</line>
            <line>Go with me to clothe you as becomes you.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  A room in PETRUCHIO'S house.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter KATHARINA and GRUMIO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>No, no, forsooth; I dare not for my life.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KATHARINA</speaker>
            <line>The more my wrong, the more his spite appears:</line>
            <line>What, did he marry me to famish me?</line>
            <line>Beggars, that come unto my father's door,</line>
            <line>Upon entreaty have a present aims;</line>
            <line>If not, elsewhere they meet with charity:</line>
            <line>But I, who never knew how to entreat,</line>
            <line>Nor never needed that I should entreat,</line>
            <line>Am starved for meat, giddy for lack of sleep,</line>
            <line>With oath kept waking and with brawling fed:</line>
            <line>And that which spites me more than all these wants,</line>
            <line>He does it under name of perfect love;</line>
            <line>As who should say, if I should sleep or eat,</line>
            <line>'Twere deadly sickness or else present death.</line>
            <line>I prithee go and get me some repast;</line>
            <line>I care not what, so it be wholesome food.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>What say you to a neat's foot?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KATHARINA</speaker>
            <line>'Tis passing good: I prithee let me have it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>I fear it is too choleric a meat.</line>
            <line>How say you to a fat tripe finely broil'd?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KATHARINA</speaker>
            <line>I like it well: good Grumio, fetch it me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>I cannot tell; I fear 'tis choleric.</line>
            <line>What say you to a piece of beef and mustard?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KATHARINA</speaker>
            <line>A dish that I do love to feed upon.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>Ay, but the mustard is too hot a little.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KATHARINA</speaker>
            <line>Why then, the beef, and let the mustard rest.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>Nay then, I will not: you shall have the mustard,</line>
            <line>Or else you get no beef of Grumio.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KATHARINA</speaker>
            <line>Then both, or one, or any thing thou wilt.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>Why then, the mustard without the beef.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KATHARINA</speaker>
            <line>Go, get thee gone, thou false deluding slave,</line>
            <stagedir>Beats him</stagedir>
            <line>That feed'st me with the very name of meat:</line>
            <line>Sorrow on thee and all the pack of you,</line>
            <line>That triumph thus upon my misery!</line>
            <line>Go, get thee gone, I say.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter PETRUCHIO and HORTENSIO with meat</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>How fares my Kate? What, sweeting, all amort?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HORTENSIO</speaker>
            <line>Mistress, what cheer?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KATHARINA</speaker>
            <line>Faith, as cold as can be.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>Pluck up thy spirits; look cheerfully upon me.</line>
            <line>Here love; thou see'st how diligent I am</line>
            <line>To dress thy meat myself and bring it thee:</line>
            <line>I am sure, sweet Kate, this kindness merits thanks.</line>
            <line>What, not a word? Nay, then thou lovest it not;</line>
            <line>And all my pains is sorted to no proof.</line>
            <line>Here, take away this dish.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KATHARINA</speaker>
            <line>I pray you, let it stand.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>The poorest service is repaid with thanks;</line>
            <line>And so shall mine, before you touch the meat.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KATHARINA</speaker>
            <line>I thank you, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HORTENSIO</speaker>
            <line>Signior Petruchio, fie! you are to blame.</line>
            <line>Come, mistress Kate, I'll bear you company.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  Eat it up all, Hortensio, if thou lovest me.</line>
            <line>Much good do it unto thy gentle heart!</line>
            <line>Kate, eat apace: and now, my honey love,</line>
            <line>Will we return unto thy father's house</line>
            <line>And revel it as bravely as the best,</line>
            <line>With silken coats and caps and golden rings,</line>
            <line>With ruffs and cuffs and fardingales and things;</line>
            <line>With scarfs and fans and double change of bravery,</line>
            <line>With amber bracelets, beads and all this knavery.</line>
            <line>What, hast thou dined? The tailor stays thy leisure,</line>
            <line>To deck thy body with his ruffling treasure.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter Tailor</stagedir>
            <line>Come, tailor, let us see these ornaments;</line>
            <line>Lay forth the gown.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter Haberdasher</stagedir>
            <line>What news with you, sir?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Haberdasher</speaker>
            <line>Here is the cap your worship did bespeak.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>Why, this was moulded on a porringer;</line>
            <line>A velvet dish: fie, fie! 'tis lewd and filthy:</line>
            <line>Why, 'tis a cockle or a walnut-shell,</line>
            <line>A knack, a toy, a trick, a baby's cap:</line>
            <line>Away with it! come, let me have a bigger.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KATHARINA</speaker>
            <line>I'll have no bigger: this doth fit the time,</line>
            <line>And gentlewomen wear such caps as these</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>When you are gentle, you shall have one too,</line>
            <line>And not till then.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HORTENSIO</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  That will not be in haste.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KATHARINA</speaker>
            <line>Why, sir, I trust I may have leave to speak;</line>
            <line>And speak I will; I am no child, no babe:</line>
            <line>Your betters have endured me say my mind,</line>
            <line>And if you cannot, best you stop your ears.</line>
            <line>My tongue will tell the anger of my heart,</line>
            <line>Or else my heart concealing it will break,</line>
            <line>And rather than it shall, I will be free</line>
            <line>Even to the uttermost, as I please, in words.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>Why, thou say'st true; it is a paltry cap,</line>
            <line>A custard-coffin, a bauble, a silken pie:</line>
            <line>I love thee well, in that thou likest it not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KATHARINA</speaker>
            <line>Love me or love me not, I like the cap;</line>
            <line>And it I will have, or I will have none.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit Haberdasher</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>Thy gown? why, ay: come, tailor, let us see't.</line>
            <line>O mercy, God! what masquing stuff is here?</line>
            <line>What's this? a sleeve? 'tis like a demi-cannon:</line>
            <line>What, up and down, carved like an apple-tart?</line>
            <line>Here's snip and nip and cut and slish and slash,</line>
            <line>Like to a censer in a barber's shop:</line>
            <line>Why, what, i' devil's name, tailor, call'st thou this?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HORTENSIO</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  I see she's like to have neither cap nor gown.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Tailor</speaker>
            <line>You bid me make it orderly and well,</line>
            <line>According to the fashion and the time.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>Marry, and did; but if you be remember'd,</line>
            <line>I did not bid you mar it to the time.</line>
            <line>Go, hop me over every kennel home,</line>
            <line>For you shall hop without my custom, sir:</line>
            <line>I'll none of it: hence! make your best of it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KATHARINA</speaker>
            <line>I never saw a better-fashion'd gown,</line>
            <line>More quaint, more pleasing, nor more commendable:</line>
            <line>Belike you mean to make a puppet of me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>Why, true; he means to make a puppet of thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Tailor</speaker>
            <line>She says your worship means to make</line>
            <line>a puppet of her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>O monstrous arrogance! Thou liest, thou thread,</line>
            <line>thou thimble,</line>
            <line>Thou yard, three-quarters, half-yard, quarter, nail!</line>
            <line>Thou flea, thou nit, thou winter-cricket thou!</line>
            <line>Braved in mine own house with a skein of thread?</line>
            <line>Away, thou rag, thou quantity, thou remnant;</line>
            <line>Or I shall so be-mete thee with thy yard</line>
            <line>As thou shalt think on prating whilst thou livest!</line>
            <line>I tell thee, I, that thou hast marr'd her gown.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Tailor</speaker>
            <line>Your worship is deceived; the gown is made</line>
            <line>Just as my master had direction:</line>
            <line>Grumio gave order how it should be done.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>I gave him no order; I gave him the stuff.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Tailor</speaker>
            <line>But how did you desire it should be made?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>Marry, sir, with needle and thread.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Tailor</speaker>
            <line>But did you not request to have it cut?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>Thou hast faced many things.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Tailor</speaker>
            <line>I have.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>Face not me: thou hast braved many men; brave not</line>
            <line>me; I will neither be faced nor braved. I say unto</line>
            <line>thee, I bid thy master cut out the gown; but I did</line>
            <line>not bid him cut it to pieces: ergo, thou liest.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Tailor</speaker>
            <line>Why, here is the note of the fashion to testify</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>Read it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>The note lies in's throat, if he say I said so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Tailor</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>  'Imprimis, a loose-bodied gown:'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>Master, if ever I said loose-bodied gown, sew me in</line>
            <line>the skirts of it, and beat me to death with a bottom</line>
            <line>of brown thread: I said a gown.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>Proceed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Tailor</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>  'With a small compassed cape:'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>I confess the cape.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Tailor</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>  'With a trunk sleeve:'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>I confess two sleeves.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Tailor</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>  'The sleeves curiously cut.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>Ay, there's the villany.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>Error i' the bill, sir; error i' the bill.</line>
            <line>I commanded the sleeves should be cut out and</line>
            <line>sewed up again; and that I'll prove upon thee,</line>
            <line>though thy little finger be armed in a thimble.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Tailor</speaker>
            <line>This is true that I say: an I had thee</line>
            <line>in place where, thou shouldst know it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>I am for thee straight: take thou the</line>
            <line>bill, give me thy mete-yard, and spare not me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HORTENSIO</speaker>
            <line>God-a-mercy, Grumio! then he shall have no odds.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>Well, sir, in brief, the gown is not for me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>You are i' the right, sir: 'tis for my mistress.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>Go, take it up unto thy master's use.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>Villain, not for thy life: take up my mistress'</line>
            <line>gown for thy master's use!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>Why, sir, what's your conceit in that?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>O, sir, the conceit is deeper than you think for:</line>
            <line>Take up my mistress' gown to his master's use!</line>
            <line>O, fie, fie, fie!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  Hortensio, say thou wilt see the tailor paid.</line>
            <line>Go take it hence; be gone, and say no more.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HORTENSIO</speaker>
            <line>Tailor, I'll pay thee for thy gown tomorrow:</line>
            <line>Take no unkindness of his hasty words:</line>
            <line>Away! I say; commend me to thy master.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit Tailor</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>Well, come, my Kate; we will unto your father's</line>
            <line>Even in these honest mean habiliments:</line>
            <line>Our purses shall be proud, our garments poor;</line>
            <line>For 'tis the mind that makes the body rich;</line>
            <line>And as the sun breaks through the darkest clouds,</line>
            <line>So honour peereth in the meanest habit.</line>
            <line>What is the jay more precious than the lark,</line>
            <line>Because his fathers are more beautiful?</line>
            <line>Or is the adder better than the eel,</line>
            <line>Because his painted skin contents the eye?</line>
            <line>O, no, good Kate; neither art thou the worse</line>
            <line>For this poor furniture and mean array.</line>
            <line>if thou account'st it shame. lay it on me;</line>
            <line>And therefore frolic: we will hence forthwith,</line>
            <line>To feast and sport us at thy father's house.</line>
            <line>Go, call my men, and let us straight to him;</line>
            <line>And bring our horses unto Long-lane end;</line>
            <line>There will we mount, and thither walk on foot</line>
            <line>Let's see; I think 'tis now some seven o'clock,</line>
            <line>And well we may come there by dinner-time.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KATHARINA</speaker>
            <line>I dare assure you, sir, 'tis almost two;</line>
            <line>And 'twill be supper-time ere you come there.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>It shall be seven ere I go to horse:</line>
            <line>Look, what I speak, or do, or think to do,</line>
            <line>You are still crossing it. Sirs, let't alone:</line>
            <line>I will not go to-day; and ere I do,</line>
            <line>It shall be what o'clock I say it is.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HORTENSIO</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  Why, so this gallant will command the sun.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-4">
      <title>SCENE IV.  Padua. Before BAPTISTA'S house.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter TRANIO, and the Pedant dressed like VINCENTIO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRANIO</speaker>
            <line>Sir, this is the house: please it you that I call?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Pedant</speaker>
            <line>Ay, what else? and but I be deceived</line>
            <line>Signior Baptista may remember me,</line>
            <line>Near twenty years ago, in Genoa,</line>
            <line>Where we were lodgers at the Pegasus.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRANIO</speaker>
            <line>'Tis well; and hold your own, in any case,</line>
            <line>With such austerity as 'longeth to a father.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Pedant</speaker>
            <line>I warrant you.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter BIONDELLO</stagedir>
            <line>But, sir, here comes your boy;</line>
            <line>'Twere good he were school'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRANIO</speaker>
            <line>Fear you not him. Sirrah Biondello,</line>
            <line>Now do your duty throughly, I advise you:</line>
            <line>Imagine 'twere the right Vincentio.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIONDELLO</speaker>
            <line>Tut, fear not me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRANIO</speaker>
            <line>But hast thou done thy errand to Baptista?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIONDELLO</speaker>
            <line>I told him that your father was at Venice,</line>
            <line>And that you look'd for him this day in Padua.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRANIO</speaker>
            <line>Thou'rt a tall fellow: hold thee that to drink.</line>
            <line>Here comes Baptista: set your countenance, sir.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter BAPTISTA and LUCENTIO</stagedir>
            <line>Signior Baptista, you are happily met.</line>
            <stagedir>To the Pedant</stagedir>
            <line>Sir, this is the gentleman I told you of:</line>
            <line>I pray you stand good father to me now,</line>
            <line>Give me Bianca for my patrimony.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Pedant</speaker>
            <line>Soft son!</line>
            <line>Sir, by your leave: having come to Padua</line>
            <line>To gather in some debts, my son Lucentio</line>
            <line>Made me acquainted with a weighty cause</line>
            <line>Of love between your daughter and himself:</line>
            <line>And, for the good report I hear of you</line>
            <line>And for the love he beareth to your daughter</line>
            <line>And she to him, to stay him not too long,</line>
            <line>I am content, in a good father's care,</line>
            <line>To have him match'd; and if you please to like</line>
            <line>No worse than I, upon some agreement</line>
            <line>Me shall you find ready and willing</line>
            <line>With one consent to have her so bestow'd;</line>
            <line>For curious I cannot be with you,</line>
            <line>Signior Baptista, of whom I hear so well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BAPTISTA</speaker>
            <line>Sir, pardon me in what I have to say:</line>
            <line>Your plainness and your shortness please me well.</line>
            <line>Right true it is, your son Lucentio here</line>
            <line>Doth love my daughter and she loveth him,</line>
            <line>Or both dissemble deeply their affections:</line>
            <line>And therefore, if you say no more than this,</line>
            <line>That like a father you will deal with him</line>
            <line>And pass my daughter a sufficient dower,</line>
            <line>The match is made, and all is done:</line>
            <line>Your son shall have my daughter with consent.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRANIO</speaker>
            <line>I thank you, sir. Where then do you know best</line>
            <line>We be affied and such assurance ta'en</line>
            <line>As shall with either part's agreement stand?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BAPTISTA</speaker>
            <line>Not in my house, Lucentio; for, you know,</line>
            <line>Pitchers have ears, and I have many servants:</line>
            <line>Besides, old Gremio is hearkening still;</line>
            <line>And happily we might be interrupted.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRANIO</speaker>
            <line>Then at my lodging, an it like you:</line>
            <line>There doth my father lie; and there, this night,</line>
            <line>We'll pass the business privately and well.</line>
            <line>Send for your daughter by your servant here:</line>
            <line>My boy shall fetch the scrivener presently.</line>
            <line>The worst is this, that, at so slender warning,</line>
            <line>You are like to have a thin and slender pittance.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BAPTISTA</speaker>
            <line>It likes me well. Biondello, hie you home,</line>
            <line>And bid Bianca make her ready straight;</line>
            <line>And, if you will, tell what hath happened,</line>
            <line>Lucentio's father is arrived in Padua,</line>
            <line>And how she's like to be Lucentio's wife.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIONDELLO</speaker>
            <line>I pray the gods she may with all my heart!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRANIO</speaker>
            <line>Dally not with the gods, but get thee gone.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit BIONDELLO</stagedir>
            <line>Signior Baptista, shall I lead the way?</line>
            <line>Welcome! one mess is like to be your cheer:</line>
            <line>Come, sir; we will better it in Pisa.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BAPTISTA</speaker>
            <line>I follow you.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt TRANIO, Pedant, and BAPTISTA</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Re-enter BIONDELLO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIONDELLO</speaker>
            <line>Cambio!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>What sayest thou, Biondello?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIONDELLO</speaker>
            <line>You saw my master wink and laugh upon you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>Biondello, what of that?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIONDELLO</speaker>
            <line>Faith, nothing; but has left me here behind, to</line>
            <line>expound the meaning or moral of his signs and tokens.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>I pray thee, moralize them.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIONDELLO</speaker>
            <line>Then thus. Baptista is safe, talking with the</line>
            <line>deceiving father of a deceitful son.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>And what of him?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIONDELLO</speaker>
            <line>His daughter is to be brought by you to the supper.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>And then?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIONDELLO</speaker>
            <line>The old priest of Saint Luke's church is at your</line>
            <line>command at all hours.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>And what of all this?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIONDELLO</speaker>
            <line>I cannot tell; expect they are busied about a</line>
            <line>counterfeit assurance: take you assurance of her,</line>
            <line>'cum privilegio ad imprimendum solum:' to the</line>
            <line>church; take the priest, clerk, and some sufficient</line>
            <line>honest witnesses: If this be not that you look for,</line>
            <line>I have no more to say, But bid Bianca farewell for</line>
            <line>ever and a day.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>Hearest thou, Biondello?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIONDELLO</speaker>
            <line>I cannot tarry: I knew a wench married in an</line>
            <line>afternoon as she went to the garden for parsley to</line>
            <line>stuff a rabbit; and so may you, sir: and so, adieu,</line>
            <line>sir. My master hath appointed me to go to Saint</line>
            <line>Luke's, to bid the priest be ready to come against</line>
            <line>you come with your appendix.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>I may, and will, if she be so contented:</line>
            <line>She will be pleased; then wherefore should I doubt?</line>
            <line>Hap what hap may, I'll roundly go about her:</line>
            <line>It shall go hard if Cambio go without her.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-5">
      <title>SCENE V.  A public road.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter PETRUCHIO, KATHARINA, HORTENSIO, and Servants</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>Come on, i' God's name; once more toward our father's.</line>
            <line>Good Lord, how bright and goodly shines the moon!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KATHARINA</speaker>
            <line>The moon! the sun: it is not moonlight now.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>I say it is the moon that shines so bright.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KATHARINA</speaker>
            <line>I know it is the sun that shines so bright.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>Now, by my mother's son, and that's myself,</line>
            <line>It shall be moon, or star, or what I list,</line>
            <line>Or ere I journey to your father's house.</line>
            <line>Go on, and fetch our horses back again.</line>
            <line>Evermore cross'd and cross'd; nothing but cross'd!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HORTENSIO</speaker>
            <line>Say as he says, or we shall never go.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KATHARINA</speaker>
            <line>Forward, I pray, since we have come so far,</line>
            <line>And be it moon, or sun, or what you please:</line>
            <line>An if you please to call it a rush-candle,</line>
            <line>Henceforth I vow it shall be so for me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>I say it is the moon.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KATHARINA</speaker>
            <line>I know it is the moon.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>Nay, then you lie: it is the blessed sun.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KATHARINA</speaker>
            <line>Then, God be bless'd, it is the blessed sun:</line>
            <line>But sun it is not, when you say it is not;</line>
            <line>And the moon changes even as your mind.</line>
            <line>What you will have it named, even that it is;</line>
            <line>And so it shall be so for Katharina.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HORTENSIO</speaker>
            <line>Petruchio, go thy ways; the field is won.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>Well, forward, forward! thus the bowl should run,</line>
            <line>And not unluckily against the bias.</line>
            <line>But, soft! company is coming here.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter VINCENTIO</stagedir>
            <stagedir>To VINCENTIO</stagedir>
            <line>Good morrow, gentle mistress: where away?</line>
            <line>Tell me, sweet Kate, and tell me truly too,</line>
            <line>Hast thou beheld a fresher gentlewoman?</line>
            <line>Such war of white and red within her cheeks!</line>
            <line>What stars do spangle heaven with such beauty,</line>
            <line>As those two eyes become that heavenly face?</line>
            <line>Fair lovely maid, once more good day to thee.</line>
            <line>Sweet Kate, embrace her for her beauty's sake.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HORTENSIO</speaker>
            <line>A' will make the man mad, to make a woman of him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KATHARINA</speaker>
            <line>Young budding virgin, fair and fresh and sweet,</line>
            <line>Whither away, or where is thy abode?</line>
            <line>Happy the parents of so fair a child;</line>
            <line>Happier the man, whom favourable stars</line>
            <line>Allot thee for his lovely bed-fellow!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>Why, how now, Kate! I hope thou art not mad:</line>
            <line>This is a man, old, wrinkled, faded, wither'd,</line>
            <line>And not a maiden, as thou say'st he is.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KATHARINA</speaker>
            <line>Pardon, old father, my mistaking eyes,</line>
            <line>That have been so bedazzled with the sun</line>
            <line>That everything I look on seemeth green:</line>
            <line>Now I perceive thou art a reverend father;</line>
            <line>Pardon, I pray thee, for my mad mistaking.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>Do, good old grandsire; and withal make known</line>
            <line>Which way thou travellest: if along with us,</line>
            <line>We shall be joyful of thy company.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>Fair sir, and you my merry mistress,</line>
            <line>That with your strange encounter much amazed me,</line>
            <line>My name is call'd Vincentio; my dwelling Pisa;</line>
            <line>And bound I am to Padua; there to visit</line>
            <line>A son of mine, which long I have not seen.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>What is his name?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>Lucentio, gentle sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>Happily we met; the happier for thy son.</line>
            <line>And now by law, as well as reverend age,</line>
            <line>I may entitle thee my loving father:</line>
            <line>The sister to my wife, this gentlewoman,</line>
            <line>Thy son by this hath married. Wonder not,</line>
            <line>Nor be grieved: she is of good esteem,</line>
            <line>Her dowery wealthy, and of worthy birth;</line>
            <line>Beside, so qualified as may beseem</line>
            <line>The spouse of any noble gentleman.</line>
            <line>Let me embrace with old Vincentio,</line>
            <line>And wander we to see thy honest son,</line>
            <line>Who will of thy arrival be full joyous.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>But is it true? or else is it your pleasure,</line>
            <line>Like pleasant travellers, to break a jest</line>
            <line>Upon the company you overtake?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HORTENSIO</speaker>
            <line>I do assure thee, father, so it is.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>Come, go along, and see the truth hereof;</line>
            <line>For our first merriment hath made thee jealous.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt all but HORTENSIO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HORTENSIO</speaker>
            <line>Well, Petruchio, this has put me in heart.</line>
            <line>Have to my widow! and if she be froward,</line>
            <line>Then hast thou taught Hortensio to be untoward.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>