<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:shakespear:dtd:act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-1">
   <title>ACT I</title>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  Padua. A public place.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter LUCENTIO and his man TRANIO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>Tranio, since for the great desire I had</line>
            <line>To see fair Padua, nursery of arts,</line>
            <line>I am arrived for fruitful Lombardy,</line>
            <line>The pleasant garden of great Italy;</line>
            <line>And by my father's love and leave am arm'd</line>
            <line>With his good will and thy good company,</line>
            <line>My trusty servant, well approved in all,</line>
            <line>Here let us breathe and haply institute</line>
            <line>A course of learning and ingenious studies.</line>
            <line>Pisa renown'd for grave citizens</line>
            <line>Gave me my being and my father first,</line>
            <line>A merchant of great traffic through the world,</line>
            <line>Vincetino come of Bentivolii.</line>
            <line>Vincetino's son brought up in Florence</line>
            <line>It shall become to serve all hopes conceived,</line>
            <line>To deck his fortune with his virtuous deeds:</line>
            <line>And therefore, Tranio, for the time I study,</line>
            <line>Virtue and that part of philosophy</line>
            <line>Will I apply that treats of happiness</line>
            <line>By virtue specially to be achieved.</line>
            <line>Tell me thy mind; for I have Pisa left</line>
            <line>And am to Padua come, as he that leaves</line>
            <line>A shallow plash to plunge him in the deep</line>
            <line>And with satiety seeks to quench his thirst.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRANIO</speaker>
            <line>Mi perdonato, gentle master mine,</line>
            <line>I am in all affected as yourself;</line>
            <line>Glad that you thus continue your resolve</line>
            <line>To suck the sweets of sweet philosophy.</line>
            <line>Only, good master, while we do admire</line>
            <line>This virtue and this moral discipline,</line>
            <line>Let's be no stoics nor no stocks, I pray;</line>
            <line>Or so devote to Aristotle's cheques</line>
            <line>As Ovid be an outcast quite abjured:</line>
            <line>Balk logic with acquaintance that you have</line>
            <line>And practise rhetoric in your common talk;</line>
            <line>Music and poesy use to quicken you;</line>
            <line>The mathematics and the metaphysics,</line>
            <line>Fall to them as you find your stomach serves you;</line>
            <line>No profit grows where is no pleasure ta'en:</line>
            <line>In brief, sir, study what you most affect.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>Gramercies, Tranio, well dost thou advise.</line>
            <line>If, Biondello, thou wert come ashore,</line>
            <line>We could at once put us in readiness,</line>
            <line>And take a lodging fit to entertain</line>
            <line>Such friends as time in Padua shall beget.</line>
            <line>But stay a while: what company is this?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRANIO</speaker>
            <line>Master, some show to welcome us to town.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter BAPTISTA, KATHARINA, BIANCA, GREMIO, and
HORTENSIO. LUCENTIO and TRANIO stand by</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BAPTISTA</speaker>
            <line>Gentlemen, importune me no farther,</line>
            <line>For how I firmly am resolved you know;</line>
            <line>That is, not bestow my youngest daughter</line>
            <line>Before I have a husband for the elder:</line>
            <line>If either of you both love Katharina,</line>
            <line>Because I know you well and love you well,</line>
            <line>Leave shall you have to court her at your pleasure.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GREMIO</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  To cart her rather: she's too rough for me.</line>
            <line>There, There, Hortensio, will you any wife?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KATHARINA</speaker>
            <line>I pray you, sir, is it your will</line>
            <line>To make a stale of me amongst these mates?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HORTENSIO</speaker>
            <line>Mates, maid! how mean you that? no mates for you,</line>
            <line>Unless you were of gentler, milder mould.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KATHARINA</speaker>
            <line>I'faith, sir, you shall never need to fear:</line>
            <line>I wis it is not half way to her heart;</line>
            <line>But if it were, doubt not her care should be</line>
            <line>To comb your noddle with a three-legg'd stool</line>
            <line>And paint your face and use you like a fool.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HORTENSIA</speaker>
            <line>From all such devils, good Lord deliver us!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GREMIO</speaker>
            <line>And me too, good Lord!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRANIO</speaker>
            <line>Hush, master! here's some good pastime toward:</line>
            <line>That wench is stark mad or wonderful froward.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>But in the other's silence do I see</line>
            <line>Maid's mild behavior and sobriety.</line>
            <line>Peace, Tranio!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRANIO</speaker>
            <line>Well said, master; mum! and gaze your fill.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BAPTISTA</speaker>
            <line>Gentlemen, that I may soon make good</line>
            <line>What I have said, Bianca, get you in:</line>
            <line>And let it not displease thee, good Bianca,</line>
            <line>For I will love thee ne'er the less, my girl.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KATHARINA</speaker>
            <line>A pretty peat! it is best</line>
            <line>Put finger in the eye, an she knew why.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIANCA</speaker>
            <line>Sister, content you in my discontent.</line>
            <line>Sir, to your pleasure humbly I subscribe:</line>
            <line>My books and instruments shall be my company,</line>
            <line>On them to took and practise by myself.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>Hark, Tranio! thou may'st hear Minerva speak.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HORTENSIO</speaker>
            <line>Signior Baptista, will you be so strange?</line>
            <line>Sorry am I that our good will effects</line>
            <line>Bianca's grief.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GREMIO</speaker>
            <line>Why will you mew her up,</line>
            <line>Signior Baptista, for this fiend of hell,</line>
            <line>And make her bear the penance of her tongue?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BAPTISTA</speaker>
            <line>Gentlemen, content ye; I am resolved:</line>
            <line>Go in, Bianca:</line>
            <stagedir>Exit BIANCA</stagedir>
            <line>And for I know she taketh most delight</line>
            <line>In music, instruments and poetry,</line>
            <line>Schoolmasters will I keep within my house,</line>
            <line>Fit to instruct her youth. If you, Hortensio,</line>
            <line>Or Signior Gremio, you, know any such,</line>
            <line>Prefer them hither; for to cunning men</line>
            <line>I will be very kind, and liberal</line>
            <line>To mine own children in good bringing up:</line>
            <line>And so farewell. Katharina, you may stay;</line>
            <line>For I have more to commune with Bianca.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KATHARINA</speaker>
            <line>Why, and I trust I may go too, may I not? What,</line>
            <line>shall I be appointed hours; as though, belike, I</line>
            <line>knew not what to take and what to leave, ha?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GREMIO</speaker>
            <line>You may go to the devil's dam: your gifts are so</line>
            <line>good, here's none will hold you. Their love is not</line>
            <line>so great, Hortensio, but we may blow our nails</line>
            <line>together, and fast it fairly out: our cakes dough on</line>
            <line>both sides. Farewell: yet for the love I bear my</line>
            <line>sweet Bianca, if I can by any means light on a fit</line>
            <line>man to teach her that wherein she delights, I will</line>
            <line>wish him to her father.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HORTENSIO</speaker>
            <line>So will I, Signior Gremio: but a word, I pray.</line>
            <line>Though the nature of our quarrel yet never brooked</line>
            <line>parle, know now, upon advice, it toucheth us both,</line>
            <line>that we may yet again have access to our fair</line>
            <line>mistress and be happy rivals in Bianco's love, to</line>
            <line>labour and effect one thing specially.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GREMIO</speaker>
            <line>What's that, I pray?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HORTENSIO</speaker>
            <line>Marry, sir, to get a husband for her sister.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GREMIO</speaker>
            <line>A husband! a devil.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HORTENSIO</speaker>
            <line>I say, a husband.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GREMIO</speaker>
            <line>I say, a devil. Thinkest thou, Hortensio, though</line>
            <line>her father be very rich, any man is so very a fool</line>
            <line>to be married to hell?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HORTENSIO</speaker>
            <line>Tush, Gremio, though it pass your patience and mine</line>
            <line>to endure her loud alarums, why, man, there be good</line>
            <line>fellows in the world, an a man could light on them,</line>
            <line>would take her with all faults, and money enough.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GREMIO</speaker>
            <line>I cannot tell; but I had as lief take her dowry with</line>
            <line>this condition, to be whipped at the high cross</line>
            <line>every morning.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HORTENSIO</speaker>
            <line>Faith, as you say, there's small choice in rotten</line>
            <line>apples. But come; since this bar in law makes us</line>
            <line>friends, it shall be so far forth friendly</line>
            <line>maintained all by helping Baptista's eldest daughter</line>
            <line>to a husband we set his youngest free for a husband,</line>
            <line>and then have to't a fresh. Sweet Bianca! Happy man</line>
            <line>be his dole! He that runs fastest gets the ring.</line>
            <line>How say you, Signior Gremio?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GREMIO</speaker>
            <line>I am agreed; and would I had given him the best</line>
            <line>horse in Padua to begin his wooing that would</line>
            <line>thoroughly woo her, wed her and bed her and rid the</line>
            <line>house of her! Come on.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt GREMIO and HORTENSIO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRANIO</speaker>
            <line>I pray, sir, tell me, is it possible</line>
            <line>That love should of a sudden take such hold?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>O Tranio, till I found it to be true,</line>
            <line>I never thought it possible or likely;</line>
            <line>But see, while idly I stood looking on,</line>
            <line>I found the effect of love in idleness:</line>
            <line>And now in plainness do confess to thee,</line>
            <line>That art to me as secret and as dear</line>
            <line>As Anna to the queen of Carthage was,</line>
            <line>Tranio, I burn, I pine, I perish, Tranio,</line>
            <line>If I achieve not this young modest girl.</line>
            <line>Counsel me, Tranio, for I know thou canst;</line>
            <line>Assist me, Tranio, for I know thou wilt.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRANIO</speaker>
            <line>Master, it is no time to chide you now;</line>
            <line>Affection is not rated from the heart:</line>
            <line>If love have touch'd you, nought remains but so,</line>
            <line>'Redime te captum quam queas minimo.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>Gramercies, lad, go forward; this contents:</line>
            <line>The rest will comfort, for thy counsel's sound.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRANIO</speaker>
            <line>Master, you look'd so longly on the maid,</line>
            <line>Perhaps you mark'd not what's the pith of all.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>O yes, I saw sweet beauty in her face,</line>
            <line>Such as the daughter of Agenor had,</line>
            <line>That made great Jove to humble him to her hand.</line>
            <line>When with his knees he kiss'd the Cretan strand.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRANIO</speaker>
            <line>Saw you no more? mark'd you not how her sister</line>
            <line>Began to scold and raise up such a storm</line>
            <line>That mortal ears might hardly endure the din?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>Tranio, I saw her coral lips to move</line>
            <line>And with her breath she did perfume the air:</line>
            <line>Sacred and sweet was all I saw in her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRANIO</speaker>
            <line>Nay, then, 'tis time to stir him from his trance.</line>
            <line>I pray, awake, sir: if you love the maid,</line>
            <line>Bend thoughts and wits to achieve her. Thus it stands:</line>
            <line>Her eldest sister is so curst and shrewd</line>
            <line>That till the father rid his hands of her,</line>
            <line>Master, your love must live a maid at home;</line>
            <line>And therefore has he closely mew'd her up,</line>
            <line>Because she will not be annoy'd with suitors.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>Ah, Tranio, what a cruel father's he!</line>
            <line>But art thou not advised, he took some care</line>
            <line>To get her cunning schoolmasters to instruct her?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRANIO</speaker>
            <line>Ay, marry, am I, sir; and now 'tis plotted.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>I have it, Tranio.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRANIO</speaker>
            <line>Master, for my hand,</line>
            <line>Both our inventions meet and jump in one.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>Tell me thine first.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRANIO</speaker>
            <line>You will be schoolmaster</line>
            <line>And undertake the teaching of the maid:</line>
            <line>That's your device.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>It is: may it be done?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRANIO</speaker>
            <line>Not possible; for who shall bear your part,</line>
            <line>And be in Padua here Vincentio's son,</line>
            <line>Keep house and ply his book, welcome his friends,</line>
            <line>Visit his countrymen and banquet them?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>Basta; content thee, for I have it full.</line>
            <line>We have not yet been seen in any house,</line>
            <line>Nor can we lie distinguish'd by our faces</line>
            <line>For man or master; then it follows thus;</line>
            <line>Thou shalt be master, Tranio, in my stead,</line>
            <line>Keep house and port and servants as I should:</line>
            <line>I will some other be, some Florentine,</line>
            <line>Some Neapolitan, or meaner man of Pisa.</line>
            <line>'Tis hatch'd and shall be so: Tranio, at once</line>
            <line>Uncase thee; take my colour'd hat and cloak:</line>
            <line>When Biondello comes, he waits on thee;</line>
            <line>But I will charm him first to keep his tongue.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRANIO</speaker>
            <line>So had you need.</line>
            <line>In brief, sir, sith it your pleasure is,</line>
            <line>And I am tied to be obedient;</line>
            <line>For so your father charged me at our parting,</line>
            <line>'Be serviceable to my son,' quoth he,</line>
            <line>Although I think 'twas in another sense;</line>
            <line>I am content to be Lucentio,</line>
            <line>Because so well I love Lucentio.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>Tranio, be so, because Lucentio loves:</line>
            <line>And let me be a slave, to achieve that maid</line>
            <line>Whose sudden sight hath thrall'd my wounded eye.</line>
            <line>Here comes the rogue.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter BIONDELLO</stagedir>
            <line>Sirrah, where have you been?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIONDELLO</speaker>
            <line>Where have I been! Nay, how now! where are you?</line>
            <line>Master, has my fellow Tranio stolen your clothes? Or</line>
            <line>you stolen his? or both? pray, what's the news?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>Sirrah, come hither: 'tis no time to jest,</line>
            <line>And therefore frame your manners to the time.</line>
            <line>Your fellow Tranio here, to save my life,</line>
            <line>Puts my apparel and my countenance on,</line>
            <line>And I for my escape have put on his;</line>
            <line>For in a quarrel since I came ashore</line>
            <line>I kill'd a man and fear I was descried:</line>
            <line>Wait you on him, I charge you, as becomes,</line>
            <line>While I make way from hence to save my life:</line>
            <line>You understand me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIONDELLO</speaker>
            <line>I, sir! ne'er a whit.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>And not a jot of Tranio in your mouth:</line>
            <line>Tranio is changed into Lucentio.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIONDELLO</speaker>
            <line>The better for him: would I were so too!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRANIO</speaker>
            <line>So could I, faith, boy, to have the next wish after,</line>
            <line>That Lucentio indeed had Baptista's youngest daughter.</line>
            <line>But, sirrah, not for my sake, but your master's, I advise</line>
            <line>You use your manners discreetly in all kind of companies:</line>
            <line>When I am alone, why, then I am Tranio;</line>
            <line>But in all places else your master Lucentio.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>Tranio, let's go: one thing more rests, that</line>
            <line>thyself execute, to make one among these wooers: if</line>
            <line>thou ask me why, sufficeth, my reasons are both good</line>
            <line>and weighty.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
         <stagedir>The presenters above speak</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Servant</speaker>
            <line>My lord, you nod; you do not mind the play.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SLY</speaker>
            <line>Yes, by Saint Anne, do I. A good matter, surely:</line>
            <line>comes there any more of it?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <line>My lord, 'tis but begun.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SLY</speaker>
            <line>'Tis a very excellent piece of work, madam lady:</line>
            <line>would 'twere done!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>They sit and mark</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  Padua. Before HORTENSIO'S house.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter PETRUCHIO and his man GRUMIO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>Verona, for a while I take my leave,</line>
            <line>To see my friends in Padua, but of all</line>
            <line>My best beloved and approved friend,</line>
            <line>Hortensio; and I trow this is his house.</line>
            <line>Here, sirrah Grumio; knock, I say.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>Knock, sir! whom should I knock? is there man has</line>
            <line>rebused your worship?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>Villain, I say, knock me here soundly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>Knock you here, sir! why, sir, what am I, sir, that</line>
            <line>I should knock you here, sir?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>Villain, I say, knock me at this gate</line>
            <line>And rap me well, or I'll knock your knave's pate.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>My master is grown quarrelsome. I should knock</line>
            <line>you first,</line>
            <line>And then I know after who comes by the worst.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>Will it not be?</line>
            <line>Faith, sirrah, an you'll not knock, I'll ring it;</line>
            <line>I'll try how you can sol, fa, and sing it.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>He wrings him by the ears</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>Help, masters, help! my master is mad.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>Now, knock when I bid you, sirrah villain!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter HORTENSIO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HORTENSIO</speaker>
            <line>How now! what's the matter? My old friend Grumio!</line>
            <line>and my good friend Petruchio! How do you all at Verona?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>Signior Hortensio, come you to part the fray?</line>
            <line>'Con tutto il cuore, ben trovato,' may I say.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HORTENSIO</speaker>
            <line>'Alla nostra casa ben venuto, molto honorato signor</line>
            <line>mio Petruchio.' Rise, Grumio, rise: we will compound</line>
            <line>this quarrel.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>Nay, 'tis no matter, sir, what he 'leges in Latin.</line>
            <line>if this be not a lawful case for me to leave his</line>
            <line>service, look you, sir, he bid me knock him and rap</line>
            <line>him soundly, sir: well, was it fit for a servant to</line>
            <line>use his master so, being perhaps, for aught I see,</line>
            <line>two and thirty, a pip out? Whom would to God I had</line>
            <line>well knock'd at first, Then had not Grumio come by the worst.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>A senseless villain! Good Hortensio,</line>
            <line>I bade the rascal knock upon your gate</line>
            <line>And could not get him for my heart to do it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>Knock at the gate! O heavens! Spake you not these</line>
            <line>words plain, 'Sirrah, knock me here, rap me here,</line>
            <line>knock me well, and knock me soundly'? And come you</line>
            <line>now with, 'knocking at the gate'?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>Sirrah, be gone, or talk not, I advise you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HORTENSIO</speaker>
            <line>Petruchio, patience; I am Grumio's pledge:</line>
            <line>Why, this's a heavy chance 'twixt him and you,</line>
            <line>Your ancient, trusty, pleasant servant Grumio.</line>
            <line>And tell me now, sweet friend, what happy gale</line>
            <line>Blows you to Padua here from old Verona?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>Such wind as scatters young men through the world,</line>
            <line>To seek their fortunes farther than at home</line>
            <line>Where small experience grows. But in a few,</line>
            <line>Signior Hortensio, thus it stands with me:</line>
            <line>Antonio, my father, is deceased;</line>
            <line>And I have thrust myself into this maze,</line>
            <line>Haply to wive and thrive as best I may:</line>
            <line>Crowns in my purse I have and goods at home,</line>
            <line>And so am come abroad to see the world.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HORTENSIO</speaker>
            <line>Petruchio, shall I then come roundly to thee</line>
            <line>And wish thee to a shrewd ill-favour'd wife?</line>
            <line>Thou'ldst thank me but a little for my counsel:</line>
            <line>And yet I'll promise thee she shall be rich</line>
            <line>And very rich: but thou'rt too much my friend,</line>
            <line>And I'll not wish thee to her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>Signior Hortensio, 'twixt such friends as we</line>
            <line>Few words suffice; and therefore, if thou know</line>
            <line>One rich enough to be Petruchio's wife,</line>
            <line>As wealth is burden of my wooing dance,</line>
            <line>Be she as foul as was Florentius' love,</line>
            <line>As old as Sibyl and as curst and shrewd</line>
            <line>As Socrates' Xanthippe, or a worse,</line>
            <line>She moves me not, or not removes, at least,</line>
            <line>Affection's edge in me, were she as rough</line>
            <line>As are the swelling Adriatic seas:</line>
            <line>I come to wive it wealthily in Padua;</line>
            <line>If wealthily, then happily in Padua.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>Nay, look you, sir, he tells you flatly what his</line>
            <line>mind is: Why give him gold enough and marry him to</line>
            <line>a puppet or an aglet-baby; or an old trot with ne'er</line>
            <line>a tooth in her head, though she have as many diseases</line>
            <line>as two and fifty horses: why, nothing comes amiss,</line>
            <line>so money comes withal.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HORTENSIO</speaker>
            <line>Petruchio, since we are stepp'd thus far in,</line>
            <line>I will continue that I broach'd in jest.</line>
            <line>I can, Petruchio, help thee to a wife</line>
            <line>With wealth enough and young and beauteous,</line>
            <line>Brought up as best becomes a gentlewoman:</line>
            <line>Her only fault, and that is faults enough,</line>
            <line>Is that she is intolerable curst</line>
            <line>And shrewd and froward, so beyond all measure</line>
            <line>That, were my state far worser than it is,</line>
            <line>I would not wed her for a mine of gold.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>Hortensio, peace! thou know'st not gold's effect:</line>
            <line>Tell me her father's name and 'tis enough;</line>
            <line>For I will board her, though she chide as loud</line>
            <line>As thunder when the clouds in autumn crack.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HORTENSIO</speaker>
            <line>Her father is Baptista Minola,</line>
            <line>An affable and courteous gentleman:</line>
            <line>Her name is Katharina Minola,</line>
            <line>Renown'd in Padua for her scolding tongue.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>I know her father, though I know not her;</line>
            <line>And he knew my deceased father well.</line>
            <line>I will not sleep, Hortensio, till I see her;</line>
            <line>And therefore let me be thus bold with you</line>
            <line>To give you over at this first encounter,</line>
            <line>Unless you will accompany me thither.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>I pray you, sir, let him go while the humour lasts.</line>
            <line>O' my word, an she knew him as well as I do, she</line>
            <line>would think scolding would do little good upon him:</line>
            <line>she may perhaps call him half a score knaves or so:</line>
            <line>why, that's nothing; an he begin once, he'll rail in</line>
            <line>his rope-tricks. I'll tell you what sir, an she</line>
            <line>stand him but a little, he will throw a figure in</line>
            <line>her face and so disfigure her with it that she</line>
            <line>shall have no more eyes to see withal than a cat.</line>
            <line>You know him not, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HORTENSIO</speaker>
            <line>Tarry, Petruchio, I must go with thee,</line>
            <line>For in Baptista's keep my treasure is:</line>
            <line>He hath the jewel of my life in hold,</line>
            <line>His youngest daughter, beautiful Binaca,</line>
            <line>And her withholds from me and other more,</line>
            <line>Suitors to her and rivals in my love,</line>
            <line>Supposing it a thing impossible,</line>
            <line>For those defects I have before rehearsed,</line>
            <line>That ever Katharina will be woo'd;</line>
            <line>Therefore this order hath Baptista ta'en,</line>
            <line>That none shall have access unto Bianca</line>
            <line>Till Katharina the curst have got a husband.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>Katharina the curst!</line>
            <line>A title for a maid of all titles the worst.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HORTENSIO</speaker>
            <line>Now shall my friend Petruchio do me grace,</line>
            <line>And offer me disguised in sober robes</line>
            <line>To old Baptista as a schoolmaster</line>
            <line>Well seen in music, to instruct Bianca;</line>
            <line>That so I may, by this device, at least</line>
            <line>Have leave and leisure to make love to her</line>
            <line>And unsuspected court her by herself.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>Here's no knavery! See, to beguile the old folks,</line>
            <line>how the young folks lay their heads together!</line>
            <stagedir>Enter GREMIO, and LUCENTIO disguised</stagedir>
            <line>Master, master, look about you: who goes there, ha?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HORTENSIO</speaker>
            <line>Peace, Grumio! it is the rival of my love.</line>
            <line>Petruchio, stand by a while.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>A proper stripling and an amorous!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GREMIO</speaker>
            <line>O, very well; I have perused the note.</line>
            <line>Hark you, sir: I'll have them very fairly bound:</line>
            <line>All books of love, see that at any hand;</line>
            <line>And see you read no other lectures to her:</line>
            <line>You understand me: over and beside</line>
            <line>Signior Baptista's liberality,</line>
            <line>I'll mend it with a largess. Take your paper too,</line>
            <line>And let me have them very well perfumed</line>
            <line>For she is sweeter than perfume itself</line>
            <line>To whom they go to. What will you read to her?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>Whate'er I read to her, I'll plead for you</line>
            <line>As for my patron, stand you so assured,</line>
            <line>As firmly as yourself were still in place:</line>
            <line>Yea, and perhaps with more successful words</line>
            <line>Than you, unless you were a scholar, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GREMIO</speaker>
            <line>O this learning, what a thing it is!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>O this woodcock, what an ass it is!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>Peace, sirrah!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HORTENSIO</speaker>
            <line>Grumio, mum! God save you, Signior Gremio.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GREMIO</speaker>
            <line>And you are well met, Signior Hortensio.</line>
            <line>Trow you whither I am going? To Baptista Minola.</line>
            <line>I promised to inquire carefully</line>
            <line>About a schoolmaster for the fair Bianca:</line>
            <line>And by good fortune I have lighted well</line>
            <line>On this young man, for learning and behavior</line>
            <line>Fit for her turn, well read in poetry</line>
            <line>And other books, good ones, I warrant ye.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HORTENSIO</speaker>
            <line>'Tis well; and I have met a gentleman</line>
            <line>Hath promised me to help me to another,</line>
            <line>A fine musician to instruct our mistress;</line>
            <line>So shall I no whit be behind in duty</line>
            <line>To fair Bianca, so beloved of me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GREMIO</speaker>
            <line>Beloved of me; and that my deeds shall prove.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>And that his bags shall prove.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HORTENSIO</speaker>
            <line>Gremio, 'tis now no time to vent our love:</line>
            <line>Listen to me, and if you speak me fair,</line>
            <line>I'll tell you news indifferent good for either.</line>
            <line>Here is a gentleman whom by chance I met,</line>
            <line>Upon agreement from us to his liking,</line>
            <line>Will undertake to woo curst Katharina,</line>
            <line>Yea, and to marry her, if her dowry please.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GREMIO</speaker>
            <line>So said, so done, is well.</line>
            <line>Hortensio, have you told him all her faults?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>I know she is an irksome brawling scold:</line>
            <line>If that be all, masters, I hear no harm.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GREMIO</speaker>
            <line>No, say'st me so, friend? What countryman?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>Born in Verona, old Antonio's son:</line>
            <line>My father dead, my fortune lives for me;</line>
            <line>And I do hope good days and long to see.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GREMIO</speaker>
            <line>O sir, such a life, with such a wife, were strange!</line>
            <line>But if you have a stomach, to't i' God's name:</line>
            <line>You shall have me assisting you in all.</line>
            <line>But will you woo this wild-cat?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>Will I live?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>Will he woo her? ay, or I'll hang her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>Why came I hither but to that intent?</line>
            <line>Think you a little din can daunt mine ears?</line>
            <line>Have I not in my time heard lions roar?</line>
            <line>Have I not heard the sea puff'd up with winds</line>
            <line>Rage like an angry boar chafed with sweat?</line>
            <line>Have I not heard great ordnance in the field,</line>
            <line>And heaven's artillery thunder in the skies?</line>
            <line>Have I not in a pitched battle heard</line>
            <line>Loud 'larums, neighing steeds, and trumpets' clang?</line>
            <line>And do you tell me of a woman's tongue,</line>
            <line>That gives not half so great a blow to hear</line>
            <line>As will a chestnut in a farmer's fire?</line>
            <line>Tush, tush! fear boys with bugs.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>For he fears none.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GREMIO</speaker>
            <line>Hortensio, hark:</line>
            <line>This gentleman is happily arrived,</line>
            <line>My mind presumes, for his own good and ours.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HORTENSIO</speaker>
            <line>I promised we would be contributors</line>
            <line>And bear his charging of wooing, whatsoe'er.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GREMIO</speaker>
            <line>And so we will, provided that he win her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <line>I would I were as sure of a good dinner.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter TRANIO brave, and BIONDELLO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRANIO</speaker>
            <line>Gentlemen, God save you. If I may be bold,</line>
            <line>Tell me, I beseech you, which is the readiest way</line>
            <line>To the house of Signior Baptista Minola?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BIONDELLO</speaker>
            <line>He that has the two fair daughters: is't he you mean?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRANIO</speaker>
            <line>Even he, Biondello.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GREMIO</speaker>
            <line>Hark you, sir; you mean not her to--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRANIO</speaker>
            <line>Perhaps, him and her, sir: what have you to do?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>Not her that chides, sir, at any hand, I pray.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRANIO</speaker>
            <line>I love no chiders, sir. Biondello, let's away.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>Well begun, Tranio.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HORTENSIO</speaker>
            <line>Sir, a word ere you go;</line>
            <line>Are you a suitor to the maid you talk of, yea or no?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRANIO</speaker>
            <line>And if I be, sir, is it any offence?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GREMIO</speaker>
            <line>No; if without more words you will get you hence.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRANIO</speaker>
            <line>Why, sir, I pray, are not the streets as free</line>
            <line>For me as for you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GREMIO</speaker>
            <line>But so is not she.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRANIO</speaker>
            <line>For what reason, I beseech you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GREMIO</speaker>
            <line>For this reason, if you'll know,</line>
            <line>That she's the choice love of Signior Gremio.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HORTENSIO</speaker>
            <line>That she's the chosen of Signior Hortensio.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRANIO</speaker>
            <line>Softly, my masters! if you be gentlemen,</line>
            <line>Do me this right; hear me with patience.</line>
            <line>Baptista is a noble gentleman,</line>
            <line>To whom my father is not all unknown;</line>
            <line>And were his daughter fairer than she is,</line>
            <line>She may more suitors have and me for one.</line>
            <line>Fair Leda's daughter had a thousand wooers;</line>
            <line>Then well one more may fair Bianca have:</line>
            <line>And so she shall; Lucentio shall make one,</line>
            <line>Though Paris came in hope to speed alone.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GREMIO</speaker>
            <line>What! this gentleman will out-talk us all.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>Sir, give him head: I know he'll prove a jade.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>Hortensio, to what end are all these words?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HORTENSIO</speaker>
            <line>Sir, let me be so bold as ask you,</line>
            <line>Did you yet ever see Baptista's daughter?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRANIO</speaker>
            <line>No, sir; but hear I do that he hath two,</line>
            <line>The one as famous for a scolding tongue</line>
            <line>As is the other for beauteous modesty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>Sir, sir, the first's for me; let her go by.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GREMIO</speaker>
            <line>Yea, leave that labour to great Hercules;</line>
            <line>And let it be more than Alcides' twelve.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETRUCHIO</speaker>
            <line>Sir, understand you this of me in sooth:</line>
            <line>The youngest daughter whom you hearken for</line>
            <line>Her father keeps from all access of suitors,</line>
            <line>And will not promise her to any man</line>
            <line>Until the elder sister first be wed:</line>
            <line>The younger then is free and not before.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRANIO</speaker>
            <line>If it be so, sir, that you are the man</line>
            <line>Must stead us all and me amongst the rest,</line>
            <line>And if you break the ice and do this feat,</line>
            <line>Achieve the elder, set the younger free</line>
            <line>For our access, whose hap shall be to have her</line>
            <line>Will not so graceless be to be ingrate.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HORTENSIO</speaker>
            <line>Sir, you say well and well you do conceive;</line>
            <line>And since you do profess to be a suitor,</line>
            <line>You must, as we do, gratify this gentleman,</line>
            <line>To whom we all rest generally beholding.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRANIO</speaker>
            <line>Sir, I shall not be slack: in sign whereof,</line>
            <line>Please ye we may contrive this afternoon,</line>
            <line>And quaff carouses to our mistress' health,</line>
            <line>And do as adversaries do in law,</line>
            <line>Strive mightily, but eat and drink as friends.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GRUMIO</speaker>
            <speaker>BIONDELLO</speaker>
            <line>O excellent motion! Fellows, let's be gone.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HORTENSIO</speaker>
            <line>The motion's good indeed and be it so,</line>
            <line>Petruchio, I shall be your ben venuto.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>