<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net/doctypes/dita/shakespear/dtd/act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-4">
   <title>ACT IV</title>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  Rome. Titus's garden.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter young LUCIUS, and LAVINIA running after him,
and the boy flies from her, with books under his
arm. Then enter TITUS and MARCUS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Young LUCIUS</speaker>
            <line>Help, grandsire, help! my aunt Lavinia</line>
            <line>Follows me every where, I know not why:</line>
            <line>Good uncle Marcus, see how swift she comes.</line>
            <line>Alas, sweet aunt, I know not what you mean.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Stand by me, Lucius; do not fear thine aunt.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>She loves thee, boy, too well to do thee harm.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Young LUCIUS</speaker>
            <line>Ay, when my father was in Rome she did.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>What means my niece Lavinia by these signs?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Fear her not, Lucius: somewhat doth she mean:</line>
            <line>See, Lucius, see how much she makes of thee:</line>
            <line>Somewhither would she have thee go with her.</line>
            <line>Ah, boy, Cornelia never with more care</line>
            <line>Read to her sons than she hath read to thee</line>
            <line>Sweet poetry and Tully's Orator.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Canst thou not guess wherefore she plies thee thus?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Young LUCIUS</speaker>
            <line>My lord, I know not, I, nor can I guess,</line>
            <line>Unless some fit or frenzy do possess her:</line>
            <line>For I have heard my grandsire say full oft,</line>
            <line>Extremity of griefs would make men mad;</line>
            <line>And I have read that Hecuba of Troy</line>
            <line>Ran mad through sorrow: that made me to fear;</line>
            <line>Although, my lord, I know my noble aunt</line>
            <line>Loves me as dear as e'er my mother did,</line>
            <line>And would not, but in fury, fright my youth:</line>
            <line>Which made me down to throw my books, and fly--</line>
            <line>Causeless, perhaps. But pardon me, sweet aunt:</line>
            <line>And, madam, if my uncle Marcus go,</line>
            <line>I will most willingly attend your ladyship.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Lucius, I will.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>LAVINIA turns over with her stumps the books which
LUCIUS has let fall</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>How now, Lavinia! Marcus, what means this?</line>
            <line>Some book there is that she desires to see.</line>
            <line>Which is it, girl, of these? Open them, boy.</line>
            <line>But thou art deeper read, and better skill'd</line>
            <line>Come, and take choice of all my library,</line>
            <line>And so beguile thy sorrow, till the heavens</line>
            <line>Reveal the damn'd contriver of this deed.</line>
            <line>Why lifts she up her arms in sequence thus?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>I think she means that there was more than one</line>
            <line>Confederate in the fact: ay, more there was;</line>
            <line>Or else to heaven she heaves them for revenge.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Lucius, what book is that she tosseth so?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Young LUCIUS</speaker>
            <line>Grandsire, 'tis Ovid's Metamorphoses;</line>
            <line>My mother gave it me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>For love of her that's gone,</line>
            <line>Perhaps she cull'd it from among the rest.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Soft! see how busily she turns the leaves!</line>
            <stagedir>Helping her</stagedir>
            <line>What would she find? Lavinia, shall I read?</line>
            <line>This is the tragic tale of Philomel,</line>
            <line>And treats of Tereus' treason and his rape:</line>
            <line>And rape, I fear, was root of thine annoy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>See, brother, see; note how she quotes the leaves.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Lavinia, wert thou thus surprised, sweet girl,</line>
            <line>Ravish'd and wrong'd, as Philomela was,</line>
            <line>Forced in the ruthless, vast, and gloomy woods? See, see!</line>
            <line>Ay, such a place there is, where we did hunt--</line>
            <line>O, had we never, never hunted there!--</line>
            <line>Pattern'd by that the poet here describes,</line>
            <line>By nature made for murders and for rapes.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>O, why should nature build so foul a den,</line>
            <line>Unless the gods delight in tragedies?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Give signs, sweet girl, for here are none</line>
            <line>but friends,</line>
            <line>What Roman lord it was durst do the deed:</line>
            <line>Or slunk not Saturnine, as Tarquin erst,</line>
            <line>That left the camp to sin in Lucrece' bed?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Sit down, sweet niece: brother, sit down by me.</line>
            <line>Apollo, Pallas, Jove, or Mercury,</line>
            <line>Inspire me, that I may this treason find!</line>
            <line>My lord, look here: look here, Lavinia:</line>
            <line>This sandy plot is plain; guide, if thou canst</line>
            <line>This after me, when I have writ my name</line>
            <line>Without the help of any hand at all.</line>
            <stagedir>He writes his name with his staff, and guides it
with feet and mouth</stagedir>
            <line>Cursed be that heart that forced us to this shift!</line>
            <line>Write thou good niece; and here display, at last,</line>
            <line>What God will have discover'd for revenge;</line>
            <line>Heaven guide thy pen to print thy sorrows plain,</line>
            <line>That we may know the traitors and the truth!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>She takes the staff in her mouth, and guides it
with her stumps, and writes</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>O, do ye read, my lord, what she hath writ?</line>
            <line>'Stuprum. Chiron. Demetrius.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>What, what! the lustful sons of Tamora</line>
            <line>Performers of this heinous, bloody deed?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Magni Dominator poli,</line>
            <line>Tam lentus audis scelera? tam lentus vides?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>O, calm thee, gentle lord; although I know</line>
            <line>There is enough written upon this earth</line>
            <line>To stir a mutiny in the mildest thoughts</line>
            <line>And arm the minds of infants to exclaims.</line>
            <line>My lord, kneel down with me; Lavinia, kneel;</line>
            <line>And kneel, sweet boy, the Roman Hector's hope;</line>
            <line>And swear with me, as, with the woful fere</line>
            <line>And father of that chaste dishonour'd dame,</line>
            <line>Lord Junius Brutus sware for Lucrece' rape,</line>
            <line>That we will prosecute by good advice</line>
            <line>Mortal revenge upon these traitorous Goths,</line>
            <line>And see their blood, or die with this reproach.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>'Tis sure enough, an you knew how.</line>
            <line>But if you hunt these bear-whelps, then beware:</line>
            <line>The dam will wake; and, if she wind you once,</line>
            <line>She's with the lion deeply still in league,</line>
            <line>And lulls him whilst she playeth on her back,</line>
            <line>And when he sleeps will she do what she list.</line>
            <line>You are a young huntsman, Marcus; let it alone;</line>
            <line>And, come, I will go get a leaf of brass,</line>
            <line>And with a gad of steel will write these words,</line>
            <line>And lay it by: the angry northern wind</line>
            <line>Will blow these sands, like Sibyl's leaves, abroad,</line>
            <line>And where's your lesson, then? Boy, what say you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Young LUCIUS</speaker>
            <line>I say, my lord, that if I were a man,</line>
            <line>Their mother's bed-chamber should not be safe</line>
            <line>For these bad bondmen to the yoke of Rome.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Ay, that's my boy! thy father hath full oft</line>
            <line>For his ungrateful country done the like.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Young LUCIUS</speaker>
            <line>And, uncle, so will I, an if I live.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Come, go with me into mine armoury;</line>
            <line>Lucius, I'll fit thee; and withal, my boy,</line>
            <line>Shalt carry from me to the empress' sons</line>
            <line>Presents that I intend to send them both:</line>
            <line>Come, come; thou'lt do thy message, wilt thou not?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Young LUCIUS</speaker>
            <line>Ay, with my dagger in their bosoms, grandsire.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>No, boy, not so; I'll teach thee another course.</line>
            <line>Lavinia, come. Marcus, look to my house:</line>
            <line>Lucius and I'll go brave it at the court:</line>
            <line>Ay, marry, will we, sir; and we'll be waited on.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt TITUS, LAVINIA, and Young LUCIUS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>O heavens, can you hear a good man groan,</line>
            <line>And not relent, or not compassion him?</line>
            <line>Marcus, attend him in his ecstasy,</line>
            <line>That hath more scars of sorrow in his heart</line>
            <line>Than foemen's marks upon his batter'd shield;</line>
            <line>But yet so just that he will not revenge.</line>
            <line>Revenge, ye heavens, for old Andronicus!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  The same. A room in the palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter, from one side, AARON, DEMETRIUS, and
CHIRON; from the other side, Young LUCIUS, and an
Attendant, with a bundle of weapons, and verses
writ upon them</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHIRON</speaker>
            <line>Demetrius, here's the son of Lucius;</line>
            <line>He hath some message to deliver us.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AARON</speaker>
            <line>Ay, some mad message from his mad grandfather.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Young LUCIUS</speaker>
            <line>My lords, with all the humbleness I may,</line>
            <line>I greet your honours from Andronicus.</line>
            <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>
            <line>And pray the Roman gods confound you both!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>Gramercy, lovely Lucius: what's the news?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Young LUCIUS</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  That you are both decipher'd, that's the news,</line>
            <line>For villains mark'd with rape.--May it please you,</line>
            <line>My grandsire, well advised, hath sent by me</line>
            <line>The goodliest weapons of his armoury</line>
            <line>To gratify your honourable youth,</line>
            <line>The hope of Rome; for so he bade me say;</line>
            <line>And so I do, and with his gifts present</line>
            <line>Your lordships, that, whenever you have need,</line>
            <line>You may be armed and appointed well:</line>
            <line>And so I leave you both:</line>
            <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>
            <line>like bloody villains.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt Young LUCIUS, and Attendant</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>What's here? A scroll; and written round about?</line>
            <line>Let's see;</line>
            <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>
            <line>'Integer vitae, scelerisque purus,</line>
            <line>Non eget Mauri jaculis, nec arcu.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHIRON</speaker>
            <line>O, 'tis a verse in Horace; I know it well:</line>
            <line>I read it in the grammar long ago.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AARON</speaker>
            <line>Ay, just; a verse in Horace; right, you have it.</line>
            <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>
            <line>Now, what a thing it is to be an ass!</line>
            <line>Here's no sound jest! the old man hath found their guilt;</line>
            <line>And sends them weapons wrapped about with lines,</line>
            <line>That wound, beyond their feeling, to the quick.</line>
            <line>But were our witty empress well afoot,</line>
            <line>She would applaud Andronicus' conceit:</line>
            <line>But let her rest in her unrest awhile.</line>
            <line>And now, young lords, was't not a happy star</line>
            <line>Led us to Rome, strangers, and more than so,</line>
            <line>Captives, to be advanced to this height?</line>
            <line>It did me good, before the palace gate</line>
            <line>To brave the tribune in his brother's hearing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>But me more good, to see so great a lord</line>
            <line>Basely insinuate and send us gifts.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AARON</speaker>
            <line>Had he not reason, Lord Demetrius?</line>
            <line>Did you not use his daughter very friendly?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>I would we had a thousand Roman dames</line>
            <line>At such a bay, by turn to serve our lust.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHIRON</speaker>
            <line>A charitable wish and full of love.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AARON</speaker>
            <line>Here lacks but your mother for to say amen.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHIRON</speaker>
            <line>And that would she for twenty thousand more.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>Come, let us go; and pray to all the gods</line>
            <line>For our beloved mother in her pains.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AARON</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  Pray to the devils; the gods have given us over.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Trumpets sound within</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>Why do the emperor's trumpets flourish thus?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHIRON</speaker>
            <line>Belike, for joy the emperor hath a son.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>Soft! who comes here?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter a Nurse, with a blackamoor Child in her arms</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Nurse</speaker>
            <line>Good morrow, lords:</line>
            <line>O, tell me, did you see Aaron the Moor?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AARON</speaker>
            <line>Well, more or less, or ne'er a whit at all,</line>
            <line>Here Aaron is; and what with Aaron now?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Nurse</speaker>
            <line>O gentle Aaron, we are all undone!</line>
            <line>Now help, or woe betide thee evermore!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AARON</speaker>
            <line>Why, what a caterwauling dost thou keep!</line>
            <line>What dost thou wrap and fumble in thine arms?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Nurse</speaker>
            <line>O, that which I would hide from heaven's eye,</line>
            <line>Our empress' shame, and stately Rome's disgrace!</line>
            <line>She is deliver'd, lords; she is deliver'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AARON</speaker>
            <line>To whom?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Nurse</speaker>
            <line>I mean, she is brought a-bed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AARON</speaker>
            <line>Well, God give her good rest! What hath he sent her?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Nurse</speaker>
            <line>A devil.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AARON</speaker>
            <line>Why, then she is the devil's dam; a joyful issue.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Nurse</speaker>
            <line>A joyless, dismal, black, and sorrowful issue:</line>
            <line>Here is the babe, as loathsome as a toad</line>
            <line>Amongst the fairest breeders of our clime:</line>
            <line>The empress sends it thee, thy stamp, thy seal,</line>
            <line>And bids thee christen it with thy dagger's point.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AARON</speaker>
            <line>'Zounds, ye whore! is black so base a hue?</line>
            <line>Sweet blowse, you are a beauteous blossom, sure.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>Villain, what hast thou done?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AARON</speaker>
            <line>That which thou canst not undo.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHIRON</speaker>
            <line>Thou hast undone our mother.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AARON</speaker>
            <line>Villain, I have done thy mother.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>And therein, hellish dog, thou hast undone.</line>
            <line>Woe to her chance, and damn'd her loathed choice!</line>
            <line>Accursed the offspring of so foul a fiend!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHIRON</speaker>
            <line>It shall not live.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AARON</speaker>
            <line>It shall not die.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Nurse</speaker>
            <line>Aaron, it must; the mother wills it so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AARON</speaker>
            <line>What, must it, nurse? then let no man but I</line>
            <line>Do execution on my flesh and blood.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>I'll broach the tadpole on my rapier's point:</line>
            <line>Nurse, give it me; my sword shall soon dispatch it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AARON</speaker>
            <line>Sooner this sword shall plough thy bowels up.</line>
            <stagedir>Takes the Child from the Nurse, and draws</stagedir>
            <line>Stay, murderous villains! will you kill your brother?</line>
            <line>Now, by the burning tapers of the sky,</line>
            <line>That shone so brightly when this boy was got,</line>
            <line>He dies upon my scimitar's sharp point</line>
            <line>That touches this my first-born son and heir!</line>
            <line>I tell you, younglings, not Enceladus,</line>
            <line>With all his threatening band of Typhon's brood,</line>
            <line>Nor great Alcides, nor the god of war,</line>
            <line>Shall seize this prey out of his father's hands.</line>
            <line>What, what, ye sanguine, shallow-hearted boys!</line>
            <line>Ye white-limed walls! ye alehouse painted signs!</line>
            <line>Coal-black is better than another hue,</line>
            <line>In that it scorns to bear another hue;</line>
            <line>For all the water in the ocean</line>
            <line>Can never turn the swan's black legs to white,</line>
            <line>Although she lave them hourly in the flood.</line>
            <line>Tell the empress from me, I am of age</line>
            <line>To keep mine own, excuse it how she can.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>Wilt thou betray thy noble mistress thus?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AARON</speaker>
            <line>My mistress is my mistress; this myself,</line>
            <line>The vigour and the picture of my youth:</line>
            <line>This before all the world do I prefer;</line>
            <line>This maugre all the world will I keep safe,</line>
            <line>Or some of you shall smoke for it in Rome.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>By this our mother is forever shamed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHIRON</speaker>
            <line>Rome will despise her for this foul escape.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Nurse</speaker>
            <line>The emperor, in his rage, will doom her death.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHIRON</speaker>
            <line>I blush to think upon this ignomy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AARON</speaker>
            <line>Why, there's the privilege your beauty bears:</line>
            <line>Fie, treacherous hue, that will betray with blushing</line>
            <line>The close enacts and counsels of the heart!</line>
            <line>Here's a young lad framed of another leer:</line>
            <line>Look, how the black slave smiles upon the father,</line>
            <line>As who should say 'Old lad, I am thine own.'</line>
            <line>He is your brother, lords, sensibly fed</line>
            <line>Of that self-blood that first gave life to you,</line>
            <line>And from that womb where you imprison'd were</line>
            <line>He is enfranchised and come to light:</line>
            <line>Nay, he is your brother by the surer side,</line>
            <line>Although my seal be stamped in his face.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Nurse</speaker>
            <line>Aaron, what shall I say unto the empress?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>Advise thee, Aaron, what is to be done,</line>
            <line>And we will all subscribe to thy advice:</line>
            <line>Save thou the child, so we may all be safe.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AARON</speaker>
            <line>Then sit we down, and let us all consult.</line>
            <line>My son and I will have the wind of you:</line>
            <line>Keep there: now talk at pleasure of your safety.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>They sit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>How many women saw this child of his?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AARON</speaker>
            <line>Why, so, brave lords! when we join in league,</line>
            <line>I am a lamb: but if you brave the Moor,</line>
            <line>The chafed boar, the mountain lioness,</line>
            <line>The ocean swells not so as Aaron storms.</line>
            <line>But say, again; how many saw the child?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Nurse</speaker>
            <line>Cornelia the midwife and myself;</line>
            <line>And no one else but the deliver'd empress.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AARON</speaker>
            <line>The empress, the midwife, and yourself:</line>
            <line>Two may keep counsel when the third's away:</line>
            <line>Go to the empress, tell her this I said.</line>
            <stagedir>He kills the nurse</stagedir>
            <line>Weke, weke! so cries a pig prepared to the spit.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>What mean'st thou, Aaron? wherefore didst thou this?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AARON</speaker>
            <line>O Lord, sir, 'tis a deed of policy:</line>
            <line>Shall she live to betray this guilt of ours,</line>
            <line>A long-tongued babbling gossip? no, lords, no:</line>
            <line>And now be it known to you my full intent.</line>
            <line>Not far, one Muli lives, my countryman;</line>
            <line>His wife but yesternight was brought to bed;</line>
            <line>His child is like to her, fair as you are:</line>
            <line>Go pack with him, and give the mother gold,</line>
            <line>And tell them both the circumstance of all;</line>
            <line>And how by this their child shall be advanced,</line>
            <line>And be received for the emperor's heir,</line>
            <line>And substituted in the place of mine,</line>
            <line>To calm this tempest whirling in the court;</line>
            <line>And let the emperor dandle him for his own.</line>
            <line>Hark ye, lords; ye see I have given her physic,</line>
            <stagedir>Pointing to the nurse</stagedir>
            <line>And you must needs bestow her funeral;</line>
            <line>The fields are near, and you are gallant grooms:</line>
            <line>This done, see that you take no longer days,</line>
            <line>But send the midwife presently to me.</line>
            <line>The midwife and the nurse well made away,</line>
            <line>Then let the ladies tattle what they please.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHIRON</speaker>
            <line>Aaron, I see thou wilt not trust the air</line>
            <line>With secrets.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>For this care of Tamora,</line>
            <line>Herself and hers are highly bound to thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt DEMETRIUS and CHIRON bearing off the
Nurse's body</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AARON</speaker>
            <line>Now to the Goths, as swift as swallow flies;</line>
            <line>There to dispose this treasure in mine arms,</line>
            <line>And secretly to greet the empress' friends.</line>
            <line>Come on, you thick lipp'd slave, I'll bear you hence;</line>
            <line>For it is you that puts us to our shifts:</line>
            <line>I'll make you feed on berries and on roots,</line>
            <line>And feed on curds and whey, and suck the goat,</line>
            <line>And cabin in a cave, and bring you up</line>
            <line>To be a warrior, and command a camp.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  The same. A public place.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter TITUS, bearing arrows with letters at the
ends of them; with him, MARCUS, Young LUCIUS,
PUBLIUS, SEMPRONIUS, CAIUS, and other Gentlemen,
with bows</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Come, Marcus; come, kinsmen; this is the way.</line>
            <line>Sir boy, now let me see your archery;</line>
            <line>Look ye draw home enough, and 'tis there straight.</line>
            <line>Terras Astraea reliquit:</line>
            <line>Be you remember'd, Marcus, she's gone, she's fled.</line>
            <line>Sirs, take you to your tools. You, cousins, shall</line>
            <line>Go sound the ocean, and cast your nets;</line>
            <line>Happily you may catch her in the sea;</line>
            <line>Yet there's as little justice as at land:</line>
            <line>No; Publius and Sempronius, you must do it;</line>
            <line>'Tis you must dig with mattock and with spade,</line>
            <line>And pierce the inmost centre of the earth:</line>
            <line>Then, when you come to Pluto's region,</line>
            <line>I pray you, deliver him this petition;</line>
            <line>Tell him, it is for justice and for aid,</line>
            <line>And that it comes from old Andronicus,</line>
            <line>Shaken with sorrows in ungrateful Rome.</line>
            <line>Ah, Rome! Well, well; I made thee miserable</line>
            <line>What time I threw the people's suffrages</line>
            <line>On him that thus doth tyrannize o'er me.</line>
            <line>Go, get you gone; and pray be careful all,</line>
            <line>And leave you not a man-of-war unsearch'd:</line>
            <line>This wicked emperor may have shipp'd her hence;</line>
            <line>And, kinsmen, then we may go pipe for justice.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>O Publius, is not this a heavy case,</line>
            <line>To see thy noble uncle thus distract?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PUBLIUS</speaker>
            <line>Therefore, my lord, it highly us concerns</line>
            <line>By day and night to attend him carefully,</line>
            <line>And feed his humour kindly as we may,</line>
            <line>Till time beget some careful remedy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Kinsmen, his sorrows are past remedy.</line>
            <line>Join with the Goths; and with revengeful war</line>
            <line>Take wreak on Rome for this ingratitude,</line>
            <line>And vengeance on the traitor Saturnine.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Publius, how now! how now, my masters!</line>
            <line>What, have you met with her?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PUBLIUS</speaker>
            <line>No, my good lord; but Pluto sends you word,</line>
            <line>If you will have Revenge from hell, you shall:</line>
            <line>Marry, for Justice, she is so employ'd,</line>
            <line>He thinks, with Jove in heaven, or somewhere else,</line>
            <line>So that perforce you must needs stay a time.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>He doth me wrong to feed me with delays.</line>
            <line>I'll dive into the burning lake below,</line>
            <line>And pull her out of Acheron by the heels.</line>
            <line>Marcus, we are but shrubs, no cedars we</line>
            <line>No big-boned men framed of the Cyclops' size;</line>
            <line>But metal, Marcus, steel to the very back,</line>
            <line>Yet wrung with wrongs more than our backs can bear:</line>
            <line>And, sith there's no justice in earth nor hell,</line>
            <line>We will solicit heaven and move the gods</line>
            <line>To send down Justice for to wreak our wrongs.</line>
            <line>Come, to this gear. You are a good archer, Marcus;</line>
            <stagedir>He gives them the arrows</stagedir>
            <line>'Ad Jovem,' that's for you: here, 'Ad Apollinem:'</line>
            <line>'Ad Martem,' that's for myself:</line>
            <line>Here, boy, to Pallas: here, to Mercury:</line>
            <line>To Saturn, Caius, not to Saturnine;</line>
            <line>You were as good to shoot against the wind.</line>
            <line>To it, boy! Marcus, loose when I bid.</line>
            <line>Of my word, I have written to effect;</line>
            <line>There's not a god left unsolicited.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Kinsmen, shoot all your shafts into the court:</line>
            <line>We will afflict the emperor in his pride.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Now, masters, draw.</line>
            <stagedir>They shoot</stagedir>
            <line>O, well said, Lucius!</line>
            <line>Good boy, in Virgo's lap; give it Pallas.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>My lord, I aim a mile beyond the moon;</line>
            <line>Your letter is with Jupiter by this.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Ha, ha!</line>
            <line>Publius, Publius, what hast thou done?</line>
            <line>See, see, thou hast shot off one of Taurus' horns.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>This was the sport, my lord: when Publius shot,</line>
            <line>The Bull, being gall'd, gave Aries such a knock</line>
            <line>That down fell both the Ram's horns in the court;</line>
            <line>And who should find them but the empress' villain?</line>
            <line>She laugh'd, and told the Moor he should not choose</line>
            <line>But give them to his master for a present.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Why, there it goes: God give his lordship joy!</line>
            <stagedir>Enter a Clown, with a basket, and two pigeons in
it</stagedir>
            <line>News, news from heaven! Marcus, the post is come.</line>
            <line>Sirrah, what tidings? have you any letters?</line>
            <line>Shall I have justice? what says Jupiter?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>O, the gibbet-maker! he says that he hath taken</line>
            <line>them down again, for the man must not be hanged till</line>
            <line>the next week.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>But what says Jupiter, I ask thee?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Alas, sir, I know not Jupiter; I never drank with him</line>
            <line>in all my life.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Why, villain, art not thou the carrier?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Ay, of my pigeons, sir; nothing else.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Why, didst thou not come from heaven?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>From heaven! alas, sir, I never came there     God</line>
            <line>forbid I should be so bold to press to heaven in my</line>
            <line>young days. Why, I am going with my pigeons to the</line>
            <line>tribunal plebs, to take up a matter of brawl</line>
            <line>betwixt my uncle and one of the emperial's men.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Why, sir, that is as fit as can be to serve for</line>
            <line>your oration; and let him deliver the pigeons to</line>
            <line>the emperor from you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Tell me, can you deliver an oration to the emperor</line>
            <line>with a grace?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Nay, truly, sir, I could never say grace in all my life.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Sirrah, come hither: make no more ado,</line>
            <line>But give your pigeons to the emperor:</line>
            <line>By me thou shalt have justice at his hands.</line>
            <line>Hold, hold; meanwhile here's money for thy charges.</line>
            <line>Give me pen and ink. Sirrah, can you with a grace</line>
            <line>deliver a supplication?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Ay, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Then here is a supplication for you. And when you</line>
            <line>come to him, at the first approach you must kneel,</line>
            <line>then kiss his foot, then deliver up your pigeons, and</line>
            <line>then look for your reward. I'll be at hand, sir; see</line>
            <line>you do it bravely.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>I warrant you, sir, let me alone.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Sirrah, hast thou a knife? come, let me see it.</line>
            <line>Here, Marcus, fold it in the oration;</line>
            <line>For thou hast made it like an humble suppliant.</line>
            <line>And when thou hast given it the emperor,</line>
            <line>Knock at my door, and tell me what he says.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>God be with you, sir; I will.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Come, Marcus, let us go. Publius, follow me.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-4">
      <title>SCENE IV.  The same. Before the palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter SATURNINUS, TAMORA, DEMETRIUS, CHIRON,
Lords, and others; SATURNINUS with the arrows in
his hand that TITUS shot</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SATURNINUS</speaker>
            <line>Why, lords, what wrongs are these! was ever seen</line>
            <line>An emperor in Rome thus overborne,</line>
            <line>Troubled, confronted thus; and, for the extent</line>
            <line>Of egal justice, used in such contempt?</line>
            <line>My lords, you know, as know the mightful gods,</line>
            <line>However these disturbers of our peace</line>
            <line>Buz in the people's ears, there nought hath pass'd,</line>
            <line>But even with law, against the willful sons</line>
            <line>Of old Andronicus. And what an if</line>
            <line>His sorrows have so overwhelm'd his wits,</line>
            <line>Shall we be thus afflicted in his wreaks,</line>
            <line>His fits, his frenzy, and his bitterness?</line>
            <line>And now he writes to heaven for his redress:</line>
            <line>See, here's to Jove, and this to Mercury;</line>
            <line>This to Apollo; this to the god of war;</line>
            <line>Sweet scrolls to fly about the streets of Rome!</line>
            <line>What's this but libelling against the senate,</line>
            <line>And blazoning our injustice every where?</line>
            <line>A goodly humour, is it not, my lords?</line>
            <line>As who would say, in Rome no justice were.</line>
            <line>But if I live, his feigned ecstasies</line>
            <line>Shall be no shelter to these outrages:</line>
            <line>But he and his shall know that justice lives</line>
            <line>In Saturninus' health, whom, if she sleep,</line>
            <line>He'll so awake as she in fury shall</line>
            <line>Cut off the proud'st conspirator that lives.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TAMORA</speaker>
            <line>My gracious lord, my lovely Saturnine,</line>
            <line>Lord of my life, commander of my thoughts,</line>
            <line>Calm thee, and bear the faults of Titus' age,</line>
            <line>The effects of sorrow for his valiant sons,</line>
            <line>Whose loss hath pierced him deep and scarr'd his heart;</line>
            <line>And rather comfort his distressed plight</line>
            <line>Than prosecute the meanest or the best</line>
            <line>For these contempts.</line>
            <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>
            <line>Why, thus it shall become</line>
            <line>High-witted Tamora to gloze with all:</line>
            <line>But, Titus, I have touched thee to the quick,</line>
            <line>Thy life-blood out: if Aaron now be wise,</line>
            <line>Then is all safe, the anchor's in the port.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter Clown</stagedir>
            <line>How now, good fellow! wouldst thou speak with us?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Yea, forsooth, an your mistership be emperial.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TAMORA</speaker>
            <line>Empress I am, but yonder sits the emperor.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>'Tis he. God and Saint Stephen give you good den:</line>
            <line>I have brought you a letter and a couple of pigeons here.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>SATURNINUS reads the letter</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SATURNINUS</speaker>
            <line>Go, take him away, and hang him presently.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>How much money must I have?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TAMORA</speaker>
            <line>Come, sirrah, you must be hanged.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Hanged! by'r lady, then I have brought up a neck to</line>
            <line>a fair end.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit, guarded</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SATURNINUS</speaker>
            <line>Despiteful and intolerable wrongs!</line>
            <line>Shall I endure this monstrous villany?</line>
            <line>I know from whence this same device proceeds:</line>
            <line>May this be borne?--as if his traitorous sons,</line>
            <line>That died by law for murder of our brother,</line>
            <line>Have by my means been butcher'd wrongfully!</line>
            <line>Go, drag the villain hither by the hair;</line>
            <line>Nor age nor honour shall shape privilege:</line>
            <line>For this proud mock I'll be thy slaughterman;</line>
            <line>Sly frantic wretch, that holp'st to make me great,</line>
            <line>In hope thyself should govern Rome and me.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter AEMILIUS</stagedir>
            <line>What news with thee, AEmilius?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AEMILIUS</speaker>
            <line>Arm, arm, my lord;--Rome never had more cause.</line>
            <line>The Goths have gather'd head; and with a power</line>
            <line>high-resolved men, bent to the spoil,</line>
            <line>They hither march amain, under conduct</line>
            <line>Of Lucius, son to old Andronicus;</line>
            <line>Who threats, in course of this revenge, to do</line>
            <line>As much as ever Coriolanus did.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SATURNINUS</speaker>
            <line>Is warlike Lucius general of the Goths?</line>
            <line>These tidings nip me, and I hang the head</line>
            <line>As flowers with frost or grass beat down with storms:</line>
            <line>Ay, now begin our sorrows to approach:</line>
            <line>'Tis he the common people love so much;</line>
            <line>Myself hath often over-heard them say,</line>
            <line>When I have walked like a private man,</line>
            <line>That Lucius' banishment was wrongfully,</line>
            <line>And they have wish'd that Lucius were their emperor.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TAMORA</speaker>
            <line>Why should you fear? is not your city strong?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SATURNINUS</speaker>
            <line>Ay, but the citizens favor Lucius,</line>
            <line>And will revolt from me to succor him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TAMORA</speaker>
            <line>King, be thy thoughts imperious, like thy name.</line>
            <line>Is the sun dimm'd, that gnats do fly in it?</line>
            <line>The eagle suffers little birds to sing,</line>
            <line>And is not careful what they mean thereby,</line>
            <line>Knowing that with the shadow of his wings</line>
            <line>He can at pleasure stint their melody:</line>
            <line>Even so mayst thou the giddy men of Rome.</line>
            <line>Then cheer thy spirit : for know, thou emperor,</line>
            <line>I will enchant the old Andronicus</line>
            <line>With words more sweet, and yet more dangerous,</line>
            <line>Than baits to fish, or honey-stalks to sheep,</line>
            <line>When as the one is wounded with the bait,</line>
            <line>The other rotted with delicious feed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SATURNINUS</speaker>
            <line>But he will not entreat his son for us.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TAMORA</speaker>
            <line>If Tamora entreat him, then he will:</line>
            <line>For I can smooth and fill his aged ear</line>
            <line>With golden promises; that, were his heart</line>
            <line>Almost impregnable, his old ears deaf,</line>
            <line>Yet should both ear and heart obey my tongue.</line>
            <stagedir>To AEmilius</stagedir>
            <line>Go thou before, be our ambassador:</line>
            <line>Say that the emperor requests a parley</line>
            <line>Of warlike Lucius, and appoint the meeting</line>
            <line>Even at his father's house, the old Andronicus.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SATURNINUS</speaker>
            <line>AEmilius, do this message honourably:</line>
            <line>And if he stand on hostage for his safety,</line>
            <line>Bid him demand what pledge will please him best.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AEMILIUS</speaker>
            <line>Your bidding shall I do effectually.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TAMORA</speaker>
            <line>Now will I to that old Andronicus;</line>
            <line>And temper him with all the art I have,</line>
            <line>To pluck proud Lucius from the warlike Goths.</line>
            <line>And now, sweet emperor, be blithe again,</line>
            <line>And bury all thy fear in my devices.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SATURNINUS</speaker>
            <line>Then go successantly, and plead to him.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>