<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:shakespear:dtd:act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-1">
   <title>ACT I</title>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  Rome. Before the Capitol.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>The Tomb of the ANDRONICI appearing; the Tribunes
and Senators aloft. Enter, below, from one side,
SATURNINUS and his Followers; and, from the other
side, BASSIANUS and his Followers; with drum and colours</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SATURNINUS</speaker>
            <line>Noble patricians, patrons of my right,</line>
            <line>Defend the justice of my cause with arms,</line>
            <line>And, countrymen, my loving followers,</line>
            <line>Plead my successive title with your swords:</line>
            <line>I am his first-born son, that was the last</line>
            <line>That wore the imperial diadem of Rome;</line>
            <line>Then let my father's honours live in me,</line>
            <line>Nor wrong mine age with this indignity.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSIANUS</speaker>
            <line>Romans, friends, followers, favorers of my right,</line>
            <line>If ever Bassianus, Caesar's son,</line>
            <line>Were gracious in the eyes of royal Rome,</line>
            <line>Keep then this passage to the Capitol</line>
            <line>And suffer not dishonour to approach</line>
            <line>The imperial seat, to virtue consecrate,</line>
            <line>To justice, continence and nobility;</line>
            <line>But let desert in pure election shine,</line>
            <line>And, Romans, fight for freedom in your choice.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter MARCUS ANDRONICUS, aloft, with the crown</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Princes, that strive by factions and by friends</line>
            <line>Ambitiously for rule and empery,</line>
            <line>Know that the people of Rome, for whom we stand</line>
            <line>A special party, have, by common voice,</line>
            <line>In election for the Roman empery,</line>
            <line>Chosen Andronicus, surnamed Pius</line>
            <line>For many good and great deserts to Rome:</line>
            <line>A nobler man, a braver warrior,</line>
            <line>Lives not this day within the city walls:</line>
            <line>He by the senate is accit'd home</line>
            <line>From weary wars against the barbarous Goths;</line>
            <line>That, with his sons, a terror to our foes,</line>
            <line>Hath yoked a nation strong, train'd up in arms.</line>
            <line>Ten years are spent since first he undertook</line>
            <line>This cause of Rome and chastised with arms</line>
            <line>Our enemies' pride: five times he hath return'd</line>
            <line>Bleeding to Rome, bearing his valiant sons</line>
            <line>In coffins from the field;</line>
            <line>And now at last, laden with horror's spoils,</line>
            <line>Returns the good Andronicus to Rome,</line>
            <line>Renowned Titus, flourishing in arms.</line>
            <line>Let us entreat, by honour of his name,</line>
            <line>Whom worthily you would have now succeed.</line>
            <line>And in the Capitol and senate's right,</line>
            <line>Whom you pretend to honour and adore,</line>
            <line>That you withdraw you and abate your strength;</line>
            <line>Dismiss your followers and, as suitors should,</line>
            <line>Plead your deserts in peace and humbleness.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SATURNINUS</speaker>
            <line>How fair the tribune speaks to calm my thoughts!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSIANUS</speaker>
            <line>Marcus Andronicus, so I do ally</line>
            <line>In thy uprightness and integrity,</line>
            <line>And so I love and honour thee and thine,</line>
            <line>Thy noble brother Titus and his sons,</line>
            <line>And her to whom my thoughts are humbled all,</line>
            <line>Gracious Lavinia, Rome's rich ornament,</line>
            <line>That I will here dismiss my loving friends,</line>
            <line>And to my fortunes and the people's favor</line>
            <line>Commit my cause in balance to be weigh'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt the followers of BASSIANUS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SATURNINUS</speaker>
            <line>Friends, that have been thus forward in my right,</line>
            <line>I thank you all and here dismiss you all,</line>
            <line>And to the love and favor of my country</line>
            <line>Commit myself, my person and the cause.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt the followers of SATURNINUS</stagedir>
            <line>Rome, be as just and gracious unto me</line>
            <line>As I am confident and kind to thee.</line>
            <line>Open the gates, and let me in.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSIANUS</speaker>
            <line>Tribunes, and me, a poor competitor.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Flourish. SATURNINUS and BASSIANUS go up into the Capitol</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Enter a Captain</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Captain</speaker>
            <line>Romans, make way: the good Andronicus.</line>
            <line>Patron of virtue, Rome's best champion,</line>
            <line>Successful in the battles that he fights,</line>
            <line>With honour and with fortune is return'd</line>
            <line>From where he circumscribed with his sword,</line>
            <line>And brought to yoke, the enemies of Rome.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Drums and trumpets sounded. Enter MARTIUS and
MUTIUS; After them, two Men bearing a coffin
covered with black; then LUCIUS and QUINTUS. After
them, TITUS ANDRONICUS; and then TAMORA, with
ALARBUS, DEMETRIUS, CHIRON, AARON, and other Goths,
prisoners; Soldiers and people following. The
Bearers set down the coffin, and TITUS speaks</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Hail, Rome, victorious in thy mourning weeds!</line>
            <line>Lo, as the bark, that hath discharged her fraught,</line>
            <line>Returns with precious jading to the bay</line>
            <line>From whence at first she weigh'd her anchorage,</line>
            <line>Cometh Andronicus, bound with laurel boughs,</line>
            <line>To re-salute his country with his tears,</line>
            <line>Tears of true joy for his return to Rome.</line>
            <line>Thou great defender of this Capitol,</line>
            <line>Stand gracious to the rites that we intend!</line>
            <line>Romans, of five and twenty valiant sons,</line>
            <line>Half of the number that King Priam had,</line>
            <line>Behold the poor remains, alive and dead!</line>
            <line>These that survive let Rome reward with love;</line>
            <line>These that I bring unto their latest home,</line>
            <line>With burial amongst their ancestors:</line>
            <line>Here Goths have given me leave to sheathe my sword.</line>
            <line>Titus, unkind and careless of thine own,</line>
            <line>Why suffer'st thou thy sons, unburied yet,</line>
            <line>To hover on the dreadful shore of Styx?</line>
            <line>Make way to lay them by their brethren.</line>
            <stagedir>The tomb is opened</stagedir>
            <line>There greet in silence, as the dead are wont,</line>
            <line>And sleep in peace, slain in your country's wars!</line>
            <line>O sacred receptacle of my joys,</line>
            <line>Sweet cell of virtue and nobility,</line>
            <line>How many sons of mine hast thou in store,</line>
            <line>That thou wilt never render to me more!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIUS</speaker>
            <line>Give us the proudest prisoner of the Goths,</line>
            <line>That we may hew his limbs, and on a pile</line>
            <line>Ad manes fratrum sacrifice his flesh,</line>
            <line>Before this earthy prison of their bones;</line>
            <line>That so the shadows be not unappeased,</line>
            <line>Nor we disturb'd with prodigies on earth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>I give him you, the noblest that survives,</line>
            <line>The eldest son of this distressed queen.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TAMORA</speaker>
            <line>Stay, Roman brethren! Gracious conqueror,</line>
            <line>Victorious Titus, rue the tears I shed,</line>
            <line>A mother's tears in passion for her son:</line>
            <line>And if thy sons were ever dear to thee,</line>
            <line>O, think my son to be as dear to me!</line>
            <line>Sufficeth not that we are brought to Rome,</line>
            <line>To beautify thy triumphs and return,</line>
            <line>Captive to thee and to thy Roman yoke,</line>
            <line>But must my sons be slaughter'd in the streets,</line>
            <line>For valiant doings in their country's cause?</line>
            <line>O, if to fight for king and commonweal</line>
            <line>Were piety in thine, it is in these.</line>
            <line>Andronicus, stain not thy tomb with blood:</line>
            <line>Wilt thou draw near the nature of the gods?</line>
            <line>Draw near them then in being merciful:</line>
            <line>Sweet mercy is nobility's true badge:</line>
            <line>Thrice noble Titus, spare my first-born son.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Patient yourself, madam, and pardon me.</line>
            <line>These are their brethren, whom you Goths beheld</line>
            <line>Alive and dead, and for their brethren slain</line>
            <line>Religiously they ask a sacrifice:</line>
            <line>To this your son is mark'd, and die he must,</line>
            <line>To appease their groaning shadows that are gone.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIUS</speaker>
            <line>Away with him! and make a fire straight;</line>
            <line>And with our swords, upon a pile of wood,</line>
            <line>Let's hew his limbs till they be clean consumed.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt LUCIUS, QUINTUS, MARTIUS, and MUTIUS, with ALARBUS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TAMORA</speaker>
            <line>O cruel, irreligious piety!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHIRON</speaker>
            <line>Was ever Scythia half so barbarous?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>Oppose not Scythia to ambitious Rome.</line>
            <line>Alarbus goes to rest; and we survive</line>
            <line>To tremble under Titus' threatening looks.</line>
            <line>Then, madam, stand resolved, but hope withal</line>
            <line>The self-same gods that arm'd the Queen of Troy</line>
            <line>With opportunity of sharp revenge</line>
            <line>Upon the Thracian tyrant in his tent,</line>
            <line>May favor Tamora, the Queen of Goths--</line>
            <line>When Goths were Goths and Tamora was queen--</line>
            <line>To quit the bloody wrongs upon her foes.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter LUCIUS, QUINTUS, MARTIUS and MUTIUS, with
their swords bloody</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIUS</speaker>
            <line>See, lord and father, how we have perform'd</line>
            <line>Our Roman rites: Alarbus' limbs are lopp'd,</line>
            <line>And entrails feed the sacrificing fire,</line>
            <line>Whose smoke, like incense, doth perfume the sky.</line>
            <line>Remaineth nought, but to inter our brethren,</line>
            <line>And with loud 'larums welcome them to Rome.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Let it be so; and let Andronicus</line>
            <line>Make this his latest farewell to their souls.</line>
            <stagedir>Trumpets sounded, and the coffin laid in the tomb</stagedir>
            <line>In peace and honour rest you here, my sons;</line>
            <line>Rome's readiest champions, repose you here in rest,</line>
            <line>Secure from worldly chances and mishaps!</line>
            <line>Here lurks no treason, here no envy swells,</line>
            <line>Here grow no damned grudges; here are no storms,</line>
            <line>No noise, but silence and eternal sleep:</line>
            <line>In peace and honour rest you here, my sons!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter LAVINIA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAVINIA</speaker>
            <line>In peace and honour live Lord Titus long;</line>
            <line>My noble lord and father, live in fame!</line>
            <line>Lo, at this tomb my tributary tears</line>
            <line>I render, for my brethren's obsequies;</line>
            <line>And at thy feet I kneel, with tears of joy,</line>
            <line>Shed on the earth, for thy return to Rome:</line>
            <line>O, bless me here with thy victorious hand,</line>
            <line>Whose fortunes Rome's best citizens applaud!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Kind Rome, that hast thus lovingly reserved</line>
            <line>The cordial of mine age to glad my heart!</line>
            <line>Lavinia, live; outlive thy father's days,</line>
            <line>And fame's eternal date, for virtue's praise!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter, below, MARCUS ANDRONICUS and Tribunes;
re-enter SATURNINUS and BASSIANUS, attended</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Long live Lord Titus, my beloved brother,</line>
            <line>Gracious triumpher in the eyes of Rome!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Thanks, gentle tribune, noble brother Marcus.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>And welcome, nephews, from successful wars,</line>
            <line>You that survive, and you that sleep in fame!</line>
            <line>Fair lords, your fortunes are alike in all,</line>
            <line>That in your country's service drew your swords:</line>
            <line>But safer triumph is this funeral pomp,</line>
            <line>That hath aspired to Solon's happiness</line>
            <line>And triumphs over chance in honour's bed.</line>
            <line>Titus Andronicus, the people of Rome,</line>
            <line>Whose friend in justice thou hast ever been,</line>
            <line>Send thee by me, their tribune and their trust,</line>
            <line>This palliament of white and spotless hue;</line>
            <line>And name thee in election for the empire,</line>
            <line>With these our late-deceased emperor's sons:</line>
            <line>Be candidatus then, and put it on,</line>
            <line>And help to set a head on headless Rome.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>A better head her glorious body fits</line>
            <line>Than his that shakes for age and feebleness:</line>
            <line>What should I don this robe, and trouble you?</line>
            <line>Be chosen with proclamations to-day,</line>
            <line>To-morrow yield up rule, resign my life,</line>
            <line>And set abroad new business for you all?</line>
            <line>Rome, I have been thy soldier forty years,</line>
            <line>And led my country's strength successfully,</line>
            <line>And buried one and twenty valiant sons,</line>
            <line>Knighted in field, slain manfully in arms,</line>
            <line>In right and service of their noble country</line>
            <line>Give me a staff of honour for mine age,</line>
            <line>But not a sceptre to control the world:</line>
            <line>Upright he held it, lords, that held it last.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Titus, thou shalt obtain and ask the empery.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SATURNINUS</speaker>
            <line>Proud and ambitious tribune, canst thou tell?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Patience, Prince Saturninus.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SATURNINUS</speaker>
            <line>Romans, do me right:</line>
            <line>Patricians, draw your swords: and sheathe them not</line>
            <line>Till Saturninus be Rome's emperor.</line>
            <line>Andronicus, would thou wert shipp'd to hell,</line>
            <line>Rather than rob me of the people's hearts!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIUS</speaker>
            <line>Proud Saturnine, interrupter of the good</line>
            <line>That noble-minded Titus means to thee!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Content thee, prince; I will restore to thee</line>
            <line>The people's hearts, and wean them from themselves.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSIANUS</speaker>
            <line>Andronicus, I do not flatter thee,</line>
            <line>But honour thee, and will do till I die:</line>
            <line>My faction if thou strengthen with thy friends,</line>
            <line>I will most thankful be; and thanks to men</line>
            <line>Of noble minds is honourable meed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>People of Rome, and people's tribunes here,</line>
            <line>I ask your voices and your suffrages:</line>
            <line>Will you bestow them friendly on Andronicus?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Tribunes</speaker>
            <line>To gratify the good Andronicus,</line>
            <line>And gratulate his safe return to Rome,</line>
            <line>The people will accept whom he admits.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Tribunes, I thank you: and this suit I make,</line>
            <line>That you create your emperor's eldest son,</line>
            <line>Lord Saturnine; whose virtues will, I hope,</line>
            <line>Reflect on Rome as Titan's rays on earth,</line>
            <line>And ripen justice in this commonweal:</line>
            <line>Then, if you will elect by my advice,</line>
            <line>Crown him and say 'Long live our emperor!'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>With voices and applause of every sort,</line>
            <line>Patricians and plebeians, we create</line>
            <line>Lord Saturninus Rome's great emperor,</line>
            <line>And say 'Long live our Emperor Saturnine!'</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>A long flourish till they come down</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SATURNINUS</speaker>
            <line>Titus Andronicus, for thy favors done</line>
            <line>To us in our election this day,</line>
            <line>I give thee thanks in part of thy deserts,</line>
            <line>And will with deeds requite thy gentleness:</line>
            <line>And, for an onset, Titus, to advance</line>
            <line>Thy name and honourable family,</line>
            <line>Lavinia will I make my empress,</line>
            <line>Rome's royal mistress, mistress of my heart,</line>
            <line>And in the sacred Pantheon her espouse:</line>
            <line>Tell me, Andronicus, doth this motion please thee?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>It doth, my worthy lord; and in this match</line>
            <line>I hold me highly honour'd of your grace:</line>
            <line>And here in sight of Rome to Saturnine,</line>
            <line>King and commander of our commonweal,</line>
            <line>The wide world's emperor, do I consecrate</line>
            <line>My sword, my chariot and my prisoners;</line>
            <line>Presents well worthy Rome's imperial lord:</line>
            <line>Receive them then, the tribute that I owe,</line>
            <line>Mine honour's ensigns humbled at thy feet.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SATURNINUS</speaker>
            <line>Thanks, noble Titus, father of my life!</line>
            <line>How proud I am of thee and of thy gifts</line>
            <line>Rome shall record, and when I do forget</line>
            <line>The least of these unspeakable deserts,</line>
            <line>Romans, forget your fealty to me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>To TAMORA</stagedir>  Now, madam, are you prisoner to</line>
            <line>an emperor;</line>
            <line>To him that, for your honour and your state,</line>
            <line>Will use you nobly and your followers.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SATURNINUS</speaker>
            <line>A goodly lady, trust me; of the hue</line>
            <line>That I would choose, were I to choose anew.</line>
            <line>Clear up, fair queen, that cloudy countenance:</line>
            <line>Though chance of war hath wrought this change of cheer,</line>
            <line>Thou comest not to be made a scorn in Rome:</line>
            <line>Princely shall be thy usage every way.</line>
            <line>Rest on my word, and let not discontent</line>
            <line>Daunt all your hopes: madam, he comforts you</line>
            <line>Can make you greater than the Queen of Goths.</line>
            <line>Lavinia, you are not displeased with this?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAVINIA</speaker>
            <line>Not I, my lord; sith true nobility</line>
            <line>Warrants these words in princely courtesy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SATURNINUS</speaker>
            <line>Thanks, sweet Lavinia. Romans, let us go;</line>
            <line>Ransomless here we set our prisoners free:</line>
            <line>Proclaim our honours, lords, with trump and drum.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Flourish. SATURNINUS courts TAMORA in dumb show</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSIANUS</speaker>
            <line>Lord Titus, by your leave, this maid is mine.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Seizing LAVINIA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>How, sir! are you in earnest then, my lord?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSIANUS</speaker>
            <line>Ay, noble Titus; and resolved withal</line>
            <line>To do myself this reason and this right.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>'Suum cuique' is our Roman justice:</line>
            <line>This prince in justice seizeth but his own.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIUS</speaker>
            <line>And that he will, and shall, if Lucius live.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Traitors, avaunt! Where is the emperor's guard?</line>
            <line>Treason, my lord! Lavinia is surprised!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SATURNINUS</speaker>
            <line>Surprised! by whom?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSIANUS</speaker>
            <line>By him that justly may</line>
            <line>Bear his betroth'd from all the world away.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt BASSIANUS and MARCUS with LAVINIA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MUTIUS</speaker>
            <line>Brothers, help to convey her hence away,</line>
            <line>And with my sword I'll keep this door safe.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt LUCIUS, QUINTUS, and MARTIUS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Follow, my lord, and I'll soon bring her back.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MUTIUS</speaker>
            <line>My lord, you pass not here.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>What, villain boy!</line>
            <line>Barr'st me my way in Rome?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Stabbing MUTIUS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MUTIUS</speaker>
            <line>Help, Lucius, help!</line>
            <stagedir>Dies</stagedir>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>During the fray, SATURNINUS, TAMORA, DEMETRIUS,
CHIRON and AARON go out and re-enter, above</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Re-enter LUCIUS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIUS</speaker>
            <line>My lord, you are unjust, and, more than so,</line>
            <line>In wrongful quarrel you have slain your son.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Nor thou, nor he, are any sons of mine;</line>
            <line>My sons would never so dishonour me:</line>
            <line>Traitor, restore Lavinia to the emperor.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIUS</speaker>
            <line>Dead, if you will; but not to be his wife,</line>
            <line>That is another's lawful promised love.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SATURNINUS</speaker>
            <line>No, Titus, no; the emperor needs her not,</line>
            <line>Nor her, nor thee, nor any of thy stock:</line>
            <line>I'll trust, by leisure, him that mocks me once;</line>
            <line>Thee never, nor thy traitorous haughty sons,</line>
            <line>Confederates all thus to dishonour me.</line>
            <line>Was there none else in Rome to make a stale,</line>
            <line>But Saturnine? Full well, Andronicus,</line>
            <line>Agree these deeds with that proud brag of thine,</line>
            <line>That said'st I begg'd the empire at thy hands.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>O monstrous! what reproachful words are these?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SATURNINUS</speaker>
            <line>But go thy ways; go, give that changing piece</line>
            <line>To him that flourish'd for her with his sword</line>
            <line>A valiant son-in-law thou shalt enjoy;</line>
            <line>One fit to bandy with thy lawless sons,</line>
            <line>To ruffle in the commonwealth of Rome.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>These words are razors to my wounded heart.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SATURNINUS</speaker>
            <line>And therefore, lovely Tamora, queen of Goths,</line>
            <line>That like the stately Phoebe 'mongst her nymphs</line>
            <line>Dost overshine the gallant'st dames of Rome,</line>
            <line>If thou be pleased with this my sudden choice,</line>
            <line>Behold, I choose thee, Tamora, for my bride,</line>
            <line>And will create thee empress of Rome,</line>
            <line>Speak, Queen of Goths, dost thou applaud my choice?</line>
            <line>And here I swear by all the Roman gods,</line>
            <line>Sith priest and holy water are so near</line>
            <line>And tapers burn so bright and every thing</line>
            <line>In readiness for Hymenaeus stand,</line>
            <line>I will not re-salute the streets of Rome,</line>
            <line>Or climb my palace, till from forth this place</line>
            <line>I lead espoused my bride along with me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TAMORA</speaker>
            <line>And here, in sight of heaven, to Rome I swear,</line>
            <line>If Saturnine advance the Queen of Goths,</line>
            <line>She will a handmaid be to his desires,</line>
            <line>A loving nurse, a mother to his youth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SATURNINUS</speaker>
            <line>Ascend, fair queen, Pantheon. Lords, accompany</line>
            <line>Your noble emperor and his lovely bride,</line>
            <line>Sent by the heavens for Prince Saturnine,</line>
            <line>Whose wisdom hath her fortune conquered:</line>
            <line>There shall we consummate our spousal rites.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt all but TITUS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>I am not bid to wait upon this bride.</line>
            <line>Titus, when wert thou wont to walk alone,</line>
            <line>Dishonour'd thus, and challenged of wrongs?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter MARCUS, LUCIUS, QUINTUS, and MARTIUS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>O Titus, see, O, see what thou hast done!</line>
            <line>In a bad quarrel slain a virtuous son.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>No, foolish tribune, no; no son of mine,</line>
            <line>Nor thou, nor these, confederates in the deed</line>
            <line>That hath dishonour'd all our family;</line>
            <line>Unworthy brother, and unworthy sons!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIUS</speaker>
            <line>But let us give him burial, as becomes;</line>
            <line>Give Mutius burial with our brethren.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Traitors, away! he rests not in this tomb:</line>
            <line>This monument five hundred years hath stood,</line>
            <line>Which I have sumptuously re-edified:</line>
            <line>Here none but soldiers and Rome's servitors</line>
            <line>Repose in fame; none basely slain in brawls:</line>
            <line>Bury him where you can; he comes not here.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>My lord, this is impiety in you:</line>
            <line>My nephew Mutius' deeds do plead for him</line>
            <line>He must be buried with his brethren.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUINTUS</speaker>
            <speaker>MARTIUS</speaker>
            <line>And shall, or him we will accompany.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>'And shall!' what villain was it that spake</line>
            <line>that word?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUINTUS</speaker>
            <line>He that would vouch it in any place but here.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>What, would you bury him in my despite?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>No, noble Titus, but entreat of thee</line>
            <line>To pardon Mutius and to bury him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Marcus, even thou hast struck upon my crest,</line>
            <line>And, with these boys, mine honour thou hast wounded:</line>
            <line>My foes I do repute you every one;</line>
            <line>So, trouble me no more, but get you gone.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARTIUS</speaker>
            <line>He is not with himself; let us withdraw.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUINTUS</speaker>
            <line>Not I, till Mutius' bones be buried.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>MARCUS and the Sons of TITUS kneel</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Brother, for in that name doth nature plead,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUINTUS</speaker>
            <line>Father, and in that name doth nature speak,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Speak thou no more, if all the rest will speed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Renowned Titus, more than half my soul,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIUS</speaker>
            <line>Dear father, soul and substance of us all,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Suffer thy brother Marcus to inter</line>
            <line>His noble nephew here in virtue's nest,</line>
            <line>That died in honour and Lavinia's cause.</line>
            <line>Thou art a Roman; be not barbarous:</line>
            <line>The Greeks upon advice did bury Ajax</line>
            <line>That slew himself; and wise Laertes' son</line>
            <line>Did graciously plead for his funerals:</line>
            <line>Let not young Mutius, then, that was thy joy</line>
            <line>Be barr'd his entrance here.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Rise, Marcus, rise.</line>
            <line>The dismall'st day is this that e'er I saw,</line>
            <line>To be dishonour'd by my sons in Rome!</line>
            <line>Well, bury him, and bury me the next.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>MUTIUS is put into the tomb</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIUS</speaker>
            <line>There lie thy bones, sweet Mutius, with thy friends,</line>
            <line>Till we with trophies do adorn thy tomb.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>All</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Kneeling</stagedir>  No man shed tears for noble Mutius;</line>
            <line>He lives in fame that died in virtue's cause.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>My lord, to step out of these dreary dumps,</line>
            <line>How comes it that the subtle Queen of Goths</line>
            <line>Is of a sudden thus advanced in Rome?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>I know not, Marcus; but I know it is,</line>
            <line>Whether by device or no, the heavens can tell:</line>
            <line>Is she not then beholding to the man</line>
            <line>That brought her for this high good turn so far?</line>
            <line>Yes, and will nobly him remunerate.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Flourish. Re-enter, from one side, SATURNINUS
attended, TAMORA, DEMETRIUS, CHIRON and AARON; from
the other, BASSIANUS, LAVINIA, and others</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SATURNINUS</speaker>
            <line>So, Bassianus, you have play'd your prize:</line>
            <line>God give you joy, sir, of your gallant bride!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSIANUS</speaker>
            <line>And you of yours, my lord! I say no more,</line>
            <line>Nor wish no less; and so, I take my leave.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SATURNINUS</speaker>
            <line>Traitor, if Rome have law or we have power,</line>
            <line>Thou and thy faction shall repent this rape.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSIANUS</speaker>
            <line>Rape, call you it, my lord, to seize my own,</line>
            <line>My truth-betrothed love and now my wife?</line>
            <line>But let the laws of Rome determine all;</line>
            <line>Meanwhile I am possess'd of that is mine.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SATURNINUS</speaker>
            <line>'Tis good, sir: you are very short with us;</line>
            <line>But, if we live, we'll be as sharp with you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSIANUS</speaker>
            <line>My lord, what I have done, as best I may,</line>
            <line>Answer I must and shall do with my life.</line>
            <line>Only thus much I give your grace to know:</line>
            <line>By all the duties that I owe to Rome,</line>
            <line>This noble gentleman, Lord Titus here,</line>
            <line>Is in opinion and in honour wrong'd;</line>
            <line>That in the rescue of Lavinia</line>
            <line>With his own hand did slay his youngest son,</line>
            <line>In zeal to you and highly moved to wrath</line>
            <line>To be controll'd in that he frankly gave:</line>
            <line>Receive him, then, to favor, Saturnine,</line>
            <line>That hath express'd himself in all his deeds</line>
            <line>A father and a friend to thee and Rome.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Prince Bassianus, leave to plead my deeds:</line>
            <line>'Tis thou and those that have dishonour'd me.</line>
            <line>Rome and the righteous heavens be my judge,</line>
            <line>How I have loved and honour'd Saturnine!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TAMORA</speaker>
            <line>My worthy lord, if ever Tamora</line>
            <line>Were gracious in those princely eyes of thine,</line>
            <line>Then hear me speak in indifferently for all;</line>
            <line>And at my suit, sweet, pardon what is past.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SATURNINUS</speaker>
            <line>What, madam! be dishonour'd openly,</line>
            <line>And basely put it up without revenge?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TAMORA</speaker>
            <line>Not so, my lord; the gods of Rome forfend</line>
            <line>I should be author to dishonour you!</line>
            <line>But on mine honour dare I undertake</line>
            <line>For good Lord Titus' innocence in all;</line>
            <line>Whose fury not dissembled speaks his griefs:</line>
            <line>Then, at my suit, look graciously on him;</line>
            <line>Lose not so noble a friend on vain suppose,</line>
            <line>Nor with sour looks afflict his gentle heart.</line>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside to SATURNINUS</stagedir>  My lord, be ruled by me,</line>
            <line>be won at last;</line>
            <line>Dissemble all your griefs and discontents:</line>
            <line>You are but newly planted in your throne;</line>
            <line>Lest, then, the people, and patricians too,</line>
            <line>Upon a just survey, take Titus' part,</line>
            <line>And so supplant you for ingratitude,</line>
            <line>Which Rome reputes to be a heinous sin,</line>
            <line>Yield at entreats; and then let me alone:</line>
            <line>I'll find a day to massacre them all</line>
            <line>And raze their faction and their family,</line>
            <line>The cruel father and his traitorous sons,</line>
            <line>To whom I sued for my dear son's life,</line>
            <line>And make them know what 'tis to let a queen</line>
            <line>Kneel in the streets and beg for grace in vain.</line>
            <stagedir>Aloud</stagedir>
            <line>Come, come, sweet emperor; come, Andronicus;</line>
            <line>Take up this good old man, and cheer the heart</line>
            <line>That dies in tempest of thy angry frown.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SATURNINUS</speaker>
            <line>Rise, Titus, rise; my empress hath prevail'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>I thank your majesty, and her, my lord:</line>
            <line>These words, these looks, infuse new life in me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TAMORA</speaker>
            <line>Titus, I am incorporate in Rome,</line>
            <line>A Roman now adopted happily,</line>
            <line>And must advise the emperor for his good.</line>
            <line>This day all quarrels die, Andronicus;</line>
            <line>And let it be mine honour, good my lord,</line>
            <line>That I have reconciled your friends and you.</line>
            <line>For you, Prince Bassianus, I have pass'd</line>
            <line>My word and promise to the emperor,</line>
            <line>That you will be more mild and tractable.</line>
            <line>And fear not lords, and you, Lavinia;</line>
            <line>By my advice, all humbled on your knees,</line>
            <line>You shall ask pardon of his majesty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIUS</speaker>
            <line>We do, and vow to heaven and to his highness,</line>
            <line>That what we did was mildly as we might,</line>
            <line>Tendering our sister's honour and our own.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>That, on mine honour, here I do protest.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SATURNINUS</speaker>
            <line>Away, and talk not; trouble us no more.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TAMORA</speaker>
            <line>Nay, nay, sweet emperor, we must all be friends:</line>
            <line>The tribune and his nephews kneel for grace;</line>
            <line>I will not be denied: sweet heart, look back.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SATURNINUS</speaker>
            <line>Marcus, for thy sake and thy brother's here,</line>
            <line>And at my lovely Tamora's entreats,</line>
            <line>I do remit these young men's heinous faults: Stand up.</line>
            <line>Lavinia, though you left me like a churl,</line>
            <line>I found a friend, and sure as death I swore</line>
            <line>I would not part a bachelor from the priest.</line>
            <line>Come, if the emperor's court can feast two brides,</line>
            <line>You are my guest, Lavinia, and your friends.</line>
            <line>This day shall be a love-day, Tamora.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>To-morrow, an it please your majesty</line>
            <line>To hunt the panther and the hart with me,</line>
            <line>With horn and hound we'll give your grace bonjour.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SATURNINUS</speaker>
            <line>Be it so, Titus, and gramercy too.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Flourish. Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>