<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net/doctypes/dita/shakespear/dtd/act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-3">
   <title>ACT III</title>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  Rome. A street.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter Judges, Senators and Tribunes, with MARTIUS
and QUINTUS, bound, passing on to the place of
execution; TITUS going before, pleading</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Hear me, grave fathers! noble tribunes, stay!</line>
            <line>For pity of mine age, whose youth was spent</line>
            <line>In dangerous wars, whilst you securely slept;</line>
            <line>For all my blood in Rome's great quarrel shed;</line>
            <line>For all the frosty nights that I have watch'd;</line>
            <line>And for these bitter tears, which now you see</line>
            <line>Filling the aged wrinkles in my cheeks;</line>
            <line>Be pitiful to my condemned sons,</line>
            <line>Whose souls are not corrupted as 'tis thought.</line>
            <line>For two and twenty sons I never wept,</line>
            <line>Because they died in honour's lofty bed.</line>
            <stagedir>Lieth down; the Judges, &amp;c., pass by him, and Exeunt</stagedir>
            <line>For these, these, tribunes, in the dust I write</line>
            <line>My heart's deep languor and my soul's sad tears:</line>
            <line>Let my tears stanch the earth's dry appetite;</line>
            <line>My sons' sweet blood will make it shame and blush.</line>
            <line>O earth, I will befriend thee more with rain,</line>
            <line>That shall distil from these two ancient urns,</line>
            <line>Than youthful April shall with all his showers:</line>
            <line>In summer's drought I'll drop upon thee still;</line>
            <line>In winter with warm tears I'll melt the snow</line>
            <line>And keep eternal spring-time on thy face,</line>
            <line>So thou refuse to drink my dear sons' blood.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter LUCIUS, with his sword drawn</stagedir>
            <line>O reverend tribunes! O gentle, aged men!</line>
            <line>Unbind my sons, reverse the doom of death;</line>
            <line>And let me say, that never wept before,</line>
            <line>My tears are now prevailing orators.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIUS</speaker>
            <line>O noble father, you lament in vain:</line>
            <line>The tribunes hear you not; no man is by;</line>
            <line>And you recount your sorrows to a stone.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Ah, Lucius, for thy brothers let me plead.</line>
            <line>Grave tribunes, once more I entreat of you,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIUS</speaker>
            <line>My gracious lord, no tribune hears you speak.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Why, tis no matter, man; if they did hear,</line>
            <line>They would not mark me, or if they did mark,</line>
            <line>They would not pity me, yet plead I must;</line>
            <line>And bootless unto them.</line>
            <line>Therefore I tell my sorrows to the stones;</line>
            <line>Who, though they cannot answer my distress,</line>
            <line>Yet in some sort they are better than the tribunes,</line>
            <line>For that they will not intercept my tale:</line>
            <line>When I do weep, they humbly at my feet</line>
            <line>Receive my tears and seem to weep with me;</line>
            <line>And, were they but attired in grave weeds,</line>
            <line>Rome could afford no tribune like to these.</line>
            <line>A stone is soft as wax,--tribunes more hard than stones;</line>
            <line>A stone is silent, and offendeth not,</line>
            <line>And tribunes with their tongues doom men to death.</line>
            <stagedir>Rises</stagedir>
            <line>But wherefore stand'st thou with thy weapon drawn?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIUS</speaker>
            <line>To rescue my two brothers from their death:</line>
            <line>For which attempt the judges have pronounced</line>
            <line>My everlasting doom of banishment.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>O happy man! they have befriended thee.</line>
            <line>Why, foolish Lucius, dost thou not perceive</line>
            <line>That Rome is but a wilderness of tigers?</line>
            <line>Tigers must prey, and Rome affords no prey</line>
            <line>But me and mine: how happy art thou, then,</line>
            <line>From these devourers to be banished!</line>
            <line>But who comes with our brother Marcus here?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter MARCUS and LAVINIA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Titus, prepare thy aged eyes to weep;</line>
            <line>Or, if not so, thy noble heart to break:</line>
            <line>I bring consuming sorrow to thine age.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Will it consume me? let me see it, then.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>This was thy daughter.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Why, Marcus, so she is.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIUS</speaker>
            <line>Ay me, this object kills me!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Faint-hearted boy, arise, and look upon her.</line>
            <line>Speak, Lavinia, what accursed hand</line>
            <line>Hath made thee handless in thy father's sight?</line>
            <line>What fool hath added water to the sea,</line>
            <line>Or brought a faggot to bright-burning Troy?</line>
            <line>My grief was at the height before thou camest,</line>
            <line>And now like Nilus, it disdaineth bounds.</line>
            <line>Give me a sword, I'll chop off my hands too;</line>
            <line>For they have fought for Rome, and all in vain;</line>
            <line>And they have nursed this woe, in feeding life;</line>
            <line>In bootless prayer have they been held up,</line>
            <line>And they have served me to effectless use:</line>
            <line>Now all the service I require of them</line>
            <line>Is that the one will help to cut the other.</line>
            <line>'Tis well, Lavinia, that thou hast no hands;</line>
            <line>For hands, to do Rome service, are but vain.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIUS</speaker>
            <line>Speak, gentle sister, who hath martyr'd thee?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>O, that delightful engine of her thoughts</line>
            <line>That blabb'd them with such pleasing eloquence,</line>
            <line>Is torn from forth that pretty hollow cage,</line>
            <line>Where, like a sweet melodious bird, it sung</line>
            <line>Sweet varied notes, enchanting every ear!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIUS</speaker>
            <line>O, say thou for her, who hath done this deed?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>O, thus I found her, straying in the park,</line>
            <line>Seeking to hide herself, as doth the deer</line>
            <line>That hath received some unrecuring wound.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>It was my deer; and he that wounded her</line>
            <line>Hath hurt me more than had he killed me dead:</line>
            <line>For now I stand as one upon a rock</line>
            <line>Environed with a wilderness of sea,</line>
            <line>Who marks the waxing tide grow wave by wave,</line>
            <line>Expecting ever when some envious surge</line>
            <line>Will in his brinish bowels swallow him.</line>
            <line>This way to death my wretched sons are gone;</line>
            <line>Here stands my other son, a banished man,</line>
            <line>And here my brother, weeping at my woes.</line>
            <line>But that which gives my soul the greatest spurn,</line>
            <line>Is dear Lavinia, dearer than my soul.</line>
            <line>Had I but seen thy picture in this plight,</line>
            <line>It would have madded me: what shall I do</line>
            <line>Now I behold thy lively body so?</line>
            <line>Thou hast no hands, to wipe away thy tears:</line>
            <line>Nor tongue, to tell me who hath martyr'd thee:</line>
            <line>Thy husband he is dead: and for his death</line>
            <line>Thy brothers are condemn'd, and dead by this.</line>
            <line>Look, Marcus! ah, son Lucius, look on her!</line>
            <line>When I did name her brothers, then fresh tears</line>
            <line>Stood on her cheeks, as doth the honey-dew</line>
            <line>Upon a gather'd lily almost wither'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Perchance she weeps because they kill'd her husband;</line>
            <line>Perchance because she knows them innocent.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>If they did kill thy husband, then be joyful</line>
            <line>Because the law hath ta'en revenge on them.</line>
            <line>No, no, they would not do so foul a deed;</line>
            <line>Witness the sorrow that their sister makes.</line>
            <line>Gentle Lavinia, let me kiss thy lips.</line>
            <line>Or make some sign how I may do thee ease:</line>
            <line>Shall thy good uncle, and thy brother Lucius,</line>
            <line>And thou, and I, sit round about some fountain,</line>
            <line>Looking all downwards to behold our cheeks</line>
            <line>How they are stain'd, as meadows, yet not dry,</line>
            <line>With miry slime left on them by a flood?</line>
            <line>And in the fountain shall we gaze so long</line>
            <line>Till the fresh taste be taken from that clearness,</line>
            <line>And made a brine-pit with our bitter tears?</line>
            <line>Or shall we cut away our hands, like thine?</line>
            <line>Or shall we bite our tongues, and in dumb shows</line>
            <line>Pass the remainder of our hateful days?</line>
            <line>What shall we do? let us, that have our tongues,</line>
            <line>Plot some deuce of further misery,</line>
            <line>To make us wonder'd at in time to come.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIUS</speaker>
            <line>Sweet father, cease your tears; for, at your grief,</line>
            <line>See how my wretched sister sobs and weeps.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Patience, dear niece. Good Titus, dry thine eyes.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Ah, Marcus, Marcus! brother, well I wot</line>
            <line>Thy napkin cannot drink a tear of mine,</line>
            <line>For thou, poor man, hast drown'd it with thine own.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIUS</speaker>
            <line>Ah, my Lavinia, I will wipe thy cheeks.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Mark, Marcus, mark! I understand her signs:</line>
            <line>Had she a tongue to speak, now would she say</line>
            <line>That to her brother which I said to thee:</line>
            <line>His napkin, with his true tears all bewet,</line>
            <line>Can do no service on her sorrowful cheeks.</line>
            <line>O, what a sympathy of woe is this,</line>
            <line>As far from help as Limbo is from bliss!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter AARON</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AARON</speaker>
            <line>Titus Andronicus, my lord the emperor</line>
            <line>Sends thee this word,--that, if thou love thy sons,</line>
            <line>Let Marcus, Lucius, or thyself, old Titus,</line>
            <line>Or any one of you, chop off your hand,</line>
            <line>And send it to the king: he for the same</line>
            <line>Will send thee hither both thy sons alive;</line>
            <line>And that shall be the ransom for their fault.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>O gracious emperor! O gentle Aaron!</line>
            <line>Did ever raven sing so like a lark,</line>
            <line>That gives sweet tidings of the sun's uprise?</line>
            <line>With all my heart, I'll send the emperor My hand:</line>
            <line>Good Aaron, wilt thou help to chop it off?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIUS</speaker>
            <line>Stay, father! for that noble hand of thine,</line>
            <line>That hath thrown down so many enemies,</line>
            <line>Shall not be sent: my hand will serve the turn:</line>
            <line>My youth can better spare my blood than you;</line>
            <line>And therefore mine shall save my brothers' lives.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Which of your hands hath not defended Rome,</line>
            <line>And rear'd aloft the bloody battle-axe,</line>
            <line>Writing destruction on the enemy's castle?</line>
            <line>O, none of both but are of high desert:</line>
            <line>My hand hath been but idle; let it serve</line>
            <line>To ransom my two nephews from their death;</line>
            <line>Then have I kept it to a worthy end.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AARON</speaker>
            <line>Nay, come, agree whose hand shall go along,</line>
            <line>For fear they die before their pardon come.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>My hand shall go.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIUS</speaker>
            <line>By heaven, it shall not go!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Sirs, strive no more: such wither'd herbs as these</line>
            <line>Are meet for plucking up, and therefore mine.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIUS</speaker>
            <line>Sweet father, if I shall be thought thy son,</line>
            <line>Let me redeem my brothers both from death.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>And, for our father's sake and mother's care,</line>
            <line>Now let me show a brother's love to thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Agree between you; I will spare my hand.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIUS</speaker>
            <line>Then I'll go fetch an axe.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>But I will use the axe.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt LUCIUS and MARCUS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Come hither, Aaron; I'll deceive them both:</line>
            <line>Lend me thy hand, and I will give thee mine.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AARON</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  If that be call'd deceit, I will be honest,</line>
            <line>And never, whilst I live, deceive men so:</line>
            <line>But I'll deceive you in another sort,</line>
            <line>And that you'll say, ere half an hour pass.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Cuts off TITUS's hand</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Re-enter LUCIUS and MARCUS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Now stay your strife: what shall be is dispatch'd.</line>
            <line>Good Aaron, give his majesty my hand:</line>
            <line>Tell him it was a hand that warded him</line>
            <line>From thousand dangers; bid him bury it</line>
            <line>More hath it merited; that let it have.</line>
            <line>As for my sons, say I account of them</line>
            <line>As jewels purchased at an easy price;</line>
            <line>And yet dear too, because I bought mine own.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AARON</speaker>
            <line>I go, Andronicus: and for thy hand</line>
            <line>Look by and by to have thy sons with thee.</line>
            <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>
            <line>Their heads, I mean. O, how this villany</line>
            <line>Doth fat me with the very thoughts of it!</line>
            <line>Let fools do good, and fair men call for grace.</line>
            <line>Aaron will have his soul black like his face.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>O, here I lift this one hand up to heaven,</line>
            <line>And bow this feeble ruin to the earth:</line>
            <line>If any power pities wretched tears,</line>
            <line>To that I call!</line>
            <stagedir>To LAVINIA</stagedir>
            <line>What, wilt thou kneel with me?</line>
            <line>Do, then, dear heart; for heaven shall hear our prayers;</line>
            <line>Or with our sighs we'll breathe the welkin dim,</line>
            <line>And stain the sun with fog, as sometime clouds</line>
            <line>When they do hug him in their melting bosoms.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>O brother, speak with possibilities,</line>
            <line>And do not break into these deep extremes.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Is not my sorrow deep, having no bottom?</line>
            <line>Then be my passions bottomless with them.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>But yet let reason govern thy lament.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>If there were reason for these miseries,</line>
            <line>Then into limits could I bind my woes:</line>
            <line>When heaven doth weep, doth not the earth o'erflow?</line>
            <line>If the winds rage, doth not the sea wax mad,</line>
            <line>Threatening the welkin with his big-swoln face?</line>
            <line>And wilt thou have a reason for this coil?</line>
            <line>I am the sea; hark, how her sighs do blow!</line>
            <line>She is the weeping welkin, I the earth:</line>
            <line>Then must my sea be moved with her sighs;</line>
            <line>Then must my earth with her continual tears</line>
            <line>Become a deluge, overflow'd and drown'd;</line>
            <line>For why my bowels cannot hide her woes,</line>
            <line>But like a drunkard must I vomit them.</line>
            <line>Then give me leave, for losers will have leave</line>
            <line>To ease their stomachs with their bitter tongues.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter a Messenger, with two heads and a hand</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>Worthy Andronicus, ill art thou repaid</line>
            <line>For that good hand thou sent'st the emperor.</line>
            <line>Here are the heads of thy two noble sons;</line>
            <line>And here's thy hand, in scorn to thee sent back;</line>
            <line>Thy griefs their sports, thy resolution mock'd;</line>
            <line>That woe is me to think upon thy woes</line>
            <line>More than remembrance of my father's death.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Now let hot AEtna cool in Sicily,</line>
            <line>And be my heart an ever-burning hell!</line>
            <line>These miseries are more than may be borne.</line>
            <line>To weep with them that weep doth ease some deal;</line>
            <line>But sorrow flouted at is double death.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIUS</speaker>
            <line>Ah, that this sight should make so deep a wound,</line>
            <line>And yet detested life not shrink thereat!</line>
            <line>That ever death should let life bear his name,</line>
            <line>Where life hath no more interest but to breathe!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>LAVINIA kisses TITUS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Alas, poor heart, that kiss is comfortless</line>
            <line>As frozen water to a starved snake.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>When will this fearful slumber have an end?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Now, farewell, flattery: die, Andronicus;</line>
            <line>Thou dost not slumber: see, thy two sons' heads,</line>
            <line>Thy warlike hand, thy mangled daughter here:</line>
            <line>Thy other banish'd son, with this dear sight</line>
            <line>Struck pale and bloodless; and thy brother, I,</line>
            <line>Even like a stony image, cold and numb.</line>
            <line>Ah, now no more will I control thy griefs:</line>
            <line>Rend off thy silver hair, thy other hand</line>
            <line>Gnawing with thy teeth; and be this dismal sight</line>
            <line>The closing up of our most wretched eyes;</line>
            <line>Now is a time to storm; why art thou still?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Ha, ha, ha!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Why dost thou laugh? it fits not with this hour.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Why, I have not another tear to shed:</line>
            <line>Besides, this sorrow is an enemy,</line>
            <line>And would usurp upon my watery eyes</line>
            <line>And make them blind with tributary tears:</line>
            <line>Then which way shall I find Revenge's cave?</line>
            <line>For these two heads do seem to speak to me,</line>
            <line>And threat me I shall never come to bliss</line>
            <line>Till all these mischiefs be return'd again</line>
            <line>Even in their throats that have committed them.</line>
            <line>Come, let me see what task I have to do.</line>
            <line>You heavy people, circle me about,</line>
            <line>That I may turn me to each one of you,</line>
            <line>And swear unto my soul to right your wrongs.</line>
            <line>The vow is made. Come, brother, take a head;</line>
            <line>And in this hand the other I will bear.</line>
            <line>Lavinia, thou shalt be employ'd: these arms!</line>
            <line>Bear thou my hand, sweet wench, between thy teeth.</line>
            <line>As for thee, boy, go get thee from my sight;</line>
            <line>Thou art an exile, and thou must not stay:</line>
            <line>Hie to the Goths, and raise an army there:</line>
            <line>And, if you love me, as I think you do,</line>
            <line>Let's kiss and part, for we have much to do.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt TITUS, MARCUS, and LAVINIA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIUS</speaker>
            <line>Farewell Andronicus, my noble father,</line>
            <line>The wofull'st man that ever lived in Rome:</line>
            <line>Farewell, proud Rome; till Lucius come again,</line>
            <line>He leaves his pledges dearer than his life:</line>
            <line>Farewell, Lavinia, my noble sister;</line>
            <line>O, would thou wert as thou tofore hast been!</line>
            <line>But now nor Lucius nor Lavinia lives</line>
            <line>But in oblivion and hateful griefs.</line>
            <line>If Lucius live, he will requite your wrongs;</line>
            <line>And make proud Saturnine and his empress</line>
            <line>Beg at the gates, like Tarquin and his queen.</line>
            <line>Now will I to the Goths, and raise a power,</line>
            <line>To be revenged on Rome and Saturnine.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  A room in Titus's house. A banquet set out.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter TITUS, MARCUS, LAVINIA and Young LUCIUS, a boy</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>So, so; now sit: and look you eat no more</line>
            <line>Than will preserve just so much strength in us</line>
            <line>As will revenge these bitter woes of ours.</line>
            <line>Marcus, unknit that sorrow-wreathen knot:</line>
            <line>Thy niece and I, poor creatures, want our hands,</line>
            <line>And cannot passionate our tenfold grief</line>
            <line>With folded arms. This poor right hand of mine</line>
            <line>Is left to tyrannize upon my breast;</line>
            <line>Who, when my heart, all mad with misery,</line>
            <line>Beats in this hollow prison of my flesh,</line>
            <line>Then thus I thump it down.</line>
            <stagedir>To LAVINIA</stagedir>
            <line>Thou map of woe, that thus dost talk in signs!</line>
            <line>When thy poor heart beats with outrageous beating,</line>
            <line>Thou canst not strike it thus to make it still.</line>
            <line>Wound it with sighing, girl, kill it with groans;</line>
            <line>Or get some little knife between thy teeth,</line>
            <line>And just against thy heart make thou a hole;</line>
            <line>That all the tears that thy poor eyes let fall</line>
            <line>May run into that sink, and soaking in</line>
            <line>Drown the lamenting fool in sea-salt tears.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Fie, brother, fie! teach her not thus to lay</line>
            <line>Such violent hands upon her tender life.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>How now! has sorrow made thee dote already?</line>
            <line>Why, Marcus, no man should be mad but I.</line>
            <line>What violent hands can she lay on her life?</line>
            <line>Ah, wherefore dost thou urge the name of hands;</line>
            <line>To bid AEneas tell the tale twice o'er,</line>
            <line>How Troy was burnt and he made miserable?</line>
            <line>O, handle not the theme, to talk of hands,</line>
            <line>Lest we remember still that we have none.</line>
            <line>Fie, fie, how franticly I square my talk,</line>
            <line>As if we should forget we had no hands,</line>
            <line>If Marcus did not name the word of hands!</line>
            <line>Come, let's fall to; and, gentle girl, eat this:</line>
            <line>Here is no drink! Hark, Marcus, what she says;</line>
            <line>I can interpret all her martyr'd signs;</line>
            <line>She says she drinks no other drink but tears,</line>
            <line>Brew'd with her sorrow, mesh'd upon her cheeks:</line>
            <line>Speechless complainer, I will learn thy thought;</line>
            <line>In thy dumb action will I be as perfect</line>
            <line>As begging hermits in their holy prayers:</line>
            <line>Thou shalt not sigh, nor hold thy stumps to heaven,</line>
            <line>Nor wink, nor nod, nor kneel, nor make a sign,</line>
            <line>But I of these will wrest an alphabet</line>
            <line>And by still practise learn to know thy meaning.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Young LUCIUS</speaker>
            <line>Good grandsire, leave these bitter deep laments:</line>
            <line>Make my aunt merry with some pleasing tale.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Alas, the tender boy, in passion moved,</line>
            <line>Doth weep to see his grandsire's heaviness.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Peace, tender sapling; thou art made of tears,</line>
            <line>And tears will quickly melt thy life away.</line>
            <stagedir>MARCUS strikes the dish with a knife</stagedir>
            <line>What dost thou strike at, Marcus, with thy knife?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>At that that I have kill'd, my lord; a fly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Out on thee, murderer! thou kill'st my heart;</line>
            <line>Mine eyes are cloy'd with view of tyranny:</line>
            <line>A deed of death done on the innocent</line>
            <line>Becomes not Titus' brother: get thee gone:</line>
            <line>I see thou art not for my company.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Alas, my lord, I have but kill'd a fly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>But how, if that fly had a father and mother?</line>
            <line>How would he hang his slender gilded wings,</line>
            <line>And buzz lamenting doings in the air!</line>
            <line>Poor harmless fly,</line>
            <line>That, with his pretty buzzing melody,</line>
            <line>Came here to make us merry! and thou hast</line>
            <line>kill'd him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Pardon me, sir; it was a black ill-favor'd fly,</line>
            <line>Like to the empress' Moor; therefore I kill'd him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>O, O, O,</line>
            <line>Then pardon me for reprehending thee,</line>
            <line>For thou hast done a charitable deed.</line>
            <line>Give me thy knife, I will insult on him;</line>
            <line>Flattering myself, as if it were the Moor</line>
            <line>Come hither purposely to poison me.--</line>
            <line>There's for thyself, and that's for Tamora.</line>
            <line>Ah, sirrah!</line>
            <line>Yet, I think, we are not brought so low,</line>
            <line>But that between us we can kill a fly</line>
            <line>That comes in likeness of a coal-black Moor.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Alas, poor man! grief has so wrought on him,</line>
            <line>He takes false shadows for true substances.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Come, take away. Lavinia, go with me:</line>
            <line>I'll to thy closet; and go read with thee</line>
            <line>Sad stories chanced in the times of old.</line>
            <line>Come, boy, and go with me: thy sight is young,</line>
            <line>And thou shalt read when mine begin to dazzle.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>