<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net/doctypes/dita/shakespear/dtd/act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-2">
   <title>ACT II</title>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  Rome. Before the Palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter AARON</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AARON</speaker>
            <line>Now climbeth Tamora Olympus' top,</line>
            <line>Safe out of fortune's shot; and sits aloft,</line>
            <line>Secure of thunder's crack or lightning flash;</line>
            <line>Advanced above pale envy's threatening reach.</line>
            <line>As when the golden sun salutes the morn,</line>
            <line>And, having gilt the ocean with his beams,</line>
            <line>Gallops the zodiac in his glistering coach,</line>
            <line>And overlooks the highest-peering hills;</line>
            <line>So Tamora:</line>
            <line>Upon her wit doth earthly honour wait,</line>
            <line>And virtue stoops and trembles at her frown.</line>
            <line>Then, Aaron, arm thy heart, and fit thy thoughts,</line>
            <line>To mount aloft with thy imperial mistress,</line>
            <line>And mount her pitch, whom thou in triumph long</line>
            <line>Hast prisoner held, fetter'd in amorous chains</line>
            <line>And faster bound to Aaron's charming eyes</line>
            <line>Than is Prometheus tied to Caucasus.</line>
            <line>Away with slavish weeds and servile thoughts!</line>
            <line>I will be bright, and shine in pearl and gold,</line>
            <line>To wait upon this new-made empress.</line>
            <line>To wait, said I? to wanton with this queen,</line>
            <line>This goddess, this Semiramis, this nymph,</line>
            <line>This siren, that will charm Rome's Saturnine,</line>
            <line>And see his shipwreck and his commonweal's.</line>
            <line>Holloa! what storm is this?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter DEMETRIUS and CHIRON, braving</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>Chiron, thy years want wit, thy wit wants edge,</line>
            <line>And manners, to intrude where I am graced;</line>
            <line>And may, for aught thou know'st, affected be.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHIRON</speaker>
            <line>Demetrius, thou dost over-ween in all;</line>
            <line>And so in this, to bear me down with braves.</line>
            <line>'Tis not the difference of a year or two</line>
            <line>Makes me less gracious or thee more fortunate:</line>
            <line>I am as able and as fit as thou</line>
            <line>To serve, and to deserve my mistress' grace;</line>
            <line>And that my sword upon thee shall approve,</line>
            <line>And plead my passions for Lavinia's love.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AARON</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  Clubs, clubs! these lovers will not keep</line>
            <line>the peace.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>Why, boy, although our mother, unadvised,</line>
            <line>Gave you a dancing-rapier by your side,</line>
            <line>Are you so desperate grown, to threat your friends?</line>
            <line>Go to; have your lath glued within your sheath</line>
            <line>Till you know better how to handle it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHIRON</speaker>
            <line>Meanwhile, sir, with the little skill I have,</line>
            <line>Full well shalt thou perceive how much I dare.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>Ay, boy, grow ye so brave?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>They draw</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AARON</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Coming forward</stagedir>  Why, how now, lords!</line>
            <line>So near the emperor's palace dare you draw,</line>
            <line>And maintain such a quarrel openly?</line>
            <line>Full well I wot the ground of all this grudge:</line>
            <line>I would not for a million of gold</line>
            <line>The cause were known to them it most concerns;</line>
            <line>Nor would your noble mother for much more</line>
            <line>Be so dishonour'd in the court of Rome.</line>
            <line>For shame, put up.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>Not I, till I have sheathed</line>
            <line>My rapier in his bosom and withal</line>
            <line>Thrust these reproachful speeches down his throat</line>
            <line>That he hath breathed in my dishonour here.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHIRON</speaker>
            <line>For that I am prepared and full resolved.</line>
            <line>Foul-spoken coward, that thunder'st with thy tongue,</line>
            <line>And with thy weapon nothing darest perform!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AARON</speaker>
            <line>Away, I say!</line>
            <line>Now, by the gods that warlike Goths adore,</line>
            <line>This petty brabble will undo us all.</line>
            <line>Why, lords, and think you not how dangerous</line>
            <line>It is to jet upon a prince's right?</line>
            <line>What, is Lavinia then become so loose,</line>
            <line>Or Bassianus so degenerate,</line>
            <line>That for her love such quarrels may be broach'd</line>
            <line>Without controlment, justice, or revenge?</line>
            <line>Young lords, beware! and should the empress know</line>
            <line>This discord's ground, the music would not please.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHIRON</speaker>
            <line>I care not, I, knew she and all the world:</line>
            <line>I love Lavinia more than all the world.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>Youngling, learn thou to make some meaner choice:</line>
            <line>Lavinia is thine elder brother's hope.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AARON</speaker>
            <line>Why, are ye mad? or know ye not, in Rome</line>
            <line>How furious and impatient they be,</line>
            <line>And cannot brook competitors in love?</line>
            <line>I tell you, lords, you do but plot your deaths</line>
            <line>By this device.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHIRON</speaker>
            <line>Aaron, a thousand deaths</line>
            <line>Would I propose to achieve her whom I love.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AARON</speaker>
            <line>To achieve her! how?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>Why makest thou it so strange?</line>
            <line>She is a woman, therefore may be woo'd;</line>
            <line>She is a woman, therefore may be won;</line>
            <line>She is Lavinia, therefore must be loved.</line>
            <line>What, man! more water glideth by the mill</line>
            <line>Than wots the miller of; and easy it is</line>
            <line>Of a cut loaf to steal a shive, we know:</line>
            <line>Though Bassianus be the emperor's brother.</line>
            <line>Better than he have worn Vulcan's badge.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AARON</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  Ay, and as good as Saturninus may.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>Then why should he despair that knows to court it</line>
            <line>With words, fair looks and liberality?</line>
            <line>What, hast not thou full often struck a doe,</line>
            <line>And borne her cleanly by the keeper's nose?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AARON</speaker>
            <line>Why, then, it seems, some certain snatch or so</line>
            <line>Would serve your turns.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHIRON</speaker>
            <line>Ay, so the turn were served.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>Aaron, thou hast hit it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AARON</speaker>
            <line>Would you had hit it too!</line>
            <line>Then should not we be tired with this ado.</line>
            <line>Why, hark ye, hark ye! and are you such fools</line>
            <line>To square for this? would it offend you, then</line>
            <line>That both should speed?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHIRON</speaker>
            <line>Faith, not me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>Nor me, so I were one.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AARON</speaker>
            <line>For shame, be friends, and join for that you jar:</line>
            <line>'Tis policy and stratagem must do</line>
            <line>That you affect; and so must you resolve,</line>
            <line>That what you cannot as you would achieve,</line>
            <line>You must perforce accomplish as you may.</line>
            <line>Take this of me: Lucrece was not more chaste</line>
            <line>Than this Lavinia, Bassianus' love.</line>
            <line>A speedier course than lingering languishment</line>
            <line>Must we pursue, and I have found the path.</line>
            <line>My lords, a solemn hunting is in hand;</line>
            <line>There will the lovely Roman ladies troop:</line>
            <line>The forest walks are wide and spacious;</line>
            <line>And many unfrequented plots there are</line>
            <line>Fitted by kind for rape and villany:</line>
            <line>Single you thither then this dainty doe,</line>
            <line>And strike her home by force, if not by words:</line>
            <line>This way, or not at all, stand you in hope.</line>
            <line>Come, come, our empress, with her sacred wit</line>
            <line>To villany and vengeance consecrate,</line>
            <line>Will we acquaint with all that we intend;</line>
            <line>And she shall file our engines with advice,</line>
            <line>That will not suffer you to square yourselves,</line>
            <line>But to your wishes' height advance you both.</line>
            <line>The emperor's court is like the house of Fame,</line>
            <line>The palace full of tongues, of eyes, and ears:</line>
            <line>The woods are ruthless, dreadful, deaf, and dull;</line>
            <line>There speak, and strike, brave boys, and take</line>
            <line>your turns;</line>
            <line>There serve your lusts, shadow'd from heaven's eye,</line>
            <line>And revel in Lavinia's treasury.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHIRON</speaker>
            <line>Thy counsel, lad, smells of no cowardice,</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>Sit fas aut nefas, till I find the stream</line>
            <line>To cool this heat, a charm to calm these fits.</line>
            <line>Per Styga, per manes vehor.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  A forest near Rome. Horns and cry of hounds heard.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter TITUS ANDRONICUS, with Hunters, &amp;c., MARCUS,
LUCIUS, QUINTUS, and MARTIUS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>The hunt is up, the morn is bright and grey,</line>
            <line>The fields are fragrant and the woods are green:</line>
            <line>Uncouple here and let us make a bay</line>
            <line>And wake the emperor and his lovely bride</line>
            <line>And rouse the prince and ring a hunter's peal,</line>
            <line>That all the court may echo with the noise.</line>
            <line>Sons, let it be your charge, as it is ours,</line>
            <line>To attend the emperor's person carefully:</line>
            <line>I have been troubled in my sleep this night,</line>
            <line>But dawning day new comfort hath inspired.</line>
            <stagedir>A cry of hounds and horns, winded in a peal. Enter
SATURNINUS, TAMORA, BASSIANUS, LAVINIA, DEMETRIUS,
CHIRON, and Attendants</stagedir>
            <line>Many good morrows to your majesty;</line>
            <line>Madam, to you as many and as good:</line>
            <line>I promised your grace a hunter's peal.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SATURNINUS</speaker>
            <line>And you have rung it lustily, my lord;</line>
            <line>Somewhat too early for new-married ladies.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSIANUS</speaker>
            <line>Lavinia, how say you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAVINIA</speaker>
            <line>I say, no;</line>
            <line>I have been broad awake two hours and more.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SATURNINUS</speaker>
            <line>Come on, then; horse and chariots let us have,</line>
            <line>And to our sport.</line>
            <stagedir>To TAMORA</stagedir>
            <line>Madam, now shall ye see</line>
            <line>Our Roman hunting.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>I have dogs, my lord,</line>
            <line>Will rouse the proudest panther in the chase,</line>
            <line>And climb the highest promontory top.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>And I have horse will follow where the game</line>
            <line>Makes way, and run like swallows o'er the plain.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>Chiron, we hunt not, we, with horse nor hound,</line>
            <line>But hope to pluck a dainty doe to ground.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  A lonely part of the forest.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter AARON, with a bag of gold</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AARON</speaker>
            <line>He that had wit would think that I had none,</line>
            <line>To bury so much gold under a tree,</line>
            <line>And never after to inherit it.</line>
            <line>Let him that thinks of me so abjectly</line>
            <line>Know that this gold must coin a stratagem,</line>
            <line>Which, cunningly effected, will beget</line>
            <line>A very excellent piece of villany:</line>
            <line>And so repose, sweet gold, for their unrest</line>
            <stagedir>Hides the gold</stagedir>
            <line>That have their alms out of the empress' chest.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter TAMORA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TAMORA</speaker>
            <line>My lovely Aaron, wherefore look'st thou sad,</line>
            <line>When every thing doth make a gleeful boast?</line>
            <line>The birds chant melody on every bush,</line>
            <line>The snake lies rolled in the cheerful sun,</line>
            <line>The green leaves quiver with the cooling wind</line>
            <line>And make a chequer'd shadow on the ground:</line>
            <line>Under their sweet shade, Aaron, let us sit,</line>
            <line>And, whilst the babbling echo mocks the hounds,</line>
            <line>Replying shrilly to the well-tuned horns,</line>
            <line>As if a double hunt were heard at once,</line>
            <line>Let us sit down and mark their yelping noise;</line>
            <line>And, after conflict such as was supposed</line>
            <line>The wandering prince and Dido once enjoy'd,</line>
            <line>When with a happy storm they were surprised</line>
            <line>And curtain'd with a counsel-keeping cave,</line>
            <line>We may, each wreathed in the other's arms,</line>
            <line>Our pastimes done, possess a golden slumber;</line>
            <line>Whiles hounds and horns and sweet melodious birds</line>
            <line>Be unto us as is a nurse's song</line>
            <line>Of lullaby to bring her babe asleep.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AARON</speaker>
            <line>Madam, though Venus govern your desires,</line>
            <line>Saturn is dominator over mine:</line>
            <line>What signifies my deadly-standing eye,</line>
            <line>My silence and my cloudy melancholy,</line>
            <line>My fleece of woolly hair that now uncurls</line>
            <line>Even as an adder when she doth unroll</line>
            <line>To do some fatal execution?</line>
            <line>No, madam, these are no venereal signs:</line>
            <line>Vengeance is in my heart, death in my hand,</line>
            <line>Blood and revenge are hammering in my head.</line>
            <line>Hark Tamora, the empress of my soul,</line>
            <line>Which never hopes more heaven than rests in thee,</line>
            <line>This is the day of doom for Bassianus:</line>
            <line>His Philomel must lose her tongue to-day,</line>
            <line>Thy sons make pillage of her chastity</line>
            <line>And wash their hands in Bassianus' blood.</line>
            <line>Seest thou this letter? take it up, I pray thee,</line>
            <line>And give the king this fatal plotted scroll.</line>
            <line>Now question me no more; we are espied;</line>
            <line>Here comes a parcel of our hopeful booty,</line>
            <line>Which dreads not yet their lives' destruction.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TAMORA</speaker>
            <line>Ah, my sweet Moor, sweeter to me than life!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AARON</speaker>
            <line>No more, great empress; Bassianus comes:</line>
            <line>Be cross with him; and I'll go fetch thy sons</line>
            <line>To back thy quarrels, whatsoe'er they be.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Enter BASSIANUS and LAVINIA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSIANUS</speaker>
            <line>Who have we here? Rome's royal empress,</line>
            <line>Unfurnish'd of her well-beseeming troop?</line>
            <line>Or is it Dian, habited like her,</line>
            <line>Who hath abandoned her holy groves</line>
            <line>To see the general hunting in this forest?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TAMORA</speaker>
            <line>Saucy controller of our private steps!</line>
            <line>Had I the power that some say Dian had,</line>
            <line>Thy temples should be planted presently</line>
            <line>With horns, as was Actaeon's; and the hounds</line>
            <line>Should drive upon thy new-transformed limbs,</line>
            <line>Unmannerly intruder as thou art!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAVINIA</speaker>
            <line>Under your patience, gentle empress,</line>
            <line>'Tis thought you have a goodly gift in horning;</line>
            <line>And to be doubted that your Moor and you</line>
            <line>Are singled forth to try experiments:</line>
            <line>Jove shield your husband from his hounds to-day!</line>
            <line>'Tis pity they should take him for a stag.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSIANUS</speaker>
            <line>Believe me, queen, your swarth Cimmerian</line>
            <line>Doth make your honour of his body's hue,</line>
            <line>Spotted, detested, and abominable.</line>
            <line>Why are you sequester'd from all your train,</line>
            <line>Dismounted from your snow-white goodly steed.</line>
            <line>And wander'd hither to an obscure plot,</line>
            <line>Accompanied but with a barbarous Moor,</line>
            <line>If foul desire had not conducted you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAVINIA</speaker>
            <line>And, being intercepted in your sport,</line>
            <line>Great reason that my noble lord be rated</line>
            <line>For sauciness. I pray you, let us hence,</line>
            <line>And let her joy her raven-colour'd love;</line>
            <line>This valley fits the purpose passing well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSIANUS</speaker>
            <line>The king my brother shall have note of this.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAVINIA</speaker>
            <line>Ay, for these slips have made him noted long:</line>
            <line>Good king, to be so mightily abused!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TAMORA</speaker>
            <line>Why have I patience to endure all this?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter DEMETRIUS and CHIRON</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>How now, dear sovereign, and our gracious mother!</line>
            <line>Why doth your highness look so pale and wan?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TAMORA</speaker>
            <line>Have I not reason, think you, to look pale?</line>
            <line>These two have 'ticed me hither to this place:</line>
            <line>A barren detested vale, you see it is;</line>
            <line>The trees, though summer, yet forlorn and lean,</line>
            <line>O'ercome with moss and baleful mistletoe:</line>
            <line>Here never shines the sun; here nothing breeds,</line>
            <line>Unless the nightly owl or fatal raven:</line>
            <line>And when they show'd me this abhorred pit,</line>
            <line>They told me, here, at dead time of the night,</line>
            <line>A thousand fiends, a thousand hissing snakes,</line>
            <line>Ten thousand swelling toads, as many urchins,</line>
            <line>Would make such fearful and confused cries</line>
            <line>As any mortal body hearing it</line>
            <line>Should straight fall mad, or else die suddenly.</line>
            <line>No sooner had they told this hellish tale,</line>
            <line>But straight they told me they would bind me here</line>
            <line>Unto the body of a dismal yew,</line>
            <line>And leave me to this miserable death:</line>
            <line>And then they call'd me foul adulteress,</line>
            <line>Lascivious Goth, and all the bitterest terms</line>
            <line>That ever ear did hear to such effect:</line>
            <line>And, had you not by wondrous fortune come,</line>
            <line>This vengeance on me had they executed.</line>
            <line>Revenge it, as you love your mother's life,</line>
            <line>Or be ye not henceforth call'd my children.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>This is a witness that I am thy son.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Stabs BASSIANUS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHIRON</speaker>
            <line>And this for me, struck home to show my strength.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Also stabs BASSIANUS, who dies</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAVINIA</speaker>
            <line>Ay, come, Semiramis, nay, barbarous Tamora,</line>
            <line>For no name fits thy nature but thy own!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TAMORA</speaker>
            <line>Give me thy poniard; you shall know, my boys</line>
            <line>Your mother's hand shall right your mother's wrong.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>Stay, madam; here is more belongs to her;</line>
            <line>First thrash the corn, then after burn the straw:</line>
            <line>This minion stood upon her chastity,</line>
            <line>Upon her nuptial vow, her loyalty,</line>
            <line>And with that painted hope braves your mightiness:</line>
            <line>And shall she carry this unto her grave?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHIRON</speaker>
            <line>An if she do, I would I were an eunuch.</line>
            <line>Drag hence her husband to some secret hole,</line>
            <line>And make his dead trunk pillow to our lust.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TAMORA</speaker>
            <line>But when ye have the honey ye desire,</line>
            <line>Let not this wasp outlive, us both to sting.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHIRON</speaker>
            <line>I warrant you, madam, we will make that sure.</line>
            <line>Come, mistress, now perforce we will enjoy</line>
            <line>That nice-preserved honesty of yours.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAVINIA</speaker>
            <line>O Tamora! thou bear'st a woman's face,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TAMORA</speaker>
            <line>I will not hear her speak; away with her!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAVINIA</speaker>
            <line>Sweet lords, entreat her hear me but a word.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>Listen, fair madam: let it be your glory</line>
            <line>To see her tears; but be your heart to them</line>
            <line>As unrelenting flint to drops of rain.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAVINIA</speaker>
            <line>When did the tiger's young ones teach the dam?</line>
            <line>O, do not learn her wrath; she taught it thee;</line>
            <line>The milk thou suck'dst from her did turn to marble;</line>
            <line>Even at thy teat thou hadst thy tyranny.</line>
            <line>Yet every mother breeds not sons alike:</line>
            <stagedir>To CHIRON</stagedir>
            <line>Do thou entreat her show a woman pity.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHIRON</speaker>
            <line>What, wouldst thou have me prove myself a bastard?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAVINIA</speaker>
            <line>'Tis true; the raven doth not hatch a lark:</line>
            <line>Yet have I heard,--O, could I find it now!--</line>
            <line>The lion moved with pity did endure</line>
            <line>To have his princely paws pared all away:</line>
            <line>Some say that ravens foster forlorn children,</line>
            <line>The whilst their own birds famish in their nests:</line>
            <line>O, be to me, though thy hard heart say no,</line>
            <line>Nothing so kind, but something pitiful!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TAMORA</speaker>
            <line>I know not what it means; away with her!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAVINIA</speaker>
            <line>O, let me teach thee! for my father's sake,</line>
            <line>That gave thee life, when well he might have</line>
            <line>slain thee,</line>
            <line>Be not obdurate, open thy deaf ears.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TAMORA</speaker>
            <line>Hadst thou in person ne'er offended me,</line>
            <line>Even for his sake am I pitiless.</line>
            <line>Remember, boys, I pour'd forth tears in vain,</line>
            <line>To save your brother from the sacrifice;</line>
            <line>But fierce Andronicus would not relent;</line>
            <line>Therefore, away with her, and use her as you will,</line>
            <line>The worse to her, the better loved of me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAVINIA</speaker>
            <line>O Tamora, be call'd a gentle queen,</line>
            <line>And with thine own hands kill me in this place!</line>
            <line>For 'tis not life that I have begg'd so long;</line>
            <line>Poor I was slain when Bassianus died.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TAMORA</speaker>
            <line>What begg'st thou, then? fond woman, let me go.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAVINIA</speaker>
            <line>'Tis present death I beg; and one thing more</line>
            <line>That womanhood denies my tongue to tell:</line>
            <line>O, keep me from their worse than killing lust,</line>
            <line>And tumble me into some loathsome pit,</line>
            <line>Where never man's eye may behold my body:</line>
            <line>Do this, and be a charitable murderer.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TAMORA</speaker>
            <line>So should I rob my sweet sons of their fee:</line>
            <line>No, let them satisfy their lust on thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>Away! for thou hast stay'd us here too long.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAVINIA</speaker>
            <line>No grace? no womanhood? Ah, beastly creature!</line>
            <line>The blot and enemy to our general name!</line>
            <line>Confusion fall--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHIRON</speaker>
            <line>Nay, then I'll stop your mouth. Bring thou her husband:</line>
            <line>This is the hole where Aaron bid us hide him.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>DEMETRIUS throws the body of BASSIANUS into the
pit; then exeunt DEMETRIUS and CHIRON, dragging
off LAVINIA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TAMORA</speaker>
            <line>Farewell, my sons: see that you make her sure.</line>
            <line>Ne'er let my heart know merry cheer indeed,</line>
            <line>Till all the Andronici be made away.</line>
            <line>Now will I hence to seek my lovely Moor,</line>
            <line>And let my spleenful sons this trull deflow'r.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Re-enter AARON, with QUINTUS and MARTIUS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AARON</speaker>
            <line>Come on, my lords, the better foot before:</line>
            <line>Straight will I bring you to the loathsome pit</line>
            <line>Where I espied the panther fast asleep.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUINTUS</speaker>
            <line>My sight is very dull, whate'er it bodes.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARTIUS</speaker>
            <line>And mine, I promise you; were't not for shame,</line>
            <line>Well could I leave our sport to sleep awhile.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Falls into the pit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUINTUS</speaker>
            <line>What art thou fall'n? What subtle hole is this,</line>
            <line>Whose mouth is cover'd with rude-growing briers,</line>
            <line>Upon whose leaves are drops of new-shed blood</line>
            <line>As fresh as morning dew distill'd on flowers?</line>
            <line>A very fatal place it seems to me.</line>
            <line>Speak, brother, hast thou hurt thee with the fall?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARTIUS</speaker>
            <line>O brother, with the dismall'st object hurt</line>
            <line>That ever eye with sight made heart lament!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AARON</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  Now will I fetch the king to find them here,</line>
            <line>That he thereby may give a likely guess</line>
            <line>How these were they that made away his brother.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARTIUS</speaker>
            <line>Why dost not comfort me, and help me out</line>
            <line>From this unhallowed and blood-stained hole?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUINTUS</speaker>
            <line>I am surprised with an uncouth fear;</line>
            <line>A chilling sweat o'er-runs my trembling joints:</line>
            <line>My heart suspects more than mine eye can see.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARTIUS</speaker>
            <line>To prove thou hast a true-divining heart,</line>
            <line>Aaron and thou look down into this den,</line>
            <line>And see a fearful sight of blood and death.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUINTUS</speaker>
            <line>Aaron is gone; and my compassionate heart</line>
            <line>Will not permit mine eyes once to behold</line>
            <line>The thing whereat it trembles by surmise;</line>
            <line>O, tell me how it is; for ne'er till now</line>
            <line>Was I a child to fear I know not what.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARTIUS</speaker>
            <line>Lord Bassianus lies embrewed here,</line>
            <line>All on a heap, like to a slaughter'd lamb,</line>
            <line>In this detested, dark, blood-drinking pit.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUINTUS</speaker>
            <line>If it be dark, how dost thou know 'tis he?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARTIUS</speaker>
            <line>Upon his bloody finger he doth wear</line>
            <line>A precious ring, that lightens all the hole,</line>
            <line>Which, like a taper in some monument,</line>
            <line>Doth shine upon the dead man's earthy cheeks,</line>
            <line>And shows the ragged entrails of the pit:</line>
            <line>So pale did shine the moon on Pyramus</line>
            <line>When he by night lay bathed in maiden blood.</line>
            <line>O brother, help me with thy fainting hand--</line>
            <line>If fear hath made thee faint, as me it hath--</line>
            <line>Out of this fell devouring receptacle,</line>
            <line>As hateful as Cocytus' misty mouth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUINTUS</speaker>
            <line>Reach me thy hand, that I may help thee out;</line>
            <line>Or, wanting strength to do thee so much good,</line>
            <line>I may be pluck'd into the swallowing womb</line>
            <line>Of this deep pit, poor Bassianus' grave.</line>
            <line>I have no strength to pluck thee to the brink.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARTIUS</speaker>
            <line>Nor I no strength to climb without thy help.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUINTUS</speaker>
            <line>Thy hand once more; I will not loose again,</line>
            <line>Till thou art here aloft, or I below:</line>
            <line>Thou canst not come to me: I come to thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Falls in</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Enter SATURNINUS with AARON</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SATURNINUS</speaker>
            <line>Along with me: I'll see what hole is here,</line>
            <line>And what he is that now is leap'd into it.</line>
            <line>Say who art thou that lately didst descend</line>
            <line>Into this gaping hollow of the earth?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARTIUS</speaker>
            <line>The unhappy son of old Andronicus:</line>
            <line>Brought hither in a most unlucky hour,</line>
            <line>To find thy brother Bassianus dead.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SATURNINUS</speaker>
            <line>My brother dead! I know thou dost but jest:</line>
            <line>He and his lady both are at the lodge</line>
            <line>Upon the north side of this pleasant chase;</line>
            <line>'Tis not an hour since I left him there.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARTIUS</speaker>
            <line>We know not where you left him all alive;</line>
            <line>But, out, alas! here have we found him dead.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter TAMORA, with Attendants; TITUS
ANDRONICUS, and Lucius</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TAMORA</speaker>
            <line>Where is my lord the king?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SATURNINUS</speaker>
            <line>Here, Tamora, though grieved with killing grief.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TAMORA</speaker>
            <line>Where is thy brother Bassianus?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SATURNINUS</speaker>
            <line>Now to the bottom dost thou search my wound:</line>
            <line>Poor Bassianus here lies murdered.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TAMORA</speaker>
            <line>Then all too late I bring this fatal writ,</line>
            <line>The complot of this timeless tragedy;</line>
            <line>And wonder greatly that man's face can fold</line>
            <line>In pleasing smiles such murderous tyranny.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>She giveth SATURNINUS a letter</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SATURNINUS</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>  'An if we miss to meet him handsomely--</line>
            <line>Sweet huntsman, Bassianus 'tis we mean--</line>
            <line>Do thou so much as dig the grave for him:</line>
            <line>Thou know'st our meaning. Look for thy reward</line>
            <line>Among the nettles at the elder-tree</line>
            <line>Which overshades the mouth of that same pit</line>
            <line>Where we decreed to bury Bassianus.</line>
            <line>Do this, and purchase us thy lasting friends.'</line>
            <line>O Tamora! was ever heard the like?</line>
            <line>This is the pit, and this the elder-tree.</line>
            <line>Look, sirs, if you can find the huntsman out</line>
            <line>That should have murdered Bassianus here.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AARON</speaker>
            <line>My gracious lord, here is the bag of gold.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SATURNINUS</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>To TITUS</stagedir>  Two of thy whelps, fell curs of</line>
            <line>bloody kind,</line>
            <line>Have here bereft my brother of his life.</line>
            <line>Sirs, drag them from the pit unto the prison:</line>
            <line>There let them bide until we have devised</line>
            <line>Some never-heard-of torturing pain for them.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TAMORA</speaker>
            <line>What, are they in this pit? O wondrous thing!</line>
            <line>How easily murder is discovered!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>High emperor, upon my feeble knee</line>
            <line>I beg this boon, with tears not lightly shed,</line>
            <line>That this fell fault of my accursed sons,</line>
            <line>Accursed if the fault be proved in them,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SATURNINUS</speaker>
            <line>If it be proved! you see it is apparent.</line>
            <line>Who found this letter? Tamora, was it you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TAMORA</speaker>
            <line>Andronicus himself did take it up.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>I did, my lord: yet let me be their bail;</line>
            <line>For, by my father's reverend tomb, I vow</line>
            <line>They shall be ready at your highness' will</line>
            <line>To answer their suspicion with their lives.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SATURNINUS</speaker>
            <line>Thou shalt not bail them: see thou follow me.</line>
            <line>Some bring the murder'd body, some the murderers:</line>
            <line>Let them not speak a word; the guilt is plain;</line>
            <line>For, by my soul, were there worse end than death,</line>
            <line>That end upon them should be executed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TAMORA</speaker>
            <line>Andronicus, I will entreat the king;</line>
            <line>Fear not thy sons; they shall do well enough.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITUS ANDRONICUS</speaker>
            <line>Come, Lucius, come; stay not to talk with them.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-4">
      <title>SCENE IV.  Another part of the forest.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter DEMETRIUS and CHIRON with LAVINIA, ravished;
her hands cut off, and her tongue cut out</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>So, now go tell, an if thy tongue can speak,</line>
            <line>Who 'twas that cut thy tongue and ravish'd thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHIRON</speaker>
            <line>Write down thy mind, bewray thy meaning so,</line>
            <line>An if thy stumps will let thee play the scribe.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>See, how with signs and tokens she can scrowl.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHIRON</speaker>
            <line>Go home, call for sweet water, wash thy hands.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>She hath no tongue to call, nor hands to wash;</line>
            <line>And so let's leave her to her silent walks.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHIRON</speaker>
            <line>An 'twere my case, I should go hang myself.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>If thou hadst hands to help thee knit the cord.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt DEMETRIUS and CHIRON</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Enter MARCUS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARCUS</speaker>
            <line>Who is this? my niece, that flies away so fast!</line>
            <line>Cousin, a word; where is your husband?</line>
            <line>If I do dream, would all my wealth would wake me!</line>
            <line>If I do wake, some planet strike me down,</line>
            <line>That I may slumber in eternal sleep!</line>
            <line>Speak, gentle niece, what stern ungentle hands</line>
            <line>Have lopp'd and hew'd and made thy body bare</line>
            <line>Of her two branches, those sweet ornaments,</line>
            <line>Whose circling shadows kings have sought to sleep in,</line>
            <line>And might not gain so great a happiness</line>
            <line>As have thy love? Why dost not speak to me?</line>
            <line>Alas, a crimson river of warm blood,</line>
            <line>Like to a bubbling fountain stirr'd with wind,</line>
            <line>Doth rise and fall between thy rosed lips,</line>
            <line>Coming and going with thy honey breath.</line>
            <line>But, sure, some Tereus hath deflowered thee,</line>
            <line>And, lest thou shouldst detect him, cut thy tongue.</line>
            <line>Ah, now thou turn'st away thy face for shame!</line>
            <line>And, notwithstanding all this loss of blood,</line>
            <line>As from a conduit with three issuing spouts,</line>
            <line>Yet do thy cheeks look red as Titan's face</line>
            <line>Blushing to be encountered with a cloud.</line>
            <line>Shall I speak for thee? shall I say 'tis so?</line>
            <line>O, that I knew thy heart; and knew the beast,</line>
            <line>That I might rail at him, to ease my mind!</line>
            <line>Sorrow concealed, like an oven stopp'd,</line>
            <line>Doth burn the heart to cinders where it is.</line>
            <line>Fair Philomela, she but lost her tongue,</line>
            <line>And in a tedious sampler sew'd her mind:</line>
            <line>But, lovely niece, that mean is cut from thee;</line>
            <line>A craftier Tereus, cousin, hast thou met,</line>
            <line>And he hath cut those pretty fingers off,</line>
            <line>That could have better sew'd than Philomel.</line>
            <line>O, had the monster seen those lily hands</line>
            <line>Tremble, like aspen-leaves, upon a lute,</line>
            <line>And make the silken strings delight to kiss them,</line>
            <line>He would not then have touch'd them for his life!</line>
            <line>Or, had he heard the heavenly harmony</line>
            <line>Which that sweet tongue hath made,</line>
            <line>He would have dropp'd his knife, and fell asleep</line>
            <line>As Cerberus at the Thracian poet's feet.</line>
            <line>Come, let us go, and make thy father blind;</line>
            <line>For such a sight will blind a father's eye:</line>
            <line>One hour's storm will drown the fragrant meads;</line>
            <line>What will whole months of tears thy father's eyes?</line>
            <line>Do not draw back, for we will mourn with thee</line>
            <line>O, could our mourning ease thy misery!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>