<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net/doctypes/dita/shakespear/dtd/act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-3">
   <title>ACT III</title>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  The wood. TITANIA lying asleep.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter QUINCE, SNUG, BOTTOM, FLUTE, SNOUT, and
STARVELING</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOTTOM</speaker>
            <line>Are we all met?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUINCE</speaker>
            <line>Pat, pat; and here's a marvellous convenient place</line>
            <line>for our rehearsal. This green plot shall be our</line>
            <line>stage, this hawthorn-brake our tiring-house; and we</line>
            <line>will do it in action as we will do it before the duke.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOTTOM</speaker>
            <line>Peter Quince,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUINCE</speaker>
            <line>What sayest thou, bully Bottom?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOTTOM</speaker>
            <line>There are things in this comedy of Pyramus and</line>
            <line>Thisby that will never please. First, Pyramus must</line>
            <line>draw a sword to kill himself; which the ladies</line>
            <line>cannot abide. How answer you that?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SNOUT</speaker>
            <line>By'r lakin, a parlous fear.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>STARVELING</speaker>
            <line>I believe we must leave the killing out, when all is done.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOTTOM</speaker>
            <line>Not a whit: I have a device to make all well.</line>
            <line>Write me a prologue; and let the prologue seem to</line>
            <line>say, we will do no harm with our swords, and that</line>
            <line>Pyramus is not killed indeed; and, for the more</line>
            <line>better assurance, tell them that I, Pyramus, am not</line>
            <line>Pyramus, but Bottom the weaver: this will put them</line>
            <line>out of fear.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUINCE</speaker>
            <line>Well, we will have such a prologue; and it shall be</line>
            <line>written in eight and six.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOTTOM</speaker>
            <line>No, make it two more; let it be written in eight and eight.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SNOUT</speaker>
            <line>Will not the ladies be afeard of the lion?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>STARVELING</speaker>
            <line>I fear it, I promise you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOTTOM</speaker>
            <line>Masters, you ought to consider with yourselves: to</line>
            <line>bring in--God shield us!--a lion among ladies, is a</line>
            <line>most dreadful thing; for there is not a more fearful</line>
            <line>wild-fowl than your lion living; and we ought to</line>
            <line>look to 't.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SNOUT</speaker>
            <line>Therefore another prologue must tell he is not a lion.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOTTOM</speaker>
            <line>Nay, you must name his name, and half his face must</line>
            <line>be seen through the lion's neck: and he himself</line>
            <line>must speak through, saying thus, or to the same</line>
            <line>defect,--'Ladies,'--or 'Fair-ladies--I would wish</line>
            <line>You,'--or 'I would request you,'--or 'I would</line>
            <line>entreat you,--not to fear, not to tremble: my life</line>
            <line>for yours. If you think I come hither as a lion, it</line>
            <line>were pity of my life: no I am no such thing; I am a</line>
            <line>man as other men are;' and there indeed let him name</line>
            <line>his name, and tell them plainly he is Snug the joiner.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUINCE</speaker>
            <line>Well it shall be so. But there is two hard things;</line>
            <line>that is, to bring the moonlight into a chamber; for,</line>
            <line>you know, Pyramus and Thisby meet by moonlight.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SNOUT</speaker>
            <line>Doth the moon shine that night we play our play?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOTTOM</speaker>
            <line>A calendar, a calendar! look in the almanac; find</line>
            <line>out moonshine, find out moonshine.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUINCE</speaker>
            <line>Yes, it doth shine that night.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOTTOM</speaker>
            <line>Why, then may you leave a casement of the great</line>
            <line>chamber window, where we play, open, and the moon</line>
            <line>may shine in at the casement.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUINCE</speaker>
            <line>Ay; or else one must come in with a bush of thorns</line>
            <line>and a lanthorn, and say he comes to disfigure, or to</line>
            <line>present, the person of Moonshine. Then, there is</line>
            <line>another thing: we must have a wall in the great</line>
            <line>chamber; for Pyramus and Thisby says the story, did</line>
            <line>talk through the chink of a wall.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SNOUT</speaker>
            <line>You can never bring in a wall. What say you, Bottom?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOTTOM</speaker>
            <line>Some man or other must present Wall: and let him</line>
            <line>have some plaster, or some loam, or some rough-cast</line>
            <line>about him, to signify wall; and let him hold his</line>
            <line>fingers thus, and through that cranny shall Pyramus</line>
            <line>and Thisby whisper.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUINCE</speaker>
            <line>If that may be, then all is well. Come, sit down,</line>
            <line>every mother's son, and rehearse your parts.</line>
            <line>Pyramus, you begin: when you have spoken your</line>
            <line>speech, enter into that brake: and so every one</line>
            <line>according to his cue.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter PUCK behind</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PUCK</speaker>
            <line>What hempen home-spuns have we swaggering here,</line>
            <line>So near the cradle of the fairy queen?</line>
            <line>What, a play toward! I'll be an auditor;</line>
            <line>An actor too, perhaps, if I see cause.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUINCE</speaker>
            <line>Speak, Pyramus. Thisby, stand forth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOTTOM</speaker>
            <line>Thisby, the flowers of odious savours sweet,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUINCE</speaker>
            <line>Odours, odours.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOTTOM</speaker>
            <line>--odours savours sweet:</line>
            <line>So hath thy breath, my dearest Thisby dear.</line>
            <line>But hark, a voice! stay thou but here awhile,</line>
            <line>And by and by I will to thee appear.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PUCK</speaker>
            <line>A stranger Pyramus than e'er played here.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLUTE</speaker>
            <line>Must I speak now?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUINCE</speaker>
            <line>Ay, marry, must you; for you must understand he goes</line>
            <line>but to see a noise that he heard, and is to come again.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLUTE</speaker>
            <line>Most radiant Pyramus, most lily-white of hue,</line>
            <line>Of colour like the red rose on triumphant brier,</line>
            <line>Most brisky juvenal and eke most lovely Jew,</line>
            <line>As true as truest horse that yet would never tire,</line>
            <line>I'll meet thee, Pyramus, at Ninny's tomb.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUINCE</speaker>
            <line>'Ninus' tomb,' man: why, you must not speak that</line>
            <line>yet; that you answer to Pyramus: you speak all your</line>
            <line>part at once, cues and all Pyramus enter: your cue</line>
            <line>is past; it is, 'never tire.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLUTE</speaker>
            <line>O,--As true as truest horse, that yet would</line>
            <line>never tire.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter PUCK, and BOTTOM with an ass's head</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOTTOM</speaker>
            <line>If I were fair, Thisby, I were only thine.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUINCE</speaker>
            <line>O monstrous! O strange! we are haunted. Pray,</line>
            <line>masters! fly, masters! Help!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt QUINCE, SNUG, FLUTE, SNOUT, and STARVELING</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PUCK</speaker>
            <line>I'll follow you, I'll lead you about a round,</line>
            <line>Through bog, through bush, through brake, through brier:</line>
            <line>Sometime a horse I'll be, sometime a hound,</line>
            <line>A hog, a headless bear, sometime a fire;</line>
            <line>And neigh, and bark, and grunt, and roar, and burn,</line>
            <line>Like horse, hound, hog, bear, fire, at every turn.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOTTOM</speaker>
            <line>Why do they run away? this is a knavery of them to</line>
            <line>make me afeard.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter SNOUT</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SNOUT</speaker>
            <line>O Bottom, thou art changed! what do I see on thee?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOTTOM</speaker>
            <line>What do you see? you see an asshead of your own, do</line>
            <line>you?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit SNOUT</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Re-enter QUINCE</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUINCE</speaker>
            <line>Bless thee, Bottom! bless thee! thou art</line>
            <line>translated.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOTTOM</speaker>
            <line>I see their knavery: this is to make an ass of me;</line>
            <line>to fright me, if they could. But I will not stir</line>
            <line>from this place, do what they can: I will walk up</line>
            <line>and down here, and I will sing, that they shall hear</line>
            <line>I am not afraid.</line>
            <stagedir>Sings</stagedir>
            <line>The ousel cock so black of hue,</line>
            <line>With orange-tawny bill,</line>
            <line>The throstle with his note so true,</line>
            <line>The wren with little quill,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITANIA</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Awaking</stagedir>  What angel wakes me from my flowery bed?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOTTOM</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Sings</stagedir>
            </line>
            <line>The finch, the sparrow and the lark,</line>
            <line>The plain-song cuckoo gray,</line>
            <line>Whose note full many a man doth mark,</line>
            <line>And dares not answer nay;--</line>
            <line>for, indeed, who would set his wit to so foolish</line>
            <line>a bird? who would give a bird the lie, though he cry</line>
            <line>'cuckoo' never so?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITANIA</speaker>
            <line>I pray thee, gentle mortal, sing again:</line>
            <line>Mine ear is much enamour'd of thy note;</line>
            <line>So is mine eye enthralled to thy shape;</line>
            <line>And thy fair virtue's force perforce doth move me</line>
            <line>On the first view to say, to swear, I love thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOTTOM</speaker>
            <line>Methinks, mistress, you should have little reason</line>
            <line>for that: and yet, to say the truth, reason and</line>
            <line>love keep little company together now-a-days; the</line>
            <line>more the pity that some honest neighbours will not</line>
            <line>make them friends. Nay, I can gleek upon occasion.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITANIA</speaker>
            <line>Thou art as wise as thou art beautiful.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOTTOM</speaker>
            <line>Not so, neither: but if I had wit enough to get out</line>
            <line>of this wood, I have enough to serve mine own turn.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITANIA</speaker>
            <line>Out of this wood do not desire to go:</line>
            <line>Thou shalt remain here, whether thou wilt or no.</line>
            <line>I am a spirit of no common rate;</line>
            <line>The summer still doth tend upon my state;</line>
            <line>And I do love thee: therefore, go with me;</line>
            <line>I'll give thee fairies to attend on thee,</line>
            <line>And they shall fetch thee jewels from the deep,</line>
            <line>And sing while thou on pressed flowers dost sleep;</line>
            <line>And I will purge thy mortal grossness so</line>
            <line>That thou shalt like an airy spirit go.</line>
            <line>Peaseblossom! Cobweb! Moth! and Mustardseed!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter PEASEBLOSSOM, COBWEB, MOTH, and MUSTARDSEED</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PEASEBLOSSOM</speaker>
            <line>Ready.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COBWEB</speaker>
            <line>And I.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOTH</speaker>
            <line>And I.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MUSTARDSEED</speaker>
            <line>And I.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALL</speaker>
            <line>Where shall we go?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITANIA</speaker>
            <line>Be kind and courteous to this gentleman;</line>
            <line>Hop in his walks and gambol in his eyes;</line>
            <line>Feed him with apricocks and dewberries,</line>
            <line>With purple grapes, green figs, and mulberries;</line>
            <line>The honey-bags steal from the humble-bees,</line>
            <line>And for night-tapers crop their waxen thighs</line>
            <line>And light them at the fiery glow-worm's eyes,</line>
            <line>To have my love to bed and to arise;</line>
            <line>And pluck the wings from Painted butterflies</line>
            <line>To fan the moonbeams from his sleeping eyes:</line>
            <line>Nod to him, elves, and do him courtesies.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PEASEBLOSSOM</speaker>
            <line>Hail, mortal!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COBWEB</speaker>
            <line>Hail!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOTH</speaker>
            <line>Hail!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MUSTARDSEED</speaker>
            <line>Hail!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOTTOM</speaker>
            <line>I cry your worship's mercy, heartily: I beseech your</line>
            <line>worship's name.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COBWEB</speaker>
            <line>Cobweb.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOTTOM</speaker>
            <line>I shall desire you of more acquaintance, good Master</line>
            <line>Cobweb: if I cut my finger, I shall make bold with</line>
            <line>you. Your name, honest gentleman?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PEASEBLOSSOM</speaker>
            <line>Peaseblossom.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOTTOM</speaker>
            <line>I pray you, commend me to Mistress Squash, your</line>
            <line>mother, and to Master Peascod, your father. Good</line>
            <line>Master Peaseblossom, I shall desire you of more</line>
            <line>acquaintance too. Your name, I beseech you, sir?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MUSTARDSEED</speaker>
            <line>Mustardseed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOTTOM</speaker>
            <line>Good Master Mustardseed, I know your patience well:</line>
            <line>that same cowardly, giant-like ox-beef hath</line>
            <line>devoured many a gentleman of your house: I promise</line>
            <line>you your kindred had made my eyes water ere now. I</line>
            <line>desire your more acquaintance, good Master</line>
            <line>Mustardseed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITANIA</speaker>
            <line>Come, wait upon him; lead him to my bower.</line>
            <line>The moon methinks looks with a watery eye;</line>
            <line>And when she weeps, weeps every little flower,</line>
            <line>Lamenting some enforced chastity.</line>
            <line>Tie up my love's tongue bring him silently.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  Another part of the wood.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter OBERON</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OBERON</speaker>
            <line>I wonder if Titania be awaked;</line>
            <line>Then, what it was that next came in her eye,</line>
            <line>Which she must dote on in extremity.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter PUCK</stagedir>
            <line>Here comes my messenger.</line>
            <line>How now, mad spirit!</line>
            <line>What night-rule now about this haunted grove?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PUCK</speaker>
            <line>My mistress with a monster is in love.</line>
            <line>Near to her close and consecrated bower,</line>
            <line>While she was in her dull and sleeping hour,</line>
            <line>A crew of patches, rude mechanicals,</line>
            <line>That work for bread upon Athenian stalls,</line>
            <line>Were met together to rehearse a play</line>
            <line>Intended for great Theseus' nuptial-day.</line>
            <line>The shallowest thick-skin of that barren sort,</line>
            <line>Who Pyramus presented, in their sport</line>
            <line>Forsook his scene and enter'd in a brake</line>
            <line>When I did him at this advantage take,</line>
            <line>An ass's nole I fixed on his head:</line>
            <line>Anon his Thisbe must be answered,</line>
            <line>And forth my mimic comes. When they him spy,</line>
            <line>As wild geese that the creeping fowler eye,</line>
            <line>Or russet-pated choughs, many in sort,</line>
            <line>Rising and cawing at the gun's report,</line>
            <line>Sever themselves and madly sweep the sky,</line>
            <line>So, at his sight, away his fellows fly;</line>
            <line>And, at our stamp, here o'er and o'er one falls;</line>
            <line>He murder cries and help from Athens calls.</line>
            <line>Their sense thus weak, lost with their fears</line>
            <line>thus strong,</line>
            <line>Made senseless things begin to do them wrong;</line>
            <line>For briers and thorns at their apparel snatch;</line>
            <line>Some sleeves, some hats, from yielders all</line>
            <line>things catch.</line>
            <line>I led them on in this distracted fear,</line>
            <line>And left sweet Pyramus translated there:</line>
            <line>When in that moment, so it came to pass,</line>
            <line>Titania waked and straightway loved an ass.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OBERON</speaker>
            <line>This falls out better than I could devise.</line>
            <line>But hast thou yet latch'd the Athenian's eyes</line>
            <line>With the love-juice, as I did bid thee do?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PUCK</speaker>
            <line>I took him sleeping,--that is finish'd too,--</line>
            <line>And the Athenian woman by his side:</line>
            <line>That, when he waked, of force she must be eyed.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter HERMIA and DEMETRIUS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OBERON</speaker>
            <line>Stand close: this is the same Athenian.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PUCK</speaker>
            <line>This is the woman, but not this the man.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>O, why rebuke you him that loves you so?</line>
            <line>Lay breath so bitter on your bitter foe.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERMIA</speaker>
            <line>Now I but chide; but I should use thee worse,</line>
            <line>For thou, I fear, hast given me cause to curse,</line>
            <line>If thou hast slain Lysander in his sleep,</line>
            <line>Being o'er shoes in blood, plunge in the deep,</line>
            <line>And kill me too.</line>
            <line>The sun was not so true unto the day</line>
            <line>As he to me: would he have stolen away</line>
            <line>From sleeping Hermia? I'll believe as soon</line>
            <line>This whole earth may be bored and that the moon</line>
            <line>May through the centre creep and so displease</line>
            <line>Her brother's noontide with Antipodes.</line>
            <line>It cannot be but thou hast murder'd him;</line>
            <line>So should a murderer look, so dead, so grim.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>So should the murder'd look, and so should I,</line>
            <line>Pierced through the heart with your stern cruelty:</line>
            <line>Yet you, the murderer, look as bright, as clear,</line>
            <line>As yonder Venus in her glimmering sphere.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERMIA</speaker>
            <line>What's this to my Lysander? where is he?</line>
            <line>Ah, good Demetrius, wilt thou give him me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>I had rather give his carcass to my hounds.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERMIA</speaker>
            <line>Out, dog! out, cur! thou drivest me past the bounds</line>
            <line>Of maiden's patience. Hast thou slain him, then?</line>
            <line>Henceforth be never number'd among men!</line>
            <line>O, once tell true, tell true, even for my sake!</line>
            <line>Durst thou have look'd upon him being awake,</line>
            <line>And hast thou kill'd him sleeping? O brave touch!</line>
            <line>Could not a worm, an adder, do so much?</line>
            <line>An adder did it; for with doubler tongue</line>
            <line>Than thine, thou serpent, never adder stung.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>You spend your passion on a misprised mood:</line>
            <line>I am not guilty of Lysander's blood;</line>
            <line>Nor is he dead, for aught that I can tell.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERMIA</speaker>
            <line>I pray thee, tell me then that he is well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>An if I could, what should I get therefore?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERMIA</speaker>
            <line>A privilege never to see me more.</line>
            <line>And from thy hated presence part I so:</line>
            <line>See me no more, whether he be dead or no.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>There is no following her in this fierce vein:</line>
            <line>Here therefore for a while I will remain.</line>
            <line>So sorrow's heaviness doth heavier grow</line>
            <line>For debt that bankrupt sleep doth sorrow owe:</line>
            <line>Which now in some slight measure it will pay,</line>
            <line>If for his tender here I make some stay.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Lies down and sleeps</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OBERON</speaker>
            <line>What hast thou done? thou hast mistaken quite</line>
            <line>And laid the love-juice on some true-love's sight:</line>
            <line>Of thy misprision must perforce ensue</line>
            <line>Some true love turn'd and not a false turn'd true.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PUCK</speaker>
            <line>Then fate o'er-rules, that, one man holding troth,</line>
            <line>A million fail, confounding oath on oath.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OBERON</speaker>
            <line>About the wood go swifter than the wind,</line>
            <line>And Helena of Athens look thou find:</line>
            <line>All fancy-sick she is and pale of cheer,</line>
            <line>With sighs of love, that costs the fresh blood dear:</line>
            <line>By some illusion see thou bring her here:</line>
            <line>I'll charm his eyes against she do appear.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PUCK</speaker>
            <line>I go, I go; look how I go,</line>
            <line>Swifter than arrow from the Tartar's bow.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OBERON</speaker>
            <line>Flower of this purple dye,</line>
            <line>Hit with Cupid's archery,</line>
            <line>Sink in apple of his eye.</line>
            <line>When his love he doth espy,</line>
            <line>Let her shine as gloriously</line>
            <line>As the Venus of the sky.</line>
            <line>When thou wakest, if she be by,</line>
            <line>Beg of her for remedy.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter PUCK</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PUCK</speaker>
            <line>Captain of our fairy band,</line>
            <line>Helena is here at hand;</line>
            <line>And the youth, mistook by me,</line>
            <line>Pleading for a lover's fee.</line>
            <line>Shall we their fond pageant see?</line>
            <line>Lord, what fools these mortals be!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OBERON</speaker>
            <line>Stand aside: the noise they make</line>
            <line>Will cause Demetrius to awake.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PUCK</speaker>
            <line>Then will two at once woo one;</line>
            <line>That must needs be sport alone;</line>
            <line>And those things do best please me</line>
            <line>That befal preposterously.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter LYSANDER and HELENA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LYSANDER</speaker>
            <line>Why should you think that I should woo in scorn?</line>
            <line>Scorn and derision never come in tears:</line>
            <line>Look, when I vow, I weep; and vows so born,</line>
            <line>In their nativity all truth appears.</line>
            <line>How can these things in me seem scorn to you,</line>
            <line>Bearing the badge of faith, to prove them true?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>You do advance your cunning more and more.</line>
            <line>When truth kills truth, O devilish-holy fray!</line>
            <line>These vows are Hermia's: will you give her o'er?</line>
            <line>Weigh oath with oath, and you will nothing weigh:</line>
            <line>Your vows to her and me, put in two scales,</line>
            <line>Will even weigh, and both as light as tales.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LYSANDER</speaker>
            <line>I had no judgment when to her I swore.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>Nor none, in my mind, now you give her o'er.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LYSANDER</speaker>
            <line>Demetrius loves her, and he loves not you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Awaking</stagedir>  O Helena, goddess, nymph, perfect, divine!</line>
            <line>To what, my love, shall I compare thine eyne?</line>
            <line>Crystal is muddy. O, how ripe in show</line>
            <line>Thy lips, those kissing cherries, tempting grow!</line>
            <line>That pure congealed white, high Taurus snow,</line>
            <line>Fann'd with the eastern wind, turns to a crow</line>
            <line>When thou hold'st up thy hand: O, let me kiss</line>
            <line>This princess of pure white, this seal of bliss!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>O spite! O hell! I see you all are bent</line>
            <line>To set against me for your merriment:</line>
            <line>If you we re civil and knew courtesy,</line>
            <line>You would not do me thus much injury.</line>
            <line>Can you not hate me, as I know you do,</line>
            <line>But you must join in souls to mock me too?</line>
            <line>If you were men, as men you are in show,</line>
            <line>You would not use a gentle lady so;</line>
            <line>To vow, and swear, and superpraise my parts,</line>
            <line>When I am sure you hate me with your hearts.</line>
            <line>You both are rivals, and love Hermia;</line>
            <line>And now both rivals, to mock Helena:</line>
            <line>A trim exploit, a manly enterprise,</line>
            <line>To conjure tears up in a poor maid's eyes</line>
            <line>With your derision! none of noble sort</line>
            <line>Would so offend a virgin, and extort</line>
            <line>A poor soul's patience, all to make you sport.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LYSANDER</speaker>
            <line>You are unkind, Demetrius; be not so;</line>
            <line>For you love Hermia; this you know I know:</line>
            <line>And here, with all good will, with all my heart,</line>
            <line>In Hermia's love I yield you up my part;</line>
            <line>And yours of Helena to me bequeath,</line>
            <line>Whom I do love and will do till my death.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>Never did mockers waste more idle breath.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>Lysander, keep thy Hermia; I will none:</line>
            <line>If e'er I loved her, all that love is gone.</line>
            <line>My heart to her but as guest-wise sojourn'd,</line>
            <line>And now to Helen is it home return'd,</line>
            <line>There to remain.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LYSANDER</speaker>
            <line>Helen, it is not so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>Disparage not the faith thou dost not know,</line>
            <line>Lest, to thy peril, thou aby it dear.</line>
            <line>Look, where thy love comes; yonder is thy dear.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter HERMIA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERMIA</speaker>
            <line>Dark night, that from the eye his function takes,</line>
            <line>The ear more quick of apprehension makes;</line>
            <line>Wherein it doth impair the seeing sense,</line>
            <line>It pays the hearing double recompense.</line>
            <line>Thou art not by mine eye, Lysander, found;</line>
            <line>Mine ear, I thank it, brought me to thy sound</line>
            <line>But why unkindly didst thou leave me so?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LYSANDER</speaker>
            <line>Why should he stay, whom love doth press to go?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERMIA</speaker>
            <line>What love could press Lysander from my side?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LYSANDER</speaker>
            <line>Lysander's love, that would not let him bide,</line>
            <line>Fair Helena, who more engilds the night</line>
            <line>Than all you fiery oes and eyes of light.</line>
            <line>Why seek'st thou me? could not this make thee know,</line>
            <line>The hate I bear thee made me leave thee so?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERMIA</speaker>
            <line>You speak not as you think: it cannot be.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>Lo, she is one of this confederacy!</line>
            <line>Now I perceive they have conjoin'd all three</line>
            <line>To fashion this false sport, in spite of me.</line>
            <line>Injurious Hermia! most ungrateful maid!</line>
            <line>Have you conspired, have you with these contrived</line>
            <line>To bait me with this foul derision?</line>
            <line>Is all the counsel that we two have shared,</line>
            <line>The sisters' vows, the hours that we have spent,</line>
            <line>When we have chid the hasty-footed time</line>
            <line>For parting us,--O, is it all forgot?</line>
            <line>All school-days' friendship, childhood innocence?</line>
            <line>We, Hermia, like two artificial gods,</line>
            <line>Have with our needles created both one flower,</line>
            <line>Both on one sampler, sitting on one cushion,</line>
            <line>Both warbling of one song, both in one key,</line>
            <line>As if our hands, our sides, voices and minds,</line>
            <line>Had been incorporate. So we grow together,</line>
            <line>Like to a double cherry, seeming parted,</line>
            <line>But yet an union in partition;</line>
            <line>Two lovely berries moulded on one stem;</line>
            <line>So, with two seeming bodies, but one heart;</line>
            <line>Two of the first, like coats in heraldry,</line>
            <line>Due but to one and crowned with one crest.</line>
            <line>And will you rent our ancient love asunder,</line>
            <line>To join with men in scorning your poor friend?</line>
            <line>It is not friendly, 'tis not maidenly:</line>
            <line>Our sex, as well as I, may chide you for it,</line>
            <line>Though I alone do feel the injury.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERMIA</speaker>
            <line>I am amazed at your passionate words.</line>
            <line>I scorn you not: it seems that you scorn me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>Have you not set Lysander, as in scorn,</line>
            <line>To follow me and praise my eyes and face?</line>
            <line>And made your other love, Demetrius,</line>
            <line>Who even but now did spurn me with his foot,</line>
            <line>To call me goddess, nymph, divine and rare,</line>
            <line>Precious, celestial? Wherefore speaks he this</line>
            <line>To her he hates? and wherefore doth Lysander</line>
            <line>Deny your love, so rich within his soul,</line>
            <line>And tender me, forsooth, affection,</line>
            <line>But by your setting on, by your consent?</line>
            <line>What thought I be not so in grace as you,</line>
            <line>So hung upon with love, so fortunate,</line>
            <line>But miserable most, to love unloved?</line>
            <line>This you should pity rather than despise.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERNIA</speaker>
            <line>I understand not what you mean by this.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>Ay, do, persever, counterfeit sad looks,</line>
            <line>Make mouths upon me when I turn my back;</line>
            <line>Wink each at other; hold the sweet jest up:</line>
            <line>This sport, well carried, shall be chronicled.</line>
            <line>If you have any pity, grace, or manners,</line>
            <line>You would not make me such an argument.</line>
            <line>But fare ye well: 'tis partly my own fault;</line>
            <line>Which death or absence soon shall remedy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LYSANDER</speaker>
            <line>Stay, gentle Helena; hear my excuse:</line>
            <line>My love, my life my soul, fair Helena!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>O excellent!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERMIA</speaker>
            <line>Sweet, do not scorn her so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>If she cannot entreat, I can compel.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LYSANDER</speaker>
            <line>Thou canst compel no more than she entreat:</line>
            <line>Thy threats have no more strength than her weak prayers.</line>
            <line>Helen, I love thee; by my life, I do:</line>
            <line>I swear by that which I will lose for thee,</line>
            <line>To prove him false that says I love thee not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>I say I love thee more than he can do.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LYSANDER</speaker>
            <line>If thou say so, withdraw, and prove it too.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>Quick, come!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERMIA</speaker>
            <line>Lysander, whereto tends all this?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LYSANDER</speaker>
            <line>Away, you Ethiope!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>No, no; he'll</line>
            <line>Seem to break loose; take on as you would follow,</line>
            <line>But yet come not: you are a tame man, go!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LYSANDER</speaker>
            <line>Hang off, thou cat, thou burr! vile thing, let loose,</line>
            <line>Or I will shake thee from me like a serpent!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERMIA</speaker>
            <line>Why are you grown so rude? what change is this?</line>
            <line>Sweet love,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LYSANDER</speaker>
            <line>Thy love! out, tawny Tartar, out!</line>
            <line>Out, loathed medicine! hated potion, hence!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERMIA</speaker>
            <line>Do you not jest?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>Yes, sooth; and so do you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LYSANDER</speaker>
            <line>Demetrius, I will keep my word with thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>I would I had your bond, for I perceive</line>
            <line>A weak bond holds you: I'll not trust your word.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LYSANDER</speaker>
            <line>What, should I hurt her, strike her, kill her dead?</line>
            <line>Although I hate her, I'll not harm her so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERMIA</speaker>
            <line>What, can you do me greater harm than hate?</line>
            <line>Hate me! wherefore? O me! what news, my love!</line>
            <line>Am not I Hermia? are not you Lysander?</line>
            <line>I am as fair now as I was erewhile.</line>
            <line>Since night you loved me; yet since night you left</line>
            <line>me:</line>
            <line>Why, then you left me--O, the gods forbid!--</line>
            <line>In earnest, shall I say?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LYSANDER</speaker>
            <line>Ay, by my life;</line>
            <line>And never did desire to see thee more.</line>
            <line>Therefore be out of hope, of question, of doubt;</line>
            <line>Be certain, nothing truer; 'tis no jest</line>
            <line>That I do hate thee and love Helena.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERMIA</speaker>
            <line>O me! you juggler! you canker-blossom!</line>
            <line>You thief of love! what, have you come by night</line>
            <line>And stolen my love's heart from him?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>Fine, i'faith!</line>
            <line>Have you no modesty, no maiden shame,</line>
            <line>No touch of bashfulness? What, will you tear</line>
            <line>Impatient answers from my gentle tongue?</line>
            <line>Fie, fie! you counterfeit, you puppet, you!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERMIA</speaker>
            <line>Puppet? why so? ay, that way goes the game.</line>
            <line>Now I perceive that she hath made compare</line>
            <line>Between our statures; she hath urged her height;</line>
            <line>And with her personage, her tall personage,</line>
            <line>Her height, forsooth, she hath prevail'd with him.</line>
            <line>And are you grown so high in his esteem;</line>
            <line>Because I am so dwarfish and so low?</line>
            <line>How low am I, thou painted maypole? speak;</line>
            <line>How low am I? I am not yet so low</line>
            <line>But that my nails can reach unto thine eyes.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>I pray you, though you mock me, gentlemen,</line>
            <line>Let her not hurt me: I was never curst;</line>
            <line>I have no gift at all in shrewishness;</line>
            <line>I am a right maid for my cowardice:</line>
            <line>Let her not strike me. You perhaps may think,</line>
            <line>Because she is something lower than myself,</line>
            <line>That I can match her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERMIA</speaker>
            <line>Lower! hark, again.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>Good Hermia, do not be so bitter with me.</line>
            <line>I evermore did love you, Hermia,</line>
            <line>Did ever keep your counsels, never wrong'd you;</line>
            <line>Save that, in love unto Demetrius,</line>
            <line>I told him of your stealth unto this wood.</line>
            <line>He follow'd you; for love I follow'd him;</line>
            <line>But he hath chid me hence and threaten'd me</line>
            <line>To strike me, spurn me, nay, to kill me too:</line>
            <line>And now, so you will let me quiet go,</line>
            <line>To Athens will I bear my folly back</line>
            <line>And follow you no further: let me go:</line>
            <line>You see how simple and how fond I am.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERMIA</speaker>
            <line>Why, get you gone: who is't that hinders you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>A foolish heart, that I leave here behind.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERMIA</speaker>
            <line>What, with Lysander?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>With Demetrius.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LYSANDER</speaker>
            <line>Be not afraid; she shall not harm thee, Helena.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>No, sir, she shall not, though you take her part.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>O, when she's angry, she is keen and shrewd!</line>
            <line>She was a vixen when she went to school;</line>
            <line>And though she be but little, she is fierce.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERMIA</speaker>
            <line>'Little' again! nothing but 'low' and 'little'!</line>
            <line>Why will you suffer her to flout me thus?</line>
            <line>Let me come to her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LYSANDER</speaker>
            <line>Get you gone, you dwarf;</line>
            <line>You minimus, of hindering knot-grass made;</line>
            <line>You bead, you acorn.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>You are too officious</line>
            <line>In her behalf that scorns your services.</line>
            <line>Let her alone: speak not of Helena;</line>
            <line>Take not her part; for, if thou dost intend</line>
            <line>Never so little show of love to her,</line>
            <line>Thou shalt aby it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LYSANDER</speaker>
            <line>Now she holds me not;</line>
            <line>Now follow, if thou darest, to try whose right,</line>
            <line>Of thine or mine, is most in Helena.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>Follow! nay, I'll go with thee, cheek by jole.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt LYSANDER and DEMETRIUS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERMIA</speaker>
            <line>You, mistress, all this coil is 'long of you:</line>
            <line>Nay, go not back.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>I will not trust you, I,</line>
            <line>Nor longer stay in your curst company.</line>
            <line>Your hands than mine are quicker for a fray,</line>
            <line>My legs are longer though, to run away.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERMIA</speaker>
            <line>I am amazed, and know not what to say.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OBERON</speaker>
            <line>This is thy negligence: still thou mistakest,</line>
            <line>Or else committ'st thy knaveries wilfully.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PUCK</speaker>
            <line>Believe me, king of shadows, I mistook.</line>
            <line>Did not you tell me I should know the man</line>
            <line>By the Athenian garment be had on?</line>
            <line>And so far blameless proves my enterprise,</line>
            <line>That I have 'nointed an Athenian's eyes;</line>
            <line>And so far am I glad it so did sort</line>
            <line>As this their jangling I esteem a sport.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OBERON</speaker>
            <line>Thou see'st these lovers seek a place to fight:</line>
            <line>Hie therefore, Robin, overcast the night;</line>
            <line>The starry welkin cover thou anon</line>
            <line>With drooping fog as black as Acheron,</line>
            <line>And lead these testy rivals so astray</line>
            <line>As one come not within another's way.</line>
            <line>Like to Lysander sometime frame thy tongue,</line>
            <line>Then stir Demetrius up with bitter wrong;</line>
            <line>And sometime rail thou like Demetrius;</line>
            <line>And from each other look thou lead them thus,</line>
            <line>Till o'er their brows death-counterfeiting sleep</line>
            <line>With leaden legs and batty wings doth creep:</line>
            <line>Then crush this herb into Lysander's eye;</line>
            <line>Whose liquor hath this virtuous property,</line>
            <line>To take from thence all error with his might,</line>
            <line>And make his eyeballs roll with wonted sight.</line>
            <line>When they next wake, all this derision</line>
            <line>Shall seem a dream and fruitless vision,</line>
            <line>And back to Athens shall the lovers wend,</line>
            <line>With league whose date till death shall never end.</line>
            <line>Whiles I in this affair do thee employ,</line>
            <line>I'll to my queen and beg her Indian boy;</line>
            <line>And then I will her charmed eye release</line>
            <line>From monster's view, and all things shall be peace.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PUCK</speaker>
            <line>My fairy lord, this must be done with haste,</line>
            <line>For night's swift dragons cut the clouds full fast,</line>
            <line>And yonder shines Aurora's harbinger;</line>
            <line>At whose approach, ghosts, wandering here and there,</line>
            <line>Troop home to churchyards: damned spirits all,</line>
            <line>That in crossways and floods have burial,</line>
            <line>Already to their wormy beds are gone;</line>
            <line>For fear lest day should look their shames upon,</line>
            <line>They willfully themselves exile from light</line>
            <line>And must for aye consort with black-brow'd night.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OBERON</speaker>
            <line>But we are spirits of another sort:</line>
            <line>I with the morning's love have oft made sport,</line>
            <line>And, like a forester, the groves may tread,</line>
            <line>Even till the eastern gate, all fiery-red,</line>
            <line>Opening on Neptune with fair blessed beams,</line>
            <line>Turns into yellow gold his salt green streams.</line>
            <line>But, notwithstanding, haste; make no delay:</line>
            <line>We may effect this business yet ere day.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PUCK</speaker>
            <line>Up and down, up and down,</line>
            <line>I will lead them up and down:</line>
            <line>I am fear'd in field and town:</line>
            <line>Goblin, lead them up and down.</line>
            <line>Here comes one.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter LYSANDER</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LYSANDER</speaker>
            <line>Where art thou, proud Demetrius? speak thou now.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PUCK</speaker>
            <line>Here, villain; drawn and ready. Where art thou?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LYSANDER</speaker>
            <line>I will be with thee straight.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PUCK</speaker>
            <line>Follow me, then,</line>
            <line>To plainer ground.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit LYSANDER, as following the voice</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Re-enter DEMETRIUS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>Lysander! speak again:</line>
            <line>Thou runaway, thou coward, art thou fled?</line>
            <line>Speak! In some bush? Where dost thou hide thy head?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PUCK</speaker>
            <line>Thou coward, art thou bragging to the stars,</line>
            <line>Telling the bushes that thou look'st for wars,</line>
            <line>And wilt not come? Come, recreant; come, thou child;</line>
            <line>I'll whip thee with a rod: he is defiled</line>
            <line>That draws a sword on thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>Yea, art thou there?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PUCK</speaker>
            <line>Follow my voice: we'll try no manhood here.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Re-enter LYSANDER</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LYSANDER</speaker>
            <line>He goes before me and still dares me on:</line>
            <line>When I come where he calls, then he is gone.</line>
            <line>The villain is much lighter-heel'd than I:</line>
            <line>I follow'd fast, but faster he did fly;</line>
            <line>That fallen am I in dark uneven way,</line>
            <line>And here will rest me.</line>
            <stagedir>Lies down</stagedir>
            <line>Come, thou gentle day!</line>
            <line>For if but once thou show me thy grey light,</line>
            <line>I'll find Demetrius and revenge this spite.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Sleeps</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Re-enter PUCK and DEMETRIUS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PUCK</speaker>
            <line>Ho, ho, ho! Coward, why comest thou not?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>Abide me, if thou darest; for well I wot</line>
            <line>Thou runn'st before me, shifting every place,</line>
            <line>And darest not stand, nor look me in the face.</line>
            <line>Where art thou now?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PUCK</speaker>
            <line>Come hither: I am here.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>Nay, then, thou mock'st me. Thou shalt buy this dear,</line>
            <line>If ever I thy face by daylight see:</line>
            <line>Now, go thy way. Faintness constraineth me</line>
            <line>To measure out my length on this cold bed.</line>
            <line>By day's approach look to be visited.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Lies down and sleeps</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Re-enter HELENA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>O weary night, O long and tedious night,</line>
            <line>Abate thy hour! Shine comforts from the east,</line>
            <line>That I may back to Athens by daylight,</line>
            <line>From these that my poor company detest:</line>
            <line>And sleep, that sometimes shuts up sorrow's eye,</line>
            <line>Steal me awhile from mine own company.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Lies down and sleeps</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PUCK</speaker>
            <line>Yet but three? Come one more;</line>
            <line>Two of both kinds make up four.</line>
            <line>Here she comes, curst and sad:</line>
            <line>Cupid is a knavish lad,</line>
            <line>Thus to make poor females mad.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter HERMIA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERMIA</speaker>
            <line>Never so weary, never so in woe,</line>
            <line>Bedabbled with the dew and torn with briers,</line>
            <line>I can no further crawl, no further go;</line>
            <line>My legs can keep no pace with my desires.</line>
            <line>Here will I rest me till the break of day.</line>
            <line>Heavens shield Lysander, if they mean a fray!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Lies down and sleeps</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PUCK</speaker>
            <line>On the ground</line>
            <line>Sleep sound:</line>
            <line>I'll apply</line>
            <line>To your eye,</line>
            <line>Gentle lover, remedy.</line>
            <stagedir>Squeezing the juice on LYSANDER's eyes</stagedir>
            <line>When thou wakest,</line>
            <line>Thou takest</line>
            <line>True delight</line>
            <line>In the sight</line>
            <line>Of thy former lady's eye:</line>
            <line>And the country proverb known,</line>
            <line>That every man should take his own,</line>
            <line>In your waking shall be shown:</line>
            <line>Jack shall have Jill;</line>
            <line>Nought shall go ill;</line>
            <line>The man shall have his mare again, and all shall be well.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>