<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:shakespear:dtd:act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-4">
   <title>ACT IV</title>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  The same. LYSANDER, DEMETRIUS, HELENA, and HERMIA lying asleep.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter TITANIA and BOTTOM; PEASEBLOSSOM, COBWEB, MOTH,
MUSTARDSEED, and other Fairies attending; OBERON
behind unseen</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITANIA</speaker>
            <line>Come, sit thee down upon this flowery bed,</line>
            <line>While I thy amiable cheeks do coy,</line>
            <line>And stick musk-roses in thy sleek smooth head,</line>
            <line>And kiss thy fair large ears, my gentle joy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOTTOM</speaker>
            <line>Where's Peaseblossom?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PEASEBLOSSOM</speaker>
            <line>Ready.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOTTOM</speaker>
            <line>Scratch my head Peaseblossom. Where's Mounsieur Cobweb?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COBWEB</speaker>
            <line>Ready.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOTTOM</speaker>
            <line>Mounsieur Cobweb, good mounsieur, get you your</line>
            <line>weapons in your hand, and kill me a red-hipped</line>
            <line>humble-bee on the top of a thistle; and, good</line>
            <line>mounsieur, bring me the honey-bag. Do not fret</line>
            <line>yourself too much in the action, mounsieur; and,</line>
            <line>good mounsieur, have a care the honey-bag break not;</line>
            <line>I would be loath to have you overflown with a</line>
            <line>honey-bag, signior. Where's Mounsieur Mustardseed?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MUSTARDSEED</speaker>
            <line>Ready.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOTTOM</speaker>
            <line>Give me your neaf, Mounsieur Mustardseed. Pray you,</line>
            <line>leave your courtesy, good mounsieur.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MUSTARDSEED</speaker>
            <line>What's your Will?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOTTOM</speaker>
            <line>Nothing, good mounsieur, but to help Cavalery Cobweb</line>
            <line>to scratch. I must to the barber's, monsieur; for</line>
            <line>methinks I am marvellous hairy about the face; and I</line>
            <line>am such a tender ass, if my hair do but tickle me,</line>
            <line>I must scratch.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITANIA</speaker>
            <line>What, wilt thou hear some music,</line>
            <line>my sweet love?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOTTOM</speaker>
            <line>I have a reasonable good ear in music. Let's have</line>
            <line>the tongs and the bones.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITANIA</speaker>
            <line>Or say, sweet love, what thou desirest to eat.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOTTOM</speaker>
            <line>Truly, a peck of provender: I could munch your good</line>
            <line>dry oats. Methinks I have a great desire to a bottle</line>
            <line>of hay: good hay, sweet hay, hath no fellow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITANIA</speaker>
            <line>I have a venturous fairy that shall seek</line>
            <line>The squirrel's hoard, and fetch thee new nuts.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOTTOM</speaker>
            <line>I had rather have a handful or two of dried peas.</line>
            <line>But, I pray you, let none of your people stir me: I</line>
            <line>have an exposition of sleep come upon me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITANIA</speaker>
            <line>Sleep thou, and I will wind thee in my arms.</line>
            <line>Fairies, begone, and be all ways away.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt fairies</stagedir>
            <line>So doth the woodbine the sweet honeysuckle</line>
            <line>Gently entwist; the female ivy so</line>
            <line>Enrings the barky fingers of the elm.</line>
            <line>O, how I love thee! how I dote on thee!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>They sleep</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Enter PUCK</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OBERON</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Advancing</stagedir>  Welcome, good Robin.</line>
            <line>See'st thou this sweet sight?</line>
            <line>Her dotage now I do begin to pity:</line>
            <line>For, meeting her of late behind the wood,</line>
            <line>Seeking sweet favours from this hateful fool,</line>
            <line>I did upbraid her and fall out with her;</line>
            <line>For she his hairy temples then had rounded</line>
            <line>With a coronet of fresh and fragrant flowers;</line>
            <line>And that same dew, which sometime on the buds</line>
            <line>Was wont to swell like round and orient pearls,</line>
            <line>Stood now within the pretty flowerets' eyes</line>
            <line>Like tears that did their own disgrace bewail.</line>
            <line>When I had at my pleasure taunted her</line>
            <line>And she in mild terms begg'd my patience,</line>
            <line>I then did ask of her her changeling child;</line>
            <line>Which straight she gave me, and her fairy sent</line>
            <line>To bear him to my bower in fairy land.</line>
            <line>And now I have the boy, I will undo</line>
            <line>This hateful imperfection of her eyes:</line>
            <line>And, gentle Puck, take this transformed scalp</line>
            <line>From off the head of this Athenian swain;</line>
            <line>That, he awaking when the other do,</line>
            <line>May all to Athens back again repair</line>
            <line>And think no more of this night's accidents</line>
            <line>But as the fierce vexation of a dream.</line>
            <line>But first I will release the fairy queen.</line>
            <line>Be as thou wast wont to be;</line>
            <line>See as thou wast wont to see:</line>
            <line>Dian's bud o'er Cupid's flower</line>
            <line>Hath such force and blessed power.</line>
            <line>Now, my Titania; wake you, my sweet queen.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITANIA</speaker>
            <line>My Oberon! what visions have I seen!</line>
            <line>Methought I was enamour'd of an ass.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OBERON</speaker>
            <line>There lies your love.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITANIA</speaker>
            <line>How came these things to pass?</line>
            <line>O, how mine eyes do loathe his visage now!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OBERON</speaker>
            <line>Silence awhile. Robin, take off this head.</line>
            <line>Titania, music call; and strike more dead</line>
            <line>Than common sleep of all these five the sense.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITANIA</speaker>
            <line>Music, ho! music, such as charmeth sleep!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Music, still</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PUCK</speaker>
            <line>Now, when thou wakest, with thine</line>
            <line>own fool's eyes peep.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OBERON</speaker>
            <line>Sound, music! Come, my queen, take hands with me,</line>
            <line>And rock the ground whereon these sleepers be.</line>
            <line>Now thou and I are new in amity,</line>
            <line>And will to-morrow midnight solemnly</line>
            <line>Dance in Duke Theseus' house triumphantly,</line>
            <line>And bless it to all fair prosperity:</line>
            <line>There shall the pairs of faithful lovers be</line>
            <line>Wedded, with Theseus, all in jollity.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PUCK</speaker>
            <line>Fairy king, attend, and mark:</line>
            <line>I do hear the morning lark.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OBERON</speaker>
            <line>Then, my queen, in silence sad,</line>
            <line>Trip we after the night's shade:</line>
            <line>We the globe can compass soon,</line>
            <line>Swifter than the wandering moon.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITANIA</speaker>
            <line>Come, my lord, and in our flight</line>
            <line>Tell me how it came this night</line>
            <line>That I sleeping here was found</line>
            <line>With these mortals on the ground.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Horns winded within</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Enter THESEUS, HIPPOLYTA, EGEUS, and train</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THESEUS</speaker>
            <line>Go, one of you, find out the forester;</line>
            <line>For now our observation is perform'd;</line>
            <line>And since we have the vaward of the day,</line>
            <line>My love shall hear the music of my hounds.</line>
            <line>Uncouple in the western valley; let them go:</line>
            <line>Dispatch, I say, and find the forester.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit an Attendant</stagedir>
            <line>We will, fair queen, up to the mountain's top,</line>
            <line>And mark the musical confusion</line>
            <line>Of hounds and echo in conjunction.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HIPPOLYTA</speaker>
            <line>I was with Hercules and Cadmus once,</line>
            <line>When in a wood of Crete they bay'd the bear</line>
            <line>With hounds of Sparta: never did I hear</line>
            <line>Such gallant chiding: for, besides the groves,</line>
            <line>The skies, the fountains, every region near</line>
            <line>Seem'd all one mutual cry: I never heard</line>
            <line>So musical a discord, such sweet thunder.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THESEUS</speaker>
            <line>My hounds are bred out of the Spartan kind,</line>
            <line>So flew'd, so sanded, and their heads are hung</line>
            <line>With ears that sweep away the morning dew;</line>
            <line>Crook-knee'd, and dew-lapp'd like Thessalian bulls;</line>
            <line>Slow in pursuit, but match'd in mouth like bells,</line>
            <line>Each under each. A cry more tuneable</line>
            <line>Was never holla'd to, nor cheer'd with horn,</line>
            <line>In Crete, in Sparta, nor in Thessaly:</line>
            <line>Judge when you hear. But, soft! what nymphs are these?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EGEUS</speaker>
            <line>My lord, this is my daughter here asleep;</line>
            <line>And this, Lysander; this Demetrius is;</line>
            <line>This Helena, old Nedar's Helena:</line>
            <line>I wonder of their being here together.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THESEUS</speaker>
            <line>No doubt they rose up early to observe</line>
            <line>The rite of May, and hearing our intent,</line>
            <line>Came here in grace our solemnity.</line>
            <line>But speak, Egeus; is not this the day</line>
            <line>That Hermia should give answer of her choice?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EGEUS</speaker>
            <line>It is, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THESEUS</speaker>
            <line>Go, bid the huntsmen wake them with their horns.</line>
            <stagedir>Horns and shout within. LYSANDER, DEMETRIUS,
HELENA, and HERMIA wake and start up</stagedir>
            <line>Good morrow, friends. Saint Valentine is past:</line>
            <line>Begin these wood-birds but to couple now?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LYSANDER</speaker>
            <line>Pardon, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THESEUS</speaker>
            <line>I pray you all, stand up.</line>
            <line>I know you two are rival enemies:</line>
            <line>How comes this gentle concord in the world,</line>
            <line>That hatred is so far from jealousy,</line>
            <line>To sleep by hate, and fear no enmity?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LYSANDER</speaker>
            <line>My lord, I shall reply amazedly,</line>
            <line>Half sleep, half waking: but as yet, I swear,</line>
            <line>I cannot truly say how I came here;</line>
            <line>But, as I think,--for truly would I speak,</line>
            <line>And now do I bethink me, so it is,--</line>
            <line>I came with Hermia hither: our intent</line>
            <line>Was to be gone from Athens, where we might,</line>
            <line>Without the peril of the Athenian law.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EGEUS</speaker>
            <line>Enough, enough, my lord; you have enough:</line>
            <line>I beg the law, the law, upon his head.</line>
            <line>They would have stolen away; they would, Demetrius,</line>
            <line>Thereby to have defeated you and me,</line>
            <line>You of your wife and me of my consent,</line>
            <line>Of my consent that she should be your wife.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>My lord, fair Helen told me of their stealth,</line>
            <line>Of this their purpose hither to this wood;</line>
            <line>And I in fury hither follow'd them,</line>
            <line>Fair Helena in fancy following me.</line>
            <line>But, my good lord, I wot not by what power,--</line>
            <line>But by some power it is,--my love to Hermia,</line>
            <line>Melted as the snow, seems to me now</line>
            <line>As the remembrance of an idle gaud</line>
            <line>Which in my childhood I did dote upon;</line>
            <line>And all the faith, the virtue of my heart,</line>
            <line>The object and the pleasure of mine eye,</line>
            <line>Is only Helena. To her, my lord,</line>
            <line>Was I betroth'd ere I saw Hermia:</line>
            <line>But, like in sickness, did I loathe this food;</line>
            <line>But, as in health, come to my natural taste,</line>
            <line>Now I do wish it, love it, long for it,</line>
            <line>And will for evermore be true to it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THESEUS</speaker>
            <line>Fair lovers, you are fortunately met:</line>
            <line>Of this discourse we more will hear anon.</line>
            <line>Egeus, I will overbear your will;</line>
            <line>For in the temple by and by with us</line>
            <line>These couples shall eternally be knit:</line>
            <line>And, for the morning now is something worn,</line>
            <line>Our purposed hunting shall be set aside.</line>
            <line>Away with us to Athens; three and three,</line>
            <line>We'll hold a feast in great solemnity.</line>
            <line>Come, Hippolyta.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt THESEUS, HIPPOLYTA, EGEUS, and train</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>These things seem small and undistinguishable,</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERMIA</speaker>
            <line>Methinks I see these things with parted eye,</line>
            <line>When every thing seems double.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>So methinks:</line>
            <line>And I have found Demetrius like a jewel,</line>
            <line>Mine own, and not mine own.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>Are you sure</line>
            <line>That we are awake? It seems to me</line>
            <line>That yet we sleep, we dream. Do not you think</line>
            <line>The duke was here, and bid us follow him?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERMIA</speaker>
            <line>Yea; and my father.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>And Hippolyta.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LYSANDER</speaker>
            <line>And he did bid us follow to the temple.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>Why, then, we are awake: let's follow him</line>
            <line>And by the way let us recount our dreams.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOTTOM</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Awaking</stagedir>  When my cue comes, call me, and I will</line>
            <line>answer: my next is, 'Most fair Pyramus.' Heigh-ho!</line>
            <line>Peter Quince! Flute, the bellows-mender! Snout,</line>
            <line>the tinker! Starveling! God's my life, stolen</line>
            <line>hence, and left me asleep! I have had a most rare</line>
            <line>vision. I have had a dream, past the wit of man to</line>
            <line>say what dream it was: man is but an ass, if he go</line>
            <line>about to expound this dream. Methought I was--there</line>
            <line>is no man can tell what. Methought I was,--and</line>
            <line>methought I had,--but man is but a patched fool, if</line>
            <line>he will offer to say what methought I had. The eye</line>
            <line>of man hath not heard, the ear of man hath not</line>
            <line>seen, man's hand is not able to taste, his tongue</line>
            <line>to conceive, nor his heart to report, what my dream</line>
            <line>was. I will get Peter Quince to write a ballad of</line>
            <line>this dream: it shall be called Bottom's Dream,</line>
            <line>because it hath no bottom; and I will sing it in the</line>
            <line>latter end of a play, before the duke:</line>
            <line>peradventure, to make it the more gracious, I shall</line>
            <line>sing it at her death.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  Athens. QUINCE'S house.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter QUINCE, FLUTE, SNOUT, and STARVELING</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUINCE</speaker>
            <line>Have you sent to Bottom's house? is he come home yet?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>STARVELING</speaker>
            <line>He cannot be heard of. Out of doubt he is</line>
            <line>transported.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLUTE</speaker>
            <line>If he come not, then the play is marred: it goes</line>
            <line>not forward, doth it?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUINCE</speaker>
            <line>It is not possible: you have not a man in all</line>
            <line>Athens able to discharge Pyramus but he.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLUTE</speaker>
            <line>No, he hath simply the best wit of any handicraft</line>
            <line>man in Athens.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUINCE</speaker>
            <line>Yea and the best person too; and he is a very</line>
            <line>paramour for a sweet voice.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLUTE</speaker>
            <line>You must say 'paragon:' a paramour is, God bless us,</line>
            <line>a thing of naught.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter SNUG</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SNUG</speaker>
            <line>Masters, the duke is coming from the temple, and</line>
            <line>there is two or three lords and ladies more married:</line>
            <line>if our sport had gone forward, we had all been made</line>
            <line>men.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLUTE</speaker>
            <line>O sweet bully Bottom! Thus hath he lost sixpence a</line>
            <line>day during his life; he could not have 'scaped</line>
            <line>sixpence a day: an the duke had not given him</line>
            <line>sixpence a day for playing Pyramus, I'll be hanged;</line>
            <line>he would have deserved it: sixpence a day in</line>
            <line>Pyramus, or nothing.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter BOTTOM</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOTTOM</speaker>
            <line>Where are these lads? where are these hearts?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUINCE</speaker>
            <line>Bottom! O most courageous day! O most happy hour!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOTTOM</speaker>
            <line>Masters, I am to discourse wonders: but ask me not</line>
            <line>what; for if I tell you, I am no true Athenian. I</line>
            <line>will tell you every thing, right as it fell out.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUINCE</speaker>
            <line>Let us hear, sweet Bottom.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOTTOM</speaker>
            <line>Not a word of me. All that I will tell you is, that</line>
            <line>the duke hath dined. Get your apparel together,</line>
            <line>good strings to your beards, new ribbons to your</line>
            <line>pumps; meet presently at the palace; every man look</line>
            <line>o'er his part; for the short and the long is, our</line>
            <line>play is preferred. In any case, let Thisby have</line>
            <line>clean linen; and let not him that plays the lion</line>
            <line>pair his nails, for they shall hang out for the</line>
            <line>lion's claws. And, most dear actors, eat no onions</line>
            <line>nor garlic, for we are to utter sweet breath; and I</line>
            <line>do not doubt but to hear them say, it is a sweet</line>
            <line>comedy. No more words: away! go, away!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>