<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net/doctypes/dita/shakespear/dtd/act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-5">
   <title>ACT V</title>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  Athens. The palace of THESEUS.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter THESEUS, HIPPOLYTA, PHILOSTRATE, Lords and
Attendants</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HIPPOLYTA</speaker>
            <line>'Tis strange my Theseus, that these</line>
            <line>lovers speak of.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THESEUS</speaker>
            <line>More strange than true: I never may believe</line>
            <line>These antique fables, nor these fairy toys.</line>
            <line>Lovers and madmen have such seething brains,</line>
            <line>Such shaping fantasies, that apprehend</line>
            <line>More than cool reason ever comprehends.</line>
            <line>The lunatic, the lover and the poet</line>
            <line>Are of imagination all compact:</line>
            <line>One sees more devils than vast hell can hold,</line>
            <line>That is, the madman: the lover, all as frantic,</line>
            <line>Sees Helen's beauty in a brow of Egypt:</line>
            <line>The poet's eye, in fine frenzy rolling,</line>
            <line>Doth glance from heaven to earth, from earth to heaven;</line>
            <line>And as imagination bodies forth</line>
            <line>The forms of things unknown, the poet's pen</line>
            <line>Turns them to shapes and gives to airy nothing</line>
            <line>A local habitation and a name.</line>
            <line>Such tricks hath strong imagination,</line>
            <line>That if it would but apprehend some joy,</line>
            <line>It comprehends some bringer of that joy;</line>
            <line>Or in the night, imagining some fear,</line>
            <line>How easy is a bush supposed a bear!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HIPPOLYTA</speaker>
            <line>But all the story of the night told over,</line>
            <line>And all their minds transfigured so together,</line>
            <line>More witnesseth than fancy's images</line>
            <line>And grows to something of great constancy;</line>
            <line>But, howsoever, strange and admirable.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THESEUS</speaker>
            <line>Here come the lovers, full of joy and mirth.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter LYSANDER, DEMETRIUS, HERMIA, and HELENA</stagedir>
            <line>Joy, gentle friends! joy and fresh days of love</line>
            <line>Accompany your hearts!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LYSANDER</speaker>
            <line>More than to us</line>
            <line>Wait in your royal walks, your board, your bed!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THESEUS</speaker>
            <line>Come now; what masques, what dances shall we have,</line>
            <line>To wear away this long age of three hours</line>
            <line>Between our after-supper and bed-time?</line>
            <line>Where is our usual manager of mirth?</line>
            <line>What revels are in hand? Is there no play,</line>
            <line>To ease the anguish of a torturing hour?</line>
            <line>Call Philostrate.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PHILOSTRATE</speaker>
            <line>Here, mighty Theseus.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THESEUS</speaker>
            <line>Say, what abridgement have you for this evening?</line>
            <line>What masque? what music? How shall we beguile</line>
            <line>The lazy time, if not with some delight?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PHILOSTRATE</speaker>
            <line>There is a brief how many sports are ripe:</line>
            <line>Make choice of which your highness will see first.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Giving a paper</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THESEUS</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>  'The battle with the Centaurs, to be sung</line>
            <line>By an Athenian eunuch to the harp.'</line>
            <line>We'll none of that: that have I told my love,</line>
            <line>In glory of my kinsman Hercules.</line>
            <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>
            <line>'The riot of the tipsy Bacchanals,</line>
            <line>Tearing the Thracian singer in their rage.'</line>
            <line>That is an old device; and it was play'd</line>
            <line>When I from Thebes came last a conqueror.</line>
            <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>
            <line>'The thrice three Muses mourning for the death</line>
            <line>Of Learning, late deceased in beggary.'</line>
            <line>That is some satire, keen and critical,</line>
            <line>Not sorting with a nuptial ceremony.</line>
            <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>
            <line>'A tedious brief scene of young Pyramus</line>
            <line>And his love Thisbe; very tragical mirth.'</line>
            <line>Merry and tragical! tedious and brief!</line>
            <line>That is, hot ice and wondrous strange snow.</line>
            <line>How shall we find the concord of this discord?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PHILOSTRATE</speaker>
            <line>A play there is, my lord, some ten words long,</line>
            <line>Which is as brief as I have known a play;</line>
            <line>But by ten words, my lord, it is too long,</line>
            <line>Which makes it tedious; for in all the play</line>
            <line>There is not one word apt, one player fitted:</line>
            <line>And tragical, my noble lord, it is;</line>
            <line>For Pyramus therein doth kill himself.</line>
            <line>Which, when I saw rehearsed, I must confess,</line>
            <line>Made mine eyes water; but more merry tears</line>
            <line>The passion of loud laughter never shed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THESEUS</speaker>
            <line>What are they that do play it?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PHILOSTRATE</speaker>
            <line>Hard-handed men that work in Athens here,</line>
            <line>Which never labour'd in their minds till now,</line>
            <line>And now have toil'd their unbreathed memories</line>
            <line>With this same play, against your nuptial.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THESEUS</speaker>
            <line>And we will hear it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PHILOSTRATE</speaker>
            <line>No, my noble lord;</line>
            <line>It is not for you: I have heard it over,</line>
            <line>And it is nothing, nothing in the world;</line>
            <line>Unless you can find sport in their intents,</line>
            <line>Extremely stretch'd and conn'd with cruel pain,</line>
            <line>To do you service.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THESEUS</speaker>
            <line>I will hear that play;</line>
            <line>For never anything can be amiss,</line>
            <line>When simpleness and duty tender it.</line>
            <line>Go, bring them in: and take your places, ladies.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit PHILOSTRATE</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HIPPOLYTA</speaker>
            <line>I love not to see wretchedness o'er charged</line>
            <line>And duty in his service perishing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THESEUS</speaker>
            <line>Why, gentle sweet, you shall see no such thing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HIPPOLYTA</speaker>
            <line>He says they can do nothing in this kind.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THESEUS</speaker>
            <line>The kinder we, to give them thanks for nothing.</line>
            <line>Our sport shall be to take what they mistake:</line>
            <line>And what poor duty cannot do, noble respect</line>
            <line>Takes it in might, not merit.</line>
            <line>Where I have come, great clerks have purposed</line>
            <line>To greet me with premeditated welcomes;</line>
            <line>Where I have seen them shiver and look pale,</line>
            <line>Make periods in the midst of sentences,</line>
            <line>Throttle their practised accent in their fears</line>
            <line>And in conclusion dumbly have broke off,</line>
            <line>Not paying me a welcome. Trust me, sweet,</line>
            <line>Out of this silence yet I pick'd a welcome;</line>
            <line>And in the modesty of fearful duty</line>
            <line>I read as much as from the rattling tongue</line>
            <line>Of saucy and audacious eloquence.</line>
            <line>Love, therefore, and tongue-tied simplicity</line>
            <line>In least speak most, to my capacity.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter PHILOSTRATE</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PHILOSTRATE</speaker>
            <line>So please your grace, the Prologue is address'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THESEUS</speaker>
            <line>Let him approach.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Flourish of trumpets</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Enter QUINCE for the Prologue</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Prologue</speaker>
            <line>If we offend, it is with our good will.</line>
            <line>That you should think, we come not to offend,</line>
            <line>But with good will. To show our simple skill,</line>
            <line>That is the true beginning of our end.</line>
            <line>Consider then we come but in despite.</line>
            <line>We do not come as minding to contest you,</line>
            <line>Our true intent is. All for your delight</line>
            <line>We are not here. That you should here repent you,</line>
            <line>The actors are at hand and by their show</line>
            <line>You shall know all that you are like to know.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THESEUS</speaker>
            <line>This fellow doth not stand upon points.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LYSANDER</speaker>
            <line>He hath rid his prologue like a rough colt; he knows</line>
            <line>not the stop. A good moral, my lord: it is not</line>
            <line>enough to speak, but to speak true.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HIPPOLYTA</speaker>
            <line>Indeed he hath played on his prologue like a child</line>
            <line>on a recorder; a sound, but not in government.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THESEUS</speaker>
            <line>His speech, was like a tangled chain; nothing</line>
            <line>impaired, but all disordered. Who is next?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter Pyramus and Thisbe, Wall, Moonshine, and Lion</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Prologue</speaker>
            <line>Gentles, perchance you wonder at this show;</line>
            <line>But wonder on, till truth make all things plain.</line>
            <line>This man is Pyramus, if you would know;</line>
            <line>This beauteous lady Thisby is certain.</line>
            <line>This man, with lime and rough-cast, doth present</line>
            <line>Wall, that vile Wall which did these lovers sunder;</line>
            <line>And through Wall's chink, poor souls, they are content</line>
            <line>To whisper. At the which let no man wonder.</line>
            <line>This man, with lanthorn, dog, and bush of thorn,</line>
            <line>Presenteth Moonshine; for, if you will know,</line>
            <line>By moonshine did these lovers think no scorn</line>
            <line>To meet at Ninus' tomb, there, there to woo.</line>
            <line>This grisly beast, which Lion hight by name,</line>
            <line>The trusty Thisby, coming first by night,</line>
            <line>Did scare away, or rather did affright;</line>
            <line>And, as she fled, her mantle she did fall,</line>
            <line>Which Lion vile with bloody mouth did stain.</line>
            <line>Anon comes Pyramus, sweet youth and tall,</line>
            <line>And finds his trusty Thisby's mantle slain:</line>
            <line>Whereat, with blade, with bloody blameful blade,</line>
            <line>He bravely broach'd is boiling bloody breast;</line>
            <line>And Thisby, tarrying in mulberry shade,</line>
            <line>His dagger drew, and died. For all the rest,</line>
            <line>Let Lion, Moonshine, Wall, and lovers twain</line>
            <line>At large discourse, while here they do remain.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt Prologue, Thisbe, Lion, and Moonshine</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THESEUS</speaker>
            <line>I wonder if the lion be to speak.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>No wonder, my lord: one lion may, when many asses do.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Wall</speaker>
            <line>In this same interlude it doth befall</line>
            <line>That I, one Snout by name, present a wall;</line>
            <line>And such a wall, as I would have you think,</line>
            <line>That had in it a crannied hole or chink,</line>
            <line>Through which the lovers, Pyramus and Thisby,</line>
            <line>Did whisper often very secretly.</line>
            <line>This loam, this rough-cast and this stone doth show</line>
            <line>That I am that same wall; the truth is so:</line>
            <line>And this the cranny is, right and sinister,</line>
            <line>Through which the fearful lovers are to whisper.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THESEUS</speaker>
            <line>Would you desire lime and hair to speak better?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>It is the wittiest partition that ever I heard</line>
            <line>discourse, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter Pyramus</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THESEUS</speaker>
            <line>Pyramus draws near the wall: silence!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Pyramus</speaker>
            <line>O grim-look'd night! O night with hue so black!</line>
            <line>O night, which ever art when day is not!</line>
            <line>O night, O night! alack, alack, alack,</line>
            <line>I fear my Thisby's promise is forgot!</line>
            <line>And thou, O wall, O sweet, O lovely wall,</line>
            <line>That stand'st between her father's ground and mine!</line>
            <line>Thou wall, O wall, O sweet and lovely wall,</line>
            <line>Show me thy chink, to blink through with mine eyne!</line>
            <stagedir>Wall holds up his fingers</stagedir>
            <line>Thanks, courteous wall: Jove shield thee well for this!</line>
            <line>But what see I? No Thisby do I see.</line>
            <line>O wicked wall, through whom I see no bliss!</line>
            <line>Cursed be thy stones for thus deceiving me!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THESEUS</speaker>
            <line>The wall, methinks, being sensible, should curse again.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Pyramus</speaker>
            <line>No, in truth, sir, he should not. 'Deceiving me'</line>
            <line>is Thisby's cue: she is to enter now, and I am to</line>
            <line>spy her through the wall. You shall see, it will</line>
            <line>fall pat as I told you. Yonder she comes.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter Thisbe</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Thisbe</speaker>
            <line>O wall, full often hast thou heard my moans,</line>
            <line>For parting my fair Pyramus and me!</line>
            <line>My cherry lips have often kiss'd thy stones,</line>
            <line>Thy stones with lime and hair knit up in thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Pyramus</speaker>
            <line>I see a voice: now will I to the chink,</line>
            <line>To spy an I can hear my Thisby's face. Thisby!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Thisbe</speaker>
            <line>My love thou art, my love I think.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Pyramus</speaker>
            <line>Think what thou wilt, I am thy lover's grace;</line>
            <line>And, like Limander, am I trusty still.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Thisbe</speaker>
            <line>And I like Helen, till the Fates me kill.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Pyramus</speaker>
            <line>Not Shafalus to Procrus was so true.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Thisbe</speaker>
            <line>As Shafalus to Procrus, I to you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Pyramus</speaker>
            <line>O kiss me through the hole of this vile wall!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Thisbe</speaker>
            <line>I kiss the wall's hole, not your lips at all.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Pyramus</speaker>
            <line>Wilt thou at Ninny's tomb meet me straightway?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Thisbe</speaker>
            <line>'Tide life, 'tide death, I come without delay.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt Pyramus and Thisbe</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Wall</speaker>
            <line>Thus have I, Wall, my part discharged so;</line>
            <line>And, being done, thus Wall away doth go.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THESEUS</speaker>
            <line>Now is the mural down between the two neighbours.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>No remedy, my lord, when walls are so wilful to hear</line>
            <line>without warning.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HIPPOLYTA</speaker>
            <line>This is the silliest stuff that ever I heard.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THESEUS</speaker>
            <line>The best in this kind are but shadows; and the worst</line>
            <line>are no worse, if imagination amend them.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HIPPOLYTA</speaker>
            <line>It must be your imagination then, and not theirs.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THESEUS</speaker>
            <line>If we imagine no worse of them than they of</line>
            <line>themselves, they may pass for excellent men. Here</line>
            <line>come two noble beasts in, a man and a lion.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter Lion and Moonshine</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lion</speaker>
            <line>You, ladies, you, whose gentle hearts do fear</line>
            <line>The smallest monstrous mouse that creeps on floor,</line>
            <line>May now perchance both quake and tremble here,</line>
            <line>When lion rough in wildest rage doth roar.</line>
            <line>Then know that I, one Snug the joiner, am</line>
            <line>A lion-fell, nor else no lion's dam;</line>
            <line>For, if I should as lion come in strife</line>
            <line>Into this place, 'twere pity on my life.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THESEUS</speaker>
            <line>A very gentle beast, of a good conscience.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>The very best at a beast, my lord, that e'er I saw.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LYSANDER</speaker>
            <line>This lion is a very fox for his valour.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THESEUS</speaker>
            <line>True; and a goose for his discretion.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>Not so, my lord; for his valour cannot carry his</line>
            <line>discretion; and the fox carries the goose.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THESEUS</speaker>
            <line>His discretion, I am sure, cannot carry his valour;</line>
            <line>for the goose carries not the fox. It is well:</line>
            <line>leave it to his discretion, and let us listen to the moon.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Moonshine</speaker>
            <line>This lanthorn doth the horned moon present;--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>He should have worn the horns on his head.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THESEUS</speaker>
            <line>He is no crescent, and his horns are</line>
            <line>invisible within the circumference.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Moonshine</speaker>
            <line>This lanthorn doth the horned moon present;</line>
            <line>Myself the man i' the moon do seem to be.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THESEUS</speaker>
            <line>This is the greatest error of all the rest: the man</line>
            <line>should be put into the lanthorn. How is it else the</line>
            <line>man i' the moon?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>He dares not come there for the candle; for, you</line>
            <line>see, it is already in snuff.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HIPPOLYTA</speaker>
            <line>I am aweary of this moon: would he would change!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THESEUS</speaker>
            <line>It appears, by his small light of discretion, that</line>
            <line>he is in the wane; but yet, in courtesy, in all</line>
            <line>reason, we must stay the time.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LYSANDER</speaker>
            <line>Proceed, Moon.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Moonshine</speaker>
            <line>All that I have to say, is, to tell you that the</line>
            <line>lanthorn is the moon; I, the man in the moon; this</line>
            <line>thorn-bush, my thorn-bush; and this dog, my dog.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>Why, all these should be in the lanthorn; for all</line>
            <line>these are in the moon. But, silence! here comes Thisbe.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter Thisbe</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Thisbe</speaker>
            <line>This is old Ninny's tomb. Where is my love?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lion</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Roaring</stagedir>  Oh--</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Thisbe runs off</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>Well roared, Lion.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THESEUS</speaker>
            <line>Well run, Thisbe.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HIPPOLYTA</speaker>
            <line>Well shone, Moon. Truly, the moon shines with a</line>
            <line>good grace.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>The Lion shakes Thisbe's mantle, and exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THESEUS</speaker>
            <line>Well moused, Lion.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LYSANDER</speaker>
            <line>And so the lion vanished.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>And then came Pyramus.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter Pyramus</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Pyramus</speaker>
            <line>Sweet Moon, I thank thee for thy sunny beams;</line>
            <line>I thank thee, Moon, for shining now so bright;</line>
            <line>For, by thy gracious, golden, glittering gleams,</line>
            <line>I trust to take of truest Thisby sight.</line>
            <line>But stay, O spite!</line>
            <line>But mark, poor knight,</line>
            <line>What dreadful dole is here!</line>
            <line>Eyes, do you see?</line>
            <line>How can it be?</line>
            <line>O dainty duck! O dear!</line>
            <line>Thy mantle good,</line>
            <line>What, stain'd with blood!</line>
            <line>Approach, ye Furies fell!</line>
            <line>O Fates, come, come,</line>
            <line>Cut thread and thrum;</line>
            <line>Quail, crush, conclude, and quell!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THESEUS</speaker>
            <line>This passion, and the death of a dear friend, would</line>
            <line>go near to make a man look sad.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HIPPOLYTA</speaker>
            <line>Beshrew my heart, but I pity the man.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Pyramus</speaker>
            <line>O wherefore, Nature, didst thou lions frame?</line>
            <line>Since lion vile hath here deflower'd my dear:</line>
            <line>Which is--no, no--which was the fairest dame</line>
            <line>That lived, that loved, that liked, that look'd</line>
            <line>with cheer.</line>
            <line>Come, tears, confound;</line>
            <line>Out, sword, and wound</line>
            <line>The pap of Pyramus;</line>
            <line>Ay, that left pap,</line>
            <line>Where heart doth hop:</line>
            <stagedir>Stabs himself</stagedir>
            <line>Thus die I, thus, thus, thus.</line>
            <line>Now am I dead,</line>
            <line>Now am I fled;</line>
            <line>My soul is in the sky:</line>
            <line>Tongue, lose thy light;</line>
            <line>Moon take thy flight:</line>
            <stagedir>Exit Moonshine</stagedir>
            <line>Now die, die, die, die, die.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Dies</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>No die, but an ace, for him; for he is but one.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LYSANDER</speaker>
            <line>Less than an ace, man; for he is dead; he is nothing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THESEUS</speaker>
            <line>With the help of a surgeon he might yet recover, and</line>
            <line>prove an ass.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HIPPOLYTA</speaker>
            <line>How chance Moonshine is gone before Thisbe comes</line>
            <line>back and finds her lover?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THESEUS</speaker>
            <line>She will find him by starlight. Here she comes; and</line>
            <line>her passion ends the play.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter Thisbe</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HIPPOLYTA</speaker>
            <line>Methinks she should not use a long one for such a</line>
            <line>Pyramus: I hope she will be brief.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>A mote will turn the balance, which Pyramus, which</line>
            <line>Thisbe, is the better; he for a man, God warrant us;</line>
            <line>she for a woman, God bless us.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LYSANDER</speaker>
            <line>She hath spied him already with those sweet eyes.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>And thus she means, videlicet:--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Thisbe</speaker>
            <line>Asleep, my love?</line>
            <line>What, dead, my dove?</line>
            <line>O Pyramus, arise!</line>
            <line>Speak, speak. Quite dumb?</line>
            <line>Dead, dead? A tomb</line>
            <line>Must cover thy sweet eyes.</line>
            <line>These My lips,</line>
            <line>This cherry nose,</line>
            <line>These yellow cowslip cheeks,</line>
            <line>Are gone, are gone:</line>
            <line>Lovers, make moan:</line>
            <line>His eyes were green as leeks.</line>
            <line>O Sisters Three,</line>
            <line>Come, come to me,</line>
            <line>With hands as pale as milk;</line>
            <line>Lay them in gore,</line>
            <line>Since you have shore</line>
            <line>With shears his thread of silk.</line>
            <line>Tongue, not a word:</line>
            <line>Come, trusty sword;</line>
            <line>Come, blade, my breast imbrue:</line>
            <stagedir>Stabs herself</stagedir>
            <line>And, farewell, friends;</line>
            <line>Thus Thisby ends:</line>
            <line>Adieu, adieu, adieu.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Dies</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THESEUS</speaker>
            <line>Moonshine and Lion are left to bury the dead.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEMETRIUS</speaker>
            <line>Ay, and Wall too.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOTTOM</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Starting up</stagedir>  No assure you; the wall is down that</line>
            <line>parted their fathers. Will it please you to see the</line>
            <line>epilogue, or to hear a Bergomask dance between two</line>
            <line>of our company?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THESEUS</speaker>
            <line>No epilogue, I pray you; for your play needs no</line>
            <line>excuse. Never excuse; for when the players are all</line>
            <line>dead, there needs none to be blamed. Marry, if he</line>
            <line>that writ it had played Pyramus and hanged himself</line>
            <line>in Thisbe's garter, it would have been a fine</line>
            <line>tragedy: and so it is, truly; and very notably</line>
            <line>discharged. But come, your Bergomask: let your</line>
            <line>epilogue alone.</line>
            <stagedir>A dance</stagedir>
            <line>The iron tongue of midnight hath told twelve:</line>
            <line>Lovers, to bed; 'tis almost fairy time.</line>
            <line>I fear we shall out-sleep the coming morn</line>
            <line>As much as we this night have overwatch'd.</line>
            <line>This palpable-gross play hath well beguiled</line>
            <line>The heavy gait of night. Sweet friends, to bed.</line>
            <line>A fortnight hold we this solemnity,</line>
            <line>In nightly revels and new jollity.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Enter PUCK</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PUCK</speaker>
            <line>Now the hungry lion roars,</line>
            <line>And the wolf behowls the moon;</line>
            <line>Whilst the heavy ploughman snores,</line>
            <line>All with weary task fordone.</line>
            <line>Now the wasted brands do glow,</line>
            <line>Whilst the screech-owl, screeching loud,</line>
            <line>Puts the wretch that lies in woe</line>
            <line>In remembrance of a shroud.</line>
            <line>Now it is the time of night</line>
            <line>That the graves all gaping wide,</line>
            <line>Every one lets forth his sprite,</line>
            <line>In the church-way paths to glide:</line>
            <line>And we fairies, that do run</line>
            <line>By the triple Hecate's team,</line>
            <line>From the presence of the sun,</line>
            <line>Following darkness like a dream,</line>
            <line>Now are frolic: not a mouse</line>
            <line>Shall disturb this hallow'd house:</line>
            <line>I am sent with broom before,</line>
            <line>To sweep the dust behind the door.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter OBERON and TITANIA with their train</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OBERON</speaker>
            <line>Through the house give gathering light,</line>
            <line>By the dead and drowsy fire:</line>
            <line>Every elf and fairy sprite</line>
            <line>Hop as light as bird from brier;</line>
            <line>And this ditty, after me,</line>
            <line>Sing, and dance it trippingly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TITANIA</speaker>
            <line>First, rehearse your song by rote</line>
            <line>To each word a warbling note:</line>
            <line>Hand in hand, with fairy grace,</line>
            <line>Will we sing, and bless this place.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Song and dance</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OBERON</speaker>
            <line>Now, until the break of day,</line>
            <line>Through this house each fairy stray.</line>
            <line>To the best bride-bed will we,</line>
            <line>Which by us shall blessed be;</line>
            <line>And the issue there create</line>
            <line>Ever shall be fortunate.</line>
            <line>So shall all the couples three</line>
            <line>Ever true in loving be;</line>
            <line>And the blots of Nature's hand</line>
            <line>Shall not in their issue stand;</line>
            <line>Never mole, hare lip, nor scar,</line>
            <line>Nor mark prodigious, such as are</line>
            <line>Despised in nativity,</line>
            <line>Shall upon their children be.</line>
            <line>With this field-dew consecrate,</line>
            <line>Every fairy take his gait;</line>
            <line>And each several chamber bless,</line>
            <line>Through this palace, with sweet peace;</line>
            <line>And the owner of it blest</line>
            <line>Ever shall in safety rest.</line>
            <line>Trip away; make no stay;</line>
            <line>Meet me all by break of day.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt OBERON, TITANIA, and train</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PUCK</speaker>
            <line>If we shadows have offended,</line>
            <line>Think but this, and all is mended,</line>
            <line>That you have but slumber'd here</line>
            <line>While these visions did appear.</line>
            <line>And this weak and idle theme,</line>
            <line>No more yielding but a dream,</line>
            <line>Gentles, do not reprehend:</line>
            <line>if you pardon, we will mend:</line>
            <line>And, as I am an honest Puck,</line>
            <line>If we have unearned luck</line>
            <line>Now to 'scape the serpent's tongue,</line>
            <line>We will make amends ere long;</line>
            <line>Else the Puck a liar call;</line>
            <line>So, good night unto you all.</line>
            <line>Give me your hands, if we be friends,</line>
            <line>And Robin shall restore amends.</line>
         </speech>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>