<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net/doctypes/dita/shakespear/dtd/act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-4">
   <title>ACT IV</title>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  Before the Tower.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter, on one side, QUEEN ELIZABETH, DUCHESS OF
YORK, and DORSET; on the other, ANNE, Duchess of
Gloucester, leading Lady Margaret Plantagenet,
CLARENCE's young Daughter</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Who meets us here?  my niece Plantagenet</line>
            <line>Led in the hand of her kind aunt of Gloucester?</line>
            <line>Now, for my life, she's wandering to the Tower,</line>
            <line>On pure heart's love to greet the tender princes.</line>
            <line>Daughter, well met.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY ANNE</speaker>
            <line>God give your graces both</line>
            <line>A happy and a joyful time of day!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>As much to you, good sister! Whither away?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY ANNE</speaker>
            <line>No farther than the Tower; and, as I guess,</line>
            <line>Upon the like devotion as yourselves,</line>
            <line>To gratulate the gentle princes there.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>Kind sister, thanks: we'll enter all together.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter BRAKENBURY</stagedir>
            <line>And, in good time, here the lieutenant comes.</line>
            <line>Master lieutenant, pray you, by your leave,</line>
            <line>How doth the prince, and my young son of York?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRAKENBURY</speaker>
            <line>Right well, dear madam. By your patience,</line>
            <line>I may not suffer you to visit them;</line>
            <line>The king hath straitly charged the contrary.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>The king! why, who's that?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRAKENBURY</speaker>
            <line>I cry you mercy: I mean the lord protector.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>The Lord protect him from that kingly title!</line>
            <line>Hath he set bounds betwixt their love and me?</line>
            <line>I am their mother; who should keep me from them?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>I am their fathers mother; I will see them.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY ANNE</speaker>
            <line>Their aunt I am in law, in love their mother:</line>
            <line>Then bring me to their sights; I'll bear thy blame</line>
            <line>And take thy office from thee, on my peril.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRAKENBURY</speaker>
            <line>No, madam, no; I may not leave it so:</line>
            <line>I am bound by oath, and therefore pardon me.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Enter LORD STANLEY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD STANLEY</speaker>
            <line>Let me but meet you, ladies, one hour hence,</line>
            <line>And I'll salute your grace of York as mother,</line>
            <line>And reverend looker on, of two fair queens.</line>
            <stagedir>To LADY ANNE</stagedir>
            <line>Come, madam, you must straight to Westminster,</line>
            <line>There to be crowned Richard's royal queen.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>O, cut my lace in sunder, that my pent heart</line>
            <line>May have some scope to beat, or else I swoon</line>
            <line>With this dead-killing news!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY ANNE</speaker>
            <line>Despiteful tidings! O unpleasing news!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DORSET</speaker>
            <line>Be of good cheer: mother, how fares your grace?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>O Dorset, speak not to me, get thee hence!</line>
            <line>Death and destruction dog thee at the heels;</line>
            <line>Thy mother's name is ominous to children.</line>
            <line>If thou wilt outstrip death, go cross the seas,</line>
            <line>And live with Richmond, from the reach of hell</line>
            <line>Go, hie thee, hie thee from this slaughter-house,</line>
            <line>Lest thou increase the number of the dead;</line>
            <line>And make me die the thrall of Margaret's curse,</line>
            <line>Nor mother, wife, nor England's counted queen.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD STANLEY</speaker>
            <line>Full of wise care is this your counsel, madam.</line>
            <line>Take all the swift advantage of the hours;</line>
            <line>You shall have letters from me to my son</line>
            <line>To meet you on the way, and welcome you.</line>
            <line>Be not ta'en tardy by unwise delay.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>O ill-dispersing wind of misery!</line>
            <line>O my accursed womb, the bed of death!</line>
            <line>A cockatrice hast thou hatch'd to the world,</line>
            <line>Whose unavoided eye is murderous.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD STANLEY</speaker>
            <line>Come, madam, come; I in all haste was sent.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY ANNE</speaker>
            <line>And I in all unwillingness will go.</line>
            <line>I would to God that the inclusive verge</line>
            <line>Of golden metal that must round my brow</line>
            <line>Were red-hot steel, to sear me to the brain!</line>
            <line>Anointed let me be with deadly venom,</line>
            <line>And die, ere men can say, God save the queen!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>Go, go, poor soul, I envy not thy glory</line>
            <line>To feed my humour, wish thyself no harm.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY ANNE</speaker>
            <line>No! why?  When he that is my husband now</line>
            <line>Came to me, as I follow'd Henry's corse,</line>
            <line>When scarce the blood was well wash'd from his hands</line>
            <line>Which issued from my other angel husband</line>
            <line>And that dead saint which then I weeping follow'd;</line>
            <line>O, when, I say, I look'd on Richard's face,</line>
            <line>This was my wish: 'Be thou,' quoth I, ' accursed,</line>
            <line>For making me, so young, so old a widow!</line>
            <line>And, when thou wed'st, let sorrow haunt thy bed;</line>
            <line>And be thy wife--if any be so mad--</line>
            <line>As miserable by the life of thee</line>
            <line>As thou hast made me by my dear lord's death!</line>
            <line>Lo, ere I can repeat this curse again,</line>
            <line>Even in so short a space, my woman's heart</line>
            <line>Grossly grew captive to his honey words</line>
            <line>And proved the subject of my own soul's curse,</line>
            <line>Which ever since hath kept my eyes from rest;</line>
            <line>For never yet one hour in his bed</line>
            <line>Have I enjoy'd the golden dew of sleep,</line>
            <line>But have been waked by his timorous dreams.</line>
            <line>Besides, he hates me for my father Warwick;</line>
            <line>And will, no doubt, shortly be rid of me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>Poor heart, adieu! I pity thy complaining.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY ANNE</speaker>
            <line>No more than from my soul I mourn for yours.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>Farewell, thou woful welcomer of glory!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY ANNE</speaker>
            <line>Adieu, poor soul, that takest thy leave of it!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>To DORSET</stagedir>
            </line>
            <line>Go thou to Richmond, and good fortune guide thee!</line>
            <stagedir>To LADY ANNE</stagedir>
            <line>Go thou to Richard, and good angels guard thee!</line>
            <stagedir>To QUEEN ELIZABETH</stagedir>
            <line>Go thou to sanctuary, and good thoughts possess thee!</line>
            <line>I to my grave, where peace and rest lie with me!</line>
            <line>Eighty odd years of sorrow have I seen,</line>
            <line>And each hour's joy wrecked with a week of teen.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>Stay, yet look back with me unto the Tower.</line>
            <line>Pity, you ancient stones, those tender babes</line>
            <line>Whom envy hath immured within your walls!</line>
            <line>Rough cradle for such little pretty ones!</line>
            <line>Rude ragged nurse, old sullen playfellow</line>
            <line>For tender princes, use my babies well!</line>
            <line>So foolish sorrow bids your stones farewell.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  London. The palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Sennet. Enter KING RICHARD III, in pomp, crowned;
BUCKINGHAM, CATESBY, a page, and others</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Stand all apart Cousin of Buckingham!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>My gracious sovereign?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Give me thy hand.</line>
            <stagedir>Here he ascendeth his throne</stagedir>
            <line>Thus high, by thy advice</line>
            <line>And thy assistance, is King Richard seated;</line>
            <line>But shall we wear these honours for a day?</line>
            <line>Or shall they last, and we rejoice in them?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Still live they and for ever may they last!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>O Buckingham, now do I play the touch,</line>
            <line>To try if thou be current gold indeed</line>
            <line>Young Edward lives: think now what I would say.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Say on, my loving lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Why, Buckingham, I say, I would be king,</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Why, so you are, my thrice renowned liege.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Ha! am I king? 'tis so: but Edward lives.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>True, noble prince.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>O bitter consequence,</line>
            <line>That Edward still should live! 'True, noble prince!'</line>
            <line>Cousin, thou wert not wont to be so dull:</line>
            <line>Shall I be plain? I wish the bastards dead;</line>
            <line>And I would have it suddenly perform'd.</line>
            <line>What sayest thou? speak suddenly; be brief.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Your grace may do your pleasure.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Tut, tut, thou art all ice, thy kindness freezeth:</line>
            <line>Say, have I thy consent that they shall die?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Give me some breath, some little pause, my lord</line>
            <line>Before I positively herein:</line>
            <line>I will resolve your grace immediately.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CATESBY</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside to a stander by</stagedir>
            </line>
            <line>The king is angry: see, he bites the lip.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>I will converse with iron-witted fools</line>
            <line>And unrespective boys: none are for me</line>
            <line>That look into me with considerate eyes:</line>
            <line>High-reaching Buckingham grows circumspect.</line>
            <line>Boy!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <line>My lord?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Know'st thou not any whom corrupting gold</line>
            <line>Would tempt unto a close exploit of death?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <line>My lord, I know a discontented gentleman,</line>
            <line>Whose humble means match not his haughty mind:</line>
            <line>Gold were as good as twenty orators,</line>
            <line>And will, no doubt, tempt him to any thing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>What is his name?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <line>His name, my lord, is Tyrrel.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>I partly know the man: go, call him hither.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit Page</stagedir>
            <line>The deep-revolving witty Buckingham</line>
            <line>No more shall be the neighbour to my counsel:</line>
            <line>Hath he so long held out with me untired,</line>
            <line>And stops he now for breath?</line>
            <stagedir>Enter STANLEY</stagedir>
            <line>How now! what news with you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>STANLEY</speaker>
            <line>My lord, I hear the Marquis Dorset's fled</line>
            <line>To Richmond, in those parts beyond the sea</line>
            <line>Where he abides.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Stands apart</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Catesby!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CATESBY</speaker>
            <line>My lord?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Rumour it abroad</line>
            <line>That Anne, my wife, is sick and like to die:</line>
            <line>I will take order for her keeping close.</line>
            <line>Inquire me out some mean-born gentleman,</line>
            <line>Whom I will marry straight to Clarence' daughter:</line>
            <line>The boy is foolish, and I fear not him.</line>
            <line>Look, how thou dream'st! I say again, give out</line>
            <line>That Anne my wife is sick and like to die:</line>
            <line>About it; for it stands me much upon,</line>
            <line>To stop all hopes whose growth may damage me.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit CATESBY</stagedir>
            <line>I must be married to my brother's daughter,</line>
            <line>Or else my kingdom stands on brittle glass.</line>
            <line>Murder her brothers, and then marry her!</line>
            <line>Uncertain way of gain! But I am in</line>
            <line>So far in blood that sin will pluck on sin:</line>
            <line>Tear-falling pity dwells not in this eye.</line>
            <stagedir>Re-enter Page, with TYRREL</stagedir>
            <line>Is thy name Tyrrel?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TYRREL</speaker>
            <line>James Tyrrel, and your most obedient subject.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Art thou, indeed?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TYRREL</speaker>
            <line>Prove me, my gracious sovereign.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Darest thou resolve to kill a friend of mine?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TYRREL</speaker>
            <line>Ay, my lord;</line>
            <line>But I had rather kill two enemies.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Why, there thou hast it: two deep enemies,</line>
            <line>Foes to my rest and my sweet sleep's disturbers</line>
            <line>Are they that I would have thee deal upon:</line>
            <line>Tyrrel, I mean those bastards in the Tower.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TYRREL</speaker>
            <line>Let me have open means to come to them,</line>
            <line>And soon I'll rid you from the fear of them.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Thou sing'st sweet music. Hark, come hither, Tyrrel</line>
            <line>Go, by this token: rise, and lend thine ear:</line>
            <stagedir>Whispers</stagedir>
            <line>There is no more but so: say it is done,</line>
            <line>And I will love thee, and prefer thee too.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TYRREL</speaker>
            <line>'Tis done, my gracious lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Shall we hear from thee, Tyrrel, ere we sleep?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TYRREL</speaker>
            <line>Ye shall, my Lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Re-enter BUCKINGHAM</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>My Lord, I have consider'd in my mind</line>
            <line>The late demand that you did sound me in.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Well, let that pass. Dorset is fled to Richmond.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>I hear that news, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Stanley, he is your wife's son well, look to it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>My lord, I claim your gift, my due by promise,</line>
            <line>For which your honour and your faith is pawn'd;</line>
            <line>The earldom of Hereford and the moveables</line>
            <line>The which you promised I should possess.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Stanley, look to your wife; if she convey</line>
            <line>Letters to Richmond, you shall answer it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>What says your highness to my just demand?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>As I remember, Henry the Sixth</line>
            <line>Did prophesy that Richmond should be king,</line>
            <line>When Richmond was a little peevish boy.</line>
            <line>A king, perhaps, perhaps,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>My lord!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>How chance the prophet could not at that time</line>
            <line>Have told me, I being by, that I should kill him?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>My lord, your promise for the earldom,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Richmond! When last I was at Exeter,</line>
            <line>The mayor in courtesy show'd me the castle,</line>
            <line>And call'd it Rougemont: at which name I started,</line>
            <line>Because a bard of Ireland told me once</line>
            <line>I should not live long after I saw Richmond.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>My Lord!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Ay, what's o'clock?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>I am thus bold to put your grace in mind</line>
            <line>Of what you promised me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Well, but what's o'clock?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Upon the stroke of ten.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Well, let it strike.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Why let it strike?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Because that, like a Jack, thou keep'st the stroke</line>
            <line>Betwixt thy begging and my meditation.</line>
            <line>I am not in the giving vein to-day.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Why, then resolve me whether you will or no.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Tut, tut,</line>
            <line>Thou troublest me; am not in the vein.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt all but BUCKINGHAM</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Is it even so? rewards he my true service</line>
            <line>With such deep contempt made I him king for this?</line>
            <line>O, let me think on Hastings, and be gone</line>
            <line>To Brecknock, while my fearful head is on!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  The same.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter TYRREL</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TYRREL</speaker>
            <line>The tyrannous and bloody deed is done.</line>
            <line>The most arch of piteous massacre</line>
            <line>That ever yet this land was guilty of.</line>
            <line>Dighton and Forrest, whom I did suborn</line>
            <line>To do this ruthless piece of butchery,</line>
            <line>Although they were flesh'd villains, bloody dogs,</line>
            <line>Melting with tenderness and kind compassion</line>
            <line>Wept like two children in their deaths' sad stories.</line>
            <line>'Lo, thus' quoth Dighton, 'lay those tender babes:'</line>
            <line>'Thus, thus,' quoth Forrest, 'girdling one another</line>
            <line>Within their innocent alabaster arms:</line>
            <line>Their lips were four red roses on a stalk,</line>
            <line>Which in their summer beauty kiss'd each other.</line>
            <line>A book of prayers on their pillow lay;</line>
            <line>Which once,' quoth Forrest, 'almost changed my mind;</line>
            <line>But O! the devil'--there the villain stopp'd</line>
            <line>Whilst Dighton thus told on: 'We smothered</line>
            <line>The most replenished sweet work of nature,</line>
            <line>That from the prime creation e'er she framed.'</line>
            <line>Thus both are gone with conscience and remorse;</line>
            <line>They could not speak; and so I left them both,</line>
            <line>To bring this tidings to the bloody king.</line>
            <line>And here he comes.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter KING RICHARD III</stagedir>
            <line>All hail, my sovereign liege!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Kind Tyrrel, am I happy in thy news?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TYRREL</speaker>
            <line>If to have done the thing you gave in charge</line>
            <line>Beget your happiness, be happy then,</line>
            <line>For it is done, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>But didst thou see them dead?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TYRREL</speaker>
            <line>I did, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>And buried, gentle Tyrrel?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TYRREL</speaker>
            <line>The chaplain of the Tower hath buried them;</line>
            <line>But how or in what place I do not know.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Come to me, Tyrrel, soon at after supper,</line>
            <line>And thou shalt tell the process of their death.</line>
            <line>Meantime, but think how I may do thee good,</line>
            <line>And be inheritor of thy desire.</line>
            <line>Farewell till soon.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit TYRREL</stagedir>
            <line>The son of Clarence have I pent up close;</line>
            <line>His daughter meanly have I match'd in marriage;</line>
            <line>The sons of Edward sleep in Abraham's bosom,</line>
            <line>And Anne my wife hath bid the world good night.</line>
            <line>Now, for I know the Breton Richmond aims</line>
            <line>At young Elizabeth, my brother's daughter,</line>
            <line>And, by that knot, looks proudly o'er the crown,</line>
            <line>To her I go, a jolly thriving wooer.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter CATESBY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CATESBY</speaker>
            <line>My lord!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Good news or bad, that thou comest in so bluntly?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CATESBY</speaker>
            <line>Bad news, my lord: Ely is fled to Richmond;</line>
            <line>And Buckingham, back'd with the hardy Welshmen,</line>
            <line>Is in the field, and still his power increaseth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Ely with Richmond troubles me more near</line>
            <line>Than Buckingham and his rash-levied army.</line>
            <line>Come, I have heard that fearful commenting</line>
            <line>Is leaden servitor to dull delay;</line>
            <line>Delay leads impotent and snail-paced beggary</line>
            <line>Then fiery expedition be my wing,</line>
            <line>Jove's Mercury, and herald for a king!</line>
            <line>Come, muster men: my counsel is my shield;</line>
            <line>We must be brief when traitors brave the field.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-4">
      <title>SCENE IV.  Before the palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter QUEEN MARGARET</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>So, now prosperity begins to mellow</line>
            <line>And drop into the rotten mouth of death.</line>
            <line>Here in these confines slily have I lurk'd,</line>
            <line>To watch the waning of mine adversaries.</line>
            <line>A dire induction am I witness to,</line>
            <line>And will to France, hoping the consequence</line>
            <line>Will prove as bitter, black, and tragical.</line>
            <line>Withdraw thee, wretched Margaret: who comes here?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter QUEEN ELIZABETH and the DUCHESS OF YORK</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>Ah, my young princes! ah, my tender babes!</line>
            <line>My unblown flowers, new-appearing sweets!</line>
            <line>If yet your gentle souls fly in the air</line>
            <line>And be not fix'd in doom perpetual,</line>
            <line>Hover about me with your airy wings</line>
            <line>And hear your mother's lamentation!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Hover about her; say, that right for right</line>
            <line>Hath dimm'd your infant morn to aged night.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>So many miseries have crazed my voice,</line>
            <line>That my woe-wearied tongue is mute and dumb,</line>
            <line>Edward Plantagenet, why art thou dead?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Plantagenet doth quit Plantagenet.</line>
            <line>Edward for Edward pays a dying debt.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>Wilt thou, O God, fly from such gentle lambs,</line>
            <line>And throw them in the entrails of the wolf?</line>
            <line>When didst thou sleep when such a deed was done?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>When holy Harry died, and my sweet son.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Blind sight, dead life, poor mortal living ghost,</line>
            <line>Woe's scene, world's shame, grave's due by life usurp'd,</line>
            <line>Brief abstract and record of tedious days,</line>
            <line>Rest thy unrest on England's lawful earth,</line>
            <stagedir>Sitting down</stagedir>
            <line>Unlawfully made drunk with innocents' blood!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>O, that thou wouldst as well afford a grave</line>
            <line>As thou canst yield a melancholy seat!</line>
            <line>Then would I hide my bones, not rest them here.</line>
            <line>O, who hath any cause to mourn but I?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Sitting down by her</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>If ancient sorrow be most reverend,</line>
            <line>Give mine the benefit of seniory,</line>
            <line>And let my woes frown on the upper hand.</line>
            <line>If sorrow can admit society,</line>
            <stagedir>Sitting down with them</stagedir>
            <line>Tell o'er your woes again by viewing mine:</line>
            <line>I had an Edward, till a Richard kill'd him;</line>
            <line>I had a Harry, till a Richard kill'd him:</line>
            <line>Thou hadst an Edward, till a Richard kill'd him;</line>
            <line>Thou hadst a Richard, till a Richard killed him;</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>I had a Richard too, and thou didst kill him;</line>
            <line>I had a Rutland too, thou holp'st to kill him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Thou hadst a Clarence too, and Richard kill'd him.</line>
            <line>From forth the kennel of thy womb hath crept</line>
            <line>A hell-hound that doth hunt us all to death:</line>
            <line>That dog, that had his teeth before his eyes,</line>
            <line>To worry lambs and lap their gentle blood,</line>
            <line>That foul defacer of God's handiwork,</line>
            <line>That excellent grand tyrant of the earth,</line>
            <line>That reigns in galled eyes of weeping souls,</line>
            <line>Thy womb let loose, to chase us to our graves.</line>
            <line>O upright, just, and true-disposing God,</line>
            <line>How do I thank thee, that this carnal cur</line>
            <line>Preys on the issue of his mother's body,</line>
            <line>And makes her pew-fellow with others' moan!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>O Harry's wife, triumph not in my woes!</line>
            <line>God witness with me, I have wept for thine.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Bear with me; I am hungry for revenge,</line>
            <line>And now I cloy me with beholding it.</line>
            <line>Thy Edward he is dead, that stabb'd my Edward:</line>
            <line>Thy other Edward dead, to quit my Edward;</line>
            <line>Young York he is but boot, because both they</line>
            <line>Match not the high perfection of my loss:</line>
            <line>Thy Clarence he is dead that kill'd my Edward;</line>
            <line>And the beholders of this tragic play,</line>
            <line>The adulterate Hastings, Rivers, Vaughan, Grey,</line>
            <line>Untimely smother'd in their dusky graves.</line>
            <line>Richard yet lives, hell's black intelligencer,</line>
            <line>Only reserved their factor, to buy souls</line>
            <line>And send them thither: but at hand, at hand,</line>
            <line>Ensues his piteous and unpitied end:</line>
            <line>Earth gapes, hell burns, fiends roar, saints pray.</line>
            <line>To have him suddenly convey'd away.</line>
            <line>Cancel his bond of life, dear God, I prey,</line>
            <line>That I may live to say, The dog is dead!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>O, thou didst prophesy the time would come</line>
            <line>That I should wish for thee to help me curse</line>
            <line>That bottled spider, that foul bunch-back'd toad!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>I call'd thee then vain flourish of my fortune;</line>
            <line>I call'd thee then poor shadow, painted queen;</line>
            <line>The presentation of but what I was;</line>
            <line>The flattering index of a direful pageant;</line>
            <line>One heaved a-high, to be hurl'd down below;</line>
            <line>A mother only mock'd with two sweet babes;</line>
            <line>A dream of what thou wert, a breath, a bubble,</line>
            <line>A sign of dignity, a garish flag,</line>
            <line>To be the aim of every dangerous shot,</line>
            <line>A queen in jest, only to fill the scene.</line>
            <line>Where is thy husband now? where be thy brothers?</line>
            <line>Where are thy children? wherein dost thou, joy?</line>
            <line>Who sues to thee and cries 'God save the queen'?</line>
            <line>Where be the bending peers that flatter'd thee?</line>
            <line>Where be the thronging troops that follow'd thee?</line>
            <line>Decline all this, and see what now thou art:</line>
            <line>For happy wife, a most distressed widow;</line>
            <line>For joyful mother, one that wails the name;</line>
            <line>For queen, a very caitiff crown'd with care;</line>
            <line>For one being sued to, one that humbly sues;</line>
            <line>For one that scorn'd at me, now scorn'd of me;</line>
            <line>For one being fear'd of all, now fearing one;</line>
            <line>For one commanding all, obey'd of none.</line>
            <line>Thus hath the course of justice wheel'd about,</line>
            <line>And left thee but a very prey to time;</line>
            <line>Having no more but thought of what thou wert,</line>
            <line>To torture thee the more, being what thou art.</line>
            <line>Thou didst usurp my place, and dost thou not</line>
            <line>Usurp the just proportion of my sorrow?</line>
            <line>Now thy proud neck bears half my burthen'd yoke;</line>
            <line>From which even here I slip my weary neck,</line>
            <line>And leave the burthen of it all on thee.</line>
            <line>Farewell, York's wife, and queen of sad mischance:</line>
            <line>These English woes will make me smile in France.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>O thou well skill'd in curses, stay awhile,</line>
            <line>And teach me how to curse mine enemies!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Forbear to sleep the nights, and fast the days;</line>
            <line>Compare dead happiness with living woe;</line>
            <line>Think that thy babes were fairer than they were,</line>
            <line>And he that slew them fouler than he is:</line>
            <line>Bettering thy loss makes the bad causer worse:</line>
            <line>Revolving this will teach thee how to curse.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>My words are dull; O, quicken them with thine!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Thy woes will make them sharp, and pierce like mine.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Why should calamity be full of words?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>Windy attorneys to their client woes,</line>
            <line>Airy succeeders of intestate joys,</line>
            <line>Poor breathing orators of miseries!</line>
            <line>Let them have scope: though what they do impart</line>
            <line>Help not all, yet do they ease the heart.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>If so, then be not tongue-tied: go with me.</line>
            <line>And in the breath of bitter words let's smother</line>
            <line>My damned son, which thy two sweet sons smother'd.</line>
            <line>I hear his drum: be copious in exclaims.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter KING RICHARD III, marching, with drums and trumpets</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Who intercepts my expedition?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>O, she that might have intercepted thee,</line>
            <line>By strangling thee in her accursed womb</line>
            <line>From all the slaughters, wretch, that thou hast done!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>Hidest thou that forehead with a golden crown,</line>
            <line>Where should be graven, if that right were right,</line>
            <line>The slaughter of the prince that owed that crown,</line>
            <line>And the dire death of my two sons and brothers?</line>
            <line>Tell me, thou villain slave, where are my children?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Thou toad, thou toad, where is thy brother Clarence?</line>
            <line>And little Ned Plantagenet, his son?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>Where is kind Hastings, Rivers, Vaughan, Grey?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>A flourish, trumpets! strike alarum, drums!</line>
            <line>Let not the heavens hear these tell-tale women</line>
            <line>Rail on the Lord's enointed: strike, I say!</line>
            <stagedir>Flourish. Alarums</stagedir>
            <line>Either be patient, and entreat me fair,</line>
            <line>Or with the clamorous report of war</line>
            <line>Thus will I drown your exclamations.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Art thou my son?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Ay, I thank God, my father, and yourself.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Then patiently hear my impatience.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Madam, I have a touch of your condition,</line>
            <line>Which cannot brook the accent of reproof.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>O, let me speak!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Do then: but I'll not hear.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>I will be mild and gentle in my speech.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>And brief, good mother; for I am in haste.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Art thou so hasty? I have stay'd for thee,</line>
            <line>God knows, in anguish, pain and agony.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>And came I not at last to comfort you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>No, by the holy rood, thou know'st it well,</line>
            <line>Thou camest on earth to make the earth my hell.</line>
            <line>A grievous burthen was thy birth to me;</line>
            <line>Tetchy and wayward was thy infancy;</line>
            <line>Thy school-days frightful, desperate, wild, and furious,</line>
            <line>Thy prime of manhood daring, bold, and venturous,</line>
            <line>Thy age confirm'd, proud, subdued, bloody,</line>
            <line>treacherous,</line>
            <line>More mild, but yet more harmful, kind in hatred:</line>
            <line>What comfortable hour canst thou name,</line>
            <line>That ever graced me in thy company?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Faith, none, but Humphrey Hour, that call'd</line>
            <line>your grace</line>
            <line>To breakfast once forth of my company.</line>
            <line>If I be so disgracious in your sight,</line>
            <line>Let me march on, and not offend your grace.</line>
            <line>Strike the drum.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>I prithee, hear me speak.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>You speak too bitterly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Hear me a word;</line>
            <line>For I shall never speak to thee again.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>So.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Either thou wilt die, by God's just ordinance,</line>
            <line>Ere from this war thou turn a conqueror,</line>
            <line>Or I with grief and extreme age shall perish</line>
            <line>And never look upon thy face again.</line>
            <line>Therefore take with thee my most heavy curse;</line>
            <line>Which, in the day of battle, tire thee more</line>
            <line>Than all the complete armour that thou wear'st!</line>
            <line>My prayers on the adverse party fight;</line>
            <line>And there the little souls of Edward's children</line>
            <line>Whisper the spirits of thine enemies</line>
            <line>And promise them success and victory.</line>
            <line>Bloody thou art, bloody will be thy end;</line>
            <line>Shame serves thy life and doth thy death attend.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>Though far more cause, yet much less spirit to curse</line>
            <line>Abides in me; I say amen to all.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Stay, madam; I must speak a word with you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>I have no more sons of the royal blood</line>
            <line>For thee to murder: for my daughters, Richard,</line>
            <line>They shall be praying nuns, not weeping queens;</line>
            <line>And therefore level not to hit their lives.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>You have a daughter call'd Elizabeth,</line>
            <line>Virtuous and fair, royal and gracious.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>And must she die for this? O, let her live,</line>
            <line>And I'll corrupt her manners, stain her beauty;</line>
            <line>Slander myself as false to Edward's bed;</line>
            <line>Throw over her the veil of infamy:</line>
            <line>So she may live unscarr'd of bleeding slaughter,</line>
            <line>I will confess she was not Edward's daughter.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Wrong not her birth, she is of royal blood.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>To save her life, I'll say she is not so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Her life is only safest in her birth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>And only in that safety died her brothers.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Lo, at their births good stars were opposite.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>No, to their lives bad friends were contrary.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>All unavoided is the doom of destiny.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>True, when avoided grace makes destiny:</line>
            <line>My babes were destined to a fairer death,</line>
            <line>If grace had bless'd thee with a fairer life.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>You speak as if that I had slain my cousins.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>Cousins, indeed; and by their uncle cozen'd</line>
            <line>Of comfort, kingdom, kindred, freedom, life.</line>
            <line>Whose hand soever lanced their tender hearts,</line>
            <line>Thy head, all indirectly, gave direction:</line>
            <line>No doubt the murderous knife was dull and blunt</line>
            <line>Till it was whetted on thy stone-hard heart,</line>
            <line>To revel in the entrails of my lambs.</line>
            <line>But that still use of grief makes wild grief tame,</line>
            <line>My tongue should to thy ears not name my boys</line>
            <line>Till that my nails were anchor'd in thine eyes;</line>
            <line>And I, in such a desperate bay of death,</line>
            <line>Like a poor bark, of sails and tackling reft,</line>
            <line>Rush all to pieces on thy rocky bosom.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Madam, so thrive I in my enterprise</line>
            <line>And dangerous success of bloody wars,</line>
            <line>As I intend more good to you and yours,</line>
            <line>Than ever you or yours were by me wrong'd!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>What good is cover'd with the face of heaven,</line>
            <line>To be discover'd, that can do me good?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>The advancement of your children, gentle lady.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>Up to some scaffold, there to lose their heads?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>No, to the dignity and height of honour</line>
            <line>The high imperial type of this earth's glory.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>Flatter my sorrows with report of it;</line>
            <line>Tell me what state, what dignity, what honour,</line>
            <line>Canst thou demise to any child of mine?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Even all I have; yea, and myself and all,</line>
            <line>Will I withal endow a child of thine;</line>
            <line>So in the Lethe of thy angry soul</line>
            <line>Thou drown the sad remembrance of those wrongs</line>
            <line>Which thou supposest I have done to thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>Be brief, lest that be process of thy kindness</line>
            <line>Last longer telling than thy kindness' date.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Then know, that from my soul I love thy daughter.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>My daughter's mother thinks it with her soul.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>What do you think?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>That thou dost love my daughter from thy soul:</line>
            <line>So from thy soul's love didst thou love her brothers;</line>
            <line>And from my heart's love I do thank thee for it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Be not so hasty to confound my meaning:</line>
            <line>I mean, that with my soul I love thy daughter,</line>
            <line>And mean to make her queen of England.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>Say then, who dost thou mean shall be her king?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Even he that makes her queen who should be else?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>What, thou?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>I, even I: what think you of it, madam?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>How canst thou woo her?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>That would I learn of you,</line>
            <line>As one that are best acquainted with her humour.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>And wilt thou learn of me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Madam, with all my heart.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>Send to her, by the man that slew her brothers,</line>
            <line>A pair of bleeding-hearts; thereon engrave</line>
            <line>Edward and York; then haply she will weep:</line>
            <line>Therefore present to her--as sometime Margaret</line>
            <line>Did to thy father, steep'd in Rutland's blood,--</line>
            <line>A handkerchief; which, say to her, did drain</line>
            <line>The purple sap from her sweet brother's body</line>
            <line>And bid her dry her weeping eyes therewith.</line>
            <line>If this inducement force her not to love,</line>
            <line>Send her a story of thy noble acts;</line>
            <line>Tell her thou madest away her uncle Clarence,</line>
            <line>Her uncle Rivers; yea, and, for her sake,</line>
            <line>Madest quick conveyance with her good aunt Anne.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Come, come, you mock me; this is not the way</line>
            <line>To win our daughter.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>There is no other way</line>
            <line>Unless thou couldst put on some other shape,</line>
            <line>And not be Richard that hath done all this.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Say that I did all this for love of her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>Nay, then indeed she cannot choose but hate thee,</line>
            <line>Having bought love with such a bloody spoil.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Look, what is done cannot be now amended:</line>
            <line>Men shall deal unadvisedly sometimes,</line>
            <line>Which after hours give leisure to repent.</line>
            <line>If I did take the kingdom from your sons,</line>
            <line>To make amends, Ill give it to your daughter.</line>
            <line>If I have kill'd the issue of your womb,</line>
            <line>To quicken your increase, I will beget</line>
            <line>Mine issue of your blood upon your daughter</line>
            <line>A grandam's name is little less in love</line>
            <line>Than is the doting title of a mother;</line>
            <line>They are as children but one step below,</line>
            <line>Even of your mettle, of your very blood;</line>
            <line>Of an one pain, save for a night of groans</line>
            <line>Endured of her, for whom you bid like sorrow.</line>
            <line>Your children were vexation to your youth,</line>
            <line>But mine shall be a comfort to your age.</line>
            <line>The loss you have is but a son being king,</line>
            <line>And by that loss your daughter is made queen.</line>
            <line>I cannot make you what amends I would,</line>
            <line>Therefore accept such kindness as I can.</line>
            <line>Dorset your son, that with a fearful soul</line>
            <line>Leads discontented steps in foreign soil,</line>
            <line>This fair alliance quickly shall call home</line>
            <line>To high promotions and great dignity:</line>
            <line>The king, that calls your beauteous daughter wife.</line>
            <line>Familiarly shall call thy Dorset brother;</line>
            <line>Again shall you be mother to a king,</line>
            <line>And all the ruins of distressful times</line>
            <line>Repair'd with double riches of content.</line>
            <line>What! we have many goodly days to see:</line>
            <line>The liquid drops of tears that you have shed</line>
            <line>Shall come again, transform'd to orient pearl,</line>
            <line>Advantaging their loan with interest</line>
            <line>Of ten times double gain of happiness.</line>
            <line>Go, then my mother, to thy daughter go</line>
            <line>Make bold her bashful years with your experience;</line>
            <line>Prepare her ears to hear a wooer's tale</line>
            <line>Put in her tender heart the aspiring flame</line>
            <line>Of golden sovereignty; acquaint the princess</line>
            <line>With the sweet silent hours of marriage joys</line>
            <line>And when this arm of mine hath chastised</line>
            <line>The petty rebel, dull-brain'd Buckingham,</line>
            <line>Bound with triumphant garlands will I come</line>
            <line>And lead thy daughter to a conqueror's bed;</line>
            <line>To whom I will retail my conquest won,</line>
            <line>And she shall be sole victress, Caesar's Caesar.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>What were I best to say? her father's brother</line>
            <line>Would be her lord? or shall I say, her uncle?</line>
            <line>Or, he that slew her brothers and her uncles?</line>
            <line>Under what title shall I woo for thee,</line>
            <line>That God, the law, my honour and her love,</line>
            <line>Can make seem pleasing to her tender years?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Infer fair England's peace by this alliance.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>Which she shall purchase with still lasting war.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Say that the king, which may command, entreats.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>That at her hands which the king's King forbids.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Say, she shall be a high and mighty queen.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>To wail the tide, as her mother doth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Say, I will love her everlastingly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>But how long shall that title 'ever' last?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Sweetly in force unto her fair life's end.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>But how long fairly shall her sweet lie last?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>So long as heaven and nature lengthens it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>So long as hell and Richard likes of it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Say, I, her sovereign, am her subject love.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>But she, your subject, loathes such sovereignty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Be eloquent in my behalf to her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>An honest tale speeds best being plainly told.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Then in plain terms tell her my loving tale.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>Plain and not honest is too harsh a style.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Your reasons are too shallow and too quick.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>O no, my reasons are too deep and dead;</line>
            <line>Too deep and dead, poor infants, in their grave.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Harp not on that string, madam; that is past.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>Harp on it still shall I till heart-strings break.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Now, by my George, my garter, and my crown,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>Profaned, dishonour'd, and the third usurp'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>I swear--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>By nothing; for this is no oath:</line>
            <line>The George, profaned, hath lost his holy honour;</line>
            <line>The garter, blemish'd, pawn'd his knightly virtue;</line>
            <line>The crown, usurp'd, disgraced his kingly glory.</line>
            <line>if something thou wilt swear to be believed,</line>
            <line>Swear then by something that thou hast not wrong'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Now, by the world--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>'Tis full of thy foul wrongs.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>My father's death--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>Thy life hath that dishonour'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Then, by myself--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>Thyself thyself misusest.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Why then, by God--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>God's wrong is most of all.</line>
            <line>If thou hadst fear'd to break an oath by Him,</line>
            <line>The unity the king thy brother made</line>
            <line>Had not been broken, nor my brother slain:</line>
            <line>If thou hadst fear'd to break an oath by Him,</line>
            <line>The imperial metal, circling now thy brow,</line>
            <line>Had graced the tender temples of my child,</line>
            <line>And both the princes had been breathing here,</line>
            <line>Which now, two tender playfellows to dust,</line>
            <line>Thy broken faith hath made a prey for worms.</line>
            <line>What canst thou swear by now?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>The time to come.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>That thou hast wronged in the time o'erpast;</line>
            <line>For I myself have many tears to wash</line>
            <line>Hereafter time, for time past wrong'd by thee.</line>
            <line>The children live, whose parents thou hast</line>
            <line>slaughter'd,</line>
            <line>Ungovern'd youth, to wail it in their age;</line>
            <line>The parents live, whose children thou hast butcher'd,</line>
            <line>Old wither'd plants, to wail it with their age.</line>
            <line>Swear not by time to come; for that thou hast</line>
            <line>Misused ere used, by time misused o'erpast.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>As I intend to prosper and repent,</line>
            <line>So thrive I in my dangerous attempt</line>
            <line>Of hostile arms! myself myself confound!</line>
            <line>Heaven and fortune bar me happy hours!</line>
            <line>Day, yield me not thy light; nor, night, thy rest!</line>
            <line>Be opposite all planets of good luck</line>
            <line>To my proceedings, if, with pure heart's love,</line>
            <line>Immaculate devotion, holy thoughts,</line>
            <line>I tender not thy beauteous princely daughter!</line>
            <line>In her consists my happiness and thine;</line>
            <line>Without her, follows to this land and me,</line>
            <line>To thee, herself, and many a Christian soul,</line>
            <line>Death, desolation, ruin and decay:</line>
            <line>It cannot be avoided but by this;</line>
            <line>It will not be avoided but by this.</line>
            <line>Therefore, good mother,--I must can you so--</line>
            <line>Be the attorney of my love to her:</line>
            <line>Plead what I will be, not what I have been;</line>
            <line>Not my deserts, but what I will deserve:</line>
            <line>Urge the necessity and state of times,</line>
            <line>And be not peevish-fond in great designs.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>Shall I be tempted of the devil thus?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Ay, if the devil tempt thee to do good.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>Shall I forget myself to be myself?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Ay, if yourself's remembrance wrong yourself.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>But thou didst kill my children.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>But in your daughter's womb I bury them:</line>
            <line>Where in that nest of spicery they shall breed</line>
            <line>Selves of themselves, to your recomforture.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>Shall I go win my daughter to thy will?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>And be a happy mother by the deed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>I go. Write to me very shortly.</line>
            <line>And you shall understand from me her mind.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Bear her my true love's kiss; and so, farewell.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit QUEEN ELIZABETH</stagedir>
            <line>Relenting fool, and shallow, changing woman!</line>
            <stagedir>Enter RATCLIFF; CATESBY following</stagedir>
            <line>How now! what news?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RATCLIFF</speaker>
            <line>My gracious sovereign, on the western coast</line>
            <line>Rideth a puissant navy; to the shore</line>
            <line>Throng many doubtful hollow-hearted friends,</line>
            <line>Unarm'd, and unresolved to beat them back:</line>
            <line>'Tis thought that Richmond is their admiral;</line>
            <line>And there they hull, expecting but the aid</line>
            <line>Of Buckingham to welcome them ashore.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Some light-foot friend post to the Duke of Norfolk:</line>
            <line>Ratcliff, thyself, or Catesby; where is he?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CATESBY</speaker>
            <line>Here, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Fly to the duke:</line>
            <stagedir>To RATCLIFF</stagedir>
            <line>Post thou to Salisbury</line>
            <line>When thou comest thither--</line>
            <stagedir>To CATESBY</stagedir>
            <line>Dull, unmindful villain,</line>
            <line>Why stand'st thou still, and go'st not to the duke?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CATESBY</speaker>
            <line>First, mighty sovereign, let me know your mind,</line>
            <line>What from your grace I shall deliver to him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>O, true, good Catesby: bid him levy straight</line>
            <line>The greatest strength and power he can make,</line>
            <line>And meet me presently at Salisbury.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CATESBY</speaker>
            <line>I go.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RATCLIFF</speaker>
            <line>What is't your highness' pleasure I shall do at</line>
            <line>Salisbury?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Why, what wouldst thou do there before I go?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RATCLIFF</speaker>
            <line>Your highness told me I should post before.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>My mind is changed, sir, my mind is changed.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter STANLEY</stagedir>
            <line>How now, what news with you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>STANLEY</speaker>
            <line>None good, my lord, to please you with the hearing;</line>
            <line>Nor none so bad, but it may well be told.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Hoyday, a riddle! neither good nor bad!</line>
            <line>Why dost thou run so many mile about,</line>
            <line>When thou mayst tell thy tale a nearer way?</line>
            <line>Once more, what news?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>STANLEY</speaker>
            <line>Richmond is on the seas.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>There let him sink, and be the seas on him!</line>
            <line>White-liver'd runagate, what doth he there?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>STANLEY</speaker>
            <line>I know not, mighty sovereign, but by guess.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Well, sir, as you guess, as you guess?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>STANLEY</speaker>
            <line>Stirr'd up by Dorset, Buckingham, and Ely,</line>
            <line>He makes for England, there to claim the crown.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Is the chair empty? is the sword unsway'd?</line>
            <line>Is the king dead? the empire unpossess'd?</line>
            <line>What heir of York is there alive but we?</line>
            <line>And who is England's king but great York's heir?</line>
            <line>Then, tell me, what doth he upon the sea?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>STANLEY</speaker>
            <line>Unless for that, my liege, I cannot guess.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Unless for that he comes to be your liege,</line>
            <line>You cannot guess wherefore the Welshman comes.</line>
            <line>Thou wilt revolt, and fly to him, I fear.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>STANLEY</speaker>
            <line>No, mighty liege; therefore mistrust me not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Where is thy power, then, to beat him back?</line>
            <line>Where are thy tenants and thy followers?</line>
            <line>Are they not now upon the western shore.</line>
            <line>Safe-conducting the rebels from their ships!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>STANLEY</speaker>
            <line>No, my good lord, my friends are in the north.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Cold friends to Richard: what do they in the north,</line>
            <line>When they should serve their sovereign in the west?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>STANLEY</speaker>
            <line>They have not been commanded, mighty sovereign:</line>
            <line>Please it your majesty to give me leave,</line>
            <line>I'll muster up my friends, and meet your grace</line>
            <line>Where and what time your majesty shall please.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Ay, ay. thou wouldst be gone to join with Richmond:</line>
            <line>I will not trust you, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>STANLEY</speaker>
            <line>Most mighty sovereign,</line>
            <line>You have no cause to hold my friendship doubtful:</line>
            <line>I never was nor never will be false.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Well,</line>
            <line>Go muster men; but, hear you, leave behind</line>
            <line>Your son, George Stanley: look your faith be firm.</line>
            <line>Or else his head's assurance is but frail.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>STANLEY</speaker>
            <line>So deal with him as I prove true to you.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Enter a Messenger</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>My gracious sovereign, now in Devonshire,</line>
            <line>As I by friends am well advertised,</line>
            <line>Sir Edward Courtney, and the haughty prelate</line>
            <line>Bishop of Exeter, his brother there,</line>
            <line>With many more confederates, are in arms.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter another Messenger</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Messenger</speaker>
            <line>My liege, in Kent the Guildfords are in arms;</line>
            <line>And every hour more competitors</line>
            <line>Flock to their aid, and still their power increaseth.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter another Messenger</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Messenger</speaker>
            <line>My lord, the army of the Duke of Buckingham--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Out on you, owls! nothing but songs of death?</line>
            <stagedir>He striketh him</stagedir>
            <line>Take that, until thou bring me better news.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Messenger</speaker>
            <line>The news I have to tell your majesty</line>
            <line>Is, that by sudden floods and fall of waters,</line>
            <line>Buckingham's army is dispersed and scatter'd;</line>
            <line>And he himself wander'd away alone,</line>
            <line>No man knows whither.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>I cry thee mercy:</line>
            <line>There is my purse to cure that blow of thine.</line>
            <line>Hath any well-advised friend proclaim'd</line>
            <line>Reward to him that brings the traitor in?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Messenger</speaker>
            <line>Such proclamation hath been made, my liege.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter another Messenger</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fourth Messenger</speaker>
            <line>Sir Thomas Lovel and Lord Marquis Dorset,</line>
            <line>'Tis said, my liege, in Yorkshire are in arms.</line>
            <line>Yet this good comfort bring I to your grace,</line>
            <line>The Breton navy is dispersed by tempest:</line>
            <line>Richmond, in Yorkshire, sent out a boat</line>
            <line>Unto the shore, to ask those on the banks</line>
            <line>If they were his assistants, yea or no;</line>
            <line>Who answer'd him, they came from Buckingham.</line>
            <line>Upon his party: he, mistrusting them,</line>
            <line>Hoisted sail and made away for Brittany.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>March on, march on, since we are up in arms;</line>
            <line>If not to fight with foreign enemies,</line>
            <line>Yet to beat down these rebels here at home.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter CATESBY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CATESBY</speaker>
            <line>My liege, the Duke of Buckingham is taken;</line>
            <line>That is the best news: that the Earl of Richmond</line>
            <line>Is with a mighty power landed at Milford,</line>
            <line>Is colder tidings, yet they must be told.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD III</speaker>
            <line>Away towards Salisbury! while we reason here,</line>
            <line>A royal battle might be won and lost</line>
            <line>Some one take order Buckingham be brought</line>
            <line>To Salisbury; the rest march on with me.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Flourish. Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-5">
      <title>SCENE V.  Lord Derby's house.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter DERBY and SIR CHRISTOPHER URSWICK</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DERBY</speaker>
            <line>Sir Christopher, tell Richmond this from me:</line>
            <line>That in the sty of this most bloody boar</line>
            <line>My son George Stanley is frank'd up in hold:</line>
            <line>If I revolt, off goes young George's head;</line>
            <line>The fear of that withholds my present aid.</line>
            <line>But, tell me, where is princely Richmond now?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHRISTOPHER</speaker>
            <line>At Pembroke, or at Harford-west, in Wales.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DERBY</speaker>
            <line>What men of name resort to him?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHRISTOPHER</speaker>
            <line>Sir Walter Herbert, a renowned soldier;</line>
            <line>Sir Gilbert Talbot, Sir William Stanley;</line>
            <line>Oxford, redoubted Pembroke, Sir James Blunt,</line>
            <line>And Rice ap Thomas with a valiant crew;</line>
            <line>And many more of noble fame and worth:</line>
            <line>And towards London they do bend their course,</line>
            <line>If by the way they be not fought withal.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DERBY</speaker>
            <line>Return unto thy lord; commend me to him:</line>
            <line>Tell him the queen hath heartily consented</line>
            <line>He shall espouse Elizabeth her daughter.</line>
            <line>These letters will resolve him of my mind. Farewell.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>