<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net/doctypes/dita/shakespear/dtd/act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-2">
   <title>ACT II</title>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  London. The palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Flourish. Enter KING EDWARD IV sick, QUEEN
ELIZABETH, DORSET, RIVERS, HASTINGS, BUCKINGHAM,
GREY, and others</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>Why, so: now have I done a good day's work:</line>
            <line>You peers, continue this united league:</line>
            <line>I every day expect an embassage</line>
            <line>From my Redeemer to redeem me hence;</line>
            <line>And now in peace my soul shall part to heaven,</line>
            <line>Since I have set my friends at peace on earth.</line>
            <line>Rivers and Hastings, take each other's hand;</line>
            <line>Dissemble not your hatred, swear your love.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RIVERS</speaker>
            <line>By heaven, my heart is purged from grudging hate:</line>
            <line>And with my hand I seal my true heart's love.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>So thrive I, as I truly swear the like!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>Take heed you dally not before your king;</line>
            <line>Lest he that is the supreme King of kings</line>
            <line>Confound your hidden falsehood, and award</line>
            <line>Either of you to be the other's end.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>So prosper I, as I swear perfect love!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RIVERS</speaker>
            <line>And I, as I love Hastings with my heart!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>Madam, yourself are not exempt in this,</line>
            <line>Nor your son Dorset, Buckingham, nor you;</line>
            <line>You have been factious one against the other,</line>
            <line>Wife, love Lord Hastings, let him kiss your hand;</line>
            <line>And what you do, do it unfeignedly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>Here, Hastings; I will never more remember</line>
            <line>Our former hatred, so thrive I and mine!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>Dorset, embrace him; Hastings, love lord marquess.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DORSET</speaker>
            <line>This interchange of love, I here protest,</line>
            <line>Upon my part shall be unviolable.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>And so swear I, my lord</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>They embrace</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>Now, princely Buckingham, seal thou this league</line>
            <line>With thy embracements to my wife's allies,</line>
            <line>And make me happy in your unity.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Whenever Buckingham doth turn his hate</line>
            <line>On you or yours,</line>
            <stagedir>To the Queen</stagedir>
            <line>but with all duteous love</line>
            <line>Doth cherish you and yours, God punish me</line>
            <line>With hate in those where I expect most love!</line>
            <line>When I have most need to employ a friend,</line>
            <line>And most assured that he is a friend</line>
            <line>Deep, hollow, treacherous, and full of guile,</line>
            <line>Be he unto me! this do I beg of God,</line>
            <line>When I am cold in zeal to yours.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>A pleasing cordial, princely Buckingham,</line>
            <line>is this thy vow unto my sickly heart.</line>
            <line>There wanteth now our brother Gloucester here,</line>
            <line>To make the perfect period of this peace.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>And, in good time, here comes the noble duke.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter GLOUCESTER</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Good morrow to my sovereign king and queen:</line>
            <line>And, princely peers, a happy time of day!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>Happy, indeed, as we have spent the day.</line>
            <line>Brother, we done deeds of charity;</line>
            <line>Made peace enmity, fair love of hate,</line>
            <line>Between these swelling wrong-incensed peers.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>A blessed labour, my most sovereign liege:</line>
            <line>Amongst this princely heap, if any here,</line>
            <line>By false intelligence, or wrong surmise,</line>
            <line>Hold me a foe;</line>
            <line>If I unwittingly, or in my rage,</line>
            <line>Have aught committed that is hardly borne</line>
            <line>By any in this presence, I desire</line>
            <line>To reconcile me to his friendly peace:</line>
            <line>'Tis death to me to be at enmity;</line>
            <line>I hate it, and desire all good men's love.</line>
            <line>First, madam, I entreat true peace of you,</line>
            <line>Which I will purchase with my duteous service;</line>
            <line>Of you, my noble cousin Buckingham,</line>
            <line>If ever any grudge were lodged between us;</line>
            <line>Of you, Lord Rivers, and, Lord Grey, of you;</line>
            <line>That without desert have frown'd on me;</line>
            <line>Dukes, earls, lords, gentlemen; indeed, of all.</line>
            <line>I do not know that Englishman alive</line>
            <line>With whom my soul is any jot at odds</line>
            <line>More than the infant that is born to-night</line>
            <line>I thank my God for my humility.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>A holy day shall this be kept hereafter:</line>
            <line>I would to God all strifes were well compounded.</line>
            <line>My sovereign liege, I do beseech your majesty</line>
            <line>To take our brother Clarence to your grace.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Why, madam, have I offer'd love for this</line>
            <line>To be so bouted in this royal presence?</line>
            <line>Who knows not that the noble duke is dead?</line>
            <stagedir>They all start</stagedir>
            <line>You do him injury to scorn his corse.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RIVERS</speaker>
            <line>Who knows not he is dead! who knows he is?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>All seeing heaven, what a world is this!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Look I so pale, Lord Dorset, as the rest?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DORSET</speaker>
            <line>Ay, my good lord; and no one in this presence</line>
            <line>But his red colour hath forsook his cheeks.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>Is Clarence dead? the order was reversed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>But he, poor soul, by your first order died,</line>
            <line>And that a winged Mercury did bear:</line>
            <line>Some tardy cripple bore the countermand,</line>
            <line>That came too lag to see him buried.</line>
            <line>God grant that some, less noble and less loyal,</line>
            <line>Nearer in bloody thoughts, but not in blood,</line>
            <line>Deserve not worse than wretched Clarence did,</line>
            <line>And yet go current from suspicion!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter DERBY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DORSET</speaker>
            <line>A boon, my sovereign, for my service done!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>I pray thee, peace: my soul is full of sorrow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DORSET</speaker>
            <line>I will not rise, unless your highness grant.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>Then speak at once what is it thou demand'st.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DORSET</speaker>
            <line>The forfeit, sovereign, of my servant's life;</line>
            <line>Who slew to-day a righteous gentleman</line>
            <line>Lately attendant on the Duke of Norfolk.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING EDWARD IV</speaker>
            <line>Have a tongue to doom my brother's death,</line>
            <line>And shall the same give pardon to a slave?</line>
            <line>My brother slew no man; his fault was thought,</line>
            <line>And yet his punishment was cruel death.</line>
            <line>Who sued to me for him? who, in my rage,</line>
            <line>Kneel'd at my feet, and bade me be advised</line>
            <line>Who spake of brotherhood? who spake of love?</line>
            <line>Who told me how the poor soul did forsake</line>
            <line>The mighty Warwick, and did fight for me?</line>
            <line>Who told me, in the field by Tewksbury</line>
            <line>When Oxford had me down, he rescued me,</line>
            <line>And said, 'Dear brother, live, and be a king'?</line>
            <line>Who told me, when we both lay in the field</line>
            <line>Frozen almost to death, how he did lap me</line>
            <line>Even in his own garments, and gave himself,</line>
            <line>All thin and naked, to the numb cold night?</line>
            <line>All this from my remembrance brutish wrath</line>
            <line>Sinfully pluck'd, and not a man of you</line>
            <line>Had so much grace to put it in my mind.</line>
            <line>But when your carters or your waiting-vassals</line>
            <line>Have done a drunken slaughter, and defaced</line>
            <line>The precious image of our dear Redeemer,</line>
            <line>You straight are on your knees for pardon, pardon;</line>
            <line>And I unjustly too, must grant it you</line>
            <line>But for my brother not a man would speak,</line>
            <line>Nor I, ungracious, speak unto myself</line>
            <line>For him, poor soul. The proudest of you all</line>
            <line>Have been beholding to him in his life;</line>
            <line>Yet none of you would once plead for his life.</line>
            <line>O God, I fear thy justice will take hold</line>
            <line>On me, and you, and mine, and yours for this!</line>
            <line>Come, Hastings, help me to my closet.</line>
            <line>Oh, poor Clarence!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt some with KING EDWARD IV and QUEEN MARGARET</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>This is the fruit of rashness! Mark'd you not</line>
            <line>How that the guilty kindred of the queen</line>
            <line>Look'd pale when they did hear of Clarence' death?</line>
            <line>O, they did urge it still unto the king!</line>
            <line>God will revenge it. But come, let us in,</line>
            <line>To comfort Edward with our company.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>We wait upon your grace.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  The palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter the DUCHESS OF YORK, with the two children of CLARENCE</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Boy</speaker>
            <line>Tell me, good grandam, is our father dead?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>No, boy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Boy</speaker>
            <line>Why do you wring your hands, and beat your breast,</line>
            <line>And cry 'O Clarence, my unhappy son!'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Girl</speaker>
            <line>Why do you look on us, and shake your head,</line>
            <line>And call us wretches, orphans, castaways</line>
            <line>If that our noble father be alive?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>My pretty cousins, you mistake me much;</line>
            <line>I do lament the sickness of the king.</line>
            <line>As loath to lose him, not your father's death;</line>
            <line>It were lost sorrow to wail one that's lost.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Boy</speaker>
            <line>Then, grandam, you conclude that he is dead.</line>
            <line>The king my uncle is to blame for this:</line>
            <line>God will revenge it; whom I will importune</line>
            <line>With daily prayers all to that effect.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Girl</speaker>
            <line>And so will I.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Peace, children, peace! the king doth love you well:</line>
            <line>Incapable and shallow innocents,</line>
            <line>You cannot guess who caused your father's death.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Boy</speaker>
            <line>Grandam, we can; for my good uncle Gloucester</line>
            <line>Told me, the king, provoked by the queen,</line>
            <line>Devised impeachments to imprison him :</line>
            <line>And when my uncle told me so, he wept,</line>
            <line>And hugg'd me in his arm, and kindly kiss'd my cheek;</line>
            <line>Bade me rely on him as on my father,</line>
            <line>And he would love me dearly as his child.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Oh, that deceit should steal such gentle shapes,</line>
            <line>And with a virtuous vizard hide foul guile!</line>
            <line>He is my son; yea, and therein my shame;</line>
            <line>Yet from my dugs he drew not this deceit.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Boy</speaker>
            <line>Think you my uncle did dissemble, grandam?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Ay, boy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Boy</speaker>
            <line>I cannot think it. Hark! what noise is this?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter QUEEN ELIZABETH, with her hair about her
ears; RIVERS, and DORSET after her</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>Oh, who shall hinder me to wail and weep,</line>
            <line>To chide my fortune, and torment myself?</line>
            <line>I'll join with black despair against my soul,</line>
            <line>And to myself become an enemy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>What means this scene of rude impatience?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>To make an act of tragic violence:</line>
            <line>Edward, my lord, your son, our king, is dead.</line>
            <line>Why grow the branches now the root is wither'd?</line>
            <line>Why wither not the leaves the sap being gone?</line>
            <line>If you will live, lament; if die, be brief,</line>
            <line>That our swift-winged souls may catch the king's;</line>
            <line>Or, like obedient subjects, follow him</line>
            <line>To his new kingdom of perpetual rest.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Ah, so much interest have I in thy sorrow</line>
            <line>As I had title in thy noble husband!</line>
            <line>I have bewept a worthy husband's death,</line>
            <line>And lived by looking on his images:</line>
            <line>But now two mirrors of his princely semblance</line>
            <line>Are crack'd in pieces by malignant death,</line>
            <line>And I for comfort have but one false glass,</line>
            <line>Which grieves me when I see my shame in him.</line>
            <line>Thou art a widow; yet thou art a mother,</line>
            <line>And hast the comfort of thy children left thee:</line>
            <line>But death hath snatch'd my husband from mine arms,</line>
            <line>And pluck'd two crutches from my feeble limbs,</line>
            <line>Edward and Clarence. O, what cause have I,</line>
            <line>Thine being but a moiety of my grief,</line>
            <line>To overgo thy plaints and drown thy cries!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Boy</speaker>
            <line>Good aunt, you wept not for our father's death;</line>
            <line>How can we aid you with our kindred tears?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Girl</speaker>
            <line>Our fatherless distress was left unmoan'd;</line>
            <line>Your widow-dolour likewise be unwept!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>Give me no help in lamentation;</line>
            <line>I am not barren to bring forth complaints</line>
            <line>All springs reduce their currents to mine eyes,</line>
            <line>That I, being govern'd by the watery moon,</line>
            <line>May send forth plenteous tears to drown the world!</line>
            <line>Oh for my husband, for my dear lord Edward!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Children</speaker>
            <line>Oh for our father, for our dear lord Clarence!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Alas for both, both mine, Edward and Clarence!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>What stay had I but Edward? and he's gone.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Children</speaker>
            <line>What stay had we but Clarence? and he's gone.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>What stays had I but they? and they are gone.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>Was never widow had so dear a loss!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Children</speaker>
            <line>Were never orphans had so dear a loss!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Was never mother had so dear a loss!</line>
            <line>Alas, I am the mother of these moans!</line>
            <line>Their woes are parcell'd, mine are general.</line>
            <line>She for an Edward weeps, and so do I;</line>
            <line>I for a Clarence weep, so doth not she:</line>
            <line>These babes for Clarence weep and so do I;</line>
            <line>I for an Edward weep, so do not they:</line>
            <line>Alas, you three, on me, threefold distress'd,</line>
            <line>Pour all your tears! I am your sorrow's nurse,</line>
            <line>And I will pamper it with lamentations.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DORSET</speaker>
            <line>Comfort, dear mother: God is much displeased</line>
            <line>That you take with unthankfulness, his doing:</line>
            <line>In common worldly things, 'tis call'd ungrateful,</line>
            <line>With dull unwilligness to repay a debt</line>
            <line>Which with a bounteous hand was kindly lent;</line>
            <line>Much more to be thus opposite with heaven,</line>
            <line>For it requires the royal debt it lent you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RIVERS</speaker>
            <line>Madam, bethink you, like a careful mother,</line>
            <line>Of the young prince your son: send straight for him</line>
            <line>Let him be crown'd; in him your comfort lives:</line>
            <line>Drown desperate sorrow in dead Edward's grave,</line>
            <line>And plant your joys in living Edward's throne.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter GLOUCESTER, BUCKINGHAM, DERBY, HASTINGS, and RATCLIFF</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Madam, have comfort: all of us have cause</line>
            <line>To wail the dimming of our shining star;</line>
            <line>But none can cure their harms by wailing them.</line>
            <line>Madam, my mother, I do cry you mercy;</line>
            <line>I did not see your grace: humbly on my knee</line>
            <line>I crave your blessing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>God bless thee; and put meekness in thy mind,</line>
            <line>Love, charity, obedience, and true duty!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  Amen; and make me die a good old man!</line>
            <line>That is the butt-end of a mother's blessing:</line>
            <line>I marvel why her grace did leave it out.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>You cloudy princes and heart-sorrowing peers,</line>
            <line>That bear this mutual heavy load of moan,</line>
            <line>Now cheer each other in each other's love</line>
            <line>Though we have spent our harvest of this king,</line>
            <line>We are to reap the harvest of his son.</line>
            <line>The broken rancour of your high-swoln hearts,</line>
            <line>But lately splinter'd, knit, and join'd together,</line>
            <line>Must gently be preserved, cherish'd, and kept:</line>
            <line>Me seemeth good, that, with some little train,</line>
            <line>Forthwith from Ludlow the young prince be fetch'd</line>
            <line>Hither to London, to be crown'd our king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RIVERS</speaker>
            <line>Why with some little train, my Lord of Buckingham?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Marry, my lord, lest, by a multitude,</line>
            <line>The new-heal'd wound of malice should break out,</line>
            <line>Which would be so much the more dangerous</line>
            <line>By how much the estate is green and yet ungovern'd:</line>
            <line>Where every horse bears his commanding rein,</line>
            <line>And may direct his course as please himself,</line>
            <line>As well the fear of harm, as harm apparent,</line>
            <line>In my opinion, ought to be prevented.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>I hope the king made peace with all of us</line>
            <line>And the compact is firm and true in me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RIVERS</speaker>
            <line>And so in me; and so, I think, in all:</line>
            <line>Yet, since it is but green, it should be put</line>
            <line>To no apparent likelihood of breach,</line>
            <line>Which haply by much company might be urged:</line>
            <line>Therefore I say with noble Buckingham,</line>
            <line>That it is meet so few should fetch the prince.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>And so say I.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Then be it so; and go we to determine</line>
            <line>Who they shall be that straight shall post to Ludlow.</line>
            <line>Madam, and you, my mother, will you go</line>
            <line>To give your censures in this weighty business?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>With all our harts.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt all but BUCKINGHAM and GLOUCESTER</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>My lord, whoever journeys to the Prince,</line>
            <line>For God's sake, let not us two be behind;</line>
            <line>For, by the way, I'll sort occasion,</line>
            <line>As index to the story we late talk'd of,</line>
            <line>To part the queen's proud kindred from the king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>My other self, my counsel's consistory,</line>
            <line>My oracle, my prophet! My dear cousin,</line>
            <line>I, like a child, will go by thy direction.</line>
            <line>Towards Ludlow then, for we'll not stay behind.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  London. A street.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter two Citizens meeting</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Neighbour, well met: whither away so fast?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Citizen</speaker>
            <line>I promise you, I scarcely know myself:</line>
            <line>Hear you the news abroad?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Ay, that the king is dead.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Bad news, by'r lady; seldom comes the better:</line>
            <line>I fear, I fear 'twill prove a troublous world.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter another Citizen</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Neighbours, God speed!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Give you good morrow, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Doth this news hold of good King Edward's death?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Ay, sir, it is too true; God help the while!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Then, masters, look to see a troublous world.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>No, no; by God's good grace his son shall reign.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Woe to the land that's govern'd by a child!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Citizen</speaker>
            <line>In him there is a hope of government,</line>
            <line>That in his nonage council under him,</line>
            <line>And in his full and ripen'd years himself,</line>
            <line>No doubt, shall then and till then govern well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>So stood the state when Henry the Sixth</line>
            <line>Was crown'd in Paris but at nine months old.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Stood the state so? No, no, good friends, God wot;</line>
            <line>For then this land was famously enrich'd</line>
            <line>With politic grave counsel; then the king</line>
            <line>Had virtuous uncles to protect his grace.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Why, so hath this, both by the father and mother.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Better it were they all came by the father,</line>
            <line>Or by the father there were none at all;</line>
            <line>For emulation now, who shall be nearest,</line>
            <line>Will touch us all too near, if God prevent not.</line>
            <line>O, full of danger is the Duke of Gloucester!</line>
            <line>And the queen's sons and brothers haught and proud:</line>
            <line>And were they to be ruled, and not to rule,</line>
            <line>This sickly land might solace as before.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Come, come, we fear the worst; all shall be well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Citizen</speaker>
            <line>When clouds appear, wise men put on their cloaks;</line>
            <line>When great leaves fall, the winter is at hand;</line>
            <line>When the sun sets, who doth not look for night?</line>
            <line>Untimely storms make men expect a dearth.</line>
            <line>All may be well; but, if God sort it so,</line>
            <line>'Tis more than we deserve, or I expect.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Truly, the souls of men are full of dread:</line>
            <line>Ye cannot reason almost with a man</line>
            <line>That looks not heavily and full of fear.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Before the times of change, still is it so:</line>
            <line>By a divine instinct men's minds mistrust</line>
            <line>Ensuing dangers; as by proof, we see</line>
            <line>The waters swell before a boisterous storm.</line>
            <line>But leave it all to God. whither away?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Marry, we were sent for to the justices.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Citizen</speaker>
            <line>And so was I: I'll bear you company.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-4">
      <title>SCENE IV.  London. The palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter the ARCHBISHOP OF YORK, young YORK, QUEEN
ELIZABETH, and the DUCHESS OF YORK</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARCHBISHOP OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Last night, I hear, they lay at Northampton;</line>
            <line>At Stony-Stratford will they be to-night:</line>
            <line>To-morrow, or next day, they will be here.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>I long with all my heart to see the prince:</line>
            <line>I hope he is much grown since last I saw him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>But I hear, no; they say my son of York</line>
            <line>Hath almost overta'en him in his growth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>Ay, mother; but I would not have it so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Why, my young cousin, it is good to grow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>Grandam, one night, as we did sit at supper,</line>
            <line>My uncle Rivers talk'd how I did grow</line>
            <line>More than my brother: 'Ay,' quoth my uncle</line>
            <line>Gloucester,</line>
            <line>'Small herbs have grace, great weeds do grow apace:'</line>
            <line>And since, methinks, I would not grow so fast,</line>
            <line>Because sweet flowers are slow and weeds make haste.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Good faith, good faith, the saying did not hold</line>
            <line>In him that did object the same to thee;</line>
            <line>He was the wretched'st thing when he was young,</line>
            <line>So long a-growing and so leisurely,</line>
            <line>That, if this rule were true, he should be gracious.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARCHBISHOP OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Why, madam, so, no doubt, he is.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>I hope he is; but yet let mothers doubt.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>Now, by my troth, if I had been remember'd,</line>
            <line>I could have given my uncle's grace a flout,</line>
            <line>To touch his growth nearer than he touch'd mine.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>How, my pretty York? I pray thee, let me hear it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>Marry, they say my uncle grew so fast</line>
            <line>That he could gnaw a crust at two hours old</line>
            <line>'Twas full two years ere I could get a tooth.</line>
            <line>Grandam, this would have been a biting jest.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>I pray thee, pretty York, who told thee this?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>Grandam, his nurse.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>His nurse! why, she was dead ere thou wert born.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>If 'twere not she, I cannot tell who told me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>A parlous boy: go to, you are too shrewd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARCHBISHOP OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Good madam, be not angry with the child.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>Pitchers have ears.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter a Messenger</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARCHBISHOP OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Here comes a messenger. What news?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>Such news, my lord, as grieves me to unfold.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>How fares the prince?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>Well, madam, and in health.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>What is thy news then?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>Lord Rivers and Lord Grey are sent to Pomfret,</line>
            <line>With them Sir Thomas Vaughan, prisoners.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Who hath committed them?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>The mighty dukes</line>
            <line>Gloucester and Buckingham.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>For what offence?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>The sum of all I can, I have disclosed;</line>
            <line>Why or for what these nobles were committed</line>
            <line>Is all unknown to me, my gracious lady.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>Ay me, I see the downfall of our house!</line>
            <line>The tiger now hath seized the gentle hind;</line>
            <line>Insulting tyranny begins to jet</line>
            <line>Upon the innocent and aweless throne:</line>
            <line>Welcome, destruction, death, and massacre!</line>
            <line>I see, as in a map, the end of all.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Accursed and unquiet wrangling days,</line>
            <line>How many of you have mine eyes beheld!</line>
            <line>My husband lost his life to get the crown;</line>
            <line>And often up and down my sons were toss'd,</line>
            <line>For me to joy and weep their gain and loss:</line>
            <line>And being seated, and domestic broils</line>
            <line>Clean over-blown, themselves, the conquerors.</line>
            <line>Make war upon themselves; blood against blood,</line>
            <line>Self against self: O, preposterous</line>
            <line>And frantic outrage, end thy damned spleen;</line>
            <line>Or let me die, to look on death no more!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>Come, come, my boy; we will to sanctuary.</line>
            <line>Madam, farewell.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>I'll go along with you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>You have no cause.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARCHBISHOP OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>My gracious lady, go;</line>
            <line>And thither bear your treasure and your goods.</line>
            <line>For my part, I'll resign unto your grace</line>
            <line>The seal I keep: and so betide to me</line>
            <line>As well I tender you and all of yours!</line>
            <line>Come, I'll conduct you to the sanctuary.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>