<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:shakespear:dtd:act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-1">
   <title>ACT I</title>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  London. A street.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter GLOUCESTER, solus</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Now is the winter of our discontent</line>
            <line>Made glorious summer by this sun of York;</line>
            <line>And all the clouds that lour'd upon our house</line>
            <line>In the deep bosom of the ocean buried.</line>
            <line>Now are our brows bound with victorious wreaths;</line>
            <line>Our bruised arms hung up for monuments;</line>
            <line>Our stern alarums changed to merry meetings,</line>
            <line>Our dreadful marches to delightful measures.</line>
            <line>Grim-visaged war hath smooth'd his wrinkled front;</line>
            <line>And now, instead of mounting barded steeds</line>
            <line>To fright the souls of fearful adversaries,</line>
            <line>He capers nimbly in a lady's chamber</line>
            <line>To the lascivious pleasing of a lute.</line>
            <line>But I, that am not shaped for sportive tricks,</line>
            <line>Nor made to court an amorous looking-glass;</line>
            <line>I, that am rudely stamp'd, and want love's majesty</line>
            <line>To strut before a wanton ambling nymph;</line>
            <line>I, that am curtail'd of this fair proportion,</line>
            <line>Cheated of feature by dissembling nature,</line>
            <line>Deformed, unfinish'd, sent before my time</line>
            <line>Into this breathing world, scarce half made up,</line>
            <line>And that so lamely and unfashionable</line>
            <line>That dogs bark at me as I halt by them;</line>
            <line>Why, I, in this weak piping time of peace,</line>
            <line>Have no delight to pass away the time,</line>
            <line>Unless to spy my shadow in the sun</line>
            <line>And descant on mine own deformity:</line>
            <line>And therefore, since I cannot prove a lover,</line>
            <line>To entertain these fair well-spoken days,</line>
            <line>I am determined to prove a villain</line>
            <line>And hate the idle pleasures of these days.</line>
            <line>Plots have I laid, inductions dangerous,</line>
            <line>By drunken prophecies, libels and dreams,</line>
            <line>To set my brother Clarence and the king</line>
            <line>In deadly hate the one against the other:</line>
            <line>And if King Edward be as true and just</line>
            <line>As I am subtle, false and treacherous,</line>
            <line>This day should Clarence closely be mew'd up,</line>
            <line>About a prophecy, which says that 'G'</line>
            <line>Of Edward's heirs the murderer shall be.</line>
            <line>Dive, thoughts, down to my soul: here</line>
            <line>Clarence comes.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter CLARENCE, guarded, and BRAKENBURY</stagedir>
            <line>Brother, good day; what means this armed guard</line>
            <line>That waits upon your grace?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>His majesty</line>
            <line>Tendering my person's safety, hath appointed</line>
            <line>This conduct to convey me to the Tower.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Upon what cause?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>Because my name is George.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Alack, my lord, that fault is none of yours;</line>
            <line>He should, for that, commit your godfathers:</line>
            <line>O, belike his majesty hath some intent</line>
            <line>That you shall be new-christen'd in the Tower.</line>
            <line>But what's the matter, Clarence?  may I know?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>Yea, Richard, when I know; for I protest</line>
            <line>As yet I do not: but, as I can learn,</line>
            <line>He hearkens after prophecies and dreams;</line>
            <line>And from the cross-row plucks the letter G.</line>
            <line>And says a wizard told him that by G</line>
            <line>His issue disinherited should be;</line>
            <line>And, for my name of George begins with G,</line>
            <line>It follows in his thought that I am he.</line>
            <line>These, as I learn, and such like toys as these</line>
            <line>Have moved his highness to commit me now.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Why, this it is, when men are ruled by women:</line>
            <line>'Tis not the king that sends you to the Tower:</line>
            <line>My Lady Grey his wife, Clarence, 'tis she</line>
            <line>That tempers him to this extremity.</line>
            <line>Was it not she and that good man of worship,</line>
            <line>Anthony Woodville, her brother there,</line>
            <line>That made him send Lord Hastings to the Tower,</line>
            <line>From whence this present day he is deliver'd?</line>
            <line>We are not safe, Clarence; we are not safe.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>By heaven, I think there's no man is secure</line>
            <line>But the queen's kindred and night-walking heralds</line>
            <line>That trudge betwixt the king and Mistress Shore.</line>
            <line>Heard ye not what an humble suppliant</line>
            <line>Lord hastings was to her for his delivery?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Humbly complaining to her deity</line>
            <line>Got my lord chamberlain his liberty.</line>
            <line>I'll tell you what; I think it is our way,</line>
            <line>If we will keep in favour with the king,</line>
            <line>To be her men and wear her livery:</line>
            <line>The jealous o'erworn widow and herself,</line>
            <line>Since that our brother dubb'd them gentlewomen.</line>
            <line>Are mighty gossips in this monarchy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRAKENBURY</speaker>
            <line>I beseech your graces both to pardon me;</line>
            <line>His majesty hath straitly given in charge</line>
            <line>That no man shall have private conference,</line>
            <line>Of what degree soever, with his brother.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Even so; an't please your worship, Brakenbury,</line>
            <line>You may partake of any thing we say:</line>
            <line>We speak no treason, man: we say the king</line>
            <line>Is wise and virtuous, and his noble queen</line>
            <line>Well struck in years, fair, and not jealous;</line>
            <line>We say that Shore's wife hath a pretty foot,</line>
            <line>A cherry lip, a bonny eye, a passing pleasing tongue;</line>
            <line>And that the queen's kindred are made gentle-folks:</line>
            <line>How say you sir? Can you deny all this?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRAKENBURY</speaker>
            <line>With this, my lord, myself have nought to do.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Naught to do with mistress Shore! I tell thee, fellow,</line>
            <line>He that doth naught with her, excepting one,</line>
            <line>Were best he do it secretly, alone.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRAKENBURY</speaker>
            <line>What one, my lord?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Her husband, knave: wouldst thou betray me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRAKENBURY</speaker>
            <line>I beseech your grace to pardon me, and withal</line>
            <line>Forbear your conference with the noble duke.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>We know thy charge, Brakenbury, and will obey.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>We are the queen's abjects, and must obey.</line>
            <line>Brother, farewell: I will unto the king;</line>
            <line>And whatsoever you will employ me in,</line>
            <line>Were it to call King Edward's widow sister,</line>
            <line>I will perform it to enfranchise you.</line>
            <line>Meantime, this deep disgrace in brotherhood</line>
            <line>Touches me deeper than you can imagine.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>I know it pleaseth neither of us well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Well, your imprisonment shall not be long;</line>
            <line>Meantime, have patience.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>I must perforce. Farewell.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt CLARENCE, BRAKENBURY, and Guard</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Go, tread the path that thou shalt ne'er return.</line>
            <line>Simple, plain Clarence! I do love thee so,</line>
            <line>That I will shortly send thy soul to heaven,</line>
            <line>If heaven will take the present at our hands.</line>
            <line>But who comes here? the new-deliver'd Hastings?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter HASTINGS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>Good time of day unto my gracious lord!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>As much unto my good lord chamberlain!</line>
            <line>Well are you welcome to the open air.</line>
            <line>How hath your lordship brook'd imprisonment?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>With patience, noble lord, as prisoners must:</line>
            <line>But I shall live, my lord, to give them thanks</line>
            <line>That were the cause of my imprisonment.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>No doubt, no doubt; and so shall Clarence too;</line>
            <line>For they that were your enemies are his,</line>
            <line>And have prevail'd as much on him as you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>More pity that the eagle should be mew'd,</line>
            <line>While kites and buzzards prey at liberty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>What news abroad?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>No news so bad abroad as this at home;</line>
            <line>The King is sickly, weak and melancholy,</line>
            <line>And his physicians fear him mightily.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Now, by Saint Paul, this news is bad indeed.</line>
            <line>O, he hath kept an evil diet long,</line>
            <line>And overmuch consumed his royal person:</line>
            <line>'Tis very grievous to be thought upon.</line>
            <line>What, is he in his bed?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>He is.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Go you before, and I will follow you.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit HASTINGS</stagedir>
            <line>He cannot live, I hope; and must not die</line>
            <line>Till George be pack'd with post-horse up to heaven.</line>
            <line>I'll in, to urge his hatred more to Clarence,</line>
            <line>With lies well steel'd with weighty arguments;</line>
            <line>And, if I fall not in my deep intent,</line>
            <line>Clarence hath not another day to live:</line>
            <line>Which done, God take King Edward to his mercy,</line>
            <line>And leave the world for me to bustle in!</line>
            <line>For then I'll marry Warwick's youngest daughter.</line>
            <line>What though I kill'd her husband and her father?</line>
            <line>The readiest way to make the wench amends</line>
            <line>Is to become her husband and her father:</line>
            <line>The which will I; not all so much for love</line>
            <line>As for another secret close intent,</line>
            <line>By marrying her which I must reach unto.</line>
            <line>But yet I run before my horse to market:</line>
            <line>Clarence still breathes; Edward still lives and reigns:</line>
            <line>When they are gone, then must I count my gains.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  The same. Another street.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter the corpse of KING HENRY the Sixth, Gentlemen
with halberds to guard it; LADY ANNE being the mourner</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY ANNE</speaker>
            <line>Set down, set down your honourable load,</line>
            <line>If honour may be shrouded in a hearse,</line>
            <line>Whilst I awhile obsequiously lament</line>
            <line>The untimely fall of virtuous Lancaster.</line>
            <line>Poor key-cold figure of a holy king!</line>
            <line>Pale ashes of the house of Lancaster!</line>
            <line>Thou bloodless remnant of that royal blood!</line>
            <line>Be it lawful that I invocate thy ghost,</line>
            <line>To hear the lamentations of Poor Anne,</line>
            <line>Wife to thy Edward, to thy slaughter'd son,</line>
            <line>Stabb'd by the selfsame hand that made these wounds!</line>
            <line>Lo, in these windows that let forth thy life,</line>
            <line>I pour the helpless balm of my poor eyes.</line>
            <line>Cursed be the hand that made these fatal holes!</line>
            <line>Cursed be the heart that had the heart to do it!</line>
            <line>Cursed the blood that let this blood from hence!</line>
            <line>More direful hap betide that hated wretch,</line>
            <line>That makes us wretched by the death of thee,</line>
            <line>Than I can wish to adders, spiders, toads,</line>
            <line>Or any creeping venom'd thing that lives!</line>
            <line>If ever he have child, abortive be it,</line>
            <line>Prodigious, and untimely brought to light,</line>
            <line>Whose ugly and unnatural aspect</line>
            <line>May fright the hopeful mother at the view;</line>
            <line>And that be heir to his unhappiness!</line>
            <line>If ever he have wife, let her he made</line>
            <line>A miserable by the death of him</line>
            <line>As I am made by my poor lord and thee!</line>
            <line>Come, now towards Chertsey with your holy load,</line>
            <line>Taken from Paul's to be interred there;</line>
            <line>And still, as you are weary of the weight,</line>
            <line>Rest you, whiles I lament King Henry's corse.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter GLOUCESTER</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Stay, you that bear the corse, and set it down.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY ANNE</speaker>
            <line>What black magician conjures up this fiend,</line>
            <line>To stop devoted charitable deeds?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Villains, set down the corse; or, by Saint Paul,</line>
            <line>I'll make a corse of him that disobeys.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Gentleman</speaker>
            <line>My lord, stand back, and let the coffin pass.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Unmanner'd dog! stand thou, when I command:</line>
            <line>Advance thy halbert higher than my breast,</line>
            <line>Or, by Saint Paul, I'll strike thee to my foot,</line>
            <line>And spurn upon thee, beggar, for thy boldness.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY ANNE</speaker>
            <line>What, do you tremble? are you all afraid?</line>
            <line>Alas, I blame you not; for you are mortal,</line>
            <line>And mortal eyes cannot endure the devil.</line>
            <line>Avaunt, thou dreadful minister of hell!</line>
            <line>Thou hadst but power over his mortal body,</line>
            <line>His soul thou canst not have; therefore be gone.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Sweet saint, for charity, be not so curst.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY ANNE</speaker>
            <line>Foul devil, for God's sake, hence, and trouble us not;</line>
            <line>For thou hast made the happy earth thy hell,</line>
            <line>Fill'd it with cursing cries and deep exclaims.</line>
            <line>If thou delight to view thy heinous deeds,</line>
            <line>Behold this pattern of thy butcheries.</line>
            <line>O, gentlemen, see, see! dead Henry's wounds</line>
            <line>Open their congeal'd mouths and bleed afresh!</line>
            <line>Blush, Blush, thou lump of foul deformity;</line>
            <line>For 'tis thy presence that exhales this blood</line>
            <line>From cold and empty veins, where no blood dwells;</line>
            <line>Thy deed, inhuman and unnatural,</line>
            <line>Provokes this deluge most unnatural.</line>
            <line>O God, which this blood madest, revenge his death!</line>
            <line>O earth, which this blood drink'st revenge his death!</line>
            <line>Either heaven with lightning strike the</line>
            <line>murderer dead,</line>
            <line>Or earth, gape open wide and eat him quick,</line>
            <line>As thou dost swallow up this good king's blood</line>
            <line>Which his hell-govern'd arm hath butchered!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Lady, you know no rules of charity,</line>
            <line>Which renders good for bad, blessings for curses.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY ANNE</speaker>
            <line>Villain, thou know'st no law of God nor man:</line>
            <line>No beast so fierce but knows some touch of pity.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>But I know none, and therefore am no beast.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY ANNE</speaker>
            <line>O wonderful, when devils tell the truth!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>More wonderful, when angels are so angry.</line>
            <line>Vouchsafe, divine perfection of a woman,</line>
            <line>Of these supposed-evils, to give me leave,</line>
            <line>By circumstance, but to acquit myself.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY ANNE</speaker>
            <line>Vouchsafe, defused infection of a man,</line>
            <line>For these known evils, but to give me leave,</line>
            <line>By circumstance, to curse thy cursed self.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Fairer than tongue can name thee, let me have</line>
            <line>Some patient leisure to excuse myself.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY ANNE</speaker>
            <line>Fouler than heart can think thee, thou canst make</line>
            <line>No excuse current, but to hang thyself.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>By such despair, I should accuse myself.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY ANNE</speaker>
            <line>And, by despairing, shouldst thou stand excused;</line>
            <line>For doing worthy vengeance on thyself,</line>
            <line>Which didst unworthy slaughter upon others.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Say that I slew them not?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY ANNE</speaker>
            <line>Why, then they are not dead:</line>
            <line>But dead they are, and devilish slave, by thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>I did not kill your husband.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY ANNE</speaker>
            <line>Why, then he is alive.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Nay, he is dead; and slain by Edward's hand.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY ANNE</speaker>
            <line>In thy foul throat thou liest: Queen Margaret saw</line>
            <line>Thy murderous falchion smoking in his blood;</line>
            <line>The which thou once didst bend against her breast,</line>
            <line>But that thy brothers beat aside the point.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>I was provoked by her slanderous tongue,</line>
            <line>which laid their guilt upon my guiltless shoulders.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY ANNE</speaker>
            <line>Thou wast provoked by thy bloody mind.</line>
            <line>Which never dreamt on aught but butcheries:</line>
            <line>Didst thou not kill this king?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>I grant ye.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY ANNE</speaker>
            <line>Dost grant me, hedgehog? then, God grant me too</line>
            <line>Thou mayst be damned for that wicked deed!</line>
            <line>O, he was gentle, mild, and virtuous!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>The fitter for the King of heaven, that hath him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY ANNE</speaker>
            <line>He is in heaven, where thou shalt never come.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Let him thank me, that holp to send him thither;</line>
            <line>For he was fitter for that place than earth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY ANNE</speaker>
            <line>And thou unfit for any place but hell.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Yes, one place else, if you will hear me name it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY ANNE</speaker>
            <line>Some dungeon.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Your bed-chamber.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY ANNE</speaker>
            <line>I'll rest betide the chamber where thou liest!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>So will it, madam till I lie with you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY ANNE</speaker>
            <line>I hope so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>I know so. But, gentle Lady Anne,</line>
            <line>To leave this keen encounter of our wits,</line>
            <line>And fall somewhat into a slower method,</line>
            <line>Is not the causer of the timeless deaths</line>
            <line>Of these Plantagenets, Henry and Edward,</line>
            <line>As blameful as the executioner?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY ANNE</speaker>
            <line>Thou art the cause, and most accursed effect.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Your beauty was the cause of that effect;</line>
            <line>Your beauty: which did haunt me in my sleep</line>
            <line>To undertake the death of all the world,</line>
            <line>So I might live one hour in your sweet bosom.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY ANNE</speaker>
            <line>If I thought that, I tell thee, homicide,</line>
            <line>These nails should rend that beauty from my cheeks.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>These eyes could never endure sweet beauty's wreck;</line>
            <line>You should not blemish it, if I stood by:</line>
            <line>As all the world is cheered by the sun,</line>
            <line>So I by that; it is my day, my life.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY ANNE</speaker>
            <line>Black night o'ershade thy day, and death thy life!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Curse not thyself, fair creature thou art both.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY ANNE</speaker>
            <line>I would I were, to be revenged on thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>It is a quarrel most unnatural,</line>
            <line>To be revenged on him that loveth you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY ANNE</speaker>
            <line>It is a quarrel just and reasonable,</line>
            <line>To be revenged on him that slew my husband.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>He that bereft thee, lady, of thy husband,</line>
            <line>Did it to help thee to a better husband.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY ANNE</speaker>
            <line>His better doth not breathe upon the earth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>He lives that loves thee better than he could.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY ANNE</speaker>
            <line>Name him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Plantagenet.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY ANNE</speaker>
            <line>Why, that was he.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>The selfsame name, but one of better nature.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY ANNE</speaker>
            <line>Where is he?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Here.</line>
            <stagedir>She spitteth at him</stagedir>
            <line>Why dost thou spit at me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY ANNE</speaker>
            <line>Would it were mortal poison, for thy sake!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Never came poison from so sweet a place.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY ANNE</speaker>
            <line>Never hung poison on a fouler toad.</line>
            <line>Out of my sight! thou dost infect my eyes.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Thine eyes, sweet lady, have infected mine.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY ANNE</speaker>
            <line>Would they were basilisks, to strike thee dead!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>I would they were, that I might die at once;</line>
            <line>For now they kill me with a living death.</line>
            <line>Those eyes of thine from mine have drawn salt tears,</line>
            <line>Shamed their aspect with store of childish drops:</line>
            <line>These eyes that never shed remorseful tear,</line>
            <line>No, when my father York and Edward wept,</line>
            <line>To hear the piteous moan that Rutland made</line>
            <line>When black-faced Clifford shook his sword at him;</line>
            <line>Nor when thy warlike father, like a child,</line>
            <line>Told the sad story of my father's death,</line>
            <line>And twenty times made pause to sob and weep,</line>
            <line>That all the standers-by had wet their cheeks</line>
            <line>Like trees bedash'd with rain: in that sad time</line>
            <line>My manly eyes did scorn an humble tear;</line>
            <line>And what these sorrows could not thence exhale,</line>
            <line>Thy beauty hath, and made them blind with weeping.</line>
            <line>I never sued to friend nor enemy;</line>
            <line>My tongue could never learn sweet smoothing word;</line>
            <line>But now thy beauty is proposed my fee,</line>
            <line>My proud heart sues, and prompts my tongue to speak.</line>
            <stagedir>She looks scornfully at him</stagedir>
            <line>Teach not thy lips such scorn, for they were made</line>
            <line>For kissing, lady, not for such contempt.</line>
            <line>If thy revengeful heart cannot forgive,</line>
            <line>Lo, here I lend thee this sharp-pointed sword;</line>
            <line>Which if thou please to hide in this true bosom.</line>
            <line>And let the soul forth that adoreth thee,</line>
            <line>I lay it naked to the deadly stroke,</line>
            <line>And humbly beg the death upon my knee.</line>
            <stagedir>He lays his breast open: she offers at it with his sword</stagedir>
            <line>Nay, do not pause; for I did kill King Henry,</line>
            <line>But 'twas thy beauty that provoked me.</line>
            <line>Nay, now dispatch; 'twas I that stabb'd young Edward,</line>
            <line>But 'twas thy heavenly face that set me on.</line>
            <stagedir>Here she lets fall the sword</stagedir>
            <line>Take up the sword again, or take up me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY ANNE</speaker>
            <line>Arise, dissembler: though I wish thy death,</line>
            <line>I will not be the executioner.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Then bid me kill myself, and I will do it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY ANNE</speaker>
            <line>I have already.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Tush, that was in thy rage:</line>
            <line>Speak it again, and, even with the word,</line>
            <line>That hand, which, for thy love, did kill thy love,</line>
            <line>Shall, for thy love, kill a far truer love;</line>
            <line>To both their deaths thou shalt be accessary.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY ANNE</speaker>
            <line>I would I knew thy heart.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>'Tis figured in my tongue.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY ANNE</speaker>
            <line>I fear me both are false.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Then never man was true.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY ANNE</speaker>
            <line>Well, well, put up your sword.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Say, then, my peace is made.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY ANNE</speaker>
            <line>That shall you know hereafter.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>But shall I live in hope?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY ANNE</speaker>
            <line>All men, I hope, live so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Vouchsafe to wear this ring.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY ANNE</speaker>
            <line>To take is not to give.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Look, how this ring encompasseth finger.</line>
            <line>Even so thy breast encloseth my poor heart;</line>
            <line>Wear both of them, for both of them are thine.</line>
            <line>And if thy poor devoted suppliant may</line>
            <line>But beg one favour at thy gracious hand,</line>
            <line>Thou dost confirm his happiness for ever.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY ANNE</speaker>
            <line>What is it?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>That it would please thee leave these sad designs</line>
            <line>To him that hath more cause to be a mourner,</line>
            <line>And presently repair to Crosby Place;</line>
            <line>Where, after I have solemnly interr'd</line>
            <line>At Chertsey monastery this noble king,</line>
            <line>And wet his grave with my repentant tears,</line>
            <line>I will with all expedient duty see you:</line>
            <line>For divers unknown reasons. I beseech you,</line>
            <line>Grant me this boon.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY ANNE</speaker>
            <line>With all my heart; and much it joys me too,</line>
            <line>To see you are become so penitent.</line>
            <line>Tressel and Berkeley, go along with me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Bid me farewell.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY ANNE</speaker>
            <line>'Tis more than you deserve;</line>
            <line>But since you teach me how to flatter you,</line>
            <line>Imagine I have said farewell already.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt LADY ANNE, TRESSEL, and BERKELEY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Sirs, take up the corse.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GENTLEMEN</speaker>
            <line>Towards Chertsey, noble lord?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>No, to White-Friars; there attend my coining.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt all but GLOUCESTER</stagedir>
            <line>Was ever woman in this humour woo'd?</line>
            <line>Was ever woman in this humour won?</line>
            <line>I'll have her; but I will not keep her long.</line>
            <line>What! I, that kill'd her husband and his father,</line>
            <line>To take her in her heart's extremest hate,</line>
            <line>With curses in her mouth, tears in her eyes,</line>
            <line>The bleeding witness of her hatred by;</line>
            <line>Having God, her conscience, and these bars</line>
            <line>against me,</line>
            <line>And I nothing to back my suit at all,</line>
            <line>But the plain devil and dissembling looks,</line>
            <line>And yet to win her, all the world to nothing!</line>
            <line>Ha!</line>
            <line>Hath she forgot already that brave prince,</line>
            <line>Edward, her lord, whom I, some three months since,</line>
            <line>Stabb'd in my angry mood at Tewksbury?</line>
            <line>A sweeter and a lovelier gentleman,</line>
            <line>Framed in the prodigality of nature,</line>
            <line>Young, valiant, wise, and, no doubt, right royal,</line>
            <line>The spacious world cannot again afford</line>
            <line>And will she yet debase her eyes on me,</line>
            <line>That cropp'd the golden prime of this sweet prince,</line>
            <line>And made her widow to a woful bed?</line>
            <line>On me, whose all not equals Edward's moiety?</line>
            <line>On me, that halt and am unshapen thus?</line>
            <line>My dukedom to a beggarly denier,</line>
            <line>I do mistake my person all this while:</line>
            <line>Upon my life, she finds, although I cannot,</line>
            <line>Myself to be a marvellous proper man.</line>
            <line>I'll be at charges for a looking-glass,</line>
            <line>And entertain some score or two of tailors,</line>
            <line>To study fashions to adorn my body:</line>
            <line>Since I am crept in favour with myself,</line>
            <line>Will maintain it with some little cost.</line>
            <line>But first I'll turn yon fellow in his grave;</line>
            <line>And then return lamenting to my love.</line>
            <line>Shine out, fair sun, till I have bought a glass,</line>
            <line>That I may see my shadow as I pass.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  The palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter QUEEN ELIZABETH, RIVERS, and GREY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RIVERS</speaker>
            <line>Have patience, madam: there's no doubt his majesty</line>
            <line>Will soon recover his accustom'd health.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GREY</speaker>
            <line>In that you brook it in, it makes him worse:</line>
            <line>Therefore, for God's sake, entertain good comfort,</line>
            <line>And cheer his grace with quick and merry words.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>If he were dead, what would betide of me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RIVERS</speaker>
            <line>No other harm but loss of such a lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>The loss of such a lord includes all harm.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GREY</speaker>
            <line>The heavens have bless'd you with a goodly son,</line>
            <line>To be your comforter when he is gone.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>Oh, he is young and his minority</line>
            <line>Is put unto the trust of Richard Gloucester,</line>
            <line>A man that loves not me, nor none of you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RIVERS</speaker>
            <line>Is it concluded that he shall be protector?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>It is determined, not concluded yet:</line>
            <line>But so it must be, if the king miscarry.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter BUCKINGHAM and DERBY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GREY</speaker>
            <line>Here come the lords of Buckingham and Derby.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Good time of day unto your royal grace!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DERBY</speaker>
            <line>God make your majesty joyful as you have been!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>The Countess Richmond, good my Lord of Derby.</line>
            <line>To your good prayers will scarcely say amen.</line>
            <line>Yet, Derby, notwithstanding she's your wife,</line>
            <line>And loves not me, be you, good lord, assured</line>
            <line>I hate not you for her proud arrogance.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DERBY</speaker>
            <line>I do beseech you, either not believe</line>
            <line>The envious slanders of her false accusers;</line>
            <line>Or, if she be accused in true report,</line>
            <line>Bear with her weakness, which, I think proceeds</line>
            <line>From wayward sickness, and no grounded malice.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RIVERS</speaker>
            <line>Saw you the king to-day, my Lord of Derby?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DERBY</speaker>
            <line>But now the Duke of Buckingham and I</line>
            <line>Are come from visiting his majesty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>What likelihood of his amendment, lords?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Madam, good hope; his grace speaks cheerfully.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>God grant him health! Did you confer with him?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Madam, we did: he desires to make atonement</line>
            <line>Betwixt the Duke of Gloucester and your brothers,</line>
            <line>And betwixt them and my lord chamberlain;</line>
            <line>And sent to warn them to his royal presence.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>Would all were well! but that will never be</line>
            <line>I fear our happiness is at the highest.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter GLOUCESTER, HASTINGS, and DORSET</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>They do me wrong, and I will not endure it:</line>
            <line>Who are they that complain unto the king,</line>
            <line>That I, forsooth, am stern, and love them not?</line>
            <line>By holy Paul, they love his grace but lightly</line>
            <line>That fill his ears with such dissentious rumours.</line>
            <line>Because I cannot flatter and speak fair,</line>
            <line>Smile in men's faces, smooth, deceive and cog,</line>
            <line>Duck with French nods and apish courtesy,</line>
            <line>I must be held a rancorous enemy.</line>
            <line>Cannot a plain man live and think no harm,</line>
            <line>But thus his simple truth must be abused</line>
            <line>By silken, sly, insinuating Jacks?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RIVERS</speaker>
            <line>To whom in all this presence speaks your grace?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>To thee, that hast nor honesty nor grace.</line>
            <line>When have I injured thee? when done thee wrong?</line>
            <line>Or thee? or thee? or any of your faction?</line>
            <line>A plague upon you all! His royal person,--</line>
            <line>Whom God preserve better than you would wish!--</line>
            <line>Cannot be quiet scarce a breathing-while,</line>
            <line>But you must trouble him with lewd complaints.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>Brother of Gloucester, you mistake the matter.</line>
            <line>The king, of his own royal disposition,</line>
            <line>And not provoked by any suitor else;</line>
            <line>Aiming, belike, at your interior hatred,</line>
            <line>Which in your outward actions shows itself</line>
            <line>Against my kindred, brothers, and myself,</line>
            <line>Makes him to send; that thereby he may gather</line>
            <line>The ground of your ill-will, and so remove it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>I cannot tell: the world is grown so bad,</line>
            <line>That wrens make prey where eagles dare not perch:</line>
            <line>Since every Jack became a gentleman</line>
            <line>There's many a gentle person made a Jack.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>Come, come, we know your meaning, brother</line>
            <line>Gloucester;</line>
            <line>You envy my advancement and my friends':</line>
            <line>God grant we never may have need of you!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Meantime, God grants that we have need of you:</line>
            <line>Your brother is imprison'd by your means,</line>
            <line>Myself disgraced, and the nobility</line>
            <line>Held in contempt; whilst many fair promotions</line>
            <line>Are daily given to ennoble those</line>
            <line>That scarce, some two days since, were worth a noble.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>By Him that raised me to this careful height</line>
            <line>From that contented hap which I enjoy'd,</line>
            <line>I never did incense his majesty</line>
            <line>Against the Duke of Clarence, but have been</line>
            <line>An earnest advocate to plead for him.</line>
            <line>My lord, you do me shameful injury,</line>
            <line>Falsely to draw me in these vile suspects.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>You may deny that you were not the cause</line>
            <line>Of my Lord Hastings' late imprisonment.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RIVERS</speaker>
            <line>She may, my lord, for--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>She may, Lord Rivers! why, who knows not so?</line>
            <line>She may do more, sir, than denying that:</line>
            <line>She may help you to many fair preferments,</line>
            <line>And then deny her aiding hand therein,</line>
            <line>And lay those honours on your high deserts.</line>
            <line>What may she not? She may, yea, marry, may she--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RIVERS</speaker>
            <line>What, marry, may she?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>What, marry, may she! marry with a king,</line>
            <line>A bachelor, a handsome stripling too:</line>
            <line>I wis your grandam had a worser match.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>My Lord of Gloucester, I have too long borne</line>
            <line>Your blunt upbraidings and your bitter scoffs:</line>
            <line>By heaven, I will acquaint his majesty</line>
            <line>With those gross taunts I often have endured.</line>
            <line>I had rather be a country servant-maid</line>
            <line>Than a great queen, with this condition,</line>
            <line>To be thus taunted, scorn'd, and baited at:</line>
            <stagedir>Enter QUEEN MARGARET, behind</stagedir>
            <line>Small joy have I in being England's queen.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>And lessen'd be that small, God, I beseech thee!</line>
            <line>Thy honour, state and seat is due to me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>What! threat you me with telling of the king?</line>
            <line>Tell him, and spare not: look, what I have said</line>
            <line>I will avouch in presence of the king:</line>
            <line>I dare adventure to be sent to the Tower.</line>
            <line>'Tis time to speak; my pains are quite forgot.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Out, devil! I remember them too well:</line>
            <line>Thou slewest my husband Henry in the Tower,</line>
            <line>And Edward, my poor son, at Tewksbury.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Ere you were queen, yea, or your husband king,</line>
            <line>I was a pack-horse in his great affairs;</line>
            <line>A weeder-out of his proud adversaries,</line>
            <line>A liberal rewarder of his friends:</line>
            <line>To royalize his blood I spilt mine own.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Yea, and much better blood than his or thine.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>In all which time you and your husband Grey</line>
            <line>Were factious for the house of Lancaster;</line>
            <line>And, Rivers, so were you. Was not your husband</line>
            <line>In Margaret's battle at Saint Alban's slain?</line>
            <line>Let me put in your minds, if you forget,</line>
            <line>What you have been ere now, and what you are;</line>
            <line>Withal, what I have been, and what I am.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>A murderous villain, and so still thou art.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Poor Clarence did forsake his father, Warwick;</line>
            <line>Yea, and forswore himself,--which Jesu pardon!--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Which God revenge!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>To fight on Edward's party for the crown;</line>
            <line>And for his meed, poor lord, he is mew'd up.</line>
            <line>I would to God my heart were flint, like Edward's;</line>
            <line>Or Edward's soft and pitiful, like mine</line>
            <line>I am too childish-foolish for this world.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Hie thee to hell for shame, and leave the world,</line>
            <line>Thou cacodemon! there thy kingdom is.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RIVERS</speaker>
            <line>My Lord of Gloucester, in those busy days</line>
            <line>Which here you urge to prove us enemies,</line>
            <line>We follow'd then our lord, our lawful king:</line>
            <line>So should we you, if you should be our king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>If I should be! I had rather be a pedlar:</line>
            <line>Far be it from my heart, the thought of it!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>As little joy, my lord, as you suppose</line>
            <line>You should enjoy, were you this country's king,</line>
            <line>As little joy may you suppose in me.</line>
            <line>That I enjoy, being the queen thereof.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>A little joy enjoys the queen thereof;</line>
            <line>For I am she, and altogether joyless.</line>
            <line>I can no longer hold me patient.</line>
            <stagedir>Advancing</stagedir>
            <line>Hear me, you wrangling pirates, that fall out</line>
            <line>In sharing that which you have pill'd from me!</line>
            <line>Which of you trembles not that looks on me?</line>
            <line>If not, that, I being queen, you bow like subjects,</line>
            <line>Yet that, by you deposed, you quake like rebels?</line>
            <line>O gentle villain, do not turn away!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Foul wrinkled witch, what makest thou in my sight?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>But repetition of what thou hast marr'd;</line>
            <line>That will I make before I let thee go.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Wert thou not banished on pain of death?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>I was; but I do find more pain in banishment</line>
            <line>Than death can yield me here by my abode.</line>
            <line>A husband and a son thou owest to me;</line>
            <line>And thou a kingdom; all of you allegiance:</line>
            <line>The sorrow that I have, by right is yours,</line>
            <line>And all the pleasures you usurp are mine.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>The curse my noble father laid on thee,</line>
            <line>When thou didst crown his warlike brows with paper</line>
            <line>And with thy scorns drew'st rivers from his eyes,</line>
            <line>And then, to dry them, gavest the duke a clout</line>
            <line>Steep'd in the faultless blood of pretty Rutland--</line>
            <line>His curses, then from bitterness of soul</line>
            <line>Denounced against thee, are all fall'n upon thee;</line>
            <line>And God, not we, hath plagued thy bloody deed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>So just is God, to right the innocent.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>O, 'twas the foulest deed to slay that babe,</line>
            <line>And the most merciless that e'er was heard of!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RIVERS</speaker>
            <line>Tyrants themselves wept when it was reported.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DORSET</speaker>
            <line>No man but prophesied revenge for it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Northumberland, then present, wept to see it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>What were you snarling all before I came,</line>
            <line>Ready to catch each other by the throat,</line>
            <line>And turn you all your hatred now on me?</line>
            <line>Did York's dread curse prevail so much with heaven?</line>
            <line>That Henry's death, my lovely Edward's death,</line>
            <line>Their kingdom's loss, my woful banishment,</line>
            <line>Could all but answer for that peevish brat?</line>
            <line>Can curses pierce the clouds and enter heaven?</line>
            <line>Why, then, give way, dull clouds, to my quick curses!</line>
            <line>If not by war, by surfeit die your king,</line>
            <line>As ours by murder, to make him a king!</line>
            <line>Edward thy son, which now is Prince of Wales,</line>
            <line>For Edward my son, which was Prince of Wales,</line>
            <line>Die in his youth by like untimely violence!</line>
            <line>Thyself a queen, for me that was a queen,</line>
            <line>Outlive thy glory, like my wretched self!</line>
            <line>Long mayst thou live to wail thy children's loss;</line>
            <line>And see another, as I see thee now,</line>
            <line>Deck'd in thy rights, as thou art stall'd in mine!</line>
            <line>Long die thy happy days before thy death;</line>
            <line>And, after many lengthen'd hours of grief,</line>
            <line>Die neither mother, wife, nor England's queen!</line>
            <line>Rivers and Dorset, you were standers by,</line>
            <line>And so wast thou, Lord Hastings, when my son</line>
            <line>Was stabb'd with bloody daggers: God, I pray him,</line>
            <line>That none of you may live your natural age,</line>
            <line>But by some unlook'd accident cut off!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Have done thy charm, thou hateful wither'd hag!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>And leave out thee? stay, dog, for thou shalt hear me.</line>
            <line>If heaven have any grievous plague in store</line>
            <line>Exceeding those that I can wish upon thee,</line>
            <line>O, let them keep it till thy sins be ripe,</line>
            <line>And then hurl down their indignation</line>
            <line>On thee, the troubler of the poor world's peace!</line>
            <line>The worm of conscience still begnaw thy soul!</line>
            <line>Thy friends suspect for traitors while thou livest,</line>
            <line>And take deep traitors for thy dearest friends!</line>
            <line>No sleep close up that deadly eye of thine,</line>
            <line>Unless it be whilst some tormenting dream</line>
            <line>Affrights thee with a hell of ugly devils!</line>
            <line>Thou elvish-mark'd, abortive, rooting hog!</line>
            <line>Thou that wast seal'd in thy nativity</line>
            <line>The slave of nature and the son of hell!</line>
            <line>Thou slander of thy mother's heavy womb!</line>
            <line>Thou loathed issue of thy father's loins!</line>
            <line>Thou rag of honour! thou detested--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Margaret.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Richard!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Ha!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>I call thee not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>I cry thee mercy then, for I had thought</line>
            <line>That thou hadst call'd me all these bitter names.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Why, so I did; but look'd for no reply.</line>
            <line>O, let me make the period to my curse!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>'Tis done by me, and ends in 'Margaret.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>Thus have you breathed your curse against yourself.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Poor painted queen, vain flourish of my fortune!</line>
            <line>Why strew'st thou sugar on that bottled spider,</line>
            <line>Whose deadly web ensnareth thee about?</line>
            <line>Fool, fool! thou whet'st a knife to kill thyself.</line>
            <line>The time will come when thou shalt wish for me</line>
            <line>To help thee curse that poisonous bunchback'd toad.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>False-boding woman, end thy frantic curse,</line>
            <line>Lest to thy harm thou move our patience.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Foul shame upon you! you have all moved mine.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RIVERS</speaker>
            <line>Were you well served, you would be taught your duty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>To serve me well, you all should do me duty,</line>
            <line>Teach me to be your queen, and you my subjects:</line>
            <line>O, serve me well, and teach yourselves that duty!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DORSET</speaker>
            <line>Dispute not with her; she is lunatic.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Peace, master marquess, you are malapert:</line>
            <line>Your fire-new stamp of honour is scarce current.</line>
            <line>O, that your young nobility could judge</line>
            <line>What 'twere to lose it, and be miserable!</line>
            <line>They that stand high have many blasts to shake them;</line>
            <line>And if they fall, they dash themselves to pieces.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Good counsel, marry: learn it, learn it, marquess.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DORSET</speaker>
            <line>It toucheth you, my lord, as much as me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Yea, and much more: but I was born so high,</line>
            <line>Our aery buildeth in the cedar's top,</line>
            <line>And dallies with the wind and scorns the sun.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>And turns the sun to shade; alas! alas!</line>
            <line>Witness my son, now in the shade of death;</line>
            <line>Whose bright out-shining beams thy cloudy wrath</line>
            <line>Hath in eternal darkness folded up.</line>
            <line>Your aery buildeth in our aery's nest.</line>
            <line>O God, that seest it, do not suffer it!</line>
            <line>As it was won with blood, lost be it so!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Have done! for shame, if not for charity.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Urge neither charity nor shame to me:</line>
            <line>Uncharitably with me have you dealt,</line>
            <line>And shamefully by you my hopes are butcher'd.</line>
            <line>My charity is outrage, life my shame</line>
            <line>And in that shame still live my sorrow's rage.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Have done, have done.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>O princely Buckingham I'll kiss thy hand,</line>
            <line>In sign of league and amity with thee:</line>
            <line>Now fair befal thee and thy noble house!</line>
            <line>Thy garments are not spotted with our blood,</line>
            <line>Nor thou within the compass of my curse.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Nor no one here; for curses never pass</line>
            <line>The lips of those that breathe them in the air.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>I'll not believe but they ascend the sky,</line>
            <line>And there awake God's gentle-sleeping peace.</line>
            <line>O Buckingham, take heed of yonder dog!</line>
            <line>Look, when he fawns, he bites; and when he bites,</line>
            <line>His venom tooth will rankle to the death:</line>
            <line>Have not to do with him, beware of him;</line>
            <line>Sin, death, and hell have set their marks on him,</line>
            <line>And all their ministers attend on him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>What doth she say, my Lord of Buckingham?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Nothing that I respect, my gracious lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>What, dost thou scorn me for my gentle counsel?</line>
            <line>And soothe the devil that I warn thee from?</line>
            <line>O, but remember this another day,</line>
            <line>When he shall split thy very heart with sorrow,</line>
            <line>And say poor Margaret was a prophetess!</line>
            <line>Live each of you the subjects to his hate,</line>
            <line>And he to yours, and all of you to God's!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>My hair doth stand on end to hear her curses.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RIVERS</speaker>
            <line>And so doth mine: I muse why she's at liberty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>I cannot blame her: by God's holy mother,</line>
            <line>She hath had too much wrong; and I repent</line>
            <line>My part thereof that I have done to her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>I never did her any, to my knowledge.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>But you have all the vantage of her wrong.</line>
            <line>I was too hot to do somebody good,</line>
            <line>That is too cold in thinking of it now.</line>
            <line>Marry, as for Clarence, he is well repaid,</line>
            <line>He is frank'd up to fatting for his pains</line>
            <line>God pardon them that are the cause of it!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RIVERS</speaker>
            <line>A virtuous and a Christian-like conclusion,</line>
            <line>To pray for them that have done scathe to us.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>So do I ever:</line>
            <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>
            <line>being well-advised.</line>
            <line>For had I cursed now, I had cursed myself.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter CATESBY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CATESBY</speaker>
            <line>Madam, his majesty doth call for you,</line>
            <line>And for your grace; and you, my noble lords.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN ELIZABETH</speaker>
            <line>Catesby, we come. Lords, will you go with us?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RIVERS</speaker>
            <line>Madam, we will attend your grace.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt all but GLOUCESTER</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>I do the wrong, and first begin to brawl.</line>
            <line>The secret mischiefs that I set abroach</line>
            <line>I lay unto the grievous charge of others.</line>
            <line>Clarence, whom I, indeed, have laid in darkness,</line>
            <line>I do beweep to many simple gulls</line>
            <line>Namely, to Hastings, Derby, Buckingham;</line>
            <line>And say it is the queen and her allies</line>
            <line>That stir the king against the duke my brother.</line>
            <line>Now, they believe it; and withal whet me</line>
            <line>To be revenged on Rivers, Vaughan, Grey:</line>
            <line>But then I sigh; and, with a piece of scripture,</line>
            <line>Tell them that God bids us do good for evil:</line>
            <line>And thus I clothe my naked villany</line>
            <line>With old odd ends stolen out of holy writ;</line>
            <line>And seem a saint, when most I play the devil.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter two Murderers</stagedir>
            <line>But, soft! here come my executioners.</line>
            <line>How now, my hardy, stout resolved mates!</line>
            <line>Are you now going to dispatch this deed?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Murderer</speaker>
            <line>We are, my lord; and come to have the warrant</line>
            <line>That we may be admitted where he is.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Well thought upon; I have it here about me.</line>
            <stagedir>Gives the warrant</stagedir>
            <line>When you have done, repair to Crosby Place.</line>
            <line>But, sirs, be sudden in the execution,</line>
            <line>Withal obdurate, do not hear him plead;</line>
            <line>For Clarence is well-spoken, and perhaps</line>
            <line>May move your hearts to pity if you mark him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Murderer</speaker>
            <line>Tush!</line>
            <line>Fear not, my lord, we will not stand to prate;</line>
            <line>Talkers are no good doers: be assured</line>
            <line>We come to use our hands and not our tongues.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Your eyes drop millstones, when fools' eyes drop tears:</line>
            <line>I like you, lads; about your business straight;</line>
            <line>Go, go, dispatch.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Murderer</speaker>
            <line>We will, my noble lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-4">
      <title>SCENE IV.  London. The Tower.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter CLARENCE and BRAKENBURY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRAKENBURY</speaker>
            <line>Why looks your grace so heavily today?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>O, I have pass'd a miserable night,</line>
            <line>So full of ugly sights, of ghastly dreams,</line>
            <line>That, as I am a Christian faithful man,</line>
            <line>I would not spend another such a night,</line>
            <line>Though 'twere to buy a world of happy days,</line>
            <line>So full of dismal terror was the time!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRAKENBURY</speaker>
            <line>What was your dream? I long to hear you tell it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>Methoughts that I had broken from the Tower,</line>
            <line>And was embark'd to cross to Burgundy;</line>
            <line>And, in my company, my brother Gloucester;</line>
            <line>Who from my cabin tempted me to walk</line>
            <line>Upon the hatches: thence we looked toward England,</line>
            <line>And cited up a thousand fearful times,</line>
            <line>During the wars of York and Lancaster</line>
            <line>That had befall'n us. As we paced along</line>
            <line>Upon the giddy footing of the hatches,</line>
            <line>Methought that Gloucester stumbled; and, in falling,</line>
            <line>Struck me, that thought to stay him, overboard,</line>
            <line>Into the tumbling billows of the main.</line>
            <line>Lord, Lord! methought, what pain it was to drown!</line>
            <line>What dreadful noise of waters in mine ears!</line>
            <line>What ugly sights of death within mine eyes!</line>
            <line>Methought I saw a thousand fearful wrecks;</line>
            <line>Ten thousand men that fishes gnaw'd upon;</line>
            <line>Wedges of gold, great anchors, heaps of pearl,</line>
            <line>Inestimable stones, unvalued jewels,</line>
            <line>All scatter'd in the bottom of the sea:</line>
            <line>Some lay in dead men's skulls; and, in those holes</line>
            <line>Where eyes did once inhabit, there were crept,</line>
            <line>As 'twere in scorn of eyes, reflecting gems,</line>
            <line>Which woo'd the slimy bottom of the deep,</line>
            <line>And mock'd the dead bones that lay scatter'd by.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRAKENBURY</speaker>
            <line>Had you such leisure in the time of death</line>
            <line>To gaze upon the secrets of the deep?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>Methought I had; and often did I strive</line>
            <line>To yield the ghost: but still the envious flood</line>
            <line>Kept in my soul, and would not let it forth</line>
            <line>To seek the empty, vast and wandering air;</line>
            <line>But smother'd it within my panting bulk,</line>
            <line>Which almost burst to belch it in the sea.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRAKENBURY</speaker>
            <line>Awaked you not with this sore agony?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>O, no, my dream was lengthen'd after life;</line>
            <line>O, then began the tempest to my soul,</line>
            <line>Who pass'd, methought, the melancholy flood,</line>
            <line>With that grim ferryman which poets write of,</line>
            <line>Unto the kingdom of perpetual night.</line>
            <line>The first that there did greet my stranger soul,</line>
            <line>Was my great father-in-law, renowned Warwick;</line>
            <line>Who cried aloud, 'What scourge for perjury</line>
            <line>Can this dark monarchy afford false Clarence?'</line>
            <line>And so he vanish'd: then came wandering by</line>
            <line>A shadow like an angel, with bright hair</line>
            <line>Dabbled in blood; and he squeak'd out aloud,</line>
            <line>'Clarence is come; false, fleeting, perjured Clarence,</line>
            <line>That stabb'd me in the field by Tewksbury;</line>
            <line>Seize on him, Furies, take him to your torments!'</line>
            <line>With that, methoughts, a legion of foul fiends</line>
            <line>Environ'd me about, and howled in mine ears</line>
            <line>Such hideous cries, that with the very noise</line>
            <line>I trembling waked, and for a season after</line>
            <line>Could not believe but that I was in hell,</line>
            <line>Such terrible impression made the dream.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRAKENBURY</speaker>
            <line>No marvel, my lord, though it affrighted you;</line>
            <line>I promise, I am afraid to hear you tell it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>O Brakenbury, I have done those things,</line>
            <line>Which now bear evidence against my soul,</line>
            <line>For Edward's sake; and see how he requites me!</line>
            <line>O God! if my deep prayers cannot appease thee,</line>
            <line>But thou wilt be avenged on my misdeeds,</line>
            <line>Yet execute thy wrath in me alone,</line>
            <line>O, spare my guiltless wife and my poor children!</line>
            <line>I pray thee, gentle keeper, stay by me;</line>
            <line>My soul is heavy, and I fain would sleep.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRAKENBURY</speaker>
            <line>I will, my lord: God give your grace good rest!</line>
            <stagedir>CLARENCE sleeps</stagedir>
            <line>Sorrow breaks seasons and reposing hours,</line>
            <line>Makes the night morning, and the noon-tide night.</line>
            <line>Princes have but their tides for their glories,</line>
            <line>An outward honour for an inward toil;</line>
            <line>And, for unfelt imagination,</line>
            <line>They often feel a world of restless cares:</line>
            <line>So that, betwixt their tides and low names,</line>
            <line>There's nothing differs but the outward fame.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter the two Murderers</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Murderer</speaker>
            <line>Ho! who's here?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRAKENBURY</speaker>
            <line>In God's name what are you, and how came you hither?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Murderer</speaker>
            <line>I would speak with Clarence, and I came hither on my legs.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRAKENBURY</speaker>
            <line>Yea, are you so brief?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Murderer</speaker>
            <line>O sir, it is better to be brief than tedious. Show</line>
            <line>him our commission; talk no more.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>BRAKENBURY reads it</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRAKENBURY</speaker>
            <line>I am, in this, commanded to deliver</line>
            <line>The noble Duke of Clarence to your hands:</line>
            <line>I will not reason what is meant hereby,</line>
            <line>Because I will be guiltless of the meaning.</line>
            <line>Here are the keys, there sits the duke asleep:</line>
            <line>I'll to the king; and signify to him</line>
            <line>That thus I have resign'd my charge to you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Murderer</speaker>
            <line>Do so, it is a point of wisdom: fare you well.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit BRAKENBURY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Murderer</speaker>
            <line>What, shall we stab him as he sleeps?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Murderer</speaker>
            <line>No; then he will say 'twas done cowardly, when he wakes.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Murderer</speaker>
            <line>When he wakes! why, fool, he shall never wake till</line>
            <line>the judgment-day.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Murderer</speaker>
            <line>Why, then he will say we stabbed him sleeping.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Murderer</speaker>
            <line>The urging of that word 'judgment' hath bred a kind</line>
            <line>of remorse in me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Murderer</speaker>
            <line>What, art thou afraid?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Murderer</speaker>
            <line>Not to kill him, having a warrant for it; but to be</line>
            <line>damned for killing him, from which no warrant can defend us.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Murderer</speaker>
            <line>I thought thou hadst been resolute.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Murderer</speaker>
            <line>So I am, to let him live.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Murderer</speaker>
            <line>Back to the Duke of Gloucester, tell him so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Murderer</speaker>
            <line>I pray thee, stay a while: I hope my holy humour</line>
            <line>will change; 'twas wont to hold me but while one</line>
            <line>would tell twenty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Murderer</speaker>
            <line>How dost thou feel thyself now?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Murderer</speaker>
            <line>'Faith, some certain dregs of conscience are yet</line>
            <line>within me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Murderer</speaker>
            <line>Remember our reward, when the deed is done.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Murderer</speaker>
            <line>'Zounds, he dies: I had forgot the reward.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Murderer</speaker>
            <line>Where is thy conscience now?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Murderer</speaker>
            <line>In the Duke of Gloucester's purse.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Murderer</speaker>
            <line>So when he opens his purse to give us our reward,</line>
            <line>thy conscience flies out.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Murderer</speaker>
            <line>Let it go; there's few or none will entertain it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Murderer</speaker>
            <line>How if it come to thee again?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Murderer</speaker>
            <line>I'll not meddle with it: it is a dangerous thing: it</line>
            <line>makes a man a coward: a man cannot steal, but it</line>
            <line>accuseth him; he cannot swear, but it cheques him;</line>
            <line>he cannot lie with his neighbour's wife, but it</line>
            <line>detects him: 'tis a blushing shamefast spirit that</line>
            <line>mutinies in a man's bosom; it fills one full of</line>
            <line>obstacles: it made me once restore a purse of gold</line>
            <line>that I found; it beggars any man that keeps it: it</line>
            <line>is turned out of all towns and cities for a</line>
            <line>dangerous thing; and every man that means to live</line>
            <line>well endeavours to trust to himself and to live</line>
            <line>without it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Murderer</speaker>
            <line>'Zounds, it is even now at my elbow, persuading me</line>
            <line>not to kill the duke.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Murderer</speaker>
            <line>Take the devil in thy mind, and relieve him not: he</line>
            <line>would insinuate with thee but to make thee sigh.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Murderer</speaker>
            <line>Tut, I am strong-framed, he cannot prevail with me,</line>
            <line>I warrant thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Murderer</speaker>
            <line>Spoke like a tail fellow that respects his</line>
            <line>reputation. Come, shall we to this gear?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Murderer</speaker>
            <line>Take him over the costard with the hilts of thy</line>
            <line>sword, and then we will chop him in the malmsey-butt</line>
            <line>in the next room.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Murderer</speaker>
            <line>O excellent devise! make a sop of him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Murderer</speaker>
            <line>Hark! he stirs: shall I strike?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Murderer</speaker>
            <line>No, first let's reason with him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>Where art thou, keeper? give me a cup of wine.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second murderer</speaker>
            <line>You shall have wine enough, my lord, anon.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>In God's name, what art thou?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Murderer</speaker>
            <line>A man, as you are.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>But not, as I am, royal.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Murderer</speaker>
            <line>Nor you, as we are, loyal.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>Thy voice is thunder, but thy looks are humble.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Murderer</speaker>
            <line>My voice is now the king's, my looks mine own.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>How darkly and how deadly dost thou speak!</line>
            <line>Your eyes do menace me: why look you pale?</line>
            <line>Who sent you hither? Wherefore do you come?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Both</speaker>
            <line>To, to, to--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>To murder me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Both</speaker>
            <line>Ay, ay.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>You scarcely have the hearts to tell me so,</line>
            <line>And therefore cannot have the hearts to do it.</line>
            <line>Wherein, my friends, have I offended you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Murderer</speaker>
            <line>Offended us you have not, but the king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>I shall be reconciled to him again.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Murderer</speaker>
            <line>Never, my lord; therefore prepare to die.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>Are you call'd forth from out a world of men</line>
            <line>To slay the innocent? What is my offence?</line>
            <line>Where are the evidence that do accuse me?</line>
            <line>What lawful quest have given their verdict up</line>
            <line>Unto the frowning judge? or who pronounced</line>
            <line>The bitter sentence of poor Clarence' death?</line>
            <line>Before I be convict by course of law,</line>
            <line>To threaten me with death is most unlawful.</line>
            <line>I charge you, as you hope to have redemption</line>
            <line>By Christ's dear blood shed for our grievous sins,</line>
            <line>That you depart and lay no hands on me</line>
            <line>The deed you undertake is damnable.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Murderer</speaker>
            <line>What we will do, we do upon command.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Murderer</speaker>
            <line>And he that hath commanded is the king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>Erroneous vassal! the great King of kings</line>
            <line>Hath in the tables of his law commanded</line>
            <line>That thou shalt do no murder: and wilt thou, then,</line>
            <line>Spurn at his edict and fulfil a man's?</line>
            <line>Take heed; for he holds vengeance in his hands,</line>
            <line>To hurl upon their heads that break his law.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Murderer</speaker>
            <line>And that same vengeance doth he hurl on thee,</line>
            <line>For false forswearing and for murder too:</line>
            <line>Thou didst receive the holy sacrament,</line>
            <line>To fight in quarrel of the house of Lancaster.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Murderer</speaker>
            <line>And, like a traitor to the name of God,</line>
            <line>Didst break that vow; and with thy treacherous blade</line>
            <line>Unrip'dst the bowels of thy sovereign's son.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Murderer</speaker>
            <line>Whom thou wert sworn to cherish and defend.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Murderer</speaker>
            <line>How canst thou urge God's dreadful law to us,</line>
            <line>When thou hast broke it in so dear degree?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>Alas! for whose sake did I that ill deed?</line>
            <line>For Edward, for my brother, for his sake: Why, sirs,</line>
            <line>He sends ye not to murder me for this</line>
            <line>For in this sin he is as deep as I.</line>
            <line>If God will be revenged for this deed.</line>
            <line>O, know you yet, he doth it publicly,</line>
            <line>Take not the quarrel from his powerful arm;</line>
            <line>He needs no indirect nor lawless course</line>
            <line>To cut off those that have offended him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Murderer</speaker>
            <line>Who made thee, then, a bloody minister,</line>
            <line>When gallant-springing brave Plantagenet,</line>
            <line>That princely novice, was struck dead by thee?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>My brother's love, the devil, and my rage.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Murderer</speaker>
            <line>Thy brother's love, our duty, and thy fault,</line>
            <line>Provoke us hither now to slaughter thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>Oh, if you love my brother, hate not me;</line>
            <line>I am his brother, and I love him well.</line>
            <line>If you be hired for meed, go back again,</line>
            <line>And I will send you to my brother Gloucester,</line>
            <line>Who shall reward you better for my life</line>
            <line>Than Edward will for tidings of my death.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Murderer</speaker>
            <line>You are deceived, your brother Gloucester hates you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>O, no, he loves me, and he holds me dear:</line>
            <line>Go you to him from me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Both</speaker>
            <line>Ay, so we will.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>Tell him, when that our princely father York</line>
            <line>Bless'd his three sons with his victorious arm,</line>
            <line>And charged us from his soul to love each other,</line>
            <line>He little thought of this divided friendship:</line>
            <line>Bid Gloucester think of this, and he will weep.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Murderer</speaker>
            <line>Ay, millstones; as be lesson'd us to weep.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>O, do not slander him, for he is kind.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Murderer</speaker>
            <line>Right,</line>
            <line>As snow in harvest. Thou deceivest thyself:</line>
            <line>'Tis he that sent us hither now to slaughter thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>It cannot be; for when I parted with him,</line>
            <line>He hugg'd me in his arms, and swore, with sobs,</line>
            <line>That he would labour my delivery.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Murderer</speaker>
            <line>Why, so he doth, now he delivers thee</line>
            <line>From this world's thraldom to the joys of heaven.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Murderer</speaker>
            <line>Make peace with God, for you must die, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>Hast thou that holy feeling in thy soul,</line>
            <line>To counsel me to make my peace with God,</line>
            <line>And art thou yet to thy own soul so blind,</line>
            <line>That thou wilt war with God by murdering me?</line>
            <line>Ah, sirs, consider, he that set you on</line>
            <line>To do this deed will hate you for the deed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Murderer</speaker>
            <line>What shall we do?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>Relent, and save your souls.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Murderer</speaker>
            <line>Relent! 'tis cowardly and womanish.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLARENCE</speaker>
            <line>Not to relent is beastly, savage, devilish.</line>
            <line>Which of you, if you were a prince's son,</line>
            <line>Being pent from liberty, as I am now,</line>
            <line>if two such murderers as yourselves came to you,</line>
            <line>Would not entreat for life?</line>
            <line>My friend, I spy some pity in thy looks:</line>
            <line>O, if thine eye be not a flatterer,</line>
            <line>Come thou on my side, and entreat for me,</line>
            <line>As you would beg, were you in my distress</line>
            <line>A begging prince what beggar pities not?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Murderer</speaker>
            <line>Look behind you, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Murderer</speaker>
            <line>Take that, and that: if all this will not do,</line>
            <stagedir>Stabs him</stagedir>
            <line>I'll drown you in the malmsey-butt within.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit, with the body</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Murderer</speaker>
            <line>A bloody deed, and desperately dispatch'd!</line>
            <line>How fain, like Pilate, would I wash my hands</line>
            <line>Of this most grievous guilty murder done!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter First Murderer</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Murderer</speaker>
            <line>How now! what mean'st thou, that thou help'st me not?</line>
            <line>By heavens, the duke shall know how slack thou art!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Murderer</speaker>
            <line>I would he knew that I had saved his brother!</line>
            <line>Take thou the fee, and tell him what I say;</line>
            <line>For I repent me that the duke is slain.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Murderer</speaker>
            <line>So do not I: go, coward as thou art.</line>
            <line>Now must I hide his body in some hole,</line>
            <line>Until the duke take order for his burial:</line>
            <line>And when I have my meed, I must away;</line>
            <line>For this will out, and here I must not stay.</line>
         </speech>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>