<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net/doctypes/dita/shakespear/dtd/act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-3">
   <title>ACT III</title>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  London. A street.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>The trumpets sound. Enter the young PRINCE EDWARD,
GLOUCESTER, BUCKINGHAM, CARDINAL, CATESBY, and others</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Welcome, sweet prince, to London, to your chamber.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Welcome, dear cousin, my thoughts' sovereign</line>
            <line>The weary way hath made you melancholy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>No, uncle; but our crosses on the way</line>
            <line>Have made it tedious, wearisome, and heavy</line>
            <line>I want more uncles here to welcome me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Sweet prince, the untainted virtue of your years</line>
            <line>Hath not yet dived into the world's deceit</line>
            <line>Nor more can you distinguish of a man</line>
            <line>Than of his outward show; which, God he knows,</line>
            <line>Seldom or never jumpeth with the heart.</line>
            <line>Those uncles which you want were dangerous;</line>
            <line>Your grace attended to their sugar'd words,</line>
            <line>But look'd not on the poison of their hearts :</line>
            <line>God keep you from them, and from such false friends!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>God keep me from false friends! but they were none.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>My lord, the mayor of London comes to greet you.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter the Lord Mayor and his train</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord Mayor</speaker>
            <line>God bless your grace with health and happy days!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>I thank you, good my lord; and thank you all.</line>
            <line>I thought my mother, and my brother York,</line>
            <line>Would long ere this have met us on the way</line>
            <line>Fie, what a slug is Hastings, that he comes not</line>
            <line>To tell us whether they will come or no!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter HASTINGS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>And, in good time, here comes the sweating lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>Welcome, my lord: what, will our mother come?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>On what occasion, God he knows, not I,</line>
            <line>The queen your mother, and your brother York,</line>
            <line>Have taken sanctuary: the tender prince</line>
            <line>Would fain have come with me to meet your grace,</line>
            <line>But by his mother was perforce withheld.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Fie, what an indirect and peevish course</line>
            <line>Is this of hers! Lord cardinal, will your grace</line>
            <line>Persuade the queen to send the Duke of York</line>
            <line>Unto his princely brother presently?</line>
            <line>If she deny, Lord Hastings, go with him,</line>
            <line>And from her jealous arms pluck him perforce.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL</speaker>
            <line>My Lord of Buckingham, if my weak oratory</line>
            <line>Can from his mother win the Duke of York,</line>
            <line>Anon expect him here; but if she be obdurate</line>
            <line>To mild entreaties, God in heaven forbid</line>
            <line>We should infringe the holy privilege</line>
            <line>Of blessed sanctuary! not for all this land</line>
            <line>Would I be guilty of so deep a sin.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>You are too senseless--obstinate, my lord,</line>
            <line>Too ceremonious and traditional</line>
            <line>Weigh it but with the grossness of this age,</line>
            <line>You break not sanctuary in seizing him.</line>
            <line>The benefit thereof is always granted</line>
            <line>To those whose dealings have deserved the place,</line>
            <line>And those who have the wit to claim the place:</line>
            <line>This prince hath neither claim'd it nor deserved it;</line>
            <line>And therefore, in mine opinion, cannot have it:</line>
            <line>Then, taking him from thence that is not there,</line>
            <line>You break no privilege nor charter there.</line>
            <line>Oft have I heard of sanctuary men;</line>
            <line>But sanctuary children ne'er till now.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL</speaker>
            <line>My lord, you shall o'er-rule my mind for once.</line>
            <line>Come on, Lord Hastings, will you go with me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>I go, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>Good lords, make all the speedy haste you may.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt CARDINAL and HASTINGS</stagedir>
            <line>Say, uncle Gloucester, if our brother come,</line>
            <line>Where shall we sojourn till our coronation?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Where it seems best unto your royal self.</line>
            <line>If I may counsel you, some day or two</line>
            <line>Your highness shall repose you at the Tower:</line>
            <line>Then where you please, and shall be thought most fit</line>
            <line>For your best health and recreation.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>I do not like the Tower, of any place.</line>
            <line>Did Julius Caesar build that place, my lord?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>He did, my gracious lord, begin that place;</line>
            <line>Which, since, succeeding ages have re-edified.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>Is it upon record, or else reported</line>
            <line>Successively from age to age, he built it?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Upon record, my gracious lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>But say, my lord, it were not register'd,</line>
            <line>Methinks the truth should live from age to age,</line>
            <line>As 'twere retail'd to all posterity,</line>
            <line>Even to the general all-ending day.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  So wise so young, they say, do never</line>
            <line>live long.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>What say you, uncle?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>I say, without characters, fame lives long.</line>
            <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>
            <line>Thus, like the formal vice, Iniquity,</line>
            <line>I moralize two meanings in one word.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>That Julius Caesar was a famous man;</line>
            <line>With what his valour did enrich his wit,</line>
            <line>His wit set down to make his valour live</line>
            <line>Death makes no conquest of this conqueror;</line>
            <line>For now he lives in fame, though not in life.</line>
            <line>I'll tell you what, my cousin Buckingham,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>What, my gracious lord?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>An if I live until I be a man,</line>
            <line>I'll win our ancient right in France again,</line>
            <line>Or die a soldier, as I lived a king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  Short summers lightly have a forward spring.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter young YORK, HASTINGS, and the CARDINAL</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Now, in good time, here comes the Duke of York.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>Richard of York! how fares our loving brother?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>Well, my dread lord; so must I call you now.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>Ay, brother, to our grief, as it is yours:</line>
            <line>Too late he died that might have kept that title,</line>
            <line>Which by his death hath lost much majesty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>How fares our cousin, noble Lord of York?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>I thank you, gentle uncle. O, my lord,</line>
            <line>You said that idle weeds are fast in growth</line>
            <line>The prince my brother hath outgrown me far.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>He hath, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>And therefore is he idle?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>O, my fair cousin, I must not say so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>Then is he more beholding to you than I.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>He may command me as my sovereign;</line>
            <line>But you have power in me as in a kinsman.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>I pray you, uncle, give me this dagger.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>My dagger, little cousin? with all my heart.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>A beggar, brother?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>Of my kind uncle, that I know will give;</line>
            <line>And being but a toy, which is no grief to give.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>A greater gift than that I'll give my cousin.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>A greater gift! O, that's the sword to it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>A gentle cousin, were it light enough.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>O, then, I see, you will part but with light gifts;</line>
            <line>In weightier things you'll say a beggar nay.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>It is too heavy for your grace to wear.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>I weigh it lightly, were it heavier.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>What, would you have my weapon, little lord?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>I would, that I might thank you as you call me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>How?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>Little.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>My Lord of York will still be cross in talk:</line>
            <line>Uncle, your grace knows how to bear with him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>You mean, to bear me, not to bear with me:</line>
            <line>Uncle, my brother mocks both you and me;</line>
            <line>Because that I am little, like an ape,</line>
            <line>He thinks that you should bear me on your shoulders.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>With what a sharp-provided wit he reasons!</line>
            <line>To mitigate the scorn he gives his uncle,</line>
            <line>He prettily and aptly taunts himself:</line>
            <line>So cunning and so young is wonderful.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>My lord, will't please you pass along?</line>
            <line>Myself and my good cousin Buckingham</line>
            <line>Will to your mother, to entreat of her</line>
            <line>To meet you at the Tower and welcome you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>What, will you go unto the Tower, my lord?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>My lord protector needs will have it so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>I shall not sleep in quiet at the Tower.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Why, what should you fear?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>Marry, my uncle Clarence' angry ghost:</line>
            <line>My grandam told me he was murdered there.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>I fear no uncles dead.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Nor none that live, I hope.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>An if they live, I hope I need not fear.</line>
            <line>But come, my lord; and with a heavy heart,</line>
            <line>Thinking on them, go I unto the Tower.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>A Sennet. Exeunt all but GLOUCESTER, BUCKINGHAM
and CATESBY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Think you, my lord, this little prating York</line>
            <line>Was not incensed by his subtle mother</line>
            <line>To taunt and scorn you thus opprobriously?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>No doubt, no doubt; O, 'tis a parlous boy;</line>
            <line>Bold, quick, ingenious, forward, capable</line>
            <line>He is all the mother's, from the top to toe.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Well, let them rest. Come hither, Catesby.</line>
            <line>Thou art sworn as deeply to effect what we intend</line>
            <line>As closely to conceal what we impart:</line>
            <line>Thou know'st our reasons urged upon the way;</line>
            <line>What think'st thou? is it not an easy matter</line>
            <line>To make William Lord Hastings of our mind,</line>
            <line>For the instalment of this noble duke</line>
            <line>In the seat royal of this famous isle?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CATESBY</speaker>
            <line>He for his father's sake so loves the prince,</line>
            <line>That he will not be won to aught against him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>What think'st thou, then, of Stanley? what will he?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CATESBY</speaker>
            <line>He will do all in all as Hastings doth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Well, then, no more but this: go, gentle Catesby,</line>
            <line>And, as it were far off sound thou Lord Hastings,</line>
            <line>How doth he stand affected to our purpose;</line>
            <line>And summon him to-morrow to the Tower,</line>
            <line>To sit about the coronation.</line>
            <line>If thou dost find him tractable to us,</line>
            <line>Encourage him, and show him all our reasons:</line>
            <line>If he be leaden, icy-cold, unwilling,</line>
            <line>Be thou so too; and so break off your talk,</line>
            <line>And give us notice of his inclination:</line>
            <line>For we to-morrow hold divided councils,</line>
            <line>Wherein thyself shalt highly be employ'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Commend me to Lord William: tell him, Catesby,</line>
            <line>His ancient knot of dangerous adversaries</line>
            <line>To-morrow are let blood at Pomfret-castle;</line>
            <line>And bid my friend, for joy of this good news,</line>
            <line>Give mistress Shore one gentle kiss the more.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Good Catesby, go, effect this business soundly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CATESBY</speaker>
            <line>My good lords both, with all the heed I may.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Shall we hear from you, Catesby, ere we sleep?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CATESBY</speaker>
            <line>You shall, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>At Crosby Place, there shall you find us both.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit CATESBY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Now, my lord, what shall we do, if we perceive</line>
            <line>Lord Hastings will not yield to our complots?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Chop off his head, man; somewhat we will do:</line>
            <line>And, look, when I am king, claim thou of me</line>
            <line>The earldom of Hereford, and the moveables</line>
            <line>Whereof the king my brother stood possess'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>I'll claim that promise at your grace's hands.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>And look to have it yielded with all willingness.</line>
            <line>Come, let us sup betimes, that afterwards</line>
            <line>We may digest our complots in some form.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  Before Lord Hastings' house.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter a Messenger</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>What, ho! my lord!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Within</stagedir>  Who knocks at the door?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>A messenger from the Lord Stanley.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter HASTINGS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>What is't o'clock?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>Upon the stroke of four.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>Cannot thy master sleep these tedious nights?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>So it should seem by that I have to say.</line>
            <line>First, he commends him to your noble lordship.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>And then?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>And then he sends you word</line>
            <line>He dreamt to-night the boar had razed his helm:</line>
            <line>Besides, he says there are two councils held;</line>
            <line>And that may be determined at the one</line>
            <line>which may make you and him to rue at the other.</line>
            <line>Therefore he sends to know your lordship's pleasure,</line>
            <line>If presently you will take horse with him,</line>
            <line>And with all speed post with him toward the north,</line>
            <line>To shun the danger that his soul divines.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>Go, fellow, go, return unto thy lord;</line>
            <line>Bid him not fear the separated councils</line>
            <line>His honour and myself are at the one,</line>
            <line>And at the other is my servant Catesby</line>
            <line>Where nothing can proceed that toucheth us</line>
            <line>Whereof I shall not have intelligence.</line>
            <line>Tell him his fears are shallow, wanting instance:</line>
            <line>And for his dreams, I wonder he is so fond</line>
            <line>To trust the mockery of unquiet slumbers</line>
            <line>To fly the boar before the boar pursues,</line>
            <line>Were to incense the boar to follow us</line>
            <line>And make pursuit where he did mean no chase.</line>
            <line>Go, bid thy master rise and come to me</line>
            <line>And we will both together to the Tower,</line>
            <line>Where, he shall see, the boar will use us kindly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>My gracious lord, I'll tell him what you say.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Enter CATESBY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CATESBY</speaker>
            <line>Many good morrows to my noble lord!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>Good morrow, Catesby; you are early stirring</line>
            <line>What news, what news, in this our tottering state?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CATESBY</speaker>
            <line>It is a reeling world, indeed, my lord;</line>
            <line>And I believe twill never stand upright</line>
            <line>Tim Richard wear the garland of the realm.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>How! wear the garland! dost thou mean the crown?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CATESBY</speaker>
            <line>Ay, my good lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>I'll have this crown of mine cut from my shoulders</line>
            <line>Ere I will see the crown so foul misplaced.</line>
            <line>But canst thou guess that he doth aim at it?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CATESBY</speaker>
            <line>Ay, on my life; and hopes to find forward</line>
            <line>Upon his party for the gain thereof:</line>
            <line>And thereupon he sends you this good news,</line>
            <line>That this same very day your enemies,</line>
            <line>The kindred of the queen, must die at Pomfret.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>Indeed, I am no mourner for that news,</line>
            <line>Because they have been still mine enemies:</line>
            <line>But, that I'll give my voice on Richard's side,</line>
            <line>To bar my master's heirs in true descent,</line>
            <line>God knows I will not do it, to the death.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CATESBY</speaker>
            <line>God keep your lordship in that gracious mind!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>But I shall laugh at this a twelve-month hence,</line>
            <line>That they who brought me in my master's hate</line>
            <line>I live to look upon their tragedy.</line>
            <line>I tell thee, Catesby--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CATESBY</speaker>
            <line>What, my lord?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>Ere a fortnight make me elder,</line>
            <line>I'll send some packing that yet think not on it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CATESBY</speaker>
            <line>'Tis a vile thing to die, my gracious lord,</line>
            <line>When men are unprepared and look not for it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>O monstrous, monstrous! and so falls it out</line>
            <line>With Rivers, Vaughan, Grey: and so 'twill do</line>
            <line>With some men else, who think themselves as safe</line>
            <line>As thou and I; who, as thou know'st, are dear</line>
            <line>To princely Richard and to Buckingham.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CATESBY</speaker>
            <line>The princes both make high account of you;</line>
            <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>
            <line>For they account his head upon the bridge.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>I know they do; and I have well deserved it.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter STANLEY</stagedir>
            <line>Come on, come on; where is your boar-spear, man?</line>
            <line>Fear you the boar, and go so unprovided?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>STANLEY</speaker>
            <line>My lord, good morrow; good morrow, Catesby:</line>
            <line>You may jest on, but, by the holy rood,</line>
            <line>I do not like these several councils, I.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>My lord,</line>
            <line>I hold my life as dear as you do yours;</line>
            <line>And never in my life, I do protest,</line>
            <line>Was it more precious to me than 'tis now:</line>
            <line>Think you, but that I know our state secure,</line>
            <line>I would be so triumphant as I am?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>STANLEY</speaker>
            <line>The lords at Pomfret, when they rode from London,</line>
            <line>Were jocund, and supposed their state was sure,</line>
            <line>And they indeed had no cause to mistrust;</line>
            <line>But yet, you see how soon the day o'ercast.</line>
            <line>This sudden stag of rancour I misdoubt:</line>
            <line>Pray God, I say, I prove a needless coward!</line>
            <line>What, shall we toward the Tower? the day is spent.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>Come, come, have with you. Wot you what, my lord?</line>
            <line>To-day the lords you talk of are beheaded.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD STANLEY</speaker>
            <line>They, for their truth, might better wear their heads</line>
            <line>Than some that have accused them wear their hats.</line>
            <line>But come, my lord, let us away.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter a Pursuivant</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>Go on before; I'll talk with this good fellow.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt STANLEY and CATESBY</stagedir>
            <line>How now, sirrah! how goes the world with thee?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Pursuivant</speaker>
            <line>The better that your lordship please to ask.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>I tell thee, man, 'tis better with me now</line>
            <line>Than when I met thee last where now we meet:</line>
            <line>Then was I going prisoner to the Tower,</line>
            <line>By the suggestion of the queen's allies;</line>
            <line>But now, I tell thee--keep it to thyself--</line>
            <line>This day those enemies are put to death,</line>
            <line>And I in better state than e'er I was.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Pursuivant</speaker>
            <line>God hold it, to your honour's good content!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>Gramercy, fellow: there, drink that for me.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Throws him his purse</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Pursuivant</speaker>
            <line>God save your lordship!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Enter a Priest</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Priest</speaker>
            <line>Well met, my lord; I am glad to see your honour.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>I thank thee, good Sir John, with all my heart.</line>
            <line>I am in your debt for your last exercise;</line>
            <line>Come the next Sabbath, and I will content you.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>He whispers in his ear</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Enter BUCKINGHAM</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>What, talking with a priest, lord chamberlain?</line>
            <line>Your friends at Pomfret, they do need the priest;</line>
            <line>Your honour hath no shriving work in hand.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>Good faith, and when I met this holy man,</line>
            <line>Those men you talk of came into my mind.</line>
            <line>What, go you toward the Tower?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>I do, my lord; but long I shall not stay</line>
            <line>I shall return before your lordship thence.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>'Tis like enough, for I stay dinner there.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  And supper too, although thou know'st it not.</line>
            <line>Come, will you go?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>I'll wait upon your lordship.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  Pomfret Castle.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter RATCLIFF, with halberds, carrying RIVERS,
GREY, and VAUGHAN to death</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RATCLIFF</speaker>
            <line>Come, bring forth the prisoners.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RIVERS</speaker>
            <line>Sir Richard Ratcliff, let me tell thee this:</line>
            <line>To-day shalt thou behold a subject die</line>
            <line>For truth, for duty, and for loyalty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GREY</speaker>
            <line>God keep the prince from all the pack of you!</line>
            <line>A knot you are of damned blood-suckers!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VAUGHAN</speaker>
            <line>You live that shall cry woe for this after.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RATCLIFF</speaker>
            <line>Dispatch; the limit of your lives is out.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RIVERS</speaker>
            <line>O Pomfret, Pomfret! O thou bloody prison,</line>
            <line>Fatal and ominous to noble peers!</line>
            <line>Within the guilty closure of thy walls</line>
            <line>Richard the second here was hack'd to death;</line>
            <line>And, for more slander to thy dismal seat,</line>
            <line>We give thee up our guiltless blood to drink.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GREY</speaker>
            <line>Now Margaret's curse is fall'n upon our heads,</line>
            <line>For standing by when Richard stabb'd her son.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RIVERS</speaker>
            <line>Then cursed she Hastings, then cursed she Buckingham,</line>
            <line>Then cursed she Richard. O, remember, God</line>
            <line>To hear her prayers for them, as now for us</line>
            <line>And for my sister and her princely sons,</line>
            <line>Be satisfied, dear God, with our true blood,</line>
            <line>Which, as thou know'st, unjustly must be spilt.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RATCLIFF</speaker>
            <line>Make haste; the hour of death is expiate.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RIVERS</speaker>
            <line>Come, Grey, come, Vaughan, let us all embrace:</line>
            <line>And take our leave, until we meet in heaven.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-4">
      <title>SCENE IV.  The Tower of London.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter BUCKINGHAM, DERBY, HASTINGS, the BISHOP OF
ELY, RATCLIFF, LOVEL, with others, and take their
seats at a table</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>My lords, at once: the cause why we are met</line>
            <line>Is, to determine of the coronation.</line>
            <line>In God's name, speak: when is the royal day?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Are all things fitting for that royal time?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DERBY</speaker>
            <line>It is, and wants but nomination.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BISHOP OF ELY</speaker>
            <line>To-morrow, then, I judge a happy day.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Who knows the lord protector's mind herein?</line>
            <line>Who is most inward with the royal duke?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BISHOP OF ELY</speaker>
            <line>Your grace, we think, should soonest know his mind.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Who, I, my lord I we know each other's faces,</line>
            <line>But for our hearts, he knows no more of mine,</line>
            <line>Than I of yours;</line>
            <line>Nor I no more of his, than you of mine.</line>
            <line>Lord Hastings, you and he are near in love.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>I thank his grace, I know he loves me well;</line>
            <line>But, for his purpose in the coronation.</line>
            <line>I have not sounded him, nor he deliver'd</line>
            <line>His gracious pleasure any way therein:</line>
            <line>But you, my noble lords, may name the time;</line>
            <line>And in the duke's behalf I'll give my voice,</line>
            <line>Which, I presume, he'll take in gentle part.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter GLOUCESTER</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BISHOP OF ELY</speaker>
            <line>Now in good time, here comes the duke himself.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>My noble lords and cousins all, good morrow.</line>
            <line>I have been long a sleeper; but, I hope,</line>
            <line>My absence doth neglect no great designs,</line>
            <line>Which by my presence might have been concluded.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Had not you come upon your cue, my lord</line>
            <line>William Lord Hastings had pronounced your part,--</line>
            <line>I mean, your voice,--for crowning of the king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Than my Lord Hastings no man might be bolder;</line>
            <line>His lordship knows me well, and loves me well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>I thank your grace.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>My lord of Ely!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BISHOP OF ELY</speaker>
            <line>My lord?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>When I was last in Holborn,</line>
            <line>I saw good strawberries in your garden there</line>
            <line>I do beseech you send for some of them.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BISHOP OF ELY</speaker>
            <line>Marry, and will, my lord, with all my heart.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Cousin of Buckingham, a word with you.</line>
            <stagedir>Drawing him aside</stagedir>
            <line>Catesby hath sounded Hastings in our business,</line>
            <line>And finds the testy gentleman so hot,</line>
            <line>As he will lose his head ere give consent</line>
            <line>His master's son, as worshipful as he terms it,</line>
            <line>Shall lose the royalty of England's throne.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Withdraw you hence, my lord, I'll follow you.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit GLOUCESTER, BUCKINGHAM following</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DERBY</speaker>
            <line>We have not yet set down this day of triumph.</line>
            <line>To-morrow, in mine opinion, is too sudden;</line>
            <line>For I myself am not so well provided</line>
            <line>As else I would be, were the day prolong'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter BISHOP OF ELY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BISHOP OF ELY</speaker>
            <line>Where is my lord protector? I have sent for these</line>
            <line>strawberries.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>His grace looks cheerfully and smooth to-day;</line>
            <line>There's some conceit or other likes him well,</line>
            <line>When he doth bid good morrow with such a spirit.</line>
            <line>I think there's never a man in Christendom</line>
            <line>That can less hide his love or hate than he;</line>
            <line>For by his face straight shall you know his heart.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DERBY</speaker>
            <line>What of his heart perceive you in his face</line>
            <line>By any likelihood he show'd to-day?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>Marry, that with no man here he is offended;</line>
            <line>For, were he, he had shown it in his looks.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DERBY</speaker>
            <line>I pray God he be not, I say.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter GLOUCESTER and BUCKINGHAM</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>I pray you all, tell me what they deserve</line>
            <line>That do conspire my death with devilish plots</line>
            <line>Of damned witchcraft, and that have prevail'd</line>
            <line>Upon my body with their hellish charms?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>The tender love I bear your grace, my lord,</line>
            <line>Makes me most forward in this noble presence</line>
            <line>To doom the offenders, whatsoever they be</line>
            <line>I say, my lord, they have deserved death.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Then be your eyes the witness of this ill:</line>
            <line>See how I am bewitch'd; behold mine arm</line>
            <line>Is, like a blasted sapling, wither'd up:</line>
            <line>And this is Edward's wife, that monstrous witch,</line>
            <line>Consorted with that harlot strumpet Shore,</line>
            <line>That by their witchcraft thus have marked me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>If they have done this thing, my gracious lord--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>If I thou protector of this damned strumpet--</line>
            <line>Tellest thou me of 'ifs'?  Thou art a traitor:</line>
            <line>Off with his head! Now, by Saint Paul I swear,</line>
            <line>I will not dine until I see the same.</line>
            <line>Lovel and Ratcliff, look that it be done:</line>
            <line>The rest, that love me, rise and follow me.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt all but HASTINGS, RATCLIFF, and LOVEL</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>Woe, woe for England! not a whit for me;</line>
            <line>For I, too fond, might have prevented this.</line>
            <line>Stanley did dream the boar did raze his helm;</line>
            <line>But I disdain'd it, and did scorn to fly:</line>
            <line>Three times to-day my foot-cloth horse did stumble,</line>
            <line>And startled, when he look'd upon the Tower,</line>
            <line>As loath to bear me to the slaughter-house.</line>
            <line>O, now I want the priest that spake to me:</line>
            <line>I now repent I told the pursuivant</line>
            <line>As 'twere triumphing at mine enemies,</line>
            <line>How they at Pomfret bloodily were butcher'd,</line>
            <line>And I myself secure in grace and favour.</line>
            <line>O Margaret, Margaret, now thy heavy curse</line>
            <line>Is lighted on poor Hastings' wretched head!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RATCLIFF</speaker>
            <line>Dispatch, my lord; the duke would be at dinner:</line>
            <line>Make a short shrift; he longs to see your head.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>O momentary grace of mortal men,</line>
            <line>Which we more hunt for than the grace of God!</line>
            <line>Who builds his hopes in air of your good looks,</line>
            <line>Lives like a drunken sailor on a mast,</line>
            <line>Ready, with every nod, to tumble down</line>
            <line>Into the fatal bowels of the deep.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LOVEL</speaker>
            <line>Come, come, dispatch; 'tis bootless to exclaim.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HASTINGS</speaker>
            <line>O bloody Richard! miserable England!</line>
            <line>I prophesy the fearful'st time to thee</line>
            <line>That ever wretched age hath look'd upon.</line>
            <line>Come, lead me to the block; bear him my head.</line>
            <line>They smile at me that shortly shall be dead.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-5">
      <title>SCENE V.  The Tower-walls.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter GLOUCESTER and BUCKINGHAM, in rotten armour,
marvellous ill-favoured</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Come, cousin, canst thou quake, and change thy colour,</line>
            <line>Murder thy breath in the middle of a word,</line>
            <line>And then begin again, and stop again,</line>
            <line>As if thou wert distraught and mad with terror?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Tut, I can counterfeit the deep tragedian;</line>
            <line>Speak and look back, and pry on every side,</line>
            <line>Tremble and start at wagging of a straw,</line>
            <line>Intending deep suspicion: ghastly looks</line>
            <line>Are at my service, like enforced smiles;</line>
            <line>And both are ready in their offices,</line>
            <line>At any time, to grace my stratagems.</line>
            <line>But what, is Catesby gone?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>He is; and, see, he brings the mayor along.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter the Lord Mayor and CATESBY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Lord mayor,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Look to the drawbridge there!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Hark! a drum.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Catesby, o'erlook the walls.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Lord mayor, the reason we have sent--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Look back, defend thee, here are enemies.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>God and our innocency defend and guard us!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Be patient, they are friends, Ratcliff and Lovel.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter LOVEL and RATCLIFF, with HASTINGS' head</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LOVEL</speaker>
            <line>Here is the head of that ignoble traitor,</line>
            <line>The dangerous and unsuspected Hastings.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>So dear I loved the man, that I must weep.</line>
            <line>I took him for the plainest harmless creature</line>
            <line>That breathed upon this earth a Christian;</line>
            <line>Made him my book wherein my soul recorded</line>
            <line>The history of all her secret thoughts:</line>
            <line>So smooth he daub'd his vice with show of virtue,</line>
            <line>That, his apparent open guilt omitted,</line>
            <line>I mean, his conversation with Shore's wife,</line>
            <line>He lived from all attainder of suspect.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Well, well, he was the covert'st shelter'd traitor</line>
            <line>That ever lived.</line>
            <line>Would you imagine, or almost believe,</line>
            <line>Were't not that, by great preservation,</line>
            <line>We live to tell it you, the subtle traitor</line>
            <line>This day had plotted, in the council-house</line>
            <line>To murder me and my good Lord of Gloucester?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord Mayor</speaker>
            <line>What, had he so?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>What, think You we are Turks or infidels?</line>
            <line>Or that we would, against the form of law,</line>
            <line>Proceed thus rashly to the villain's death,</line>
            <line>But that the extreme peril of the case,</line>
            <line>The peace of England and our persons' safety,</line>
            <line>Enforced us to this execution?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord Mayor</speaker>
            <line>Now, fair befall you! he deserved his death;</line>
            <line>And you my good lords, both have well proceeded,</line>
            <line>To warn false traitors from the like attempts.</line>
            <line>I never look'd for better at his hands,</line>
            <line>After he once fell in with Mistress Shore.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Yet had not we determined he should die,</line>
            <line>Until your lordship came to see his death;</line>
            <line>Which now the loving haste of these our friends,</line>
            <line>Somewhat against our meaning, have prevented:</line>
            <line>Because, my lord, we would have had you heard</line>
            <line>The traitor speak, and timorously confess</line>
            <line>The manner and the purpose of his treason;</line>
            <line>That you might well have signified the same</line>
            <line>Unto the citizens, who haply may</line>
            <line>Misconstrue us in him and wail his death.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord Mayor</speaker>
            <line>But, my good lord, your grace's word shall serve,</line>
            <line>As well as I had seen and heard him speak</line>
            <line>And doubt you not, right noble princes both,</line>
            <line>But I'll acquaint our duteous citizens</line>
            <line>With all your just proceedings in this cause.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>And to that end we wish'd your lord-ship here,</line>
            <line>To avoid the carping censures of the world.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>But since you come too late of our intents,</line>
            <line>Yet witness what you hear we did intend:</line>
            <line>And so, my good lord mayor, we bid farewell.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit Lord Mayor</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Go, after, after, cousin Buckingham.</line>
            <line>The mayor towards Guildhall hies him in all post:</line>
            <line>There, at your meet'st advantage of the time,</line>
            <line>Infer the bastardy of Edward's children:</line>
            <line>Tell them how Edward put to death a citizen,</line>
            <line>Only for saying he would make his son</line>
            <line>Heir to the crown; meaning indeed his house,</line>
            <line>Which, by the sign thereof was termed so.</line>
            <line>Moreover, urge his hateful luxury</line>
            <line>And bestial appetite in change of lust;</line>
            <line>Which stretched to their servants, daughters, wives,</line>
            <line>Even where his lustful eye or savage heart,</line>
            <line>Without control, listed to make his prey.</line>
            <line>Nay, for a need, thus far come near my person:</line>
            <line>Tell them, when that my mother went with child</line>
            <line>Of that unsatiate Edward, noble York</line>
            <line>My princely father then had wars in France</line>
            <line>And, by just computation of the time,</line>
            <line>Found that the issue was not his begot;</line>
            <line>Which well appeared in his lineaments,</line>
            <line>Being nothing like the noble duke my father:</line>
            <line>But touch this sparingly, as 'twere far off,</line>
            <line>Because you know, my lord, my mother lives.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Fear not, my lord, I'll play the orator</line>
            <line>As if the golden fee for which I plead</line>
            <line>Were for myself: and so, my lord, adieu.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>If you thrive well, bring them to Baynard's Castle;</line>
            <line>Where you shall find me well accompanied</line>
            <line>With reverend fathers and well-learned bishops.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>I go: and towards three or four o'clock</line>
            <line>Look for the news that the Guildhall affords.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit BUCKINGHAM</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Go, Lovel, with all speed to Doctor Shaw;</line>
            <stagedir>To CATESBY</stagedir>
            <line>Go thou to Friar Penker; bid them both</line>
            <line>Meet me within this hour at Baynard's Castle.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt all but GLOUCESTER</stagedir>
            <line>Now will I in, to take some privy order,</line>
            <line>To draw the brats of Clarence out of sight;</line>
            <line>And to give notice, that no manner of person</line>
            <line>At any time have recourse unto the princes.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-6">
      <title>SCENE VI.  The same.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter a Scrivener, with a paper in his hand</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Scrivener</speaker>
            <line>This is the indictment of the good Lord Hastings;</line>
            <line>Which in a set hand fairly is engross'd,</line>
            <line>That it may be this day read over in Paul's.</line>
            <line>And mark how well the sequel hangs together:</line>
            <line>Eleven hours I spent to write it over,</line>
            <line>For yesternight by Catesby was it brought me;</line>
            <line>The precedent was full as long a-doing:</line>
            <line>And yet within these five hours lived Lord Hastings,</line>
            <line>Untainted, unexamined, free, at liberty</line>
            <line>Here's a good world the while! Why who's so gross,</line>
            <line>That seeth not this palpable device?</line>
            <line>Yet who's so blind, but says he sees it not?</line>
            <line>Bad is the world; and all will come to nought,</line>
            <line>When such bad dealings must be seen in thought.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-7">
      <title>SCENE VII.  Baynard's Castle.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter GLOUCESTER and BUCKINGHAM, at several doors</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>How now, my lord, what say the citizens?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Now, by the holy mother of our Lord,</line>
            <line>The citizens are mum and speak not a word.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Touch'd you the bastardy of Edward's children?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>I did; with his contract with Lady Lucy,</line>
            <line>And his contract by deputy in France;</line>
            <line>The insatiate greediness of his desires,</line>
            <line>And his enforcement of the city wives;</line>
            <line>His tyranny for trifles; his own bastardy,</line>
            <line>As being got, your father then in France,</line>
            <line>His resemblance, being not like the duke;</line>
            <line>Withal I did infer your lineaments,</line>
            <line>Being the right idea of your father,</line>
            <line>Both in your form and nobleness of mind;</line>
            <line>Laid open all your victories in Scotland,</line>
            <line>Your dicipline in war, wisdom in peace,</line>
            <line>Your bounty, virtue, fair humility:</line>
            <line>Indeed, left nothing fitting for the purpose</line>
            <line>Untouch'd, or slightly handled, in discourse</line>
            <line>And when mine oratory grew to an end</line>
            <line>I bid them that did love their country's good</line>
            <line>Cry 'God save Richard, England's royal king!'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Ah! and did they so?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>No, so God help me, they spake not a word;</line>
            <line>But, like dumb statues or breathing stones,</line>
            <line>Gazed each on other, and look'd deadly pale.</line>
            <line>Which when I saw, I reprehended them;</line>
            <line>And ask'd the mayor what meant this wilful silence:</line>
            <line>His answer was, the people were not wont</line>
            <line>To be spoke to but by the recorder.</line>
            <line>Then he was urged to tell my tale again,</line>
            <line>'Thus saith the duke, thus hath the duke inferr'd;'</line>
            <line>But nothing spake in warrant from himself.</line>
            <line>When he had done, some followers of mine own,</line>
            <line>At the lower end of the hall, hurl'd up their caps,</line>
            <line>And some ten voices cried 'God save King Richard!'</line>
            <line>And thus I took the vantage of those few,</line>
            <line>'Thanks, gentle citizens and friends,' quoth I;</line>
            <line>'This general applause and loving shout</line>
            <line>Argues your wisdoms and your love to Richard:'</line>
            <line>And even here brake off, and came away.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>What tongueless blocks were they! would not they speak?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>No, by my troth, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Will not the mayor then and his brethren come?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>The mayor is here at hand: intend some fear;</line>
            <line>Be not you spoke with, but by mighty suit:</line>
            <line>And look you get a prayer-book in your hand,</line>
            <line>And stand betwixt two churchmen, good my lord;</line>
            <line>For on that ground I'll build a holy descant:</line>
            <line>And be not easily won to our request:</line>
            <line>Play the maid's part, still answer nay, and take it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>I go; and if you plead as well for them</line>
            <line>As I can say nay to thee for myself,</line>
            <line>No doubt well bring it to a happy issue.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Go, go, up to the leads; the lord mayor knocks.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit GLOUCESTER</stagedir>
            <stagedir>Enter the Lord Mayor and Citizens</stagedir>
            <line>Welcome my lord; I dance attendance here;</line>
            <line>I think the duke will not be spoke withal.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter CATESBY</stagedir>
            <line>Here comes his servant: how now, Catesby,</line>
            <line>What says he?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CATESBY</speaker>
            <line>My lord: he doth entreat your grace;</line>
            <line>To visit him to-morrow or next day:</line>
            <line>He is within, with two right reverend fathers,</line>
            <line>Divinely bent to meditation;</line>
            <line>And no worldly suit would he be moved,</line>
            <line>To draw him from his holy exercise.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Return, good Catesby, to thy lord again;</line>
            <line>Tell him, myself, the mayor and citizens,</line>
            <line>In deep designs and matters of great moment,</line>
            <line>No less importing than our general good,</line>
            <line>Are come to have some conference with his grace.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CATESBY</speaker>
            <line>I'll tell him what you say, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Ah, ha, my lord, this prince is not an Edward!</line>
            <line>He is not lolling on a lewd day-bed,</line>
            <line>But on his knees at meditation;</line>
            <line>Not dallying with a brace of courtezans,</line>
            <line>But meditating with two deep divines;</line>
            <line>Not sleeping, to engross his idle body,</line>
            <line>But praying, to enrich his watchful soul:</line>
            <line>Happy were England, would this gracious prince</line>
            <line>Take on himself the sovereignty thereof:</line>
            <line>But, sure, I fear, we shall ne'er win him to it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord Mayor</speaker>
            <line>Marry, God forbid his grace should say us nay!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>I fear he will.</line>
            <stagedir>Re-enter CATESBY</stagedir>
            <line>How now, Catesby, what says your lord?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CATESBY</speaker>
            <line>My lord,</line>
            <line>He wonders to what end you have assembled</line>
            <line>Such troops of citizens to speak with him,</line>
            <line>His grace not being warn'd thereof before:</line>
            <line>My lord, he fears you mean no good to him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Sorry I am my noble cousin should</line>
            <line>Suspect me, that I mean no good to him:</line>
            <line>By heaven, I come in perfect love to him;</line>
            <line>And so once more return and tell his grace.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit CATESBY</stagedir>
            <line>When holy and devout religious men</line>
            <line>Are at their beads, 'tis hard to draw them thence,</line>
            <line>So sweet is zealous contemplation.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter GLOUCESTER aloft, between two Bishops.
CATESBY returns</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord Mayor</speaker>
            <line>See, where he stands between two clergymen!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Two props of virtue for a Christian prince,</line>
            <line>To stay him from the fall of vanity:</line>
            <line>And, see, a book of prayer in his hand,</line>
            <line>True ornaments to know a holy man.</line>
            <line>Famous Plantagenet, most gracious prince,</line>
            <line>Lend favourable ears to our request;</line>
            <line>And pardon us the interruption</line>
            <line>Of thy devotion and right Christian zeal.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>My lord, there needs no such apology:</line>
            <line>I rather do beseech you pardon me,</line>
            <line>Who, earnest in the service of my God,</line>
            <line>Neglect the visitation of my friends.</line>
            <line>But, leaving this, what is your grace's pleasure?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Even that, I hope, which pleaseth God above,</line>
            <line>And all good men of this ungovern'd isle.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>I do suspect I have done some offence</line>
            <line>That seems disgracious in the city's eyes,</line>
            <line>And that you come to reprehend my ignorance.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>You have, my lord: would it might please your grace,</line>
            <line>At our entreaties, to amend that fault!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Else wherefore breathe I in a Christian land?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Then know, it is your fault that you resign</line>
            <line>The supreme seat, the throne majestical,</line>
            <line>The scepter'd office of your ancestors,</line>
            <line>Your state of fortune and your due of birth,</line>
            <line>The lineal glory of your royal house,</line>
            <line>To the corruption of a blemished stock:</line>
            <line>Whilst, in the mildness of your sleepy thoughts,</line>
            <line>Which here we waken to our country's good,</line>
            <line>This noble isle doth want her proper limbs;</line>
            <line>Her face defaced with scars of infamy,</line>
            <line>Her royal stock graft with ignoble plants,</line>
            <line>And almost shoulder'd in the swallowing gulf</line>
            <line>Of blind forgetfulness and dark oblivion.</line>
            <line>Which to recure, we heartily solicit</line>
            <line>Your gracious self to take on you the charge</line>
            <line>And kingly government of this your land,</line>
            <line>Not as protector, steward, substitute,</line>
            <line>Or lowly factor for another's gain;</line>
            <line>But as successively from blood to blood,</line>
            <line>Your right of birth, your empery, your own.</line>
            <line>For this, consorted with the citizens,</line>
            <line>Your very worshipful and loving friends,</line>
            <line>And by their vehement instigation,</line>
            <line>In this just suit come I to move your grace.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>I know not whether to depart in silence,</line>
            <line>Or bitterly to speak in your reproof.</line>
            <line>Best fitteth my degree or your condition</line>
            <line>If not to answer, you might haply think</line>
            <line>Tongue-tied ambition, not replying, yielded</line>
            <line>To bear the golden yoke of sovereignty,</line>
            <line>Which fondly you would here impose on me;</line>
            <line>If to reprove you for this suit of yours,</line>
            <line>So season'd with your faithful love to me.</line>
            <line>Then, on the other side, I cheque'd my friends.</line>
            <line>Therefore, to speak, and to avoid the first,</line>
            <line>And then, in speaking, not to incur the last,</line>
            <line>Definitively thus I answer you.</line>
            <line>Your love deserves my thanks; but my desert</line>
            <line>Unmeritable shuns your high request.</line>
            <line>First if all obstacles were cut away,</line>
            <line>And that my path were even to the crown,</line>
            <line>As my ripe revenue and due by birth</line>
            <line>Yet so much is my poverty of spirit,</line>
            <line>So mighty and so many my defects,</line>
            <line>As I had rather hide me from my greatness,</line>
            <line>Being a bark to brook no mighty sea,</line>
            <line>Than in my greatness covet to be hid,</line>
            <line>And in the vapour of my glory smother'd.</line>
            <line>But, God be thank'd, there's no need of me,</line>
            <line>And much I need to help you, if need were;</line>
            <line>The royal tree hath left us royal fruit,</line>
            <line>Which, mellow'd by the stealing hours of time,</line>
            <line>Will well become the seat of majesty,</line>
            <line>And make, no doubt, us happy by his reign.</line>
            <line>On him I lay what you would lay on me,</line>
            <line>The right and fortune of his happy stars;</line>
            <line>Which God defend that I should wring from him!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>My lord, this argues conscience in your grace;</line>
            <line>But the respects thereof are nice and trivial,</line>
            <line>All circumstances well considered.</line>
            <line>You say that Edward is your brother's son:</line>
            <line>So say we too, but not by Edward's wife;</line>
            <line>For first he was contract to Lady Lucy--</line>
            <line>Your mother lives a witness to that vow--</line>
            <line>And afterward by substitute betroth'd</line>
            <line>To Bona, sister to the King of France.</line>
            <line>These both put by a poor petitioner,</line>
            <line>A care-crazed mother of a many children,</line>
            <line>A beauty-waning and distressed widow,</line>
            <line>Even in the afternoon of her best days,</line>
            <line>Made prize and purchase of his lustful eye,</line>
            <line>Seduced the pitch and height of all his thoughts</line>
            <line>To base declension and loathed bigamy</line>
            <line>By her, in his unlawful bed, he got</line>
            <line>This Edward, whom our manners term the prince.</line>
            <line>More bitterly could I expostulate,</line>
            <line>Save that, for reverence to some alive,</line>
            <line>I give a sparing limit to my tongue.</line>
            <line>Then, good my lord, take to your royal self</line>
            <line>This proffer'd benefit of dignity;</line>
            <line>If non to bless us and the land withal,</line>
            <line>Yet to draw forth your noble ancestry</line>
            <line>From the corruption of abusing times,</line>
            <line>Unto a lineal true-derived course.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord Mayor</speaker>
            <line>Do, good my lord, your citizens entreat you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Refuse not, mighty lord, this proffer'd love.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CATESBY</speaker>
            <line>O, make them joyful, grant their lawful suit!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Alas, why would you heap these cares on me?</line>
            <line>I am unfit for state and majesty;</line>
            <line>I do beseech you, take it not amiss;</line>
            <line>I cannot nor I will not yield to you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>If you refuse it,--as, in love and zeal,</line>
            <line>Loath to depose the child, Your brother's son;</line>
            <line>As well we know your tenderness of heart</line>
            <line>And gentle, kind, effeminate remorse,</line>
            <line>Which we have noted in you to your kin,</line>
            <line>And egally indeed to all estates,--</line>
            <line>Yet whether you accept our suit or no,</line>
            <line>Your brother's son shall never reign our king;</line>
            <line>But we will plant some other in the throne,</line>
            <line>To the disgrace and downfall of your house:</line>
            <line>And in this resolution here we leave you.--</line>
            <line>Come, citizens: 'zounds! I'll entreat no more.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>O, do not swear, my lord of Buckingham.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit BUCKINGHAM with the Citizens</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CATESBY</speaker>
            <line>Call them again, my lord, and accept their suit.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANOTHER</speaker>
            <line>Do, good my lord, lest all the land do rue it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Would you enforce me to a world of care?</line>
            <line>Well, call them again. I am not made of stone,</line>
            <line>But penetrable to your. kind entreats,</line>
            <line>Albeit against my conscience and my soul.</line>
            <stagedir>Re-enter BUCKINGHAM and the rest</stagedir>
            <line>Cousin of Buckingham, and you sage, grave men,</line>
            <line>Since you will buckle fortune on my back,</line>
            <line>To bear her burthen, whether I will or no,</line>
            <line>I must have patience to endure the load:</line>
            <line>But if black scandal or foul-faced reproach</line>
            <line>Attend the sequel of your imposition,</line>
            <line>Your mere enforcement shall acquittance me</line>
            <line>From all the impure blots and stains thereof;</line>
            <line>For God he knows, and you may partly see,</line>
            <line>How far I am from the desire thereof.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord Mayor</speaker>
            <line>God bless your grace! we see it, and will say it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>In saying so, you shall but say the truth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Then I salute you with this kingly title:</line>
            <line>Long live Richard, England's royal king!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord Mayor</speaker>
            <speaker>Citizens</speaker>
            <line>Amen.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>To-morrow will it please you to be crown'd?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Even when you please, since you will have it so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>To-morrow, then, we will attend your grace:</line>
            <line>And so most joyfully we take our leave.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Come, let us to our holy task again.</line>
            <line>Farewell, good cousin; farewell, gentle friends.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>