<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:shakespear:dtd:act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-2">
   <title>ACT II</title>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  Ely House.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter JOHN OF GAUNT sick, with the DUKE OF YORK,
&amp;c</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOHN OF GAUNT</speaker>
            <line>Will the king come, that I may breathe my last</line>
            <line>In wholesome counsel to his unstaid youth?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Vex not yourself, nor strive not with your breath;</line>
            <line>For all in vain comes counsel to his ear.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOHN OF GAUNT</speaker>
            <line>O, but they say the tongues of dying men</line>
            <line>Enforce attention like deep harmony:</line>
            <line>Where words are scarce, they are seldom spent in vain,</line>
            <line>For they breathe truth that breathe their words in pain.</line>
            <line>He that no more must say is listen'd more</line>
            <line>Than they whom youth and ease have taught to glose;</line>
            <line>More are men's ends mark'd than their lives before:</line>
            <line>The setting sun, and music at the close,</line>
            <line>As the last taste of sweets, is sweetest last,</line>
            <line>Writ in remembrance more than things long past:</line>
            <line>Though Richard my life's counsel would not hear,</line>
            <line>My death's sad tale may yet undeaf his ear.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>No; it is stopp'd with other flattering sounds,</line>
            <line>As praises, of whose taste the wise are fond,</line>
            <line>Lascivious metres, to whose venom sound</line>
            <line>The open ear of youth doth always listen;</line>
            <line>Report of fashions in proud Italy,</line>
            <line>Whose manners still our tardy apish nation</line>
            <line>Limps after in base imitation.</line>
            <line>Where doth the world thrust forth a vanity--</line>
            <line>So it be new, there's no respect how vile--</line>
            <line>That is not quickly buzzed into his ears?</line>
            <line>Then all too late comes counsel to be heard,</line>
            <line>Where will doth mutiny with wit's regard.</line>
            <line>Direct not him whose way himself will choose:</line>
            <line>'Tis breath thou lack'st, and that breath wilt thou lose.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOHN OF GAUNT</speaker>
            <line>Methinks I am a prophet new inspired</line>
            <line>And thus expiring do foretell of him:</line>
            <line>His rash fierce blaze of riot cannot last,</line>
            <line>For violent fires soon burn out themselves;</line>
            <line>Small showers last long, but sudden storms are short;</line>
            <line>He tires betimes that spurs too fast betimes;</line>
            <line>With eager feeding food doth choke the feeder:</line>
            <line>Light vanity, insatiate cormorant,</line>
            <line>Consuming means, soon preys upon itself.</line>
            <line>This royal throne of kings, this scepter'd isle,</line>
            <line>This earth of majesty, this seat of Mars,</line>
            <line>This other Eden, demi-paradise,</line>
            <line>This fortress built by Nature for herself</line>
            <line>Against infection and the hand of war,</line>
            <line>This happy breed of men, this little world,</line>
            <line>This precious stone set in the silver sea,</line>
            <line>Which serves it in the office of a wall,</line>
            <line>Or as a moat defensive to a house,</line>
            <line>Against the envy of less happier lands,</line>
            <line>This blessed plot, this earth, this realm, this England,</line>
            <line>This nurse, this teeming womb of royal kings,</line>
            <line>Fear'd by their breed and famous by their birth,</line>
            <line>Renowned for their deeds as far from home,</line>
            <line>For Christian service and true chivalry,</line>
            <line>As is the sepulchre in stubborn Jewry,</line>
            <line>Of the world's ransom, blessed Mary's Son,</line>
            <line>This land of such dear souls, this dear dear land,</line>
            <line>Dear for her reputation through the world,</line>
            <line>Is now leased out, I die pronouncing it,</line>
            <line>Like to a tenement or pelting farm:</line>
            <line>England, bound in with the triumphant sea</line>
            <line>Whose rocky shore beats back the envious siege</line>
            <line>Of watery Neptune, is now bound in with shame,</line>
            <line>With inky blots and rotten parchment bonds:</line>
            <line>That England, that was wont to conquer others,</line>
            <line>Hath made a shameful conquest of itself.</line>
            <line>Ah, would the scandal vanish with my life,</line>
            <line>How happy then were my ensuing death!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter KING RICHARD II and QUEEN, DUKE OF AUMERLE,
BUSHY, GREEN, BAGOT, LORD ROSS, and LORD
WILLOUGHBY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>The king is come: deal mildly with his youth;</line>
            <line>For young hot colts being raged do rage the more.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN</speaker>
            <line>How fares our noble uncle, Lancaster?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>What comfort, man? how is't with aged Gaunt?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOHN OF GAUNT</speaker>
            <line>O how that name befits my composition!</line>
            <line>Old Gaunt indeed, and gaunt in being old:</line>
            <line>Within me grief hath kept a tedious fast;</line>
            <line>And who abstains from meat that is not gaunt?</line>
            <line>For sleeping England long time have I watch'd;</line>
            <line>Watching breeds leanness, leanness is all gaunt:</line>
            <line>The pleasure that some fathers feed upon,</line>
            <line>Is my strict fast; I mean, my children's looks;</line>
            <line>And therein fasting, hast thou made me gaunt:</line>
            <line>Gaunt am I for the grave, gaunt as a grave,</line>
            <line>Whose hollow womb inherits nought but bones.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>Can sick men play so nicely with their names?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOHN OF GAUNT</speaker>
            <line>No, misery makes sport to mock itself:</line>
            <line>Since thou dost seek to kill my name in me,</line>
            <line>I mock my name, great king, to flatter thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>Should dying men flatter with those that live?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOHN OF GAUNT</speaker>
            <line>No, no, men living flatter those that die.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>Thou, now a-dying, say'st thou flatterest me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOHN OF GAUNT</speaker>
            <line>O, no! thou diest, though I the sicker be.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>I am in health, I breathe, and see thee ill.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOHN OF GAUNT</speaker>
            <line>Now He that made me knows I see thee ill;</line>
            <line>Ill in myself to see, and in thee seeing ill.</line>
            <line>Thy death-bed is no lesser than thy land</line>
            <line>Wherein thou liest in reputation sick;</line>
            <line>And thou, too careless patient as thou art,</line>
            <line>Commit'st thy anointed body to the cure</line>
            <line>Of those physicians that first wounded thee:</line>
            <line>A thousand flatterers sit within thy crown,</line>
            <line>Whose compass is no bigger than thy head;</line>
            <line>And yet, incaged in so small a verge,</line>
            <line>The waste is no whit lesser than thy land.</line>
            <line>O, had thy grandsire with a prophet's eye</line>
            <line>Seen how his son's son should destroy his sons,</line>
            <line>From forth thy reach he would have laid thy shame,</line>
            <line>Deposing thee before thou wert possess'd,</line>
            <line>Which art possess'd now to depose thyself.</line>
            <line>Why, cousin, wert thou regent of the world,</line>
            <line>It were a shame to let this land by lease;</line>
            <line>But for thy world enjoying but this land,</line>
            <line>Is it not more than shame to shame it so?</line>
            <line>Landlord of England art thou now, not king:</line>
            <line>Thy state of law is bondslave to the law; And thou--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>A lunatic lean-witted fool,</line>
            <line>Presuming on an ague's privilege,</line>
            <line>Darest with thy frozen admonition</line>
            <line>Make pale our cheek, chasing the royal blood</line>
            <line>With fury from his native residence.</line>
            <line>Now, by my seat's right royal majesty,</line>
            <line>Wert thou not brother to great Edward's son,</line>
            <line>This tongue that runs so roundly in thy head</line>
            <line>Should run thy head from thy unreverent shoulders.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOHN OF GAUNT</speaker>
            <line>O, spare me not, my brother Edward's son,</line>
            <line>For that I was his father Edward's son;</line>
            <line>That blood already, like the pelican,</line>
            <line>Hast thou tapp'd out and drunkenly caroused:</line>
            <line>My brother Gloucester, plain well-meaning soul,</line>
            <line>Whom fair befal in heaven 'mongst happy souls!</line>
            <line>May be a precedent and witness good</line>
            <line>That thou respect'st not spilling Edward's blood:</line>
            <line>Join with the present sickness that I have;</line>
            <line>And thy unkindness be like crooked age,</line>
            <line>To crop at once a too long wither'd flower.</line>
            <line>Live in thy shame, but die not shame with thee!</line>
            <line>These words hereafter thy tormentors be!</line>
            <line>Convey me to my bed, then to my grave:</line>
            <line>Love they to live that love and honour have.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit, borne off by his Attendants</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>And let them die that age and sullens have;</line>
            <line>For both hast thou, and both become the grave.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>I do beseech your majesty, impute his words</line>
            <line>To wayward sickliness and age in him:</line>
            <line>He loves you, on my life, and holds you dear</line>
            <line>As Harry Duke of Hereford, were he here.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>Right, you say true: as Hereford's love, so his;</line>
            <line>As theirs, so mine; and all be as it is.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter NORTHUMBERLAND</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>My liege, old Gaunt commends him to your majesty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>What says he?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>Nay, nothing; all is said</line>
            <line>His tongue is now a stringless instrument;</line>
            <line>Words, life and all, old Lancaster hath spent.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Be York the next that must be bankrupt so!</line>
            <line>Though death be poor, it ends a mortal woe.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>The ripest fruit first falls, and so doth he;</line>
            <line>His time is spent, our pilgrimage must be.</line>
            <line>So much for that. Now for our Irish wars:</line>
            <line>We must supplant those rough rug-headed kerns,</line>
            <line>Which live like venom where no venom else</line>
            <line>But only they have privilege to live.</line>
            <line>And for these great affairs do ask some charge,</line>
            <line>Towards our assistance we do seize to us</line>
            <line>The plate, corn, revenues and moveables,</line>
            <line>Whereof our uncle Gaunt did stand possess'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>How long shall I be patient? ah, how long</line>
            <line>Shall tender duty make me suffer wrong?</line>
            <line>Not Gloucester's death, nor Hereford's banishment</line>
            <line>Not Gaunt's rebukes, nor England's private wrongs,</line>
            <line>Nor the prevention of poor Bolingbroke</line>
            <line>About his marriage, nor my own disgrace,</line>
            <line>Have ever made me sour my patient cheek,</line>
            <line>Or bend one wrinkle on my sovereign's face.</line>
            <line>I am the last of noble Edward's sons,</line>
            <line>Of whom thy father, Prince of Wales, was first:</line>
            <line>In war was never lion raged more fierce,</line>
            <line>In peace was never gentle lamb more mild,</line>
            <line>Than was that young and princely gentleman.</line>
            <line>His face thou hast, for even so look'd he,</line>
            <line>Accomplish'd with the number of thy hours;</line>
            <line>But when he frown'd, it was against the French</line>
            <line>And not against his friends; his noble hand</line>
            <line>Did will what he did spend and spent not that</line>
            <line>Which his triumphant father's hand had won;</line>
            <line>His hands were guilty of no kindred blood,</line>
            <line>But bloody with the enemies of his kin.</line>
            <line>O Richard! York is too far gone with grief,</line>
            <line>Or else he never would compare between.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>Why, uncle, what's the matter?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>O my liege,</line>
            <line>Pardon me, if you please; if not, I, pleased</line>
            <line>Not to be pardon'd, am content withal.</line>
            <line>Seek you to seize and gripe into your hands</line>
            <line>The royalties and rights of banish'd Hereford?</line>
            <line>Is not Gaunt dead, and doth not Hereford live?</line>
            <line>Was not Gaunt just, and is not Harry true?</line>
            <line>Did not the one deserve to have an heir?</line>
            <line>Is not his heir a well-deserving son?</line>
            <line>Take Hereford's rights away, and take from Time</line>
            <line>His charters and his customary rights;</line>
            <line>Let not to-morrow then ensue to-day;</line>
            <line>Be not thyself; for how art thou a king</line>
            <line>But by fair sequence and succession?</line>
            <line>Now, afore God--God forbid I say true!--</line>
            <line>If you do wrongfully seize Hereford's rights,</line>
            <line>Call in the letters patent that he hath</line>
            <line>By his attorneys-general to sue</line>
            <line>His livery, and deny his offer'd homage,</line>
            <line>You pluck a thousand dangers on your head,</line>
            <line>You lose a thousand well-disposed hearts</line>
            <line>And prick my tender patience, to those thoughts</line>
            <line>Which honour and allegiance cannot think.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>Think what you will, we seize into our hands</line>
            <line>His plate, his goods, his money and his lands.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>I'll not be by the while: my liege, farewell:</line>
            <line>What will ensue hereof, there's none can tell;</line>
            <line>But by bad courses may be understood</line>
            <line>That their events can never fall out good.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>Go, Bushy, to the Earl of Wiltshire straight:</line>
            <line>Bid him repair to us to Ely House</line>
            <line>To see this business. To-morrow next</line>
            <line>We will for Ireland; and 'tis time, I trow:</line>
            <line>And we create, in absence of ourself,</line>
            <line>Our uncle York lord governor of England;</line>
            <line>For he is just and always loved us well.</line>
            <line>Come on, our queen: to-morrow must we part;</line>
            <line>Be merry, for our time of stay is short</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Flourish. Exeunt KING RICHARD II, QUEEN, DUKE OF
AUMERLE, BUSHY, GREEN, and BAGOT</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>Well, lords, the Duke of Lancaster is dead.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD ROSS</speaker>
            <line>And living too; for now his son is duke.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD WILLOUGHBY</speaker>
            <line>Barely in title, not in revenue.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>Richly in both, if justice had her right.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD ROSS</speaker>
            <line>My heart is great; but it must break with silence,</line>
            <line>Ere't be disburden'd with a liberal tongue.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>Nay, speak thy mind; and let him ne'er speak more</line>
            <line>That speaks thy words again to do thee harm!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD WILLOUGHBY</speaker>
            <line>Tends that thou wouldst speak to the Duke of Hereford?</line>
            <line>If it be so, out with it boldly, man;</line>
            <line>Quick is mine ear to hear of good towards him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD ROSS</speaker>
            <line>No good at all that I can do for him;</line>
            <line>Unless you call it good to pity him,</line>
            <line>Bereft and gelded of his patrimony.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>Now, afore God, 'tis shame such wrongs are borne</line>
            <line>In him, a royal prince, and many moe</line>
            <line>Of noble blood in this declining land.</line>
            <line>The king is not himself, but basely led</line>
            <line>By flatterers; and what they will inform,</line>
            <line>Merely in hate, 'gainst any of us all,</line>
            <line>That will the king severely prosecute</line>
            <line>'Gainst us, our lives, our children, and our heirs.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD ROSS</speaker>
            <line>The commons hath he pill'd with grievous taxes,</line>
            <line>And quite lost their hearts: the nobles hath he fined</line>
            <line>For ancient quarrels, and quite lost their hearts.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD WILLOUGHBY</speaker>
            <line>And daily new exactions are devised,</line>
            <line>As blanks, benevolences, and I wot not what:</line>
            <line>But what, o' God's name, doth become of this?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>Wars have not wasted it, for warr'd he hath not,</line>
            <line>But basely yielded upon compromise</line>
            <line>That which his noble ancestors achieved with blows:</line>
            <line>More hath he spent in peace than they in wars.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD ROSS</speaker>
            <line>The Earl of Wiltshire hath the realm in farm.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD WILLOUGHBY</speaker>
            <line>The king's grown bankrupt, like a broken man.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>Reproach and dissolution hangeth over him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD ROSS</speaker>
            <line>He hath not money for these Irish wars,</line>
            <line>His burthenous taxations notwithstanding,</line>
            <line>But by the robbing of the banish'd duke.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>His noble kinsman: most degenerate king!</line>
            <line>But, lords, we hear this fearful tempest sing,</line>
            <line>Yet see no shelter to avoid the storm;</line>
            <line>We see the wind sit sore upon our sails,</line>
            <line>And yet we strike not, but securely perish.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD ROSS</speaker>
            <line>We see the very wreck that we must suffer;</line>
            <line>And unavoided is the danger now,</line>
            <line>For suffering so the causes of our wreck.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>Not so; even through the hollow eyes of death</line>
            <line>I spy life peering; but I dare not say</line>
            <line>How near the tidings of our comfort is.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD WILLOUGHBY</speaker>
            <line>Nay, let us share thy thoughts, as thou dost ours.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD ROSS</speaker>
            <line>Be confident to speak, Northumberland:</line>
            <line>We three are but thyself; and, speaking so,</line>
            <line>Thy words are but as thoughts; therefore, be bold.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>Then thus: I have from Port le Blanc, a bay</line>
            <line>In Brittany, received intelligence</line>
            <line>That Harry Duke of Hereford, Rainold Lord Cobham,</line>
            <line>That late broke from the Duke of Exeter,</line>
            <line>His brother, Archbishop late of Canterbury,</line>
            <line>Sir Thomas Erpingham, Sir John Ramston,</line>
            <line>Sir John Norbery, Sir Robert Waterton and Francis Quoint,</line>
            <line>All these well furnish'd by the Duke of Bretagne</line>
            <line>With eight tall ships, three thousand men of war,</line>
            <line>Are making hither with all due expedience</line>
            <line>And shortly mean to touch our northern shore:</line>
            <line>Perhaps they had ere this, but that they stay</line>
            <line>The first departing of the king for Ireland.</line>
            <line>If then we shall shake off our slavish yoke,</line>
            <line>Imp out our drooping country's broken wing,</line>
            <line>Redeem from broking pawn the blemish'd crown,</line>
            <line>Wipe off the dust that hides our sceptre's gilt</line>
            <line>And make high majesty look like itself,</line>
            <line>Away with me in post to Ravenspurgh;</line>
            <line>But if you faint, as fearing to do so,</line>
            <line>Stay and be secret, and myself will go.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD ROSS</speaker>
            <line>To horse, to horse! urge doubts to them that fear.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD WILLOUGHBY</speaker>
            <line>Hold out my horse, and I will first be there.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  The palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter QUEEN, BUSHY, and BAGOT</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUSHY</speaker>
            <line>Madam, your majesty is too much sad:</line>
            <line>You promised, when you parted with the king,</line>
            <line>To lay aside life-harming heaviness</line>
            <line>And entertain a cheerful disposition.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN</speaker>
            <line>To please the king I did; to please myself</line>
            <line>I cannot do it; yet I know no cause</line>
            <line>Why I should welcome such a guest as grief,</line>
            <line>Save bidding farewell to so sweet a guest</line>
            <line>As my sweet Richard: yet again, methinks,</line>
            <line>Some unborn sorrow, ripe in fortune's womb,</line>
            <line>Is coming towards me, and my inward soul</line>
            <line>With nothing trembles: at some thing it grieves,</line>
            <line>More than with parting from my lord the king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUSHY</speaker>
            <line>Each substance of a grief hath twenty shadows,</line>
            <line>Which shows like grief itself, but is not so;</line>
            <line>For sorrow's eye, glazed with blinding tears,</line>
            <line>Divides one thing entire to many objects;</line>
            <line>Like perspectives, which rightly gazed upon</line>
            <line>Show nothing but confusion, eyed awry</line>
            <line>Distinguish form: so your sweet majesty,</line>
            <line>Looking awry upon your lord's departure,</line>
            <line>Find shapes of grief, more than himself, to wail;</line>
            <line>Which, look'd on as it is, is nought but shadows</line>
            <line>Of what it is not. Then, thrice-gracious queen,</line>
            <line>More than your lord's departure weep not: more's not seen;</line>
            <line>Or if it be, 'tis with false sorrow's eye,</line>
            <line>Which for things true weeps things imaginary.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN</speaker>
            <line>It may be so; but yet my inward soul</line>
            <line>Persuades me it is otherwise: howe'er it be,</line>
            <line>I cannot but be sad; so heavy sad</line>
            <line>As, though on thinking on no thought I think,</line>
            <line>Makes me with heavy nothing faint and shrink.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUSHY</speaker>
            <line>'Tis nothing but conceit, my gracious lady.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN</speaker>
            <line>'Tis nothing less: conceit is still derived</line>
            <line>From some forefather grief; mine is not so,</line>
            <line>For nothing had begot my something grief;</line>
            <line>Or something hath the nothing that I grieve:</line>
            <line>'Tis in reversion that I do possess;</line>
            <line>But what it is, that is not yet known; what</line>
            <line>I cannot name; 'tis nameless woe, I wot.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter GREEN</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GREEN</speaker>
            <line>God save your majesty! and well met, gentlemen:</line>
            <line>I hope the king is not yet shipp'd for Ireland.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN</speaker>
            <line>Why hopest thou so? 'tis better hope he is;</line>
            <line>For his designs crave haste, his haste good hope:</line>
            <line>Then wherefore dost thou hope he is not shipp'd?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GREEN</speaker>
            <line>That he, our hope, might have retired his power,</line>
            <line>And driven into despair an enemy's hope,</line>
            <line>Who strongly hath set footing in this land:</line>
            <line>The banish'd Bolingbroke repeals himself,</line>
            <line>And with uplifted arms is safe arrived</line>
            <line>At Ravenspurgh.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN</speaker>
            <line>Now God in heaven forbid!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GREEN</speaker>
            <line>Ah, madam, 'tis too true: and that is worse,</line>
            <line>The Lord Northumberland, his son young Henry Percy,</line>
            <line>The Lords of Ross, Beaumond, and Willoughby,</line>
            <line>With all their powerful friends, are fled to him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUSHY</speaker>
            <line>Why have you not proclaim'd Northumberland</line>
            <line>And all the rest revolted faction traitors?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GREEN</speaker>
            <line>We have: whereupon the Earl of Worcester</line>
            <line>Hath broke his staff, resign'd his stewardship,</line>
            <line>And all the household servants fled with him</line>
            <line>To Bolingbroke.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN</speaker>
            <line>So, Green, thou art the midwife to my woe,</line>
            <line>And Bolingbroke my sorrow's dismal heir:</line>
            <line>Now hath my soul brought forth her prodigy,</line>
            <line>And I, a gasping new-deliver'd mother,</line>
            <line>Have woe to woe, sorrow to sorrow join'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUSHY</speaker>
            <line>Despair not, madam.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN</speaker>
            <line>Who shall hinder me?</line>
            <line>I will despair, and be at enmity</line>
            <line>With cozening hope: he is a flatterer,</line>
            <line>A parasite, a keeper back of death,</line>
            <line>Who gently would dissolve the bands of life,</line>
            <line>Which false hope lingers in extremity.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter DUKE OF YORK</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GREEN</speaker>
            <line>Here comes the Duke of York.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN</speaker>
            <line>With signs of war about his aged neck:</line>
            <line>O, full of careful business are his looks!</line>
            <line>Uncle, for God's sake, speak comfortable words.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Should I do so, I should belie my thoughts:</line>
            <line>Comfort's in heaven; and we are on the earth,</line>
            <line>Where nothing lives but crosses, cares and grief.</line>
            <line>Your husband, he is gone to save far off,</line>
            <line>Whilst others come to make him lose at home:</line>
            <line>Here am I left to underprop his land,</line>
            <line>Who, weak with age, cannot support myself:</line>
            <line>Now comes the sick hour that his surfeit made;</line>
            <line>Now shall he try his friends that flatter'd him.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter a Servant</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>My lord, your son was gone before I came.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>He was? Why, so! go all which way it will!</line>
            <line>The nobles they are fled, the commons they are cold,</line>
            <line>And will, I fear, revolt on Hereford's side.</line>
            <line>Sirrah, get thee to Plashy, to my sister Gloucester;</line>
            <line>Bid her send me presently a thousand pound:</line>
            <line>Hold, take my ring.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>My lord, I had forgot to tell your lordship,</line>
            <line>To-day, as I came by, I called there;</line>
            <line>But I shall grieve you to report the rest.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>What is't, knave?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>An hour before I came, the duchess died.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>God for his mercy! what a tide of woes</line>
            <line>Comes rushing on this woeful land at once!</line>
            <line>I know not what to do: I would to God,</line>
            <line>So my untruth had not provoked him to it,</line>
            <line>The king had cut off my head with my brother's.</line>
            <line>What, are there no posts dispatch'd for Ireland?</line>
            <line>How shall we do for money for these wars?</line>
            <line>Come, sister,--cousin, I would say--pray, pardon me.</line>
            <line>Go, fellow, get thee home, provide some carts</line>
            <line>And bring away the armour that is there.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit Servant</stagedir>
            <line>Gentlemen, will you go muster men?</line>
            <line>If I know how or which way to order these affairs</line>
            <line>Thus thrust disorderly into my hands,</line>
            <line>Never believe me. Both are my kinsmen:</line>
            <line>The one is my sovereign, whom both my oath</line>
            <line>And duty bids defend; the other again</line>
            <line>Is my kinsman, whom the king hath wrong'd,</line>
            <line>Whom conscience and my kindred bids to right.</line>
            <line>Well, somewhat we must do. Come, cousin, I'll</line>
            <line>Dispose of you.</line>
            <line>Gentlemen, go, muster up your men,</line>
            <line>And meet me presently at Berkeley.</line>
            <line>I should to Plashy too;</line>
            <line>But time will not permit: all is uneven,</line>
            <line>And every thing is left at six and seven.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt DUKE OF YORK and QUEEN</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUSHY</speaker>
            <line>The wind sits fair for news to go to Ireland,</line>
            <line>But none returns. For us to levy power</line>
            <line>Proportionable to the enemy</line>
            <line>Is all unpossible.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GREEN</speaker>
            <line>Besides, our nearness to the king in love</line>
            <line>Is near the hate of those love not the king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BAGOT</speaker>
            <line>And that's the wavering commons: for their love</line>
            <line>Lies in their purses, and whoso empties them</line>
            <line>By so much fills their hearts with deadly hate.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUSHY</speaker>
            <line>Wherein the king stands generally condemn'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BAGOT</speaker>
            <line>If judgement lie in them, then so do we,</line>
            <line>Because we ever have been near the king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GREEN</speaker>
            <line>Well, I will for refuge straight to Bristol castle:</line>
            <line>The Earl of Wiltshire is already there.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUSHY</speaker>
            <line>Thither will I with you; for little office</line>
            <line>The hateful commons will perform for us,</line>
            <line>Except like curs to tear us all to pieces.</line>
            <line>Will you go along with us?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BAGOT</speaker>
            <line>No; I will to Ireland to his majesty.</line>
            <line>Farewell: if heart's presages be not vain,</line>
            <line>We three here art that ne'er shall meet again.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUSHY</speaker>
            <line>That's as York thrives to beat back Bolingbroke.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GREEN</speaker>
            <line>Alas, poor duke! the task he undertakes</line>
            <line>Is numbering sands and drinking oceans dry:</line>
            <line>Where one on his side fights, thousands will fly.</line>
            <line>Farewell at once, for once, for all, and ever.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUSHY</speaker>
            <line>Well, we may meet again.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BAGOT</speaker>
            <line>I fear me, never.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  Wilds in Gloucestershire.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter HENRY BOLINGBROKE and NORTHUMBERLAND, with Forces</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>How far is it, my lord, to Berkeley now?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>Believe me, noble lord,</line>
            <line>I am a stranger here in Gloucestershire:</line>
            <line>These high wild hills and rough uneven ways</line>
            <line>Draws out our miles, and makes them wearisome,</line>
            <line>And yet your fair discourse hath been as sugar,</line>
            <line>Making the hard way sweet and delectable.</line>
            <line>But I bethink me what a weary way</line>
            <line>From Ravenspurgh to Cotswold will be found</line>
            <line>In Ross and Willoughby, wanting your company,</line>
            <line>Which, I protest, hath very much beguiled</line>
            <line>The tediousness and process of my travel:</line>
            <line>But theirs is sweetened with the hope to have</line>
            <line>The present benefit which I possess;</line>
            <line>And hope to joy is little less in joy</line>
            <line>Than hope enjoy'd: by this the weary lords</line>
            <line>Shall make their way seem short, as mine hath done</line>
            <line>By sight of what I have, your noble company.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Of much less value is my company</line>
            <line>Than your good words. But who comes here?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter HENRY PERCY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>It is my son, young Harry Percy,</line>
            <line>Sent from my brother Worcester, whencesoever.</line>
            <line>Harry, how fares your uncle?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY PERCY</speaker>
            <line>I had thought, my lord, to have learn'd his health of you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>Why, is he not with the queen?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY PERCY</speaker>
            <line>No, my good Lord; he hath forsook the court,</line>
            <line>Broken his staff of office and dispersed</line>
            <line>The household of the king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>What was his reason?</line>
            <line>He was not so resolved when last we spake together.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY PERCY</speaker>
            <line>Because your lordship was proclaimed traitor.</line>
            <line>But he, my lord, is gone to Ravenspurgh,</line>
            <line>To offer service to the Duke of Hereford,</line>
            <line>And sent me over by Berkeley, to discover</line>
            <line>What power the Duke of York had levied there;</line>
            <line>Then with directions to repair to Ravenspurgh.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>Have you forgot the Duke of Hereford, boy?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY PERCY</speaker>
            <line>No, my good lord, for that is not forgot</line>
            <line>Which ne'er I did remember: to my knowledge,</line>
            <line>I never in my life did look on him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>Then learn to know him now; this is the duke.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY PERCY</speaker>
            <line>My gracious lord, I tender you my service,</line>
            <line>Such as it is, being tender, raw and young:</line>
            <line>Which elder days shall ripen and confirm</line>
            <line>To more approved service and desert.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>I thank thee, gentle Percy; and be sure</line>
            <line>I count myself in nothing else so happy</line>
            <line>As in a soul remembering my good friends;</line>
            <line>And, as my fortune ripens with thy love,</line>
            <line>It shall be still thy true love's recompense:</line>
            <line>My heart this covenant makes, my hand thus seals it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>How far is it to Berkeley? and what stir</line>
            <line>Keeps good old York there with his men of war?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY PERCY</speaker>
            <line>There stands the castle, by yon tuft of trees,</line>
            <line>Mann'd with three hundred men, as I have heard;</line>
            <line>And in it are the Lords of York, Berkeley, and Seymour;</line>
            <line>None else of name and noble estimate.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter LORD ROSS and LORD WILLOUGHBY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>Here come the Lords of Ross and Willoughby,</line>
            <line>Bloody with spurring, fiery-red with haste.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Welcome, my lords. I wot your love pursues</line>
            <line>A banish'd traitor: all my treasury</line>
            <line>Is yet but unfelt thanks, which more enrich'd</line>
            <line>Shall be your love and labour's recompense.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD ROSS</speaker>
            <line>Your presence makes us rich, most noble lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD WILLOUGHBY</speaker>
            <line>And far surmounts our labour to attain it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Evermore thanks, the exchequer of the poor;</line>
            <line>Which, till my infant fortune comes to years,</line>
            <line>Stands for my bounty. But who comes here?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter LORD BERKELEY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>It is my Lord of Berkeley, as I guess.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD BERKELEY</speaker>
            <line>My Lord of Hereford, my message is to you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>My lord, my answer is--to Lancaster;</line>
            <line>And I am come to seek that name in England;</line>
            <line>And I must find that title in your tongue,</line>
            <line>Before I make reply to aught you say.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD BERKELEY</speaker>
            <line>Mistake me not, my lord; 'tis not my meaning</line>
            <line>To raze one title of your honour out:</line>
            <line>To you, my lord, I come, what lord you will,</line>
            <line>From the most gracious regent of this land,</line>
            <line>The Duke of York, to know what pricks you on</line>
            <line>To take advantage of the absent time</line>
            <line>And fright our native peace with self-born arms.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter DUKE OF YORK attended</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>I shall not need transport my words by you;</line>
            <line>Here comes his grace in person. My noble uncle!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Kneels</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Show me thy humble heart, and not thy knee,</line>
            <line>Whose duty is deceiveable and false.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>My gracious uncle--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Tut, tut!</line>
            <line>Grace me no grace, nor uncle me no uncle:</line>
            <line>I am no traitor's uncle; and that word 'grace.'</line>
            <line>In an ungracious mouth is but profane.</line>
            <line>Why have those banish'd and forbidden legs</line>
            <line>Dared once to touch a dust of England's ground?</line>
            <line>But then more 'why?' why have they dared to march</line>
            <line>So many miles upon her peaceful bosom,</line>
            <line>Frighting her pale-faced villages with war</line>
            <line>And ostentation of despised arms?</line>
            <line>Comest thou because the anointed king is hence?</line>
            <line>Why, foolish boy, the king is left behind,</line>
            <line>And in my loyal bosom lies his power.</line>
            <line>Were I but now the lord of such hot youth</line>
            <line>As when brave Gaunt, thy father, and myself</line>
            <line>Rescued the Black Prince, that young Mars of men,</line>
            <line>From forth the ranks of many thousand French,</line>
            <line>O, then how quickly should this arm of mine.</line>
            <line>Now prisoner to the palsy, chastise thee</line>
            <line>And minister correction to thy fault!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>My gracious uncle, let me know my fault:</line>
            <line>On what condition stands it and wherein?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Even in condition of the worst degree,</line>
            <line>In gross rebellion and detested treason:</line>
            <line>Thou art a banish'd man, and here art come</line>
            <line>Before the expiration of thy time,</line>
            <line>In braving arms against thy sovereign.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>As I was banish'd, I was banish'd Hereford;</line>
            <line>But as I come, I come for Lancaster.</line>
            <line>And, noble uncle, I beseech your grace</line>
            <line>Look on my wrongs with an indifferent eye:</line>
            <line>You are my father, for methinks in you</line>
            <line>I see old Gaunt alive; O, then, my father,</line>
            <line>Will you permit that I shall stand condemn'd</line>
            <line>A wandering vagabond; my rights and royalties</line>
            <line>Pluck'd from my arms perforce and given away</line>
            <line>To upstart unthrifts? Wherefore was I born?</line>
            <line>If that my cousin king be King of England,</line>
            <line>It must be granted I am Duke of Lancaster.</line>
            <line>You have a son, Aumerle, my noble cousin;</line>
            <line>Had you first died, and he been thus trod down,</line>
            <line>He should have found his uncle Gaunt a father,</line>
            <line>To rouse his wrongs and chase them to the bay.</line>
            <line>I am denied to sue my livery here,</line>
            <line>And yet my letters-patents give me leave:</line>
            <line>My father's goods are all distrain'd and sold,</line>
            <line>And these and all are all amiss employ'd.</line>
            <line>What would you have me do? I am a subject,</line>
            <line>And I challenge law: attorneys are denied me;</line>
            <line>And therefore, personally I lay my claim</line>
            <line>To my inheritance of free descent.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>The noble duke hath been too much abused.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD ROSS</speaker>
            <line>It stands your grace upon to do him right.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD WILLOUGHBY</speaker>
            <line>Base men by his endowments are made great.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>My lords of England, let me tell you this:</line>
            <line>I have had feeling of my cousin's wrongs</line>
            <line>And laboured all I could to do him right;</line>
            <line>But in this kind to come, in braving arms,</line>
            <line>Be his own carver and cut out his way,</line>
            <line>To find out right with wrong, it may not be;</line>
            <line>And you that do abet him in this kind</line>
            <line>Cherish rebellion and are rebels all.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>The noble duke hath sworn his coming is</line>
            <line>But for his own; and for the right of that</line>
            <line>We all have strongly sworn to give him aid;</line>
            <line>And let him ne'er see joy that breaks that oath!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Well, well, I see the issue of these arms:</line>
            <line>I cannot mend it, I must needs confess,</line>
            <line>Because my power is weak and all ill left:</line>
            <line>But if I could, by Him that gave me life,</line>
            <line>I would attach you all and make you stoop</line>
            <line>Unto the sovereign mercy of the king;</line>
            <line>But since I cannot, be it known to you</line>
            <line>I do remain as neuter. So, fare you well;</line>
            <line>Unless you please to enter in the castle</line>
            <line>And there repose you for this night.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>An offer, uncle, that we will accept:</line>
            <line>But we must win your grace to go with us</line>
            <line>To Bristol castle, which they say is held</line>
            <line>By Bushy, Bagot and their complices,</line>
            <line>The caterpillars of the commonwealth,</line>
            <line>Which I have sworn to weed and pluck away.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>It may be I will go with you: but yet I'll pause;</line>
            <line>For I am loath to break our country's laws.</line>
            <line>Nor friends nor foes, to me welcome you are:</line>
            <line>Things past redress are now with me past care.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-4">
      <title>SCENE IV.  A camp in Wales.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter EARL OF SALISBURY and a Welsh Captain</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Captain</speaker>
            <line>My lord of Salisbury, we have stay'd ten days,</line>
            <line>And hardly kept our countrymen together,</line>
            <line>And yet we hear no tidings from the king;</line>
            <line>Therefore we will disperse ourselves: farewell.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EARL OF SALISBURY</speaker>
            <line>Stay yet another day, thou trusty Welshman:</line>
            <line>The king reposeth all his confidence in thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Captain</speaker>
            <line>'Tis thought the king is dead; we will not stay.</line>
            <line>The bay-trees in our country are all wither'd</line>
            <line>And meteors fright the fixed stars of heaven;</line>
            <line>The pale-faced moon looks bloody on the earth</line>
            <line>And lean-look'd prophets whisper fearful change;</line>
            <line>Rich men look sad and ruffians dance and leap,</line>
            <line>The one in fear to lose what they enjoy,</line>
            <line>The other to enjoy by rage and war:</line>
            <line>These signs forerun the death or fall of kings.</line>
            <line>Farewell: our countrymen are gone and fled,</line>
            <line>As well assured Richard their king is dead.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EARL OF SALISBURY</speaker>
            <line>Ah, Richard, with the eyes of heavy mind</line>
            <line>I see thy glory like a shooting star</line>
            <line>Fall to the base earth from the firmament.</line>
            <line>Thy sun sets weeping in the lowly west,</line>
            <line>Witnessing storms to come, woe and unrest:</line>
            <line>Thy friends are fled to wait upon thy foes,</line>
            <line>And crossly to thy good all fortune goes.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>