<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:shakespear:dtd:act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-3">
   <title>ACT III</title>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  Bristol. Before the castle.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter HENRY BOLINGBROKE, DUKE OF YORK,
NORTHUMBERLAND, LORD ROSS, HENRY PERCY, LORD
WILLOUGHBY, with BUSHY and GREEN, prisoners</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Bring forth these men.</line>
            <line>Bushy and Green, I will not vex your souls--</line>
            <line>Since presently your souls must part your bodies--</line>
            <line>With too much urging your pernicious lives,</line>
            <line>For 'twere no charity; yet, to wash your blood</line>
            <line>From off my hands, here in the view of men</line>
            <line>I will unfold some causes of your deaths.</line>
            <line>You have misled a prince, a royal king,</line>
            <line>A happy gentleman in blood and lineaments,</line>
            <line>By you unhappied and disfigured clean:</line>
            <line>You have in manner with your sinful hours</line>
            <line>Made a divorce betwixt his queen and him,</line>
            <line>Broke the possession of a royal bed</line>
            <line>And stain'd the beauty of a fair queen's cheeks</line>
            <line>With tears drawn from her eyes by your foul wrongs.</line>
            <line>Myself, a prince by fortune of my birth,</line>
            <line>Near to the king in blood, and near in love</line>
            <line>Till you did make him misinterpret me,</line>
            <line>Have stoop'd my neck under your injuries,</line>
            <line>And sigh'd my English breath in foreign clouds,</line>
            <line>Eating the bitter bread of banishment;</line>
            <line>Whilst you have fed upon my signories,</line>
            <line>Dispark'd my parks and fell'd my forest woods,</line>
            <line>From my own windows torn my household coat,</line>
            <line>Razed out my imprese, leaving me no sign,</line>
            <line>Save men's opinions and my living blood,</line>
            <line>To show the world I am a gentleman.</line>
            <line>This and much more, much more than twice all this,</line>
            <line>Condemns you to the death. See them deliver'd over</line>
            <line>To execution and the hand of death.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUSHY</speaker>
            <line>More welcome is the stroke of death to me</line>
            <line>Than Bolingbroke to England. Lords, farewell.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GREEN</speaker>
            <line>My comfort is that heaven will take our souls</line>
            <line>And plague injustice with the pains of hell.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>My Lord Northumberland, see them dispatch'd.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt NORTHUMBERLAND and others, with the
prisoners</stagedir>
            <line>Uncle, you say the queen is at your house;</line>
            <line>For God's sake, fairly let her be entreated:</line>
            <line>Tell her I send to her my kind commends;</line>
            <line>Take special care my greetings be deliver'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>A gentleman of mine I have dispatch'd</line>
            <line>With letters of your love to her at large.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Thank, gentle uncle. Come, lords, away.</line>
            <line>To fight with Glendower and his complices:</line>
            <line>Awhile to work, and after holiday.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  The coast of Wales. A castle in view.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Drums; flourish and colours. Enter KING RICHARD
II, the BISHOP OF CARLISLE, DUKE OF AUMERLE, and Soldiers</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>Barkloughly castle call they this at hand?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
            <line>Yea, my lord. How brooks your grace the air,</line>
            <line>After your late tossing on the breaking seas?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>Needs must I like it well: I weep for joy</line>
            <line>To stand upon my kingdom once again.</line>
            <line>Dear earth, I do salute thee with my hand,</line>
            <line>Though rebels wound thee with their horses' hoofs:</line>
            <line>As a long-parted mother with her child</line>
            <line>Plays fondly with her tears and smiles in meeting,</line>
            <line>So, weeping, smiling, greet I thee, my earth,</line>
            <line>And do thee favours with my royal hands.</line>
            <line>Feed not thy sovereign's foe, my gentle earth,</line>
            <line>Nor with thy sweets comfort his ravenous sense;</line>
            <line>But let thy spiders, that suck up thy venom,</line>
            <line>And heavy-gaited toads lie in their way,</line>
            <line>Doing annoyance to the treacherous feet</line>
            <line>Which with usurping steps do trample thee:</line>
            <line>Yield stinging nettles to mine enemies;</line>
            <line>And when they from thy bosom pluck a flower,</line>
            <line>Guard it, I pray thee, with a lurking adder</line>
            <line>Whose double tongue may with a mortal touch</line>
            <line>Throw death upon thy sovereign's enemies.</line>
            <line>Mock not my senseless conjuration, lords:</line>
            <line>This earth shall have a feeling and these stones</line>
            <line>Prove armed soldiers, ere her native king</line>
            <line>Shall falter under foul rebellion's arms.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BISHOP OF CARLISLE</speaker>
            <line>Fear not, my lord: that Power that made you king</line>
            <line>Hath power to keep you king in spite of all.</line>
            <line>The means that heaven yields must be embraced,</line>
            <line>And not neglected; else, if heaven would,</line>
            <line>And we will not, heaven's offer we refuse,</line>
            <line>The proffer'd means of succor and redress.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
            <line>He means, my lord, that we are too remiss;</line>
            <line>Whilst Bolingbroke, through our security,</line>
            <line>Grows strong and great in substance and in power.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>Discomfortable cousin! know'st thou not</line>
            <line>That when the searching eye of heaven is hid,</line>
            <line>Behind the globe, that lights the lower world,</line>
            <line>Then thieves and robbers range abroad unseen</line>
            <line>In murders and in outrage, boldly here;</line>
            <line>But when from under this terrestrial ball</line>
            <line>He fires the proud tops of the eastern pines</line>
            <line>And darts his light through every guilty hole,</line>
            <line>Then murders, treasons and detested sins,</line>
            <line>The cloak of night being pluck'd from off their backs,</line>
            <line>Stand bare and naked, trembling at themselves?</line>
            <line>So when this thief, this traitor, Bolingbroke,</line>
            <line>Who all this while hath revell'd in the night</line>
            <line>Whilst we were wandering with the antipodes,</line>
            <line>Shall see us rising in our throne, the east,</line>
            <line>His treasons will sit blushing in his face,</line>
            <line>Not able to endure the sight of day,</line>
            <line>But self-affrighted tremble at his sin.</line>
            <line>Not all the water in the rough rude sea</line>
            <line>Can wash the balm off from an anointed king;</line>
            <line>The breath of worldly men cannot depose</line>
            <line>The deputy elected by the Lord:</line>
            <line>For every man that Bolingbroke hath press'd</line>
            <line>To lift shrewd steel against our golden crown,</line>
            <line>God for his Richard hath in heavenly pay</line>
            <line>A glorious angel: then, if angels fight,</line>
            <line>Weak men must fall, for heaven still guards the right.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter EARL OF SALISBURY</stagedir>
            <line>Welcome, my lord how far off lies your power?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EARL OF SALISBURY</speaker>
            <line>Nor near nor farther off, my gracious lord,</line>
            <line>Than this weak arm: discomfort guides my tongue</line>
            <line>And bids me speak of nothing but despair.</line>
            <line>One day too late, I fear me, noble lord,</line>
            <line>Hath clouded all thy happy days on earth:</line>
            <line>O, call back yesterday, bid time return,</line>
            <line>And thou shalt have twelve thousand fighting men!</line>
            <line>To-day, to-day, unhappy day, too late,</line>
            <line>O'erthrows thy joys, friends, fortune and thy state:</line>
            <line>For all the Welshmen, hearing thou wert dead.</line>
            <line>Are gone to Bolingbroke, dispersed and fled.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
            <line>Comfort, my liege; why looks your grace so pale?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>But now the blood of twenty thousand men</line>
            <line>Did triumph in my face, and they are fled;</line>
            <line>And, till so much blood thither come again,</line>
            <line>Have I not reason to look pale and dead?</line>
            <line>All souls that will be safe fly from my side,</line>
            <line>For time hath set a blot upon my pride.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
            <line>Comfort, my liege; remember who you are.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>I had forgot myself; am I not king?</line>
            <line>Awake, thou coward majesty! thou sleepest.</line>
            <line>Is not the king's name twenty thousand names?</line>
            <line>Arm, arm, my name! a puny subject strikes</line>
            <line>At thy great glory. Look not to the ground,</line>
            <line>Ye favourites of a king: are we not high?</line>
            <line>High be our thoughts: I know my uncle York</line>
            <line>Hath power enough to serve our turn. But who comes here?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter SIR STEPHEN SCROOP</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR STEPHEN SCROOP</speaker>
            <line>More health and happiness betide my liege</line>
            <line>Than can my care-tuned tongue deliver him!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>Mine ear is open and my heart prepared;</line>
            <line>The worst is worldly loss thou canst unfold.</line>
            <line>Say, is my kingdom lost? why, 'twas my care</line>
            <line>And what loss is it to be rid of care?</line>
            <line>Strives Bolingbroke to be as great as we?</line>
            <line>Greater he shall not be; if he serve God,</line>
            <line>We'll serve Him too and be his fellow so:</line>
            <line>Revolt our subjects? that we cannot mend;</line>
            <line>They break their faith to God as well as us:</line>
            <line>Cry woe, destruction, ruin and decay:</line>
            <line>The worst is death, and death will have his day.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR STEPHEN SCROOP</speaker>
            <line>Glad am I that your highness is so arm'd</line>
            <line>To bear the tidings of calamity.</line>
            <line>Like an unseasonable stormy day,</line>
            <line>Which makes the silver rivers drown their shores,</line>
            <line>As if the world were all dissolved to tears,</line>
            <line>So high above his limits swells the rage</line>
            <line>Of Bolingbroke, covering your fearful land</line>
            <line>With hard bright steel and hearts harder than steel.</line>
            <line>White-beards have arm'd their thin and hairless scalps</line>
            <line>Against thy majesty; boys, with women's voices,</line>
            <line>Strive to speak big and clap their female joints</line>
            <line>In stiff unwieldy arms against thy crown:</line>
            <line>The very beadsmen learn to bend their bows</line>
            <line>Of double-fatal yew against thy state;</line>
            <line>Yea, distaff-women manage rusty bills</line>
            <line>Against thy seat: both young and old rebel,</line>
            <line>And all goes worse than I have power to tell.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>Too well, too well thou tell'st a tale so ill.</line>
            <line>Where is the Earl of Wiltshire? where is Bagot?</line>
            <line>What is become of Bushy? where is Green?</line>
            <line>That they have let the dangerous enemy</line>
            <line>Measure our confines with such peaceful steps?</line>
            <line>If we prevail, their heads shall pay for it:</line>
            <line>I warrant they have made peace with Bolingbroke.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR STEPHEN SCROOP</speaker>
            <line>Peace have they made with him indeed, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>O villains, vipers, damn'd without redemption!</line>
            <line>Dogs, easily won to fawn on any man!</line>
            <line>Snakes, in my heart-blood warm'd, that sting my heart!</line>
            <line>Three Judases, each one thrice worse than Judas!</line>
            <line>Would they make peace? terrible hell make war</line>
            <line>Upon their spotted souls for this offence!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR STEPHEN SCROOP</speaker>
            <line>Sweet love, I see, changing his property,</line>
            <line>Turns to the sourest and most deadly hate:</line>
            <line>Again uncurse their souls; their peace is made</line>
            <line>With heads, and not with hands; those whom you curse</line>
            <line>Have felt the worst of death's destroying wound</line>
            <line>And lie full low, graved in the hollow ground.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
            <line>Is Bushy, Green, and the Earl of Wiltshire dead?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR STEPHEN SCROOP</speaker>
            <line>Ay, all of them at Bristol lost their heads.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
            <line>Where is the duke my father with his power?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>No matter where; of comfort no man speak:</line>
            <line>Let's talk of graves, of worms, and epitaphs;</line>
            <line>Make dust our paper and with rainy eyes</line>
            <line>Write sorrow on the bosom of the earth,</line>
            <line>Let's choose executors and talk of wills:</line>
            <line>And yet not so, for what can we bequeath</line>
            <line>Save our deposed bodies to the ground?</line>
            <line>Our lands, our lives and all are Bolingbroke's,</line>
            <line>And nothing can we call our own but death</line>
            <line>And that small model of the barren earth</line>
            <line>Which serves as paste and cover to our bones.</line>
            <line>For God's sake, let us sit upon the ground</line>
            <line>And tell sad stories of the death of kings;</line>
            <line>How some have been deposed; some slain in war,</line>
            <line>Some haunted by the ghosts they have deposed;</line>
            <line>Some poison'd by their wives: some sleeping kill'd;</line>
            <line>All murder'd: for within the hollow crown</line>
            <line>That rounds the mortal temples of a king</line>
            <line>Keeps Death his court and there the antic sits,</line>
            <line>Scoffing his state and grinning at his pomp,</line>
            <line>Allowing him a breath, a little scene,</line>
            <line>To monarchize, be fear'd and kill with looks,</line>
            <line>Infusing him with self and vain conceit,</line>
            <line>As if this flesh which walls about our life,</line>
            <line>Were brass impregnable, and humour'd thus</line>
            <line>Comes at the last and with a little pin</line>
            <line>Bores through his castle wall, and farewell king!</line>
            <line>Cover your heads and mock not flesh and blood</line>
            <line>With solemn reverence: throw away respect,</line>
            <line>Tradition, form and ceremonious duty,</line>
            <line>For you have but mistook me all this while:</line>
            <line>I live with bread like you, feel want,</line>
            <line>Taste grief, need friends: subjected thus,</line>
            <line>How can you say to me, I am a king?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BISHOP OF CARLISLE</speaker>
            <line>My lord, wise men ne'er sit and wail their woes,</line>
            <line>But presently prevent the ways to wail.</line>
            <line>To fear the foe, since fear oppresseth strength,</line>
            <line>Gives in your weakness strength unto your foe,</line>
            <line>And so your follies fight against yourself.</line>
            <line>Fear and be slain; no worse can come to fight:</line>
            <line>And fight and die is death destroying death;</line>
            <line>Where fearing dying pays death servile breath.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
            <line>My father hath a power; inquire of him</line>
            <line>And learn to make a body of a limb.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>Thou chidest me well: proud Bolingbroke, I come</line>
            <line>To change blows with thee for our day of doom.</line>
            <line>This ague fit of fear is over-blown;</line>
            <line>An easy task it is to win our own.</line>
            <line>Say, Scroop, where lies our uncle with his power?</line>
            <line>Speak sweetly, man, although thy looks be sour.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR STEPHEN SCROOP</speaker>
            <line>Men judge by the complexion of the sky</line>
            <line>The state and inclination of the day:</line>
            <line>So may you by my dull and heavy eye,</line>
            <line>My tongue hath but a heavier tale to say.</line>
            <line>I play the torturer, by small and small</line>
            <line>To lengthen out the worst that must be spoken:</line>
            <line>Your uncle York is join'd with Bolingbroke,</line>
            <line>And all your northern castles yielded up,</line>
            <line>And all your southern gentlemen in arms</line>
            <line>Upon his party.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>Thou hast said enough.</line>
            <line>Beshrew thee, cousin, which didst lead me forth</line>
            <stagedir>To DUKE OF AUMERLE</stagedir>
            <line>Of that sweet way I was in to despair!</line>
            <line>What say you now? what comfort have we now?</line>
            <line>By heaven, I'll hate him everlastingly</line>
            <line>That bids me be of comfort any more.</line>
            <line>Go to Flint castle: there I'll pine away;</line>
            <line>A king, woe's slave, shall kingly woe obey.</line>
            <line>That power I have, discharge; and let them go</line>
            <line>To ear the land that hath some hope to grow,</line>
            <line>For I have none: let no man speak again</line>
            <line>To alter this, for counsel is but vain.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
            <line>My liege, one word.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>He does me double wrong</line>
            <line>That wounds me with the flatteries of his tongue.</line>
            <line>Discharge my followers: let them hence away,</line>
            <line>From Richard's night to Bolingbroke's fair day.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  Wales. Before Flint castle.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter, with drum and colours, HENRY BOLINGBROKE,
DUKE OF YORK, NORTHUMBERLAND, Attendants, and forces</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>So that by this intelligence we learn</line>
            <line>The Welshmen are dispersed, and Salisbury</line>
            <line>Is gone to meet the king, who lately landed</line>
            <line>With some few private friends upon this coast.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>The news is very fair and good, my lord:</line>
            <line>Richard not far from hence hath hid his head.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>It would beseem the Lord Northumberland</line>
            <line>To say 'King Richard:' alack the heavy day</line>
            <line>When such a sacred king should hide his head.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>Your grace mistakes; only to be brief</line>
            <line>Left I his title out.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>The time hath been,</line>
            <line>Would you have been so brief with him, he would</line>
            <line>Have been so brief with you, to shorten you,</line>
            <line>For taking so the head, your whole head's length.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Mistake not, uncle, further than you should.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Take not, good cousin, further than you should.</line>
            <line>Lest you mistake the heavens are o'er our heads.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>I know it, uncle, and oppose not myself</line>
            <line>Against their will. But who comes here?</line>
            <stagedir>Enter HENRY PERCY</stagedir>
            <line>Welcome, Harry: what, will not this castle yield?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY PERCY</speaker>
            <line>The castle royally is mann'd, my lord,</line>
            <line>Against thy entrance.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Royally!</line>
            <line>Why, it contains no king?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY PERCY</speaker>
            <line>Yes, my good lord,</line>
            <line>It doth contain a king; King Richard lies</line>
            <line>Within the limits of yon lime and stone:</line>
            <line>And with him are the Lord Aumerle, Lord Salisbury,</line>
            <line>Sir Stephen Scroop, besides a clergyman</line>
            <line>Of holy reverence; who, I cannot learn.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>O, belike it is the Bishop of Carlisle.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Noble lords,</line>
            <line>Go to the rude ribs of that ancient castle;</line>
            <line>Through brazen trumpet send the breath of parley</line>
            <line>Into his ruin'd ears, and thus deliver:</line>
            <line>Henry Bolingbroke</line>
            <line>On both his knees doth kiss King Richard's hand</line>
            <line>And sends allegiance and true faith of heart</line>
            <line>To his most royal person, hither come</line>
            <line>Even at his feet to lay my arms and power,</line>
            <line>Provided that my banishment repeal'd</line>
            <line>And lands restored again be freely granted:</line>
            <line>If not, I'll use the advantage of my power</line>
            <line>And lay the summer's dust with showers of blood</line>
            <line>Rain'd from the wounds of slaughter'd Englishmen:</line>
            <line>The which, how far off from the mind of Bolingbroke</line>
            <line>It is, such crimson tempest should bedrench</line>
            <line>The fresh green lap of fair King Richard's land,</line>
            <line>My stooping duty tenderly shall show.</line>
            <line>Go, signify as much, while here we march</line>
            <line>Upon the grassy carpet of this plain.</line>
            <line>Let's march without the noise of threatening drum,</line>
            <line>That from this castle's tatter'd battlements</line>
            <line>Our fair appointments may be well perused.</line>
            <line>Methinks King Richard and myself should meet</line>
            <line>With no less terror than the elements</line>
            <line>Of fire and water, when their thundering shock</line>
            <line>At meeting tears the cloudy cheeks of heaven.</line>
            <line>Be he the fire, I'll be the yielding water:</line>
            <line>The rage be his, whilst on the earth I rain</line>
            <line>My waters; on the earth, and not on him.</line>
            <line>March on, and mark King Richard how he looks.</line>
            <stagedir>Parle without, and answer within. Then a flourish.
Enter on the walls, KING RICHARD II, the BISHOP OF
CARLISLE, DUKE OF AUMERLE, SIR STEPHEN SCROOP, and
EARL OF SALISBURY</stagedir>
            <line>See, see, King Richard doth himself appear,</line>
            <line>As doth the blushing discontented sun</line>
            <line>From out the fiery portal of the east,</line>
            <line>When he perceives the envious clouds are bent</line>
            <line>To dim his glory and to stain the track</line>
            <line>Of his bright passage to the occident.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Yet looks he like a king: behold, his eye,</line>
            <line>As bright as is the eagle's, lightens forth</line>
            <line>Controlling majesty: alack, alack, for woe,</line>
            <line>That any harm should stain so fair a show!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>We are amazed; and thus long have we stood</line>
            <line>To watch the fearful bending of thy knee,</line>
            <stagedir>To NORTHUMBERLAND</stagedir>
            <line>Because we thought ourself thy lawful king:</line>
            <line>And if we be, how dare thy joints forget</line>
            <line>To pay their awful duty to our presence?</line>
            <line>If we be not, show us the hand of God</line>
            <line>That hath dismissed us from our stewardship;</line>
            <line>For well we know, no hand of blood and bone</line>
            <line>Can gripe the sacred handle of our sceptre,</line>
            <line>Unless he do profane, steal, or usurp.</line>
            <line>And though you think that all, as you have done,</line>
            <line>Have torn their souls by turning them from us,</line>
            <line>And we are barren and bereft of friends;</line>
            <line>Yet know, my master, God omnipotent,</line>
            <line>Is mustering in his clouds on our behalf</line>
            <line>Armies of pestilence; and they shall strike</line>
            <line>Your children yet unborn and unbegot,</line>
            <line>That lift your vassal hands against my head</line>
            <line>And threat the glory of my precious crown.</line>
            <line>Tell Bolingbroke--for yond methinks he stands--</line>
            <line>That every stride he makes upon my land</line>
            <line>Is dangerous treason: he is come to open</line>
            <line>The purple testament of bleeding war;</line>
            <line>But ere the crown he looks for live in peace,</line>
            <line>Ten thousand bloody crowns of mothers' sons</line>
            <line>Shall ill become the flower of England's face,</line>
            <line>Change the complexion of her maid-pale peace</line>
            <line>To scarlet indignation and bedew</line>
            <line>Her pastures' grass with faithful English blood.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>The king of heaven forbid our lord the king</line>
            <line>Should so with civil and uncivil arms</line>
            <line>Be rush'd upon! Thy thrice noble cousin</line>
            <line>Harry Bolingbroke doth humbly kiss thy hand;</line>
            <line>And by the honourable tomb he swears,</line>
            <line>That stands upon your royal grandsire's bones,</line>
            <line>And by the royalties of both your bloods,</line>
            <line>Currents that spring from one most gracious head,</line>
            <line>And by the buried hand of warlike Gaunt,</line>
            <line>And by the worth and honour of himself,</line>
            <line>Comprising all that may be sworn or said,</line>
            <line>His coming hither hath no further scope</line>
            <line>Than for his lineal royalties and to beg</line>
            <line>Enfranchisement immediate on his knees:</line>
            <line>Which on thy royal party granted once,</line>
            <line>His glittering arms he will commend to rust,</line>
            <line>His barbed steeds to stables, and his heart</line>
            <line>To faithful service of your majesty.</line>
            <line>This swears he, as he is a prince, is just;</line>
            <line>And, as I am a gentleman, I credit him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>Northumberland, say thus the king returns:</line>
            <line>His noble cousin is right welcome hither;</line>
            <line>And all the number of his fair demands</line>
            <line>Shall be accomplish'd without contradiction:</line>
            <line>With all the gracious utterance thou hast</line>
            <line>Speak to his gentle hearing kind commends.</line>
            <line>We do debase ourselves, cousin, do we not,</line>
            <stagedir>To DUKE OF AUMERLE</stagedir>
            <line>To look so poorly and to speak so fair?</line>
            <line>Shall we call back Northumberland, and send</line>
            <line>Defiance to the traitor, and so die?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
            <line>No, good my lord; let's fight with gentle words</line>
            <line>Till time lend friends and friends their helpful swords.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>O God, O God! that e'er this tongue of mine,</line>
            <line>That laid the sentence of dread banishment</line>
            <line>On yon proud man, should take it off again</line>
            <line>With words of sooth! O that I were as great</line>
            <line>As is my grief, or lesser than my name!</line>
            <line>Or that I could forget what I have been,</line>
            <line>Or not remember what I must be now!</line>
            <line>Swell'st thou, proud heart? I'll give thee scope to beat,</line>
            <line>Since foes have scope to beat both thee and me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
            <line>Northumberland comes back from Bolingbroke.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>What must the king do now? must he submit?</line>
            <line>The king shall do it: must he be deposed?</line>
            <line>The king shall be contented: must he lose</line>
            <line>The name of king? o' God's name, let it go:</line>
            <line>I'll give my jewels for a set of beads,</line>
            <line>My gorgeous palace for a hermitage,</line>
            <line>My gay apparel for an almsman's gown,</line>
            <line>My figured goblets for a dish of wood,</line>
            <line>My sceptre for a palmer's walking staff,</line>
            <line>My subjects for a pair of carved saints</line>
            <line>And my large kingdom for a little grave,</line>
            <line>A little little grave, an obscure grave;</line>
            <line>Or I'll be buried in the king's highway,</line>
            <line>Some way of common trade, where subjects' feet</line>
            <line>May hourly trample on their sovereign's head;</line>
            <line>For on my heart they tread now whilst I live;</line>
            <line>And buried once, why not upon my head?</line>
            <line>Aumerle, thou weep'st, my tender-hearted cousin!</line>
            <line>We'll make foul weather with despised tears;</line>
            <line>Our sighs and they shall lodge the summer corn,</line>
            <line>And make a dearth in this revolting land.</line>
            <line>Or shall we play the wantons with our woes,</line>
            <line>And make some pretty match with shedding tears?</line>
            <line>As thus, to drop them still upon one place,</line>
            <line>Till they have fretted us a pair of graves</line>
            <line>Within the earth; and, therein laid,--there lies</line>
            <line>Two kinsmen digg'd their graves with weeping eyes.</line>
            <line>Would not this ill do well? Well, well, I see</line>
            <line>I talk but idly, and you laugh at me.</line>
            <line>Most mighty prince, my Lord Northumberland,</line>
            <line>What says King Bolingbroke? will his majesty</line>
            <line>Give Richard leave to live till Richard die?</line>
            <line>You make a leg, and Bolingbroke says ay.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>My lord, in the base court he doth attend</line>
            <line>To speak with you; may it please you to come down.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>Down, down I come; like glistering Phaethon,</line>
            <line>Wanting the manage of unruly jades.</line>
            <line>In the base court? Base court, where kings grow base,</line>
            <line>To come at traitors' calls and do them grace.</line>
            <line>In the base court? Come down? Down, court!</line>
            <line>down, king!</line>
            <line>For night-owls shriek where mounting larks</line>
            <line>should sing.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt from above</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>What says his majesty?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>Sorrow and grief of heart</line>
            <line>Makes him speak fondly, like a frantic man</line>
            <line>Yet he is come.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter KING RICHARD and his attendants below</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Stand all apart,</line>
            <line>And show fair duty to his majesty.</line>
            <stagedir>He kneels down</stagedir>
            <line>My gracious lord,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>Fair cousin, you debase your princely knee</line>
            <line>To make the base earth proud with kissing it:</line>
            <line>Me rather had my heart might feel your love</line>
            <line>Than my unpleased eye see your courtesy.</line>
            <line>Up, cousin, up; your heart is up, I know,</line>
            <line>Thus high at least, although your knee be low.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>My gracious lord, I come but for mine own.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>Your own is yours, and I am yours, and all.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>So far be mine, my most redoubted lord,</line>
            <line>As my true service shall deserve your love.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>Well you deserve: they well deserve to have,</line>
            <line>That know the strong'st and surest way to get.</line>
            <line>Uncle, give me your hands: nay, dry your eyes;</line>
            <line>Tears show their love, but want their remedies.</line>
            <line>Cousin, I am too young to be your father,</line>
            <line>Though you are old enough to be my heir.</line>
            <line>What you will have, I'll give, and willing too;</line>
            <line>For do we must what force will have us do.</line>
            <line>Set on towards London, cousin, is it so?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Yea, my good lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>Then I must not say no.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Flourish. Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-4">
      <title>SCENE IV.  LANGLEY. The DUKE OF YORK's garden.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter the QUEEN and two Ladies</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN</speaker>
            <line>What sport shall we devise here in this garden,</line>
            <line>To drive away the heavy thought of care?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lady</speaker>
            <line>Madam, we'll play at bowls.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN</speaker>
            <line>'Twill make me think the world is full of rubs,</line>
            <line>And that my fortune rubs against the bias.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lady</speaker>
            <line>Madam, we'll dance.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN</speaker>
            <line>My legs can keep no measure in delight,</line>
            <line>When my poor heart no measure keeps in grief:</line>
            <line>Therefore, no dancing, girl; some other sport.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lady</speaker>
            <line>Madam, we'll tell tales.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN</speaker>
            <line>Of sorrow or of joy?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lady</speaker>
            <line>Of either, madam.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN</speaker>
            <line>Of neither, girl:</line>
            <line>For of joy, being altogether wanting,</line>
            <line>It doth remember me the more of sorrow;</line>
            <line>Or if of grief, being altogether had,</line>
            <line>It adds more sorrow to my want of joy:</line>
            <line>For what I have I need not to repeat;</line>
            <line>And what I want it boots not to complain.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lady</speaker>
            <line>Madam, I'll sing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN</speaker>
            <line>'Tis well that thou hast cause</line>
            <line>But thou shouldst please me better, wouldst thou weep.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lady</speaker>
            <line>I could weep, madam, would it do you good.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN</speaker>
            <line>And I could sing, would weeping do me good,</line>
            <line>And never borrow any tear of thee.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter a Gardener, and two Servants</stagedir>
            <line>But stay, here come the gardeners:</line>
            <line>Let's step into the shadow of these trees.</line>
            <line>My wretchedness unto a row of pins,</line>
            <line>They'll talk of state; for every one doth so</line>
            <line>Against a change; woe is forerun with woe.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>QUEEN and Ladies retire</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Gardener</speaker>
            <line>Go, bind thou up yon dangling apricocks,</line>
            <line>Which, like unruly children, make their sire</line>
            <line>Stoop with oppression of their prodigal weight:</line>
            <line>Give some supportance to the bending twigs.</line>
            <line>Go thou, and like an executioner,</line>
            <line>Cut off the heads of too fast growing sprays,</line>
            <line>That look too lofty in our commonwealth:</line>
            <line>All must be even in our government.</line>
            <line>You thus employ'd, I will go root away</line>
            <line>The noisome weeds, which without profit suck</line>
            <line>The soil's fertility from wholesome flowers.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>Why should we in the compass of a pale</line>
            <line>Keep law and form and due proportion,</line>
            <line>Showing, as in a model, our firm estate,</line>
            <line>When our sea-walled garden, the whole land,</line>
            <line>Is full of weeds, her fairest flowers choked up,</line>
            <line>Her fruit-trees all upturned, her hedges ruin'd,</line>
            <line>Her knots disorder'd and her wholesome herbs</line>
            <line>Swarming with caterpillars?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Gardener</speaker>
            <line>Hold thy peace:</line>
            <line>He that hath suffer'd this disorder'd spring</line>
            <line>Hath now himself met with the fall of leaf:</line>
            <line>The weeds which his broad-spreading leaves did shelter,</line>
            <line>That seem'd in eating him to hold him up,</line>
            <line>Are pluck'd up root and all by Bolingbroke,</line>
            <line>I mean the Earl of Wiltshire, Bushy, Green.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>What, are they dead?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Gardener</speaker>
            <line>They are; and Bolingbroke</line>
            <line>Hath seized the wasteful king. O, what pity is it</line>
            <line>That he had not so trimm'd and dress'd his land</line>
            <line>As we this garden! We at time of year</line>
            <line>Do wound the bark, the skin of our fruit-trees,</line>
            <line>Lest, being over-proud in sap and blood,</line>
            <line>With too much riches it confound itself:</line>
            <line>Had he done so to great and growing men,</line>
            <line>They might have lived to bear and he to taste</line>
            <line>Their fruits of duty: superfluous branches</line>
            <line>We lop away, that bearing boughs may live:</line>
            <line>Had he done so, himself had borne the crown,</line>
            <line>Which waste of idle hours hath quite thrown down.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>What, think you then the king shall be deposed?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Gardener</speaker>
            <line>Depress'd he is already, and deposed</line>
            <line>'Tis doubt he will be: letters came last night</line>
            <line>To a dear friend of the good Duke of York's,</line>
            <line>That tell black tidings.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN</speaker>
            <line>O, I am press'd to death through want of speaking!</line>
            <stagedir>Coming forward</stagedir>
            <line>Thou, old Adam's likeness, set to dress this garden,</line>
            <line>How dares thy harsh rude tongue sound this unpleasing news?</line>
            <line>What Eve, what serpent, hath suggested thee</line>
            <line>To make a second fall of cursed man?</line>
            <line>Why dost thou say King Richard is deposed?</line>
            <line>Darest thou, thou little better thing than earth,</line>
            <line>Divine his downfall? Say, where, when, and how,</line>
            <line>Camest thou by this ill tidings? speak, thou wretch.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Gardener</speaker>
            <line>Pardon me, madam: little joy have I</line>
            <line>To breathe this news; yet what I say is true.</line>
            <line>King Richard, he is in the mighty hold</line>
            <line>Of Bolingbroke: their fortunes both are weigh'd:</line>
            <line>In your lord's scale is nothing but himself,</line>
            <line>And some few vanities that make him light;</line>
            <line>But in the balance of great Bolingbroke,</line>
            <line>Besides himself, are all the English peers,</line>
            <line>And with that odds he weighs King Richard down.</line>
            <line>Post you to London, and you will find it so;</line>
            <line>I speak no more than every one doth know.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN</speaker>
            <line>Nimble mischance, that art so light of foot,</line>
            <line>Doth not thy embassage belong to me,</line>
            <line>And am I last that knows it? O, thou think'st</line>
            <line>To serve me last, that I may longest keep</line>
            <line>Thy sorrow in my breast. Come, ladies, go,</line>
            <line>To meet at London London's king in woe.</line>
            <line>What, was I born to this, that my sad look</line>
            <line>Should grace the triumph of great Bolingbroke?</line>
            <line>Gardener, for telling me these news of woe,</line>
            <line>Pray God the plants thou graft'st may never grow.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt QUEEN and Ladies</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GARDENER</speaker>
            <line>Poor queen! so that thy state might be no worse,</line>
            <line>I would my skill were subject to thy curse.</line>
            <line>Here did she fall a tear; here in this place</line>
            <line>I'll set a bank of rue, sour herb of grace:</line>
            <line>Rue, even for ruth, here shortly shall be seen,</line>
            <line>In the remembrance of a weeping queen.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>