<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:shakespear:dtd:act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-1">
   <title>ACT I</title>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  London. KING RICHARD II's palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter KING RICHARD II, JOHN OF GAUNT, with other
Nobles and Attendants</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>Old John of Gaunt, time-honour'd Lancaster,</line>
            <line>Hast thou, according to thy oath and band,</line>
            <line>Brought hither Henry Hereford thy bold son,</line>
            <line>Here to make good the boisterous late appeal,</line>
            <line>Which then our leisure would not let us hear,</line>
            <line>Against the Duke of Norfolk, Thomas Mowbray?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOHN OF GAUNT</speaker>
            <line>I have, my liege.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>Tell me, moreover, hast thou sounded him,</line>
            <line>If he appeal the duke on ancient malice;</line>
            <line>Or worthily, as a good subject should,</line>
            <line>On some known ground of treachery in him?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOHN OF GAUNT</speaker>
            <line>As near as I could sift him on that argument,</line>
            <line>On some apparent danger seen in him</line>
            <line>Aim'd at your highness, no inveterate malice.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>Then call them to our presence; face to face,</line>
            <line>And frowning brow to brow, ourselves will hear</line>
            <line>The accuser and the accused freely speak:</line>
            <line>High-stomach'd are they both, and full of ire,</line>
            <line>In rage deaf as the sea, hasty as fire.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter HENRY BOLINGBROKE and THOMAS MOWBRAY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Many years of happy days befal</line>
            <line>My gracious sovereign, my most loving liege!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THOMAS MOWBRAY</speaker>
            <line>Each day still better other's happiness;</line>
            <line>Until the heavens, envying earth's good hap,</line>
            <line>Add an immortal title to your crown!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>We thank you both: yet one but flatters us,</line>
            <line>As well appeareth by the cause you come;</line>
            <line>Namely to appeal each other of high treason.</line>
            <line>Cousin of Hereford, what dost thou object</line>
            <line>Against the Duke of Norfolk, Thomas Mowbray?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>First, heaven be the record to my speech!</line>
            <line>In the devotion of a subject's love,</line>
            <line>Tendering the precious safety of my prince,</line>
            <line>And free from other misbegotten hate,</line>
            <line>Come I appellant to this princely presence.</line>
            <line>Now, Thomas Mowbray, do I turn to thee,</line>
            <line>And mark my greeting well; for what I speak</line>
            <line>My body shall make good upon this earth,</line>
            <line>Or my divine soul answer it in heaven.</line>
            <line>Thou art a traitor and a miscreant,</line>
            <line>Too good to be so and too bad to live,</line>
            <line>Since the more fair and crystal is the sky,</line>
            <line>The uglier seem the clouds that in it fly.</line>
            <line>Once more, the more to aggravate the note,</line>
            <line>With a foul traitor's name stuff I thy throat;</line>
            <line>And wish, so please my sovereign, ere I move,</line>
            <line>What my tongue speaks my right drawn sword may prove.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THOMAS MOWBRAY</speaker>
            <line>Let not my cold words here accuse my zeal:</line>
            <line>'Tis not the trial of a woman's war,</line>
            <line>The bitter clamour of two eager tongues,</line>
            <line>Can arbitrate this cause betwixt us twain;</line>
            <line>The blood is hot that must be cool'd for this:</line>
            <line>Yet can I not of such tame patience boast</line>
            <line>As to be hush'd and nought at all to say:</line>
            <line>First, the fair reverence of your highness curbs me</line>
            <line>From giving reins and spurs to my free speech;</line>
            <line>Which else would post until it had return'd</line>
            <line>These terms of treason doubled down his throat.</line>
            <line>Setting aside his high blood's royalty,</line>
            <line>And let him be no kinsman to my liege,</line>
            <line>I do defy him, and I spit at him;</line>
            <line>Call him a slanderous coward and a villain:</line>
            <line>Which to maintain I would allow him odds,</line>
            <line>And meet him, were I tied to run afoot</line>
            <line>Even to the frozen ridges of the Alps,</line>
            <line>Or any other ground inhabitable,</line>
            <line>Where ever Englishman durst set his foot.</line>
            <line>Mean time let this defend my loyalty,</line>
            <line>By all my hopes, most falsely doth he lie.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Pale trembling coward, there I throw my gage,</line>
            <line>Disclaiming here the kindred of the king,</line>
            <line>And lay aside my high blood's royalty,</line>
            <line>Which fear, not reverence, makes thee to except.</line>
            <line>If guilty dread have left thee so much strength</line>
            <line>As to take up mine honour's pawn, then stoop:</line>
            <line>By that and all the rites of knighthood else,</line>
            <line>Will I make good against thee, arm to arm,</line>
            <line>What I have spoke, or thou canst worse devise.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THOMAS MOWBRAY</speaker>
            <line>I take it up; and by that sword I swear</line>
            <line>Which gently laid my knighthood on my shoulder,</line>
            <line>I'll answer thee in any fair degree,</line>
            <line>Or chivalrous design of knightly trial:</line>
            <line>And when I mount, alive may I not light,</line>
            <line>If I be traitor or unjustly fight!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>What doth our cousin lay to Mowbray's charge?</line>
            <line>It must be great that can inherit us</line>
            <line>So much as of a thought of ill in him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Look, what I speak, my life shall prove it true;</line>
            <line>That Mowbray hath received eight thousand nobles</line>
            <line>In name of lendings for your highness' soldiers,</line>
            <line>The which he hath detain'd for lewd employments,</line>
            <line>Like a false traitor and injurious villain.</line>
            <line>Besides I say and will in battle prove,</line>
            <line>Or here or elsewhere to the furthest verge</line>
            <line>That ever was survey'd by English eye,</line>
            <line>That all the treasons for these eighteen years</line>
            <line>Complotted and contrived in this land</line>
            <line>Fetch from false Mowbray their first head and spring.</line>
            <line>Further I say and further will maintain</line>
            <line>Upon his bad life to make all this good,</line>
            <line>That he did plot the Duke of Gloucester's death,</line>
            <line>Suggest his soon-believing adversaries,</line>
            <line>And consequently, like a traitor coward,</line>
            <line>Sluiced out his innocent soul through streams of blood:</line>
            <line>Which blood, like sacrificing Abel's, cries,</line>
            <line>Even from the tongueless caverns of the earth,</line>
            <line>To me for justice and rough chastisement;</line>
            <line>And, by the glorious worth of my descent,</line>
            <line>This arm shall do it, or this life be spent.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>How high a pitch his resolution soars!</line>
            <line>Thomas of Norfolk, what say'st thou to this?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THOMAS MOWBRAY</speaker>
            <line>O, let my sovereign turn away his face</line>
            <line>And bid his ears a little while be deaf,</line>
            <line>Till I have told this slander of his blood,</line>
            <line>How God and good men hate so foul a liar.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>Mowbray, impartial are our eyes and ears:</line>
            <line>Were he my brother, nay, my kingdom's heir,</line>
            <line>As he is but my father's brother's son,</line>
            <line>Now, by my sceptre's awe, I make a vow,</line>
            <line>Such neighbour nearness to our sacred blood</line>
            <line>Should nothing privilege him, nor partialize</line>
            <line>The unstooping firmness of my upright soul:</line>
            <line>He is our subject, Mowbray; so art thou:</line>
            <line>Free speech and fearless I to thee allow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THOMAS MOWBRAY</speaker>
            <line>Then, Bolingbroke, as low as to thy heart,</line>
            <line>Through the false passage of thy throat, thou liest.</line>
            <line>Three parts of that receipt I had for Calais</line>
            <line>Disbursed I duly to his highness' soldiers;</line>
            <line>The other part reserved I by consent,</line>
            <line>For that my sovereign liege was in my debt</line>
            <line>Upon remainder of a dear account,</line>
            <line>Since last I went to France to fetch his queen:</line>
            <line>Now swallow down that lie. For Gloucester's death,</line>
            <line>I slew him not; but to my own disgrace</line>
            <line>Neglected my sworn duty in that case.</line>
            <line>For you, my noble Lord of Lancaster,</line>
            <line>The honourable father to my foe</line>
            <line>Once did I lay an ambush for your life,</line>
            <line>A trespass that doth vex my grieved soul</line>
            <line>But ere I last received the sacrament</line>
            <line>I did confess it, and exactly begg'd</line>
            <line>Your grace's pardon, and I hope I had it.</line>
            <line>This is my fault: as for the rest appeall'd,</line>
            <line>It issues from the rancour of a villain,</line>
            <line>A recreant and most degenerate traitor</line>
            <line>Which in myself I boldly will defend;</line>
            <line>And interchangeably hurl down my gage</line>
            <line>Upon this overweening traitor's foot,</line>
            <line>To prove myself a loyal gentleman</line>
            <line>Even in the best blood chamber'd in his bosom.</line>
            <line>In haste whereof, most heartily I pray</line>
            <line>Your highness to assign our trial day.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>Wrath-kindled gentlemen, be ruled by me;</line>
            <line>Let's purge this choler without letting blood:</line>
            <line>This we prescribe, though no physician;</line>
            <line>Deep malice makes too deep incision;</line>
            <line>Forget, forgive; conclude and be agreed;</line>
            <line>Our doctors say this is no month to bleed.</line>
            <line>Good uncle, let this end where it begun;</line>
            <line>We'll calm the Duke of Norfolk, you your son.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOHN OF GAUNT</speaker>
            <line>To be a make-peace shall become my age:</line>
            <line>Throw down, my son, the Duke of Norfolk's gage.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>And, Norfolk, throw down his.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOHN OF GAUNT</speaker>
            <line>When, Harry, when?</line>
            <line>Obedience bids I should not bid again.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>Norfolk, throw down, we bid; there is no boot.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THOMAS MOWBRAY</speaker>
            <line>Myself I throw, dread sovereign, at thy foot.</line>
            <line>My life thou shalt command, but not my shame:</line>
            <line>The one my duty owes; but my fair name,</line>
            <line>Despite of death that lives upon my grave,</line>
            <line>To dark dishonour's use thou shalt not have.</line>
            <line>I am disgraced, impeach'd and baffled here,</line>
            <line>Pierced to the soul with slander's venom'd spear,</line>
            <line>The which no balm can cure but his heart-blood</line>
            <line>Which breathed this poison.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>Rage must be withstood:</line>
            <line>Give me his gage: lions make leopards tame.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THOMAS MOWBRAY</speaker>
            <line>Yea, but not change his spots: take but my shame.</line>
            <line>And I resign my gage. My dear dear lord,</line>
            <line>The purest treasure mortal times afford</line>
            <line>Is spotless reputation: that away,</line>
            <line>Men are but gilded loam or painted clay.</line>
            <line>A jewel in a ten-times-barr'd-up chest</line>
            <line>Is a bold spirit in a loyal breast.</line>
            <line>Mine honour is my life; both grow in one:</line>
            <line>Take honour from me, and my life is done:</line>
            <line>Then, dear my liege, mine honour let me try;</line>
            <line>In that I live and for that will I die.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>Cousin, throw up your gage; do you begin.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>O, God defend my soul from such deep sin!</line>
            <line>Shall I seem crest-fall'n in my father's sight?</line>
            <line>Or with pale beggar-fear impeach my height</line>
            <line>Before this out-dared dastard? Ere my tongue</line>
            <line>Shall wound my honour with such feeble wrong,</line>
            <line>Or sound so base a parle, my teeth shall tear</line>
            <line>The slavish motive of recanting fear,</line>
            <line>And spit it bleeding in his high disgrace,</line>
            <line>Where shame doth harbour, even in Mowbray's face.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit JOHN OF GAUNT</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>We were not born to sue, but to command;</line>
            <line>Which since we cannot do to make you friends,</line>
            <line>Be ready, as your lives shall answer it,</line>
            <line>At Coventry, upon Saint Lambert's day:</line>
            <line>There shall your swords and lances arbitrate</line>
            <line>The swelling difference of your settled hate:</line>
            <line>Since we can not atone you, we shall see</line>
            <line>Justice design the victor's chivalry.</line>
            <line>Lord marshal, command our officers at arms</line>
            <line>Be ready to direct these home alarms.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  The DUKE OF LANCASTER'S palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter JOHN OF GAUNT with DUCHESS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOHN OF GAUNT</speaker>
            <line>Alas, the part I had in Woodstock's blood</line>
            <line>Doth more solicit me than your exclaims,</line>
            <line>To stir against the butchers of his life!</line>
            <line>But since correction lieth in those hands</line>
            <line>Which made the fault that we cannot correct,</line>
            <line>Put we our quarrel to the will of heaven;</line>
            <line>Who, when they see the hours ripe on earth,</line>
            <line>Will rain hot vengeance on offenders' heads.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS</speaker>
            <line>Finds brotherhood in thee no sharper spur?</line>
            <line>Hath love in thy old blood no living fire?</line>
            <line>Edward's seven sons, whereof thyself art one,</line>
            <line>Were as seven vials of his sacred blood,</line>
            <line>Or seven fair branches springing from one root:</line>
            <line>Some of those seven are dried by nature's course,</line>
            <line>Some of those branches by the Destinies cut;</line>
            <line>But Thomas, my dear lord, my life, my Gloucester,</line>
            <line>One vial full of Edward's sacred blood,</line>
            <line>One flourishing branch of his most royal root,</line>
            <line>Is crack'd, and all the precious liquor spilt,</line>
            <line>Is hack'd down, and his summer leaves all faded,</line>
            <line>By envy's hand and murder's bloody axe.</line>
            <line>Ah, Gaunt, his blood was thine! that bed, that womb,</line>
            <line>That metal, that self-mould, that fashion'd thee</line>
            <line>Made him a man; and though thou livest and breathest,</line>
            <line>Yet art thou slain in him: thou dost consent</line>
            <line>In some large measure to thy father's death,</line>
            <line>In that thou seest thy wretched brother die,</line>
            <line>Who was the model of thy father's life.</line>
            <line>Call it not patience, Gaunt; it is despair:</line>
            <line>In suffering thus thy brother to be slaughter'd,</line>
            <line>Thou showest the naked pathway to thy life,</line>
            <line>Teaching stern murder how to butcher thee:</line>
            <line>That which in mean men we intitle patience</line>
            <line>Is pale cold cowardice in noble breasts.</line>
            <line>What shall I say? to safeguard thine own life,</line>
            <line>The best way is to venge my Gloucester's death.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOHN OF GAUNT</speaker>
            <line>God's is the quarrel; for God's substitute,</line>
            <line>His deputy anointed in His sight,</line>
            <line>Hath caused his death: the which if wrongfully,</line>
            <line>Let heaven revenge; for I may never lift</line>
            <line>An angry arm against His minister.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS</speaker>
            <line>Where then, alas, may I complain myself?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOHN OF GAUNT</speaker>
            <line>To God, the widow's champion and defence.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS</speaker>
            <line>Why, then, I will. Farewell, old Gaunt.</line>
            <line>Thou goest to Coventry, there to behold</line>
            <line>Our cousin Hereford and fell Mowbray fight:</line>
            <line>O, sit my husband's wrongs on Hereford's spear,</line>
            <line>That it may enter butcher Mowbray's breast!</line>
            <line>Or, if misfortune miss the first career,</line>
            <line>Be Mowbray's sins so heavy in his bosom,</line>
            <line>They may break his foaming courser's back,</line>
            <line>And throw the rider headlong in the lists,</line>
            <line>A caitiff recreant to my cousin Hereford!</line>
            <line>Farewell, old Gaunt: thy sometimes brother's wife</line>
            <line>With her companion grief must end her life.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOHN OF GAUNT</speaker>
            <line>Sister, farewell; I must to Coventry:</line>
            <line>As much good stay with thee as go with me!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS</speaker>
            <line>Yet one word more: grief boundeth where it falls,</line>
            <line>Not with the empty hollowness, but weight:</line>
            <line>I take my leave before I have begun,</line>
            <line>For sorrow ends not when it seemeth done.</line>
            <line>Commend me to thy brother, Edmund York.</line>
            <line>Lo, this is all:--nay, yet depart not so;</line>
            <line>Though this be all, do not so quickly go;</line>
            <line>I shall remember more. Bid him--ah, what?--</line>
            <line>With all good speed at Plashy visit me.</line>
            <line>Alack, and what shall good old York there see</line>
            <line>But empty lodgings and unfurnish'd walls,</line>
            <line>Unpeopled offices, untrodden stones?</line>
            <line>And what hear there for welcome but my groans?</line>
            <line>Therefore commend me; let him not come there,</line>
            <line>To seek out sorrow that dwells every where.</line>
            <line>Desolate, desolate, will I hence and die:</line>
            <line>The last leave of thee takes my weeping eye.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  The lists at Coventry.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter the Lord Marshal and the DUKE OF AUMERLE</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord Marshal</speaker>
            <line>My Lord Aumerle, is Harry Hereford arm'd?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
            <line>Yea, at all points; and longs to enter in.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord Marshal</speaker>
            <line>The Duke of Norfolk, sprightfully and bold,</line>
            <line>Stays but the summons of the appellant's trumpet.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
            <line>Why, then, the champions are prepared, and stay</line>
            <line>For nothing but his majesty's approach.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>The trumpets sound, and KING RICHARD enters with
his nobles, JOHN OF GAUNT, BUSHY, BAGOT, GREEN, and
others. When they are set, enter THOMAS MOWBRAY in
arms, defendant, with a Herald</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>Marshal, demand of yonder champion</line>
            <line>The cause of his arrival here in arms:</line>
            <line>Ask him his name and orderly proceed</line>
            <line>To swear him in the justice of his cause.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord Marshal</speaker>
            <line>In God's name and the king's, say who thou art</line>
            <line>And why thou comest thus knightly clad in arms,</line>
            <line>Against what man thou comest, and what thy quarrel:</line>
            <line>Speak truly, on thy knighthood and thy oath;</line>
            <line>As so defend thee heaven and thy valour!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THOMAS MOWBRAY</speaker>
            <line>My name is Thomas Mowbray, Duke of Norfolk;</line>
            <line>Who hither come engaged by my oath--</line>
            <line>Which God defend a knight should violate!--</line>
            <line>Both to defend my loyalty and truth</line>
            <line>To God, my king and my succeeding issue,</line>
            <line>Against the Duke of Hereford that appeals me</line>
            <line>And, by the grace of God and this mine arm,</line>
            <line>To prove him, in defending of myself,</line>
            <line>A traitor to my God, my king, and me:</line>
            <line>And as I truly fight, defend me heaven!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>The trumpets sound. Enter HENRY BOLINGBROKE,
appellant, in armour, with a Herald</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>Marshal, ask yonder knight in arms,</line>
            <line>Both who he is and why he cometh hither</line>
            <line>Thus plated in habiliments of war,</line>
            <line>And formally, according to our law,</line>
            <line>Depose him in the justice of his cause.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord Marshal</speaker>
            <line>What is thy name? and wherefore comest thou hither,</line>
            <line>Before King Richard in his royal lists?</line>
            <line>Against whom comest thou? and what's thy quarrel?</line>
            <line>Speak like a true knight, so defend thee heaven!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Harry of Hereford, Lancaster and Derby</line>
            <line>Am I; who ready here do stand in arms,</line>
            <line>To prove, by God's grace and my body's valour,</line>
            <line>In lists, on Thomas Mowbray, Duke of Norfolk,</line>
            <line>That he is a traitor, foul and dangerous,</line>
            <line>To God of heaven, King Richard and to me;</line>
            <line>And as I truly fight, defend me heaven!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord Marshal</speaker>
            <line>On pain of death, no person be so bold</line>
            <line>Or daring-hardy as to touch the lists,</line>
            <line>Except the marshal and such officers</line>
            <line>Appointed to direct these fair designs.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Lord marshal, let me kiss my sovereign's hand,</line>
            <line>And bow my knee before his majesty:</line>
            <line>For Mowbray and myself are like two men</line>
            <line>That vow a long and weary pilgrimage;</line>
            <line>Then let us take a ceremonious leave</line>
            <line>And loving farewell of our several friends.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord Marshal</speaker>
            <line>The appellant in all duty greets your highness,</line>
            <line>And craves to kiss your hand and take his leave.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>We will descend and fold him in our arms.</line>
            <line>Cousin of Hereford, as thy cause is right,</line>
            <line>So be thy fortune in this royal fight!</line>
            <line>Farewell, my blood; which if to-day thou shed,</line>
            <line>Lament we may, but not revenge thee dead.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>O let no noble eye profane a tear</line>
            <line>For me, if I be gored with Mowbray's spear:</line>
            <line>As confident as is the falcon's flight</line>
            <line>Against a bird, do I with Mowbray fight.</line>
            <line>My loving lord, I take my leave of you;</line>
            <line>Of you, my noble cousin, Lord Aumerle;</line>
            <line>Not sick, although I have to do with death,</line>
            <line>But lusty, young, and cheerly drawing breath.</line>
            <line>Lo, as at English feasts, so I regreet</line>
            <line>The daintiest last, to make the end most sweet:</line>
            <line>O thou, the earthly author of my blood,</line>
            <line>Whose youthful spirit, in me regenerate,</line>
            <line>Doth with a twofold vigour lift me up</line>
            <line>To reach at victory above my head,</line>
            <line>Add proof unto mine armour with thy prayers;</line>
            <line>And with thy blessings steel my lance's point,</line>
            <line>That it may enter Mowbray's waxen coat,</line>
            <line>And furbish new the name of John a Gaunt,</line>
            <line>Even in the lusty havior of his son.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOHN OF GAUNT</speaker>
            <line>God in thy good cause make thee prosperous!</line>
            <line>Be swift like lightning in the execution;</line>
            <line>And let thy blows, doubly redoubled,</line>
            <line>Fall like amazing thunder on the casque</line>
            <line>Of thy adverse pernicious enemy:</line>
            <line>Rouse up thy youthful blood, be valiant and live.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Mine innocency and Saint George to thrive!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THOMAS MOWBRAY</speaker>
            <line>However God or fortune cast my lot,</line>
            <line>There lives or dies, true to King Richard's throne,</line>
            <line>A loyal, just and upright gentleman:</line>
            <line>Never did captive with a freer heart</line>
            <line>Cast off his chains of bondage and embrace</line>
            <line>His golden uncontroll'd enfranchisement,</line>
            <line>More than my dancing soul doth celebrate</line>
            <line>This feast of battle with mine adversary.</line>
            <line>Most mighty liege, and my companion peers,</line>
            <line>Take from my mouth the wish of happy years:</line>
            <line>As gentle and as jocund as to jest</line>
            <line>Go I to fight: truth hath a quiet breast.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>Farewell, my lord: securely I espy</line>
            <line>Virtue with valour couched in thine eye.</line>
            <line>Order the trial, marshal, and begin.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord Marshal</speaker>
            <line>Harry of Hereford, Lancaster and Derby,</line>
            <line>Receive thy lance; and God defend the right!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Strong as a tower in hope, I cry amen.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord Marshal</speaker>
            <line>Go bear this lance to Thomas, Duke of Norfolk.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Herald</speaker>
            <line>Harry of Hereford, Lancaster and Derby,</line>
            <line>Stands here for God, his sovereign and himself,</line>
            <line>On pain to be found false and recreant,</line>
            <line>To prove the Duke of Norfolk, Thomas Mowbray,</line>
            <line>A traitor to his God, his king and him;</line>
            <line>And dares him to set forward to the fight.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Herald</speaker>
            <line>Here standeth Thomas Mowbray, Duke of Norfolk,</line>
            <line>On pain to be found false and recreant,</line>
            <line>Both to defend himself and to approve</line>
            <line>Henry of Hereford, Lancaster, and Derby,</line>
            <line>To God, his sovereign and to him disloyal;</line>
            <line>Courageously and with a free desire</line>
            <line>Attending but the signal to begin.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord Marshal</speaker>
            <line>Sound, trumpets; and set forward, combatants.</line>
            <stagedir>A charge sounded</stagedir>
            <line>Stay, the king hath thrown his warder down.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>Let them lay by their helmets and their spears,</line>
            <line>And both return back to their chairs again:</line>
            <line>Withdraw with us: and let the trumpets sound</line>
            <line>While we return these dukes what we decree.</line>
            <stagedir>A long flourish</stagedir>
            <line>Draw near,</line>
            <line>And list what with our council we have done.</line>
            <line>For that our kingdom's earth should not be soil'd</line>
            <line>With that dear blood which it hath fostered;</line>
            <line>And for our eyes do hate the dire aspect</line>
            <line>Of civil wounds plough'd up with neighbours' sword;</line>
            <line>And for we think the eagle-winged pride</line>
            <line>Of sky-aspiring and ambitious thoughts,</line>
            <line>With rival-hating envy, set on you</line>
            <line>To wake our peace, which in our country's cradle</line>
            <line>Draws the sweet infant breath of gentle sleep;</line>
            <line>Which so roused up with boisterous untuned drums,</line>
            <line>With harsh resounding trumpets' dreadful bray,</line>
            <line>And grating shock of wrathful iron arms,</line>
            <line>Might from our quiet confines fright fair peace</line>
            <line>And make us wade even in our kindred's blood,</line>
            <line>Therefore, we banish you our territories:</line>
            <line>You, cousin Hereford, upon pain of life,</line>
            <line>Till twice five summers have enrich'd our fields</line>
            <line>Shall not regreet our fair dominions,</line>
            <line>But tread the stranger paths of banishment.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Your will be done: this must my comfort be,</line>
            <line>Sun that warms you here shall shine on me;</line>
            <line>And those his golden beams to you here lent</line>
            <line>Shall point on me and gild my banishment.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>Norfolk, for thee remains a heavier doom,</line>
            <line>Which I with some unwillingness pronounce:</line>
            <line>The sly slow hours shall not determinate</line>
            <line>The dateless limit of thy dear exile;</line>
            <line>The hopeless word of 'never to return'</line>
            <line>Breathe I against thee, upon pain of life.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THOMAS MOWBRAY</speaker>
            <line>A heavy sentence, my most sovereign liege,</line>
            <line>And all unlook'd for from your highness' mouth:</line>
            <line>A dearer merit, not so deep a maim</line>
            <line>As to be cast forth in the common air,</line>
            <line>Have I deserved at your highness' hands.</line>
            <line>The language I have learn'd these forty years,</line>
            <line>My native English, now I must forego:</line>
            <line>And now my tongue's use is to me no more</line>
            <line>Than an unstringed viol or a harp,</line>
            <line>Or like a cunning instrument cased up,</line>
            <line>Or, being open, put into his hands</line>
            <line>That knows no touch to tune the harmony:</line>
            <line>Within my mouth you have engaol'd my tongue,</line>
            <line>Doubly portcullis'd with my teeth and lips;</line>
            <line>And dull unfeeling barren ignorance</line>
            <line>Is made my gaoler to attend on me.</line>
            <line>I am too old to fawn upon a nurse,</line>
            <line>Too far in years to be a pupil now:</line>
            <line>What is thy sentence then but speechless death,</line>
            <line>Which robs my tongue from breathing native breath?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>It boots thee not to be compassionate:</line>
            <line>After our sentence plaining comes too late.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THOMAS MOWBRAY</speaker>
            <line>Then thus I turn me from my country's light,</line>
            <line>To dwell in solemn shades of endless night.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>Return again, and take an oath with thee.</line>
            <line>Lay on our royal sword your banish'd hands;</line>
            <line>Swear by the duty that you owe to God--</line>
            <line>Our part therein we banish with yourselves--</line>
            <line>To keep the oath that we administer:</line>
            <line>You never shall, so help you truth and God!</line>
            <line>Embrace each other's love in banishment;</line>
            <line>Nor never look upon each other's face;</line>
            <line>Nor never write, regreet, nor reconcile</line>
            <line>This louring tempest of your home-bred hate;</line>
            <line>Nor never by advised purpose meet</line>
            <line>To plot, contrive, or complot any ill</line>
            <line>'Gainst us, our state, our subjects, or our land.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>I swear.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THOMAS MOWBRAY</speaker>
            <line>And I, to keep all this.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Norfolk, so far as to mine enemy:--</line>
            <line>By this time, had the king permitted us,</line>
            <line>One of our souls had wander'd in the air.</line>
            <line>Banish'd this frail sepulchre of our flesh,</line>
            <line>As now our flesh is banish'd from this land:</line>
            <line>Confess thy treasons ere thou fly the realm;</line>
            <line>Since thou hast far to go, bear not along</line>
            <line>The clogging burthen of a guilty soul.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THOMAS MOWBRAY</speaker>
            <line>No, Bolingbroke: if ever I were traitor,</line>
            <line>My name be blotted from the book of life,</line>
            <line>And I from heaven banish'd as from hence!</line>
            <line>But what thou art, God, thou, and I do know;</line>
            <line>And all too soon, I fear, the king shall rue.</line>
            <line>Farewell, my liege. Now no way can I stray;</line>
            <line>Save back to England, all the world's my way.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>Uncle, even in the glasses of thine eyes</line>
            <line>I see thy grieved heart: thy sad aspect</line>
            <line>Hath from the number of his banish'd years</line>
            <line>Pluck'd four away.</line>
            <stagedir>To HENRY BOLINGBROKE</stagedir>
            <line>Six frozen winter spent,</line>
            <line>Return with welcome home from banishment.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>How long a time lies in one little word!</line>
            <line>Four lagging winters and four wanton springs</line>
            <line>End in a word: such is the breath of kings.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOHN OF GAUNT</speaker>
            <line>I thank my liege, that in regard of me</line>
            <line>He shortens four years of my son's exile:</line>
            <line>But little vantage shall I reap thereby;</line>
            <line>For, ere the six years that he hath to spend</line>
            <line>Can change their moons and bring their times about</line>
            <line>My oil-dried lamp and time-bewasted light</line>
            <line>Shall be extinct with age and endless night;</line>
            <line>My inch of taper will be burnt and done,</line>
            <line>And blindfold death not let me see my son.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>Why uncle, thou hast many years to live.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOHN OF GAUNT</speaker>
            <line>But not a minute, king, that thou canst give:</line>
            <line>Shorten my days thou canst with sullen sorrow,</line>
            <line>And pluck nights from me, but not lend a morrow;</line>
            <line>Thou canst help time to furrow me with age,</line>
            <line>But stop no wrinkle in his pilgrimage;</line>
            <line>Thy word is current with him for my death,</line>
            <line>But dead, thy kingdom cannot buy my breath.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>Thy son is banish'd upon good advice,</line>
            <line>Whereto thy tongue a party-verdict gave:</line>
            <line>Why at our justice seem'st thou then to lour?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOHN OF GAUNT</speaker>
            <line>Things sweet to taste prove in digestion sour.</line>
            <line>You urged me as a judge; but I had rather</line>
            <line>You would have bid me argue like a father.</line>
            <line>O, had it been a stranger, not my child,</line>
            <line>To smooth his fault I should have been more mild:</line>
            <line>A partial slander sought I to avoid,</line>
            <line>And in the sentence my own life destroy'd.</line>
            <line>Alas, I look'd when some of you should say,</line>
            <line>I was too strict to make mine own away;</line>
            <line>But you gave leave to my unwilling tongue</line>
            <line>Against my will to do myself this wrong.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>Cousin, farewell; and, uncle, bid him so:</line>
            <line>Six years we banish him, and he shall go.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Flourish. Exeunt KING RICHARD II and train</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
            <line>Cousin, farewell: what presence must not know,</line>
            <line>From where you do remain let paper show.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord Marshal</speaker>
            <line>My lord, no leave take I; for I will ride,</line>
            <line>As far as land will let me, by your side.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOHN OF GAUNT</speaker>
            <line>O, to what purpose dost thou hoard thy words,</line>
            <line>That thou return'st no greeting to thy friends?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>I have too few to take my leave of you,</line>
            <line>When the tongue's office should be prodigal</line>
            <line>To breathe the abundant dolour of the heart.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOHN OF GAUNT</speaker>
            <line>Thy grief is but thy absence for a time.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Joy absent, grief is present for that time.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOHN OF GAUNT</speaker>
            <line>What is six winters? they are quickly gone.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>To men in joy; but grief makes one hour ten.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOHN OF GAUNT</speaker>
            <line>Call it a travel that thou takest for pleasure.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>My heart will sigh when I miscall it so,</line>
            <line>Which finds it an inforced pilgrimage.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOHN OF GAUNT</speaker>
            <line>The sullen passage of thy weary steps</line>
            <line>Esteem as foil wherein thou art to set</line>
            <line>The precious jewel of thy home return.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Nay, rather, every tedious stride I make</line>
            <line>Will but remember me what a deal of world</line>
            <line>I wander from the jewels that I love.</line>
            <line>Must I not serve a long apprenticehood</line>
            <line>To foreign passages, and in the end,</line>
            <line>Having my freedom, boast of nothing else</line>
            <line>But that I was a journeyman to grief?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOHN OF GAUNT</speaker>
            <line>All places that the eye of heaven visits</line>
            <line>Are to a wise man ports and happy havens.</line>
            <line>Teach thy necessity to reason thus;</line>
            <line>There is no virtue like necessity.</line>
            <line>Think not the king did banish thee,</line>
            <line>But thou the king. Woe doth the heavier sit,</line>
            <line>Where it perceives it is but faintly borne.</line>
            <line>Go, say I sent thee forth to purchase honour</line>
            <line>And not the king exiled thee; or suppose</line>
            <line>Devouring pestilence hangs in our air</line>
            <line>And thou art flying to a fresher clime:</line>
            <line>Look, what thy soul holds dear, imagine it</line>
            <line>To lie that way thou go'st, not whence thou comest:</line>
            <line>Suppose the singing birds musicians,</line>
            <line>The grass whereon thou tread'st the presence strew'd,</line>
            <line>The flowers fair ladies, and thy steps no more</line>
            <line>Than a delightful measure or a dance;</line>
            <line>For gnarling sorrow hath less power to bite</line>
            <line>The man that mocks at it and sets it light.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>O, who can hold a fire in his hand</line>
            <line>By thinking on the frosty Caucasus?</line>
            <line>Or cloy the hungry edge of appetite</line>
            <line>By bare imagination of a feast?</line>
            <line>Or wallow naked in December snow</line>
            <line>By thinking on fantastic summer's heat?</line>
            <line>O, no! the apprehension of the good</line>
            <line>Gives but the greater feeling to the worse:</line>
            <line>Fell sorrow's tooth doth never rankle more</line>
            <line>Than when he bites, but lanceth not the sore.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOHN OF GAUNT</speaker>
            <line>Come, come, my son, I'll bring thee on thy way:</line>
            <line>Had I thy youth and cause, I would not stay.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Then, England's ground, farewell; sweet soil, adieu;</line>
            <line>My mother, and my nurse, that bears me yet!</line>
            <line>Where'er I wander, boast of this I can,</line>
            <line>Though banish'd, yet a trueborn Englishman.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-4">
      <title>SCENE IV.  The court.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter KING RICHARD II, with BAGOT and GREEN at one
door; and the DUKE OF AUMERLE at another</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>We did observe. Cousin Aumerle,</line>
            <line>How far brought you high Hereford on his way?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
            <line>I brought high Hereford, if you call him so,</line>
            <line>But to the next highway, and there I left him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>And say, what store of parting tears were shed?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
            <line>Faith, none for me; except the north-east wind,</line>
            <line>Which then blew bitterly against our faces,</line>
            <line>Awaked the sleeping rheum, and so by chance</line>
            <line>Did grace our hollow parting with a tear.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>What said our cousin when you parted with him?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
            <line>'Farewell:'</line>
            <line>And, for my heart disdained that my tongue</line>
            <line>Should so profane the word, that taught me craft</line>
            <line>To counterfeit oppression of such grief</line>
            <line>That words seem'd buried in my sorrow's grave.</line>
            <line>Marry, would the word 'farewell' have lengthen'd hours</line>
            <line>And added years to his short banishment,</line>
            <line>He should have had a volume of farewells;</line>
            <line>But since it would not, he had none of me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>He is our cousin, cousin; but 'tis doubt,</line>
            <line>When time shall call him home from banishment,</line>
            <line>Whether our kinsman come to see his friends.</line>
            <line>Ourself and Bushy, Bagot here and Green</line>
            <line>Observed his courtship to the common people;</line>
            <line>How he did seem to dive into their hearts</line>
            <line>With humble and familiar courtesy,</line>
            <line>What reverence he did throw away on slaves,</line>
            <line>Wooing poor craftsmen with the craft of smiles</line>
            <line>And patient underbearing of his fortune,</line>
            <line>As 'twere to banish their affects with him.</line>
            <line>Off goes his bonnet to an oyster-wench;</line>
            <line>A brace of draymen bid God speed him well</line>
            <line>And had the tribute of his supple knee,</line>
            <line>With 'Thanks, my countrymen, my loving friends;'</line>
            <line>As were our England in reversion his,</line>
            <line>And he our subjects' next degree in hope.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GREEN</speaker>
            <line>Well, he is gone; and with him go these thoughts.</line>
            <line>Now for the rebels which stand out in Ireland,</line>
            <line>Expedient manage must be made, my liege,</line>
            <line>Ere further leisure yield them further means</line>
            <line>For their advantage and your highness' loss.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>We will ourself in person to this war:</line>
            <line>And, for our coffers, with too great a court</line>
            <line>And liberal largess, are grown somewhat light,</line>
            <line>We are inforced to farm our royal realm;</line>
            <line>The revenue whereof shall furnish us</line>
            <line>For our affairs in hand: if that come short,</line>
            <line>Our substitutes at home shall have blank charters;</line>
            <line>Whereto, when they shall know what men are rich,</line>
            <line>They shall subscribe them for large sums of gold</line>
            <line>And send them after to supply our wants;</line>
            <line>For we will make for Ireland presently.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter BUSHY</stagedir>
            <line>Bushy, what news?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUSHY</speaker>
            <line>Old John of Gaunt is grievous sick, my lord,</line>
            <line>Suddenly taken; and hath sent post haste</line>
            <line>To entreat your majesty to visit him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>Where lies he?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUSHY</speaker>
            <line>At Ely House.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>Now put it, God, in the physician's mind</line>
            <line>To help him to his grave immediately!</line>
            <line>The lining of his coffers shall make coats</line>
            <line>To deck our soldiers for these Irish wars.</line>
            <line>Come, gentlemen, let's all go visit him:</line>
            <line>Pray God we may make haste, and come too late!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>All</speaker>
            <line>Amen.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>