<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net/doctypes/dita/shakespear/dtd/act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-5">
   <title>ACT V</title>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  London. A street leading to the Tower.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter QUEEN and Ladies</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN</speaker>
            <line>This way the king will come; this is the way</line>
            <line>To Julius Caesar's ill-erected tower,</line>
            <line>To whose flint bosom my condemned lord</line>
            <line>Is doom'd a prisoner by proud Bolingbroke:</line>
            <line>Here let us rest, if this rebellious earth</line>
            <line>Have any resting for her true king's queen.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter KING RICHARD II and Guard</stagedir>
            <line>But soft, but see, or rather do not see,</line>
            <line>My fair rose wither: yet look up, behold,</line>
            <line>That you in pity may dissolve to dew,</line>
            <line>And wash him fresh again with true-love tears.</line>
            <line>Ah, thou, the model where old Troy did stand,</line>
            <line>Thou map of honour, thou King Richard's tomb,</line>
            <line>And not King Richard; thou most beauteous inn,</line>
            <line>Why should hard-favour'd grief be lodged in thee,</line>
            <line>When triumph is become an alehouse guest?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>Join not with grief, fair woman, do not so,</line>
            <line>To make my end too sudden: learn, good soul,</line>
            <line>To think our former state a happy dream;</line>
            <line>From which awaked, the truth of what we are</line>
            <line>Shows us but this: I am sworn brother, sweet,</line>
            <line>To grim Necessity, and he and I</line>
            <line>Will keep a league till death. Hie thee to France</line>
            <line>And cloister thee in some religious house:</line>
            <line>Our holy lives must win a new world's crown,</line>
            <line>Which our profane hours here have stricken down.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN</speaker>
            <line>What, is my Richard both in shape and mind</line>
            <line>Transform'd and weaken'd? hath Bolingbroke deposed</line>
            <line>Thine intellect? hath he been in thy heart?</line>
            <line>The lion dying thrusteth forth his paw,</line>
            <line>And wounds the earth, if nothing else, with rage</line>
            <line>To be o'erpower'd; and wilt thou, pupil-like,</line>
            <line>Take thy correction mildly, kiss the rod,</line>
            <line>And fawn on rage with base humility,</line>
            <line>Which art a lion and a king of beasts?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>A king of beasts, indeed; if aught but beasts,</line>
            <line>I had been still a happy king of men.</line>
            <line>Good sometime queen, prepare thee hence for France:</line>
            <line>Think I am dead and that even here thou takest,</line>
            <line>As from my death-bed, thy last living leave.</line>
            <line>In winter's tedious nights sit by the fire</line>
            <line>With good old folks and let them tell thee tales</line>
            <line>Of woeful ages long ago betid;</line>
            <line>And ere thou bid good night, to quit their griefs,</line>
            <line>Tell thou the lamentable tale of me</line>
            <line>And send the hearers weeping to their beds:</line>
            <line>For why, the senseless brands will sympathize</line>
            <line>The heavy accent of thy moving tongue</line>
            <line>And in compassion weep the fire out;</line>
            <line>And some will mourn in ashes, some coal-black,</line>
            <line>For the deposing of a rightful king.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter NORTHUMBERLAND and others</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>My lord, the mind of Bolingbroke is changed:</line>
            <line>You must to Pomfret, not unto the Tower.</line>
            <line>And, madam, there is order ta'en for you;</line>
            <line>With all swift speed you must away to France.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>Northumberland, thou ladder wherewithal</line>
            <line>The mounting Bolingbroke ascends my throne,</line>
            <line>The time shall not be many hours of age</line>
            <line>More than it is ere foul sin gathering head</line>
            <line>Shalt break into corruption: thou shalt think,</line>
            <line>Though he divide the realm and give thee half,</line>
            <line>It is too little, helping him to all;</line>
            <line>And he shall think that thou, which know'st the way</line>
            <line>To plant unrightful kings, wilt know again,</line>
            <line>Being ne'er so little urged, another way</line>
            <line>To pluck him headlong from the usurped throne.</line>
            <line>The love of wicked men converts to fear;</line>
            <line>That fear to hate, and hate turns one or both</line>
            <line>To worthy danger and deserved death.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>My guilt be on my head, and there an end.</line>
            <line>Take leave and part; for you must part forthwith.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>Doubly divorced! Bad men, you violate</line>
            <line>A twofold marriage, 'twixt my crown and me,</line>
            <line>And then betwixt me and my married wife.</line>
            <line>Let me unkiss the oath 'twixt thee and me;</line>
            <line>And yet not so, for with a kiss 'twas made.</line>
            <line>Part us, Northumberland; I toward the north,</line>
            <line>Where shivering cold and sickness pines the clime;</line>
            <line>My wife to France: from whence, set forth in pomp,</line>
            <line>She came adorned hither like sweet May,</line>
            <line>Sent back like Hallowmas or short'st of day.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN</speaker>
            <line>And must we be divided? must we part?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>Ay, hand from hand, my love, and heart from heart.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN</speaker>
            <line>Banish us both and send the king with me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>That were some love but little policy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN</speaker>
            <line>Then whither he goes, thither let me go.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>So two, together weeping, make one woe.</line>
            <line>Weep thou for me in France, I for thee here;</line>
            <line>Better far off than near, be ne'er the near.</line>
            <line>Go, count thy way with sighs; I mine with groans.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN</speaker>
            <line>So longest way shall have the longest moans.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>Twice for one step I'll groan, the way being short,</line>
            <line>And piece the way out with a heavy heart.</line>
            <line>Come, come, in wooing sorrow let's be brief,</line>
            <line>Since, wedding it, there is such length in grief;</line>
            <line>One kiss shall stop our mouths, and dumbly part;</line>
            <line>Thus give I mine, and thus take I thy heart.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN</speaker>
            <line>Give me mine own again; 'twere no good part</line>
            <line>To take on me to keep and kill thy heart.</line>
            <line>So, now I have mine own again, be gone,</line>
            <line>That I might strive to kill it with a groan.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>We make woe wanton with this fond delay:</line>
            <line>Once more, adieu; the rest let sorrow say.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  The DUKE OF YORK's palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter DUKE OF YORK and DUCHESS OF YORK</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>My lord, you told me you would tell the rest,</line>
            <line>When weeping made you break the story off,</line>
            <line>of our two cousins coming into London.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Where did I leave?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>At that sad stop, my lord,</line>
            <line>Where rude misgovern'd hands from windows' tops</line>
            <line>Threw dust and rubbish on King Richard's head.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Then, as I said, the duke, great Bolingbroke,</line>
            <line>Mounted upon a hot and fiery steed</line>
            <line>Which his aspiring rider seem'd to know,</line>
            <line>With slow but stately pace kept on his course,</line>
            <line>Whilst all tongues cried 'God save thee,</line>
            <line>Bolingbroke!'</line>
            <line>You would have thought the very windows spake,</line>
            <line>So many greedy looks of young and old</line>
            <line>Through casements darted their desiring eyes</line>
            <line>Upon his visage, and that all the walls</line>
            <line>With painted imagery had said at once</line>
            <line>'Jesu preserve thee! welcome, Bolingbroke!'</line>
            <line>Whilst he, from the one side to the other turning,</line>
            <line>Bareheaded, lower than his proud steed's neck,</line>
            <line>Bespake them thus: 'I thank you, countrymen:'</line>
            <line>And thus still doing, thus he pass'd along.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Alack, poor Richard! where rode he the whilst?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>As in a theatre, the eyes of men,</line>
            <line>After a well-graced actor leaves the stage,</line>
            <line>Are idly bent on him that enters next,</line>
            <line>Thinking his prattle to be tedious;</line>
            <line>Even so, or with much more contempt, men's eyes</line>
            <line>Did scowl on gentle Richard; no man cried 'God save him!'</line>
            <line>No joyful tongue gave him his welcome home:</line>
            <line>But dust was thrown upon his sacred head:</line>
            <line>Which with such gentle sorrow he shook off,</line>
            <line>His face still combating with tears and smiles,</line>
            <line>The badges of his grief and patience,</line>
            <line>That had not God, for some strong purpose, steel'd</line>
            <line>The hearts of men, they must perforce have melted</line>
            <line>And barbarism itself have pitied him.</line>
            <line>But heaven hath a hand in these events,</line>
            <line>To whose high will we bound our calm contents.</line>
            <line>To Bolingbroke are we sworn subjects now,</line>
            <line>Whose state and honour I for aye allow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Here comes my son Aumerle.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Aumerle that was;</line>
            <line>But that is lost for being Richard's friend,</line>
            <line>And, madam, you must call him Rutland now:</line>
            <line>I am in parliament pledge for his truth</line>
            <line>And lasting fealty to the new-made king.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter DUKE OF AUMERLE</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Welcome, my son: who are the violets now</line>
            <line>That strew the green lap of the new come spring?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
            <line>Madam, I know not, nor I greatly care not:</line>
            <line>God knows I had as lief be none as one.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Well, bear you well in this new spring of time,</line>
            <line>Lest you be cropp'd before you come to prime.</line>
            <line>What news from Oxford? hold those justs and triumphs?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
            <line>For aught I know, my lord, they do.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>You will be there, I know.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
            <line>If God prevent not, I purpose so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>What seal is that, that hangs without thy bosom?</line>
            <line>Yea, look'st thou pale? let me see the writing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
            <line>My lord, 'tis nothing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>No matter, then, who see it;</line>
            <line>I will be satisfied; let me see the writing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
            <line>I do beseech your grace to pardon me:</line>
            <line>It is a matter of small consequence,</line>
            <line>Which for some reasons I would not have seen.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Which for some reasons, sir, I mean to see.</line>
            <line>I fear, I fear,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>What should you fear?</line>
            <line>'Tis nothing but some bond, that he is enter'd into</line>
            <line>For gay apparel 'gainst the triumph day.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Bound to himself! what doth he with a bond</line>
            <line>That he is bound to? Wife, thou art a fool.</line>
            <line>Boy, let me see the writing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
            <line>I do beseech you, pardon me; I may not show it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>I will be satisfied; let me see it, I say.</line>
            <stagedir>He plucks it out of his bosom and reads it</stagedir>
            <line>Treason! foul treason! Villain! traitor! slave!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>What is the matter, my lord?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Ho! who is within there?</line>
            <stagedir>Enter a Servant</stagedir>
            <line>Saddle my horse.</line>
            <line>God for his mercy, what treachery is here!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Why, what is it, my lord?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Give me my boots, I say; saddle my horse.</line>
            <line>Now, by mine honour, by my life, by my troth,</line>
            <line>I will appeach the villain.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>What is the matter?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Peace, foolish woman.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>I will not peace. What is the matter, Aumerle.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
            <line>Good mother, be content; it is no more</line>
            <line>Than my poor life must answer.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Thy life answer!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Bring me my boots: I will unto the king.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter Servant with boots</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Strike him, Aumerle. Poor boy, thou art amazed.</line>
            <line>Hence, villain! never more come in my sight.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Give me my boots, I say.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Why, York, what wilt thou do?</line>
            <line>Wilt thou not hide the trespass of thine own?</line>
            <line>Have we more sons? or are we like to have?</line>
            <line>Is not my teeming date drunk up with time?</line>
            <line>And wilt thou pluck my fair son from mine age,</line>
            <line>And rob me of a happy mother's name?</line>
            <line>Is he not like thee? is he not thine own?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Thou fond mad woman,</line>
            <line>Wilt thou conceal this dark conspiracy?</line>
            <line>A dozen of them here have ta'en the sacrament,</line>
            <line>And interchangeably set down their hands,</line>
            <line>To kill the king at Oxford.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>He shall be none;</line>
            <line>We'll keep him here: then what is that to him?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Away, fond woman! were he twenty times my son,</line>
            <line>I would appeach him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Hadst thou groan'd for him</line>
            <line>As I have done, thou wouldst be more pitiful.</line>
            <line>But now I know thy mind; thou dost suspect</line>
            <line>That I have been disloyal to thy bed,</line>
            <line>And that he is a bastard, not thy son:</line>
            <line>Sweet York, sweet husband, be not of that mind:</line>
            <line>He is as like thee as a man may be,</line>
            <line>Not like to me, or any of my kin,</line>
            <line>And yet I love him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Make way, unruly woman!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>After, Aumerle! mount thee upon his horse;</line>
            <line>Spur post, and get before him to the king,</line>
            <line>And beg thy pardon ere he do accuse thee.</line>
            <line>I'll not be long behind; though I be old,</line>
            <line>I doubt not but to ride as fast as York:</line>
            <line>And never will I rise up from the ground</line>
            <line>Till Bolingbroke have pardon'd thee. Away, be gone!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  A royal palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter HENRY BOLINGBROKE, HENRY PERCY, and other Lords</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Can no man tell me of my unthrifty son?</line>
            <line>'Tis full three months since I did see him last;</line>
            <line>If any plague hang over us, 'tis he.</line>
            <line>I would to God, my lords, he might be found:</line>
            <line>Inquire at London, 'mongst the taverns there,</line>
            <line>For there, they say, he daily doth frequent,</line>
            <line>With unrestrained loose companions,</line>
            <line>Even such, they say, as stand in narrow lanes,</line>
            <line>And beat our watch, and rob our passengers;</line>
            <line>Which he, young wanton and effeminate boy,</line>
            <line>Takes on the point of honour to support</line>
            <line>So dissolute a crew.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY PERCY</speaker>
            <line>My lord, some two days since I saw the prince,</line>
            <line>And told him of those triumphs held at Oxford.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>And what said the gallant?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY PERCY</speaker>
            <line>His answer was, he would unto the stews,</line>
            <line>And from the common'st creature pluck a glove,</line>
            <line>And wear it as a favour; and with that</line>
            <line>He would unhorse the lustiest challenger.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>As dissolute as desperate; yet through both</line>
            <line>I see some sparks of better hope, which elder years</line>
            <line>May happily bring forth. But who comes here?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter DUKE OF AUMERLE</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
            <line>Where is the king?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>What means our cousin, that he stares and looks</line>
            <line>So wildly?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
            <line>God save your grace! I do beseech your majesty,</line>
            <line>To have some conference with your grace alone.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Withdraw yourselves, and leave us here alone.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt HENRY PERCY and Lords</stagedir>
            <line>What is the matter with our cousin now?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
            <line>For ever may my knees grow to the earth,</line>
            <line>My tongue cleave to my roof within my mouth</line>
            <line>Unless a pardon ere I rise or speak.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Intended or committed was this fault?</line>
            <line>If on the first, how heinous e'er it be,</line>
            <line>To win thy after-love I pardon thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
            <line>Then give me leave that I may turn the key,</line>
            <line>That no man enter till my tale be done.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Have thy desire.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Within</stagedir>  My liege, beware; look to thyself;</line>
            <line>Thou hast a traitor in thy presence there.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Villain, I'll make thee safe.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Drawing</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
            <line>Stay thy revengeful hand; thou hast no cause to fear.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Within</stagedir>  Open the door, secure, foolhardy king:</line>
            <line>Shall I for love speak treason to thy face?</line>
            <line>Open the door, or I will break it open.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter DUKE OF YORK</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>What is the matter, uncle? speak;</line>
            <line>Recover breath; tell us how near is danger,</line>
            <line>That we may arm us to encounter it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Peruse this writing here, and thou shalt know</line>
            <line>The treason that my haste forbids me show.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
            <line>Remember, as thou read'st, thy promise pass'd:</line>
            <line>I do repent me; read not my name there</line>
            <line>My heart is not confederate with my hand.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>It was, villain, ere thy hand did set it down.</line>
            <line>I tore it from the traitor's bosom, king;</line>
            <line>Fear, and not love, begets his penitence:</line>
            <line>Forget to pity him, lest thy pity prove</line>
            <line>A serpent that will sting thee to the heart.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>O heinous, strong and bold conspiracy!</line>
            <line>O loyal father of a treacherous son!</line>
            <line>Thou sheer, immaculate and silver fountain,</line>
            <line>From when this stream through muddy passages</line>
            <line>Hath held his current and defiled himself!</line>
            <line>Thy overflow of good converts to bad,</line>
            <line>And thy abundant goodness shall excuse</line>
            <line>This deadly blot in thy digressing son.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>So shall my virtue be his vice's bawd;</line>
            <line>And he shall spend mine honour with his shame,</line>
            <line>As thriftless sons their scraping fathers' gold.</line>
            <line>Mine honour lives when his dishonour dies,</line>
            <line>Or my shamed life in his dishonour lies:</line>
            <line>Thou kill'st me in his life; giving him breath,</line>
            <line>The traitor lives, the true man's put to death.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Within</stagedir>  What ho, my liege! for God's sake,</line>
            <line>let me in.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>What shrill-voiced suppliant makes this eager cry?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>A woman, and thy aunt, great king; 'tis I.</line>
            <line>Speak with me, pity me, open the door.</line>
            <line>A beggar begs that never begg'd before.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Our scene is alter'd from a serious thing,</line>
            <line>And now changed to 'The Beggar and the King.'</line>
            <line>My dangerous cousin, let your mother in:</line>
            <line>I know she is come to pray for your foul sin.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>If thou do pardon, whosoever pray,</line>
            <line>More sins for this forgiveness prosper may.</line>
            <line>This fester'd joint cut off, the rest rest sound;</line>
            <line>This let alone will all the rest confound.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter DUCHESS OF YORK</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>O king, believe not this hard-hearted man!</line>
            <line>Love loving not itself none other can.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Thou frantic woman, what dost thou make here?</line>
            <line>Shall thy old dugs once more a traitor rear?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Sweet York, be patient. Hear me, gentle liege.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Kneels</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Rise up, good aunt.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Not yet, I thee beseech:</line>
            <line>For ever will I walk upon my knees,</line>
            <line>And never see day that the happy sees,</line>
            <line>Till thou give joy; until thou bid me joy,</line>
            <line>By pardoning Rutland, my transgressing boy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
            <line>Unto my mother's prayers I bend my knee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Against them both my true joints bended be.</line>
            <line>Ill mayst thou thrive, if thou grant any grace!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Pleads he in earnest? look upon his face;</line>
            <line>His eyes do drop no tears, his prayers are in jest;</line>
            <line>His words come from his mouth, ours from our breast:</line>
            <line>He prays but faintly and would be denied;</line>
            <line>We pray with heart and soul and all beside:</line>
            <line>His weary joints would gladly rise, I know;</line>
            <line>Our knees shall kneel till to the ground they grow:</line>
            <line>His prayers are full of false hypocrisy;</line>
            <line>Ours of true zeal and deep integrity.</line>
            <line>Our prayers do out-pray his; then let them have</line>
            <line>That mercy which true prayer ought to have.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Good aunt, stand up.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Nay, do not say, 'stand up;'</line>
            <line>Say, 'pardon' first, and afterwards 'stand up.'</line>
            <line>And if I were thy nurse, thy tongue to teach,</line>
            <line>'Pardon' should be the first word of thy speech.</line>
            <line>I never long'd to hear a word till now;</line>
            <line>Say 'pardon,' king; let pity teach thee how:</line>
            <line>The word is short, but not so short as sweet;</line>
            <line>No word like 'pardon' for kings' mouths so meet.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Speak it in French, king; say, 'pardonne moi.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Dost thou teach pardon pardon to destroy?</line>
            <line>Ah, my sour husband, my hard-hearted lord,</line>
            <line>That set'st the word itself against the word!</line>
            <line>Speak 'pardon' as 'tis current in our land;</line>
            <line>The chopping French we do not understand.</line>
            <line>Thine eye begins to speak; set thy tongue there;</line>
            <line>Or in thy piteous heart plant thou thine ear;</line>
            <line>That hearing how our plaints and prayers do pierce,</line>
            <line>Pity may move thee 'pardon' to rehearse.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Good aunt, stand up.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>I do not sue to stand;</line>
            <line>Pardon is all the suit I have in hand.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>I pardon him, as God shall pardon me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>O happy vantage of a kneeling knee!</line>
            <line>Yet am I sick for fear: speak it again;</line>
            <line>Twice saying 'pardon' doth not pardon twain,</line>
            <line>But makes one pardon strong.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>With all my heart</line>
            <line>I pardon him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>A god on earth thou art.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>But for our trusty brother-in-law and the abbot,</line>
            <line>With all the rest of that consorted crew,</line>
            <line>Destruction straight shall dog them at the heels.</line>
            <line>Good uncle, help to order several powers</line>
            <line>To Oxford, or where'er these traitors are:</line>
            <line>They shall not live within this world, I swear,</line>
            <line>But I will have them, if I once know where.</line>
            <line>Uncle, farewell: and, cousin too, adieu:</line>
            <line>Your mother well hath pray'd, and prove you true.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Come, my old son: I pray God make thee new.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-4">
      <title>SCENE IV.  The same.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter EXTON and Servant</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EXTON</speaker>
            <line>Didst thou not mark the king, what words he spake,</line>
            <line>'Have I no friend will rid me of this living fear?'</line>
            <line>Was it not so?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>These were his very words.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EXTON</speaker>
            <line>'Have I no friend?' quoth he: he spake it twice,</line>
            <line>And urged it twice together, did he not?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>He did.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EXTON</speaker>
            <line>And speaking it, he wistly look'd on me,</line>
            <line>And who should say, 'I would thou wert the man'</line>
            <line>That would divorce this terror from my heart;'</line>
            <line>Meaning the king at Pomfret. Come, let's go:</line>
            <line>I am the king's friend, and will rid his foe.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-5">
      <title>SCENE V.  Pomfret castle.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter KING RICHARD</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>I have been studying how I may compare</line>
            <line>This prison where I live unto the world:</line>
            <line>And for because the world is populous</line>
            <line>And here is not a creature but myself,</line>
            <line>I cannot do it; yet I'll hammer it out.</line>
            <line>My brain I'll prove the female to my soul,</line>
            <line>My soul the father; and these two beget</line>
            <line>A generation of still-breeding thoughts,</line>
            <line>And these same thoughts people this little world,</line>
            <line>In humours like the people of this world,</line>
            <line>For no thought is contented. The better sort,</line>
            <line>As thoughts of things divine, are intermix'd</line>
            <line>With scruples and do set the word itself</line>
            <line>Against the word:</line>
            <line>As thus, 'Come, little ones,' and then again,</line>
            <line>'It is as hard to come as for a camel</line>
            <line>To thread the postern of a small needle's eye.'</line>
            <line>Thoughts tending to ambition, they do plot</line>
            <line>Unlikely wonders; how these vain weak nails</line>
            <line>May tear a passage through the flinty ribs</line>
            <line>Of this hard world, my ragged prison walls,</line>
            <line>And, for they cannot, die in their own pride.</line>
            <line>Thoughts tending to content flatter themselves</line>
            <line>That they are not the first of fortune's slaves,</line>
            <line>Nor shall not be the last; like silly beggars</line>
            <line>Who sitting in the stocks refuge their shame,</line>
            <line>That many have and others must sit there;</line>
            <line>And in this thought they find a kind of ease,</line>
            <line>Bearing their own misfortunes on the back</line>
            <line>Of such as have before endured the like.</line>
            <line>Thus play I in one person many people,</line>
            <line>And none contented: sometimes am I king;</line>
            <line>Then treasons make me wish myself a beggar,</line>
            <line>And so I am: then crushing penury</line>
            <line>Persuades me I was better when a king;</line>
            <line>Then am I king'd again: and by and by</line>
            <line>Think that I am unking'd by Bolingbroke,</line>
            <line>And straight am nothing: but whate'er I be,</line>
            <line>Nor I nor any man that but man is</line>
            <line>With nothing shall be pleased, till he be eased</line>
            <line>With being nothing. Music do I hear?</line>
            <stagedir>Music</stagedir>
            <line>Ha, ha! keep time: how sour sweet music is,</line>
            <line>When time is broke and no proportion kept!</line>
            <line>So is it in the music of men's lives.</line>
            <line>And here have I the daintiness of ear</line>
            <line>To cheque time broke in a disorder'd string;</line>
            <line>But for the concord of my state and time</line>
            <line>Had not an ear to hear my true time broke.</line>
            <line>I wasted time, and now doth time waste me;</line>
            <line>For now hath time made me his numbering clock:</line>
            <line>My thoughts are minutes; and with sighs they jar</line>
            <line>Their watches on unto mine eyes, the outward watch,</line>
            <line>Whereto my finger, like a dial's point,</line>
            <line>Is pointing still, in cleansing them from tears.</line>
            <line>Now sir, the sound that tells what hour it is</line>
            <line>Are clamorous groans, which strike upon my heart,</line>
            <line>Which is the bell: so sighs and tears and groans</line>
            <line>Show minutes, times, and hours: but my time</line>
            <line>Runs posting on in Bolingbroke's proud joy,</line>
            <line>While I stand fooling here, his Jack o' the clock.</line>
            <line>This music mads me; let it sound no more;</line>
            <line>For though it have holp madmen to their wits,</line>
            <line>In me it seems it will make wise men mad.</line>
            <line>Yet blessing on his heart that gives it me!</line>
            <line>For 'tis a sign of love; and love to Richard</line>
            <line>Is a strange brooch in this all-hating world.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter a Groom of the Stable</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Groom</speaker>
            <line>Hail, royal prince!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>Thanks, noble peer;</line>
            <line>The cheapest of us is ten groats too dear.</line>
            <line>What art thou? and how comest thou hither,</line>
            <line>Where no man never comes but that sad dog</line>
            <line>That brings me food to make misfortune live?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Groom</speaker>
            <line>I was a poor groom of thy stable, king,</line>
            <line>When thou wert king; who, travelling towards York,</line>
            <line>With much ado at length have gotten leave</line>
            <line>To look upon my sometimes royal master's face.</line>
            <line>O, how it yearn'd my heart when I beheld</line>
            <line>In London streets, that coronation-day,</line>
            <line>When Bolingbroke rode on roan Barbary,</line>
            <line>That horse that thou so often hast bestrid,</line>
            <line>That horse that I so carefully have dress'd!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>Rode he on Barbary? Tell me, gentle friend,</line>
            <line>How went he under him?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Groom</speaker>
            <line>So proudly as if he disdain'd the ground.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>So proud that Bolingbroke was on his back!</line>
            <line>That jade hath eat bread from my royal hand;</line>
            <line>This hand hath made him proud with clapping him.</line>
            <line>Would he not stumble? would he not fall down,</line>
            <line>Since pride must have a fall, and break the neck</line>
            <line>Of that proud man that did usurp his back?</line>
            <line>Forgiveness, horse! why do I rail on thee,</line>
            <line>Since thou, created to be awed by man,</line>
            <line>Wast born to bear? I was not made a horse;</line>
            <line>And yet I bear a burthen like an ass,</line>
            <line>Spurr'd, gall'd and tired by jouncing Bolingbroke.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter Keeper, with a dish</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Keeper</speaker>
            <line>Fellow, give place; here is no longer stay.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>If thou love me, 'tis time thou wert away.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Groom</speaker>
            <line>What my tongue dares not, that my heart shall say.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Keeper</speaker>
            <line>My lord, will't please you to fall to?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>Taste of it first, as thou art wont to do.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Keeper</speaker>
            <line>My lord, I dare not: Sir Pierce of Exton, who</line>
            <line>lately came from the king, commands the contrary.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>The devil take Henry of Lancaster and thee!</line>
            <line>Patience is stale, and I am weary of it.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Beats the keeper</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Keeper</speaker>
            <line>Help, help, help!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter EXTON and Servants, armed</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>How now! what means death in this rude assault?</line>
            <line>Villain, thy own hand yields thy death's instrument.</line>
            <stagedir>Snatching an axe from a Servant and killing him</stagedir>
            <line>Go thou, and fill another room in hell.</line>
            <stagedir>He kills another. Then Exton strikes him down</stagedir>
            <line>That hand shall burn in never-quenching fire</line>
            <line>That staggers thus my person. Exton, thy fierce hand</line>
            <line>Hath with the king's blood stain'd the king's own land.</line>
            <line>Mount, mount, my soul! thy seat is up on high;</line>
            <line>Whilst my gross flesh sinks downward, here to die.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Dies</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EXTON</speaker>
            <line>As full of valour as of royal blood:</line>
            <line>Both have I spill'd; O would the deed were good!</line>
            <line>For now the devil, that told me I did well,</line>
            <line>Says that this deed is chronicled in hell.</line>
            <line>This dead king to the living king I'll bear</line>
            <line>Take hence the rest, and give them burial here.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-6">
      <title>SCENE VI.  Windsor castle.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Flourish. Enter HENRY BOLINGBROKE, DUKE OF YORK,
with other Lords, and Attendants</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Kind uncle York, the latest news we hear</line>
            <line>Is that the rebels have consumed with fire</line>
            <line>Our town of Cicester in Gloucestershire;</line>
            <line>But whether they be ta'en or slain we hear not.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter NORTHUMBERLAND</stagedir>
            <line>Welcome, my lord what is the news?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>First, to thy sacred state wish I all happiness.</line>
            <line>The next news is, I have to London sent</line>
            <line>The heads of Oxford, Salisbury, Blunt, and Kent:</line>
            <line>The manner of their taking may appear</line>
            <line>At large discoursed in this paper here.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>We thank thee, gentle Percy, for thy pains;</line>
            <line>And to thy worth will add right worthy gains.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter LORD FITZWATER</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD FITZWATER</speaker>
            <line>My lord, I have from Oxford sent to London</line>
            <line>The heads of Brocas and Sir Bennet Seely,</line>
            <line>Two of the dangerous consorted traitors</line>
            <line>That sought at Oxford thy dire overthrow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Thy pains, Fitzwater, shall not be forgot;</line>
            <line>Right noble is thy merit, well I wot.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter HENRY PERCY, and the BISHOP OF CARLISLE</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY PERCY</speaker>
            <line>The grand conspirator, Abbot of Westminster,</line>
            <line>With clog of conscience and sour melancholy</line>
            <line>Hath yielded up his body to the grave;</line>
            <line>But here is Carlisle living, to abide</line>
            <line>Thy kingly doom and sentence of his pride.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Carlisle, this is your doom:</line>
            <line>Choose out some secret place, some reverend room,</line>
            <line>More than thou hast, and with it joy thy life;</line>
            <line>So as thou livest in peace, die free from strife:</line>
            <line>For though mine enemy thou hast ever been,</line>
            <line>High sparks of honour in thee have I seen.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter EXTON, with persons bearing a coffin</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EXTON</speaker>
            <line>Great king, within this coffin I present</line>
            <line>Thy buried fear: herein all breathless lies</line>
            <line>The mightiest of thy greatest enemies,</line>
            <line>Richard of Bordeaux, by me hither brought.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Exton, I thank thee not; for thou hast wrought</line>
            <line>A deed of slander with thy fatal hand</line>
            <line>Upon my head and all this famous land.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EXTON</speaker>
            <line>From your own mouth, my lord, did I this deed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>They love not poison that do poison need,</line>
            <line>Nor do I thee: though I did wish him dead,</line>
            <line>I hate the murderer, love him murdered.</line>
            <line>The guilt of conscience take thou for thy labour,</line>
            <line>But neither my good word nor princely favour:</line>
            <line>With Cain go wander through shades of night,</line>
            <line>And never show thy head by day nor light.</line>
            <line>Lords, I protest, my soul is full of woe,</line>
            <line>That blood should sprinkle me to make me grow:</line>
            <line>Come, mourn with me for that I do lament,</line>
            <line>And put on sullen black incontinent:</line>
            <line>I'll make a voyage to the Holy Land,</line>
            <line>To wash this blood off from my guilty hand:</line>
            <line>March sadly after; grace my mournings here;</line>
            <line>In weeping after this untimely bier.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>