<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net/doctypes/dita/shakespear/dtd/act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-4">
   <title>ACT IV</title>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  Westminster Hall.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter, as to the Parliament, HENRY BOLINGBROKE,
DUKE OF AUMERLE, NORTHUMBERLAND, HENRY PERCY, LORD
FITZWATER, DUKE OF SURREY, the BISHOP OF CARLISLE,
the Abbot Of Westminster, and another Lord, Herald,
Officers, and BAGOT</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Call forth Bagot.</line>
            <line>Now, Bagot, freely speak thy mind;</line>
            <line>What thou dost know of noble Gloucester's death,</line>
            <line>Who wrought it with the king, and who perform'd</line>
            <line>The bloody office of his timeless end.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BAGOT</speaker>
            <line>Then set before my face the Lord Aumerle.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Cousin, stand forth, and look upon that man.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BAGOT</speaker>
            <line>My Lord Aumerle, I know your daring tongue</line>
            <line>Scorns to unsay what once it hath deliver'd.</line>
            <line>In that dead time when Gloucester's death was plotted,</line>
            <line>I heard you say, 'Is not my arm of length,</line>
            <line>That reacheth from the restful English court</line>
            <line>As far as Calais, to mine uncle's head?'</line>
            <line>Amongst much other talk, that very time,</line>
            <line>I heard you say that you had rather refuse</line>
            <line>The offer of an hundred thousand crowns</line>
            <line>Than Bolingbroke's return to England;</line>
            <line>Adding withal how blest this land would be</line>
            <line>In this your cousin's death.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
            <line>Princes and noble lords,</line>
            <line>What answer shall I make to this base man?</line>
            <line>Shall I so much dishonour my fair stars,</line>
            <line>On equal terms to give him chastisement?</line>
            <line>Either I must, or have mine honour soil'd</line>
            <line>With the attainder of his slanderous lips.</line>
            <line>There is my gage, the manual seal of death,</line>
            <line>That marks thee out for hell: I say, thou liest,</line>
            <line>And will maintain what thou hast said is false</line>
            <line>In thy heart-blood, though being all too base</line>
            <line>To stain the temper of my knightly sword.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Bagot, forbear; thou shalt not take it up.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
            <line>Excepting one, I would he were the best</line>
            <line>In all this presence that hath moved me so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD FITZWATER</speaker>
            <line>If that thy valour stand on sympathy,</line>
            <line>There is my gage, Aumerle, in gage to thine:</line>
            <line>By that fair sun which shows me where thou stand'st,</line>
            <line>I heard thee say, and vauntingly thou spakest it</line>
            <line>That thou wert cause of noble Gloucester's death.</line>
            <line>If thou deny'st it twenty times, thou liest;</line>
            <line>And I will turn thy falsehood to thy heart,</line>
            <line>Where it was forged, with my rapier's point.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
            <line>Thou darest not, coward, live to see that day.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD FITZWATER</speaker>
            <line>Now by my soul, I would it were this hour.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
            <line>Fitzwater, thou art damn'd to hell for this.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY PERCY</speaker>
            <line>Aumerle, thou liest; his honour is as true</line>
            <line>In this appeal as thou art all unjust;</line>
            <line>And that thou art so, there I throw my gage,</line>
            <line>To prove it on thee to the extremest point</line>
            <line>Of mortal breathing: seize it, if thou darest.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
            <line>An if I do not, may my hands rot off</line>
            <line>And never brandish more revengeful steel</line>
            <line>Over the glittering helmet of my foe!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord</speaker>
            <line>I task the earth to the like, forsworn Aumerle;</line>
            <line>And spur thee on with full as many lies</line>
            <line>As may be holloa'd in thy treacherous ear</line>
            <line>From sun to sun: there is my honour's pawn;</line>
            <line>Engage it to the trial, if thou darest.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
            <line>Who sets me else? by heaven, I'll throw at all:</line>
            <line>I have a thousand spirits in one breast,</line>
            <line>To answer twenty thousand such as you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF SURREY</speaker>
            <line>My Lord Fitzwater, I do remember well</line>
            <line>The very time Aumerle and you did talk.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD FITZWATER</speaker>
            <line>'Tis very true: you were in presence then;</line>
            <line>And you can witness with me this is true.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF SURREY</speaker>
            <line>As false, by heaven, as heaven itself is true.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD FITZWATER</speaker>
            <line>Surrey, thou liest.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF SURREY</speaker>
            <line>Dishonourable boy!</line>
            <line>That lie shall lie so heavy on my sword,</line>
            <line>That it shall render vengeance and revenge</line>
            <line>Till thou the lie-giver and that lie do lie</line>
            <line>In earth as quiet as thy father's skull:</line>
            <line>In proof whereof, there is my honour's pawn;</line>
            <line>Engage it to the trial, if thou darest.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LORD FITZWATER</speaker>
            <line>How fondly dost thou spur a forward horse!</line>
            <line>If I dare eat, or drink, or breathe, or live,</line>
            <line>I dare meet Surrey in a wilderness,</line>
            <line>And spit upon him, whilst I say he lies,</line>
            <line>And lies, and lies: there is my bond of faith,</line>
            <line>To tie thee to my strong correction.</line>
            <line>As I intend to thrive in this new world,</line>
            <line>Aumerle is guilty of my true appeal:</line>
            <line>Besides, I heard the banish'd Norfolk say</line>
            <line>That thou, Aumerle, didst send two of thy men</line>
            <line>To execute the noble duke at Calais.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
            <line>Some honest Christian trust me with a gage</line>
            <line>That Norfolk lies: here do I throw down this,</line>
            <line>If he may be repeal'd, to try his honour.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>These differences shall all rest under gage</line>
            <line>Till Norfolk be repeal'd: repeal'd he shall be,</line>
            <line>And, though mine enemy, restored again</line>
            <line>To all his lands and signories: when he's return'd,</line>
            <line>Against Aumerle we will enforce his trial.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BISHOP OF CARLISLE</speaker>
            <line>That honourable day shall ne'er be seen.</line>
            <line>Many a time hath banish'd Norfolk fought</line>
            <line>For Jesu Christ in glorious Christian field,</line>
            <line>Streaming the ensign of the Christian cross</line>
            <line>Against black pagans, Turks, and Saracens:</line>
            <line>And toil'd with works of war, retired himself</line>
            <line>To Italy; and there at Venice gave</line>
            <line>His body to that pleasant country's earth,</line>
            <line>And his pure soul unto his captain Christ,</line>
            <line>Under whose colours he had fought so long.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Why, bishop, is Norfolk dead?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BISHOP OF CARLISLE</speaker>
            <line>As surely as I live, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Sweet peace conduct his sweet soul to the bosom</line>
            <line>Of good old Abraham! Lords appellants,</line>
            <line>Your differences shall all rest under gage</line>
            <line>Till we assign you to your days of trial.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter DUKE OF YORK, attended</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Great Duke of Lancaster, I come to thee</line>
            <line>From plume-pluck'd Richard; who with willing soul</line>
            <line>Adopts thee heir, and his high sceptre yields</line>
            <line>To the possession of thy royal hand:</line>
            <line>Ascend his throne, descending now from him;</line>
            <line>And long live Henry, fourth of that name!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>In God's name, I'll ascend the regal throne.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BISHOP OF CARLISLE</speaker>
            <line>Marry. God forbid!</line>
            <line>Worst in this royal presence may I speak,</line>
            <line>Yet best beseeming me to speak the truth.</line>
            <line>Would God that any in this noble presence</line>
            <line>Were enough noble to be upright judge</line>
            <line>Of noble Richard! then true noblesse would</line>
            <line>Learn him forbearance from so foul a wrong.</line>
            <line>What subject can give sentence on his king?</line>
            <line>And who sits here that is not Richard's subject?</line>
            <line>Thieves are not judged but they are by to hear,</line>
            <line>Although apparent guilt be seen in them;</line>
            <line>And shall the figure of God's majesty,</line>
            <line>His captain, steward, deputy-elect,</line>
            <line>Anointed, crowned, planted many years,</line>
            <line>Be judged by subject and inferior breath,</line>
            <line>And he himself not present? O, forfend it, God,</line>
            <line>That in a Christian climate souls refined</line>
            <line>Should show so heinous, black, obscene a deed!</line>
            <line>I speak to subjects, and a subject speaks,</line>
            <line>Stirr'd up by God, thus boldly for his king:</line>
            <line>My Lord of Hereford here, whom you call king,</line>
            <line>Is a foul traitor to proud Hereford's king:</line>
            <line>And if you crown him, let me prophesy:</line>
            <line>The blood of English shall manure the ground,</line>
            <line>And future ages groan for this foul act;</line>
            <line>Peace shall go sleep with Turks and infidels,</line>
            <line>And in this seat of peace tumultuous wars</line>
            <line>Shall kin with kin and kind with kind confound;</line>
            <line>Disorder, horror, fear and mutiny</line>
            <line>Shall here inhabit, and this land be call'd</line>
            <line>The field of Golgotha and dead men's skulls.</line>
            <line>O, if you raise this house against this house,</line>
            <line>It will the woefullest division prove</line>
            <line>That ever fell upon this cursed earth.</line>
            <line>Prevent it, resist it, let it not be so,</line>
            <line>Lest child, child's children, cry against you woe!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>Well have you argued, sir; and, for your pains,</line>
            <line>Of capital treason we arrest you here.</line>
            <line>My Lord of Westminster, be it your charge</line>
            <line>To keep him safely till his day of trial.</line>
            <line>May it please you, lords, to grant the commons' suit.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Fetch hither Richard, that in common view</line>
            <line>He may surrender; so we shall proceed</line>
            <line>Without suspicion.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>I will be his conduct.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Lords, you that here are under our arrest,</line>
            <line>Procure your sureties for your days of answer.</line>
            <line>Little are we beholding to your love,</line>
            <line>And little look'd for at your helping hands.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter DUKE OF YORK, with KING RICHARD II, and
Officers bearing the regalia</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>Alack, why am I sent for to a king,</line>
            <line>Before I have shook off the regal thoughts</line>
            <line>Wherewith I reign'd? I hardly yet have learn'd</line>
            <line>To insinuate, flatter, bow, and bend my limbs:</line>
            <line>Give sorrow leave awhile to tutor me</line>
            <line>To this submission. Yet I well remember</line>
            <line>The favours of these men: were they not mine?</line>
            <line>Did they not sometime cry, 'all hail!' to me?</line>
            <line>So Judas did to Christ: but he, in twelve,</line>
            <line>Found truth in all but one: I, in twelve thousand, none.</line>
            <line>God save the king! Will no man say amen?</line>
            <line>Am I both priest and clerk? well then, amen.</line>
            <line>God save the king! although I be not he;</line>
            <line>And yet, amen, if heaven do think him me.</line>
            <line>To do what service am I sent for hither?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>To do that office of thine own good will</line>
            <line>Which tired majesty did make thee offer,</line>
            <line>The resignation of thy state and crown</line>
            <line>To Henry Bolingbroke.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>Give me the crown. Here, cousin, seize the crown;</line>
            <line>Here cousin:</line>
            <line>On this side my hand, and on that side yours.</line>
            <line>Now is this golden crown like a deep well</line>
            <line>That owes two buckets, filling one another,</line>
            <line>The emptier ever dancing in the air,</line>
            <line>The other down, unseen and full of water:</line>
            <line>That bucket down and full of tears am I,</line>
            <line>Drinking my griefs, whilst you mount up on high.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>I thought you had been willing to resign.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>My crown I am; but still my griefs are mine:</line>
            <line>You may my glories and my state depose,</line>
            <line>But not my griefs; still am I king of those.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Part of your cares you give me with your crown.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>Your cares set up do not pluck my cares down.</line>
            <line>My care is loss of care, by old care done;</line>
            <line>Your care is gain of care, by new care won:</line>
            <line>The cares I give I have, though given away;</line>
            <line>They tend the crown, yet still with me they stay.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Are you contented to resign the crown?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>Ay, no; no, ay; for I must nothing be;</line>
            <line>Therefore no no, for I resign to thee.</line>
            <line>Now mark me, how I will undo myself;</line>
            <line>I give this heavy weight from off my head</line>
            <line>And this unwieldy sceptre from my hand,</line>
            <line>The pride of kingly sway from out my heart;</line>
            <line>With mine own tears I wash away my balm,</line>
            <line>With mine own hands I give away my crown,</line>
            <line>With mine own tongue deny my sacred state,</line>
            <line>With mine own breath release all duty's rites:</line>
            <line>All pomp and majesty I do forswear;</line>
            <line>My manors, rents, revenues I forego;</line>
            <line>My acts, decrees, and statutes I deny:</line>
            <line>God pardon all oaths that are broke to me!</line>
            <line>God keep all vows unbroke that swear to thee!</line>
            <line>Make me, that nothing have, with nothing grieved,</line>
            <line>And thou with all pleased, that hast all achieved!</line>
            <line>Long mayst thou live in Richard's seat to sit,</line>
            <line>And soon lie Richard in an earthly pit!</line>
            <line>God save King Harry, unking'd Richard says,</line>
            <line>And send him many years of sunshine days!</line>
            <line>What more remains?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>No more, but that you read</line>
            <line>These accusations and these grievous crimes</line>
            <line>Committed by your person and your followers</line>
            <line>Against the state and profit of this land;</line>
            <line>That, by confessing them, the souls of men</line>
            <line>May deem that you are worthily deposed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>Must I do so? and must I ravel out</line>
            <line>My weaved-up folly? Gentle Northumberland,</line>
            <line>If thy offences were upon record,</line>
            <line>Would it not shame thee in so fair a troop</line>
            <line>To read a lecture of them? If thou wouldst,</line>
            <line>There shouldst thou find one heinous article,</line>
            <line>Containing the deposing of a king</line>
            <line>And cracking the strong warrant of an oath,</line>
            <line>Mark'd with a blot, damn'd in the book of heaven:</line>
            <line>Nay, all of you that stand and look upon,</line>
            <line>Whilst that my wretchedness doth bait myself,</line>
            <line>Though some of you with Pilate wash your hands</line>
            <line>Showing an outward pity; yet you Pilates</line>
            <line>Have here deliver'd me to my sour cross,</line>
            <line>And water cannot wash away your sin.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>My lord, dispatch; read o'er these articles.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>Mine eyes are full of tears, I cannot see:</line>
            <line>And yet salt water blinds them not so much</line>
            <line>But they can see a sort of traitors here.</line>
            <line>Nay, if I turn mine eyes upon myself,</line>
            <line>I find myself a traitor with the rest;</line>
            <line>For I have given here my soul's consent</line>
            <line>To undeck the pompous body of a king;</line>
            <line>Made glory base and sovereignty a slave,</line>
            <line>Proud majesty a subject, state a peasant.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>My lord,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>No lord of thine, thou haught insulting man,</line>
            <line>Nor no man's lord; I have no name, no title,</line>
            <line>No, not that name was given me at the font,</line>
            <line>But 'tis usurp'd: alack the heavy day,</line>
            <line>That I have worn so many winters out,</line>
            <line>And know not now what name to call myself!</line>
            <line>O that I were a mockery king of snow,</line>
            <line>Standing before the sun of Bolingbroke,</line>
            <line>To melt myself away in water-drops!</line>
            <line>Good king, great king, and yet not greatly good,</line>
            <line>An if my word be sterling yet in England,</line>
            <line>Let it command a mirror hither straight,</line>
            <line>That it may show me what a face I have,</line>
            <line>Since it is bankrupt of his majesty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Go some of you and fetch a looking-glass.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit an attendant</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>Read o'er this paper while the glass doth come.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>Fiend, thou torment'st me ere I come to hell!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Urge it no more, my Lord Northumberland.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>The commons will not then be satisfied.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>They shall be satisfied: I'll read enough,</line>
            <line>When I do see the very book indeed</line>
            <line>Where all my sins are writ, and that's myself.</line>
            <stagedir>Re-enter Attendant, with a glass</stagedir>
            <line>Give me the glass, and therein will I read.</line>
            <line>No deeper wrinkles yet? hath sorrow struck</line>
            <line>So many blows upon this face of mine,</line>
            <line>And made no deeper wounds? O flattering glass,</line>
            <line>Like to my followers in prosperity,</line>
            <line>Thou dost beguile me! Was this face the face</line>
            <line>That every day under his household roof</line>
            <line>Did keep ten thousand men? was this the face</line>
            <line>That, like the sun, did make beholders wink?</line>
            <line>Was this the face that faced so many follies,</line>
            <line>And was at last out-faced by Bolingbroke?</line>
            <line>A brittle glory shineth in this face:</line>
            <line>As brittle as the glory is the face;</line>
            <stagedir>Dashes the glass against the ground</stagedir>
            <line>For there it is, crack'd in a hundred shivers.</line>
            <line>Mark, silent king, the moral of this sport,</line>
            <line>How soon my sorrow hath destroy'd my face.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>The shadow of your sorrow hath destroy'd</line>
            <line>The shadow or your face.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>Say that again.</line>
            <line>The shadow of my sorrow! ha! let's see:</line>
            <line>'Tis very true, my grief lies all within;</line>
            <line>And these external manners of laments</line>
            <line>Are merely shadows to the unseen grief</line>
            <line>That swells with silence in the tortured soul;</line>
            <line>There lies the substance: and I thank thee, king,</line>
            <line>For thy great bounty, that not only givest</line>
            <line>Me cause to wail but teachest me the way</line>
            <line>How to lament the cause. I'll beg one boon,</line>
            <line>And then be gone and trouble you no more.</line>
            <line>Shall I obtain it?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Name it, fair cousin.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>'Fair cousin'? I am greater than a king:</line>
            <line>For when I was a king, my flatterers</line>
            <line>Were then but subjects; being now a subject,</line>
            <line>I have a king here to my flatterer.</line>
            <line>Being so great, I have no need to beg.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Yet ask.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>And shall I have?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>You shall.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>Then give me leave to go.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Whither?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>Whither you will, so I were from your sights.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Go, some of you convey him to the Tower.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING RICHARD II</speaker>
            <line>O, good! convey? conveyers are you all,</line>
            <line>That rise thus nimbly by a true king's fall.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt KING RICHARD II, some Lords, and a Guard</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HENRY BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>On Wednesday next we solemnly set down</line>
            <line>Our coronation: lords, prepare yourselves.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt all except the BISHOP OF CARLISLE, the Abbot
of Westminster, and DUKE OF AUMERLE</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Abbot</speaker>
            <line>A woeful pageant have we here beheld.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BISHOP OF CARLISLE</speaker>
            <line>The woe's to come; the children yet unborn.</line>
            <line>Shall feel this day as sharp to them as thorn.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF AUMERLE</speaker>
            <line>You holy clergymen, is there no plot</line>
            <line>To rid the realm of this pernicious blot?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Abbot</speaker>
            <line>My lord,</line>
            <line>Before I freely speak my mind herein,</line>
            <line>You shall not only take the sacrament</line>
            <line>To bury mine intents, but also to effect</line>
            <line>Whatever I shall happen to devise.</line>
            <line>I see your brows are full of discontent,</line>
            <line>Your hearts of sorrow and your eyes of tears:</line>
            <line>Come home with me to supper; and I'll lay</line>
            <line>A plot shall show us all a merry day.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>