<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:shakespear:dtd:act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-5">
   <title>ACT V</title>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  Before LEONATO'S house.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter LEONATO and ANTONIO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>If you go on thus, you will kill yourself:</line>
            <line>And 'tis not wisdom thus to second grief</line>
            <line>Against yourself.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>I pray thee, cease thy counsel,</line>
            <line>Which falls into mine ears as profitless</line>
            <line>As water in a sieve: give not me counsel;</line>
            <line>Nor let no comforter delight mine ear</line>
            <line>But such a one whose wrongs do suit with mine.</line>
            <line>Bring me a father that so loved his child,</line>
            <line>Whose joy of her is overwhelm'd like mine,</line>
            <line>And bid him speak of patience;</line>
            <line>Measure his woe the length and breadth of mine</line>
            <line>And let it answer every strain for strain,</line>
            <line>As thus for thus and such a grief for such,</line>
            <line>In every lineament, branch, shape, and form:</line>
            <line>If such a one will smile and stroke his beard,</line>
            <line>Bid sorrow wag, cry 'hem!' when he should groan,</line>
            <line>Patch grief with proverbs, make misfortune drunk</line>
            <line>With candle-wasters; bring him yet to me,</line>
            <line>And I of him will gather patience.</line>
            <line>But there is no such man: for, brother, men</line>
            <line>Can counsel and speak comfort to that grief</line>
            <line>Which they themselves not feel; but, tasting it,</line>
            <line>Their counsel turns to passion, which before</line>
            <line>Would give preceptial medicine to rage,</line>
            <line>Fetter strong madness in a silken thread,</line>
            <line>Charm ache with air and agony with words:</line>
            <line>No, no; 'tis all men's office to speak patience</line>
            <line>To those that wring under the load of sorrow,</line>
            <line>But no man's virtue nor sufficiency</line>
            <line>To be so moral when he shall endure</line>
            <line>The like himself. Therefore give me no counsel:</line>
            <line>My griefs cry louder than advertisement.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>Therein do men from children nothing differ.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>I pray thee, peace. I will be flesh and blood;</line>
            <line>For there was never yet philosopher</line>
            <line>That could endure the toothache patiently,</line>
            <line>However they have writ the style of gods</line>
            <line>And made a push at chance and sufferance.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>Yet bend not all the harm upon yourself;</line>
            <line>Make those that do offend you suffer too.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>There thou speak'st reason: nay, I will do so.</line>
            <line>My soul doth tell me Hero is belied;</line>
            <line>And that shall Claudio know; so shall the prince</line>
            <line>And all of them that thus dishonour her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>Here comes the prince and Claudio hastily.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter DON PEDRO and CLAUDIO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>Good den, good den.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Good day to both of you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>Hear you. my lords,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>We have some haste, Leonato.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>Some haste, my lord! well, fare you well, my lord:</line>
            <line>Are you so hasty now? well, all is one.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>Nay, do not quarrel with us, good old man.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>If he could right himself with quarreling,</line>
            <line>Some of us would lie low.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Who wrongs him?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>Marry, thou dost wrong me; thou dissembler, thou:--</line>
            <line>Nay, never lay thy hand upon thy sword;</line>
            <line>I fear thee not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Marry, beshrew my hand,</line>
            <line>If it should give your age such cause of fear:</line>
            <line>In faith, my hand meant nothing to my sword.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>Tush, tush, man; never fleer and jest at me:</line>
            <line>I speak not like a dotard nor a fool,</line>
            <line>As under privilege of age to brag</line>
            <line>What I have done being young, or what would do</line>
            <line>Were I not old. Know, Claudio, to thy head,</line>
            <line>Thou hast so wrong'd mine innocent child and me</line>
            <line>That I am forced to lay my reverence by</line>
            <line>And, with grey hairs and bruise of many days,</line>
            <line>Do challenge thee to trial of a man.</line>
            <line>I say thou hast belied mine innocent child;</line>
            <line>Thy slander hath gone through and through her heart,</line>
            <line>And she lies buried with her ancestors;</line>
            <line>O, in a tomb where never scandal slept,</line>
            <line>Save this of hers, framed by thy villany!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>My villany?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>Thine, Claudio; thine, I say.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>You say not right, old man.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>My lord, my lord,</line>
            <line>I'll prove it on his body, if he dare,</line>
            <line>Despite his nice fence and his active practise,</line>
            <line>His May of youth and bloom of lustihood.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Away! I will not have to do with you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>Canst thou so daff me? Thou hast kill'd my child:</line>
            <line>If thou kill'st me, boy, thou shalt kill a man.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>He shall kill two of us, and men indeed:</line>
            <line>But that's no matter; let him kill one first;</line>
            <line>Win me and wear me; let him answer me.</line>
            <line>Come, follow me, boy; come, sir boy, come, follow me:</line>
            <line>Sir boy, I'll whip you from your foining fence;</line>
            <line>Nay, as I am a gentleman, I will.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>Brother,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>Content yourself. God knows I loved my niece;</line>
            <line>And she is dead, slander'd to death by villains,</line>
            <line>That dare as well answer a man indeed</line>
            <line>As I dare take a serpent by the tongue:</line>
            <line>Boys, apes, braggarts, Jacks, milksops!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>Brother Antony,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>Hold you content. What, man! I know them, yea,</line>
            <line>And what they weigh, even to the utmost scruple,--</line>
            <line>Scrambling, out-facing, fashion-monging boys,</line>
            <line>That lie and cog and flout, deprave and slander,</line>
            <line>Go anticly, show outward hideousness,</line>
            <line>And speak off half a dozen dangerous words,</line>
            <line>How they might hurt their enemies, if they durst;</line>
            <line>And this is all.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>But, brother Antony,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>Come, 'tis no matter:</line>
            <line>Do not you meddle; let me deal in this.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>Gentlemen both, we will not wake your patience.</line>
            <line>My heart is sorry for your daughter's death:</line>
            <line>But, on my honour, she was charged with nothing</line>
            <line>But what was true and very full of proof.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>My lord, my lord,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>I will not hear you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>No? Come, brother; away! I will be heard.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>And shall, or some of us will smart for it.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt LEONATO and ANTONIO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>See, see; here comes the man we went to seek.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter BENEDICK</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Now, signior, what news?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Good day, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>Welcome, signior: you are almost come to part</line>
            <line>almost a fray.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>We had like to have had our two noses snapped off</line>
            <line>with two old men without teeth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>Leonato and his brother. What thinkest thou? Had</line>
            <line>we fought, I doubt we should have been too young for them.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>In a false quarrel there is no true valour. I came</line>
            <line>to seek you both.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>We have been up and down to seek thee; for we are</line>
            <line>high-proof melancholy and would fain have it beaten</line>
            <line>away. Wilt thou use thy wit?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>It is in my scabbard: shall I draw it?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>Dost thou wear thy wit by thy side?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Never any did so, though very many have been beside</line>
            <line>their wit. I will bid thee draw, as we do the</line>
            <line>minstrels; draw, to pleasure us.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>As I am an honest man, he looks pale. Art thou</line>
            <line>sick, or angry?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>What, courage, man! What though care killed a cat,</line>
            <line>thou hast mettle enough in thee to kill care.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Sir, I shall meet your wit in the career, and you</line>
            <line>charge it against me. I pray you choose another subject.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Nay, then, give him another staff: this last was</line>
            <line>broke cross.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>By this light, he changes more and more: I think</line>
            <line>he be angry indeed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>If he be, he knows how to turn his girdle.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Shall I speak a word in your ear?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>God bless me from a challenge!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside to CLAUDIO</stagedir>  You are a villain; I jest not:</line>
            <line>I will make it good how you dare, with what you</line>
            <line>dare, and when you dare. Do me right, or I will</line>
            <line>protest your cowardice. You have killed a sweet</line>
            <line>lady, and her death shall fall heavy on you. Let me</line>
            <line>hear from you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Well, I will meet you, so I may have good cheer.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>What, a feast, a feast?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>I' faith, I thank him; he hath bid me to a calf's</line>
            <line>head and a capon; the which if I do not carve most</line>
            <line>curiously, say my knife's naught. Shall I not find</line>
            <line>a woodcock too?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Sir, your wit ambles well; it goes easily.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>I'll tell thee how Beatrice praised thy wit the</line>
            <line>other day. I said, thou hadst a fine wit: 'True,'</line>
            <line>said she, 'a fine little one.' 'No,' said I, 'a</line>
            <line>great wit:' 'Right,' says she, 'a great gross one.'</line>
            <line>'Nay,' said I, 'a good wit:' 'Just,' said she, 'it</line>
            <line>hurts nobody.' 'Nay,' said I, 'the gentleman</line>
            <line>is wise:' 'Certain,' said she, 'a wise gentleman.'</line>
            <line>'Nay,' said I, 'he hath the tongues:' 'That I</line>
            <line>believe,' said she, 'for he swore a thing to me on</line>
            <line>Monday night, which he forswore on Tuesday morning;</line>
            <line>there's a double tongue; there's two tongues.' Thus</line>
            <line>did she, an hour together, transshape thy particular</line>
            <line>virtues: yet at last she concluded with a sigh, thou</line>
            <line>wast the properest man in Italy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>For the which she wept heartily and said she cared</line>
            <line>not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>Yea, that she did: but yet, for all that, an if she</line>
            <line>did not hate him deadly, she would love him dearly:</line>
            <line>the old man's daughter told us all.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>All, all; and, moreover, God saw him when he was</line>
            <line>hid in the garden.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>But when shall we set the savage bull's horns on</line>
            <line>the sensible Benedick's head?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Yea, and text underneath, 'Here dwells Benedick the</line>
            <line>married man'?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Fare you well, boy: you know my mind. I will leave</line>
            <line>you now to your gossip-like humour: you break jests</line>
            <line>as braggarts do their blades, which God be thanked,</line>
            <line>hurt not. My lord, for your many courtesies I thank</line>
            <line>you: I must discontinue your company: your brother</line>
            <line>the bastard is fled from Messina: you have among</line>
            <line>you killed a sweet and innocent lady. For my Lord</line>
            <line>Lackbeard there, he and I shall meet: and, till</line>
            <line>then, peace be with him.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>He is in earnest.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>In most profound earnest; and, I'll warrant you, for</line>
            <line>the love of Beatrice.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>And hath challenged thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Most sincerely.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>What a pretty thing man is when he goes in his</line>
            <line>doublet and hose and leaves off his wit!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>He is then a giant to an ape; but then is an ape a</line>
            <line>doctor to such a man.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>But, soft you, let me be: pluck up, my heart, and</line>
            <line>be sad. Did he not say, my brother was fled?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter DOGBERRY, VERGES, and the Watch, with CONRADE
and BORACHIO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOGBERRY</speaker>
            <line>Come you, sir: if justice cannot tame you, she</line>
            <line>shall ne'er weigh more reasons in her balance: nay,</line>
            <line>an you be a cursing hypocrite once, you must be looked to.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>How now? two of my brother's men bound! Borachio</line>
            <line>one!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Hearken after their offence, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>Officers, what offence have these men done?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOGBERRY</speaker>
            <line>Marry, sir, they have committed false report;</line>
            <line>moreover, they have spoken untruths; secondarily,</line>
            <line>they are slanders; sixth and lastly, they have</line>
            <line>belied a lady; thirdly, they have verified unjust</line>
            <line>things; and, to conclude, they are lying knaves.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>First, I ask thee what they have done; thirdly, I</line>
            <line>ask thee what's their offence; sixth and lastly, why</line>
            <line>they are committed; and, to conclude, what you lay</line>
            <line>to their charge.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Rightly reasoned, and in his own division: and, by</line>
            <line>my troth, there's one meaning well suited.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>Who have you offended, masters, that you are thus</line>
            <line>bound to your answer? this learned constable is</line>
            <line>too cunning to be understood: what's your offence?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BORACHIO</speaker>
            <line>Sweet prince, let me go no farther to mine answer:</line>
            <line>do you hear me, and let this count kill me. I have</line>
            <line>deceived even your very eyes: what your wisdoms</line>
            <line>could not discover, these shallow fools have brought</line>
            <line>to light: who in the night overheard me confessing</line>
            <line>to this man how Don John your brother incensed me</line>
            <line>to slander the Lady Hero, how you were brought into</line>
            <line>the orchard and saw me court Margaret in Hero's</line>
            <line>garments, how you disgraced her, when you should</line>
            <line>marry her: my villany they have upon record; which</line>
            <line>I had rather seal with my death than repeat over</line>
            <line>to my shame. The lady is dead upon mine and my</line>
            <line>master's false accusation; and, briefly, I desire</line>
            <line>nothing but the reward of a villain.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>Runs not this speech like iron through your blood?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>I have drunk poison whiles he utter'd it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>But did my brother set thee on to this?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BORACHIO</speaker>
            <line>Yea, and paid me richly for the practise of it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>He is composed and framed of treachery:</line>
            <line>And fled he is upon this villany.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Sweet Hero! now thy image doth appear</line>
            <line>In the rare semblance that I loved it first.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOGBERRY</speaker>
            <line>Come, bring away the plaintiffs: by this time our</line>
            <line>sexton hath reformed Signior Leonato of the matter:</line>
            <line>and, masters, do not forget to specify, when time</line>
            <line>and place shall serve, that I am an ass.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VERGES</speaker>
            <line>Here, here comes master Signior Leonato, and the</line>
            <line>Sexton too.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter LEONATO and ANTONIO, with the Sexton</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>Which is the villain? let me see his eyes,</line>
            <line>That, when I note another man like him,</line>
            <line>I may avoid him: which of these is he?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BORACHIO</speaker>
            <line>If you would know your wronger, look on me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>Art thou the slave that with thy breath hast kill'd</line>
            <line>Mine innocent child?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BORACHIO</speaker>
            <line>Yea, even I alone.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>No, not so, villain; thou beliest thyself:</line>
            <line>Here stand a pair of honourable men;</line>
            <line>A third is fled, that had a hand in it.</line>
            <line>I thank you, princes, for my daughter's death:</line>
            <line>Record it with your high and worthy deeds:</line>
            <line>'Twas bravely done, if you bethink you of it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>I know not how to pray your patience;</line>
            <line>Yet I must speak. Choose your revenge yourself;</line>
            <line>Impose me to what penance your invention</line>
            <line>Can lay upon my sin: yet sinn'd I not</line>
            <line>But in mistaking.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>By my soul, nor I:</line>
            <line>And yet, to satisfy this good old man,</line>
            <line>I would bend under any heavy weight</line>
            <line>That he'll enjoin me to.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>I cannot bid you bid my daughter live;</line>
            <line>That were impossible: but, I pray you both,</line>
            <line>Possess the people in Messina here</line>
            <line>How innocent she died; and if your love</line>
            <line>Can labour ought in sad invention,</line>
            <line>Hang her an epitaph upon her tomb</line>
            <line>And sing it to her bones, sing it to-night:</line>
            <line>To-morrow morning come you to my house,</line>
            <line>And since you could not be my son-in-law,</line>
            <line>Be yet my nephew: my brother hath a daughter,</line>
            <line>Almost the copy of my child that's dead,</line>
            <line>And she alone is heir to both of us:</line>
            <line>Give her the right you should have given her cousin,</line>
            <line>And so dies my revenge.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>O noble sir,</line>
            <line>Your over-kindness doth wring tears from me!</line>
            <line>I do embrace your offer; and dispose</line>
            <line>For henceforth of poor Claudio.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>To-morrow then I will expect your coming;</line>
            <line>To-night I take my leave. This naughty man</line>
            <line>Shall face to face be brought to Margaret,</line>
            <line>Who I believe was pack'd in all this wrong,</line>
            <line>Hired to it by your brother.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BORACHIO</speaker>
            <line>No, by my soul, she was not,</line>
            <line>Nor knew not what she did when she spoke to me,</line>
            <line>But always hath been just and virtuous</line>
            <line>In any thing that I do know by her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOGBERRY</speaker>
            <line>Moreover, sir, which indeed is not under white and</line>
            <line>black, this plaintiff here, the offender, did call</line>
            <line>me ass: I beseech you, let it be remembered in his</line>
            <line>punishment. And also, the watch heard them talk of</line>
            <line>one Deformed: they say be wears a key in his ear and</line>
            <line>a lock hanging by it, and borrows money in God's</line>
            <line>name, the which he hath used so long and never paid</line>
            <line>that now men grow hard-hearted and will lend nothing</line>
            <line>for God's sake: pray you, examine him upon that point.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>I thank thee for thy care and honest pains.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOGBERRY</speaker>
            <line>Your worship speaks like a most thankful and</line>
            <line>reverend youth; and I praise God for you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>There's for thy pains.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOGBERRY</speaker>
            <line>God save the foundation!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>Go, I discharge thee of thy prisoner, and I thank thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOGBERRY</speaker>
            <line>I leave an arrant knave with your worship; which I</line>
            <line>beseech your worship to correct yourself, for the</line>
            <line>example of others. God keep your worship! I wish</line>
            <line>your worship well; God restore you to health! I</line>
            <line>humbly give you leave to depart; and if a merry</line>
            <line>meeting may be wished, God prohibit it! Come, neighbour.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt DOGBERRY and VERGES</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>Until to-morrow morning, lords, farewell.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>Farewell, my lords: we look for you to-morrow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>We will not fail.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>To-night I'll mourn with Hero.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>To the Watch</stagedir>  Bring you these fellows on. We'll</line>
            <line>talk with Margaret,</line>
            <line>How her acquaintance grew with this lewd fellow.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt, severally</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  LEONATO'S garden.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter BENEDICK and MARGARET, meeting</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Pray thee, sweet Mistress Margaret, deserve well at</line>
            <line>my hands by helping me to the speech of Beatrice.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Will you then write me a sonnet in praise of my beauty?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>In so high a style, Margaret, that no man living</line>
            <line>shall come over it; for, in most comely truth, thou</line>
            <line>deservest it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>To have no man come over me! why, shall I always</line>
            <line>keep below stairs?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Thy wit is as quick as the greyhound's mouth; it catches.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>And yours as blunt as the fencer's foils, which hit,</line>
            <line>but hurt not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>A most manly wit, Margaret; it will not hurt a</line>
            <line>woman: and so, I pray thee, call Beatrice: I give</line>
            <line>thee the bucklers.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Give us the swords; we have bucklers of our own.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>If you use them, Margaret, you must put in the</line>
            <line>pikes with a vice; and they are dangerous weapons for maids.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Well, I will call Beatrice to you, who I think hath legs.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>And therefore will come.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit MARGARET</stagedir>
            <stagedir>Sings</stagedir>
            <line>The god of love,</line>
            <line>That sits above,</line>
            <line>And knows me, and knows me,</line>
            <line>How pitiful I deserve,--</line>
            <line>I mean in singing; but in loving, Leander the good</line>
            <line>swimmer, Troilus the first employer of panders, and</line>
            <line>a whole bookful of these quondam carpet-mangers,</line>
            <line>whose names yet run smoothly in the even road of a</line>
            <line>blank verse, why, they were never so truly turned</line>
            <line>over and over as my poor self in love. Marry, I</line>
            <line>cannot show it in rhyme; I have tried: I can find</line>
            <line>out no rhyme to 'lady' but 'baby,' an innocent</line>
            <line>rhyme; for 'scorn,' 'horn,' a hard rhyme; for,</line>
            <line>'school,' 'fool,' a babbling rhyme; very ominous</line>
            <line>endings: no, I was not born under a rhyming planet,</line>
            <line>nor I cannot woo in festival terms.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter BEATRICE</stagedir>
            <line>Sweet Beatrice, wouldst thou come when I called thee?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>Yea, signior, and depart when you bid me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>O, stay but till then!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>'Then' is spoken; fare you well now: and yet, ere</line>
            <line>I go, let me go with that I came; which is, with</line>
            <line>knowing what hath passed between you and Claudio.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Only foul words; and thereupon I will kiss thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>Foul words is but foul wind, and foul wind is but</line>
            <line>foul breath, and foul breath is noisome; therefore I</line>
            <line>will depart unkissed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Thou hast frighted the word out of his right sense,</line>
            <line>so forcible is thy wit. But I must tell thee</line>
            <line>plainly, Claudio undergoes my challenge; and either</line>
            <line>I must shortly hear from him, or I will subscribe</line>
            <line>him a coward. And, I pray thee now, tell me for</line>
            <line>which of my bad parts didst thou first fall in love with me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>For them all together; which maintained so politic</line>
            <line>a state of evil that they will not admit any good</line>
            <line>part to intermingle with them. But for which of my</line>
            <line>good parts did you first suffer love for me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Suffer love! a good epithet! I do suffer love</line>
            <line>indeed, for I love thee against my will.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>In spite of your heart, I think; alas, poor heart!</line>
            <line>If you spite it for my sake, I will spite it for</line>
            <line>yours; for I will never love that which my friend hates.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Thou and I are too wise to woo peaceably.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>It appears not in this confession: there's not one</line>
            <line>wise man among twenty that will praise himself.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>An old, an old instance, Beatrice, that lived in</line>
            <line>the lime of good neighbours. If a man do not erect</line>
            <line>in this age his own tomb ere he dies, he shall live</line>
            <line>no longer in monument than the bell rings and the</line>
            <line>widow weeps.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>And how long is that, think you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Question: why, an hour in clamour and a quarter in</line>
            <line>rheum: therefore is it most expedient for the</line>
            <line>wise, if Don Worm, his conscience, find no</line>
            <line>impediment to the contrary, to be the trumpet of his</line>
            <line>own virtues, as I am to myself. So much for</line>
            <line>praising myself, who, I myself will bear witness, is</line>
            <line>praiseworthy: and now tell me, how doth your cousin?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>Very ill.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>And how do you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>Very ill too.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Serve God, love me and mend. There will I leave</line>
            <line>you too, for here comes one in haste.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter URSULA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>URSULA</speaker>
            <line>Madam, you must come to your uncle. Yonder's old</line>
            <line>coil at home: it is proved my Lady Hero hath been</line>
            <line>falsely accused, the prince and Claudio mightily</line>
            <line>abused; and Don John is the author of all, who is</line>
            <line>fed and gone. Will you come presently?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>Will you go hear this news, signior?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>I will live in thy heart, die in thy lap, and be</line>
            <line>buried in thy eyes; and moreover I will go with</line>
            <line>thee to thy uncle's.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  A church.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter DON PEDRO, CLAUDIO, and three or four
with tapers</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Is this the monument of Leonato?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord</speaker>
            <line>It is, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Reading out of a scroll</stagedir>
            </line>
            <line>Done to death by slanderous tongues</line>
            <line>Was the Hero that here lies:</line>
            <line>Death, in guerdon of her wrongs,</line>
            <line>Gives her fame which never dies.</line>
            <line>So the life that died with shame</line>
            <line>Lives in death with glorious fame.</line>
            <line>Hang thou there upon the tomb,</line>
            <line>Praising her when I am dumb.</line>
            <line>Now, music, sound, and sing your solemn hymn.</line>
            <subhead>SONG.</subhead>
            <line>Pardon, goddess of the night,</line>
            <line>Those that slew thy virgin knight;</line>
            <line>For the which, with songs of woe,</line>
            <line>Round about her tomb they go.</line>
            <line>Midnight, assist our moan;</line>
            <line>Help us to sigh and groan,</line>
            <line>Heavily, heavily:</line>
            <line>Graves, yawn and yield your dead,</line>
            <line>Till death be uttered,</line>
            <line>Heavily, heavily.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Now, unto thy bones good night!</line>
            <line>Yearly will I do this rite.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>Good morrow, masters; put your torches out:</line>
            <line>The wolves have prey'd; and look, the gentle day,</line>
            <line>Before the wheels of Phoebus, round about</line>
            <line>Dapples the drowsy east with spots of grey.</line>
            <line>Thanks to you all, and leave us: fare you well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Good morrow, masters: each his several way.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>Come, let us hence, and put on other weeds;</line>
            <line>And then to Leonato's we will go.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>And Hymen now with luckier issue speed's</line>
            <line>Than this for whom we render'd up this woe.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-4">
      <title>SCENE IV.  A room in LEONATO'S house.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter LEONATO, ANTONIO, BENEDICK, BEATRICE,
MARGARET, URSULA, FRIAR FRANCIS, and HERO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FRIAR FRANCIS</speaker>
            <line>Did I not tell you she was innocent?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>So are the prince and Claudio, who accused her</line>
            <line>Upon the error that you heard debated:</line>
            <line>But Margaret was in some fault for this,</line>
            <line>Although against her will, as it appears</line>
            <line>In the true course of all the question.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>Well, I am glad that all things sort so well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>And so am I, being else by faith enforced</line>
            <line>To call young Claudio to a reckoning for it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>Well, daughter, and you gentle-women all,</line>
            <line>Withdraw into a chamber by yourselves,</line>
            <line>And when I send for you, come hither mask'd.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt Ladies</stagedir>
            <line>The prince and Claudio promised by this hour</line>
            <line>To visit me. You know your office, brother:</line>
            <line>You must be father to your brother's daughter</line>
            <line>And give her to young Claudio.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>Which I will do with confirm'd countenance.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Friar, I must entreat your pains, I think.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FRIAR FRANCIS</speaker>
            <line>To do what, signior?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>To bind me, or undo me; one of them.</line>
            <line>Signior Leonato, truth it is, good signior,</line>
            <line>Your niece regards me with an eye of favour.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>That eye my daughter lent her: 'tis most true.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>And I do with an eye of love requite her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>The sight whereof I think you had from me,</line>
            <line>From Claudio and the prince: but what's your will?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Your answer, sir, is enigmatical:</line>
            <line>But, for my will, my will is your good will</line>
            <line>May stand with ours, this day to be conjoin'd</line>
            <line>In the state of honourable marriage:</line>
            <line>In which, good friar, I shall desire your help.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>My heart is with your liking.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FRIAR FRANCIS</speaker>
            <line>And my help.</line>
            <line>Here comes the prince and Claudio.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter DON PEDRO and CLAUDIO, and two or
three others</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>Good morrow to this fair assembly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>Good morrow, prince; good morrow, Claudio:</line>
            <line>We here attend you. Are you yet determined</line>
            <line>To-day to marry with my brother's daughter?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>I'll hold my mind, were she an Ethiope.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>Call her forth, brother; here's the friar ready.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit ANTONIO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>Good morrow, Benedick. Why, what's the matter,</line>
            <line>That you have such a February face,</line>
            <line>So full of frost, of storm and cloudiness?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>I think he thinks upon the savage bull.</line>
            <line>Tush, fear not, man; we'll tip thy horns with gold</line>
            <line>And all Europa shall rejoice at thee,</line>
            <line>As once Europa did at lusty Jove,</line>
            <line>When he would play the noble beast in love.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Bull Jove, sir, had an amiable low;</line>
            <line>And some such strange bull leap'd your father's cow,</line>
            <line>And got a calf in that same noble feat</line>
            <line>Much like to you, for you have just his bleat.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>For this I owe you: here comes other reckonings.</line>
            <stagedir>Re-enter ANTONIO, with the Ladies masked</stagedir>
            <line>Which is the lady I must seize upon?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>This same is she, and I do give you her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Why, then she's mine. Sweet, let me see your face.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>No, that you shall not, till you take her hand</line>
            <line>Before this friar and swear to marry her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Give me your hand: before this holy friar,</line>
            <line>I am your husband, if you like of me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERO</speaker>
            <line>And when I lived, I was your other wife:</line>
            <stagedir>Unmasking</stagedir>
            <line>And when you loved, you were my other husband.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Another Hero!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERO</speaker>
            <line>Nothing certainer:</line>
            <line>One Hero died defiled, but I do live,</line>
            <line>And surely as I live, I am a maid.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>The former Hero! Hero that is dead!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>She died, my lord, but whiles her slander lived.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FRIAR FRANCIS</speaker>
            <line>All this amazement can I qualify:</line>
            <line>When after that the holy rites are ended,</line>
            <line>I'll tell you largely of fair Hero's death:</line>
            <line>Meantime let wonder seem familiar,</line>
            <line>And to the chapel let us presently.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Soft and fair, friar. Which is Beatrice?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Unmasking</stagedir>  I answer to that name. What is your will?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Do not you love me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>Why, no; no more than reason.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Why, then your uncle and the prince and Claudio</line>
            <line>Have been deceived; they swore you did.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>Do not you love me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Troth, no; no more than reason.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>Why, then my cousin Margaret and Ursula</line>
            <line>Are much deceived; for they did swear you did.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>They swore that you were almost sick for me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>They swore that you were well-nigh dead for me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>'Tis no such matter. Then you do not love me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>No, truly, but in friendly recompense.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>Come, cousin, I am sure you love the gentleman.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>And I'll be sworn upon't that he loves her;</line>
            <line>For here's a paper written in his hand,</line>
            <line>A halting sonnet of his own pure brain,</line>
            <line>Fashion'd to Beatrice.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERO</speaker>
            <line>And here's another</line>
            <line>Writ in my cousin's hand, stolen from her pocket,</line>
            <line>Containing her affection unto Benedick.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>A miracle! here's our own hands against our hearts.</line>
            <line>Come, I will have thee; but, by this light, I take</line>
            <line>thee for pity.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>I would not deny you; but, by this good day, I yield</line>
            <line>upon great persuasion; and partly to save your life,</line>
            <line>for I was told you were in a consumption.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Peace! I will stop your mouth.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Kissing her</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>How dost thou, Benedick, the married man?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>I'll tell thee what, prince; a college of</line>
            <line>wit-crackers cannot flout me out of my humour. Dost</line>
            <line>thou think I  care for a satire or an epigram? No:</line>
            <line>if a man will be beaten with brains, a' shall wear</line>
            <line>nothing handsome about him. In brief, since I do</line>
            <line>purpose to marry, I will think nothing to any</line>
            <line>purpose that the world can say against it; and</line>
            <line>therefore never flout at me for what I have said</line>
            <line>against it; for man is a giddy thing, and this is my</line>
            <line>conclusion. For thy part, Claudio, I did think to</line>
            <line>have beaten thee, but in that thou art like to be my</line>
            <line>kinsman, live unbruised and love my cousin.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>I had well hoped thou wouldst have denied Beatrice,</line>
            <line>that I might have cudgelled thee out of thy single</line>
            <line>life, to make thee a double-dealer; which, out of</line>
            <line>question, thou wilt be, if my cousin do not look</line>
            <line>exceedingly narrowly to thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Come, come, we are friends: let's have a dance ere</line>
            <line>we are married, that we may lighten our own hearts</line>
            <line>and our wives' heels.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>We'll have dancing afterward.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>First, of my word; therefore play, music. Prince,</line>
            <line>thou art sad; get thee a wife, get thee a wife:</line>
            <line>there is no staff more reverend than one tipped with horn.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter a Messenger</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>My lord, your brother John is ta'en in flight,</line>
            <line>And brought with armed men back to Messina.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Think not on him till to-morrow:</line>
            <line>I'll devise thee brave punishments for him.</line>
            <line>Strike up, pipers.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Dance</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>