<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net/doctypes/dita/shakespear/dtd/act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-2">
   <title>ACT II</title>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  A hall in LEONATO'S house.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter LEONATO, ANTONIO, HERO, BEATRICE, and others</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>Was not Count John here at supper?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>I saw him not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>How tartly that gentleman looks! I never can see</line>
            <line>him but I am heart-burned an hour after.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERO</speaker>
            <line>He is of a very melancholy disposition.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>He were an excellent man that were made just in the</line>
            <line>midway between him and Benedick: the one is too</line>
            <line>like an image and says nothing, and the other too</line>
            <line>like my lady's eldest son, evermore tattling.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>Then half Signior Benedick's tongue in Count John's</line>
            <line>mouth, and half Count John's melancholy in Signior</line>
            <line>Benedick's face,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>With a good leg and a good foot, uncle, and money</line>
            <line>enough in his purse, such a man would win any woman</line>
            <line>in the world, if a' could get her good-will.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>By my troth, niece, thou wilt never get thee a</line>
            <line>husband, if thou be so shrewd of thy tongue.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>In faith, she's too curst.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>Too curst is more than curst: I shall lessen God's</line>
            <line>sending that way; for it is said, 'God sends a curst</line>
            <line>cow short horns;' but to a cow too curst he sends none.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>So, by being too curst, God will send you no horns.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>Just, if he send me no husband; for the which</line>
            <line>blessing I am at him upon my knees every morning and</line>
            <line>evening. Lord, I could not endure a husband with a</line>
            <line>beard on his face: I had rather lie in the woollen.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>You may light on a husband that hath no beard.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>What should I do with him? dress him in my apparel</line>
            <line>and make him my waiting-gentlewoman? He that hath a</line>
            <line>beard is more than a youth, and he that hath no</line>
            <line>beard is less than a man: and he that is more than</line>
            <line>a youth is not for me, and he that is less than a</line>
            <line>man, I am not for him: therefore, I will even take</line>
            <line>sixpence in earnest of the bear-ward, and lead his</line>
            <line>apes into hell.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>Well, then, go you into hell?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>No, but to the gate; and there will the devil meet</line>
            <line>me, like an old cuckold, with horns on his head, and</line>
            <line>say 'Get you to heaven, Beatrice, get you to</line>
            <line>heaven; here's no place for you maids:' so deliver</line>
            <line>I up my apes, and away to Saint Peter for the</line>
            <line>heavens; he shows me where the bachelors sit, and</line>
            <line>there live we as merry as the day is long.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>To HERO</stagedir>  Well, niece, I trust you will be ruled</line>
            <line>by your father.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>Yes, faith; it is my cousin's duty to make curtsy</line>
            <line>and say 'Father, as it please you.' But yet for all</line>
            <line>that, cousin, let him be a handsome fellow, or else</line>
            <line>make another curtsy and say 'Father, as it please</line>
            <line>me.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>Well, niece, I hope to see you one day fitted with a husband.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>Not till God make men of some other metal than</line>
            <line>earth. Would it not grieve a woman to be</line>
            <line>overmastered with a pierce of valiant dust? to make</line>
            <line>an account of her life to a clod of wayward marl?</line>
            <line>No, uncle, I'll none: Adam's sons are my brethren;</line>
            <line>and, truly, I hold it a sin to match in my kindred.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>Daughter, remember what I told you: if the prince</line>
            <line>do solicit you in that kind, you know your answer.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>The fault will be in the music, cousin, if you be</line>
            <line>not wooed in good time: if the prince be too</line>
            <line>important, tell him there is measure in every thing</line>
            <line>and so dance out the answer. For, hear me, Hero:</line>
            <line>wooing, wedding, and repenting, is as a Scotch jig,</line>
            <line>a measure, and a cinque pace: the first suit is hot</line>
            <line>and hasty, like a Scotch jig, and full as</line>
            <line>fantastical; the wedding, mannerly-modest, as a</line>
            <line>measure, full of state and ancientry; and then comes</line>
            <line>repentance and, with his bad legs, falls into the</line>
            <line>cinque pace faster and faster, till he sink into his grave.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>Cousin, you apprehend passing shrewdly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>I have a good eye, uncle; I can see a church by daylight.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>The revellers are entering, brother: make good room.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>All put on their masks</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Enter DON PEDRO, CLAUDIO, BENEDICK, BALTHASAR,
DON JOHN, BORACHIO, MARGARET, URSULA and others, masked</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>Lady, will you walk about with your friend?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERO</speaker>
            <line>So you walk softly and look sweetly and say nothing,</line>
            <line>I am yours for the walk; and especially when I walk away.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>With me in your company?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERO</speaker>
            <line>I may say so, when I please.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>And when please you to say so?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERO</speaker>
            <line>When I like your favour; for God defend the lute</line>
            <line>should be like the case!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>My visor is Philemon's roof; within the house is Jove.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERO</speaker>
            <line>Why, then, your visor should be thatched.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>Speak low, if you speak love.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Drawing her aside</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BALTHASAR</speaker>
            <line>Well, I would you did like me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>So would not I, for your own sake; for I have many</line>
            <line>ill-qualities.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BALTHASAR</speaker>
            <line>Which is one?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>I say my prayers aloud.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BALTHASAR</speaker>
            <line>I love you the better: the hearers may cry, Amen.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>God match me with a good dancer!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BALTHASAR</speaker>
            <line>Amen.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>And God keep him out of my sight when the dance is</line>
            <line>done! Answer, clerk.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BALTHASAR</speaker>
            <line>No more words: the clerk is answered.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>URSULA</speaker>
            <line>I know you well enough; you are Signior Antonio.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>At a word, I am not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>URSULA</speaker>
            <line>I know you by the waggling of your head.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>To tell you true, I counterfeit him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>URSULA</speaker>
            <line>You could never do him so ill-well, unless you were</line>
            <line>the very man. Here's his dry hand up and down: you</line>
            <line>are he, you are he.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>At a word, I am not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>URSULA</speaker>
            <line>Come, come, do you think I do not know you by your</line>
            <line>excellent wit? can virtue hide itself? Go to,</line>
            <line>mum, you are he: graces will appear, and there's an</line>
            <line>end.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>Will you not tell me who told you so?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>No, you shall pardon me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>Nor will you not tell me who you are?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Not now.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>That I was disdainful, and that I had my good wit</line>
            <line>out of the 'Hundred Merry Tales:'--well this was</line>
            <line>Signior Benedick that said so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>What's he?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>I am sure you know him well enough.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Not I, believe me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>Did he never make you laugh?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>I pray you, what is he?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>Why, he is the prince's jester: a very dull fool;</line>
            <line>only his gift is in devising impossible slanders:</line>
            <line>none but libertines delight in him; and the</line>
            <line>commendation is not in his wit, but in his villany;</line>
            <line>for he both pleases men and angers them, and then</line>
            <line>they laugh at him and beat him. I am sure he is in</line>
            <line>the fleet: I would he had boarded me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>When I know the gentleman, I'll tell him what you say.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>Do, do: he'll but break a comparison or two on me;</line>
            <line>which, peradventure not marked or not laughed at,</line>
            <line>strikes him into melancholy; and then there's a</line>
            <line>partridge wing saved, for the fool will eat no</line>
            <line>supper that night.</line>
            <stagedir>Music</stagedir>
            <line>We must follow the leaders.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>In every good thing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>Nay, if they lead to any ill, I will leave them at</line>
            <line>the next turning.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Dance. Then exeunt all except DON JOHN, BORACHIO,
and CLAUDIO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON JOHN</speaker>
            <line>Sure my brother is amorous on Hero and hath</line>
            <line>withdrawn her father to break with him about it.</line>
            <line>The ladies follow her and but one visor remains.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BORACHIO</speaker>
            <line>And that is Claudio: I know him by his bearing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON JOHN</speaker>
            <line>Are not you Signior Benedick?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>You know me well; I am he.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON JOHN</speaker>
            <line>Signior, you are very near my brother in his love:</line>
            <line>he is enamoured on Hero; I pray you, dissuade him</line>
            <line>from her: she is no equal for his birth: you may</line>
            <line>do the part of an honest man in it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>How know you he loves her?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON JOHN</speaker>
            <line>I heard him swear his affection.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BORACHIO</speaker>
            <line>So did I too; and he swore he would marry her to-night.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON JOHN</speaker>
            <line>Come, let us to the banquet.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt DON JOHN and BORACHIO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Thus answer I in the name of Benedick,</line>
            <line>But hear these ill news with the ears of Claudio.</line>
            <line>'Tis certain so; the prince wooes for himself.</line>
            <line>Friendship is constant in all other things</line>
            <line>Save in the office and affairs of love:</line>
            <line>Therefore, all hearts in love use their own tongues;</line>
            <line>Let every eye negotiate for itself</line>
            <line>And trust no agent; for beauty is a witch</line>
            <line>Against whose charms faith melteth into blood.</line>
            <line>This is an accident of hourly proof,</line>
            <line>Which I mistrusted not. Farewell, therefore, Hero!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter BENEDICK</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Count Claudio?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Yea, the same.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Come, will you go with me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Whither?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Even to the next willow, about your own business,</line>
            <line>county. What fashion will you wear the garland of?</line>
            <line>about your neck, like an usurer's chain? or under</line>
            <line>your arm, like a lieutenant's scarf? You must wear</line>
            <line>it one way, for the prince hath got your Hero.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>I wish him joy of her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Why, that's spoken like an honest drovier: so they</line>
            <line>sell bullocks. But did you think the prince would</line>
            <line>have served you thus?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>I pray you, leave me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Ho! now you strike like the blind man: 'twas the</line>
            <line>boy that stole your meat, and you'll beat the post.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>If it will not be, I'll leave you.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Alas, poor hurt fowl! now will he creep into sedges.</line>
            <line>But that my Lady Beatrice should know me, and not</line>
            <line>know me! The prince's fool! Ha? It may be I go</line>
            <line>under that title because I am merry. Yea, but so I</line>
            <line>am apt to do myself wrong; I am not so reputed: it</line>
            <line>is the base, though bitter, disposition of Beatrice</line>
            <line>that puts the world into her person and so gives me</line>
            <line>out. Well, I'll be revenged as I may.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter DON PEDRO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>Now, signior, where's the count? did you see him?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Troth, my lord, I have played the part of Lady Fame.</line>
            <line>I found him here as melancholy as a lodge in a</line>
            <line>warren: I told him, and I think I told him true,</line>
            <line>that your grace had got the good will of this young</line>
            <line>lady; and I offered him my company to a willow-tree,</line>
            <line>either to make him a garland, as being forsaken, or</line>
            <line>to bind him up a rod, as being worthy to be whipped.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>To be whipped! What's his fault?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>The flat transgression of a schoolboy, who, being</line>
            <line>overjoyed with finding a birds' nest, shows it his</line>
            <line>companion, and he steals it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>Wilt thou make a trust a transgression? The</line>
            <line>transgression is in the stealer.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Yet it had not been amiss the rod had been made,</line>
            <line>and the garland too; for the garland he might have</line>
            <line>worn himself, and the rod he might have bestowed on</line>
            <line>you, who, as I take it, have stolen his birds' nest.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>I will but teach them to sing, and restore them to</line>
            <line>the owner.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>If their singing answer your saying, by my faith,</line>
            <line>you say honestly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>The Lady Beatrice hath a quarrel to you: the</line>
            <line>gentleman that danced with her told her she is much</line>
            <line>wronged by you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>O, she misused me past the endurance of a block!</line>
            <line>an oak but with one green leaf on it would have</line>
            <line>answered her; my very visor began to assume life and</line>
            <line>scold with her. She told me, not thinking I had been</line>
            <line>myself, that I was the prince's jester, that I was</line>
            <line>duller than a great thaw; huddling jest upon jest</line>
            <line>with such impossible conveyance upon me that I stood</line>
            <line>like a man at a mark, with a whole army shooting at</line>
            <line>me. She speaks poniards, and every word stabs:</line>
            <line>if her breath were as terrible as her terminations,</line>
            <line>there were no living near her; she would infect to</line>
            <line>the north star. I would not marry her, though she</line>
            <line>were endowed with all that Adam bad left him before</line>
            <line>he transgressed: she would have made Hercules have</line>
            <line>turned spit, yea, and have cleft his club to make</line>
            <line>the fire too. Come, talk not of her: you shall find</line>
            <line>her the infernal Ate in good apparel. I would to God</line>
            <line>some scholar would conjure her; for certainly, while</line>
            <line>she is here, a man may live as quiet in hell as in a</line>
            <line>sanctuary; and people sin upon purpose, because they</line>
            <line>would go thither; so, indeed, all disquiet, horror</line>
            <line>and perturbation follows her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>Look, here she comes.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter CLAUDIO, BEATRICE, HERO, and LEONATO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Will your grace command me any service to the</line>
            <line>world's end? I will go on the slightest errand now</line>
            <line>to the Antipodes that you can devise to send me on;</line>
            <line>I will fetch you a tooth-picker now from the</line>
            <line>furthest inch of Asia, bring you the length of</line>
            <line>Prester John's foot, fetch you a hair off the great</line>
            <line>Cham's beard, do you any embassage to the Pigmies,</line>
            <line>rather than hold three words' conference with this</line>
            <line>harpy. You have no employment for me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>None, but to desire your good company.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>O God, sir, here's a dish I love not: I cannot</line>
            <line>endure my Lady Tongue.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>Come, lady, come; you have lost the heart of</line>
            <line>Signior Benedick.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>Indeed, my lord, he lent it me awhile; and I gave</line>
            <line>him use for it, a double heart for his single one:</line>
            <line>marry, once before he won it of me with false dice,</line>
            <line>therefore your grace may well say I have lost it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>You have put him down, lady, you have put him down.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>So I would not he should do me, my lord, lest I</line>
            <line>should prove the mother of fools. I have brought</line>
            <line>Count Claudio, whom you sent me to seek.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>Why, how now, count! wherefore are you sad?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Not sad, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>How then? sick?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Neither, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>The count is neither sad, nor sick, nor merry, nor</line>
            <line>well; but civil count, civil as an orange, and</line>
            <line>something of that jealous complexion.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>I' faith, lady, I think your blazon to be true;</line>
            <line>though, I'll be sworn, if he be so, his conceit is</line>
            <line>false. Here, Claudio, I have wooed in thy name, and</line>
            <line>fair Hero is won: I have broke with her father,</line>
            <line>and his good will obtained: name the day of</line>
            <line>marriage, and God give thee joy!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>Count, take of me my daughter, and with her my</line>
            <line>fortunes: his grace hath made the match, and an</line>
            <line>grace say Amen to it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>Speak, count, 'tis your cue.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Silence is the perfectest herald of joy: I were</line>
            <line>but little happy, if I could say how much. Lady, as</line>
            <line>you are mine, I am yours: I give away myself for</line>
            <line>you and dote upon the exchange.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>Speak, cousin; or, if you cannot, stop his mouth</line>
            <line>with a kiss, and let not him speak neither.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>In faith, lady, you have a merry heart.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>Yea, my lord; I thank it, poor fool, it keeps on</line>
            <line>the windy side of care. My cousin tells him in his</line>
            <line>ear that he is in her heart.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>And so she doth, cousin.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>Good Lord, for alliance! Thus goes every one to the</line>
            <line>world but I, and I am sunburnt; I may sit in a</line>
            <line>corner and cry heigh-ho for a husband!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>Lady Beatrice, I will get you one.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>I would rather have one of your father's getting.</line>
            <line>Hath your grace ne'er a brother like you? Your</line>
            <line>father got excellent husbands, if a maid could come by them.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>Will you have me, lady?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>No, my lord, unless I might have another for</line>
            <line>working-days: your grace is too costly to wear</line>
            <line>every day. But, I beseech your grace, pardon me: I</line>
            <line>was born to speak all mirth and no matter.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>Your silence most offends me, and to be merry best</line>
            <line>becomes you; for, out of question, you were born in</line>
            <line>a merry hour.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>No, sure, my lord, my mother cried; but then there</line>
            <line>was a star danced, and under that was I born.</line>
            <line>Cousins, God give you joy!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>Niece, will you look to those things I told you of?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>I cry you mercy, uncle. By your grace's pardon.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>By my troth, a pleasant-spirited lady.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>There's little of the melancholy element in her, my</line>
            <line>lord: she is never sad but when she sleeps, and</line>
            <line>not ever sad then; for I have heard my daughter say,</line>
            <line>she hath often dreamed of unhappiness and waked</line>
            <line>herself with laughing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>She cannot endure to hear tell of a husband.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>O, by no means: she mocks all her wooers out of suit.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>She were an excellent wife for Benedict.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>O Lord, my lord, if they were but a week married,</line>
            <line>they would talk themselves mad.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>County Claudio, when mean you to go to church?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>To-morrow, my lord: time goes on crutches till love</line>
            <line>have all his rites.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>Not till Monday, my dear son, which is hence a just</line>
            <line>seven-night; and a time too brief, too, to have all</line>
            <line>things answer my mind.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>Come, you shake the head at so long a breathing:</line>
            <line>but, I warrant thee, Claudio, the time shall not go</line>
            <line>dully by us. I will in the interim undertake one of</line>
            <line>Hercules' labours; which is, to bring Signior</line>
            <line>Benedick and the Lady Beatrice into a mountain of</line>
            <line>affection the one with the other. I would fain have</line>
            <line>it a match, and I doubt not but to fashion it, if</line>
            <line>you three will but minister such assistance as I</line>
            <line>shall give you direction.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>My lord, I am for you, though it cost me ten</line>
            <line>nights' watchings.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>And I, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>And you too, gentle Hero?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERO</speaker>
            <line>I will do any modest office, my lord, to help my</line>
            <line>cousin to a good husband.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>And Benedick is not the unhopefullest husband that</line>
            <line>I know. Thus far can I praise him; he is of a noble</line>
            <line>strain, of approved valour and confirmed honesty. I</line>
            <line>will teach you how to humour your cousin, that she</line>
            <line>shall fall in love with Benedick; and I, with your</line>
            <line>two helps, will so practise on Benedick that, in</line>
            <line>despite of his quick wit and his queasy stomach, he</line>
            <line>shall fall in love with Beatrice. If we can do this,</line>
            <line>Cupid is no longer an archer: his glory shall be</line>
            <line>ours, for we are the only love-gods. Go in with me,</line>
            <line>and I will tell you my drift.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  The same.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter DON JOHN and BORACHIO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON JOHN</speaker>
            <line>It is so; the Count Claudio shall marry the</line>
            <line>daughter of Leonato.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BORACHIO</speaker>
            <line>Yea, my lord; but I can cross it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON JOHN</speaker>
            <line>Any bar, any cross, any impediment will be</line>
            <line>medicinable to me: I am sick in displeasure to him,</line>
            <line>and whatsoever comes athwart his affection ranges</line>
            <line>evenly with mine. How canst thou cross this marriage?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BORACHIO</speaker>
            <line>Not honestly, my lord; but so covertly that no</line>
            <line>dishonesty shall appear in me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON JOHN</speaker>
            <line>Show me briefly how.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BORACHIO</speaker>
            <line>I think I told your lordship a year since, how much</line>
            <line>I am in the favour of Margaret, the waiting</line>
            <line>gentlewoman to Hero.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON JOHN</speaker>
            <line>I remember.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BORACHIO</speaker>
            <line>I can, at any unseasonable instant of the night,</line>
            <line>appoint her to look out at her lady's chamber window.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON JOHN</speaker>
            <line>What life is in that, to be the death of this marriage?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BORACHIO</speaker>
            <line>The poison of that lies in you to temper. Go you to</line>
            <line>the prince your brother; spare not to tell him that</line>
            <line>he hath wronged his honour in marrying the renowned</line>
            <line>Claudio--whose estimation do you mightily hold</line>
            <line>up--to a contaminated stale, such a one as Hero.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON JOHN</speaker>
            <line>What proof shall I make of that?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BORACHIO</speaker>
            <line>Proof enough to misuse the prince, to vex Claudio,</line>
            <line>to undo Hero and kill Leonato. Look you for any</line>
            <line>other issue?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON JOHN</speaker>
            <line>Only to despite them, I will endeavour any thing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BORACHIO</speaker>
            <line>Go, then; find me a meet hour to draw Don Pedro and</line>
            <line>the Count Claudio alone: tell them that you know</line>
            <line>that Hero loves me; intend a kind of zeal both to the</line>
            <line>prince and Claudio, as,--in love of your brother's</line>
            <line>honour, who hath made this match, and his friend's</line>
            <line>reputation, who is thus like to be cozened with the</line>
            <line>semblance of a maid,--that you have discovered</line>
            <line>thus. They will scarcely believe this without trial:</line>
            <line>offer them instances; which shall bear no less</line>
            <line>likelihood than to see me at her chamber-window,</line>
            <line>hear me call Margaret Hero, hear Margaret term me</line>
            <line>Claudio; and bring them to see this the very night</line>
            <line>before the intended wedding,--for in the meantime I</line>
            <line>will so fashion the matter that Hero shall be</line>
            <line>absent,--and there shall appear such seeming truth</line>
            <line>of Hero's disloyalty that jealousy shall be called</line>
            <line>assurance and all the preparation overthrown.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON JOHN</speaker>
            <line>Grow this to what adverse issue it can, I will put</line>
            <line>it in practise. Be cunning in the working this, and</line>
            <line>thy fee is a thousand ducats.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BORACHIO</speaker>
            <line>Be you constant in the accusation, and my cunning</line>
            <line>shall not shame me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON JOHN</speaker>
            <line>I will presently go learn their day of marriage.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  LEONATO'S orchard.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter BENEDICK</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Boy!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter Boy</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Boy</speaker>
            <line>Signior?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>In my chamber-window lies a book: bring it hither</line>
            <line>to me in the orchard.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Boy</speaker>
            <line>I am here already, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>I know that; but I would have thee hence, and here again.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit Boy</stagedir>
            <line>I do much wonder that one man, seeing how much</line>
            <line>another man is a fool when he dedicates his</line>
            <line>behaviors to love, will, after he hath laughed at</line>
            <line>such shallow follies in others, become the argument</line>
            <line>of his own scorn by failing in love: and such a man</line>
            <line>is Claudio. I have known when there was no music</line>
            <line>with him but the drum and the fife; and now had he</line>
            <line>rather hear the tabour and the pipe: I have known</line>
            <line>when he would have walked ten mile a-foot to see a</line>
            <line>good armour; and now will he lie ten nights awake,</line>
            <line>carving the fashion of a new doublet. He was wont to</line>
            <line>speak plain and to the purpose, like an honest man</line>
            <line>and a soldier; and now is he turned orthography; his</line>
            <line>words are a very fantastical banquet, just so many</line>
            <line>strange dishes. May I be so converted and see with</line>
            <line>these eyes? I cannot tell; I think not: I will not</line>
            <line>be sworn, but love may transform me to an oyster; but</line>
            <line>I'll take my oath on it, till he have made an oyster</line>
            <line>of me, he shall never make me such a fool. One woman</line>
            <line>is fair, yet I am well; another is wise, yet I am</line>
            <line>well; another virtuous, yet I am well; but till all</line>
            <line>graces be in one woman, one woman shall not come in</line>
            <line>my grace. Rich she shall be, that's certain; wise,</line>
            <line>or I'll none; virtuous, or I'll never cheapen her;</line>
            <line>fair, or I'll   never look on her; mild, or come not</line>
            <line>near me; noble, or not I for an angel; of good</line>
            <line>discourse, an excellent musician, and her hair shall</line>
            <line>be of what colour it please God. Ha! the prince and</line>
            <line>Monsieur Love! I will hide me in the arbour.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Withdraws</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Enter DON PEDRO, CLAUDIO, and LEONATO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>Come, shall we hear this music?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Yea, my good lord. How still the evening is,</line>
            <line>As hush'd on purpose to grace harmony!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>See you where Benedick hath hid himself?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>O, very well, my lord: the music ended,</line>
            <line>We'll fit the kid-fox with a pennyworth.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter BALTHASAR with Music</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>Come, Balthasar, we'll hear that song again.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BALTHASAR</speaker>
            <line>O, good my lord, tax not so bad a voice</line>
            <line>To slander music any more than once.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>It is the witness still of excellency</line>
            <line>To put a strange face on his own perfection.</line>
            <line>I pray thee, sing, and let me woo no more.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BALTHASAR</speaker>
            <line>Because you talk of wooing, I will sing;</line>
            <line>Since many a wooer doth commence his suit</line>
            <line>To her he thinks not worthy, yet he wooes,</line>
            <line>Yet will he swear he loves.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>Now, pray thee, come;</line>
            <line>Or, if thou wilt hold longer argument,</line>
            <line>Do it in notes.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BALTHASAR</speaker>
            <line>Note this before my notes;</line>
            <line>There's not a note of mine that's worth the noting.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>Why, these are very crotchets that he speaks;</line>
            <line>Note, notes, forsooth, and nothing.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Air</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Now, divine air! now is his soul ravished! Is it</line>
            <line>not strange that sheeps' guts should hale souls out</line>
            <line>of men's bodies? Well, a horn for my money, when</line>
            <line>all's done.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>The Song</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BALTHASAR</speaker>
            <line>Sigh no more, ladies, sigh no more,</line>
            <line>Men were deceivers ever,</line>
            <line>One foot in sea and one on shore,</line>
            <line>To one thing constant never:</line>
            <line>Then sigh not so, but let them go,</line>
            <line>And be you blithe and bonny,</line>
            <line>Converting all your sounds of woe</line>
            <line>Into Hey nonny, nonny.</line>
            <line>Sing no more ditties, sing no moe,</line>
            <line>Of dumps so dull and heavy;</line>
            <line>The fraud of men was ever so,</line>
            <line>Since summer first was leafy:</line>
            <line>Then sigh not so, &amp;c.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>By my troth, a good song.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BALTHASAR</speaker>
            <line>And an ill singer, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>Ha, no, no, faith; thou singest well enough for a shift.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>An he had been a dog that should have howled thus,</line>
            <line>they would have hanged him: and I pray God his bad</line>
            <line>voice bode no mischief. I had as lief have heard the</line>
            <line>night-raven, come what plague could have come after</line>
            <line>it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>Yea, marry, dost thou hear, Balthasar? I pray thee,</line>
            <line>get us some excellent music; for to-morrow night we</line>
            <line>would have it at the Lady Hero's chamber-window.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BALTHASAR</speaker>
            <line>The best I can, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>Do so: farewell.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit BALTHASAR</stagedir>
            <line>Come hither, Leonato. What was it you told me of</line>
            <line>to-day, that your niece Beatrice was in love with</line>
            <line>Signior Benedick?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>O, ay: stalk on. stalk on; the fowl sits. I did</line>
            <line>never think that lady would have loved any man.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>No, nor I neither; but most wonderful that she</line>
            <line>should so dote on Signior Benedick, whom she hath in</line>
            <line>all outward behaviors seemed ever to abhor.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Is't possible? Sits the wind in that corner?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>By my troth, my lord, I cannot tell what to think</line>
            <line>of it but that she loves him with an enraged</line>
            <line>affection: it is past the infinite of thought.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>May be she doth but counterfeit.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Faith, like enough.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>O God, counterfeit! There was never counterfeit of</line>
            <line>passion came so near the life of passion as she</line>
            <line>discovers it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>Why, what effects of passion shows she?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Bait the hook well; this fish will bite.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>What effects, my lord? She will sit you, you heard</line>
            <line>my daughter tell you how.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>She did, indeed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>How, how, pray you? You amaze me: I would have I</line>
            <line>thought her spirit had been invincible against all</line>
            <line>assaults of affection.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>I would have sworn it had, my lord; especially</line>
            <line>against Benedick.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>I should think this a gull, but that the</line>
            <line>white-bearded fellow speaks it: knavery cannot,</line>
            <line>sure, hide himself in such reverence.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>He hath ta'en the infection: hold it up.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>Hath she made her affection known to Benedick?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>No; and swears she never will: that's her torment.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>'Tis true, indeed; so your daughter says: 'Shall</line>
            <line>I,' says she, 'that have so oft encountered him</line>
            <line>with scorn, write to him that I love him?'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>This says she now when she is beginning to write to</line>
            <line>him; for she'll be up twenty times a night, and</line>
            <line>there will she sit in her smock till she have writ a</line>
            <line>sheet of paper: my daughter tells us all.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Now you talk of a sheet of paper, I remember a</line>
            <line>pretty jest your daughter told us of.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>O, when she had writ it and was reading it over, she</line>
            <line>found Benedick and Beatrice between the sheet?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>That.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>O, she tore the letter into a thousand halfpence;</line>
            <line>railed at herself, that she should be so immodest</line>
            <line>to write to one that she knew would flout her; 'I</line>
            <line>measure him,' says she, 'by my own spirit; for I</line>
            <line>should flout him, if he writ to me; yea, though I</line>
            <line>love him, I should.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Then down upon her knees she falls, weeps, sobs,</line>
            <line>beats her heart, tears her hair, prays, curses; 'O</line>
            <line>sweet Benedick! God give me patience!'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>She doth indeed; my daughter says so: and the</line>
            <line>ecstasy hath so much overborne her that my daughter</line>
            <line>is sometime afeared she will do a desperate outrage</line>
            <line>to herself: it is very true.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>It were good that Benedick knew of it by some</line>
            <line>other, if she will not discover it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>To what end? He would make but a sport of it and</line>
            <line>torment the poor lady worse.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>An he should, it were an alms to hang him. She's an</line>
            <line>excellent sweet lady; and, out of all suspicion,</line>
            <line>she is virtuous.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>And she is exceeding wise.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>In every thing but in loving Benedick.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>O, my lord, wisdom and blood combating in so tender</line>
            <line>a body, we have ten proofs to one that blood hath</line>
            <line>the victory. I am sorry for her, as I have just</line>
            <line>cause, being her uncle and her guardian.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>I would she had bestowed this dotage on me: I would</line>
            <line>have daffed all other respects and made her half</line>
            <line>myself. I pray you, tell Benedick of it, and hear</line>
            <line>what a' will say.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>Were it good, think you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Hero thinks surely she will die; for she says she</line>
            <line>will die, if he love her not, and she will die, ere</line>
            <line>she make her love known, and she will die, if he woo</line>
            <line>her, rather than she will bate one breath of her</line>
            <line>accustomed crossness.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>She doth well: if she should make tender of her</line>
            <line>love, 'tis very possible he'll scorn it; for the</line>
            <line>man, as you know all, hath a contemptible spirit.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>He is a very proper man.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>He hath indeed a good outward happiness.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Before God! and, in my mind, very wise.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>He doth indeed show some sparks that are like wit.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>And I take him to be valiant.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>As Hector, I assure you: and in the managing of</line>
            <line>quarrels you may say he is wise; for either he</line>
            <line>avoids them with great discretion, or undertakes</line>
            <line>them with a most Christian-like fear.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>If he do fear God, a' must necessarily keep peace:</line>
            <line>if he break the peace, he ought to enter into a</line>
            <line>quarrel with fear and trembling.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>And so will he do; for the man doth fear God,</line>
            <line>howsoever it seems not in him by some large jests</line>
            <line>he will make. Well I am sorry for your niece. Shall</line>
            <line>we go seek Benedick, and tell him of her love?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Never tell him, my lord: let her wear it out with</line>
            <line>good counsel.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>Nay, that's impossible: she may wear her heart out first.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>Well, we will hear further of it by your daughter:</line>
            <line>let it cool the while. I love Benedick well; and I</line>
            <line>could wish he would modestly examine himself, to see</line>
            <line>how much he is unworthy so good a lady.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>My lord, will you walk? dinner is ready.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>If he do not dote on her upon this, I will never</line>
            <line>trust my expectation.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>Let there be the same net spread for her; and that</line>
            <line>must your daughter and her gentlewomen carry. The</line>
            <line>sport will be, when they hold one an opinion of</line>
            <line>another's dotage, and no such matter: that's the</line>
            <line>scene that I would see, which will be merely a</line>
            <line>dumb-show. Let us send her to call him in to dinner.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt DON PEDRO, CLAUDIO, and LEONATO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Coming forward</stagedir>  This can be no trick: the</line>
            <line>conference was sadly borne. They have the truth of</line>
            <line>this from Hero. They seem to pity the lady: it</line>
            <line>seems her affections have their full bent. Love me!</line>
            <line>why, it must be requited. I hear how I am censured:</line>
            <line>they say I will bear myself proudly, if I perceive</line>
            <line>the love come from her; they say too that she will</line>
            <line>rather die than give any sign of affection. I did</line>
            <line>never think to marry: I must not seem proud: happy</line>
            <line>are they that hear their detractions and can put</line>
            <line>them to mending. They say the lady is fair; 'tis a</line>
            <line>truth, I can bear them witness; and virtuous; 'tis</line>
            <line>so, I cannot reprove it; and wise, but for loving</line>
            <line>me; by my troth, it is no addition to her wit, nor</line>
            <line>no great argument of her folly, for I will be</line>
            <line>horribly in love with her. I may chance have some</line>
            <line>odd quirks and remnants of wit broken on me,</line>
            <line>because I have railed so long against marriage: but</line>
            <line>doth not the appetite alter? a man loves the meat</line>
            <line>in his youth that he cannot endure in his age.</line>
            <line>Shall quips and sentences and these paper bullets of</line>
            <line>the brain awe a man from the career of his humour?</line>
            <line>No, the world must be peopled. When I said I would</line>
            <line>die a bachelor, I did not think I should live till I</line>
            <line>were married. Here comes Beatrice. By this day!</line>
            <line>she's a fair lady: I do spy some marks of love in</line>
            <line>her.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter BEATRICE</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>Against my will I am sent to bid you come in to dinner.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Fair Beatrice, I thank you for your pains.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>I took no more pains for those thanks than you take</line>
            <line>pains to thank me: if it had been painful, I would</line>
            <line>not have come.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>You take pleasure then in the message?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>Yea, just so much as you may take upon a knife's</line>
            <line>point and choke a daw withal. You have no stomach,</line>
            <line>signior: fare you well.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Ha! 'Against my will I am sent to bid you come in</line>
            <line>to dinner;' there's a double meaning in that 'I took</line>
            <line>no more pains for those thanks than you took pains</line>
            <line>to thank me.' that's as much as to say, Any pains</line>
            <line>that I take for you is as easy as thanks. If I do</line>
            <line>not take pity of her, I am a villain; if I do not</line>
            <line>love her, I am a Jew. I will go get her picture.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>