<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:shakespear:dtd:act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-4">
   <title>ACT IV</title>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  A church.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter DON PEDRO, DON JOHN, LEONATO, FRIAR FRANCIS,
CLAUDIO, BENEDICK, HERO, BEATRICE, and Attendants</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>Come, Friar Francis, be brief; only to the plain</line>
            <line>form of marriage, and you shall recount their</line>
            <line>particular duties afterwards.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FRIAR FRANCIS</speaker>
            <line>You come hither, my lord, to marry this lady.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>No.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>To be married to her: friar, you come to marry her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FRIAR FRANCIS</speaker>
            <line>Lady, you come hither to be married to this count.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERO</speaker>
            <line>I do.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FRIAR FRANCIS</speaker>
            <line>If either of you know any inward impediment why you</line>
            <line>should not be conjoined, charge you, on your souls,</line>
            <line>to utter it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Know you any, Hero?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERO</speaker>
            <line>None, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FRIAR FRANCIS</speaker>
            <line>Know you any, count?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>I dare make his answer, none.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>O, what men dare do! what men may do! what men daily</line>
            <line>do, not knowing what they do!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>How now! interjections? Why, then, some be of</line>
            <line>laughing, as, ah, ha, he!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Stand thee by, friar. Father, by your leave:</line>
            <line>Will you with free and unconstrained soul</line>
            <line>Give me this maid, your daughter?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>As freely, son, as God did give her me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>And what have I to give you back, whose worth</line>
            <line>May counterpoise this rich and precious gift?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>Nothing, unless you render her again.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Sweet prince, you learn me noble thankfulness.</line>
            <line>There, Leonato, take her back again:</line>
            <line>Give not this rotten orange to your friend;</line>
            <line>She's but the sign and semblance of her honour.</line>
            <line>Behold how like a maid she blushes here!</line>
            <line>O, what authority and show of truth</line>
            <line>Can cunning sin cover itself withal!</line>
            <line>Comes not that blood as modest evidence</line>
            <line>To witness simple virtue? Would you not swear,</line>
            <line>All you that see her, that she were a maid,</line>
            <line>By these exterior shows? But she is none:</line>
            <line>She knows the heat of a luxurious bed;</line>
            <line>Her blush is guiltiness, not modesty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>What do you mean, my lord?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Not to be married,</line>
            <line>Not to knit my soul to an approved wanton.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>Dear my lord, if you, in your own proof,</line>
            <line>Have vanquish'd the resistance of her youth,</line>
            <line>And made defeat of her virginity,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>I know what you would say: if I have known her,</line>
            <line>You will say she did embrace me as a husband,</line>
            <line>And so extenuate the 'forehand sin:</line>
            <line>No, Leonato,</line>
            <line>I never tempted her with word too large;</line>
            <line>But, as a brother to his sister, show'd</line>
            <line>Bashful sincerity and comely love.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERO</speaker>
            <line>And seem'd I ever otherwise to you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Out on thee! Seeming! I will write against it:</line>
            <line>You seem to me as Dian in her orb,</line>
            <line>As chaste as is the bud ere it be blown;</line>
            <line>But you are more intemperate in your blood</line>
            <line>Than Venus, or those pamper'd animals</line>
            <line>That rage in savage sensuality.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERO</speaker>
            <line>Is my lord well, that he doth speak so wide?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>Sweet prince, why speak not you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>What should I speak?</line>
            <line>I stand dishonour'd, that have gone about</line>
            <line>To link my dear friend to a common stale.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>Are these things spoken, or do I but dream?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON JOHN</speaker>
            <line>Sir, they are spoken, and these things are true.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>This looks not like a nuptial.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERO</speaker>
            <line>True! O God!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Leonato, stand I here?</line>
            <line>Is this the prince? is this the prince's brother?</line>
            <line>Is this face Hero's? are our eyes our own?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>All this is so: but what of this, my lord?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Let me but move one question to your daughter;</line>
            <line>And, by that fatherly and kindly power</line>
            <line>That you have in her, bid her answer truly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>I charge thee do so, as thou art my child.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERO</speaker>
            <line>O, God defend me! how am I beset!</line>
            <line>What kind of catechising call you this?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>To make you answer truly to your name.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERO</speaker>
            <line>Is it not Hero? Who can blot that name</line>
            <line>With any just reproach?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Marry, that can Hero;</line>
            <line>Hero itself can blot out Hero's virtue.</line>
            <line>What man was he talk'd with you yesternight</line>
            <line>Out at your window betwixt twelve and one?</line>
            <line>Now, if you are a maid, answer to this.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERO</speaker>
            <line>I talk'd with no man at that hour, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>Why, then are you no maiden. Leonato,</line>
            <line>I am sorry you must hear: upon mine honour,</line>
            <line>Myself, my brother and this grieved count</line>
            <line>Did see her, hear her, at that hour last night</line>
            <line>Talk with a ruffian at her chamber-window</line>
            <line>Who hath indeed, most like a liberal villain,</line>
            <line>Confess'd the vile encounters they have had</line>
            <line>A thousand times in secret.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON JOHN</speaker>
            <line>Fie, fie! they are not to be named, my lord,</line>
            <line>Not to be spoke of;</line>
            <line>There is not chastity enough in language</line>
            <line>Without offence to utter them. Thus, pretty lady,</line>
            <line>I am sorry for thy much misgovernment.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>O Hero, what a Hero hadst thou been,</line>
            <line>If half thy outward graces had been placed</line>
            <line>About thy thoughts and counsels of thy heart!</line>
            <line>But fare thee well, most foul, most fair! farewell,</line>
            <line>Thou pure impiety and impious purity!</line>
            <line>For thee I'll lock up all the gates of love,</line>
            <line>And on my eyelids shall conjecture hang,</line>
            <line>To turn all beauty into thoughts of harm,</line>
            <line>And never shall it more be gracious.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>Hath no man's dagger here a point for me?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>HERO swoons</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>Why, how now, cousin! wherefore sink you down?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON JOHN</speaker>
            <line>Come, let us go. These things, come thus to light,</line>
            <line>Smother her spirits up.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt DON PEDRO, DON JOHN, and CLAUDIO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>How doth the lady?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>Dead, I think. Help, uncle!</line>
            <line>Hero! why, Hero! Uncle! Signior Benedick! Friar!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>O Fate! take not away thy heavy hand.</line>
            <line>Death is the fairest cover for her shame</line>
            <line>That may be wish'd for.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>How now, cousin Hero!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FRIAR FRANCIS</speaker>
            <line>Have comfort, lady.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>Dost thou look up?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FRIAR FRANCIS</speaker>
            <line>Yea, wherefore should she not?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>Wherefore! Why, doth not every earthly thing</line>
            <line>Cry shame upon her? Could she here deny</line>
            <line>The story that is printed in her blood?</line>
            <line>Do not live, Hero; do not ope thine eyes:</line>
            <line>For, did I think thou wouldst not quickly die,</line>
            <line>Thought I thy spirits were stronger than thy shames,</line>
            <line>Myself would, on the rearward of reproaches,</line>
            <line>Strike at thy life. Grieved I, I had but one?</line>
            <line>Chid I for that at frugal nature's frame?</line>
            <line>O, one too much by thee! Why had I one?</line>
            <line>Why ever wast thou lovely in my eyes?</line>
            <line>Why had I not with charitable hand</line>
            <line>Took up a beggar's issue at my gates,</line>
            <line>Who smirch'd thus and mired with infamy,</line>
            <line>I might have said 'No part of it is mine;</line>
            <line>This shame derives itself from unknown loins'?</line>
            <line>But mine and mine I loved and mine I praised</line>
            <line>And mine that I was proud on, mine so much</line>
            <line>That I myself was to myself not mine,</line>
            <line>Valuing of her,--why, she, O, she is fallen</line>
            <line>Into a pit of ink, that the wide sea</line>
            <line>Hath drops too few to wash her clean again</line>
            <line>And salt too little which may season give</line>
            <line>To her foul-tainted flesh!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Sir, sir, be patient.</line>
            <line>For my part, I am so attired in wonder,</line>
            <line>I know not what to say.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>O, on my soul, my cousin is belied!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Lady, were you her bedfellow last night?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>No, truly not; although, until last night,</line>
            <line>I have this twelvemonth been her bedfellow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>Confirm'd, confirm'd! O, that is stronger made</line>
            <line>Which was before barr'd up with ribs of iron!</line>
            <line>Would the two princes lie, and Claudio lie,</line>
            <line>Who loved her so, that, speaking of her foulness,</line>
            <line>Wash'd it with tears? Hence from her! let her die.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FRIAR FRANCIS</speaker>
            <line>Hear me a little; for I have only been</line>
            <line>Silent so long and given way unto</line>
            <line>This course of fortune</line>
            <line>By noting of the lady. I have mark'd</line>
            <line>A thousand blushing apparitions</line>
            <line>To start into her face, a thousand innocent shames</line>
            <line>In angel whiteness beat away those blushes;</line>
            <line>And in her eye there hath appear'd a fire,</line>
            <line>To burn the errors that these princes hold</line>
            <line>Against her maiden truth. Call me a fool;</line>
            <line>Trust not my reading nor my observations,</line>
            <line>Which with experimental seal doth warrant</line>
            <line>The tenor of my book; trust not my age,</line>
            <line>My reverence, calling, nor divinity,</line>
            <line>If this sweet lady lie not guiltless here</line>
            <line>Under some biting error.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>Friar, it cannot be.</line>
            <line>Thou seest that all the grace that she hath left</line>
            <line>Is that she will not add to her damnation</line>
            <line>A sin of perjury; she not denies it:</line>
            <line>Why seek'st thou then to cover with excuse</line>
            <line>That which appears in proper nakedness?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FRIAR FRANCIS</speaker>
            <line>Lady, what man is he you are accused of?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERO</speaker>
            <line>They know that do accuse me; I know none:</line>
            <line>If I know more of any man alive</line>
            <line>Than that which maiden modesty doth warrant,</line>
            <line>Let all my sins lack mercy! O my father,</line>
            <line>Prove you that any man with me conversed</line>
            <line>At hours unmeet, or that I yesternight</line>
            <line>Maintain'd the change of words with any creature,</line>
            <line>Refuse me, hate me, torture me to death!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FRIAR FRANCIS</speaker>
            <line>There is some strange misprision in the princes.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Two of them have the very bent of honour;</line>
            <line>And if their wisdoms be misled in this,</line>
            <line>The practise of it lives in John the bastard,</line>
            <line>Whose spirits toil in frame of villanies.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>I know not. If they speak but truth of her,</line>
            <line>These hands shall tear her; if they wrong her honour,</line>
            <line>The proudest of them shall well hear of it.</line>
            <line>Time hath not yet so dried this blood of mine,</line>
            <line>Nor age so eat up my invention,</line>
            <line>Nor fortune made such havoc of my means,</line>
            <line>Nor my bad life reft me so much of friends,</line>
            <line>But they shall find, awaked in such a kind,</line>
            <line>Both strength of limb and policy of mind,</line>
            <line>Ability in means and choice of friends,</line>
            <line>To quit me of them throughly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FRIAR FRANCIS</speaker>
            <line>Pause awhile,</line>
            <line>And let my counsel sway you in this case.</line>
            <line>Your daughter here the princes left for dead:</line>
            <line>Let her awhile be secretly kept in,</line>
            <line>And publish it that she is dead indeed;</line>
            <line>Maintain a mourning ostentation</line>
            <line>And on your family's old monument</line>
            <line>Hang mournful epitaphs and do all rites</line>
            <line>That appertain unto a burial.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>What shall become of this? what will this do?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FRIAR FRANCIS</speaker>
            <line>Marry, this well carried shall on her behalf</line>
            <line>Change slander to remorse; that is some good:</line>
            <line>But not for that dream I on this strange course,</line>
            <line>But on this travail look for greater birth.</line>
            <line>She dying, as it must so be maintain'd,</line>
            <line>Upon the instant that she was accused,</line>
            <line>Shall be lamented, pitied and excused</line>
            <line>Of every hearer: for it so falls out</line>
            <line>That what we have we prize not to the worth</line>
            <line>Whiles we enjoy it, but being lack'd and lost,</line>
            <line>Why, then we rack the value, then we find</line>
            <line>The virtue that possession would not show us</line>
            <line>Whiles it was ours. So will it fare with Claudio:</line>
            <line>When he shall hear she died upon his words,</line>
            <line>The idea of her life shall sweetly creep</line>
            <line>Into his study of imagination,</line>
            <line>And every lovely organ of her life</line>
            <line>Shall come apparell'd in more precious habit,</line>
            <line>More moving-delicate and full of life,</line>
            <line>Into the eye and prospect of his soul,</line>
            <line>Than when she lived indeed; then shall he mourn,</line>
            <line>If ever love had interest in his liver,</line>
            <line>And wish he had not so accused her,</line>
            <line>No, though he thought his accusation true.</line>
            <line>Let this be so, and doubt not but success</line>
            <line>Will fashion the event in better shape</line>
            <line>Than I can lay it down in likelihood.</line>
            <line>But if all aim but this be levell'd false,</line>
            <line>The supposition of the lady's death</line>
            <line>Will quench the wonder of her infamy:</line>
            <line>And if it sort not well, you may conceal her,</line>
            <line>As best befits her wounded reputation,</line>
            <line>In some reclusive and religious life,</line>
            <line>Out of all eyes, tongues, minds and injuries.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Signior Leonato, let the friar advise you:</line>
            <line>And though you know my inwardness and love</line>
            <line>Is very much unto the prince and Claudio,</line>
            <line>Yet, by mine honour, I will deal in this</line>
            <line>As secretly and justly as your soul</line>
            <line>Should with your body.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>Being that I flow in grief,</line>
            <line>The smallest twine may lead me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FRIAR FRANCIS</speaker>
            <line>'Tis well consented: presently away;</line>
            <line>For to strange sores strangely they strain the cure.</line>
            <line>Come, lady, die to live: this wedding-day</line>
            <line>Perhaps is but prolong'd: have patience and endure.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt all but BENEDICK and BEATRICE</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Lady Beatrice, have you wept all this while?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>Yea, and I will weep a while longer.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>I will not desire that.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>You have no reason; I do it freely.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Surely I do believe your fair cousin is wronged.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>Ah, how much might the man deserve of me that would right her!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Is there any way to show such friendship?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>A very even way, but no such friend.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>May a man do it?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>It is a man's office, but not yours.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>I do love nothing in the world so well as you: is</line>
            <line>not that strange?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>As strange as the thing I know not. It were as</line>
            <line>possible for me to say I loved nothing so well as</line>
            <line>you: but believe me not; and yet I lie not; I</line>
            <line>confess nothing, nor I deny nothing. I am sorry for my cousin.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>By my sword, Beatrice, thou lovest me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>Do not swear, and eat it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>I will swear by it that you love me; and I will make</line>
            <line>him eat it that says I love not you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>Will you not eat your word?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>With no sauce that can be devised to it. I protest</line>
            <line>I love thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>Why, then, God forgive me!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>What offence, sweet Beatrice?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>You have stayed me in a happy hour: I was about to</line>
            <line>protest I loved you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>And do it with all thy heart.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>I love you with so much of my heart that none is</line>
            <line>left to protest.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Come, bid me do any thing for thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>Kill Claudio.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Ha! not for the wide world.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>You kill me to deny it. Farewell.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Tarry, sweet Beatrice.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>I am gone, though I am here: there is no love in</line>
            <line>you: nay, I pray you, let me go.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Beatrice,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>In faith, I will go.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>We'll be friends first.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>You dare easier be friends with me than fight with mine enemy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Is Claudio thine enemy?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>Is he not approved in the height a villain, that</line>
            <line>hath slandered, scorned, dishonoured my kinswoman? O</line>
            <line>that I were a man! What, bear her in hand until they</line>
            <line>come to take hands; and then, with public</line>
            <line>accusation, uncovered slander, unmitigated rancour,</line>
            <line>--O God, that I were a man! I would eat his heart</line>
            <line>in the market-place.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Hear me, Beatrice,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>Talk with a man out at a window! A proper saying!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Nay, but, Beatrice,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>Sweet Hero! She is wronged, she is slandered, she is undone.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Beat--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>Princes and counties! Surely, a princely testimony,</line>
            <line>a goodly count, Count Comfect; a sweet gallant,</line>
            <line>surely! O that I were a man for his sake! or that I</line>
            <line>had any friend would be a man for my sake! But</line>
            <line>manhood is melted into courtesies, valour into</line>
            <line>compliment, and men are only turned into tongue, and</line>
            <line>trim ones too: he is now as valiant as Hercules</line>
            <line>that only tells a lie and swears it. I cannot be a</line>
            <line>man with wishing, therefore I will die a woman with grieving.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Tarry, good Beatrice. By this hand, I love thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>Use it for my love some other way than swearing by it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Think you in your soul the Count Claudio hath wronged Hero?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>Yea, as sure as I have a thought or a soul.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Enough, I am engaged; I will challenge him. I will</line>
            <line>kiss your hand, and so I leave you. By this hand,</line>
            <line>Claudio shall render me a dear account. As you</line>
            <line>hear of me, so think of me. Go, comfort your</line>
            <line>cousin: I must say she is dead: and so, farewell.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  A prison.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter DOGBERRY, VERGES, and Sexton, in gowns; and
the Watch, with CONRADE and BORACHIO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOGBERRY</speaker>
            <line>Is our whole dissembly appeared?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VERGES</speaker>
            <line>O, a stool and a cushion for the sexton.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Sexton</speaker>
            <line>Which be the malefactors?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOGBERRY</speaker>
            <line>Marry, that am I and my partner.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VERGES</speaker>
            <line>Nay, that's certain; we have the exhibition to examine.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Sexton</speaker>
            <line>But which are the offenders that are to be</line>
            <line>examined? let them come before master constable.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOGBERRY</speaker>
            <line>Yea, marry, let them come before me. What is your</line>
            <line>name, friend?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BORACHIO</speaker>
            <line>Borachio.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOGBERRY</speaker>
            <line>Pray, write down, Borachio. Yours, sirrah?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CONRADE</speaker>
            <line>I am a gentleman, sir, and my name is Conrade.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOGBERRY</speaker>
            <line>Write down, master gentleman Conrade. Masters, do</line>
            <line>you serve God?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CONRADE</speaker>
            <speaker>BORACHIO</speaker>
            <line>Yea, sir, we hope.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOGBERRY</speaker>
            <line>Write down, that they hope they serve God: and</line>
            <line>write God first; for God defend but God should go</line>
            <line>before such villains! Masters, it is proved already</line>
            <line>that you are little better than false knaves; and it</line>
            <line>will go near to be thought so shortly. How answer</line>
            <line>you for yourselves?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CONRADE</speaker>
            <line>Marry, sir, we say we are none.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOGBERRY</speaker>
            <line>A marvellous witty fellow, I assure you: but I</line>
            <line>will go about with him. Come you hither, sirrah; a</line>
            <line>word in your ear: sir, I say to you, it is thought</line>
            <line>you are false knaves.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BORACHIO</speaker>
            <line>Sir, I say to you we are none.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOGBERRY</speaker>
            <line>Well, stand aside. 'Fore God, they are both in a</line>
            <line>tale. Have you writ down, that they are none?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Sexton</speaker>
            <line>Master constable, you go not the way to examine:</line>
            <line>you must call forth the watch that are their accusers.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOGBERRY</speaker>
            <line>Yea, marry, that's the eftest way. Let the watch</line>
            <line>come forth. Masters, I charge you, in the prince's</line>
            <line>name, accuse these men.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Watchman</speaker>
            <line>This man said, sir, that Don John, the prince's</line>
            <line>brother, was a villain.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOGBERRY</speaker>
            <line>Write down Prince John a villain. Why, this is flat</line>
            <line>perjury, to call a prince's brother villain.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BORACHIO</speaker>
            <line>Master constable,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOGBERRY</speaker>
            <line>Pray thee, fellow, peace: I do not like thy look,</line>
            <line>I promise thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Sexton</speaker>
            <line>What heard you him say else?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Watchman</speaker>
            <line>Marry, that he had received a thousand ducats of</line>
            <line>Don John for accusing the Lady Hero wrongfully.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOGBERRY</speaker>
            <line>Flat burglary as ever was committed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VERGES</speaker>
            <line>Yea, by mass, that it is.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Sexton</speaker>
            <line>What else, fellow?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Watchman</speaker>
            <line>And that Count Claudio did mean, upon his words, to</line>
            <line>disgrace Hero before the whole assembly. and not marry her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOGBERRY</speaker>
            <line>O villain! thou wilt be condemned into everlasting</line>
            <line>redemption for this.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Sexton</speaker>
            <line>What else?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Watchman</speaker>
            <line>This is all.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Sexton</speaker>
            <line>And this is more, masters, than you can deny.</line>
            <line>Prince John is this morning secretly stolen away;</line>
            <line>Hero was in this manner accused, in this very manner</line>
            <line>refused, and upon the grief of this suddenly died.</line>
            <line>Master constable, let these men be bound, and</line>
            <line>brought to Leonato's: I will go before and show</line>
            <line>him their examination.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOGBERRY</speaker>
            <line>Come, let them be opinioned.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VERGES</speaker>
            <line>Let them be in the hands--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CONRADE</speaker>
            <line>Off, coxcomb!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOGBERRY</speaker>
            <line>God's my life, where's the sexton? let him write</line>
            <line>down the prince's officer coxcomb. Come, bind them.</line>
            <line>Thou naughty varlet!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CONRADE</speaker>
            <line>Away! you are an ass, you are an ass.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOGBERRY</speaker>
            <line>Dost thou not suspect my place? dost thou not</line>
            <line>suspect my years? O that he were here to write me</line>
            <line>down an ass! But, masters, remember that I am an</line>
            <line>ass; though it be not written down, yet forget not</line>
            <line>that I am an ass. No, thou villain, thou art full of</line>
            <line>piety, as shall be proved upon thee by good witness.</line>
            <line>I am a wise fellow, and, which is more, an officer,</line>
            <line>and, which is more, a householder, and, which is</line>
            <line>more, as pretty a piece of flesh as any is in</line>
            <line>Messina, and one that knows the law, go to; and a</line>
            <line>rich fellow enough, go to; and a fellow that hath</line>
            <line>had losses, and one that hath two gowns and every</line>
            <line>thing handsome about him. Bring him away. O that</line>
            <line>I had been writ down an ass!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>