<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:shakespear:dtd:act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-3">
   <title>ACT III</title>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  LEONATO'S garden.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter HERO, MARGARET, and URSULA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERO</speaker>
            <line>Good Margaret, run thee to the parlor;</line>
            <line>There shalt thou find my cousin Beatrice</line>
            <line>Proposing with the prince and Claudio:</line>
            <line>Whisper her ear and tell her, I and Ursula</line>
            <line>Walk in the orchard and our whole discourse</line>
            <line>Is all of her; say that thou overheard'st us;</line>
            <line>And bid her steal into the pleached bower,</line>
            <line>Where honeysuckles, ripen'd by the sun,</line>
            <line>Forbid the sun to enter, like favourites,</line>
            <line>Made proud by princes, that advance their pride</line>
            <line>Against that power that bred it: there will she hide her,</line>
            <line>To listen our purpose.  This is thy office;</line>
            <line>Bear thee well in it and leave us alone.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>I'll make her come, I warrant you, presently.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERO</speaker>
            <line>Now, Ursula, when Beatrice doth come,</line>
            <line>As we do trace this alley up and down,</line>
            <line>Our talk must only be of Benedick.</line>
            <line>When I do name him, let it be thy part</line>
            <line>To praise him more than ever man did merit:</line>
            <line>My talk to thee must be how Benedick</line>
            <line>Is sick in love with Beatrice. Of this matter</line>
            <line>Is little Cupid's crafty arrow made,</line>
            <line>That only wounds by hearsay.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter BEATRICE, behind</stagedir>
            <line>Now begin;</line>
            <line>For look where Beatrice, like a lapwing, runs</line>
            <line>Close by the ground, to hear our conference.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>URSULA</speaker>
            <line>The pleasant'st angling is to see the fish</line>
            <line>Cut with her golden oars the silver stream,</line>
            <line>And greedily devour the treacherous bait:</line>
            <line>So angle we for Beatrice; who even now</line>
            <line>Is couched in the woodbine coverture.</line>
            <line>Fear you not my part of the dialogue.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERO</speaker>
            <line>Then go we near her, that her ear lose nothing</line>
            <line>Of the false sweet bait that we lay for it.</line>
            <stagedir>Approaching the bower</stagedir>
            <line>No, truly, Ursula, she is too disdainful;</line>
            <line>I know her spirits are as coy and wild</line>
            <line>As haggerds of the rock.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>URSULA</speaker>
            <line>But are you sure</line>
            <line>That Benedick loves Beatrice so entirely?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERO</speaker>
            <line>So says the prince and my new-trothed lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>URSULA</speaker>
            <line>And did they bid you tell her of it, madam?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERO</speaker>
            <line>They did entreat me to acquaint her of it;</line>
            <line>But I persuaded them, if they loved Benedick,</line>
            <line>To wish him wrestle with affection,</line>
            <line>And never to let Beatrice know of it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>URSULA</speaker>
            <line>Why did you so? Doth not the gentleman</line>
            <line>Deserve as full as fortunate a bed</line>
            <line>As ever Beatrice shall couch upon?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERO</speaker>
            <line>O god of love! I know he doth deserve</line>
            <line>As much as may be yielded to a man:</line>
            <line>But Nature never framed a woman's heart</line>
            <line>Of prouder stuff than that of Beatrice;</line>
            <line>Disdain and scorn ride sparkling in her eyes,</line>
            <line>Misprising what they look on, and her wit</line>
            <line>Values itself so highly that to her</line>
            <line>All matter else seems weak: she cannot love,</line>
            <line>Nor take no shape nor project of affection,</line>
            <line>She is so self-endeared.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>URSULA</speaker>
            <line>Sure, I think so;</line>
            <line>And therefore certainly it were not good</line>
            <line>She knew his love, lest she make sport at it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERO</speaker>
            <line>Why, you speak truth. I never yet saw man,</line>
            <line>How wise, how noble, young, how rarely featured,</line>
            <line>But she would spell him backward: if fair-faced,</line>
            <line>She would swear the gentleman should be her sister;</line>
            <line>If black, why, Nature, drawing of an antique,</line>
            <line>Made a foul blot; if tall, a lance ill-headed;</line>
            <line>If low, an agate very vilely cut;</line>
            <line>If speaking, why, a vane blown with all winds;</line>
            <line>If silent, why, a block moved with none.</line>
            <line>So turns she every man the wrong side out</line>
            <line>And never gives to truth and virtue that</line>
            <line>Which simpleness and merit purchaseth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>URSULA</speaker>
            <line>Sure, sure, such carping is not commendable.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERO</speaker>
            <line>No, not to be so odd and from all fashions</line>
            <line>As Beatrice is, cannot be commendable:</line>
            <line>But who dare tell her so? If I should speak,</line>
            <line>She would mock me into air; O, she would laugh me</line>
            <line>Out of myself, press me to death with wit.</line>
            <line>Therefore let Benedick, like cover'd fire,</line>
            <line>Consume away in sighs, waste inwardly:</line>
            <line>It were a better death than die with mocks,</line>
            <line>Which is as bad as die with tickling.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>URSULA</speaker>
            <line>Yet tell her of it: hear what she will say.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERO</speaker>
            <line>No; rather I will go to Benedick</line>
            <line>And counsel him to fight against his passion.</line>
            <line>And, truly, I'll devise some honest slanders</line>
            <line>To stain my cousin with: one doth not know</line>
            <line>How much an ill word may empoison liking.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>URSULA</speaker>
            <line>O, do not do your cousin such a wrong.</line>
            <line>She cannot be so much without true judgment--</line>
            <line>Having so swift and excellent a wit</line>
            <line>As she is prized to have--as to refuse</line>
            <line>So rare a gentleman as Signior Benedick.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERO</speaker>
            <line>He is the only man of Italy.</line>
            <line>Always excepted my dear Claudio.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>URSULA</speaker>
            <line>I pray you, be not angry with me, madam,</line>
            <line>Speaking my fancy: Signior Benedick,</line>
            <line>For shape, for bearing, argument and valour,</line>
            <line>Goes foremost in report through Italy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERO</speaker>
            <line>Indeed, he hath an excellent good name.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>URSULA</speaker>
            <line>His excellence did earn it, ere he had it.</line>
            <line>When are you married, madam?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERO</speaker>
            <line>Why, every day, to-morrow. Come, go in:</line>
            <line>I'll show thee some attires, and have thy counsel</line>
            <line>Which is the best to furnish me to-morrow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>URSULA</speaker>
            <line>She's limed, I warrant you: we have caught her, madam.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERO</speaker>
            <line>If it proves so, then loving goes by haps:</line>
            <line>Some Cupid kills with arrows, some with traps.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt HERO and URSULA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Coming forward</stagedir>
            </line>
            <line>What fire is in mine ears? Can this be true?</line>
            <line>Stand I condemn'd for pride and scorn so much?</line>
            <line>Contempt, farewell! and maiden pride, adieu!</line>
            <line>No glory lives behind the back of such.</line>
            <line>And, Benedick, love on; I will requite thee,</line>
            <line>Taming my wild heart to thy loving hand:</line>
            <line>If thou dost love, my kindness shall incite thee</line>
            <line>To bind our loves up in a holy band;</line>
            <line>For others say thou dost deserve, and I</line>
            <line>Believe it better than reportingly.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  A room in LEONATO'S house</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter DON PEDRO, CLAUDIO, BENEDICK, and LEONATO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>I do but stay till your marriage be consummate, and</line>
            <line>then go I toward Arragon.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>I'll bring you thither, my lord, if you'll</line>
            <line>vouchsafe me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>Nay, that would be as great a soil in the new gloss</line>
            <line>of your marriage as to show a child his new coat</line>
            <line>and forbid him to wear it. I will only be bold</line>
            <line>with Benedick for his company; for, from the crown</line>
            <line>of his head to the sole of his foot, he is all</line>
            <line>mirth: he hath twice or thrice cut Cupid's</line>
            <line>bow-string and the little hangman dare not shoot at</line>
            <line>him; he hath a heart as sound as a bell and his</line>
            <line>tongue is the clapper, for what his heart thinks his</line>
            <line>tongue speaks.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Gallants, I am not as I have been.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>So say I methinks you are sadder.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>I hope he be in love.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>Hang him, truant! there's no true drop of blood in</line>
            <line>him, to be truly touched with love: if he be sad,</line>
            <line>he wants money.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>I have the toothache.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>Draw it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Hang it!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>You must hang it first, and draw it afterwards.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>What! sigh for the toothache?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>Where is but a humour or a worm.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Well, every one can master a grief but he that has</line>
            <line>it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Yet say I, he is in love.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>There is no appearance of fancy in him, unless it be</line>
            <line>a fancy that he hath to strange disguises; as, to be</line>
            <line>a Dutchman today, a Frenchman to-morrow, or in the</line>
            <line>shape of two countries at once, as, a German from</line>
            <line>the waist downward, all slops, and a Spaniard from</line>
            <line>the hip upward, no doublet. Unless he have a fancy</line>
            <line>to this foolery, as it appears he hath, he is no</line>
            <line>fool for fancy, as you would have it appear he is.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>If he be not in love with some woman, there is no</line>
            <line>believing old signs: a' brushes his hat o'</line>
            <line>mornings; what should that bode?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>Hath any man seen him at the barber's?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>No, but the barber's man hath been seen with him,</line>
            <line>and the old ornament of his cheek hath already</line>
            <line>stuffed tennis-balls.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>Indeed, he looks younger than he did, by the loss of a beard.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>Nay, a' rubs himself with civet: can you smell him</line>
            <line>out by that?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>That's as much as to say, the sweet youth's in love.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>The greatest note of it is his melancholy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>And when was he wont to wash his face?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>Yea, or to paint himself? for the which, I hear</line>
            <line>what they say of him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Nay, but his jesting spirit; which is now crept into</line>
            <line>a lute-string and now governed by stops.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>Indeed, that tells a heavy tale for him: conclude,</line>
            <line>conclude he is in love.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Nay, but I know who loves him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>That would I know too: I warrant, one that knows him not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Yes, and his ill conditions; and, in despite of</line>
            <line>all, dies for him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>She shall be buried with her face upwards.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENEDICK</speaker>
            <line>Yet is this no charm for the toothache. Old</line>
            <line>signior, walk aside with me: I have studied eight</line>
            <line>or nine wise words to speak to you, which these</line>
            <line>hobby-horses must not hear.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt BENEDICK and LEONATO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>For my life, to break with him about Beatrice.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>'Tis even so. Hero and Margaret have by this</line>
            <line>played their parts with Beatrice; and then the two</line>
            <line>bears will not bite one another when they meet.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter DON JOHN</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON JOHN</speaker>
            <line>My lord and brother, God save you!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>Good den, brother.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON JOHN</speaker>
            <line>If your leisure served, I would speak with you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>In private?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON JOHN</speaker>
            <line>If it please you: yet Count Claudio may hear; for</line>
            <line>what I would speak of concerns him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>What's the matter?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON JOHN</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>To CLAUDIO</stagedir>  Means your lordship to be married</line>
            <line>to-morrow?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>You know he does.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON JOHN</speaker>
            <line>I know not that, when he knows what I know.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>If there be any impediment, I pray you discover it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON JOHN</speaker>
            <line>You may think I love you not: let that appear</line>
            <line>hereafter, and aim better at me by that I now will</line>
            <line>manifest. For my brother, I think he holds you</line>
            <line>well, and in dearness of heart hath holp to effect</line>
            <line>your ensuing marriage;--surely suit ill spent and</line>
            <line>labour ill bestowed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>Why, what's the matter?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON JOHN</speaker>
            <line>I came hither to tell you; and, circumstances</line>
            <line>shortened, for she has been too long a talking of,</line>
            <line>the lady is disloyal.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Who, Hero?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>Even she; Leonato's Hero, your Hero, every man's Hero:</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Disloyal?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON JOHN</speaker>
            <line>The word is too good to paint out her wickedness; I</line>
            <line>could say she were worse: think you of a worse</line>
            <line>title, and I will fit her to it. Wonder not till</line>
            <line>further warrant: go but with me to-night, you shall</line>
            <line>see her chamber-window entered, even the night</line>
            <line>before her wedding-day: if you love her then,</line>
            <line>to-morrow wed her; but it would better fit your honour</line>
            <line>to change your mind.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>May this be so?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>I will not think it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON JOHN</speaker>
            <line>If you dare not trust that you see, confess not</line>
            <line>that you know: if you will follow me, I will show</line>
            <line>you enough; and when you have seen more and heard</line>
            <line>more, proceed accordingly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>If I see any thing to-night why I should not marry</line>
            <line>her to-morrow in the congregation, where I should</line>
            <line>wed, there will I shame her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>And, as I wooed for thee to obtain her, I will join</line>
            <line>with thee to disgrace her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON JOHN</speaker>
            <line>I will disparage her no farther till you are my</line>
            <line>witnesses: bear it coldly but till midnight, and</line>
            <line>let the issue show itself.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON PEDRO</speaker>
            <line>O day untowardly turned!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>O mischief strangely thwarting!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DON JOHN</speaker>
            <line>O plague right well prevented! so will you say when</line>
            <line>you have seen the sequel.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  A street.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter DOGBERRY and VERGES with the Watch</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOGBERRY</speaker>
            <line>Are you good men and true?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VERGES</speaker>
            <line>Yea, or else it were pity but they should suffer</line>
            <line>salvation, body and soul.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOGBERRY</speaker>
            <line>Nay, that were a punishment too good for them, if</line>
            <line>they should have any allegiance in them, being</line>
            <line>chosen for the prince's watch.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VERGES</speaker>
            <line>Well, give them their charge, neighbour Dogberry.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOGBERRY</speaker>
            <line>First, who think you the most desertless man to be</line>
            <line>constable?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Watchman</speaker>
            <line>Hugh Otecake, sir, or George Seacole; for they can</line>
            <line>write and read.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOGBERRY</speaker>
            <line>Come hither, neighbour Seacole. God hath blessed</line>
            <line>you with a good name: to be a well-favoured man is</line>
            <line>the gift of fortune; but to write and read comes by nature.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Watchman</speaker>
            <line>Both which, master constable,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOGBERRY</speaker>
            <line>You have: I knew it would be your answer. Well,</line>
            <line>for your favour, sir, why, give God thanks, and make</line>
            <line>no boast of it; and for your writing and reading,</line>
            <line>let that appear when there is no need of such</line>
            <line>vanity. You are thought here to be the most</line>
            <line>senseless and fit man for the constable of the</line>
            <line>watch; therefore bear you the lantern. This is your</line>
            <line>charge: you shall comprehend all vagrom men; you are</line>
            <line>to bid any man stand, in the prince's name.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Watchman</speaker>
            <line>How if a' will not stand?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOGBERRY</speaker>
            <line>Why, then, take no note of him, but let him go; and</line>
            <line>presently call the rest of the watch together and</line>
            <line>thank God you are rid of a knave.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VERGES</speaker>
            <line>If he will not stand when he is bidden, he is none</line>
            <line>of the prince's subjects.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOGBERRY</speaker>
            <line>True, and they are to meddle with none but the</line>
            <line>prince's subjects. You shall also make no noise in</line>
            <line>the streets; for, for the watch to babble and to</line>
            <line>talk is most tolerable and not to be endured.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Watchman</speaker>
            <line>We will rather sleep than talk: we know what</line>
            <line>belongs to a watch.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOGBERRY</speaker>
            <line>Why, you speak like an ancient and most quiet</line>
            <line>watchman; for I cannot see how sleeping should</line>
            <line>offend: only, have a care that your bills be not</line>
            <line>stolen. Well, you are to call at all the</line>
            <line>ale-houses, and bid those that are drunk get them to bed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Watchman</speaker>
            <line>How if they will not?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOGBERRY</speaker>
            <line>Why, then, let them alone till they are sober: if</line>
            <line>they make you not then the better answer, you may</line>
            <line>say they are not the men you took them for.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Watchman</speaker>
            <line>Well, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOGBERRY</speaker>
            <line>If you meet a thief, you may suspect him, by virtue</line>
            <line>of your office, to be no true man; and, for such</line>
            <line>kind of men, the less you meddle or make with them,</line>
            <line>why the more is for your honesty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Watchman</speaker>
            <line>If we know him to be a thief, shall we not lay</line>
            <line>hands on him?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOGBERRY</speaker>
            <line>Truly, by your office, you may; but I think they</line>
            <line>that touch pitch will be defiled: the most peaceable</line>
            <line>way for you, if you do take a thief, is to let him</line>
            <line>show himself what he is and steal out of your company.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VERGES</speaker>
            <line>You have been always called a merciful man, partner.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOGBERRY</speaker>
            <line>Truly, I would not hang a dog by my will, much more</line>
            <line>a man who hath any honesty in him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VERGES</speaker>
            <line>If you hear a child cry in the night, you must call</line>
            <line>to the nurse and bid her still it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Watchman</speaker>
            <line>How if the nurse be asleep and will not hear us?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOGBERRY</speaker>
            <line>Why, then, depart in peace, and let the child wake</line>
            <line>her with crying; for the ewe that will not hear her</line>
            <line>lamb when it baes will never answer a calf when he bleats.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VERGES</speaker>
            <line>'Tis very true.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOGBERRY</speaker>
            <line>This is the end of the charge:--you, constable, are</line>
            <line>to present the prince's own person: if you meet the</line>
            <line>prince in the night, you may stay him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VERGES</speaker>
            <line>Nay, by'r our lady, that I think a' cannot.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOGBERRY</speaker>
            <line>Five shillings to one on't, with any man that knows</line>
            <line>the statutes, he may stay him: marry, not without</line>
            <line>the prince be willing; for, indeed, the watch ought</line>
            <line>to offend no man; and it is an offence to stay a</line>
            <line>man against his will.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VERGES</speaker>
            <line>By'r lady, I think it be so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOGBERRY</speaker>
            <line>Ha, ha, ha! Well, masters, good night: an there be</line>
            <line>any matter of weight chances, call up me: keep your</line>
            <line>fellows' counsels and your own; and good night.</line>
            <line>Come, neighbour.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Watchman</speaker>
            <line>Well, masters, we hear our charge: let us go sit here</line>
            <line>upon the church-bench till two, and then all to bed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOGBERRY</speaker>
            <line>One word more, honest neighbours. I pray you watch</line>
            <line>about Signior Leonato's door; for the wedding being</line>
            <line>there to-morrow, there is a great coil to-night.</line>
            <line>Adieu: be vigitant, I beseech you.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt DOGBERRY and VERGES</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Enter BORACHIO and CONRADE</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BORACHIO</speaker>
            <line>What Conrade!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Watchman</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  Peace! stir not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BORACHIO</speaker>
            <line>Conrade, I say!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CONRADE</speaker>
            <line>Here, man; I am at thy elbow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BORACHIO</speaker>
            <line>Mass, and my elbow itched; I thought there would a</line>
            <line>scab follow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CONRADE</speaker>
            <line>I will owe thee an answer for that: and now forward</line>
            <line>with thy tale.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BORACHIO</speaker>
            <line>Stand thee close, then, under this pent-house, for</line>
            <line>it drizzles rain; and I will, like a true drunkard,</line>
            <line>utter all to thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Watchman</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  Some treason, masters: yet stand close.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BORACHIO</speaker>
            <line>Therefore know I have earned of Don John a thousand ducats.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CONRADE</speaker>
            <line>Is it possible that any villany should be so dear?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BORACHIO</speaker>
            <line>Thou shouldst rather ask if it were possible any</line>
            <line>villany should be so rich; for when rich villains</line>
            <line>have need of poor ones, poor ones may make what</line>
            <line>price they will.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CONRADE</speaker>
            <line>I wonder at it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BORACHIO</speaker>
            <line>That shows thou art unconfirmed. Thou knowest that</line>
            <line>the fashion of a doublet, or a hat, or a cloak, is</line>
            <line>nothing to a man.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CONRADE</speaker>
            <line>Yes, it is apparel.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BORACHIO</speaker>
            <line>I mean, the fashion.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CONRADE</speaker>
            <line>Yes, the fashion is the fashion.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BORACHIO</speaker>
            <line>Tush! I may as well say the fool's the fool. But</line>
            <line>seest thou not what a deformed thief this fashion</line>
            <line>is?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Watchman</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  I know that Deformed; a' has been a vile</line>
            <line>thief this seven year; a' goes up and down like a</line>
            <line>gentleman: I remember his name.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BORACHIO</speaker>
            <line>Didst thou not hear somebody?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CONRADE</speaker>
            <line>No; 'twas the vane on the house.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BORACHIO</speaker>
            <line>Seest thou not, I say, what a deformed thief this</line>
            <line>fashion is? how giddily a' turns about all the hot</line>
            <line>bloods between fourteen and five-and-thirty?</line>
            <line>sometimes fashioning them like Pharaoh's soldiers</line>
            <line>in the reeky painting, sometime like god Bel's</line>
            <line>priests in the old church-window, sometime like the</line>
            <line>shaven Hercules in the smirched worm-eaten tapestry,</line>
            <line>where his codpiece seems as massy as his club?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CONRADE</speaker>
            <line>All this I see; and I see that the fashion wears</line>
            <line>out more apparel than the man. But art not thou</line>
            <line>thyself giddy with the fashion too, that thou hast</line>
            <line>shifted out of thy tale into telling me of the fashion?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BORACHIO</speaker>
            <line>Not so, neither: but know that I have to-night</line>
            <line>wooed Margaret, the Lady Hero's gentlewoman, by the</line>
            <line>name of Hero: she leans me out at her mistress'</line>
            <line>chamber-window, bids me a thousand times good</line>
            <line>night,--I tell this tale vilely:--I should first</line>
            <line>tell thee how the prince, Claudio and my master,</line>
            <line>planted and placed and possessed by my master Don</line>
            <line>John, saw afar off in the orchard this amiable encounter.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CONRADE</speaker>
            <line>And thought they Margaret was Hero?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BORACHIO</speaker>
            <line>Two of them did, the prince and Claudio; but the</line>
            <line>devil my master knew she was Margaret; and partly</line>
            <line>by his oaths, which first possessed them, partly by</line>
            <line>the dark night, which did deceive them, but chiefly</line>
            <line>by my villany, which did confirm any slander that</line>
            <line>Don John had made, away went Claudio enraged; swore</line>
            <line>he would meet her, as he was appointed, next morning</line>
            <line>at the temple, and there, before the whole</line>
            <line>congregation, shame her with what he saw o'er night</line>
            <line>and send her home again without a husband.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Watchman</speaker>
            <line>We charge you, in the prince's name, stand!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Watchman</speaker>
            <line>Call up the right master constable. We have here</line>
            <line>recovered the most dangerous piece of lechery that</line>
            <line>ever was known in the commonwealth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Watchman</speaker>
            <line>And one Deformed is one of them: I know him; a'</line>
            <line>wears a lock.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CONRADE</speaker>
            <line>Masters, masters,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Watchman</speaker>
            <line>You'll be made bring Deformed forth, I warrant you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CONRADE</speaker>
            <line>Masters,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Watchman</speaker>
            <line>Never speak: we charge you let us obey you to go with us.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BORACHIO</speaker>
            <line>We are like to prove a goodly commodity, being taken</line>
            <line>up of these men's bills.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CONRADE</speaker>
            <line>A commodity in question, I warrant you. Come, we'll obey you.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-4">
      <title>SCENE IV.  HERO's apartment.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter HERO, MARGARET, and URSULA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERO</speaker>
            <line>Good Ursula, wake my cousin Beatrice, and desire</line>
            <line>her to rise.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>URSULA</speaker>
            <line>I will, lady.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERO</speaker>
            <line>And bid her come hither.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>URSULA</speaker>
            <line>Well.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Troth, I think your other rabato were better.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERO</speaker>
            <line>No, pray thee, good Meg, I'll wear this.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>By my troth, 's not so good; and I warrant your</line>
            <line>cousin will say so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERO</speaker>
            <line>My cousin's a fool, and thou art another: I'll wear</line>
            <line>none but this.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>I like the new tire within excellently, if the hair</line>
            <line>were a thought browner; and your gown's a most rare</line>
            <line>fashion, i' faith. I saw the Duchess of Milan's</line>
            <line>gown that they praise so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERO</speaker>
            <line>O, that exceeds, they say.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>By my troth, 's but a night-gown in respect of</line>
            <line>yours: cloth o' gold, and cuts, and laced with</line>
            <line>silver, set with pearls, down sleeves, side sleeves,</line>
            <line>and skirts, round underborne with a bluish tinsel:</line>
            <line>but for a fine, quaint, graceful and excellent</line>
            <line>fashion, yours is worth ten on 't.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERO</speaker>
            <line>God give me joy to wear it! for my heart is</line>
            <line>exceeding heavy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>'Twill be heavier soon by the weight of a man.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERO</speaker>
            <line>Fie upon thee! art not ashamed?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Of what, lady? of speaking honourably? Is not</line>
            <line>marriage honourable in a beggar? Is not your lord</line>
            <line>honourable without marriage? I think you would have</line>
            <line>me say, 'saving your reverence, a husband:' and bad</line>
            <line>thinking do not wrest true speaking, I'll offend</line>
            <line>nobody: is there any harm in 'the heavier for a</line>
            <line>husband'? None, I think, and it be the right husband</line>
            <line>and the right wife; otherwise 'tis light, and not</line>
            <line>heavy: ask my Lady Beatrice else; here she comes.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter BEATRICE</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERO</speaker>
            <line>Good morrow, coz.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>Good morrow, sweet Hero.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERO</speaker>
            <line>Why how now? do you speak in the sick tune?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>I am out of all other tune, methinks.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Clap's into 'Light o' love;' that goes without a</line>
            <line>burden: do you sing it, and I'll dance it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>Ye light o' love, with your heels! then, if your</line>
            <line>husband have stables enough, you'll see he shall</line>
            <line>lack no barns.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>O illegitimate construction! I scorn that with my heels.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>'Tis almost five o'clock, cousin; tis time you were</line>
            <line>ready. By my troth, I am exceeding ill: heigh-ho!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>For a hawk, a horse, or a husband?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>For the letter that begins them all, H.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Well, and you be not turned Turk, there's no more</line>
            <line>sailing by the star.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>What means the fool, trow?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Nothing I; but God send every one their heart's desire!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERO</speaker>
            <line>These gloves the count sent me; they are an</line>
            <line>excellent perfume.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>I am stuffed, cousin; I cannot smell.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>A maid, and stuffed! there's goodly catching of cold.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>O, God help me! God help me! how long have you</line>
            <line>professed apprehension?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Even since you left it. Doth not my wit become me rarely?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>It is not seen enough, you should wear it in your</line>
            <line>cap. By my troth, I am sick.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Get you some of this distilled Carduus Benedictus,</line>
            <line>and lay it to your heart: it is the only thing for a qualm.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERO</speaker>
            <line>There thou prickest her with a thistle.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>Benedictus! why Benedictus? you have some moral in</line>
            <line>this Benedictus.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Moral! no, by my troth, I have no moral meaning; I</line>
            <line>meant, plain holy-thistle. You may think perchance</line>
            <line>that I think you are in love: nay, by'r lady, I am</line>
            <line>not such a fool to think what I list, nor I list</line>
            <line>not to think what I can, nor indeed I cannot think,</line>
            <line>if I would think my heart out of thinking, that you</line>
            <line>are in love or that you will be in love or that you</line>
            <line>can be in love. Yet Benedick was such another, and</line>
            <line>now is he become a man: he swore he would never</line>
            <line>marry, and yet now, in despite of his heart, he eats</line>
            <line>his meat without grudging: and how you may be</line>
            <line>converted I know not, but methinks you look with</line>
            <line>your eyes as other women do.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEATRICE</speaker>
            <line>What pace is this that thy tongue keeps?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Not a false gallop.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter URSULA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>URSULA</speaker>
            <line>Madam, withdraw: the prince, the count, Signior</line>
            <line>Benedick, Don John, and all the gallants of the</line>
            <line>town, are come to fetch you to church.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERO</speaker>
            <line>Help to dress me, good coz, good Meg, good Ursula.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-5">
      <title>SCENE V.  Another room in LEONATO'S house.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter LEONATO, with DOGBERRY and VERGES</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>What would you with me, honest neighbour?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOGBERRY</speaker>
            <line>Marry, sir, I would have some confidence with you</line>
            <line>that decerns you nearly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>Brief, I pray you; for you see it is a busy time with me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOGBERRY</speaker>
            <line>Marry, this it is, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VERGES</speaker>
            <line>Yes, in truth it is, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>What is it, my good friends?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOGBERRY</speaker>
            <line>Goodman Verges, sir, speaks a little off the</line>
            <line>matter: an old man, sir, and his wits are not so</line>
            <line>blunt as, God help, I would desire they were; but,</line>
            <line>in faith, honest as the skin between his brows.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VERGES</speaker>
            <line>Yes, I thank God I am as honest as any man living</line>
            <line>that is an old man and no honester than I.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOGBERRY</speaker>
            <line>Comparisons are odorous: palabras, neighbour Verges.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>Neighbours, you are tedious.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOGBERRY</speaker>
            <line>It pleases your worship to say so, but we are the</line>
            <line>poor duke's officers; but truly, for mine own part,</line>
            <line>if I were as tedious as a king, I could find it in</line>
            <line>my heart to bestow it all of your worship.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>All thy tediousness on me, ah?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOGBERRY</speaker>
            <line>Yea, an 'twere a thousand pound more than 'tis; for</line>
            <line>I hear as good exclamation on your worship as of any</line>
            <line>man in the city; and though I be but a poor man, I</line>
            <line>am glad to hear it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VERGES</speaker>
            <line>And so am I.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>I would fain know what you have to say.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VERGES</speaker>
            <line>Marry, sir, our watch to-night, excepting your</line>
            <line>worship's presence, ha' ta'en a couple of as arrant</line>
            <line>knaves as any in Messina.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOGBERRY</speaker>
            <line>A good old man, sir; he will be talking: as they</line>
            <line>say, when the age is in, the wit is out: God help</line>
            <line>us! it is a world to see. Well said, i' faith,</line>
            <line>neighbour Verges: well, God's a good man; an two men</line>
            <line>ride of a horse, one must ride behind. An honest</line>
            <line>soul, i' faith, sir; by my troth he is, as ever</line>
            <line>broke bread; but God is to be worshipped; all men</line>
            <line>are not alike; alas, good neighbour!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>Indeed, neighbour, he comes too short of you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOGBERRY</speaker>
            <line>Gifts that God gives.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>I must leave you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOGBERRY</speaker>
            <line>One word, sir: our watch, sir, have indeed</line>
            <line>comprehended two aspicious persons, and we would</line>
            <line>have them this morning examined before your worship.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>Take their examination yourself and bring it me: I</line>
            <line>am now in great haste, as it may appear unto you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOGBERRY</speaker>
            <line>It shall be suffigance.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>Drink some wine ere you go: fare you well.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter a Messenger</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>My lord, they stay for you to give your daughter to</line>
            <line>her husband.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONATO</speaker>
            <line>I'll wait upon them: I am ready.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt LEONATO and Messenger</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOGBERRY</speaker>
            <line>Go, good partner, go, get you to Francis Seacole;</line>
            <line>bid him bring his pen and inkhorn to the gaol: we</line>
            <line>are now to examination these men.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VERGES</speaker>
            <line>And we must do it wisely.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DOGBERRY</speaker>
            <line>We will spare for no wit, I warrant you; here's</line>
            <line>that shall drive some of them to a non-come: only</line>
            <line>get the learned writer to set down our</line>
            <line>excommunication and meet me at the gaol.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>