<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.org:doctypes:dita:topic" "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.org:doctypes:dita:topic">
<topic
  id="topic-1">
  <title>Publishers and Publishing Documents</title>
  <body>
    <p>For the purposes of this project, "publishing documents" means documents produced as the
      primary business deliverable of a Publishing enterprise and usually representing a profit
      center. These publication types include:<ul>
        <li>Commercially-published fiction and non-fiction trade books, e.g., novels, biography,
          general-non-fiction, self-help, etc. These are documents that are mostly or entirely
          narrative.</li>
        <li>Textbooks: primary, secondary, post-secondary, etc. These are documents that can reflect
          intensive designs and complex combinations of design elements.</li>
        <li>Periodicals, including glossy magazines, journals, and newsletters.</li>
        <li>Travel and nature guides.</li>
        <li>Encyclopedias and dictionaries.</li>
        <li>General-audience technical publications, e.g., after-market automotive repair
          manuals.</li>
        <li>General-audience training and testing, such as standardized test preparation, industrial
          certification training and testing, etc.</li>
      </ul></p>
    <p>There is, of course, significant overlap between the domains of publishing documents, business documents, and technical documents. However, Publishers and publishing are usually distinguished by the following business characteristics and drivers:<ul>
      <li>Typographic quality and distinction is often a primary requirement. Publications have to look good and be visually distinguished from their competitors in the marketplace.</li>
      <li>Publishing deadlines are driven by external, invariant forces, such as school calendars, industry events, world events, marketing goals and requirements, etc.</li>
      <li>Re-use of content on a small scale (below the topic level) is usually not a requirement or not a common requirement.</li>
      <li>Repurposing of content at relatively large granularity to different media or in different publications is usually a very strong requirement (e.g., syndication of articles or chapters, print, Web, and e-book delivery of entire publications, etc.)</li>
      <li>Authoring is done by outside authors for whom the primary or only practical authoring tool is Microsoft Word or whatever the Author happens to use.</li>
      <li>Publishing business processes must tolerate content changes made very late in the process, even when a publication has been typeset and the "plates" are on the printer.</li>
      <li>Localization, at least by the original publishers, is not a requirement for many, if not most, Publishing documents.</li>
      </ul></p>
    <p>These characteristics of Publishers and publishing documents distinguish them from technical
      documents and from business documents, primarily in the way that the business realities
      determine both the nature of the publishing development and fulfillment process and the nature
      of the tools and technology that can be brought to bear. For example, for most publishing
      documents, it is simply not practical to use traditional batch-composition technology because
      every publication is a unique page design and because human intervention is almost always
      needed to ensure appropriate typographic quality. By the same token, the XML-based authoring
      tools on which Technical Documentors have depended for decades are simply impractical for use
      in the 3rd-party authoring of most publications. Likewise, XML design decisions that reflect
      Technical Documentation needs for consistency and repeatability are often exactly the wrong
      decisions for Publishers, who must be able to support arbitrary and unpredictable information
      structures and formatting requirements.</p>
    <p>Fortunately, the DITA standard is both sufficiently general and sufficiently powerful to
      provide a compelling basis for Publishing-specific XML applications. DITA, by its unique
      characteristics as an XML application standard, provides the following value to publishers:<ul>
        <li>Minimizes the cost of startup of XML-based publishing processes. This is entirely
          because of the Specialization feature of the DITA standard. This project helps to reduce
          the inherently low cost even more by providing a starter set of DITA system components
          that all Publishers need. Because DITA-aware processors, content management systems, and
          editors should be able to work with any DITA-based content regardless of how it's been
          specialized, the cost of acquiring and configuring software components should be
          significantly lower for DITA-based systems than for any other XML-based system, simply
          because most software features should <b>just work</b> out of the box for <i>all valid
            DITA content</i>.</li>
        <li>Minimizes the cost of ongoing system maintenance and enhancement. Because of the nature
          of how Specialization works, new software components should work for all new
          specializations <i>without modification</i>. This means that systems will tend to require
          less change over time as the markup design evolves, because processing that worked before
          continues to work. Assuming good engineering practices are followed that take advantage of
          specialization, adding new functionality to an existing system should get easier over
          time, not harder.</li>
        <li>Maximizes the inherent interchangability of content. Again, this is entirely because of
          the Specialization feature of the DITA standard: DITA-based content from one Publisher can
          be used, immediately, with DITA-based content and tools of another Publisher <i>without
            modification.</i>. This is irrespective of how either party has specialized their
          content to add the custom elements needed to meet their local business requirements.</li>
      </ul></p>
  </body>
</topic>
