<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE task PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:task" "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:task">
<task
  id="taskId">
  <title>Using the DITA For Publishers Source</title>
  <taskbody>
    <context>
      <p>You can also use the DITA For Publishers materials directly from the project's source code control system. You can also use the materials as a model for local development setups for developing your own DITA specializations. The materials are managed using git through SourceForge. You can use any git client to access the source code, such as TortoisGit, the Atlasian SourceTree tool, or a git plugin for Eclipse.</p>
    </context>
    <steps>
      <step>
        <cmd>Using a git client, clone the repository to your local machine, following the instructions on the project's code access page: <xref format="html"
          href="https://sourceforge.net/p/dita4publishers/git" scope="external"
          >https://sourceforge.net/p/dita4publishers/git</xref>. (Note that the "rc" branch has the latest code and is the one you should normally be working with.)</cmd>
      </step>
      <step>
        <cmd>Create a file named <filepath>build.properties</filepath> or <filepath
            >.build.properties</filepath>, either in the project's directory or in your home
          directory.</cmd>
        <info>
          <p>This file is used by the project's Ant build script to configure the location of the
            DITA Open Toolkit.</p>
        </info>
      </step>
      <step>
        <cmd>Edit the <filepath>build.properties</filepath> file you just created and add the
          property "dita-ot-dir".</cmd>
        <stepresult>
          <p>The property specification should look like
            this:<codeblock>dita-ot-dir=<i>{path-to-toolkit}</i></codeblock></p>
          <p>Where "<i>{path-to-toolkit}</i> is wherever directory contains your Toolkit, e.g.
            "c:/dita-ot" or "/Applications/Oxygen/frameworks/dita/DITA-OT" or whatever.</p>
          <p>If you use Oxygen or similar tool that provides a Toolkit and maintain multiple
            versions of the tool, it can be useful to define a separate property for the editor
            location,
            e.g.:<codeblock>oxygen_home=/Applications/oxygen_10.2
dita-ot-dir=${oxygen_home}/frameworks/dita/DITA-OT</codeblock></p>
        </stepresult>
      </step>
      <step>
        <cmd>Save the file.</cmd>
      </step>
      <step>
        <cmd>Test the DITA for Publishers' Ant file by running the target
          "deploy-toolkit-plugins".</cmd>
        <info>
          <p>From a command line where the dita4publishers directory is the current directory, run
            this command (assuming Ant in your PATH):</p>
          <codeblock>ant deploy-toolkit-plugins</codeblock>
          <p>You should see messages indicating that the plugins have been copied to your toolkit
            and the integrate task has been run.</p>
        </info>
      </step>
    </steps>
    <result>
      <p>You should now be ready to use the Publishing specializations with the Toolkit and edit
        documents that use them using any XML editor that uses your Toolkit to get the DTDs its
        needs (e.g., OxygenXML).</p>
      <p>Other editors may require more work to configure to enable editing.</p>
    </result>
  </taskbody>
</task>
