<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:concept" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="conceptId">
  <title>Variables Domain</title>
  <shortdesc>The variables domain provides markup for declaring and referencing
    variables that are scoped by the map and topic hierarchy.</shortdesc>
  <conbody>
    <p>Variables are declared in map metadata, topicref metadata, topic prologs,
      and topic content. Variable definitions are specializations of
      <xmlelem>data</xmlelem> and may occur wherever <xmlelem>data</xmlelem> is
      allowed.</p>
    <p>References may occur anywhere that <xmlelem>keyword</xmlelem> or
      <xmlelem>text</xmlelem> is allowed.</p>
    <p>Variable resolution is done at output processing time, meaning the last
      step in a normal DITA process. This means that all content references and
      all filtering should have been applied by the time variable references and
      definitions are processed. This means you can use normal content reference
      and filtering facilities to determine the effective values of variable
      definitions and variable references.</p>
    <p>Note that as of D4P version 0.9.19 the Variables mechanism does not
      attempt to cover all use cases. It is intentionally simple so as to make
      implementation easy and foster use and experimentation in order to gather
      futher requirements. A complete variables facility, such as would be
      appropriate for inclusion in the DITA specification, could be quite a bit
      more complicated. </p>
  </conbody>
  <concept
    id="topic_yyg_twl_y3">
    <title>Variable Definitions:
      <xmlelem>d4p-variable-definition</xmlelem></title>
    <conbody>
      <p>Variable definitions are defined using the
        <xmlelem>d4p-variable-definition</xmlelem> element and always contained
        by the <xmlelem>d4p-variable-definitions</xmlelem>
        element:<codeblock>  &lt;topicmeta>
    <b>&lt;d4p-variable-definitions></b>
      <b>&lt;d4p-variable-definition</b> name="prodname"
       >&lt;tm>MyProduct&lt;/tm>&lt;/d4p-variable-definition>
    &lt;/d4p-variable-definitions>
  &lt;/topicmeta></codeblock></p>
      <p>The <xmlatt>name</xmlatt> attribute is the name of the variable, by
        which it is referenced using <xmlelem>d4p-variableref-keyword</xmlelem>
        or <xmlelem>d4p-variableref-text</xmlelem>.</p>
      <p>The attribute value may be specified either using the
        <xmlatt>value</xmlatt> attribute or in the content of the
        <xmlelem>d4p-variable-definition</xmlelem> element. If
        <xmlatt>value</xmlatt> is specified then the content of the element is
        ignored. This allows you to use the content of the variable definition
        as documentation for the variable if you choose.</p>
      <p>If you put the variable value in the content then you may use any
        markup allowed where the variable reference is allowed (or, more
        accurately, where the content can be usefully and correctly processed,
        which is not quite the same thing).</p>
      <p>Note that variable references are not content references and so the
        same strict content model consistency constraints do not necessarily
        apply. However, you should be careful to only put markup in variables
        that will be correctly and appropriately processed in the context where
        the variables are referenced. In practice, this means limiting your
        content to normal inline markup and avoiding things like footnotes,
        cross references, block elements, and so on. If you want to impose more
        constraints on what is allowed in variable definitions, you can use
        constraint modules or further specialization to do so. The base markup
        as defined by the D4P project errs on the side of generality.</p>
    </conbody>
  </concept>
  <concept
    id="concept_k13_zzl_y3">
    <title>Variable References: <xmlelem>d4p-variableref_keyword</xmlelem> and
      <xmlelem>d4p-variableref_text</xmlelem></title>
    <conbody>
      <p>Variables may be referenced in any context where
        <xmlelem>keyword</xmlelem> or <xmlelem>text</xmlelem> are allowed, using
        the corresponding specialization,
        <xmlelem>d4p-variableref_keyword</xmlelem> or
        <xmlelem>d4p-variableref_text</xmlelem>.</p>
      <p>The content of the reference element is the variable
        name:<codeblock>&lt;p>The <b>&lt;d4p-variableref_keyword>prodname&lt;/d4p-variableref_keyword></b> 
product...&lt;/p></codeblock></p>
      <p>If the variable cannot be resolved (or you don't have processing
        support for D4P variables installed, then the content of the reference
        element is used, just as for normal <xmlelem>keyword</xmlelem> or
        <xmlelem>text</xmlelem> processing. If the variable can be resolved,
        then the nearest variable definition is used to determine the effective
        value.</p>
      <p>The effective binding for a variable is determined as follows:<ol
        id="ol_h1g_r1m_y3">
        <li>In all cases, only the direct element and map tree ancestry of the
          reference is considered. Definitions in sibling topics, maps, or
          topicrefs are never considered for the purpose of determining the
          effective definition for a given reference. </li>
        <li>Definitions in topic prologs are used only when no other effective
          definition is available. Variable definitions within topic prologs
          serve as default or fallback values. As for other definitions, the
          nearest ancestor topic prolog with a definition determines the
          effective fallback value.</li>
        <li>The nearest definition within ancestor elements determines the
          effective binding. For elements within topics, this includes any
          ancestry within the topic body. Note that the placement of the
          definition within the ancestor is not important—in particular, the
          variable definition could come after the subelement that contains the
          reference. </li>
        <li>For topics referenced from maps, if there is no definition within
          the topic, then the nearest definition in the map tree ancestry
          determines the effective binding. That is, definitions are scoped by
          topicrefs such that the definition in the nearest topicref to the
          topic that references the topic provides the binding.</li>
        <li>If the variable is not defined within the topic or within any
          topicref in the map tree ancestry, then any definition within the
          map's metadata is used. This means that root maps may define default
          values for variables.</li>
        <li>If a variable is not defined anywhere, processors may choose to
          provide default values or otherwise allow for run-time definition of
          variables.</li>
        </ol></p>
      <note>Because submap metadata is not always maintained or necessarily even
        available in all processing contexts, variables defined in the
        <xmlelem>topicmeta</xmlelem> child of submap elements will be ignored.
        If you want to define variables in submaps, use a wrappter topicref
        element around the topicrefs, either <xmlelem>topicgroup</xmlelem> or
        another allowed topicref type.</note>
      <p>Stated more informally, the intent of these rules is that elements
        define variable scopes within topics and topicrefs define scopes within
        maps.</p>
    </conbody>
  </concept>
</concept>
