<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net/doctypes/dita/shakespear/dtd/act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-1">
   <title>ACT I</title>
   <prologue id="act-1-prologue">
      <title>PROLOGUE</title>
      <prologue-body>
         <speech>
            <speaker/>
            <line>Two households, both alike in dignity,</line>
            <line>In fair Verona, where we lay our scene,</line>
            <line>From ancient grudge break to new mutiny,</line>
            <line>Where civil blood makes civil hands unclean.</line>
            <line>From forth the fatal loins of these two foes</line>
            <line>A pair of star-cross'd lovers take their life;</line>
            <line>Whole misadventured piteous overthrows</line>
            <line>Do with their death bury their parents' strife.</line>
            <line>The fearful passage of their death-mark'd love,</line>
            <line>And the continuance of their parents' rage,</line>
            <line>Which, but their children's end, nought could remove,</line>
            <line>Is now the two hours' traffic of our stage;</line>
            <line>The which if you with patient ears attend,</line>
            <line>What here shall miss, our toil shall strive to mend.</line>
         </speech>
      </prologue-body>
   </prologue>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  Verona. A public place.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter SAMPSON and GREGORY, of the house of Capulet,
armed with swords and bucklers</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SAMPSON</speaker>
            <line>Gregory, o' my word, we'll not carry coals.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GREGORY</speaker>
            <line>No, for then we should be colliers.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SAMPSON</speaker>
            <line>I mean, an we be in choler, we'll draw.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GREGORY</speaker>
            <line>Ay, while you live, draw your neck out o' the collar.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SAMPSON</speaker>
            <line>I strike quickly, being moved.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GREGORY</speaker>
            <line>But thou art not quickly moved to strike.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SAMPSON</speaker>
            <line>A dog of the house of Montague moves me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GREGORY</speaker>
            <line>To move is to stir; and to be valiant is to stand:</line>
            <line>therefore, if thou art moved, thou runn'st away.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SAMPSON</speaker>
            <line>A dog of that house shall move me to stand: I will</line>
            <line>take the wall of any man or maid of Montague's.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GREGORY</speaker>
            <line>That shows thee a weak slave; for the weakest goes</line>
            <line>to the wall.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SAMPSON</speaker>
            <line>True; and therefore women, being the weaker vessels,</line>
            <line>are ever thrust to the wall: therefore I will push</line>
            <line>Montague's men from the wall, and thrust his maids</line>
            <line>to the wall.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GREGORY</speaker>
            <line>The quarrel is between our masters and us their men.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SAMPSON</speaker>
            <line>'Tis all one, I will show myself a tyrant: when I</line>
            <line>have fought with the men, I will be cruel with the</line>
            <line>maids, and cut off their heads.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GREGORY</speaker>
            <line>The heads of the maids?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SAMPSON</speaker>
            <line>Ay, the heads of the maids, or their maidenheads;</line>
            <line>take it in what sense thou wilt.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GREGORY</speaker>
            <line>They must take it in sense that feel it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SAMPSON</speaker>
            <line>Me they shall feel while I am able to stand: and</line>
            <line>'tis known I am a pretty piece of flesh.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GREGORY</speaker>
            <line>'Tis well thou art not fish; if thou hadst, thou</line>
            <line>hadst been poor John. Draw thy tool! here comes</line>
            <line>two of the house of the Montagues.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SAMPSON</speaker>
            <line>My naked weapon is out: quarrel, I will back thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GREGORY</speaker>
            <line>How! turn thy back and run?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SAMPSON</speaker>
            <line>Fear me not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GREGORY</speaker>
            <line>No, marry; I fear thee!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SAMPSON</speaker>
            <line>Let us take the law of our sides; let them begin.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GREGORY</speaker>
            <line>I will frown as I pass by, and let them take it as</line>
            <line>they list.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SAMPSON</speaker>
            <line>Nay, as they dare. I will bite my thumb at them;</line>
            <line>which is a disgrace to them, if they bear it.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter ABRAHAM and BALTHASAR</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ABRAHAM</speaker>
            <line>Do you bite your thumb at us, sir?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SAMPSON</speaker>
            <line>I do bite my thumb, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ABRAHAM</speaker>
            <line>Do you bite your thumb at us, sir?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SAMPSON</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside to GREGORY</stagedir>  Is the law of our side, if I say</line>
            <line>ay?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GREGORY</speaker>
            <line>No.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SAMPSON</speaker>
            <line>No, sir, I do not bite my thumb at you, sir, but I</line>
            <line>bite my thumb, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GREGORY</speaker>
            <line>Do you quarrel, sir?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ABRAHAM</speaker>
            <line>Quarrel sir! no, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SAMPSON</speaker>
            <line>If you do, sir, I am for you: I serve as good a man as you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ABRAHAM</speaker>
            <line>No better.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SAMPSON</speaker>
            <line>Well, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GREGORY</speaker>
            <line>Say 'better:' here comes one of my master's kinsmen.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SAMPSON</speaker>
            <line>Yes, better, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ABRAHAM</speaker>
            <line>You lie.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SAMPSON</speaker>
            <line>Draw, if you be men. Gregory, remember thy swashing blow.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>They fight</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Enter BENVOLIO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>Part, fools!</line>
            <line>Put up your swords; you know not what you do.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Beats down their swords</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Enter TYBALT</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TYBALT</speaker>
            <line>What, art thou drawn among these heartless hinds?</line>
            <line>Turn thee, Benvolio, look upon thy death.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>I do but keep the peace: put up thy sword,</line>
            <line>Or manage it to part these men with me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TYBALT</speaker>
            <line>What, drawn, and talk of peace! I hate the word,</line>
            <line>As I hate hell, all Montagues, and thee:</line>
            <line>Have at thee, coward!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>They fight</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Enter, several of both houses, who join the fray;
then enter Citizens, with clubs</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>Clubs, bills, and partisans! strike! beat them down!</line>
            <line>Down with the Capulets! down with the Montagues!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter CAPULET in his gown, and LADY CAPULET</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAPULET</speaker>
            <line>What noise is this? Give me my long sword, ho!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY CAPULET</speaker>
            <line>A crutch, a crutch! why call you for a sword?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAPULET</speaker>
            <line>My sword, I say! Old Montague is come,</line>
            <line>And flourishes his blade in spite of me.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter MONTAGUE and LADY MONTAGUE</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MONTAGUE</speaker>
            <line>Thou villain Capulet,--Hold me not, let me go.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY MONTAGUE</speaker>
            <line>Thou shalt not stir a foot to seek a foe.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter PRINCE, with Attendants</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE</speaker>
            <line>Rebellious subjects, enemies to peace,</line>
            <line>Profaners of this neighbour-stained steel,--</line>
            <line>Will they not hear? What, ho! you men, you beasts,</line>
            <line>That quench the fire of your pernicious rage</line>
            <line>With purple fountains issuing from your veins,</line>
            <line>On pain of torture, from those bloody hands</line>
            <line>Throw your mistemper'd weapons to the ground,</line>
            <line>And hear the sentence of your moved prince.</line>
            <line>Three civil brawls, bred of an airy word,</line>
            <line>By thee, old Capulet, and Montague,</line>
            <line>Have thrice disturb'd the quiet of our streets,</line>
            <line>And made Verona's ancient citizens</line>
            <line>Cast by their grave beseeming ornaments,</line>
            <line>To wield old partisans, in hands as old,</line>
            <line>Canker'd with peace, to part your canker'd hate:</line>
            <line>If ever you disturb our streets again,</line>
            <line>Your lives shall pay the forfeit of the peace.</line>
            <line>For this time, all the rest depart away:</line>
            <line>You Capulet; shall go along with me:</line>
            <line>And, Montague, come you this afternoon,</line>
            <line>To know our further pleasure in this case,</line>
            <line>To old Free-town, our common judgment-place.</line>
            <line>Once more, on pain of death, all men depart.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt all but MONTAGUE, LADY MONTAGUE, and BENVOLIO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MONTAGUE</speaker>
            <line>Who set this ancient quarrel new abroach?</line>
            <line>Speak, nephew, were you by when it began?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>Here were the servants of your adversary,</line>
            <line>And yours, close fighting ere I did approach:</line>
            <line>I drew to part them: in the instant came</line>
            <line>The fiery Tybalt, with his sword prepared,</line>
            <line>Which, as he breathed defiance to my ears,</line>
            <line>He swung about his head and cut the winds,</line>
            <line>Who nothing hurt withal hiss'd him in scorn:</line>
            <line>While we were interchanging thrusts and blows,</line>
            <line>Came more and more and fought on part and part,</line>
            <line>Till the prince came, who parted either part.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY MONTAGUE</speaker>
            <line>O, where is Romeo? saw you him to-day?</line>
            <line>Right glad I am he was not at this fray.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>Madam, an hour before the worshipp'd sun</line>
            <line>Peer'd forth the golden window of the east,</line>
            <line>A troubled mind drave me to walk abroad;</line>
            <line>Where, underneath the grove of sycamore</line>
            <line>That westward rooteth from the city's side,</line>
            <line>So early walking did I see your son:</line>
            <line>Towards him I made, but he was ware of me</line>
            <line>And stole into the covert of the wood:</line>
            <line>I, measuring his affections by my own,</line>
            <line>That most are busied when they're most alone,</line>
            <line>Pursued my humour not pursuing his,</line>
            <line>And gladly shunn'd who gladly fled from me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MONTAGUE</speaker>
            <line>Many a morning hath he there been seen,</line>
            <line>With tears augmenting the fresh morning dew.</line>
            <line>Adding to clouds more clouds with his deep sighs;</line>
            <line>But all so soon as the all-cheering sun</line>
            <line>Should in the furthest east begin to draw</line>
            <line>The shady curtains from Aurora's bed,</line>
            <line>Away from the light steals home my heavy son,</line>
            <line>And private in his chamber pens himself,</line>
            <line>Shuts up his windows, locks far daylight out</line>
            <line>And makes himself an artificial night:</line>
            <line>Black and portentous must this humour prove,</line>
            <line>Unless good counsel may the cause remove.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>My noble uncle, do you know the cause?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MONTAGUE</speaker>
            <line>I neither know it nor can learn of him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>Have you importuned him by any means?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MONTAGUE</speaker>
            <line>Both by myself and many other friends:</line>
            <line>But he, his own affections' counsellor,</line>
            <line>Is to himself--I will not say how true--</line>
            <line>But to himself so secret and so close,</line>
            <line>So far from sounding and discovery,</line>
            <line>As is the bud bit with an envious worm,</line>
            <line>Ere he can spread his sweet leaves to the air,</line>
            <line>Or dedicate his beauty to the sun.</line>
            <line>Could we but learn from whence his sorrows grow.</line>
            <line>We would as willingly give cure as know.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter ROMEO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>See, where he comes: so please you, step aside;</line>
            <line>I'll know his grievance, or be much denied.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MONTAGUE</speaker>
            <line>I would thou wert so happy by thy stay,</line>
            <line>To hear true shrift. Come, madam, let's away.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt MONTAGUE and LADY MONTAGUE</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>Good-morrow, cousin.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROMEO</speaker>
            <line>Is the day so young?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>But new struck nine.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROMEO</speaker>
            <line>Ay me! sad hours seem long.</line>
            <line>Was that my father that went hence so fast?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>It was. What sadness lengthens Romeo's hours?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROMEO</speaker>
            <line>Not having that, which, having, makes them short.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>In love?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROMEO</speaker>
            <line>Out--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>Of love?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROMEO</speaker>
            <line>Out of her favour, where I am in love.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>Alas, that love, so gentle in his view,</line>
            <line>Should be so tyrannous and rough in proof!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROMEO</speaker>
            <line>Alas, that love, whose view is muffled still,</line>
            <line>Should, without eyes, see pathways to his will!</line>
            <line>Where shall we dine? O me! What fray was here?</line>
            <line>Yet tell me not, for I have heard it all.</line>
            <line>Here's much to do with hate, but more with love.</line>
            <line>Why, then, O brawling love! O loving hate!</line>
            <line>O any thing, of nothing first create!</line>
            <line>O heavy lightness! serious vanity!</line>
            <line>Mis-shapen chaos of well-seeming forms!</line>
            <line>Feather of lead, bright smoke, cold fire,</line>
            <line>sick health!</line>
            <line>Still-waking sleep, that is not what it is!</line>
            <line>This love feel I, that feel no love in this.</line>
            <line>Dost thou not laugh?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>No, coz, I rather weep.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROMEO</speaker>
            <line>Good heart, at what?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>At thy good heart's oppression.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROMEO</speaker>
            <line>Why, such is love's transgression.</line>
            <line>Griefs of mine own lie heavy in my breast,</line>
            <line>Which thou wilt propagate, to have it prest</line>
            <line>With more of thine: this love that thou hast shown</line>
            <line>Doth add more grief to too much of mine own.</line>
            <line>Love is a smoke raised with the fume of sighs;</line>
            <line>Being purged, a fire sparkling in lovers' eyes;</line>
            <line>Being vex'd a sea nourish'd with lovers' tears:</line>
            <line>What is it else? a madness most discreet,</line>
            <line>A choking gall and a preserving sweet.</line>
            <line>Farewell, my coz.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>Soft! I will go along;</line>
            <line>An if you leave me so, you do me wrong.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROMEO</speaker>
            <line>Tut, I have lost myself; I am not here;</line>
            <line>This is not Romeo, he's some other where.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>Tell me in sadness, who is that you love.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROMEO</speaker>
            <line>What, shall I groan and tell thee?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>Groan! why, no.</line>
            <line>But sadly tell me who.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROMEO</speaker>
            <line>Bid a sick man in sadness make his will:</line>
            <line>Ah, word ill urged to one that is so ill!</line>
            <line>In sadness, cousin, I do love a woman.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>I aim'd so near, when I supposed you loved.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROMEO</speaker>
            <line>A right good mark-man! And she's fair I love.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>A right fair mark, fair coz, is soonest hit.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROMEO</speaker>
            <line>Well, in that hit you miss: she'll not be hit</line>
            <line>With Cupid's arrow; she hath Dian's wit;</line>
            <line>And, in strong proof of chastity well arm'd,</line>
            <line>From love's weak childish bow she lives unharm'd.</line>
            <line>She will not stay the siege of loving terms,</line>
            <line>Nor bide the encounter of assailing eyes,</line>
            <line>Nor ope her lap to saint-seducing gold:</line>
            <line>O, she is rich in beauty, only poor,</line>
            <line>That when she dies with beauty dies her store.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>Then she hath sworn that she will still live chaste?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROMEO</speaker>
            <line>She hath, and in that sparing makes huge waste,</line>
            <line>For beauty starved with her severity</line>
            <line>Cuts beauty off from all posterity.</line>
            <line>She is too fair, too wise, wisely too fair,</line>
            <line>To merit bliss by making me despair:</line>
            <line>She hath forsworn to love, and in that vow</line>
            <line>Do I live dead that live to tell it now.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>Be ruled by me, forget to think of her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROMEO</speaker>
            <line>O, teach me how I should forget to think.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>By giving liberty unto thine eyes;</line>
            <line>Examine other beauties.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROMEO</speaker>
            <line>'Tis the way</line>
            <line>To call hers exquisite, in question more:</line>
            <line>These happy masks that kiss fair ladies' brows</line>
            <line>Being black put us in mind they hide the fair;</line>
            <line>He that is strucken blind cannot forget</line>
            <line>The precious treasure of his eyesight lost:</line>
            <line>Show me a mistress that is passing fair,</line>
            <line>What doth her beauty serve, but as a note</line>
            <line>Where I may read who pass'd that passing fair?</line>
            <line>Farewell: thou canst not teach me to forget.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>I'll pay that doctrine, or else die in debt.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  A street.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter CAPULET, PARIS, and Servant</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAPULET</speaker>
            <line>But Montague is bound as well as I,</line>
            <line>In penalty alike; and 'tis not hard, I think,</line>
            <line>For men so old as we to keep the peace.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PARIS</speaker>
            <line>Of honourable reckoning are you both;</line>
            <line>And pity 'tis you lived at odds so long.</line>
            <line>But now, my lord, what say you to my suit?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAPULET</speaker>
            <line>But saying o'er what I have said before:</line>
            <line>My child is yet a stranger in the world;</line>
            <line>She hath not seen the change of fourteen years,</line>
            <line>Let two more summers wither in their pride,</line>
            <line>Ere we may think her ripe to be a bride.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PARIS</speaker>
            <line>Younger than she are happy mothers made.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAPULET</speaker>
            <line>And too soon marr'd are those so early made.</line>
            <line>The earth hath swallow'd all my hopes but she,</line>
            <line>She is the hopeful lady of my earth:</line>
            <line>But woo her, gentle Paris, get her heart,</line>
            <line>My will to her consent is but a part;</line>
            <line>An she agree, within her scope of choice</line>
            <line>Lies my consent and fair according voice.</line>
            <line>This night I hold an old accustom'd feast,</line>
            <line>Whereto I have invited many a guest,</line>
            <line>Such as I love; and you, among the store,</line>
            <line>One more, most welcome, makes my number more.</line>
            <line>At my poor house look to behold this night</line>
            <line>Earth-treading stars that make dark heaven light:</line>
            <line>Such comfort as do lusty young men feel</line>
            <line>When well-apparell'd April on the heel</line>
            <line>Of limping winter treads, even such delight</line>
            <line>Among fresh female buds shall you this night</line>
            <line>Inherit at my house; hear all, all see,</line>
            <line>And like her most whose merit most shall be:</line>
            <line>Which on more view, of many mine being one</line>
            <line>May stand in number, though in reckoning none,</line>
            <line>Come, go with me.</line>
            <stagedir>To Servant, giving a paper</stagedir>
            <line>Go, sirrah, trudge about</line>
            <line>Through fair Verona; find those persons out</line>
            <line>Whose names are written there, and to them say,</line>
            <line>My house and welcome on their pleasure stay.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt CAPULET and PARIS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>Find them out whose names are written here! It is</line>
            <line>written, that the shoemaker should meddle with his</line>
            <line>yard, and the tailor with his last, the fisher with</line>
            <line>his pencil, and the painter with his nets; but I am</line>
            <line>sent to find those persons whose names are here</line>
            <line>writ, and can never find what names the writing</line>
            <line>person hath here writ. I must to the learned.--In good time.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter BENVOLIO and ROMEO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>Tut, man, one fire burns out another's burning,</line>
            <line>One pain is lessen'd by another's anguish;</line>
            <line>Turn giddy, and be holp by backward turning;</line>
            <line>One desperate grief cures with another's languish:</line>
            <line>Take thou some new infection to thy eye,</line>
            <line>And the rank poison of the old will die.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROMEO</speaker>
            <line>Your plaintain-leaf is excellent for that.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>For what, I pray thee?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROMEO</speaker>
            <line>For your broken shin.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>Why, Romeo, art thou mad?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROMEO</speaker>
            <line>Not mad, but bound more than a mad-man is;</line>
            <line>Shut up in prison, kept without my food,</line>
            <line>Whipp'd and tormented and--God-den, good fellow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>God gi' god-den. I pray, sir, can you read?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROMEO</speaker>
            <line>Ay, mine own fortune in my misery.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>Perhaps you have learned it without book: but, I</line>
            <line>pray, can you read any thing you see?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROMEO</speaker>
            <line>Ay, if I know the letters and the language.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>Ye say honestly: rest you merry!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROMEO</speaker>
            <line>Stay, fellow; I can read.</line>
            <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>
            <line>'Signior Martino and his wife and daughters;</line>
            <line>County Anselme and his beauteous sisters; the lady</line>
            <line>widow of Vitravio; Signior Placentio and his lovely</line>
            <line>nieces; Mercutio and his brother Valentine; mine</line>
            <line>uncle Capulet, his wife and daughters; my fair niece</line>
            <line>Rosaline; Livia; Signior Valentio and his cousin</line>
            <line>Tybalt, Lucio and the lively Helena.' A fair</line>
            <line>assembly: whither should they come?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>Up.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROMEO</speaker>
            <line>Whither?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>To supper; to our house.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROMEO</speaker>
            <line>Whose house?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>My master's.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROMEO</speaker>
            <line>Indeed, I should have ask'd you that before.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>Now I'll tell you without asking: my master is the</line>
            <line>great rich Capulet; and if you be not of the house</line>
            <line>of Montagues, I pray, come and crush a cup of wine.</line>
            <line>Rest you merry!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>At this same ancient feast of Capulet's</line>
            <line>Sups the fair Rosaline whom thou so lovest,</line>
            <line>With all the admired beauties of Verona:</line>
            <line>Go thither; and, with unattainted eye,</line>
            <line>Compare her face with some that I shall show,</line>
            <line>And I will make thee think thy swan a crow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROMEO</speaker>
            <line>When the devout religion of mine eye</line>
            <line>Maintains such falsehood, then turn tears to fires;</line>
            <line>And these, who often drown'd could never die,</line>
            <line>Transparent heretics, be burnt for liars!</line>
            <line>One fairer than my love! the all-seeing sun</line>
            <line>Ne'er saw her match since first the world begun.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>Tut, you saw her fair, none else being by,</line>
            <line>Herself poised with herself in either eye:</line>
            <line>But in that crystal scales let there be weigh'd</line>
            <line>Your lady's love against some other maid</line>
            <line>That I will show you shining at this feast,</line>
            <line>And she shall scant show well that now shows best.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROMEO</speaker>
            <line>I'll go along, no such sight to be shown,</line>
            <line>But to rejoice in splendor of mine own.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  A room in Capulet's house.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter LADY CAPULET and Nurse</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY CAPULET</speaker>
            <line>Nurse, where's my daughter? call her forth to me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Nurse</speaker>
            <line>Now, by my maidenhead, at twelve year old,</line>
            <line>I bade her come. What, lamb! what, ladybird!</line>
            <line>God forbid! Where's this girl? What, Juliet!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter JULIET</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JULIET</speaker>
            <line>How now! who calls?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Nurse</speaker>
            <line>Your mother.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JULIET</speaker>
            <line>Madam, I am here.</line>
            <line>What is your will?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY CAPULET</speaker>
            <line>This is the matter:--Nurse, give leave awhile,</line>
            <line>We must talk in secret:--nurse, come back again;</line>
            <line>I have remember'd me, thou's hear our counsel.</line>
            <line>Thou know'st my daughter's of a pretty age.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Nurse</speaker>
            <line>Faith, I can tell her age unto an hour.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY CAPULET</speaker>
            <line>She's not fourteen.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Nurse</speaker>
            <line>I'll lay fourteen of my teeth,--</line>
            <line>And yet, to my teeth be it spoken, I have but four--</line>
            <line>She is not fourteen. How long is it now</line>
            <line>To Lammas-tide?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY CAPULET</speaker>
            <line>A fortnight and odd days.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Nurse</speaker>
            <line>Even or odd, of all days in the year,</line>
            <line>Come Lammas-eve at night shall she be fourteen.</line>
            <line>Susan and she--God rest all Christian souls!--</line>
            <line>Were of an age: well, Susan is with God;</line>
            <line>She was too good for me: but, as I said,</line>
            <line>On Lammas-eve at night shall she be fourteen;</line>
            <line>That shall she, marry; I remember it well.</line>
            <line>'Tis since the earthquake now eleven years;</line>
            <line>And she was wean'd,--I never shall forget it,--</line>
            <line>Of all the days of the year, upon that day:</line>
            <line>For I had then laid wormwood to my dug,</line>
            <line>Sitting in the sun under the dove-house wall;</line>
            <line>My lord and you were then at Mantua:--</line>
            <line>Nay, I do bear a brain:--but, as I said,</line>
            <line>When it did taste the wormwood on the nipple</line>
            <line>Of my dug and felt it bitter, pretty fool,</line>
            <line>To see it tetchy and fall out with the dug!</line>
            <line>Shake quoth the dove-house: 'twas no need, I trow,</line>
            <line>To bid me trudge:</line>
            <line>And since that time it is eleven years;</line>
            <line>For then she could stand alone; nay, by the rood,</line>
            <line>She could have run and waddled all about;</line>
            <line>For even the day before, she broke her brow:</line>
            <line>And then my husband--God be with his soul!</line>
            <line>A' was a merry man--took up the child:</line>
            <line>'Yea,' quoth he, 'dost thou fall upon thy face?</line>
            <line>Thou wilt fall backward when thou hast more wit;</line>
            <line>Wilt thou not, Jule?' and, by my holidame,</line>
            <line>The pretty wretch left crying and said 'Ay.'</line>
            <line>To see, now, how a jest shall come about!</line>
            <line>I warrant, an I should live a thousand years,</line>
            <line>I never should forget it: 'Wilt thou not, Jule?' quoth he;</line>
            <line>And, pretty fool, it stinted and said 'Ay.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY CAPULET</speaker>
            <line>Enough of this; I pray thee, hold thy peace.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Nurse</speaker>
            <line>Yes, madam: yet I cannot choose but laugh,</line>
            <line>To think it should leave crying and say 'Ay.'</line>
            <line>And yet, I warrant, it had upon its brow</line>
            <line>A bump as big as a young cockerel's stone;</line>
            <line>A parlous knock; and it cried bitterly:</line>
            <line>'Yea,' quoth my husband,'fall'st upon thy face?</line>
            <line>Thou wilt fall backward when thou comest to age;</line>
            <line>Wilt thou not, Jule?' it stinted and said 'Ay.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JULIET</speaker>
            <line>And stint thou too, I pray thee, nurse, say I.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Nurse</speaker>
            <line>Peace, I have done. God mark thee to his grace!</line>
            <line>Thou wast the prettiest babe that e'er I nursed:</line>
            <line>An I might live to see thee married once,</line>
            <line>I have my wish.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY CAPULET</speaker>
            <line>Marry, that 'marry' is the very theme</line>
            <line>I came to talk of. Tell me, daughter Juliet,</line>
            <line>How stands your disposition to be married?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JULIET</speaker>
            <line>It is an honour that I dream not of.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Nurse</speaker>
            <line>An honour! were not I thine only nurse,</line>
            <line>I would say thou hadst suck'd wisdom from thy teat.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY CAPULET</speaker>
            <line>Well, think of marriage now; younger than you,</line>
            <line>Here in Verona, ladies of esteem,</line>
            <line>Are made already mothers: by my count,</line>
            <line>I was your mother much upon these years</line>
            <line>That you are now a maid. Thus then in brief:</line>
            <line>The valiant Paris seeks you for his love.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Nurse</speaker>
            <line>A man, young lady! lady, such a man</line>
            <line>As all the world--why, he's a man of wax.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY CAPULET</speaker>
            <line>Verona's summer hath not such a flower.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Nurse</speaker>
            <line>Nay, he's a flower; in faith, a very flower.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY CAPULET</speaker>
            <line>What say you? can you love the gentleman?</line>
            <line>This night you shall behold him at our feast;</line>
            <line>Read o'er the volume of young Paris' face,</line>
            <line>And find delight writ there with beauty's pen;</line>
            <line>Examine every married lineament,</line>
            <line>And see how one another lends content</line>
            <line>And what obscured in this fair volume lies</line>
            <line>Find written in the margent of his eyes.</line>
            <line>This precious book of love, this unbound lover,</line>
            <line>To beautify him, only lacks a cover:</line>
            <line>The fish lives in the sea, and 'tis much pride</line>
            <line>For fair without the fair within to hide:</line>
            <line>That book in many's eyes doth share the glory,</line>
            <line>That in gold clasps locks in the golden story;</line>
            <line>So shall you share all that he doth possess,</line>
            <line>By having him, making yourself no less.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Nurse</speaker>
            <line>No less! nay, bigger; women grow by men.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY CAPULET</speaker>
            <line>Speak briefly, can you like of Paris' love?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JULIET</speaker>
            <line>I'll look to like, if looking liking move:</line>
            <line>But no more deep will I endart mine eye</line>
            <line>Than your consent gives strength to make it fly.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter a Servant</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>Madam, the guests are come, supper served up, you</line>
            <line>called, my young lady asked for, the nurse cursed in</line>
            <line>the pantry, and every thing in extremity. I must</line>
            <line>hence to wait; I beseech you, follow straight.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LADY CAPULET</speaker>
            <line>We follow thee.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit Servant</stagedir>
            <line>Juliet, the county stays.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Nurse</speaker>
            <line>Go, girl, seek happy nights to happy days.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-4">
      <title>SCENE IV.  A street.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter ROMEO, MERCUTIO, BENVOLIO, with five or six
Maskers, Torch-bearers, and others</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROMEO</speaker>
            <line>What, shall this speech be spoke for our excuse?</line>
            <line>Or shall we on without a apology?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>The date is out of such prolixity:</line>
            <line>We'll have no Cupid hoodwink'd with a scarf,</line>
            <line>Bearing a Tartar's painted bow of lath,</line>
            <line>Scaring the ladies like a crow-keeper;</line>
            <line>Nor no without-book prologue, faintly spoke</line>
            <line>After the prompter, for our entrance:</line>
            <line>But let them measure us by what they will;</line>
            <line>We'll measure them a measure, and be gone.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROMEO</speaker>
            <line>Give me a torch: I am not for this ambling;</line>
            <line>Being but heavy, I will bear the light.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MERCUTIO</speaker>
            <line>Nay, gentle Romeo, we must have you dance.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROMEO</speaker>
            <line>Not I, believe me: you have dancing shoes</line>
            <line>With nimble soles: I have a soul of lead</line>
            <line>So stakes me to the ground I cannot move.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MERCUTIO</speaker>
            <line>You are a lover; borrow Cupid's wings,</line>
            <line>And soar with them above a common bound.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROMEO</speaker>
            <line>I am too sore enpierced with his shaft</line>
            <line>To soar with his light feathers, and so bound,</line>
            <line>I cannot bound a pitch above dull woe:</line>
            <line>Under love's heavy burden do I sink.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MERCUTIO</speaker>
            <line>And, to sink in it, should you burden love;</line>
            <line>Too great oppression for a tender thing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROMEO</speaker>
            <line>Is love a tender thing? it is too rough,</line>
            <line>Too rude, too boisterous, and it pricks like thorn.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MERCUTIO</speaker>
            <line>If love be rough with you, be rough with love;</line>
            <line>Prick love for pricking, and you beat love down.</line>
            <line>Give me a case to put my visage in:</line>
            <line>A visor for a visor! what care I</line>
            <line>What curious eye doth quote deformities?</line>
            <line>Here are the beetle brows shall blush for me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>Come, knock and enter; and no sooner in,</line>
            <line>But every man betake him to his legs.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROMEO</speaker>
            <line>A torch for me: let wantons light of heart</line>
            <line>Tickle the senseless rushes with their heels,</line>
            <line>For I am proverb'd with a grandsire phrase;</line>
            <line>I'll be a candle-holder, and look on.</line>
            <line>The game was ne'er so fair, and I am done.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MERCUTIO</speaker>
            <line>Tut, dun's the mouse, the constable's own word:</line>
            <line>If thou art dun, we'll draw thee from the mire</line>
            <line>Of this sir-reverence love, wherein thou stick'st</line>
            <line>Up to the ears. Come, we burn daylight, ho!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROMEO</speaker>
            <line>Nay, that's not so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MERCUTIO</speaker>
            <line>I mean, sir, in delay</line>
            <line>We waste our lights in vain, like lamps by day.</line>
            <line>Take our good meaning, for our judgment sits</line>
            <line>Five times in that ere once in our five wits.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROMEO</speaker>
            <line>And we mean well in going to this mask;</line>
            <line>But 'tis no wit to go.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MERCUTIO</speaker>
            <line>Why, may one ask?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROMEO</speaker>
            <line>I dream'd a dream to-night.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MERCUTIO</speaker>
            <line>And so did I.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROMEO</speaker>
            <line>Well, what was yours?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MERCUTIO</speaker>
            <line>That dreamers often lie.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROMEO</speaker>
            <line>In bed asleep, while they do dream things true.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MERCUTIO</speaker>
            <line>O, then, I see Queen Mab hath been with you.</line>
            <line>She is the fairies' midwife, and she comes</line>
            <line>In shape no bigger than an agate-stone</line>
            <line>On the fore-finger of an alderman,</line>
            <line>Drawn with a team of little atomies</line>
            <line>Athwart men's noses as they lie asleep;</line>
            <line>Her wagon-spokes made of long spiders' legs,</line>
            <line>The cover of the wings of grasshoppers,</line>
            <line>The traces of the smallest spider's web,</line>
            <line>The collars of the moonshine's watery beams,</line>
            <line>Her whip of cricket's bone, the lash of film,</line>
            <line>Her wagoner a small grey-coated gnat,</line>
            <line>Not so big as a round little worm</line>
            <line>Prick'd from the lazy finger of a maid;</line>
            <line>Her chariot is an empty hazel-nut</line>
            <line>Made by the joiner squirrel or old grub,</line>
            <line>Time out o' mind the fairies' coachmakers.</line>
            <line>And in this state she gallops night by night</line>
            <line>Through lovers' brains, and then they dream of love;</line>
            <line>O'er courtiers' knees, that dream on court'sies straight,</line>
            <line>O'er lawyers' fingers, who straight dream on fees,</line>
            <line>O'er ladies ' lips, who straight on kisses dream,</line>
            <line>Which oft the angry Mab with blisters plagues,</line>
            <line>Because their breaths with sweetmeats tainted are:</line>
            <line>Sometime she gallops o'er a courtier's nose,</line>
            <line>And then dreams he of smelling out a suit;</line>
            <line>And sometime comes she with a tithe-pig's tail</line>
            <line>Tickling a parson's nose as a' lies asleep,</line>
            <line>Then dreams, he of another benefice:</line>
            <line>Sometime she driveth o'er a soldier's neck,</line>
            <line>And then dreams he of cutting foreign throats,</line>
            <line>Of breaches, ambuscadoes, Spanish blades,</line>
            <line>Of healths five-fathom deep; and then anon</line>
            <line>Drums in his ear, at which he starts and wakes,</line>
            <line>And being thus frighted swears a prayer or two</line>
            <line>And sleeps again. This is that very Mab</line>
            <line>That plats the manes of horses in the night,</line>
            <line>And bakes the elflocks in foul sluttish hairs,</line>
            <line>Which once untangled, much misfortune bodes:</line>
            <line>This is the hag, when maids lie on their backs,</line>
            <line>That presses them and learns them first to bear,</line>
            <line>Making them women of good carriage:</line>
            <line>This is she--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROMEO</speaker>
            <line>Peace, peace, Mercutio, peace!</line>
            <line>Thou talk'st of nothing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MERCUTIO</speaker>
            <line>True, I talk of dreams,</line>
            <line>Which are the children of an idle brain,</line>
            <line>Begot of nothing but vain fantasy,</line>
            <line>Which is as thin of substance as the air</line>
            <line>And more inconstant than the wind, who wooes</line>
            <line>Even now the frozen bosom of the north,</line>
            <line>And, being anger'd, puffs away from thence,</line>
            <line>Turning his face to the dew-dropping south.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>This wind, you talk of, blows us from ourselves;</line>
            <line>Supper is done, and we shall come too late.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROMEO</speaker>
            <line>I fear, too early: for my mind misgives</line>
            <line>Some consequence yet hanging in the stars</line>
            <line>Shall bitterly begin his fearful date</line>
            <line>With this night's revels and expire the term</line>
            <line>Of a despised life closed in my breast</line>
            <line>By some vile forfeit of untimely death.</line>
            <line>But He, that hath the steerage of my course,</line>
            <line>Direct my sail! On, lusty gentlemen.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>Strike, drum.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-5">
      <title>SCENE V.  A hall in Capulet's house.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Musicians waiting. Enter Servingmen with napkins</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Servant</speaker>
            <line>Where's Potpan, that he helps not to take away? He</line>
            <line>shift a trencher? he scrape a trencher!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Servant</speaker>
            <line>When good manners shall lie all in one or two men's</line>
            <line>hands and they unwashed too, 'tis a foul thing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Servant</speaker>
            <line>Away with the joint-stools, remove the</line>
            <line>court-cupboard, look to the plate. Good thou, save</line>
            <line>me a piece of marchpane; and, as thou lovest me, let</line>
            <line>the porter let in Susan Grindstone and Nell.</line>
            <line>Antony, and Potpan!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Servant</speaker>
            <line>Ay, boy, ready.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Servant</speaker>
            <line>You are looked for and called for, asked for and</line>
            <line>sought for, in the great chamber.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Servant</speaker>
            <line>We cannot be here and there too. Cheerly, boys; be</line>
            <line>brisk awhile, and the longer liver take all.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter CAPULET, with JULIET and others of his house,
meeting the Guests and Maskers</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAPULET</speaker>
            <line>Welcome, gentlemen! ladies that have their toes</line>
            <line>Unplagued with corns will have a bout with you.</line>
            <line>Ah ha, my mistresses! which of you all</line>
            <line>Will now deny to dance? she that makes dainty,</line>
            <line>She, I'll swear, hath corns; am I come near ye now?</line>
            <line>Welcome, gentlemen! I have seen the day</line>
            <line>That I have worn a visor and could tell</line>
            <line>A whispering tale in a fair lady's ear,</line>
            <line>Such as would please: 'tis gone, 'tis gone, 'tis gone:</line>
            <line>You are welcome, gentlemen! come, musicians, play.</line>
            <line>A hall, a hall! give room! and foot it, girls.</line>
            <stagedir>Music plays, and they dance</stagedir>
            <line>More light, you knaves; and turn the tables up,</line>
            <line>And quench the fire, the room is grown too hot.</line>
            <line>Ah, sirrah, this unlook'd-for sport comes well.</line>
            <line>Nay, sit, nay, sit, good cousin Capulet;</line>
            <line>For you and I are past our dancing days:</line>
            <line>How long is't now since last yourself and I</line>
            <line>Were in a mask?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Capulet</speaker>
            <line>By'r lady, thirty years.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAPULET</speaker>
            <line>What, man! 'tis not so much, 'tis not so much:</line>
            <line>'Tis since the nuptials of Lucentio,</line>
            <line>Come pentecost as quickly as it will,</line>
            <line>Some five and twenty years; and then we mask'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Capulet</speaker>
            <line>'Tis more, 'tis more, his son is elder, sir;</line>
            <line>His son is thirty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAPULET</speaker>
            <line>Will you tell me that?</line>
            <line>His son was but a ward two years ago.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROMEO</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>To a Servingman</stagedir>  What lady is that, which doth</line>
            <line>enrich the hand</line>
            <line>Of yonder knight?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>I know not, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROMEO</speaker>
            <line>O, she doth teach the torches to burn bright!</line>
            <line>It seems she hangs upon the cheek of night</line>
            <line>Like a rich jewel in an Ethiope's ear;</line>
            <line>Beauty too rich for use, for earth too dear!</line>
            <line>So shows a snowy dove trooping with crows,</line>
            <line>As yonder lady o'er her fellows shows.</line>
            <line>The measure done, I'll watch her place of stand,</line>
            <line>And, touching hers, make blessed my rude hand.</line>
            <line>Did my heart love till now? forswear it, sight!</line>
            <line>For I ne'er saw true beauty till this night.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TYBALT</speaker>
            <line>This, by his voice, should be a Montague.</line>
            <line>Fetch me my rapier, boy. What dares the slave</line>
            <line>Come hither, cover'd with an antic face,</line>
            <line>To fleer and scorn at our solemnity?</line>
            <line>Now, by the stock and honour of my kin,</line>
            <line>To strike him dead, I hold it not a sin.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAPULET</speaker>
            <line>Why, how now, kinsman! wherefore storm you so?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TYBALT</speaker>
            <line>Uncle, this is a Montague, our foe,</line>
            <line>A villain that is hither come in spite,</line>
            <line>To scorn at our solemnity this night.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAPULET</speaker>
            <line>Young Romeo is it?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TYBALT</speaker>
            <line>'Tis he, that villain Romeo.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAPULET</speaker>
            <line>Content thee, gentle coz, let him alone;</line>
            <line>He bears him like a portly gentleman;</line>
            <line>And, to say truth, Verona brags of him</line>
            <line>To be a virtuous and well-govern'd youth:</line>
            <line>I would not for the wealth of all the town</line>
            <line>Here in my house do him disparagement:</line>
            <line>Therefore be patient, take no note of him:</line>
            <line>It is my will, the which if thou respect,</line>
            <line>Show a fair presence and put off these frowns,</line>
            <line>And ill-beseeming semblance for a feast.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TYBALT</speaker>
            <line>It fits, when such a villain is a guest:</line>
            <line>I'll not endure him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAPULET</speaker>
            <line>He shall be endured:</line>
            <line>What, goodman boy! I say, he shall: go to;</line>
            <line>Am I the master here, or you? go to.</line>
            <line>You'll not endure him! God shall mend my soul!</line>
            <line>You'll make a mutiny among my guests!</line>
            <line>You will set cock-a-hoop! you'll be the man!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TYBALT</speaker>
            <line>Why, uncle, 'tis a shame.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAPULET</speaker>
            <line>Go to, go to;</line>
            <line>You are a saucy boy: is't so, indeed?</line>
            <line>This trick may chance to scathe you, I know what:</line>
            <line>You must contrary me! marry, 'tis time.</line>
            <line>Well said, my hearts! You are a princox; go:</line>
            <line>Be quiet, or--More light, more light! For shame!</line>
            <line>I'll make you quiet. What, cheerly, my hearts!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TYBALT</speaker>
            <line>Patience perforce with wilful choler meeting</line>
            <line>Makes my flesh tremble in their different greeting.</line>
            <line>I will withdraw: but this intrusion shall</line>
            <line>Now seeming sweet convert to bitter gall.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROMEO</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>To JULIET</stagedir>  If I profane with my unworthiest hand</line>
            <line>This holy shrine, the gentle fine is this:</line>
            <line>My lips, two blushing pilgrims, ready stand</line>
            <line>To smooth that rough touch with a tender kiss.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JULIET</speaker>
            <line>Good pilgrim, you do wrong your hand too much,</line>
            <line>Which mannerly devotion shows in this;</line>
            <line>For saints have hands that pilgrims' hands do touch,</line>
            <line>And palm to palm is holy palmers' kiss.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROMEO</speaker>
            <line>Have not saints lips, and holy palmers too?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JULIET</speaker>
            <line>Ay, pilgrim, lips that they must use in prayer.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROMEO</speaker>
            <line>O, then, dear saint, let lips do what hands do;</line>
            <line>They pray, grant thou, lest faith turn to despair.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JULIET</speaker>
            <line>Saints do not move, though grant for prayers' sake.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROMEO</speaker>
            <line>Then move not, while my prayer's effect I take.</line>
            <line>Thus from my lips, by yours, my sin is purged.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JULIET</speaker>
            <line>Then have my lips the sin that they have took.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROMEO</speaker>
            <line>Sin from thy lips? O trespass sweetly urged!</line>
            <line>Give me my sin again.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JULIET</speaker>
            <line>You kiss by the book.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Nurse</speaker>
            <line>Madam, your mother craves a word with you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROMEO</speaker>
            <line>What is her mother?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Nurse</speaker>
            <line>Marry, bachelor,</line>
            <line>Her mother is the lady of the house,</line>
            <line>And a good lady, and a wise and virtuous</line>
            <line>I nursed her daughter, that you talk'd withal;</line>
            <line>I tell you, he that can lay hold of her</line>
            <line>Shall have the chinks.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROMEO</speaker>
            <line>Is she a Capulet?</line>
            <line>O dear account! my life is my foe's debt.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BENVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>Away, begone; the sport is at the best.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ROMEO</speaker>
            <line>Ay, so I fear; the more is my unrest.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAPULET</speaker>
            <line>Nay, gentlemen, prepare not to be gone;</line>
            <line>We have a trifling foolish banquet towards.</line>
            <line>Is it e'en so? why, then, I thank you all</line>
            <line>I thank you, honest gentlemen; good night.</line>
            <line>More torches here! Come on then, let's to bed.</line>
            <line>Ah, sirrah, by my fay, it waxes late:</line>
            <line>I'll to my rest.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt all but JULIET and Nurse</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JULIET</speaker>
            <line>Come hither, nurse. What is yond gentleman?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Nurse</speaker>
            <line>The son and heir of old Tiberio.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JULIET</speaker>
            <line>What's he that now is going out of door?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Nurse</speaker>
            <line>Marry, that, I think, be young Petrucio.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JULIET</speaker>
            <line>What's he that follows there, that would not dance?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Nurse</speaker>
            <line>I know not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JULIET</speaker>
            <line>Go ask his name: if he be married.</line>
            <line>My grave is like to be my wedding bed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Nurse</speaker>
            <line>His name is Romeo, and a Montague;</line>
            <line>The only son of your great enemy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JULIET</speaker>
            <line>My only love sprung from my only hate!</line>
            <line>Too early seen unknown, and known too late!</line>
            <line>Prodigious birth of love it is to me,</line>
            <line>That I must love a loathed enemy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Nurse</speaker>
            <line>What's this? what's this?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JULIET</speaker>
            <line>A rhyme I learn'd even now</line>
            <line>Of one I danced withal.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>One calls within 'Juliet.'</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Nurse</speaker>
            <line>Anon, anon!</line>
            <line>Come, let's away; the strangers all are gone.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>