<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:shakespear:dtd:act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-5">
   <title>ACT V</title>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  Britain. The Roman camp.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter POSTHUMUS, with a bloody handkerchief</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POSTHUMUS LEONATUS</speaker>
            <line>Yea, bloody cloth, I'll keep thee, for I wish'd</line>
            <line>Thou shouldst be colour'd thus. You married ones,</line>
            <line>If each of you should take this course, how many</line>
            <line>Must murder wives much better than themselves</line>
            <line>For wrying but a little! O Pisanio!</line>
            <line>Every good servant does not all commands:</line>
            <line>No bond but to do just ones. Gods! if you</line>
            <line>Should have ta'en vengeance on my faults, I never</line>
            <line>Had lived to put on this: so had you saved</line>
            <line>The noble Imogen to repent, and struck</line>
            <line>Me, wretch more worth your vengeance. But, alack,</line>
            <line>You snatch some hence for little faults; that's love,</line>
            <line>To have them fall no more: you some permit</line>
            <line>To second ills with ills, each elder worse,</line>
            <line>And make them dread it, to the doers' thrift.</line>
            <line>But Imogen is your own: do your best wills,</line>
            <line>And make me blest to obey! I am brought hither</line>
            <line>Among the Italian gentry, and to fight</line>
            <line>Against my lady's kingdom: 'tis enough</line>
            <line>That, Britain, I have kill'd thy mistress; peace!</line>
            <line>I'll give no wound to thee. Therefore, good heavens,</line>
            <line>Hear patiently my purpose: I'll disrobe me</line>
            <line>Of these Italian weeds and suit myself</line>
            <line>As does a Briton peasant: so I'll fight</line>
            <line>Against the part I come with; so I'll die</line>
            <line>For thee, O Imogen, even for whom my life</line>
            <line>Is every breath a death; and thus, unknown,</line>
            <line>Pitied nor hated, to the face of peril</line>
            <line>Myself I'll dedicate. Let me make men know</line>
            <line>More valour in me than my habits show.</line>
            <line>Gods, put the strength o' the Leonati in me!</line>
            <line>To shame the guise o' the world, I will begin</line>
            <line>The fashion, less without and more within.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  Field of battle between the British and Roman camps.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter, from one side, LUCIUS, IACHIMO, and
the Roman Army: from the other side, the
British Army; POSTHUMUS LEONATUS following,
like a poor soldier. They march over and go
out. Then enter again, in skirmish, IACHIMO
and POSTHUMUS LEONATUS he vanquisheth and disarmeth
IACHIMO, and then leaves him</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IACHIMO</speaker>
            <line>The heaviness and guilt within my bosom</line>
            <line>Takes off my manhood: I have belied a lady,</line>
            <line>The princess of this country, and the air on't</line>
            <line>Revengingly enfeebles me; or could this carl,</line>
            <line>A very drudge of nature's, have subdued me</line>
            <line>In my profession? Knighthoods and honours, borne</line>
            <line>As I wear mine, are titles but of scorn.</line>
            <line>If that thy gentry, Britain, go before</line>
            <line>This lout as he exceeds our lords, the odds</line>
            <line>Is that we scarce are men and you are gods.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <stagedir>The battle continues; the Britons fly; CYMBELINE is
taken: then enter, to his rescue, BELARIUS,
GUIDERIUS, and ARVIRAGUS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BELARIUS</speaker>
            <line>Stand, stand! We have the advantage of the ground;</line>
            <line>The lane is guarded: nothing routs us but</line>
            <line>The villany of our fears.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GUIDERIUS</speaker>
            <speaker>ARVIRAGUS</speaker>
            <line>Stand, stand, and fight!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter POSTHUMUS LEONATUS, and seconds the
Britons: they rescue CYMBELINE, and exeunt. Then
re-enter LUCIUS, and IACHIMO, with IMOGEN</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAIUS LUCIUS</speaker>
            <line>Away, boy, from the troops, and save thyself;</line>
            <line>For friends kill friends, and the disorder's such</line>
            <line>As war were hoodwink'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IACHIMO</speaker>
            <line>'Tis their fresh supplies.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAIUS LUCIUS</speaker>
            <line>It is a day turn'd strangely: or betimes</line>
            <line>Let's reinforce, or fly.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  Another part of the field.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter POSTHUMUS LEONATUS and a British Lord</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord</speaker>
            <line>Camest thou from where they made the stand?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POSTHUMUS LEONATUS</speaker>
            <line>I did.</line>
            <line>Though you, it seems, come from the fliers.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord</speaker>
            <line>I did.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POSTHUMUS LEONATUS</speaker>
            <line>No blame be to you, sir; for all was lost,</line>
            <line>But that the heavens fought: the king himself</line>
            <line>Of his wings destitute, the army broken,</line>
            <line>And but the backs of Britons seen, all flying</line>
            <line>Through a straight lane; the enemy full-hearted,</line>
            <line>Lolling the tongue with slaughtering, having work</line>
            <line>More plentiful than tools to do't, struck down</line>
            <line>Some mortally, some slightly touch'd, some falling</line>
            <line>Merely through fear; that the straight pass was damm'd</line>
            <line>With dead men hurt behind, and cowards living</line>
            <line>To die with lengthen'd shame.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord</speaker>
            <line>Where was this lane?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POSTHUMUS LEONATUS</speaker>
            <line>Close by the battle, ditch'd, and wall'd with turf;</line>
            <line>Which gave advantage to an ancient soldier,</line>
            <line>An honest one, I warrant; who deserved</line>
            <line>So long a breeding as his white beard came to,</line>
            <line>In doing this for's country: athwart the lane,</line>
            <line>He, with two striplings-lads more like to run</line>
            <line>The country base than to commit such slaughter</line>
            <line>With faces fit for masks, or rather fairer</line>
            <line>Than those for preservation cased, or shame--</line>
            <line>Made good the passage; cried to those that fled,</line>
            <line>'Our Britain s harts die flying, not our men:</line>
            <line>To darkness fleet souls that fly backwards. Stand;</line>
            <line>Or we are Romans and will give you that</line>
            <line>Like beasts which you shun beastly, and may save,</line>
            <line>But to look back in frown: stand, stand.'</line>
            <line>These three,</line>
            <line>Three thousand confident, in act as many--</line>
            <line>For three performers are the file when all</line>
            <line>The rest do nothing--with this word 'Stand, stand,'</line>
            <line>Accommodated by the place, more charming</line>
            <line>With their own nobleness, which could have turn'd</line>
            <line>A distaff to a lance, gilded pale looks,</line>
            <line>Part shame, part spirit renew'd; that some,</line>
            <line>turn'd coward</line>
            <line>But by example--O, a sin in war,</line>
            <line>Damn'd in the first beginners!--gan to look</line>
            <line>The way that they did, and to grin like lions</line>
            <line>Upon the pikes o' the hunters. Then began</line>
            <line>A stop i' the chaser, a retire, anon</line>
            <line>A rout, confusion thick; forthwith they fly</line>
            <line>Chickens, the way which they stoop'd eagles; slaves,</line>
            <line>The strides they victors made: and now our cowards,</line>
            <line>Like fragments in hard voyages, became</line>
            <line>The life o' the need: having found the backdoor open</line>
            <line>Of the unguarded hearts, heavens, how they wound!</line>
            <line>Some slain before; some dying; some their friends</line>
            <line>O'er borne i' the former wave: ten, chased by one,</line>
            <line>Are now each one the slaughter-man of twenty:</line>
            <line>Those that would die or ere resist are grown</line>
            <line>The mortal bugs o' the field.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord</speaker>
            <line>This was strange chance</line>
            <line>A narrow lane, an old man, and two boys.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POSTHUMUS LEONATUS</speaker>
            <line>Nay, do not wonder at it: you are made</line>
            <line>Rather to wonder at the things you hear</line>
            <line>Than to work any. Will you rhyme upon't,</line>
            <line>And vent it for a mockery? Here is one:</line>
            <line>'Two boys, an old man twice a boy, a lane,</line>
            <line>Preserved the Britons, was the Romans' bane.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord</speaker>
            <line>Nay, be not angry, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POSTHUMUS LEONATUS</speaker>
            <line>'Lack, to what end?</line>
            <line>Who dares not stand his foe, I'll be his friend;</line>
            <line>For if he'll do as he is made to do,</line>
            <line>I know he'll quickly fly my friendship too.</line>
            <line>You have put me into rhyme.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lord</speaker>
            <line>Farewell; you're angry.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POSTHUMUS LEONATUS</speaker>
            <line>Still going?</line>
            <stagedir>Exit Lord</stagedir>
            <line>This is a lord! O noble misery,</line>
            <line>To be i' the field, and ask 'what news?' of me!</line>
            <line>To-day how many would have given their honours</line>
            <line>To have saved their carcasses! took heel to do't,</line>
            <line>And yet died too! I, in mine own woe charm'd,</line>
            <line>Could not find death where I did hear him groan,</line>
            <line>Nor feel him where he struck: being an ugly monster,</line>
            <line>'Tis strange he hides him in fresh cups, soft beds,</line>
            <line>Sweet words; or hath more ministers than we</line>
            <line>That draw his knives i' the war. Well, I will find him</line>
            <line>For being now a favourer to the Briton,</line>
            <line>No more a Briton, I have resumed again</line>
            <line>The part I came in: fight I will no more,</line>
            <line>But yield me to the veriest hind that shall</line>
            <line>Once touch my shoulder. Great the slaughter is</line>
            <line>Here made by the Roman; great the answer be</line>
            <line>Britons must take. For me, my ransom's death;</line>
            <line>On either side I come to spend my breath;</line>
            <line>Which neither here I'll keep nor bear again,</line>
            <line>But end it by some means for Imogen.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter two British Captains and Soldiers</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Captain</speaker>
            <line>Great Jupiter be praised! Lucius is taken.</line>
            <line>'Tis thought the old man and his sons were angels.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Captain</speaker>
            <line>There was a fourth man, in a silly habit,</line>
            <line>That gave the affront with them.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Captain</speaker>
            <line>So 'tis reported:</line>
            <line>But none of 'em can be found. Stand! who's there?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POSTHUMUS LEONATUS</speaker>
            <line>A Roman,</line>
            <line>Who had not now been drooping here, if seconds</line>
            <line>Had answer'd him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Captain</speaker>
            <line>Lay hands on him; a dog!</line>
            <line>A leg of Rome shall not return to tell</line>
            <line>What crows have peck'd them here. He brags</line>
            <line>his service</line>
            <line>As if he were of note: bring him to the king.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter CYMBELINE, BELARIUS, GUIDERIUS, ARVIRAGUS,
PISANIO, Soldiers, Attendants, and Roman Captives.
The Captains present POSTHUMUS LEONATUS to
CYMBELINE, who delivers him over to a Gaoler:
then exeunt omnes</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-4">
      <title>SCENE IV.  A British prison.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter POSTHUMUS LEONATUS and two Gaolers</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Gaoler</speaker>
            <line>You shall not now be stol'n, you have locks upon you;</line>
            <line>So graze as you find pasture.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Gaoler</speaker>
            <line>Ay, or a stomach.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt Gaolers</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POSTHUMUS LEONATUS</speaker>
            <line>Most welcome, bondage! for thou art away,</line>
            <line>think, to liberty: yet am I better</line>
            <line>Than one that's sick o' the gout; since he had rather</line>
            <line>Groan so in perpetuity than be cured</line>
            <line>By the sure physician, death, who is the key</line>
            <line>To unbar these locks. My conscience, thou art fetter'd</line>
            <line>More than my shanks and wrists: you good gods, give me</line>
            <line>The penitent instrument to pick that bolt,</line>
            <line>Then, free for ever! Is't enough I am sorry?</line>
            <line>So children temporal fathers do appease;</line>
            <line>Gods are more full of mercy. Must I repent?</line>
            <line>I cannot do it better than in gyves,</line>
            <line>Desired more than constrain'd: to satisfy,</line>
            <line>If of my freedom 'tis the main part, take</line>
            <line>No stricter render of me than my all.</line>
            <line>I know you are more clement than vile men,</line>
            <line>Who of their broken debtors take a third,</line>
            <line>A sixth, a tenth, letting them thrive again</line>
            <line>On their abatement: that's not my desire:</line>
            <line>For Imogen's dear life take mine; and though</line>
            <line>'Tis not so dear, yet 'tis a life; you coin'd it:</line>
            <line>'Tween man and man they weigh not every stamp;</line>
            <line>Though light, take pieces for the figure's sake:</line>
            <line>You rather mine, being yours: and so, great powers,</line>
            <line>If you will take this audit, take this life,</line>
            <line>And cancel these cold bonds. O Imogen!</line>
            <line>I'll speak to thee in silence.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Sleeps</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Solemn music. Enter, as in an apparition,
SICILIUS LEONATUS, father to Posthumus Leonatus,
an old man, attired like a warrior; leading in
his hand an ancient matron, his wife, and mother
to Posthumus Leonatus, with music before them:
then, after other music, follow the two young
Leonati, brothers to Posthumus Leonatus, with
wounds as they died in the wars. They circle
Posthumus Leonatus round, as he lies sleeping</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Sicilius Leonatus</speaker>
            <line>No more, thou thunder-master, show</line>
            <line>Thy spite on mortal flies:</line>
            <line>With Mars fall out, with Juno chide,</line>
            <line>That thy adulteries</line>
            <line>Rates and revenges.</line>
            <line>Hath my poor boy done aught but well,</line>
            <line>Whose face I never saw?</line>
            <line>I died whilst in the womb he stay'd</line>
            <line>Attending nature's law:</line>
            <line>Whose father then, as men report</line>
            <line>Thou orphans' father art,</line>
            <line>Thou shouldst have been, and shielded him</line>
            <line>From this earth-vexing smart.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Mother</speaker>
            <line>Lucina lent not me her aid,</line>
            <line>But took me in my throes;</line>
            <line>That from me was Posthumus ript,</line>
            <line>Came crying 'mongst his foes,</line>
            <line>A thing of pity!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Sicilius Leonatus</speaker>
            <line>Great nature, like his ancestry,</line>
            <line>Moulded the stuff so fair,</line>
            <line>That he deserved the praise o' the world,</line>
            <line>As great Sicilius' heir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Brother</speaker>
            <line>When once he was mature for man,</line>
            <line>In Britain where was he</line>
            <line>That could stand up his parallel;</line>
            <line>Or fruitful object be</line>
            <line>In eye of Imogen, that best</line>
            <line>Could deem his dignity?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Mother</speaker>
            <line>With marriage wherefore was he mock'd,</line>
            <line>To be exiled, and thrown</line>
            <line>From Leonati seat, and cast</line>
            <line>From her his dearest one,</line>
            <line>Sweet Imogen?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Sicilius Leonatus</speaker>
            <line>Why did you suffer Iachimo,</line>
            <line>Slight thing of Italy,</line>
            <line>To taint his nobler heart and brain</line>
            <line>With needless jealosy;</line>
            <line>And to become the geck and scorn</line>
            <line>O' th' other's villany?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Brother</speaker>
            <line>For this from stiller seats we came,</line>
            <line>Our parents and us twain,</line>
            <line>That striking in our country's cause</line>
            <line>Fell bravely and were slain,</line>
            <line>Our fealty and Tenantius' right</line>
            <line>With honour to maintain.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Brother</speaker>
            <line>Like hardiment Posthumus hath</line>
            <line>To Cymbeline perform'd:</line>
            <line>Then, Jupiter, thou king of gods,</line>
            <line>Why hast thou thus adjourn'd</line>
            <line>The graces for his merits due,</line>
            <line>Being all to dolours turn'd?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Sicilius Leonatus</speaker>
            <line>Thy crystal window ope; look out;</line>
            <line>No longer exercise</line>
            <line>Upon a valiant race thy harsh</line>
            <line>And potent injuries.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Mother</speaker>
            <line>Since, Jupiter, our son is good,</line>
            <line>Take off his miseries.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Sicilius Leonatus</speaker>
            <line>Peep through thy marble mansion; help;</line>
            <line>Or we poor ghosts will cry</line>
            <line>To the shining synod of the rest</line>
            <line>Against thy deity.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Brother</speaker>
            <speaker>Second Brother</speaker>
            <line>Help, Jupiter; or we appeal,</line>
            <line>And from thy justice fly.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Jupiter descends in thunder and lightning, sitting
upon an eagle: he throws a thunderbolt. The
Apparitions fall on their knees</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Jupiter</speaker>
            <line>No more, you petty spirits of region low,</line>
            <line>Offend our hearing; hush! How dare you ghosts</line>
            <line>Accuse the thunderer, whose bolt, you know,</line>
            <line>Sky-planted batters all rebelling coasts?</line>
            <line>Poor shadows of Elysium, hence, and rest</line>
            <line>Upon your never-withering banks of flowers:</line>
            <line>Be not with mortal accidents opprest;</line>
            <line>No care of yours it is; you know 'tis ours.</line>
            <line>Whom best I love I cross; to make my gift,</line>
            <line>The more delay'd, delighted. Be content;</line>
            <line>Your low-laid son our godhead will uplift:</line>
            <line>His comforts thrive, his trials well are spent.</line>
            <line>Our Jovial star reign'd at his birth, and in</line>
            <line>Our temple was he married. Rise, and fade.</line>
            <line>He shall be lord of lady Imogen,</line>
            <line>And happier much by his affliction made.</line>
            <line>This tablet lay upon his breast, wherein</line>
            <line>Our pleasure his full fortune doth confine:</line>
            <line>and so, away: no further with your din</line>
            <line>Express impatience, lest you stir up mine.</line>
            <line>Mount, eagle, to my palace crystalline.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Ascends</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Sicilius Leonatus</speaker>
            <line>He came in thunder; his celestial breath</line>
            <line>Was sulphurous to smell: the holy eagle</line>
            <line>Stoop'd as to foot us: his ascension is</line>
            <line>More sweet than our blest fields: his royal bird</line>
            <line>Prunes the immortal wing and cloys his beak,</line>
            <line>As when his god is pleased.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>All</speaker>
            <line>Thanks, Jupiter!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Sicilius Leonatus</speaker>
            <line>The marble pavement closes, he is enter'd</line>
            <line>His radiant root. Away! and, to be blest,</line>
            <line>Let us with care perform his great behest.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>The Apparitions vanish</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Posthumus Leonatus</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Waking</stagedir>  Sleep, thou hast been a grandsire, and begot</line>
            <line>A father to me; and thou hast created</line>
            <line>A mother and two brothers: but, O scorn!</line>
            <line>Gone! they went hence so soon as they were born:</line>
            <line>And so I am awake. Poor wretches that depend</line>
            <line>On greatness' favour dream as I have done,</line>
            <line>Wake and find nothing. But, alas, I swerve:</line>
            <line>Many dream not to find, neither deserve,</line>
            <line>And yet are steep'd in favours: so am I,</line>
            <line>That have this golden chance and know not why.</line>
            <line>What fairies haunt this ground? A book? O rare one!</line>
            <line>Be not, as is our fangled world, a garment</line>
            <line>Nobler than that it covers: let thy effects</line>
            <line>So follow, to be most unlike our courtiers,</line>
            <line>As good as promise.</line>
            <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>
            <line>'When as a lion's whelp shall, to himself unknown,</line>
            <line>without seeking find, and be embraced by a piece of</line>
            <line>tender air; and when from a stately cedar shall be</line>
            <line>lopped branches, which, being dead many years,</line>
            <line>shall after revive, be jointed to the old stock and</line>
            <line>freshly grow; then shall Posthumus end his miseries,</line>
            <line>Britain be fortunate and flourish in peace and plenty.'</line>
            <line>'Tis still a dream, or else such stuff as madmen</line>
            <line>Tongue and brain not; either both or nothing;</line>
            <line>Or senseless speaking or a speaking such</line>
            <line>As sense cannot untie. Be what it is,</line>
            <line>The action of my life is like it, which</line>
            <line>I'll keep, if but for sympathy.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter First Gaoler</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Gaoler</speaker>
            <line>Come, sir, are you ready for death?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POSTHUMUS LEONATUS</speaker>
            <line>Over-roasted rather; ready long ago.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Gaoler</speaker>
            <line>Hanging is the word, sir: if</line>
            <line>you be ready for that, you are well cooked.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POSTHUMUS LEONATUS</speaker>
            <line>So, if I prove a good repast to the</line>
            <line>spectators, the dish pays the shot.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Gaoler</speaker>
            <line>A heavy reckoning for you, sir. But the comfort is,</line>
            <line>you shall be called to no more payments, fear no</line>
            <line>more tavern-bills; which are often the sadness of</line>
            <line>parting, as the procuring of mirth: you come in</line>
            <line>flint for want of meat, depart reeling with too</line>
            <line>much drink; sorry that you have paid too much, and</line>
            <line>sorry that you are paid too much; purse and brain</line>
            <line>both empty; the brain the heavier for being too</line>
            <line>light, the purse too light, being drawn of</line>
            <line>heaviness: of this contradiction you shall now be</line>
            <line>quit. O, the charity of a penny cord! It sums up</line>
            <line>thousands in a trice: you have no true debitor and</line>
            <line>creditor but it; of what's past, is, and to come,</line>
            <line>the discharge: your neck, sir, is pen, book and</line>
            <line>counters; so the acquittance follows.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POSTHUMUS LEONATUS</speaker>
            <line>I am merrier to die than thou art to live.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Gaoler</speaker>
            <line>Indeed, sir, he that sleeps feels not the</line>
            <line>tooth-ache: but a man that were to sleep your</line>
            <line>sleep, and a hangman to help him to bed, I think he</line>
            <line>would change places with his officer; for, look you,</line>
            <line>sir, you know not which way you shall go.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POSTHUMUS LEONATUS</speaker>
            <line>Yes, indeed do I, fellow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Gaoler</speaker>
            <line>Your death has eyes in 's head then; I have not seen</line>
            <line>him so pictured: you must either be directed by</line>
            <line>some that take upon them to know, or do take upon</line>
            <line>yourself that which I am sure you do not know, or</line>
            <line>jump the after inquiry on your own peril: and how</line>
            <line>you shall speed in your journey's end, I think you'll</line>
            <line>never return to tell one.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POSTHUMUS LEONATUS</speaker>
            <line>I tell thee, fellow, there are none want eyes to</line>
            <line>direct them the way I am going, but such as wink and</line>
            <line>will not use them.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Gaoler</speaker>
            <line>What an infinite mock is this, that a man should</line>
            <line>have the best use of eyes to see the way of</line>
            <line>blindness! I am sure hanging's the way of winking.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter a Messenger</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>Knock off his manacles; bring your prisoner to the king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POSTHUMUS LEONATUS</speaker>
            <line>Thou bring'st good news; I am called to be made free.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Gaoler</speaker>
            <line>I'll be hang'd then.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POSTHUMUS LEONATUS</speaker>
            <line>Thou shalt be then freer than a gaoler; no bolts for the dead.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt POSTHUMUS LEONATUS and Messenger</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Gaoler</speaker>
            <line>Unless a man would marry a gallows and beget young</line>
            <line>gibbets, I never saw one so prone. Yet, on my</line>
            <line>conscience, there are verier knaves desire to live,</line>
            <line>for all he be a Roman: and there be some of them</line>
            <line>too that die against their wills; so should I, if I</line>
            <line>were one. I would we were all of one mind, and one</line>
            <line>mind good; O, there were desolation of gaolers and</line>
            <line>gallowses! I speak against my present profit, but</line>
            <line>my wish hath a preferment in 't.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-5">
      <title>SCENE V.  Cymbeline's tent.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter CYMBELINE, BELARIUS, GUIDERIUS, ARVIRAGUS,
PISANIO, Lords, Officers, and Attendants</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>Stand by my side, you whom the gods have made</line>
            <line>Preservers of my throne. Woe is my heart</line>
            <line>That the poor soldier that so richly fought,</line>
            <line>Whose rags shamed gilded arms, whose naked breast</line>
            <line>Stepp'd before larges of proof, cannot be found:</line>
            <line>He shall be happy that can find him, if</line>
            <line>Our grace can make him so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BELARIUS</speaker>
            <line>I never saw</line>
            <line>Such noble fury in so poor a thing;</line>
            <line>Such precious deeds in one that promises nought</line>
            <line>But beggary and poor looks.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>No tidings of him?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISANIO</speaker>
            <line>He hath been search'd among the dead and living,</line>
            <line>But no trace of him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>To my grief, I am</line>
            <line>The heir of his reward;</line>
            <stagedir>To BELARIUS, GUIDERIUS, and ARVIRAGUS</stagedir>
            <line>which I will add</line>
            <line>To you, the liver, heart and brain of Britain,</line>
            <line>By whom I grant she lives. 'Tis now the time</line>
            <line>To ask of whence you are. Report it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BELARIUS</speaker>
            <line>Sir,</line>
            <line>In Cambria are we born, and gentlemen:</line>
            <line>Further to boast were neither true nor modest,</line>
            <line>Unless I add, we are honest.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>Bow your knees.</line>
            <line>Arise my knights o' the battle: I create you</line>
            <line>Companions to our person and will fit you</line>
            <line>With dignities becoming your estates.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter CORNELIUS and Ladies</stagedir>
            <line>There's business in these faces. Why so sadly</line>
            <line>Greet you our victory? you look like Romans,</line>
            <line>And not o' the court of Britain.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORNELIUS</speaker>
            <line>Hail, great king!</line>
            <line>To sour your happiness, I must report</line>
            <line>The queen is dead.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>Who worse than a physician</line>
            <line>Would this report become? But I consider,</line>
            <line>By medicine life may be prolong'd, yet death</line>
            <line>Will seize the doctor too. How ended she?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORNELIUS</speaker>
            <line>With horror, madly dying, like her life,</line>
            <line>Which, being cruel to the world, concluded</line>
            <line>Most cruel to herself. What she confess'd</line>
            <line>I will report, so please you: these her women</line>
            <line>Can trip me, if I err; who with wet cheeks</line>
            <line>Were present when she finish'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>Prithee, say.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORNELIUS</speaker>
            <line>First, she confess'd she never loved you, only</line>
            <line>Affected greatness got by you, not you:</line>
            <line>Married your royalty, was wife to your place;</line>
            <line>Abhorr'd your person.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>She alone knew this;</line>
            <line>And, but she spoke it dying, I would not</line>
            <line>Believe her lips in opening it. Proceed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORNELIUS</speaker>
            <line>Your daughter, whom she bore in hand to love</line>
            <line>With such integrity, she did confess</line>
            <line>Was as a scorpion to her sight; whose life,</line>
            <line>But that her flight prevented it, she had</line>
            <line>Ta'en off by poison.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>O most delicate fiend!</line>
            <line>Who is 't can read a woman? Is there more?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORNELIUS</speaker>
            <line>More, sir, and worse. She did confess she had</line>
            <line>For you a mortal mineral; which, being took,</line>
            <line>Should by the minute feed on life and lingering</line>
            <line>By inches waste you: in which time she purposed,</line>
            <line>By watching, weeping, tendance, kissing, to</line>
            <line>O'ercome you with her show, and in time,</line>
            <line>When she had fitted you with her craft, to work</line>
            <line>Her son into the adoption of the crown:</line>
            <line>But, failing of her end by his strange absence,</line>
            <line>Grew shameless-desperate; open'd, in despite</line>
            <line>Of heaven and men, her purposes; repented</line>
            <line>The evils she hatch'd were not effected; so</line>
            <line>Despairing died.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>Heard you all this, her women?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lady</speaker>
            <line>We did, so please your highness.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>Mine eyes</line>
            <line>Were not in fault, for she was beautiful;</line>
            <line>Mine ears, that heard her flattery; nor my heart,</line>
            <line>That thought her like her seeming; it had</line>
            <line>been vicious</line>
            <line>To have mistrusted her: yet, O my daughter!</line>
            <line>That it was folly in me, thou mayst say,</line>
            <line>And prove it in thy feeling. Heaven mend all!</line>
            <stagedir>Enter LUCIUS, IACHIMO, the Soothsayer, and other
Roman Prisoners, guarded; POSTHUMUS LEONATUS
behind, and IMOGEN</stagedir>
            <line>Thou comest not, Caius, now for tribute that</line>
            <line>The Britons have razed out, though with the loss</line>
            <line>Of many a bold one; whose kinsmen have made suit</line>
            <line>That their good souls may be appeased with slaughter</line>
            <line>Of you their captives, which ourself have granted:</line>
            <line>So think of your estate.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAIUS LUCIUS</speaker>
            <line>Consider, sir, the chance of war: the day</line>
            <line>Was yours by accident; had it gone with us,</line>
            <line>We should not, when the blood was cool,</line>
            <line>have threaten'd</line>
            <line>Our prisoners with the sword. But since the gods</line>
            <line>Will have it thus, that nothing but our lives</line>
            <line>May be call'd ransom, let it come: sufficeth</line>
            <line>A Roman with a Roman's heart can suffer:</line>
            <line>Augustus lives to think on't: and so much</line>
            <line>For my peculiar care. This one thing only</line>
            <line>I will entreat; my boy, a Briton born,</line>
            <line>Let him be ransom'd: never master had</line>
            <line>A page so kind, so duteous, diligent,</line>
            <line>So tender over his occasions, true,</line>
            <line>So feat, so nurse-like: let his virtue join</line>
            <line>With my request, which I make bold your highness</line>
            <line>Cannot deny; he hath done no Briton harm,</line>
            <line>Though he have served a Roman: save him, sir,</line>
            <line>And spare no blood beside.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>I have surely seen him:</line>
            <line>His favour is familiar to me. Boy,</line>
            <line>Thou hast look'd thyself into my grace,</line>
            <line>And art mine own. I know not why, wherefore,</line>
            <line>To say 'live, boy:' ne'er thank thy master; live:</line>
            <line>And ask of Cymbeline what boon thou wilt,</line>
            <line>Fitting my bounty and thy state, I'll give it;</line>
            <line>Yea, though thou do demand a prisoner,</line>
            <line>The noblest ta'en.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>I humbly thank your highness.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAIUS LUCIUS</speaker>
            <line>I do not bid thee beg my life, good lad;</line>
            <line>And yet I know thou wilt.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>No, no: alack,</line>
            <line>There's other work in hand: I see a thing</line>
            <line>Bitter to me as death: your life, good master,</line>
            <line>Must shuffle for itself.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAIUS LUCIUS</speaker>
            <line>The boy disdains me,</line>
            <line>He leaves me, scorns me: briefly die their joys</line>
            <line>That place them on the truth of girls and boys.</line>
            <line>Why stands he so perplex'd?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>What wouldst thou, boy?</line>
            <line>I love thee more and more: think more and more</line>
            <line>What's best to ask. Know'st him thou look'st on? speak,</line>
            <line>Wilt have him live? Is he thy kin? thy friend?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>He is a Roman; no more kin to me</line>
            <line>Than I to your highness; who, being born your vassal,</line>
            <line>Am something nearer.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>Wherefore eyest him so?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>I'll tell you, sir, in private, if you please</line>
            <line>To give me hearing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>Ay, with all my heart,</line>
            <line>And lend my best attention. What's thy name?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>Fidele, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>Thou'rt my good youth, my page;</line>
            <line>I'll be thy master: walk with me; speak freely.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>CYMBELINE and IMOGEN converse apart</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BELARIUS</speaker>
            <line>Is not this boy revived from death?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARVIRAGUS</speaker>
            <line>One sand another</line>
            <line>Not more resembles that sweet rosy lad</line>
            <line>Who died, and was Fidele. What think you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GUIDERIUS</speaker>
            <line>The same dead thing alive.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BELARIUS</speaker>
            <line>Peace, peace! see further; he eyes us not; forbear;</line>
            <line>Creatures may be alike: were 't he, I am sure</line>
            <line>He would have spoke to us.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GUIDERIUS</speaker>
            <line>But we saw him dead.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BELARIUS</speaker>
            <line>Be silent; let's see further.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISANIO</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir> It is my mistress:</line>
            <line>Since she is living, let the time run on</line>
            <line>To good or bad.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>CYMBELINE and IMOGEN come forward</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>Come, stand thou by our side;</line>
            <line>Make thy demand aloud.</line>
            <stagedir>To IACHIMO</stagedir>
            <line>Sir, step you forth;</line>
            <line>Give answer to this boy, and do it freely;</line>
            <line>Or, by our greatness and the grace of it,</line>
            <line>Which is our honour, bitter torture shall</line>
            <line>Winnow the truth from falsehood. On, speak to him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>My boon is, that this gentleman may render</line>
            <line>Of whom he had this ring.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POSTHUMUS LEONATUS</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>                 What's that to him?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>That diamond upon your finger, say</line>
            <line>How came it yours?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IACHIMO</speaker>
            <line>Thou'lt torture me to leave unspoken that</line>
            <line>Which, to be spoke, would torture thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>How! me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IACHIMO</speaker>
            <line>I am glad to be constrain'd to utter that</line>
            <line>Which torments me to conceal. By villany</line>
            <line>I got this ring: 'twas Leonatus' jewel;</line>
            <line>Whom thou didst banish; and--which more may</line>
            <line>grieve thee,</line>
            <line>As it doth me--a nobler sir ne'er lived</line>
            <line>'Twixt sky and ground. Wilt thou hear more, my lord?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>All that belongs to this.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IACHIMO</speaker>
            <line>That paragon, thy daughter,--</line>
            <line>For whom my heart drops blood, and my false spirits</line>
            <line>Quail to remember--Give me leave; I faint.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>My daughter! what of her? Renew thy strength:</line>
            <line>I had rather thou shouldst live while nature will</line>
            <line>Than die ere I hear more: strive, man, and speak.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IACHIMO</speaker>
            <line>Upon a time,--unhappy was the clock</line>
            <line>That struck the hour!--it was in Rome,--accursed</line>
            <line>The mansion where!--'twas at a feast,--O, would</line>
            <line>Our viands had been poison'd, or at least</line>
            <line>Those which I heaved to head!--the good Posthumus--</line>
            <line>What should I say? he was too good to be</line>
            <line>Where ill men were; and was the best of all</line>
            <line>Amongst the rarest of good ones,--sitting sadly,</line>
            <line>Hearing us praise our loves of Italy</line>
            <line>For beauty that made barren the swell'd boast</line>
            <line>Of him that best could speak, for feature, laming</line>
            <line>The shrine of Venus, or straight-pight Minerva.</line>
            <line>Postures beyond brief nature, for condition,</line>
            <line>A shop of all the qualities that man</line>
            <line>Loves woman for, besides that hook of wiving,</line>
            <line>Fairness which strikes the eye--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>I stand on fire:</line>
            <line>Come to the matter.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IACHIMO</speaker>
            <line>All too soon I shall,</line>
            <line>Unless thou wouldst grieve quickly. This Posthumus,</line>
            <line>Most like a noble lord in love and one</line>
            <line>That had a royal lover, took his hint;</line>
            <line>And, not dispraising whom we praised,--therein</line>
            <line>He was as calm as virtue--he began</line>
            <line>His mistress' picture; which by his tongue</line>
            <line>being made,</line>
            <line>And then a mind put in't, either our brags</line>
            <line>Were crack'd of kitchen-trolls, or his description</line>
            <line>Proved us unspeaking sots.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>Nay, nay, to the purpose.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IACHIMO</speaker>
            <line>Your daughter's chastity--there it begins.</line>
            <line>He spake of her, as Dian had hot dreams,</line>
            <line>And she alone were cold: whereat I, wretch,</line>
            <line>Made scruple of his praise; and wager'd with him</line>
            <line>Pieces of gold 'gainst this which then he wore</line>
            <line>Upon his honour'd finger, to attain</line>
            <line>In suit the place of's bed and win this ring</line>
            <line>By hers and mine adultery. He, true knight,</line>
            <line>No lesser of her honour confident</line>
            <line>Than I did truly find her, stakes this ring;</line>
            <line>And would so, had it been a carbuncle</line>
            <line>Of Phoebus' wheel, and might so safely, had it</line>
            <line>Been all the worth of's car. Away to Britain</line>
            <line>Post I in this design: well may you, sir,</line>
            <line>Remember me at court; where I was taught</line>
            <line>Of your chaste daughter the wide difference</line>
            <line>'Twixt amorous and villanous. Being thus quench'd</line>
            <line>Of hope, not longing, mine Italian brain</line>
            <line>'Gan in your duller Britain operate</line>
            <line>Most vilely; for my vantage, excellent:</line>
            <line>And, to be brief, my practise so prevail'd,</line>
            <line>That I return'd with simular proof enough</line>
            <line>To make the noble Leonatus mad,</line>
            <line>By wounding his belief in her renown</line>
            <line>With tokens thus, and thus; averting notes</line>
            <line>Of chamber-hanging, pictures, this her bracelet,--</line>
            <line>O cunning, how I got it!--nay, some marks</line>
            <line>Of secret on her person, that he could not</line>
            <line>But think her bond of chastity quite crack'd,</line>
            <line>I having ta'en the forfeit. Whereupon--</line>
            <line>Methinks, I see him now--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POSTHUMUS LEONATUS</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Advancing</stagedir>             Ay, so thou dost,</line>
            <line>Italian fiend! Ay me, most credulous fool,</line>
            <line>Egregious murderer, thief, any thing</line>
            <line>That's due to all the villains past, in being,</line>
            <line>To come! O, give me cord, or knife, or poison,</line>
            <line>Some upright justicer! Thou, king, send out</line>
            <line>For torturers ingenious: it is I</line>
            <line>That all the abhorred things o' the earth amend</line>
            <line>By being worse than they. I am Posthumus,</line>
            <line>That kill'd thy daughter:--villain-like, I lie--</line>
            <line>That caused a lesser villain than myself,</line>
            <line>A sacrilegious thief, to do't: the temple</line>
            <line>Of virtue was she; yea, and she herself.</line>
            <line>Spit, and throw stones, cast mire upon me, set</line>
            <line>The dogs o' the street to bay me: every villain</line>
            <line>Be call'd Posthumus Leonitus; and</line>
            <line>Be villany less than 'twas! O Imogen!</line>
            <line>My queen, my life, my wife! O Imogen,</line>
            <line>Imogen, Imogen!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>Peace, my lord; hear, hear--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POSTHUMUS LEONATUS</speaker>
            <line>Shall's have a play of this? Thou scornful page,</line>
            <line>There lie thy part.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Striking her: she falls</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISANIO</speaker>
            <line>O, gentlemen, help!</line>
            <line>Mine and your mistress! O, my lord Posthumus!</line>
            <line>You ne'er kill'd Imogen til now. Help, help!</line>
            <line>Mine honour'd lady!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>Does the world go round?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POSTHUMUS LEONATUS</speaker>
            <line>How come these staggers on me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISANIO</speaker>
            <line>Wake, my mistress!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>If this be so, the gods do mean to strike me</line>
            <line>To death with mortal joy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISANIO</speaker>
            <line>How fares thy mistress?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>O, get thee from my sight;</line>
            <line>Thou gavest me poison: dangerous fellow, hence!</line>
            <line>Breathe not where princes are.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>The tune of Imogen!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISANIO</speaker>
            <line>Lady,</line>
            <line>The gods throw stones of sulphur on me, if</line>
            <line>That box I gave you was not thought by me</line>
            <line>A precious thing: I had it from the queen.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>New matter still?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>It poison'd me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORNELIUS</speaker>
            <line>O gods!</line>
            <line>I left out one thing which the queen confess'd.</line>
            <line>Which must approve thee honest: 'If Pisanio</line>
            <line>Have,' said she, 'given his mistress that confection</line>
            <line>Which I gave him for cordial, she is served</line>
            <line>As I would serve a rat.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>What's this, Comelius?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORNELIUS</speaker>
            <line>The queen, sir, very oft importuned me</line>
            <line>To temper poisons for her, still pretending</line>
            <line>The satisfaction of her knowledge only</line>
            <line>In killing creatures vile, as cats and dogs,</line>
            <line>Of no esteem: I, dreading that her purpose</line>
            <line>Was of more danger, did compound for her</line>
            <line>A certain stuff, which, being ta'en, would cease</line>
            <line>The present power of life, but in short time</line>
            <line>All offices of nature should again</line>
            <line>Do their due functions. Have you ta'en of it?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>Most like I did, for I was dead.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BELARIUS</speaker>
            <line>My boys,</line>
            <line>There was our error.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GUIDERIUS</speaker>
            <line>This is, sure, Fidele.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>Why did you throw your wedded lady from you?</line>
            <line>Think that you are upon a rock; and now</line>
            <line>Throw me again.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Embracing him</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POSTHUMUS LEONATUS</speaker>
            <line>Hang there like a fruit, my soul,</line>
            <line>Till the tree die!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>How now, my flesh, my child!</line>
            <line>What, makest thou me a dullard in this act?</line>
            <line>Wilt thou not speak to me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Kneeling</stagedir>               Your blessing, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BELARIUS</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>To GUIDERIUS and ARVIRAGUS</stagedir>  Though you did love</line>
            <line>this youth, I blame ye not:</line>
            <line>You had a motive for't.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>My tears that fall</line>
            <line>Prove holy water on thee! Imogen,</line>
            <line>Thy mother's dead.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>I am sorry for't, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>O, she was nought; and long of her it was</line>
            <line>That we meet here so strangely: but her son</line>
            <line>Is gone, we know not how nor where.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISANIO</speaker>
            <line>My lord,</line>
            <line>Now fear is from me, I'll speak troth. Lord Cloten,</line>
            <line>Upon my lady's missing, came to me</line>
            <line>With his sword drawn; foam'd at the mouth, and swore,</line>
            <line>If I discover'd not which way she was gone,</line>
            <line>It was my instant death. By accident,</line>
            <line>had a feigned letter of my master's</line>
            <line>Then in my pocket; which directed him</line>
            <line>To seek her on the mountains near to Milford;</line>
            <line>Where, in a frenzy, in my master's garments,</line>
            <line>Which he enforced from me, away he posts</line>
            <line>With unchaste purpose and with oath to violate</line>
            <line>My lady's honour: what became of him</line>
            <line>I further know not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GUIDERIUS</speaker>
            <line>Let me end the story:</line>
            <line>I slew him there.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>Marry, the gods forfend!</line>
            <line>I would not thy good deeds should from my lips</line>
            <line>Pluck a bard sentence: prithee, valiant youth,</line>
            <line>Deny't again.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GUIDERIUS</speaker>
            <line>I have spoke it, and I did it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>He was a prince.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GUIDERIUS</speaker>
            <line>A most incivil one: the wrongs he did me</line>
            <line>Were nothing prince-like; for he did provoke me</line>
            <line>With language that would make me spurn the sea,</line>
            <line>If it could so roar to me: I cut off's head;</line>
            <line>And am right glad he is not standing here</line>
            <line>To tell this tale of mine.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>I am sorry for thee:</line>
            <line>By thine own tongue thou art condemn'd, and must</line>
            <line>Endure our law: thou'rt dead.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>That headless man</line>
            <line>I thought had been my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>Bind the offender,</line>
            <line>And take him from our presence.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BELARIUS</speaker>
            <line>Stay, sir king:</line>
            <line>This man is better than the man he slew,</line>
            <line>As well descended as thyself; and hath</line>
            <line>More of thee merited than a band of Clotens</line>
            <line>Had ever scar for.</line>
            <stagedir>To the Guard</stagedir>
            <line>Let his arms alone;</line>
            <line>They were not born for bondage.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>Why, old soldier,</line>
            <line>Wilt thou undo the worth thou art unpaid for,</line>
            <line>By tasting of our wrath? How of descent</line>
            <line>As good as we?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARVIRAGUS</speaker>
            <line>In that he spake too far.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>And thou shalt die for't.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BELARIUS</speaker>
            <line>We will die all three:</line>
            <line>But I will prove that two on's are as good</line>
            <line>As I have given out him. My sons, I must,</line>
            <line>For mine own part, unfold a dangerous speech,</line>
            <line>Though, haply, well for you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARVIRAGUS</speaker>
            <line>Your danger's ours.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GUIDERIUS</speaker>
            <line>And our good his.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BELARIUS</speaker>
            <line>Have at it then, by leave.</line>
            <line>Thou hadst, great king, a subject who</line>
            <line>Was call'd Belarius.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>What of him? he is</line>
            <line>A banish'd traitor.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BELARIUS</speaker>
            <line>He it is that hath</line>
            <line>Assumed this age; indeed a banish'd man;</line>
            <line>I know not how a traitor.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>Take him hence:</line>
            <line>The whole world shall not save him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BELARIUS</speaker>
            <line>Not too hot:</line>
            <line>First pay me for the nursing of thy sons;</line>
            <line>And let it be confiscate all, so soon</line>
            <line>As I have received it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>Nursing of my sons!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BELARIUS</speaker>
            <line>I am too blunt and saucy: here's my knee:</line>
            <line>Ere I arise, I will prefer my sons;</line>
            <line>Then spare not the old father. Mighty sir,</line>
            <line>These two young gentlemen, that call me father</line>
            <line>And think they are my sons, are none of mine;</line>
            <line>They are the issue of your loins, my liege,</line>
            <line>And blood of your begetting.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>How! my issue!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BELARIUS</speaker>
            <line>So sure as you your father's. I, old Morgan,</line>
            <line>Am that Belarius whom you sometime banish'd:</line>
            <line>Your pleasure was my mere offence, my punishment</line>
            <line>Itself, and all my treason; that I suffer'd</line>
            <line>Was all the harm I did. These gentle princes--</line>
            <line>For such and so they are--these twenty years</line>
            <line>Have I train'd up: those arts they have as I</line>
            <line>Could put into them; my breeding was, sir, as</line>
            <line>Your highness knows. Their nurse, Euriphile,</line>
            <line>Whom for the theft I wedded, stole these children</line>
            <line>Upon my banishment: I moved her to't,</line>
            <line>Having received the punishment before,</line>
            <line>For that which I did then: beaten for loyalty</line>
            <line>Excited me to treason: their dear loss,</line>
            <line>The more of you 'twas felt, the more it shaped</line>
            <line>Unto my end of stealing them. But, gracious sir,</line>
            <line>Here are your sons again; and I must lose</line>
            <line>Two of the sweet'st companions in the world.</line>
            <line>The benediction of these covering heavens</line>
            <line>Fall on their heads like dew! for they are worthy</line>
            <line>To inlay heaven with stars.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>Thou weep'st, and speak'st.</line>
            <line>The service that you three have done is more</line>
            <line>Unlike than this thou tell'st. I lost my children:</line>
            <line>If these be they, I know not how to wish</line>
            <line>A pair of worthier sons.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BELARIUS</speaker>
            <line>Be pleased awhile.</line>
            <line>This gentleman, whom I call Polydore,</line>
            <line>Most worthy prince, as yours, is true Guiderius:</line>
            <line>This gentleman, my Cadwal, Arviragus,</line>
            <line>Your younger princely son; he, sir, was lapp'd</line>
            <line>In a most curious mantle, wrought by the hand</line>
            <line>Of his queen mother, which for more probation</line>
            <line>I can with ease produce.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>Guiderius had</line>
            <line>Upon his neck a mole, a sanguine star;</line>
            <line>It was a mark of wonder.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BELARIUS</speaker>
            <line>This is he;</line>
            <line>Who hath upon him still that natural stamp:</line>
            <line>It was wise nature's end in the donation,</line>
            <line>To be his evidence now.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>O, what, am I</line>
            <line>A mother to the birth of three? Ne'er mother</line>
            <line>Rejoiced deliverance more. Blest pray you be,</line>
            <line>That, after this strange starting from your orbs,</line>
            <line>may reign in them now! O Imogen,</line>
            <line>Thou hast lost by this a kingdom.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>No, my lord;</line>
            <line>I have got two worlds by 't. O my gentle brothers,</line>
            <line>Have we thus met? O, never say hereafter</line>
            <line>But I am truest speaker you call'd me brother,</line>
            <line>When I was but your sister; I you brothers,</line>
            <line>When ye were so indeed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>Did you e'er meet?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARVIRAGUS</speaker>
            <line>Ay, my good lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GUIDERIUS</speaker>
            <line>And at first meeting loved;</line>
            <line>Continued so, until we thought he died.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CORNELIUS</speaker>
            <line>By the queen's dram she swallow'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>O rare instinct!</line>
            <line>When shall I hear all through? This fierce</line>
            <line>abridgement</line>
            <line>Hath to it circumstantial branches, which</line>
            <line>Distinction should be rich in. Where? how lived You?</line>
            <line>And when came you to serve our Roman captive?</line>
            <line>How parted with your brothers? how first met them?</line>
            <line>Why fled you from the court? and whither? These,</line>
            <line>And your three motives to the battle, with</line>
            <line>I know not how much more, should be demanded;</line>
            <line>And all the other by-dependencies,</line>
            <line>From chance to chance: but nor the time nor place</line>
            <line>Will serve our long inter'gatories. See,</line>
            <line>Posthumus anchors upon Imogen,</line>
            <line>And she, like harmless lightning, throws her eye</line>
            <line>On him, her brother, me, her master, hitting</line>
            <line>Each object with a joy: the counterchange</line>
            <line>Is severally in all. Let's quit this ground,</line>
            <line>And smoke the temple with our sacrifices.</line>
            <stagedir>To BELARIUS</stagedir>
            <line>Thou art my brother; so we'll hold thee ever.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>You are my father too, and did relieve me,</line>
            <line>To see this gracious season.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>All o'erjoy'd,</line>
            <line>Save these in bonds: let them be joyful too,</line>
            <line>For they shall taste our comfort.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>My good master,</line>
            <line>I will yet do you service.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAIUS LUCIUS</speaker>
            <line>Happy be you!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>The forlorn soldier, that so nobly fought,</line>
            <line>He would have well becomed this place, and graced</line>
            <line>The thankings of a king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POSTHUMUS LEONATUS</speaker>
            <line>I am, sir,</line>
            <line>The soldier that did company these three</line>
            <line>In poor beseeming; 'twas a fitment for</line>
            <line>The purpose I then follow'd. That I was he,</line>
            <line>Speak, Iachimo: I had you down and might</line>
            <line>Have made you finish.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IACHIMO</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Kneeling</stagedir>          I am down again:</line>
            <line>But now my heavy conscience sinks my knee,</line>
            <line>As then your force did. Take that life, beseech you,</line>
            <line>Which I so often owe: but your ring first;</line>
            <line>And here the bracelet of the truest princess</line>
            <line>That ever swore her faith.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POSTHUMUS LEONATUS</speaker>
            <line>Kneel not to me:</line>
            <line>The power that I have on you is, to spare you;</line>
            <line>The malice towards you to forgive you: live,</line>
            <line>And deal with others better.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>Nobly doom'd!</line>
            <line>We'll learn our freeness of a son-in-law;</line>
            <line>Pardon's the word to all.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARVIRAGUS</speaker>
            <line>You holp us, sir,</line>
            <line>As you did mean indeed to be our brother;</line>
            <line>Joy'd are we that you are.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POSTHUMUS LEONATUS</speaker>
            <line>Your servant, princes. Good my lord of Rome,</line>
            <line>Call forth your soothsayer: as I slept, methought</line>
            <line>Great Jupiter, upon his eagle back'd,</line>
            <line>Appear'd to me, with other spritely shows</line>
            <line>Of mine own kindred: when I waked, I found</line>
            <line>This label on my bosom; whose containing</line>
            <line>Is so from sense in hardness, that I can</line>
            <line>Make no collection of it: let him show</line>
            <line>His skill in the construction.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAIUS LUCIUS</speaker>
            <line>Philarmonus!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Soothsayer</speaker>
            <line>Here, my good lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAIUS LUCIUS</speaker>
            <line>Read, and declare the meaning.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Soothsayer</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>  'When as a lion's whelp shall, to himself</line>
            <line>unknown, without seeking find, and be embraced by a</line>
            <line>piece of tender air; and when from a stately cedar</line>
            <line>shall be lopped branches, which, being dead many</line>
            <line>years, shall after revive, be jointed to the old</line>
            <line>stock, and freshly grow; then shall Posthumus end</line>
            <line>his miseries, Britain be fortunate and flourish in</line>
            <line>peace and plenty.'</line>
            <line>Thou, Leonatus, art the lion's whelp;</line>
            <line>The fit and apt construction of thy name,</line>
            <line>Being Leonatus, doth import so much.</line>
            <stagedir>To CYMBELINE</stagedir>
            <line>The piece of tender air, thy virtuous daughter,</line>
            <line>Which we call 'mollis aer;' and 'mollis aer'</line>
            <line>We term it 'mulier:' which 'mulier' I divine</line>
            <line>Is this most constant wife; who, even now,</line>
            <line>Answering the letter of the oracle,</line>
            <line>Unknown to you, unsought, were clipp'd about</line>
            <line>With this most tender air.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>This hath some seeming.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Soothsayer</speaker>
            <line>The lofty cedar, royal Cymbeline,</line>
            <line>Personates thee: and thy lopp'd branches point</line>
            <line>Thy two sons forth; who, by Belarius stol'n,</line>
            <line>For many years thought dead, are now revived,</line>
            <line>To the majestic cedar join'd, whose issue</line>
            <line>Promises Britain peace and plenty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>Well</line>
            <line>My peace we will begin. And, Caius Lucius,</line>
            <line>Although the victor, we submit to Caesar,</line>
            <line>And to the Roman empire; promising</line>
            <line>To pay our wonted tribute, from the which</line>
            <line>We were dissuaded by our wicked queen;</line>
            <line>Whom heavens, in justice, both on her and hers,</line>
            <line>Have laid most heavy hand.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Soothsayer</speaker>
            <line>The fingers of the powers above do tune</line>
            <line>The harmony of this peace. The vision</line>
            <line>Which I made known to Lucius, ere the stroke</line>
            <line>Of this yet scarce-cold battle, at this instant</line>
            <line>Is full accomplish'd; for the Roman eagle,</line>
            <line>From south to west on wing soaring aloft,</line>
            <line>Lessen'd herself, and in the beams o' the sun</line>
            <line>So vanish'd: which foreshow'd our princely eagle,</line>
            <line>The imperial Caesar, should again unite</line>
            <line>His favour with the radiant Cymbeline,</line>
            <line>Which shines here in the west.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>Laud we the gods;</line>
            <line>And let our crooked smokes climb to their nostrils</line>
            <line>From our blest altars. Publish we this peace</line>
            <line>To all our subjects. Set we forward: let</line>
            <line>A Roman and a British ensign wave</line>
            <line>Friendly together: so through Lud's-town march:</line>
            <line>And in the temple of great Jupiter</line>
            <line>Our peace we'll ratify; seal it with feasts.</line>
            <line>Set on there! Never was a war did cease,</line>
            <line>Ere bloody hands were wash'd, with such a peace.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>