<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:shakespear:dtd:act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-3">
   <title>ACT III</title>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  Britain. A hall in Cymbeline's palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter in state, CYMBELINE, QUEEN, CLOTEN,
and Lords at one door, and at another,
CAIUS LUCIUS and Attendants</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>Now say, what would Augustus Caesar with us?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAIUS LUCIUS</speaker>
            <line>When Julius Caesar, whose remembrance yet</line>
            <line>Lives in men's eyes and will to ears and tongues</line>
            <line>Be theme and hearing ever, was in this Britain</line>
            <line>And conquer'd it, Cassibelan, thine uncle,--</line>
            <line>Famous in Caesar's praises, no whit less</line>
            <line>Than in his feats deserving it--for him</line>
            <line>And his succession granted Rome a tribute,</line>
            <line>Yearly three thousand pounds, which by thee lately</line>
            <line>Is left untender'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN</speaker>
            <line>And, to kill the marvel,</line>
            <line>Shall be so ever.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLOTEN</speaker>
            <line>There be many Caesars,</line>
            <line>Ere such another Julius. Britain is</line>
            <line>A world by itself; and we will nothing pay</line>
            <line>For wearing our own noses.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN</speaker>
            <line>That opportunity</line>
            <line>Which then they had to take from 's, to resume</line>
            <line>We have again. Remember, sir, my liege,</line>
            <line>The kings your ancestors, together with</line>
            <line>The natural bravery of your isle, which stands</line>
            <line>As Neptune's park, ribbed and paled in</line>
            <line>With rocks unscalable and roaring waters,</line>
            <line>With sands that will not bear your enemies' boats,</line>
            <line>But suck them up to the topmast. A kind of conquest</line>
            <line>Caesar made here; but made not here his brag</line>
            <line>Of 'Came' and 'saw' and 'overcame: ' with shame--</line>
            <line>That first that ever touch'd him--he was carried</line>
            <line>From off our coast, twice beaten; and his shipping--</line>
            <line>Poor ignorant baubles!-- upon our terrible seas,</line>
            <line>Like egg-shells moved upon their surges, crack'd</line>
            <line>As easily 'gainst our rocks: for joy whereof</line>
            <line>The famed Cassibelan, who was once at point--</line>
            <line>O giglot fortune!--to master Caesar's sword,</line>
            <line>Made Lud's town with rejoicing fires bright</line>
            <line>And Britons strut with courage.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLOTEN</speaker>
            <line>Come, there's no more tribute to be paid: our</line>
            <line>kingdom is stronger than it was at that time; and,</line>
            <line>as I said, there is no moe such Caesars: other of</line>
            <line>them may have crook'd noses, but to owe such</line>
            <line>straight arms, none.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>Son, let your mother end.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLOTEN</speaker>
            <line>We have yet many among us can gripe as hard as</line>
            <line>Cassibelan: I do not say I am one; but I have a</line>
            <line>hand. Why tribute? why should we pay tribute? If</line>
            <line>Caesar can hide the sun from us with a blanket, or</line>
            <line>put the moon in his pocket, we will pay him tribute</line>
            <line>for light; else, sir, no more tribute, pray you now.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>You must know,</line>
            <line>Till the injurious Romans did extort</line>
            <line>This tribute from us, we were free:</line>
            <line>Caesar's ambition,</line>
            <line>Which swell'd so much that it did almost stretch</line>
            <line>The sides o' the world, against all colour here</line>
            <line>Did put the yoke upon 's; which to shake off</line>
            <line>Becomes a warlike people, whom we reckon</line>
            <line>Ourselves to be.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLOTEN</speaker>
            <speaker>Lords</speaker>
            <line>We do.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>Say, then, to Caesar,</line>
            <line>Our ancestor was that Mulmutius which</line>
            <line>Ordain'd our laws, whose use the sword of Caesar</line>
            <line>Hath too much mangled; whose repair and franchise</line>
            <line>Shall, by the power we hold, be our good deed,</line>
            <line>Though Rome be therefore angry: Mulmutius made our laws,</line>
            <line>Who was the first of Britain which did put</line>
            <line>His brows within a golden crown and call'd</line>
            <line>Himself a king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAIUS LUCIUS</speaker>
            <line>I am sorry, Cymbeline,</line>
            <line>That I am to pronounce Augustus Caesar--</line>
            <line>Caesar, that hath more kings his servants than</line>
            <line>Thyself domestic officers--thine enemy:</line>
            <line>Receive it from me, then: war and confusion</line>
            <line>In Caesar's name pronounce I 'gainst thee: look</line>
            <line>For fury not to be resisted. Thus defied,</line>
            <line>I thank thee for myself.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>Thou art welcome, Caius.</line>
            <line>Thy Caesar knighted me; my youth I spent</line>
            <line>Much under him; of him I gather'd honour;</line>
            <line>Which he to seek of me again, perforce,</line>
            <line>Behoves me keep at utterance. I am perfect</line>
            <line>That the Pannonians and Dalmatians for</line>
            <line>Their liberties are now in arms; a precedent</line>
            <line>Which not to read would show the Britons cold:</line>
            <line>So Caesar shall not find them.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAIUS LUCIUS</speaker>
            <line>Let proof speak.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLOTEN</speaker>
            <line>His majesty bids you welcome. Make</line>
            <line>pastime with us a day or two, or longer: if</line>
            <line>you seek us afterwards in other terms, you</line>
            <line>shall find us in our salt-water girdle: if you</line>
            <line>beat us out of it, it is yours; if you fall in</line>
            <line>the adventure, our crows shall fare the better</line>
            <line>for you; and there's an end.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAIUS LUCIUS</speaker>
            <line>So, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>I know your master's pleasure and he mine:</line>
            <line>All the remain is 'Welcome!'</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  Another room in the palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter PISANIO, with a letter</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISANIO</speaker>
            <line>How? of adultery? Wherefore write you not</line>
            <line>What monster's her accuser? Leonatus,</line>
            <line>O master! what a strange infection</line>
            <line>Is fall'n into thy ear! What false Italian,</line>
            <line>As poisonous-tongued as handed, hath prevail'd</line>
            <line>On thy too ready hearing? Disloyal! No:</line>
            <line>She's punish'd for her truth, and undergoes,</line>
            <line>More goddess-like than wife-like, such assaults</line>
            <line>As would take in some virtue. O my master!</line>
            <line>Thy mind to her is now as low as were</line>
            <line>Thy fortunes. How! that I should murder her?</line>
            <line>Upon the love and truth and vows which I</line>
            <line>Have made to thy command? I, her? her blood?</line>
            <line>If it be so to do good service, never</line>
            <line>Let me be counted serviceable. How look I,</line>
            <line>That I should seem to lack humanity</line>
            <line>so much as this fact comes to?</line>
            <stagedir>Reading</stagedir>
            <line>'Do't: the letter</line>
            <line>that I have sent her, by her own command</line>
            <line>Shall give thee opportunity.' O damn'd paper!</line>
            <line>Black as the ink that's on thee! Senseless bauble,</line>
            <line>Art thou a feodary for this act, and look'st</line>
            <line>So virgin-like without? Lo, here she comes.</line>
            <line>I am ignorant in what I am commanded.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter IMOGEN</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>How now, Pisanio!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISANIO</speaker>
            <line>Madam, here is a letter from my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>Who? thy lord? that is my lord, Leonatus!</line>
            <line>O, learn'd indeed were that astronomer</line>
            <line>That knew the stars as I his characters;</line>
            <line>He'ld lay the future open. You good gods,</line>
            <line>Let what is here contain'd relish of love,</line>
            <line>Of my lord's health, of his content, yet not</line>
            <line>That we two are asunder; let that grieve him:</line>
            <line>Some griefs are med'cinable; that is one of them,</line>
            <line>For it doth physic love: of his content,</line>
            <line>All but in that! Good wax, thy leave. Blest be</line>
            <line>You bees that make these locks of counsel! Lovers</line>
            <line>And men in dangerous bonds pray not alike:</line>
            <line>Though forfeiters you cast in prison, yet</line>
            <line>You clasp young Cupid's tables. Good news, gods!</line>
            <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>
            <line>'Justice, and your father's wrath, should he take me</line>
            <line>in his dominion, could not be so cruel to me, as</line>
            <line>you, O the dearest of creatures, would even renew me</line>
            <line>with your eyes. Take notice that I am in Cambria,</line>
            <line>at Milford-Haven: what your own love will out of</line>
            <line>this advise you, follow. So he wishes you all</line>
            <line>happiness, that remains loyal to his vow, and your,</line>
            <line>increasing in love,</line>
            <line>LEONATUS POSTHUMUS.'</line>
            <line>O, for a horse with wings! Hear'st thou, Pisanio?</line>
            <line>He is at Milford-Haven: read, and tell me</line>
            <line>How far 'tis thither. If one of mean affairs</line>
            <line>May plod it in a week, why may not I</line>
            <line>Glide thither in a day? Then, true Pisanio,--</line>
            <line>Who long'st, like me, to see thy lord; who long'st,--</line>
            <line>let me bate,-but not like me--yet long'st,</line>
            <line>But in a fainter kind:--O, not like me;</line>
            <line>For mine's beyond beyond--say, and speak thick;</line>
            <line>Love's counsellor should fill the bores of hearing,</line>
            <line>To the smothering of the sense--how far it is</line>
            <line>To this same blessed Milford: and by the way</line>
            <line>Tell me how Wales was made so happy as</line>
            <line>To inherit such a haven: but first of all,</line>
            <line>How we may steal from hence, and for the gap</line>
            <line>That we shall make in time, from our hence-going</line>
            <line>And our return, to excuse: but first, how get hence:</line>
            <line>Why should excuse be born or e'er begot?</line>
            <line>We'll talk of that hereafter. Prithee, speak,</line>
            <line>How many score of miles may we well ride</line>
            <line>'Twixt hour and hour?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISANIO</speaker>
            <line>One score 'twixt sun and sun,</line>
            <line>Madam, 's enough for you:</line>
            <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>
            <line>and too much too.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>Why, one that rode to's execution, man,</line>
            <line>Could never go so slow: I have heard of</line>
            <line>riding wagers,</line>
            <line>Where horses have been nimbler than the sands</line>
            <line>That run i' the clock's behalf. But this is foolery:</line>
            <line>Go bid my woman feign a sickness; say</line>
            <line>She'll home to her father: and provide me presently</line>
            <line>A riding-suit, no costlier than would fit</line>
            <line>A franklin's housewife.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISANIO</speaker>
            <line>Madam, you're best consider.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>I see before me, man: nor here, nor here,</line>
            <line>Nor what ensues, but have a fog in them,</line>
            <line>That I cannot look through. Away, I prithee;</line>
            <line>Do as I bid thee: there's no more to say,</line>
            <line>Accessible is none but Milford way.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  Wales: a mountainous country with a cave.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter, from the cave, BELARIUS; GUIDERIUS,
and ARVIRAGUS following</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BELARIUS</speaker>
            <line>A goodly day not to keep house, with such</line>
            <line>Whose roof's as low as ours! Stoop, boys; this gate</line>
            <line>Instructs you how to adore the heavens and bows you</line>
            <line>To a morning's holy office: the gates of monarchs</line>
            <line>Are arch'd so high that giants may jet through</line>
            <line>And keep their impious turbans on, without</line>
            <line>Good morrow to the sun. Hail, thou fair heaven!</line>
            <line>We house i' the rock, yet use thee not so hardly</line>
            <line>As prouder livers do.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GUIDERIUS</speaker>
            <line>Hail, heaven!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARVIRAGUS</speaker>
            <line>Hail, heaven!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BELARIUS</speaker>
            <line>Now for our mountain sport: up to yond hill;</line>
            <line>Your legs are young; I'll tread these flats. Consider,</line>
            <line>When you above perceive me like a crow,</line>
            <line>That it is place which lessens and sets off;</line>
            <line>And you may then revolve what tales I have told you</line>
            <line>Of courts, of princes, of the tricks in war:</line>
            <line>This service is not service, so being done,</line>
            <line>But being so allow'd: to apprehend thus,</line>
            <line>Draws us a profit from all things we see;</line>
            <line>And often, to our comfort, shall we find</line>
            <line>The sharded beetle in a safer hold</line>
            <line>Than is the full-wing'd eagle. O, this life</line>
            <line>Is nobler than attending for a cheque,</line>
            <line>Richer than doing nothing for a bauble,</line>
            <line>Prouder than rustling in unpaid-for silk:</line>
            <line>Such gain the cap of him that makes 'em fine,</line>
            <line>Yet keeps his book uncross'd: no life to ours.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GUIDERIUS</speaker>
            <line>Out of your proof you speak: we, poor unfledged,</line>
            <line>Have never wing'd from view o' the nest, nor know not</line>
            <line>What air's from home. Haply this life is best,</line>
            <line>If quiet life be best; sweeter to you</line>
            <line>That have a sharper known; well corresponding</line>
            <line>With your stiff age: but unto us it is</line>
            <line>A cell of ignorance; travelling a-bed;</line>
            <line>A prison for a debtor, that not dares</line>
            <line>To stride a limit.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARVIRAGUS</speaker>
            <line>What should we speak of</line>
            <line>When we are old as you? when we shall hear</line>
            <line>The rain and wind beat dark December, how,</line>
            <line>In this our pinching cave, shall we discourse</line>
            <line>The freezing hours away? We have seen nothing;</line>
            <line>We are beastly, subtle as the fox for prey,</line>
            <line>Like warlike as the wolf for what we eat;</line>
            <line>Our valour is to chase what flies; our cage</line>
            <line>We make a quire, as doth the prison'd bird,</line>
            <line>And sing our bondage freely.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BELARIUS</speaker>
            <line>How you speak!</line>
            <line>Did you but know the city's usuries</line>
            <line>And felt them knowingly; the art o' the court</line>
            <line>As hard to leave as keep; whose top to climb</line>
            <line>Is certain falling, or so slippery that</line>
            <line>The fear's as bad as falling; the toil o' the war,</line>
            <line>A pain that only seems to seek out danger</line>
            <line>I' the name of fame and honour; which dies i'</line>
            <line>the search,</line>
            <line>And hath as oft a slanderous epitaph</line>
            <line>As record of fair act; nay, many times,</line>
            <line>Doth ill deserve by doing well; what's worse,</line>
            <line>Must court'sy at the censure:--O boys, this story</line>
            <line>The world may read in me: my body's mark'd</line>
            <line>With Roman swords, and my report was once</line>
            <line>First with the best of note: Cymbeline loved me,</line>
            <line>And when a soldier was the theme, my name</line>
            <line>Was not far off: then was I as a tree</line>
            <line>Whose boughs did bend with fruit: but in one night,</line>
            <line>A storm or robbery, call it what you will,</line>
            <line>Shook down my mellow hangings, nay, my leaves,</line>
            <line>And left me bare to weather.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GUIDERIUS</speaker>
            <line>Uncertain favour!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BELARIUS</speaker>
            <line>My fault being nothing--as I have told you oft--</line>
            <line>But that two villains, whose false oaths prevail'd</line>
            <line>Before my perfect honour, swore to Cymbeline</line>
            <line>I was confederate with the Romans: so</line>
            <line>Follow'd my banishment, and this twenty years</line>
            <line>This rock and these demesnes have been my world;</line>
            <line>Where I have lived at honest freedom, paid</line>
            <line>More pious debts to heaven than in all</line>
            <line>The fore-end of my time. But up to the mountains!</line>
            <line>This is not hunters' language: he that strikes</line>
            <line>The venison first shall be the lord o' the feast;</line>
            <line>To him the other two shall minister;</line>
            <line>And we will fear no poison, which attends</line>
            <line>In place of greater state. I'll meet you in the valleys.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt GUIDERIUS and ARVIRAGUS</stagedir>
            <line>How hard it is to hide the sparks of nature!</line>
            <line>These boys know little they are sons to the king;</line>
            <line>Nor Cymbeline dreams that they are alive.</line>
            <line>They think they are mine; and though train'd</line>
            <line>up thus meanly</line>
            <line>I' the cave wherein they bow, their thoughts do hit</line>
            <line>The roofs of palaces, and nature prompts them</line>
            <line>In simple and low things to prince it much</line>
            <line>Beyond the trick of others. This Polydore,</line>
            <line>The heir of Cymbeline and Britain, who</line>
            <line>The king his father call'd Guiderius,--Jove!</line>
            <line>When on my three-foot stool I sit and tell</line>
            <line>The warlike feats I have done, his spirits fly out</line>
            <line>Into my story: say 'Thus, mine enemy fell,</line>
            <line>And thus I set my foot on 's neck;' even then</line>
            <line>The princely blood flows in his cheek, he sweats,</line>
            <line>Strains his young nerves and puts himself in posture</line>
            <line>That acts my words. The younger brother, Cadwal,</line>
            <line>Once Arviragus, in as like a figure,</line>
            <line>Strikes life into my speech and shows much more</line>
            <line>His own conceiving.--Hark, the game is roused!</line>
            <line>O Cymbeline! heaven and my conscience knows</line>
            <line>Thou didst unjustly banish me: whereon,</line>
            <line>At three and two years old, I stole these babes;</line>
            <line>Thinking to bar thee of succession, as</line>
            <line>Thou reft'st me of my lands. Euriphile,</line>
            <line>Thou wast their nurse; they took thee for</line>
            <line>their mother,</line>
            <line>And every day do honour to her grave:</line>
            <line>Myself, Belarius, that am Morgan call'd,</line>
            <line>They take for natural father. The game is up.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-4">
      <title>SCENE IV.  Country near Milford-Haven.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter PISANIO and IMOGEN</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>Thou told'st me, when we came from horse, the place</line>
            <line>Was near at hand: ne'er long'd my mother so</line>
            <line>To see me first, as I have now. Pisanio! man!</line>
            <line>Where is Posthumus? What is in thy mind,</line>
            <line>That makes thee stare thus? Wherefore breaks that sigh</line>
            <line>From the inward of thee? One, but painted thus,</line>
            <line>Would be interpreted a thing perplex'd</line>
            <line>Beyond self-explication: put thyself</line>
            <line>Into a havior of less fear, ere wildness</line>
            <line>Vanquish my staider senses. What's the matter?</line>
            <line>Why tender'st thou that paper to me, with</line>
            <line>A look untender? If't be summer news,</line>
            <line>Smile to't before; if winterly, thou need'st</line>
            <line>But keep that countenance still. My husband's hand!</line>
            <line>That drug-damn'd Italy hath out-craftied him,</line>
            <line>And he's at some hard point. Speak, man: thy tongue</line>
            <line>May take off some extremity, which to read</line>
            <line>Would be even mortal to me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISANIO</speaker>
            <line>Please you, read;</line>
            <line>And you shall find me, wretched man, a thing</line>
            <line>The most disdain'd of fortune.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>  'Thy mistress, Pisanio, hath played the</line>
            <line>strumpet in my bed; the testimonies whereof lie</line>
            <line>bleeding in me. I speak not out of weak surmises,</line>
            <line>but from proof as strong as my grief and as certain</line>
            <line>as I expect my revenge. That part thou, Pisanio,</line>
            <line>must act for me, if thy faith be not tainted with</line>
            <line>the breach of hers. Let thine own hands take away</line>
            <line>her life: I shall give thee opportunity at</line>
            <line>Milford-Haven. She hath my letter for the purpose</line>
            <line>where, if thou fear to strike and to make me certain</line>
            <line>it is done, thou art the pandar to her dishonour and</line>
            <line>equally to me disloyal.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISANIO</speaker>
            <line>What shall I need to draw my sword? the paper</line>
            <line>Hath cut her throat already. No, 'tis slander,</line>
            <line>Whose edge is sharper than the sword, whose tongue</line>
            <line>Outvenoms all the worms of Nile, whose breath</line>
            <line>Rides on the posting winds and doth belie</line>
            <line>All corners of the world: kings, queens and states,</line>
            <line>Maids, matrons, nay, the secrets of the grave</line>
            <line>This viperous slander enters. What cheer, madam?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>False to his bed! What is it to be false?</line>
            <line>To lie in watch there and to think on him?</line>
            <line>To weep 'twixt clock and clock? if sleep</line>
            <line>charge nature,</line>
            <line>To break it with a fearful dream of him</line>
            <line>And cry myself awake? that's false to's bed, is it?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISANIO</speaker>
            <line>Alas, good lady!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>I false! Thy conscience witness: Iachimo,</line>
            <line>Thou didst accuse him of incontinency;</line>
            <line>Thou then look'dst like a villain; now methinks</line>
            <line>Thy favour's good enough. Some jay of Italy</line>
            <line>Whose mother was her painting, hath betray'd him:</line>
            <line>Poor I am stale, a garment out of fashion;</line>
            <line>And, for I am richer than to hang by the walls,</line>
            <line>I must be ripp'd:--to pieces with me!--O,</line>
            <line>Men's vows are women's traitors! All good seeming,</line>
            <line>By thy revolt, O husband, shall be thought</line>
            <line>Put on for villany; not born where't grows,</line>
            <line>But worn a bait for ladies.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISANIO</speaker>
            <line>Good madam, hear me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>True honest men being heard, like false Aeneas,</line>
            <line>Were in his time thought false, and Sinon's weeping</line>
            <line>Did scandal many a holy tear, took pity</line>
            <line>From most true wretchedness: so thou, Posthumus,</line>
            <line>Wilt lay the leaven on all proper men;</line>
            <line>Goodly and gallant shall be false and perjured</line>
            <line>From thy great fall. Come, fellow, be thou honest:</line>
            <line>Do thou thy master's bidding: when thou see'st him,</line>
            <line>A little witness my obedience: look!</line>
            <line>I draw the sword myself: take it, and hit</line>
            <line>The innocent mansion of my love, my heart;</line>
            <line>Fear not; 'tis empty of all things but grief;</line>
            <line>Thy master is not there, who was indeed</line>
            <line>The riches of it: do his bidding; strike</line>
            <line>Thou mayst be valiant in a better cause;</line>
            <line>But now thou seem'st a coward.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISANIO</speaker>
            <line>Hence, vile instrument!</line>
            <line>Thou shalt not damn my hand.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>Why, I must die;</line>
            <line>And if I do not by thy hand, thou art</line>
            <line>No servant of thy master's. Against self-slaughter</line>
            <line>There is a prohibition so divine</line>
            <line>That cravens my weak hand. Come, here's my heart.</line>
            <line>Something's afore't. Soft, soft! we'll no defence;</line>
            <line>Obedient as the scabbard. What is here?</line>
            <line>The scriptures of the loyal Leonatus,</line>
            <line>All turn'd to heresy? Away, away,</line>
            <line>Corrupters of my faith! you shall no more</line>
            <line>Be stomachers to my heart. Thus may poor fools</line>
            <line>Believe false teachers: though those that</line>
            <line>are betray'd</line>
            <line>Do feel the treason sharply, yet the traitor</line>
            <line>Stands in worse case of woe.</line>
            <line>And thou, Posthumus, thou that didst set up</line>
            <line>My disobedience 'gainst the king my father</line>
            <line>And make me put into contempt the suits</line>
            <line>Of princely fellows, shalt hereafter find</line>
            <line>It is no act of common passage, but</line>
            <line>A strain of rareness: and I grieve myself</line>
            <line>To think, when thou shalt be disedged by her</line>
            <line>That now thou tirest on, how thy memory</line>
            <line>Will then be pang'd by me. Prithee, dispatch:</line>
            <line>The lamb entreats the butcher: where's thy knife?</line>
            <line>Thou art too slow to do thy master's bidding,</line>
            <line>When I desire it too.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISANIO</speaker>
            <line>O gracious lady,</line>
            <line>Since I received command to do this business</line>
            <line>I have not slept one wink.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>Do't, and to bed then.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISANIO</speaker>
            <line>I'll wake mine eye-balls blind first.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>Wherefore then</line>
            <line>Didst undertake it? Why hast thou abused</line>
            <line>So many miles with a pretence? this place?</line>
            <line>Mine action and thine own? our horses' labour?</line>
            <line>The time inviting thee? the perturb'd court,</line>
            <line>For my being absent? whereunto I never</line>
            <line>Purpose return. Why hast thou gone so far,</line>
            <line>To be unbent when thou hast ta'en thy stand,</line>
            <line>The elected deer before thee?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISANIO</speaker>
            <line>But to win time</line>
            <line>To lose so bad employment; in the which</line>
            <line>I have consider'd of a course. Good lady,</line>
            <line>Hear me with patience.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>Talk thy tongue weary; speak</line>
            <line>I have heard I am a strumpet; and mine ear</line>
            <line>Therein false struck, can take no greater wound,</line>
            <line>Nor tent to bottom that. But speak.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISANIO</speaker>
            <line>Then, madam,</line>
            <line>I thought you would not back again.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>Most like;</line>
            <line>Bringing me here to kill me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISANIO</speaker>
            <line>Not so, neither:</line>
            <line>But if I were as wise as honest, then</line>
            <line>My purpose would prove well. It cannot be</line>
            <line>But that my master is abused:</line>
            <line>Some villain, ay, and singular in his art.</line>
            <line>Hath done you both this cursed injury.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>Some Roman courtezan.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISANIO</speaker>
            <line>No, on my life.</line>
            <line>I'll give but notice you are dead and send him</line>
            <line>Some bloody sign of it; for 'tis commanded</line>
            <line>I should do so: you shall be miss'd at court,</line>
            <line>And that will well confirm it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>Why good fellow,</line>
            <line>What shall I do the where? where bide? how live?</line>
            <line>Or in my life what comfort, when I am</line>
            <line>Dead to my husband?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISANIO</speaker>
            <line>If you'll back to the court--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>No court, no father; nor no more ado</line>
            <line>With that harsh, noble, simple nothing,</line>
            <line>That Cloten, whose love-suit hath been to me</line>
            <line>As fearful as a siege.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISANIO</speaker>
            <line>If not at court,</line>
            <line>Then not in Britain must you bide.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>Where then</line>
            <line>Hath Britain all the sun that shines? Day, night,</line>
            <line>Are they not but in Britain? I' the world's volume</line>
            <line>Our Britain seems as of it, but not in 't;</line>
            <line>In a great pool a swan's nest: prithee, think</line>
            <line>There's livers out of Britain.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISANIO</speaker>
            <line>I am most glad</line>
            <line>You think of other place. The ambassador,</line>
            <line>Lucius the Roman, comes to Milford-Haven</line>
            <line>To-morrow: now, if you could wear a mind</line>
            <line>Dark as your fortune is, and but disguise</line>
            <line>That which, to appear itself, must not yet be</line>
            <line>But by self-danger, you should tread a course</line>
            <line>Pretty and full of view; yea, haply, near</line>
            <line>The residence of Posthumus; so nigh at least</line>
            <line>That though his actions were not visible, yet</line>
            <line>Report should render him hourly to your ear</line>
            <line>As truly as he moves.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>O, for such means!</line>
            <line>Though peril to my modesty, not death on't,</line>
            <line>I would adventure.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISANIO</speaker>
            <line>Well, then, here's the point:</line>
            <line>You must forget to be a woman; change</line>
            <line>Command into obedience: fear and niceness--</line>
            <line>The handmaids of all women, or, more truly,</line>
            <line>Woman its pretty self--into a waggish courage:</line>
            <line>Ready in gibes, quick-answer'd, saucy and</line>
            <line>As quarrelous as the weasel; nay, you must</line>
            <line>Forget that rarest treasure of your cheek,</line>
            <line>Exposing it--but, O, the harder heart!</line>
            <line>Alack, no remedy!--to the greedy touch</line>
            <line>Of common-kissing Titan, and forget</line>
            <line>Your laboursome and dainty trims, wherein</line>
            <line>You made great Juno angry.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>Nay, be brief</line>
            <line>I see into thy end, and am almost</line>
            <line>A man already.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISANIO</speaker>
            <line>First, make yourself but like one.</line>
            <line>Fore-thinking this, I have already fit--</line>
            <line>'Tis in my cloak-bag--doublet, hat, hose, all</line>
            <line>That answer to them: would you in their serving,</line>
            <line>And with what imitation you can borrow</line>
            <line>From youth of such a season, 'fore noble Lucius</line>
            <line>Present yourself, desire his service, tell him</line>
            <line>wherein you're happy,--which you'll make him know,</line>
            <line>If that his head have ear in music,--doubtless</line>
            <line>With joy he will embrace you, for he's honourable</line>
            <line>And doubling that, most holy. Your means abroad,</line>
            <line>You have me, rich; and I will never fail</line>
            <line>Beginning nor supplyment.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>Thou art all the comfort</line>
            <line>The gods will diet me with. Prithee, away:</line>
            <line>There's more to be consider'd; but we'll even</line>
            <line>All that good time will give us: this attempt</line>
            <line>I am soldier to, and will abide it with</line>
            <line>A prince's courage. Away, I prithee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISANIO</speaker>
            <line>Well, madam, we must take a short farewell,</line>
            <line>Lest, being miss'd, I be suspected of</line>
            <line>Your carriage from the court. My noble mistress,</line>
            <line>Here is a box; I had it from the queen:</line>
            <line>What's in't is precious; if you are sick at sea,</line>
            <line>Or stomach-qualm'd at land, a dram of this</line>
            <line>Will drive away distemper. To some shade,</line>
            <line>And fit you to your manhood. May the gods</line>
            <line>Direct you to the best!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>Amen: I thank thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt, severally</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-5">
      <title>SCENE V.  A room in Cymbeline's palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter CYMBELINE, QUEEN, CLOTEN, LUCIUS,
Lords, and Attendants</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>Thus far; and so farewell.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAIUS LUCIUS</speaker>
            <line>Thanks, royal sir.</line>
            <line>My emperor hath wrote, I must from hence;</line>
            <line>And am right sorry that I must report ye</line>
            <line>My master's enemy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>Our subjects, sir,</line>
            <line>Will not endure his yoke; and for ourself</line>
            <line>To show less sovereignty than they, must needs</line>
            <line>Appear unkinglike.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAIUS LUCIUS</speaker>
            <line>So, sir: I desire of you</line>
            <line>A conduct over-land to Milford-Haven.</line>
            <line>Madam, all joy befal your grace!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN</speaker>
            <line>And you!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>My lords, you are appointed for that office;</line>
            <line>The due of honour in no point omit.</line>
            <line>So farewell, noble Lucius.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAIUS LUCIUS</speaker>
            <line>Your hand, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLOTEN</speaker>
            <line>Receive it friendly; but from this time forth</line>
            <line>I wear it as your enemy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAIUS LUCIUS</speaker>
            <line>Sir, the event</line>
            <line>Is yet to name the winner: fare you well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>Leave not the worthy Lucius, good my lords,</line>
            <line>Till he have cross'd the Severn. Happiness!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt LUCIUS and Lords</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN</speaker>
            <line>He goes hence frowning: but it honours us</line>
            <line>That we have given him cause.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLOTEN</speaker>
            <line>'Tis all the better;</line>
            <line>Your valiant Britons have their wishes in it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>Lucius hath wrote already to the emperor</line>
            <line>How it goes here. It fits us therefore ripely</line>
            <line>Our chariots and our horsemen be in readiness:</line>
            <line>The powers that he already hath in Gallia</line>
            <line>Will soon be drawn to head, from whence he moves</line>
            <line>His war for Britain.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN</speaker>
            <line>'Tis not sleepy business;</line>
            <line>But must be look'd to speedily and strongly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>Our expectation that it would be thus</line>
            <line>Hath made us forward. But, my gentle queen,</line>
            <line>Where is our daughter? She hath not appear'd</line>
            <line>Before the Roman, nor to us hath tender'd</line>
            <line>The duty of the day: she looks us like</line>
            <line>A thing more made of malice than of duty:</line>
            <line>We have noted it. Call her before us; for</line>
            <line>We have been too slight in sufferance.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit an Attendant</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN</speaker>
            <line>Royal sir,</line>
            <line>Since the exile of Posthumus, most retired</line>
            <line>Hath her life been; the cure whereof, my lord,</line>
            <line>'Tis time must do. Beseech your majesty,</line>
            <line>Forbear sharp speeches to her: she's a lady</line>
            <line>So tender of rebukes that words are strokes</line>
            <line>And strokes death to her.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter Attendant</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>Where is she, sir? How</line>
            <line>Can her contempt be answer'd?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Attendant</speaker>
            <line>Please you, sir,</line>
            <line>Her chambers are all lock'd; and there's no answer</line>
            <line>That will be given to the loudest noise we make.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN</speaker>
            <line>My lord, when last I went to visit her,</line>
            <line>She pray'd me to excuse her keeping close,</line>
            <line>Whereto constrain'd by her infirmity,</line>
            <line>She should that duty leave unpaid to you,</line>
            <line>Which daily she was bound to proffer: this</line>
            <line>She wish'd me to make known; but our great court</line>
            <line>Made me to blame in memory.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>Her doors lock'd?</line>
            <line>Not seen of late? Grant, heavens, that which I fear</line>
            <line>Prove false!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN</speaker>
            <line>Son, I say, follow the king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLOTEN</speaker>
            <line>That man of hers, Pisanio, her old servant,</line>
            <line>have not seen these two days.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN</speaker>
            <line>Go, look after.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit CLOTEN</stagedir>
            <line>Pisanio, thou that stand'st so for Posthumus!</line>
            <line>He hath a drug of mine; I pray his absence</line>
            <line>Proceed by swallowing that, for he believes</line>
            <line>It is a thing most precious. But for her,</line>
            <line>Where is she gone? Haply, despair hath seized her,</line>
            <line>Or, wing'd with fervor of her love, she's flown</line>
            <line>To her desired Posthumus: gone she is</line>
            <line>To death or to dishonour; and my end</line>
            <line>Can make good use of either: she being down,</line>
            <line>I have the placing of the British crown.</line>
            <stagedir>Re-enter CLOTEN</stagedir>
            <line>How now, my son!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLOTEN</speaker>
            <line>'Tis certain she is fled.</line>
            <line>Go in and cheer the king: he rages; none</line>
            <line>Dare come about him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>            All the better: may</line>
            <line>This night forestall him of the coming day!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLOTEN</speaker>
            <line>I love and hate her: for she's fair and royal,</line>
            <line>And that she hath all courtly parts more exquisite</line>
            <line>Than lady, ladies, woman; from every one</line>
            <line>The best she hath, and she, of all compounded,</line>
            <line>Outsells them all; I love her therefore: but</line>
            <line>Disdaining me and throwing favours on</line>
            <line>The low Posthumus slanders so her judgment</line>
            <line>That what's else rare is choked; and in that point</line>
            <line>I will conclude to hate her, nay, indeed,</line>
            <line>To be revenged upon her. For when fools Shall--</line>
            <stagedir>Enter PISANIO</stagedir>
            <line>Who is here? What, are you packing, sirrah?</line>
            <line>Come hither: ah, you precious pander! Villain,</line>
            <line>Where is thy lady? In a word; or else</line>
            <line>Thou art straightway with the fiends.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISANIO</speaker>
            <line>O, good my lord!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLOTEN</speaker>
            <line>Where is thy lady? Or, by Jupiter,--</line>
            <line>I will not ask again. Close villain,</line>
            <line>I'll have this secret from thy heart, or rip</line>
            <line>Thy heart to find it. Is she with Posthumus?</line>
            <line>From whose so many weights of baseness cannot</line>
            <line>A dram of worth be drawn.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISANIO</speaker>
            <line>Alas, my lord,</line>
            <line>How can she be with him? When was she missed?</line>
            <line>He is in Rome.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLOTEN</speaker>
            <line>Where is she, sir? Come nearer;</line>
            <line>No further halting: satisfy me home</line>
            <line>What is become of her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISANIO</speaker>
            <line>O, my all-worthy lord!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLOTEN</speaker>
            <line>All-worthy villain!</line>
            <line>Discover where thy mistress is at once,</line>
            <line>At the next word: no more of 'worthy lord!'</line>
            <line>Speak, or thy silence on the instant is</line>
            <line>Thy condemnation and thy death.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISANIO</speaker>
            <line>Then, sir,</line>
            <line>This paper is the history of my knowledge</line>
            <line>Touching her flight.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Presenting a letter</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLOTEN</speaker>
            <line>Let's see't. I will pursue her</line>
            <line>Even to Augustus' throne.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISANIO</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>                 Or this, or perish.</line>
            <line>She's far enough; and what he learns by this</line>
            <line>May prove his travel, not her danger.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLOTEN</speaker>
            <line>Hum!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISANIO</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  I'll write to my lord she's dead. O Imogen,</line>
            <line>Safe mayst thou wander, safe return again!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLOTEN</speaker>
            <line>Sirrah, is this letter true?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISANIO</speaker>
            <line>Sir, as I think.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLOTEN</speaker>
            <line>It is Posthumus' hand; I know't. Sirrah, if thou</line>
            <line>wouldst not be a villain, but do me true service,</line>
            <line>undergo those employments wherein I should have</line>
            <line>cause to use thee with a serious industry, that is,</line>
            <line>what villany soe'er I bid thee do, to perform it</line>
            <line>directly and truly, I would think thee an honest</line>
            <line>man: thou shouldst neither want my means for thy</line>
            <line>relief nor my voice for thy preferment.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISANIO</speaker>
            <line>Well, my good lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLOTEN</speaker>
            <line>Wilt thou serve me? for since patiently and</line>
            <line>constantly thou hast stuck to the bare fortune of</line>
            <line>that beggar Posthumus, thou canst not, in the</line>
            <line>course of gratitude, but be a diligent follower of</line>
            <line>mine: wilt thou serve me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISANIO</speaker>
            <line>Sir, I will.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLOTEN</speaker>
            <line>Give me thy hand; here's my purse. Hast any of thy</line>
            <line>late master's garments in thy possession?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISANIO</speaker>
            <line>I have, my lord, at my lodging, the same suit he</line>
            <line>wore when he took leave of my lady and mistress.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLOTEN</speaker>
            <line>The first service thou dost me, fetch that suit</line>
            <line>hither: let it be thy lint service; go.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISANIO</speaker>
            <line>I shall, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLOTEN</speaker>
            <line>Meet thee at Milford-Haven!--I forgot to ask him one</line>
            <line>thing; I'll remember't anon:--even there, thou</line>
            <line>villain Posthumus, will I kill thee. I would these</line>
            <line>garments were come. She said upon a time--the</line>
            <line>bitterness of it I now belch from my heart--that she</line>
            <line>held the very garment of Posthumus in more respect</line>
            <line>than my noble and natural person together with the</line>
            <line>adornment of my qualities. With that suit upon my</line>
            <line>back, will I ravish her: first kill him, and in her</line>
            <line>eyes; there shall she see my valour, which will then</line>
            <line>be a torment to her contempt. He on the ground, my</line>
            <line>speech of insultment ended on his dead body, and</line>
            <line>when my lust hath dined,--which, as I say, to vex</line>
            <line>her I will execute in the clothes that she so</line>
            <line>praised,--to the court I'll knock her back, foot</line>
            <line>her home again. She hath despised me rejoicingly,</line>
            <line>and I'll be merry in my revenge.</line>
            <stagedir>Re-enter PISANIO, with the clothes</stagedir>
            <line>Be those the garments?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISANIO</speaker>
            <line>Ay, my noble lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLOTEN</speaker>
            <line>How long is't since she went to Milford-Haven?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISANIO</speaker>
            <line>She can scarce be there yet.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLOTEN</speaker>
            <line>Bring this apparel to my chamber; that is the second</line>
            <line>thing that I have commanded thee: the third is,</line>
            <line>that thou wilt be a voluntary mute to my design. Be</line>
            <line>but duteous, and true preferment shall tender itself</line>
            <line>to thee. My revenge is now at Milford: would I had</line>
            <line>wings to follow it! Come, and be true.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISANIO</speaker>
            <line>Thou bid'st me to my loss: for true to thee</line>
            <line>Were to prove false, which I will never be,</line>
            <line>To him that is most true. To Milford go,</line>
            <line>And find not her whom thou pursuest. Flow, flow,</line>
            <line>You heavenly blessings, on her! This fool's speed</line>
            <line>Be cross'd with slowness; labour be his meed!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-6">
      <title>SCENE VI.  Wales. Before the cave of Belarius.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter IMOGEN, in boy's clothes</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>I see a man's life is a tedious one:</line>
            <line>I have tired myself, and for two nights together</line>
            <line>Have made the ground my bed. I should be sick,</line>
            <line>But that my resolution helps me. Milford,</line>
            <line>When from the mountain-top Pisanio show'd thee,</line>
            <line>Thou wast within a ken: O Jove! I think</line>
            <line>Foundations fly the wretched; such, I mean,</line>
            <line>Where they should be relieved. Two beggars told me</line>
            <line>I could not miss my way: will poor folks lie,</line>
            <line>That have afflictions on them, knowing 'tis</line>
            <line>A punishment or trial? Yes; no wonder,</line>
            <line>When rich ones scarce tell true. To lapse in fulness</line>
            <line>Is sorer than to lie for need, and falsehood</line>
            <line>Is worse in kings than beggars. My dear lord!</line>
            <line>Thou art one o' the false ones. Now I think on thee,</line>
            <line>My hunger's gone; but even before, I was</line>
            <line>At point to sink for food. But what is this?</line>
            <line>Here is a path to't: 'tis some savage hold:</line>
            <line>I were best not to call; I dare not call:</line>
            <line>yet famine,</line>
            <line>Ere clean it o'erthrow nature, makes it valiant,</line>
            <line>Plenty and peace breeds cowards: hardness ever</line>
            <line>Of hardiness is mother. Ho! who's here?</line>
            <line>If any thing that's civil, speak; if savage,</line>
            <line>Take or lend. Ho! No answer? Then I'll enter.</line>
            <line>Best draw my sword: and if mine enemy</line>
            <line>But fear the sword like me, he'll scarcely look on't.</line>
            <line>Such a foe, good heavens!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit, to the cave</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Enter BELARIUS, GUIDERIUS, and ARVIRAGUS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BELARIUS</speaker>
            <line>You, Polydote, have proved best woodman and</line>
            <line>Are master of the feast: Cadwal and I</line>
            <line>Will play the cook and servant; 'tis our match:</line>
            <line>The sweat of industry would dry and die,</line>
            <line>But for the end it works to. Come; our stomachs</line>
            <line>Will make what's homely savoury: weariness</line>
            <line>Can snore upon the flint, when resty sloth</line>
            <line>Finds the down pillow hard. Now peace be here,</line>
            <line>Poor house, that keep'st thyself!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GUIDERIUS</speaker>
            <line>I am thoroughly weary.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARVIRAGUS</speaker>
            <line>I am weak with toil, yet strong in appetite.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GUIDERIUS</speaker>
            <line>There is cold meat i' the cave; we'll browse on that,</line>
            <line>Whilst what we have kill'd be cook'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BELARIUS</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Looking into the cave</stagedir>
            </line>
            <line>Stay; come not in.</line>
            <line>But that it eats our victuals, I should think</line>
            <line>Here were a fairy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GUIDERIUS</speaker>
            <line>What's the matter, sir?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BELARIUS</speaker>
            <line>By Jupiter, an angel! or, if not,</line>
            <line>An earthly paragon! Behold divineness</line>
            <line>No elder than a boy!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter IMOGEN</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>Good masters, harm me not:</line>
            <line>Before I enter'd here, I call'd; and thought</line>
            <line>To have begg'd or bought what I have took:</line>
            <line>good troth,</line>
            <line>I have stol'n nought, nor would not, though I had found</line>
            <line>Gold strew'd i' the floor. Here's money for my meat:</line>
            <line>I would have left it on the board so soon</line>
            <line>As I had made my meal, and parted</line>
            <line>With prayers for the provider.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GUIDERIUS</speaker>
            <line>Money, youth?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARVIRAGUS</speaker>
            <line>All gold and silver rather turn to dirt!</line>
            <line>As 'tis no better reckon'd, but of those</line>
            <line>Who worship dirty gods.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>I see you're angry:</line>
            <line>Know, if you kill me for my fault, I should</line>
            <line>Have died had I not made it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BELARIUS</speaker>
            <line>Whither bound?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>To Milford-Haven.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BELARIUS</speaker>
            <line>What's your name?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>Fidele, sir. I have a kinsman who</line>
            <line>Is bound for Italy; he embark'd at Milford;</line>
            <line>To whom being going, almost spent with hunger,</line>
            <line>I am fall'n in this offence.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BELARIUS</speaker>
            <line>Prithee, fair youth,</line>
            <line>Think us no churls, nor measure our good minds</line>
            <line>By this rude place we live in. Well encounter'd!</line>
            <line>'Tis almost night: you shall have better cheer</line>
            <line>Ere you depart: and thanks to stay and eat it.</line>
            <line>Boys, bid him welcome.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GUIDERIUS</speaker>
            <line>Were you a woman, youth,</line>
            <line>I should woo hard but be your groom. In honesty,</line>
            <line>I bid for you as I'd buy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARVIRAGUS</speaker>
            <line>I'll make't my comfort</line>
            <line>He is a man; I'll love him as my brother:</line>
            <line>And such a welcome as I'd give to him</line>
            <line>After long absence, such is yours: most welcome!</line>
            <line>Be sprightly, for you fall 'mongst friends.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>'Mongst friends,</line>
            <line>If brothers.</line>
            <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>
            <line>Would it had been so, that they</line>
            <line>Had been my father's sons! then had my prize</line>
            <line>Been less, and so more equal ballasting</line>
            <line>To thee, Posthumus.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BELARIUS</speaker>
            <line>He wrings at some distress.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GUIDERIUS</speaker>
            <line>Would I could free't!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARVIRAGUS</speaker>
            <line>Or I, whate'er it be,</line>
            <line>What pain it cost, what danger. God's!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BELARIUS</speaker>
            <line>Hark, boys.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Whispering</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>Great men,</line>
            <line>That had a court no bigger than this cave,</line>
            <line>That did attend themselves and had the virtue</line>
            <line>Which their own conscience seal'd them--laying by</line>
            <line>That nothing-gift of differing multitudes--</line>
            <line>Could not out-peer these twain. Pardon me, gods!</line>
            <line>I'd change my sex to be companion with them,</line>
            <line>Since Leonatus's false.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BELARIUS</speaker>
            <line>It shall be so.</line>
            <line>Boys, we'll go dress our hunt. Fair youth, come in:</line>
            <line>Discourse is heavy, fasting; when we have supp'd,</line>
            <line>We'll mannerly demand thee of thy story,</line>
            <line>So far as thou wilt speak it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GUIDERIUS</speaker>
            <line>Pray, draw near.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARVIRAGUS</speaker>
            <line>The night to the owl and morn to the lark</line>
            <line>less welcome.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>Thanks, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARVIRAGUS</speaker>
            <line>I pray, draw near.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-7">
      <title>SCENE VII.  Rome. A public place.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter two Senators and Tribunes</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>This is the tenor of the emperor's writ:</line>
            <line>That since the common men are now in action</line>
            <line>'Gainst the Pannonians and Dalmatians,</line>
            <line>And that the legions now in Gallia are</line>
            <line>Full weak to undertake our wars against</line>
            <line>The fall'n-off Britons, that we do incite</line>
            <line>The gentry to this business. He creates</line>
            <line>Lucius preconsul: and to you the tribunes,</line>
            <line>For this immediate levy, he commends</line>
            <line>His absolute commission. Long live Caesar!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Tribune</speaker>
            <line>Is Lucius general of the forces?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Senator</speaker>
            <line>Ay.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Tribune</speaker>
            <line>Remaining now in Gallia?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>With those legions</line>
            <line>Which I have spoke of, whereunto your levy</line>
            <line>Must be supplyant: the words of your commission</line>
            <line>Will tie you to the numbers and the time</line>
            <line>Of their dispatch.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Tribune</speaker>
            <line>We will discharge our duty.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>