<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net/doctypes/dita/shakespear/dtd/act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-2">
   <title>ACT II</title>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  Britain. Before Cymbeline's palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter CLOTEN and two Lords</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLOTEN</speaker>
            <line>Was there ever man had such luck! when I kissed the</line>
            <line>jack, upon an up-cast to be hit away! I had a</line>
            <line>hundred pound on't: and then a whoreson jackanapes</line>
            <line>must take me up for swearing; as if I borrowed mine</line>
            <line>oaths of him and might not spend them at my pleasure.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>What got he by that? You have broke his pate with</line>
            <line>your bowl.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  If his wit had been like him that broke it,</line>
            <line>it would have run all out.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLOTEN</speaker>
            <line>When a gentleman is disposed to swear, it is not for</line>
            <line>any standers-by to curtail his oaths, ha?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>No my lord;</line>
            <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>
            <line>nor crop the ears of them.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLOTEN</speaker>
            <line>Whoreson dog! I give him satisfaction?</line>
            <line>Would he had been one of my rank!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  To have smelt like a fool.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLOTEN</speaker>
            <line>I am not vexed more at any thing in the earth: a</line>
            <line>pox on't! I had rather not be so noble as I am;</line>
            <line>they dare not fight with me, because of the queen my</line>
            <line>mother: every Jack-slave hath his bellyful of</line>
            <line>fighting, and I must go up and down like a cock that</line>
            <line>nobody can match.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  You are cock and capon too; and you crow,</line>
            <line>cock, with your comb on.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLOTEN</speaker>
            <line>Sayest thou?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>It is not fit your lordship should undertake every</line>
            <line>companion that you give offence to.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLOTEN</speaker>
            <line>No, I know that: but it is fit I should commit</line>
            <line>offence to my inferiors.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>Ay, it is fit for your lordship only.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLOTEN</speaker>
            <line>Why, so I say.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>Did you hear of a stranger that's come to court to-night?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLOTEN</speaker>
            <line>A stranger, and I not know on't!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  He's a strange fellow himself, and knows it</line>
            <line>not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>There's an Italian come; and, 'tis thought, one of</line>
            <line>Leonatus' friends.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLOTEN</speaker>
            <line>Leonatus! a banished rascal; and he's another,</line>
            <line>whatsoever he be. Who told you of this stranger?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>One of your lordship's pages.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLOTEN</speaker>
            <line>Is it fit I went to look upon him? is there no</line>
            <line>derogation in't?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>You cannot derogate, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLOTEN</speaker>
            <line>Not easily, I think.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  You are a fool granted; therefore your</line>
            <line>issues, being foolish, do not derogate.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLOTEN</speaker>
            <line>Come, I'll go see this Italian: what I have lost</line>
            <line>to-day at bowls I'll win to-night of him. Come, go.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>I'll attend your lordship.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt CLOTEN and First Lord</stagedir>
            <line>That such a crafty devil as is his mother</line>
            <line>Should yield the world this ass! a woman that</line>
            <line>Bears all down with her brain; and this her son</line>
            <line>Cannot take two from twenty, for his heart,</line>
            <line>And leave eighteen. Alas, poor princess,</line>
            <line>Thou divine Imogen, what thou endurest,</line>
            <line>Betwixt a father by thy step-dame govern'd,</line>
            <line>A mother hourly coining plots, a wooer</line>
            <line>More hateful than the foul expulsion is</line>
            <line>Of thy dear husband, than that horrid act</line>
            <line>Of the divorce he'ld make! The heavens hold firm</line>
            <line>The walls of thy dear honour, keep unshaked</line>
            <line>That temple, thy fair mind, that thou mayst stand,</line>
            <line>To enjoy thy banish'd lord and this great land!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  Imogen's bedchamber in Cymbeline's palace: a trunk in one corner of it.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>IMOGEN in bed, reading; a Lady attending</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>Who's there? my woman Helen?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lady</speaker>
            <line>Please you, madam</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>What hour is it?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lady</speaker>
            <line>Almost midnight, madam.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>I have read three hours then: mine eyes are weak:</line>
            <line>Fold down the leaf where I have left: to bed:</line>
            <line>Take not away the taper, leave it burning;</line>
            <line>And if thou canst awake by four o' the clock,</line>
            <line>I prithee, call me. Sleep hath seized me wholly</line>
            <stagedir>Exit Lady</stagedir>
            <line>To your protection I commend me, gods.</line>
            <line>From fairies and the tempters of the night</line>
            <line>Guard me, beseech ye.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Sleeps. IACHIMO comes from the trunk</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IACHIMO</speaker>
            <line>The crickets sing, and man's o'er-labour'd sense</line>
            <line>Repairs itself by rest. Our Tarquin thus</line>
            <line>Did softly press the rushes, ere he waken'd</line>
            <line>The chastity he wounded. Cytherea,</line>
            <line>How bravely thou becomest thy bed, fresh lily,</line>
            <line>And whiter than the sheets! That I might touch!</line>
            <line>But kiss; one kiss! Rubies unparagon'd,</line>
            <line>How dearly they do't! 'Tis her breathing that</line>
            <line>Perfumes the chamber thus: the flame o' the taper</line>
            <line>Bows toward her, and would under-peep her lids,</line>
            <line>To see the enclosed lights, now canopied</line>
            <line>Under these windows, white and azure laced</line>
            <line>With blue of heaven's own tinct. But my design,</line>
            <line>To note the chamber: I will write all down:</line>
            <line>Such and such pictures; there the window; such</line>
            <line>The adornment of her bed; the arras; figures,</line>
            <line>Why, such and such; and the contents o' the story.</line>
            <line>Ah, but some natural notes about her body,</line>
            <line>Above ten thousand meaner moveables</line>
            <line>Would testify, to enrich mine inventory.</line>
            <line>O sleep, thou ape of death, lie dull upon her!</line>
            <line>And be her sense but as a monument,</line>
            <line>Thus in a chapel lying! Come off, come off:</line>
            <stagedir>Taking off her bracelet</stagedir>
            <line>As slippery as the Gordian knot was hard!</line>
            <line>'Tis mine; and this will witness outwardly,</line>
            <line>As strongly as the conscience does within,</line>
            <line>To the madding of her lord. On her left breast</line>
            <line>A mole cinque-spotted, like the crimson drops</line>
            <line>I' the bottom of a cowslip: here's a voucher,</line>
            <line>Stronger than ever law could make: this secret</line>
            <line>Will force him think I have pick'd the lock and ta'en</line>
            <line>The treasure of her honour. No more. To what end?</line>
            <line>Why should I write this down, that's riveted,</line>
            <line>Screw'd to my memory? She hath been reading late</line>
            <line>The tale of Tereus; here the leaf's turn'd down</line>
            <line>Where Philomel gave up. I have enough:</line>
            <line>To the trunk again, and shut the spring of it.</line>
            <line>Swift, swift, you dragons of the night, that dawning</line>
            <line>May bare the raven's eye! I lodge in fear;</line>
            <line>Though this a heavenly angel, hell is here.</line>
            <stagedir>Clock strikes</stagedir>
            <line>One, two, three: time, time!</line>
            <stagedir>Goes into the trunk. The scene closes</stagedir>
         </speech>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-3">
      <title>Scene III  An ante-chamber adjoining Imogen's apartments.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter CLOTEN and Lords</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>Your lordship is the most patient man in loss, the</line>
            <line>most coldest that ever turned up ace.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLOTEN</speaker>
            <line>It would make any man cold to lose.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>But not every man patient after the noble temper of</line>
            <line>your lordship. You are most hot and furious when you win.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLOTEN</speaker>
            <line>Winning will put any man into courage. If I could</line>
            <line>get this foolish Imogen, I should have gold enough.</line>
            <line>It's almost morning, is't not?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>Day, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLOTEN</speaker>
            <line>I would this music would come: I am advised to give</line>
            <line>her music o' mornings; they say it will penetrate.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter Musicians</stagedir>
            <line>Come on; tune: if you can penetrate her with your</line>
            <line>fingering, so; we'll try with tongue too: if none</line>
            <line>will do, let her remain; but I'll never give o'er.</line>
            <line>First, a very excellent good-conceited thing;</line>
            <line>after, a wonderful sweet air, with admirable rich</line>
            <line>words to it: and then let her consider.</line>
            <stagedir>SONG</stagedir>
            <line>Hark, hark! the lark at heaven's gate sings,</line>
            <line>And Phoebus 'gins arise,</line>
            <line>His steeds to water at those springs</line>
            <line>On chaliced flowers that lies;</line>
            <line>And winking Mary-buds begin</line>
            <line>To ope their golden eyes:</line>
            <line>With every thing that pretty is,</line>
            <line>My lady sweet, arise:</line>
            <line>Arise, arise.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLOTEN</speaker>
            <line>So, get you gone. If this penetrate, I will</line>
            <line>consider your music the better: if it do not, it is</line>
            <line>a vice in her ears, which horse-hairs and</line>
            <line>calves'-guts, nor the voice of unpaved eunuch to</line>
            <line>boot, can never amend.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt Musicians</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>Here comes the king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLOTEN</speaker>
            <line>I am glad I was up so late; for that's the reason I</line>
            <line>was up so early: he cannot choose but take this</line>
            <line>service I have done fatherly.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter CYMBELINE and QUEEN</stagedir>
            <line>Good morrow to your majesty and to my gracious mother.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>Attend you here the door of our stern daughter?</line>
            <line>Will she not forth?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLOTEN</speaker>
            <line>I have assailed her with music, but she vouchsafes no notice.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>The exile of her minion is too new;</line>
            <line>She hath not yet forgot him: some more time</line>
            <line>Must wear the print of his remembrance out,</line>
            <line>And then she's yours.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN</speaker>
            <line>You are most bound to the king,</line>
            <line>Who lets go by no vantages that may</line>
            <line>Prefer you to his daughter. Frame yourself</line>
            <line>To orderly soliciting, and be friended</line>
            <line>With aptness of the season; make denials</line>
            <line>Increase your services; so seem as if</line>
            <line>You were inspired to do those duties which</line>
            <line>You tender to her; that you in all obey her,</line>
            <line>Save when command to your dismission tends,</line>
            <line>And therein you are senseless.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLOTEN</speaker>
            <line>Senseless! not so.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter a Messenger</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>So like you, sir, ambassadors from Rome;</line>
            <line>The one is Caius Lucius.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CYMBELINE</speaker>
            <line>A worthy fellow,</line>
            <line>Albeit he comes on angry purpose now;</line>
            <line>But that's no fault of his: we must receive him</line>
            <line>According to the honour of his sender;</line>
            <line>And towards himself, his goodness forespent on us,</line>
            <line>We must extend our notice. Our dear son,</line>
            <line>When you have given good morning to your mistress,</line>
            <line>Attend the queen and us; we shall have need</line>
            <line>To employ you towards this Roman. Come, our queen.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt all but CLOTEN</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLOTEN</speaker>
            <line>If she be up, I'll speak with her; if not,</line>
            <line>Let her lie still and dream.</line>
            <stagedir>Knocks</stagedir>
            <line>By your leave, ho!</line>
            <line>I Know her women are about her: what</line>
            <line>If I do line one of their hands? 'Tis gold</line>
            <line>Which buys admittance; oft it doth; yea, and makes</line>
            <line>Diana's rangers false themselves, yield up</line>
            <line>Their deer to the stand o' the stealer; and 'tis gold</line>
            <line>Which makes the true man kill'd and saves the thief;</line>
            <line>Nay, sometime hangs both thief and true man: what</line>
            <line>Can it not do and undo? I will make</line>
            <line>One of her women lawyer to me, for</line>
            <line>I yet not understand the case myself.</line>
            <stagedir>Knocks</stagedir>
            <line>By your leave.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter a Lady</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lady</speaker>
            <line>Who's there that knocks?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLOTEN</speaker>
            <line>A gentleman.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lady</speaker>
            <line>No more?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLOTEN</speaker>
            <line>Yes, and a gentlewoman's son.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lady</speaker>
            <line>That's more</line>
            <line>Than some, whose tailors are as dear as yours,</line>
            <line>Can justly boast of. What's your lordship's pleasure?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLOTEN</speaker>
            <line>Your lady's person: is she ready?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lady</speaker>
            <line>Ay,</line>
            <line>To keep her chamber.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLOTEN</speaker>
            <line>There is gold for you;</line>
            <line>Sell me your good report.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lady</speaker>
            <line>How! my good name? or to report of you</line>
            <line>What I shall think is good?--The princess!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter IMOGEN</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLOTEN</speaker>
            <line>Good morrow, fairest: sister, your sweet hand.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit Lady</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>Good morrow, sir. You lay out too much pains</line>
            <line>For purchasing but trouble; the thanks I give</line>
            <line>Is telling you that I am poor of thanks</line>
            <line>And scarce can spare them.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLOTEN</speaker>
            <line>Still, I swear I love you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>If you but said so, 'twere as deep with me:</line>
            <line>If you swear still, your recompense is still</line>
            <line>That I regard it not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLOTEN</speaker>
            <line>This is no answer.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>But that you shall not say I yield being silent,</line>
            <line>I would not speak. I pray you, spare me: 'faith,</line>
            <line>I shall unfold equal discourtesy</line>
            <line>To your best kindness: one of your great knowing</line>
            <line>Should learn, being taught, forbearance.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLOTEN</speaker>
            <line>To leave you in your madness, 'twere my sin:</line>
            <line>I will not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>Fools are not mad folks.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLOTEN</speaker>
            <line>Do you call me fool?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>As I am mad, I do:</line>
            <line>If you'll be patient, I'll no more be mad;</line>
            <line>That cures us both. I am much sorry, sir,</line>
            <line>You put me to forget a lady's manners,</line>
            <line>By being so verbal: and learn now, for all,</line>
            <line>That I, which know my heart, do here pronounce,</line>
            <line>By the very truth of it, I care not for you,</line>
            <line>And am so near the lack of charity--</line>
            <line>To accuse myself--I hate you; which I had rather</line>
            <line>You felt than make't my boast.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLOTEN</speaker>
            <line>You sin against</line>
            <line>Obedience, which you owe your father. For</line>
            <line>The contract you pretend with that base wretch,</line>
            <line>One bred of alms and foster'd with cold dishes,</line>
            <line>With scraps o' the court, it is no contract, none:</line>
            <line>And though it be allow'd in meaner parties--</line>
            <line>Yet who than he more mean?--to knit their souls,</line>
            <line>On whom there is no more dependency</line>
            <line>But brats and beggary, in self-figured knot;</line>
            <line>Yet you are curb'd from that enlargement by</line>
            <line>The consequence o' the crown, and must not soil</line>
            <line>The precious note of it with a base slave.</line>
            <line>A hilding for a livery, a squire's cloth,</line>
            <line>A pantler, not so eminent.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>Profane fellow</line>
            <line>Wert thou the son of Jupiter and no more</line>
            <line>But what thou art besides, thou wert too base</line>
            <line>To be his groom: thou wert dignified enough,</line>
            <line>Even to the point of envy, if 'twere made</line>
            <line>Comparative for your virtues, to be styled</line>
            <line>The under-hangman of his kingdom, and hated</line>
            <line>For being preferred so well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLOTEN</speaker>
            <line>The south-fog rot him!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>He never can meet more mischance than come</line>
            <line>To be but named of thee. His meanest garment,</line>
            <line>That ever hath but clipp'd his body, is dearer</line>
            <line>In my respect than all the hairs above thee,</line>
            <line>Were they all made such men. How now, Pisanio!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter PISANIO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLOTEN</speaker>
            <line>'His garment!' Now the devil--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>To Dorothy my woman hie thee presently--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLOTEN</speaker>
            <line>'His garment!'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>I am sprited with a fool.</line>
            <line>Frighted, and anger'd worse: go bid my woman</line>
            <line>Search for a jewel that too casually</line>
            <line>Hath left mine arm: it was thy master's: 'shrew me,</line>
            <line>If I would lose it for a revenue</line>
            <line>Of any king's in Europe. I do think</line>
            <line>I saw't this morning: confident I am</line>
            <line>Last night 'twas on mine arm; I kiss'd it:</line>
            <line>I hope it be not gone to tell my lord</line>
            <line>That I kiss aught but he.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PISANIO</speaker>
            <line>'Twill not be lost.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>I hope so: go and search.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit PISANIO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLOTEN</speaker>
            <line>You have abused me:</line>
            <line>'His meanest garment!'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>Ay, I said so, sir:</line>
            <line>If you will make't an action, call witness to't.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLOTEN</speaker>
            <line>I will inform your father.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IMOGEN</speaker>
            <line>Your mother too:</line>
            <line>She's my good lady, and will conceive, I hope,</line>
            <line>But the worst of me. So, I leave you, sir,</line>
            <line>To the worst of discontent.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLOTEN</speaker>
            <line>I'll be revenged:</line>
            <line>'His meanest garment!' Well.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-4">
      <title>SCENE IV.  Rome. Philario's house.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter POSTHUMUS and PHILARIO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POSTHUMUS LEONATUS</speaker>
            <line>Fear it not, sir: I would I were so sure</line>
            <line>To win the king as I am bold her honour</line>
            <line>Will remain hers.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PHILARIO</speaker>
            <line>What means do you make to him?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POSTHUMUS LEONATUS</speaker>
            <line>Not any, but abide the change of time,</line>
            <line>Quake in the present winter's state and wish</line>
            <line>That warmer days would come: in these sear'd hopes,</line>
            <line>I barely gratify your love; they failing,</line>
            <line>I must die much your debtor.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PHILARIO</speaker>
            <line>Your very goodness and your company</line>
            <line>O'erpays all I can do. By this, your king</line>
            <line>Hath heard of great Augustus: Caius Lucius</line>
            <line>Will do's commission throughly: and I think</line>
            <line>He'll grant the tribute, send the arrearages,</line>
            <line>Or look upon our Romans, whose remembrance</line>
            <line>Is yet fresh in their grief.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POSTHUMUS LEONATUS</speaker>
            <line>I do believe,</line>
            <line>Statist though I am none, nor like to be,</line>
            <line>That this will prove a war; and you shall hear</line>
            <line>The legions now in Gallia sooner landed</line>
            <line>In our not-fearing Britain than have tidings</line>
            <line>Of any penny tribute paid. Our countrymen</line>
            <line>Are men more order'd than when Julius Caesar</line>
            <line>Smiled at their lack of skill, but found</line>
            <line>their courage</line>
            <line>Worthy his frowning at: their discipline,</line>
            <line>Now mingled with their courages, will make known</line>
            <line>To their approvers they are people such</line>
            <line>That mend upon the world.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter IACHIMO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PHILARIO</speaker>
            <line>See! Iachimo!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POSTHUMUS LEONATUS</speaker>
            <line>The swiftest harts have posted you by land;</line>
            <line>And winds of all the comers kiss'd your sails,</line>
            <line>To make your vessel nimble.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PHILARIO</speaker>
            <line>Welcome, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POSTHUMUS LEONATUS</speaker>
            <line>I hope the briefness of your answer made</line>
            <line>The speediness of your return.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IACHIMO</speaker>
            <line>Your lady</line>
            <line>Is one of the fairest that I have look'd upon.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POSTHUMUS LEONATUS</speaker>
            <line>And therewithal the best; or let her beauty</line>
            <line>Look through a casement to allure false hearts</line>
            <line>And be false with them.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IACHIMO</speaker>
            <line>Here are letters for you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POSTHUMUS LEONATUS</speaker>
            <line>Their tenor good, I trust.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IACHIMO</speaker>
            <line>'Tis very like.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PHILARIO</speaker>
            <line>Was Caius Lucius in the Britain court</line>
            <line>When you were there?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IACHIMO</speaker>
            <line>He was expected then,</line>
            <line>But not approach'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POSTHUMUS LEONATUS</speaker>
            <line>All is well yet.</line>
            <line>Sparkles this stone as it was wont? or is't not</line>
            <line>Too dull for your good wearing?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IACHIMO</speaker>
            <line>If I had lost it,</line>
            <line>I should have lost the worth of it in gold.</line>
            <line>I'll make a journey twice as far, to enjoy</line>
            <line>A second night of such sweet shortness which</line>
            <line>Was mine in Britain, for the ring is won.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POSTHUMUS LEONATUS</speaker>
            <line>The stone's too hard to come by.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IACHIMO</speaker>
            <line>Not a whit,</line>
            <line>Your lady being so easy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POSTHUMUS LEONATUS</speaker>
            <line>Make not, sir,</line>
            <line>Your loss your sport: I hope you know that we</line>
            <line>Must not continue friends.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IACHIMO</speaker>
            <line>Good sir, we must,</line>
            <line>If you keep covenant. Had I not brought</line>
            <line>The knowledge of your mistress home, I grant</line>
            <line>We were to question further: but I now</line>
            <line>Profess myself the winner of her honour,</line>
            <line>Together with your ring; and not the wronger</line>
            <line>Of her or you, having proceeded but</line>
            <line>By both your wills.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POSTHUMUS LEONATUS</speaker>
            <line>If you can make't apparent</line>
            <line>That you have tasted her in bed, my hand</line>
            <line>And ring is yours; if not, the foul opinion</line>
            <line>You had of her pure honour gains or loses</line>
            <line>Your sword or mine, or masterless leaves both</line>
            <line>To who shall find them.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IACHIMO</speaker>
            <line>Sir, my circumstances,</line>
            <line>Being so near the truth as I will make them,</line>
            <line>Must first induce you to believe: whose strength</line>
            <line>I will confirm with oath; which, I doubt not,</line>
            <line>You'll give me leave to spare, when you shall find</line>
            <line>You need it not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POSTHUMUS LEONATUS</speaker>
            <line>Proceed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IACHIMO</speaker>
            <line>First, her bedchamber,--</line>
            <line>Where, I confess, I slept not, but profess</line>
            <line>Had that was well worth watching--it was hang'd</line>
            <line>With tapesty of silk and silver; the story</line>
            <line>Proud Cleopatra, when she met her Roman,</line>
            <line>And Cydnus swell'd above the banks, or for</line>
            <line>The press of boats or pride: a piece of work</line>
            <line>So bravely done, so rich, that it did strive</line>
            <line>In workmanship and value; which I wonder'd</line>
            <line>Could be so rarely and exactly wrought,</line>
            <line>Since the true life on't was--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POSTHUMUS LEONATUS</speaker>
            <line>This is true;</line>
            <line>And this you might have heard of here, by me,</line>
            <line>Or by some other.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IACHIMO</speaker>
            <line>More particulars</line>
            <line>Must justify my knowledge.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POSTHUMUS LEONATUS</speaker>
            <line>So they must,</line>
            <line>Or do your honour injury.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IACHIMO</speaker>
            <line>The chimney</line>
            <line>Is south the chamber, and the chimney-piece</line>
            <line>Chaste Dian bathing: never saw I figures</line>
            <line>So likely to report themselves: the cutter</line>
            <line>Was as another nature, dumb; outwent her,</line>
            <line>Motion and breath left out.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POSTHUMUS LEONATUS</speaker>
            <line>This is a thing</line>
            <line>Which you might from relation likewise reap,</line>
            <line>Being, as it is, much spoke of.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IACHIMO</speaker>
            <line>The roof o' the chamber</line>
            <line>With golden cherubins is fretted: her andirons--</line>
            <line>I had forgot them--were two winking Cupids</line>
            <line>Of silver, each on one foot standing, nicely</line>
            <line>Depending on their brands.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POSTHUMUS LEONATUS</speaker>
            <line>This is her honour!</line>
            <line>Let it be granted you have seen all this--and praise</line>
            <line>Be given to your remembrance--the description</line>
            <line>Of what is in her chamber nothing saves</line>
            <line>The wager you have laid.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IACHIMO</speaker>
            <line>Then, if you can,</line>
            <stagedir>Showing the bracelet</stagedir>
            <line>Be pale: I beg but leave to air this jewel; see!</line>
            <line>And now 'tis up again: it must be married</line>
            <line>To that your diamond; I'll keep them.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POSTHUMUS LEONATUS</speaker>
            <line>Jove!</line>
            <line>Once more let me behold it: is it that</line>
            <line>Which I left with her?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IACHIMO</speaker>
            <line>Sir--I thank her--that:</line>
            <line>She stripp'd it from her arm; I see her yet;</line>
            <line>Her pretty action did outsell her gift,</line>
            <line>And yet enrich'd it too: she gave it me, and said</line>
            <line>She prized it once.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POSTHUMUS LEONATUS</speaker>
            <line>May be she pluck'd it off</line>
            <line>To send it me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IACHIMO</speaker>
            <line>She writes so to you, doth she?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POSTHUMUS LEONATUS</speaker>
            <line>O, no, no, no! 'tis true. Here, take this too;</line>
            <stagedir>Gives the ring</stagedir>
            <line>It is a basilisk unto mine eye,</line>
            <line>Kills me to look on't. Let there be no honour</line>
            <line>Where there is beauty; truth, where semblance; love,</line>
            <line>Where there's another man: the vows of women</line>
            <line>Of no more bondage be, to where they are made,</line>
            <line>Than they are to their virtues; which is nothing.</line>
            <line>O, above measure false!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PHILARIO</speaker>
            <line>Have patience, sir,</line>
            <line>And take your ring again; 'tis not yet won:</line>
            <line>It may be probable she lost it; or</line>
            <line>Who knows if one of her women, being corrupted,</line>
            <line>Hath stol'n it from her?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POSTHUMUS LEONATUS</speaker>
            <line>Very true;</line>
            <line>And so, I hope, he came by't. Back my ring:</line>
            <line>Render to me some corporal sign about her,</line>
            <line>More evident than this; for this was stolen.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IACHIMO</speaker>
            <line>By Jupiter, I had it from her arm.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POSTHUMUS LEONATUS</speaker>
            <line>Hark you, he swears; by Jupiter he swears.</line>
            <line>'Tis true:--nay, keep the ring--'tis true: I am sure</line>
            <line>She would not lose it: her attendants are</line>
            <line>All sworn and honourable:--they induced to steal it!</line>
            <line>And by a stranger!--No, he hath enjoyed her:</line>
            <line>The cognizance of her incontinency</line>
            <line>Is this: she hath bought the name of whore</line>
            <line>thus dearly.</line>
            <line>There, take thy hire; and all the fiends of hell</line>
            <line>Divide themselves between you!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PHILARIO</speaker>
            <line>Sir, be patient:</line>
            <line>This is not strong enough to be believed</line>
            <line>Of one persuaded well of--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POSTHUMUS LEONATUS</speaker>
            <line>Never talk on't;</line>
            <line>She hath been colted by him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IACHIMO</speaker>
            <line>If you seek</line>
            <line>For further satisfying, under her breast--</line>
            <line>Worthy the pressing--lies a mole, right proud</line>
            <line>Of that most delicate lodging: by my life,</line>
            <line>I kiss'd it; and it gave me present hunger</line>
            <line>To feed again, though full. You do remember</line>
            <line>This stain upon her?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POSTHUMUS LEONATUS</speaker>
            <line>Ay, and it doth confirm</line>
            <line>Another stain, as big as hell can hold,</line>
            <line>Were there no more but it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IACHIMO</speaker>
            <line>Will you hear more?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POSTHUMUS LEONATUS</speaker>
            <line>Spare your arithmetic: never count the turns;</line>
            <line>Once, and a million!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IACHIMO</speaker>
            <line>I'll be sworn--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POSTHUMUS LEONATUS</speaker>
            <line>No swearing.</line>
            <line>If you will swear you have not done't, you lie;</line>
            <line>And I will kill thee, if thou dost deny</line>
            <line>Thou'st made me cuckold.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IACHIMO</speaker>
            <line>I'll deny nothing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POSTHUMUS LEONATUS</speaker>
            <line>O, that I had her here, to tear her limb-meal!</line>
            <line>I will go there and do't, i' the court, before</line>
            <line>Her father. I'll do something--</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PHILARIO</speaker>
            <line>Quite besides</line>
            <line>The government of patience! You have won:</line>
            <line>Let's follow him, and pervert the present wrath</line>
            <line>He hath against himself.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IACHIMO</speaker>
            <line>With an my heart.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-5">
      <title>SCENE V.  Another room in Philario's house.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter POSTHUMUS LEONATUS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POSTHUMUS LEONATUS</speaker>
            <line>Is there no way for men to be but women</line>
            <line>Must be half-workers? We are all bastards;</line>
            <line>And that most venerable man which I</line>
            <line>Did call my father, was I know not where</line>
            <line>When I was stamp'd; some coiner with his tools</line>
            <line>Made me a counterfeit: yet my mother seem'd</line>
            <line>The Dian of that time so doth my wife</line>
            <line>The nonpareil of this. O, vengeance, vengeance!</line>
            <line>Me of my lawful pleasure she restrain'd</line>
            <line>And pray'd me oft forbearance; did it with</line>
            <line>A pudency so rosy the sweet view on't</line>
            <line>Might well have warm'd old Saturn; that I thought her</line>
            <line>As chaste as unsunn'd snow. O, all the devils!</line>
            <line>This yellow Iachimo, in an hour,--wast not?--</line>
            <line>Or less,--at first?--perchance he spoke not, but,</line>
            <line>Like a full-acorn'd boar, a German one,</line>
            <line>Cried 'O!' and mounted; found no opposition</line>
            <line>But what he look'd for should oppose and she</line>
            <line>Should from encounter guard. Could I find out</line>
            <line>The woman's part in me! For there's no motion</line>
            <line>That tends to vice in man, but I affirm</line>
            <line>It is the woman's part: be it lying, note it,</line>
            <line>The woman's; flattering, hers; deceiving, hers;</line>
            <line>Lust and rank thoughts, hers, hers; revenges, hers;</line>
            <line>Ambitions, covetings, change of prides, disdain,</line>
            <line>Nice longing, slanders, mutability,</line>
            <line>All faults that may be named, nay, that hell knows,</line>
            <line>Why, hers, in part or all; but rather, all;</line>
            <line>For even to vice</line>
            <line>They are not constant but are changing still</line>
            <line>One vice, but of a minute old, for one</line>
            <line>Not half so old as that. I'll write against them,</line>
            <line>Detest them, curse them: yet 'tis greater skill</line>
            <line>In a true hate, to pray they have their will:</line>
            <line>The very devils cannot plague them better.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>