<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:shakespear:dtd:act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-1">
   <title>ACT I</title>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  Venice. A street.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter RODERIGO and IAGO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RODERIGO</speaker>
            <line>Tush! never tell me; I take it much unkindly</line>
            <line>That thou, Iago, who hast had my purse</line>
            <line>As if the strings were thine, shouldst know of this.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IAGO</speaker>
            <line>'Sblood, but you will not hear me:</line>
            <line>If ever I did dream of such a matter, Abhor me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RODERIGO</speaker>
            <line>Thou told'st me thou didst hold him in thy hate.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IAGO</speaker>
            <line>Despise me, if I do not. Three great ones of the city,</line>
            <line>In personal suit to make me his lieutenant,</line>
            <line>Off-capp'd to him: and, by the faith of man,</line>
            <line>I know my price, I am worth no worse a place:</line>
            <line>But he; as loving his own pride and purposes,</line>
            <line>Evades them, with a bombast circumstance</line>
            <line>Horribly stuff'd with epithets of war;</line>
            <line>And, in conclusion,</line>
            <line>Nonsuits my mediators; for, 'Certes,' says he,</line>
            <line>'I have already chose my officer.'</line>
            <line>And what was he?</line>
            <line>Forsooth, a great arithmetician,</line>
            <line>One Michael Cassio, a Florentine,</line>
            <line>A fellow almost damn'd in a fair wife;</line>
            <line>That never set a squadron in the field,</line>
            <line>Nor the division of a battle knows</line>
            <line>More than a spinster; unless the bookish theoric,</line>
            <line>Wherein the toged consuls can propose</line>
            <line>As masterly as he: mere prattle, without practise,</line>
            <line>Is all his soldiership. But he, sir, had the election:</line>
            <line>And I, of whom his eyes had seen the proof</line>
            <line>At Rhodes, at Cyprus and on other grounds</line>
            <line>Christian and heathen, must be be-lee'd and calm'd</line>
            <line>By debitor and creditor: this counter-caster,</line>
            <line>He, in good time, must his lieutenant be,</line>
            <line>And I--God bless the mark!--his Moorship's ancient.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RODERIGO</speaker>
            <line>By heaven, I rather would have been his hangman.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IAGO</speaker>
            <line>Why, there's no remedy; 'tis the curse of service,</line>
            <line>Preferment goes by letter and affection,</line>
            <line>And not by old gradation, where each second</line>
            <line>Stood heir to the first. Now, sir, be judge yourself,</line>
            <line>Whether I in any just term am affined</line>
            <line>To love the Moor.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RODERIGO</speaker>
            <line>I would not follow him then.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IAGO</speaker>
            <line>O, sir, content you;</line>
            <line>I follow him to serve my turn upon him:</line>
            <line>We cannot all be masters, nor all masters</line>
            <line>Cannot be truly follow'd. You shall mark</line>
            <line>Many a duteous and knee-crooking knave,</line>
            <line>That, doting on his own obsequious bondage,</line>
            <line>Wears out his time, much like his master's ass,</line>
            <line>For nought but provender, and when he's old, cashier'd:</line>
            <line>Whip me such honest knaves. Others there are</line>
            <line>Who, trimm'd in forms and visages of duty,</line>
            <line>Keep yet their hearts attending on themselves,</line>
            <line>And, throwing but shows of service on their lords,</line>
            <line>Do well thrive by them and when they have lined</line>
            <line>their coats</line>
            <line>Do themselves homage: these fellows have some soul;</line>
            <line>And such a one do I profess myself. For, sir,</line>
            <line>It is as sure as you are Roderigo,</line>
            <line>Were I the Moor, I would not be Iago:</line>
            <line>In following him, I follow but myself;</line>
            <line>Heaven is my judge, not I for love and duty,</line>
            <line>But seeming so, for my peculiar end:</line>
            <line>For when my outward action doth demonstrate</line>
            <line>The native act and figure of my heart</line>
            <line>In compliment extern, 'tis not long after</line>
            <line>But I will wear my heart upon my sleeve</line>
            <line>For daws to peck at: I am not what I am.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RODERIGO</speaker>
            <line>What a full fortune does the thicklips owe</line>
            <line>If he can carry't thus!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IAGO</speaker>
            <line>Call up her father,</line>
            <line>Rouse him: make after him, poison his delight,</line>
            <line>Proclaim him in the streets; incense her kinsmen,</line>
            <line>And, though he in a fertile climate dwell,</line>
            <line>Plague him with flies: though that his joy be joy,</line>
            <line>Yet throw such changes of vexation on't,</line>
            <line>As it may lose some colour.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RODERIGO</speaker>
            <line>Here is her father's house; I'll call aloud.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IAGO</speaker>
            <line>Do, with like timorous accent and dire yell</line>
            <line>As when, by night and negligence, the fire</line>
            <line>Is spied in populous cities.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RODERIGO</speaker>
            <line>What, ho, Brabantio! Signior Brabantio, ho!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IAGO</speaker>
            <line>Awake! what, ho, Brabantio! thieves! thieves! thieves!</line>
            <line>Look to your house, your daughter and your bags!</line>
            <line>Thieves! thieves!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>BRABANTIO appears above, at a window</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRABANTIO</speaker>
            <line>What is the reason of this terrible summons?</line>
            <line>What is the matter there?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RODERIGO</speaker>
            <line>Signior, is all your family within?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IAGO</speaker>
            <line>Are your doors lock'd?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRABANTIO</speaker>
            <line>Why, wherefore ask you this?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IAGO</speaker>
            <line>'Zounds, sir, you're robb'd; for shame, put on</line>
            <line>your gown;</line>
            <line>Your heart is burst, you have lost half your soul;</line>
            <line>Even now, now, very now, an old black ram</line>
            <line>Is topping your white ewe. Arise, arise;</line>
            <line>Awake the snorting citizens with the bell,</line>
            <line>Or else the devil will make a grandsire of you:</line>
            <line>Arise, I say.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRABANTIO</speaker>
            <line>What, have you lost your wits?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RODERIGO</speaker>
            <line>Most reverend signior, do you know my voice?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRABANTIO</speaker>
            <line>Not I what are you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RODERIGO</speaker>
            <line>My name is Roderigo.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRABANTIO</speaker>
            <line>The worser welcome:</line>
            <line>I have charged thee not to haunt about my doors:</line>
            <line>In honest plainness thou hast heard me say</line>
            <line>My daughter is not for thee; and now, in madness,</line>
            <line>Being full of supper and distempering draughts,</line>
            <line>Upon malicious bravery, dost thou come</line>
            <line>To start my quiet.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RODERIGO</speaker>
            <line>Sir, sir, sir,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRABANTIO</speaker>
            <line>But thou must needs be sure</line>
            <line>My spirit and my place have in them power</line>
            <line>To make this bitter to thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RODERIGO</speaker>
            <line>Patience, good sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRABANTIO</speaker>
            <line>What tell'st thou me of robbing? this is Venice;</line>
            <line>My house is not a grange.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RODERIGO</speaker>
            <line>Most grave Brabantio,</line>
            <line>In simple and pure soul I come to you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IAGO</speaker>
            <line>'Zounds, sir, you are one of those that will not</line>
            <line>serve God, if the devil bid you. Because we come to</line>
            <line>do you service and you think we are ruffians, you'll</line>
            <line>have your daughter covered with a Barbary horse;</line>
            <line>you'll have your nephews neigh to you; you'll have</line>
            <line>coursers for cousins and gennets for germans.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRABANTIO</speaker>
            <line>What profane wretch art thou?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IAGO</speaker>
            <line>I am one, sir, that comes to tell you your daughter</line>
            <line>and the Moor are now making the beast with two backs.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRABANTIO</speaker>
            <line>Thou art a villain.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IAGO</speaker>
            <line>You are--a senator.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRABANTIO</speaker>
            <line>This thou shalt answer; I know thee, Roderigo.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RODERIGO</speaker>
            <line>Sir, I will answer any thing. But, I beseech you,</line>
            <line>If't be your pleasure and most wise consent,</line>
            <line>As partly I find it is, that your fair daughter,</line>
            <line>At this odd-even and dull watch o' the night,</line>
            <line>Transported, with no worse nor better guard</line>
            <line>But with a knave of common hire, a gondolier,</line>
            <line>To the gross clasps of a lascivious Moor--</line>
            <line>If this be known to you and your allowance,</line>
            <line>We then have done you bold and saucy wrongs;</line>
            <line>But if you know not this, my manners tell me</line>
            <line>We have your wrong rebuke. Do not believe</line>
            <line>That, from the sense of all civility,</line>
            <line>I thus would play and trifle with your reverence:</line>
            <line>Your daughter, if you have not given her leave,</line>
            <line>I say again, hath made a gross revolt;</line>
            <line>Tying her duty, beauty, wit and fortunes</line>
            <line>In an extravagant and wheeling stranger</line>
            <line>Of here and every where. Straight satisfy yourself:</line>
            <line>If she be in her chamber or your house,</line>
            <line>Let loose on me the justice of the state</line>
            <line>For thus deluding you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRABANTIO</speaker>
            <line>Strike on the tinder, ho!</line>
            <line>Give me a taper! call up all my people!</line>
            <line>This accident is not unlike my dream:</line>
            <line>Belief of it oppresses me already.</line>
            <line>Light, I say! light!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit above</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IAGO</speaker>
            <line>Farewell; for I must leave you:</line>
            <line>It seems not meet, nor wholesome to my place,</line>
            <line>To be produced--as, if I stay, I shall--</line>
            <line>Against the Moor: for, I do know, the state,</line>
            <line>However this may gall him with some cheque,</line>
            <line>Cannot with safety cast him, for he's embark'd</line>
            <line>With such loud reason to the Cyprus wars,</line>
            <line>Which even now stand in act, that, for their souls,</line>
            <line>Another of his fathom they have none,</line>
            <line>To lead their business: in which regard,</line>
            <line>Though I do hate him as I do hell-pains.</line>
            <line>Yet, for necessity of present life,</line>
            <line>I must show out a flag and sign of love,</line>
            <line>Which is indeed but sign. That you shall surely find him,</line>
            <line>Lead to the Sagittary the raised search;</line>
            <line>And there will I be with him. So, farewell.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Enter, below, BRABANTIO, and Servants with torches</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRABANTIO</speaker>
            <line>It is too true an evil: gone she is;</line>
            <line>And what's to come of my despised time</line>
            <line>Is nought but bitterness. Now, Roderigo,</line>
            <line>Where didst thou see her? O unhappy girl!</line>
            <line>With the Moor, say'st thou? Who would be a father!</line>
            <line>How didst thou know 'twas she? O she deceives me</line>
            <line>Past thought! What said she to you? Get more tapers:</line>
            <line>Raise all my kindred. Are they married, think you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RODERIGO</speaker>
            <line>Truly, I think they are.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRABANTIO</speaker>
            <line>O heaven! How got she out? O treason of the blood!</line>
            <line>Fathers, from hence trust not your daughters' minds</line>
            <line>By what you see them act. Is there not charms</line>
            <line>By which the property of youth and maidhood</line>
            <line>May be abused? Have you not read, Roderigo,</line>
            <line>Of some such thing?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RODERIGO</speaker>
            <line>Yes, sir, I have indeed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRABANTIO</speaker>
            <line>Call up my brother. O, would you had had her!</line>
            <line>Some one way, some another. Do you know</line>
            <line>Where we may apprehend her and the Moor?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RODERIGO</speaker>
            <line>I think I can discover him, if you please,</line>
            <line>To get good guard and go along with me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRABANTIO</speaker>
            <line>Pray you, lead on. At every house I'll call;</line>
            <line>I may command at most. Get weapons, ho!</line>
            <line>And raise some special officers of night.</line>
            <line>On, good Roderigo: I'll deserve your pains.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  Another street.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter OTHELLO, IAGO, and Attendants with torches</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IAGO</speaker>
            <line>Though in the trade of war I have slain men,</line>
            <line>Yet do I hold it very stuff o' the conscience</line>
            <line>To do no contrived murder: I lack iniquity</line>
            <line>Sometimes to do me service: nine or ten times</line>
            <line>I had thought to have yerk'd him here under the ribs.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OTHELLO</speaker>
            <line>'Tis better as it is.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IAGO</speaker>
            <line>Nay, but he prated,</line>
            <line>And spoke such scurvy and provoking terms</line>
            <line>Against your honour</line>
            <line>That, with the little godliness I have,</line>
            <line>I did full hard forbear him. But, I pray you, sir,</line>
            <line>Are you fast married? Be assured of this,</line>
            <line>That the magnifico is much beloved,</line>
            <line>And hath in his effect a voice potential</line>
            <line>As double as the duke's: he will divorce you;</line>
            <line>Or put upon you what restraint and grievance</line>
            <line>The law, with all his might to enforce it on,</line>
            <line>Will give him cable.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OTHELLO</speaker>
            <line>Let him do his spite:</line>
            <line>My services which I have done the signiory</line>
            <line>Shall out-tongue his complaints. 'Tis yet to know,--</line>
            <line>Which, when I know that boasting is an honour,</line>
            <line>I shall promulgate--I fetch my life and being</line>
            <line>From men of royal siege, and my demerits</line>
            <line>May speak unbonneted to as proud a fortune</line>
            <line>As this that I have reach'd: for know, Iago,</line>
            <line>But that I love the gentle Desdemona,</line>
            <line>I would not my unhoused free condition</line>
            <line>Put into circumscription and confine</line>
            <line>For the sea's worth. But, look! what lights come yond?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IAGO</speaker>
            <line>Those are the raised father and his friends:</line>
            <line>You were best go in.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OTHELLO</speaker>
            <line>Not I I must be found:</line>
            <line>My parts, my title and my perfect soul</line>
            <line>Shall manifest me rightly. Is it they?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IAGO</speaker>
            <line>By Janus, I think no.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter CASSIO, and certain Officers with torches</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OTHELLO</speaker>
            <line>The servants of the duke, and my lieutenant.</line>
            <line>The goodness of the night upon you, friends!</line>
            <line>What is the news?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIO</speaker>
            <line>The duke does greet you, general,</line>
            <line>And he requires your haste-post-haste appearance,</line>
            <line>Even on the instant.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OTHELLO</speaker>
            <line>What is the matter, think you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIO</speaker>
            <line>Something from Cyprus as I may divine:</line>
            <line>It is a business of some heat: the galleys</line>
            <line>Have sent a dozen sequent messengers</line>
            <line>This very night at one another's heels,</line>
            <line>And many of the consuls, raised and met,</line>
            <line>Are at the duke's already: you have been</line>
            <line>hotly call'd for;</line>
            <line>When, being not at your lodging to be found,</line>
            <line>The senate hath sent about three several guests</line>
            <line>To search you out.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OTHELLO</speaker>
            <line>'Tis well I am found by you.</line>
            <line>I will but spend a word here in the house,</line>
            <line>And go with you.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIO</speaker>
            <line>Ancient, what makes he here?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IAGO</speaker>
            <line>'Faith, he to-night hath boarded a land carack:</line>
            <line>If it prove lawful prize, he's made for ever.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIO</speaker>
            <line>I do not understand.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IAGO</speaker>
            <line>He's married.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIO</speaker>
            <line>To who?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter OTHELLO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IAGO</speaker>
            <line>Marry, to--Come, captain, will you go?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OTHELLO</speaker>
            <line>Have with you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CASSIO</speaker>
            <line>Here comes another troop to seek for you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IAGO</speaker>
            <line>It is Brabantio. General, be advised;</line>
            <line>He comes to bad intent.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter BRABANTIO, RODERIGO, and Officers with
torches and weapons</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OTHELLO</speaker>
            <line>Holla! stand there!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RODERIGO</speaker>
            <line>Signior, it is the Moor.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRABANTIO</speaker>
            <line>Down with him, thief!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>They draw on both sides</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IAGO</speaker>
            <line>You, Roderigo! come, sir, I am for you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OTHELLO</speaker>
            <line>Keep up your bright swords, for the dew will rust them.</line>
            <line>Good signior, you shall more command with years</line>
            <line>Than with your weapons.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRABANTIO</speaker>
            <line>O thou foul thief, where hast thou stow'd my daughter?</line>
            <line>Damn'd as thou art, thou hast enchanted her;</line>
            <line>For I'll refer me to all things of sense,</line>
            <line>If she in chains of magic were not bound,</line>
            <line>Whether a maid so tender, fair and happy,</line>
            <line>So opposite to marriage that she shunned</line>
            <line>The wealthy curled darlings of our nation,</line>
            <line>Would ever have, to incur a general mock,</line>
            <line>Run from her guardage to the sooty bosom</line>
            <line>Of such a thing as thou, to fear, not to delight.</line>
            <line>Judge me the world, if 'tis not gross in sense</line>
            <line>That thou hast practised on her with foul charms,</line>
            <line>Abused her delicate youth with drugs or minerals</line>
            <line>That weaken motion: I'll have't disputed on;</line>
            <line>'Tis probable and palpable to thinking.</line>
            <line>I therefore apprehend and do attach thee</line>
            <line>For an abuser of the world, a practiser</line>
            <line>Of arts inhibited and out of warrant.</line>
            <line>Lay hold upon him: if he do resist,</line>
            <line>Subdue him at his peril.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OTHELLO</speaker>
            <line>Hold your hands,</line>
            <line>Both you of my inclining, and the rest:</line>
            <line>Were it my cue to fight, I should have known it</line>
            <line>Without a prompter. Where will you that I go</line>
            <line>To answer this your charge?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRABANTIO</speaker>
            <line>To prison, till fit time</line>
            <line>Of law and course of direct session</line>
            <line>Call thee to answer.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OTHELLO</speaker>
            <line>What if I do obey?</line>
            <line>How may the duke be therewith satisfied,</line>
            <line>Whose messengers are here about my side,</line>
            <line>Upon some present business of the state</line>
            <line>To bring me to him?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Officer</speaker>
            <line>'Tis true, most worthy signior;</line>
            <line>The duke's in council and your noble self,</line>
            <line>I am sure, is sent for.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRABANTIO</speaker>
            <line>How! the duke in council!</line>
            <line>In this time of the night! Bring him away:</line>
            <line>Mine's not an idle cause: the duke himself,</line>
            <line>Or any of my brothers of the state,</line>
            <line>Cannot but feel this wrong as 'twere their own;</line>
            <line>For if such actions may have passage free,</line>
            <line>Bond-slaves and pagans shall our statesmen be.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  A council-chamber.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>The DUKE and Senators sitting at a table; Officers
attending</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF VENICE</speaker>
            <line>There is no composition in these news</line>
            <line>That gives them credit.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>Indeed, they are disproportion'd;</line>
            <line>My letters say a hundred and seven galleys.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF VENICE</speaker>
            <line>And mine, a hundred and forty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Senator</speaker>
            <line>And mine, two hundred:</line>
            <line>But though they jump not on a just account,--</line>
            <line>As in these cases, where the aim reports,</line>
            <line>'Tis oft with difference--yet do they all confirm</line>
            <line>A Turkish fleet, and bearing up to Cyprus.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF VENICE</speaker>
            <line>Nay, it is possible enough to judgment:</line>
            <line>I do not so secure me in the error,</line>
            <line>But the main article I do approve</line>
            <line>In fearful sense.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Sailor</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Within</stagedir>  What, ho! what, ho! what, ho!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Officer</speaker>
            <line>A messenger from the galleys.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter a Sailor</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF VENICE</speaker>
            <line>Now, what's the business?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Sailor</speaker>
            <line>The Turkish preparation makes for Rhodes;</line>
            <line>So was I bid report here to the state</line>
            <line>By Signior Angelo.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF VENICE</speaker>
            <line>How say you by this change?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>This cannot be,</line>
            <line>By no assay of reason: 'tis a pageant,</line>
            <line>To keep us in false gaze. When we consider</line>
            <line>The importancy of Cyprus to the Turk,</line>
            <line>And let ourselves again but understand,</line>
            <line>That as it more concerns the Turk than Rhodes,</line>
            <line>So may he with more facile question bear it,</line>
            <line>For that it stands not in such warlike brace,</line>
            <line>But altogether lacks the abilities</line>
            <line>That Rhodes is dress'd in: if we make thought of this,</line>
            <line>We must not think the Turk is so unskilful</line>
            <line>To leave that latest which concerns him first,</line>
            <line>Neglecting an attempt of ease and gain,</line>
            <line>To wake and wage a danger profitless.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF VENICE</speaker>
            <line>Nay, in all confidence, he's not for Rhodes.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Officer</speaker>
            <line>Here is more news.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter a Messenger</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>The Ottomites, reverend and gracious,</line>
            <line>Steering with due course towards the isle of Rhodes,</line>
            <line>Have there injointed them with an after fleet.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>Ay, so I thought. How many, as you guess?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>Of thirty sail: and now they do restem</line>
            <line>Their backward course, bearing with frank appearance</line>
            <line>Their purposes toward Cyprus. Signior Montano,</line>
            <line>Your trusty and most valiant servitor,</line>
            <line>With his free duty recommends you thus,</line>
            <line>And prays you to believe him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF VENICE</speaker>
            <line>'Tis certain, then, for Cyprus.</line>
            <line>Marcus Luccicos, is not he in town?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>He's now in Florence.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF VENICE</speaker>
            <line>Write from us to him; post-post-haste dispatch.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>Here comes Brabantio and the valiant Moor.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter BRABANTIO, OTHELLO, IAGO, RODERIGO, and Officers</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF VENICE</speaker>
            <line>Valiant Othello, we must straight employ you</line>
            <line>Against the general enemy Ottoman.</line>
            <stagedir>To BRABANTIO</stagedir>
            <line>I did not see you; welcome, gentle signior;</line>
            <line>We lack'd your counsel and your help tonight.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRABANTIO</speaker>
            <line>So did I yours. Good your grace, pardon me;</line>
            <line>Neither my place nor aught I heard of business</line>
            <line>Hath raised me from my bed, nor doth the general care</line>
            <line>Take hold on me, for my particular grief</line>
            <line>Is of so flood-gate and o'erbearing nature</line>
            <line>That it engluts and swallows other sorrows</line>
            <line>And it is still itself.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF VENICE</speaker>
            <line>Why, what's the matter?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRABANTIO</speaker>
            <line>My daughter! O, my daughter!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF VENICE</speaker>
            <speaker>Senator</speaker>
            <line>Dead?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRABANTIO</speaker>
            <line>Ay, to me;</line>
            <line>She is abused, stol'n from me, and corrupted</line>
            <line>By spells and medicines bought of mountebanks;</line>
            <line>For nature so preposterously to err,</line>
            <line>Being not deficient, blind, or lame of sense,</line>
            <line>Sans witchcraft could not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF VENICE</speaker>
            <line>Whoe'er he be that in this foul proceeding</line>
            <line>Hath thus beguiled your daughter of herself</line>
            <line>And you of her, the bloody book of law</line>
            <line>You shall yourself read in the bitter letter</line>
            <line>After your own sense, yea, though our proper son</line>
            <line>Stood in your action.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRABANTIO</speaker>
            <line>Humbly I thank your grace.</line>
            <line>Here is the man, this Moor, whom now, it seems,</line>
            <line>Your special mandate for the state-affairs</line>
            <line>Hath hither brought.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF VENICE</speaker>
            <speaker>Senator</speaker>
            <line>We are very sorry for't.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF VENICE</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>To OTHELLO</stagedir>  What, in your own part, can you say to this?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRABANTIO</speaker>
            <line>Nothing, but this is so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OTHELLO</speaker>
            <line>Most potent, grave, and reverend signiors,</line>
            <line>My very noble and approved good masters,</line>
            <line>That I have ta'en away this old man's daughter,</line>
            <line>It is most true; true, I have married her:</line>
            <line>The very head and front of my offending</line>
            <line>Hath this extent, no more. Rude am I in my speech,</line>
            <line>And little bless'd with the soft phrase of peace:</line>
            <line>For since these arms of mine had seven years' pith,</line>
            <line>Till now some nine moons wasted, they have used</line>
            <line>Their dearest action in the tented field,</line>
            <line>And little of this great world can I speak,</line>
            <line>More than pertains to feats of broil and battle,</line>
            <line>And therefore little shall I grace my cause</line>
            <line>In speaking for myself. Yet, by your gracious patience,</line>
            <line>I will a round unvarnish'd tale deliver</line>
            <line>Of my whole course of love; what drugs, what charms,</line>
            <line>What conjuration and what mighty magic,</line>
            <line>For such proceeding I am charged withal,</line>
            <line>I won his daughter.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRABANTIO</speaker>
            <line>A maiden never bold;</line>
            <line>Of spirit so still and quiet, that her motion</line>
            <line>Blush'd at herself; and she, in spite of nature,</line>
            <line>Of years, of country, credit, every thing,</line>
            <line>To fall in love with what she fear'd to look on!</line>
            <line>It is a judgment maim'd and most imperfect</line>
            <line>That will confess perfection so could err</line>
            <line>Against all rules of nature, and must be driven</line>
            <line>To find out practises of cunning hell,</line>
            <line>Why this should be. I therefore vouch again</line>
            <line>That with some mixtures powerful o'er the blood,</line>
            <line>Or with some dram conjured to this effect,</line>
            <line>He wrought upon her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF VENICE</speaker>
            <line>To vouch this, is no proof,</line>
            <line>Without more wider and more overt test</line>
            <line>Than these thin habits and poor likelihoods</line>
            <line>Of modern seeming do prefer against him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>But, Othello, speak:</line>
            <line>Did you by indirect and forced courses</line>
            <line>Subdue and poison this young maid's affections?</line>
            <line>Or came it by request and such fair question</line>
            <line>As soul to soul affordeth?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OTHELLO</speaker>
            <line>I do beseech you,</line>
            <line>Send for the lady to the Sagittary,</line>
            <line>And let her speak of me before her father:</line>
            <line>If you do find me foul in her report,</line>
            <line>The trust, the office I do hold of you,</line>
            <line>Not only take away, but let your sentence</line>
            <line>Even fall upon my life.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF VENICE</speaker>
            <line>Fetch Desdemona hither.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OTHELLO</speaker>
            <line>Ancient, conduct them: you best know the place.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt IAGO and Attendants</stagedir>
            <line>And, till she come, as truly as to heaven</line>
            <line>I do confess the vices of my blood,</line>
            <line>So justly to your grave ears I'll present</line>
            <line>How I did thrive in this fair lady's love,</line>
            <line>And she in mine.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF VENICE</speaker>
            <line>Say it, Othello.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OTHELLO</speaker>
            <line>Her father loved me; oft invited me;</line>
            <line>Still question'd me the story of my life,</line>
            <line>From year to year, the battles, sieges, fortunes,</line>
            <line>That I have passed.</line>
            <line>I ran it through, even from my boyish days,</line>
            <line>To the very moment that he bade me tell it;</line>
            <line>Wherein I spake of most disastrous chances,</line>
            <line>Of moving accidents by flood and field</line>
            <line>Of hair-breadth scapes i' the imminent deadly breach,</line>
            <line>Of being taken by the insolent foe</line>
            <line>And sold to slavery, of my redemption thence</line>
            <line>And portance in my travels' history:</line>
            <line>Wherein of antres vast and deserts idle,</line>
            <line>Rough quarries, rocks and hills whose heads touch heaven</line>
            <line>It was my hint to speak,--such was the process;</line>
            <line>And of the Cannibals that each other eat,</line>
            <line>The Anthropophagi and men whose heads</line>
            <line>Do grow beneath their shoulders. This to hear</line>
            <line>Would Desdemona seriously incline:</line>
            <line>But still the house-affairs would draw her thence:</line>
            <line>Which ever as she could with haste dispatch,</line>
            <line>She'ld come again, and with a greedy ear</line>
            <line>Devour up my discourse: which I observing,</line>
            <line>Took once a pliant hour, and found good means</line>
            <line>To draw from her a prayer of earnest heart</line>
            <line>That I would all my pilgrimage dilate,</line>
            <line>Whereof by parcels she had something heard,</line>
            <line>But not intentively: I did consent,</line>
            <line>And often did beguile her of her tears,</line>
            <line>When I did speak of some distressful stroke</line>
            <line>That my youth suffer'd. My story being done,</line>
            <line>She gave me for my pains a world of sighs:</line>
            <line>She swore, in faith, twas strange, 'twas passing strange,</line>
            <line>'Twas pitiful, 'twas wondrous pitiful:</line>
            <line>She wish'd she had not heard it, yet she wish'd</line>
            <line>That heaven had made her such a man: she thank'd me,</line>
            <line>And bade me, if I had a friend that loved her,</line>
            <line>I should but teach him how to tell my story.</line>
            <line>And that would woo her. Upon this hint I spake:</line>
            <line>She loved me for the dangers I had pass'd,</line>
            <line>And I loved her that she did pity them.</line>
            <line>This only is the witchcraft I have used:</line>
            <line>Here comes the lady; let her witness it.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter DESDEMONA, IAGO, and Attendants</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF VENICE</speaker>
            <line>I think this tale would win my daughter too.</line>
            <line>Good Brabantio,</line>
            <line>Take up this mangled matter at the best:</line>
            <line>Men do their broken weapons rather use</line>
            <line>Than their bare hands.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRABANTIO</speaker>
            <line>I pray you, hear her speak:</line>
            <line>If she confess that she was half the wooer,</line>
            <line>Destruction on my head, if my bad blame</line>
            <line>Light on the man! Come hither, gentle mistress:</line>
            <line>Do you perceive in all this noble company</line>
            <line>Where most you owe obedience?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DESDEMONA</speaker>
            <line>My noble father,</line>
            <line>I do perceive here a divided duty:</line>
            <line>To you I am bound for life and education;</line>
            <line>My life and education both do learn me</line>
            <line>How to respect you; you are the lord of duty;</line>
            <line>I am hitherto your daughter: but here's my husband,</line>
            <line>And so much duty as my mother show'd</line>
            <line>To you, preferring you before her father,</line>
            <line>So much I challenge that I may profess</line>
            <line>Due to the Moor my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRABANTIO</speaker>
            <line>God be wi' you! I have done.</line>
            <line>Please it your grace, on to the state-affairs:</line>
            <line>I had rather to adopt a child than get it.</line>
            <line>Come hither, Moor:</line>
            <line>I here do give thee that with all my heart</line>
            <line>Which, but thou hast already, with all my heart</line>
            <line>I would keep from thee. For your sake, jewel,</line>
            <line>I am glad at soul I have no other child:</line>
            <line>For thy escape would teach me tyranny,</line>
            <line>To hang clogs on them. I have done, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF VENICE</speaker>
            <line>Let me speak like yourself, and lay a sentence,</line>
            <line>Which, as a grise or step, may help these lovers</line>
            <line>Into your favour.</line>
            <line>When remedies are past, the griefs are ended</line>
            <line>By seeing the worst, which late on hopes depended.</line>
            <line>To mourn a mischief that is past and gone</line>
            <line>Is the next way to draw new mischief on.</line>
            <line>What cannot be preserved when fortune takes</line>
            <line>Patience her injury a mockery makes.</line>
            <line>The robb'd that smiles steals something from the thief;</line>
            <line>He robs himself that spends a bootless grief.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRABANTIO</speaker>
            <line>So let the Turk of Cyprus us beguile;</line>
            <line>We lose it not, so long as we can smile.</line>
            <line>He bears the sentence well that nothing bears</line>
            <line>But the free comfort which from thence he hears,</line>
            <line>But he bears both the sentence and the sorrow</line>
            <line>That, to pay grief, must of poor patience borrow.</line>
            <line>These sentences, to sugar, or to gall,</line>
            <line>Being strong on both sides, are equivocal:</line>
            <line>But words are words; I never yet did hear</line>
            <line>That the bruised heart was pierced through the ear.</line>
            <line>I humbly beseech you, proceed to the affairs of state.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF VENICE</speaker>
            <line>The Turk with a most mighty preparation makes for</line>
            <line>Cyprus. Othello, the fortitude of the place is best</line>
            <line>known to you; and though we have there a substitute</line>
            <line>of most allowed sufficiency, yet opinion, a</line>
            <line>sovereign mistress of effects, throws a more safer</line>
            <line>voice on you: you must therefore be content to</line>
            <line>slubber the gloss of your new fortunes with this</line>
            <line>more stubborn and boisterous expedition.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OTHELLO</speaker>
            <line>The tyrant custom, most grave senators,</line>
            <line>Hath made the flinty and steel couch of war</line>
            <line>My thrice-driven bed of down: I do agnise</line>
            <line>A natural and prompt alacrity</line>
            <line>I find in hardness, and do undertake</line>
            <line>These present wars against the Ottomites.</line>
            <line>Most humbly therefore bending to your state,</line>
            <line>I crave fit disposition for my wife.</line>
            <line>Due reference of place and exhibition,</line>
            <line>With such accommodation and besort</line>
            <line>As levels with her breeding.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF VENICE</speaker>
            <line>If you please,</line>
            <line>Be't at her father's.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRABANTIO</speaker>
            <line>I'll not have it so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OTHELLO</speaker>
            <line>Nor I.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DESDEMONA</speaker>
            <line>Nor I; I would not there reside,</line>
            <line>To put my father in impatient thoughts</line>
            <line>By being in his eye. Most gracious duke,</line>
            <line>To my unfolding lend your prosperous ear;</line>
            <line>And let me find a charter in your voice,</line>
            <line>To assist my simpleness.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF VENICE</speaker>
            <line>What would You, Desdemona?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DESDEMONA</speaker>
            <line>That I did love the Moor to live with him,</line>
            <line>My downright violence and storm of fortunes</line>
            <line>May trumpet to the world: my heart's subdued</line>
            <line>Even to the very quality of my lord:</line>
            <line>I saw Othello's visage in his mind,</line>
            <line>And to his honour and his valiant parts</line>
            <line>Did I my soul and fortunes consecrate.</line>
            <line>So that, dear lords, if I be left behind,</line>
            <line>A moth of peace, and he go to the war,</line>
            <line>The rites for which I love him are bereft me,</line>
            <line>And I a heavy interim shall support</line>
            <line>By his dear absence. Let me go with him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OTHELLO</speaker>
            <line>Let her have your voices.</line>
            <line>Vouch with me, heaven, I therefore beg it not,</line>
            <line>To please the palate of my appetite,</line>
            <line>Nor to comply with heat--the young affects</line>
            <line>In me defunct--and proper satisfaction.</line>
            <line>But to be free and bounteous to her mind:</line>
            <line>And heaven defend your good souls, that you think</line>
            <line>I will your serious and great business scant</line>
            <line>For she is with me: no, when light-wing'd toys</line>
            <line>Of feather'd Cupid seal with wanton dullness</line>
            <line>My speculative and officed instruments,</line>
            <line>That my disports corrupt and taint my business,</line>
            <line>Let housewives make a skillet of my helm,</line>
            <line>And all indign and base adversities</line>
            <line>Make head against my estimation!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF VENICE</speaker>
            <line>Be it as you shall privately determine,</line>
            <line>Either for her stay or going: the affair cries haste,</line>
            <line>And speed must answer it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>You must away to-night.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OTHELLO</speaker>
            <line>With all my heart.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF VENICE</speaker>
            <line>At nine i' the morning here we'll meet again.</line>
            <line>Othello, leave some officer behind,</line>
            <line>And he shall our commission bring to you;</line>
            <line>With such things else of quality and respect</line>
            <line>As doth import you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OTHELLO</speaker>
            <line>So please your grace, my ancient;</line>
            <line>A man he is of honest and trust:</line>
            <line>To his conveyance I assign my wife,</line>
            <line>With what else needful your good grace shall think</line>
            <line>To be sent after me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE OF VENICE</speaker>
            <line>Let it be so.</line>
            <line>Good night to every one.</line>
            <stagedir>To BRABANTIO</stagedir>
            <line>And, noble signior,</line>
            <line>If virtue no delighted beauty lack,</line>
            <line>Your son-in-law is far more fair than black.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Senator</speaker>
            <line>Adieu, brave Moor, use Desdemona well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BRABANTIO</speaker>
            <line>Look to her, Moor, if thou hast eyes to see:</line>
            <line>She has deceived her father, and may thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt DUKE OF VENICE, Senators, Officers, &amp;c</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OTHELLO</speaker>
            <line>My life upon her faith! Honest Iago,</line>
            <line>My Desdemona must I leave to thee:</line>
            <line>I prithee, let thy wife attend on her:</line>
            <line>And bring them after in the best advantage.</line>
            <line>Come, Desdemona: I have but an hour</line>
            <line>Of love, of worldly matters and direction,</line>
            <line>To spend with thee: we must obey the time.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt OTHELLO and DESDEMONA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RODERIGO</speaker>
            <line>Iago,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IAGO</speaker>
            <line>What say'st thou, noble heart?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RODERIGO</speaker>
            <line>What will I do, thinkest thou?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IAGO</speaker>
            <line>Why, go to bed, and sleep.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RODERIGO</speaker>
            <line>I will incontinently drown myself.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IAGO</speaker>
            <line>If thou dost, I shall never love thee after. Why,</line>
            <line>thou silly gentleman!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RODERIGO</speaker>
            <line>It is silliness to live when to live is torment; and</line>
            <line>then have we a prescription to die when death is our physician.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IAGO</speaker>
            <line>O villainous! I have looked upon the world for four</line>
            <line>times seven years; and since I could distinguish</line>
            <line>betwixt a benefit and an injury, I never found man</line>
            <line>that knew how to love himself. Ere I would say, I</line>
            <line>would drown myself for the love of a guinea-hen, I</line>
            <line>would change my humanity with a baboon.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RODERIGO</speaker>
            <line>What should I do? I confess it is my shame to be so</line>
            <line>fond; but it is not in my virtue to amend it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IAGO</speaker>
            <line>Virtue! a fig! 'tis in ourselves that we are thus</line>
            <line>or thus. Our bodies are our gardens, to the which</line>
            <line>our wills are gardeners: so that if we will plant</line>
            <line>nettles, or sow lettuce, set hyssop and weed up</line>
            <line>thyme, supply it with one gender of herbs, or</line>
            <line>distract it with many, either to have it sterile</line>
            <line>with idleness, or manured with industry, why, the</line>
            <line>power and corrigible authority of this lies in our</line>
            <line>wills. If the balance of our lives had not one</line>
            <line>scale of reason to poise another of sensuality, the</line>
            <line>blood and baseness of our natures would conduct us</line>
            <line>to most preposterous conclusions: but we have</line>
            <line>reason to cool our raging motions, our carnal</line>
            <line>stings, our unbitted lusts, whereof I take this that</line>
            <line>you call love to be a sect or scion.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RODERIGO</speaker>
            <line>It cannot be.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IAGO</speaker>
            <line>It is merely a lust of the blood and a permission of</line>
            <line>the will. Come, be a man. Drown thyself! drown</line>
            <line>cats and blind puppies. I have professed me thy</line>
            <line>friend and I confess me knit to thy deserving with</line>
            <line>cables of perdurable toughness; I could never</line>
            <line>better stead thee than now. Put money in thy</line>
            <line>purse; follow thou the wars; defeat thy favour with</line>
            <line>an usurped beard; I say, put money in thy purse. It</line>
            <line>cannot be that Desdemona should long continue her</line>
            <line>love to the Moor,-- put money in thy purse,--nor he</line>
            <line>his to her: it was a violent commencement, and thou</line>
            <line>shalt see an answerable sequestration:--put but</line>
            <line>money in thy purse. These Moors are changeable in</line>
            <line>their wills: fill thy purse with money:--the food</line>
            <line>that to him now is as luscious as locusts, shall be</line>
            <line>to him shortly as bitter as coloquintida. She must</line>
            <line>change for youth: when she is sated with his body,</line>
            <line>she will find the error of her choice: she must</line>
            <line>have change, she must: therefore put money in thy</line>
            <line>purse. If thou wilt needs damn thyself, do it a</line>
            <line>more delicate way than drowning. Make all the money</line>
            <line>thou canst: if sanctimony and a frail vow betwixt</line>
            <line>an erring barbarian and a supersubtle Venetian not</line>
            <line>too hard for my wits and all the tribe of hell, thou</line>
            <line>shalt enjoy her; therefore make money. A pox of</line>
            <line>drowning thyself! it is clean out of the way: seek</line>
            <line>thou rather to be hanged in compassing thy joy than</line>
            <line>to be drowned and go without her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RODERIGO</speaker>
            <line>Wilt thou be fast to my hopes, if I depend on</line>
            <line>the issue?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IAGO</speaker>
            <line>Thou art sure of me:--go, make money:--I have told</line>
            <line>thee often, and I re-tell thee again and again, I</line>
            <line>hate the Moor: my cause is hearted; thine hath no</line>
            <line>less reason. Let us be conjunctive in our revenge</line>
            <line>against him: if thou canst cuckold him, thou dost</line>
            <line>thyself a pleasure, me a sport. There are many</line>
            <line>events in the womb of time which will be delivered.</line>
            <line>Traverse! go, provide thy money. We will have more</line>
            <line>of this to-morrow. Adieu.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RODERIGO</speaker>
            <line>Where shall we meet i' the morning?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IAGO</speaker>
            <line>At my lodging.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RODERIGO</speaker>
            <line>I'll be with thee betimes.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IAGO</speaker>
            <line>Go to; farewell. Do you hear, Roderigo?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RODERIGO</speaker>
            <line>What say you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IAGO</speaker>
            <line>No more of drowning, do you hear?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RODERIGO</speaker>
            <line>I am changed: I'll go sell all my land.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IAGO</speaker>
            <line>Thus do I ever make my fool my purse:</line>
            <line>For I mine own gain'd knowledge should profane,</line>
            <line>If I would time expend with such a snipe.</line>
            <line>But for my sport and profit. I hate the Moor:</line>
            <line>And it is thought abroad, that 'twixt my sheets</line>
            <line>He has done my office: I know not if't be true;</line>
            <line>But I, for mere suspicion in that kind,</line>
            <line>Will do as if for surety. He holds me well;</line>
            <line>The better shall my purpose work on him.</line>
            <line>Cassio's a proper man: let me see now:</line>
            <line>To get his place and to plume up my will</line>
            <line>In double knavery--How, how? Let's see:--</line>
            <line>After some time, to abuse Othello's ear</line>
            <line>That he is too familiar with his wife.</line>
            <line>He hath a person and a smooth dispose</line>
            <line>To be suspected, framed to make women false.</line>
            <line>The Moor is of a free and open nature,</line>
            <line>That thinks men honest that but seem to be so,</line>
            <line>And will as tenderly be led by the nose</line>
            <line>As asses are.</line>
            <line>I have't. It is engender'd. Hell and night</line>
            <line>Must bring this monstrous birth to the world's light.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>