<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.org:doctypes:dita:concept" "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.org:doctypes:dita:concept">
<concept id="conceptId">
  <title>Release Notes: Version 1.0.0RC17</title>
  <shortdesc>Version 1.0.0RC17</shortdesc>
  <prolog>
    <metadata>
      <keywords>
        <indexterm>
          <indexterm>release notes<indexterm>Version 1.0.0RC17</indexterm></indexterm>
        </indexterm>
      </keywords>
    </metadata>
  </prolog>
  <conbody>
    <section>
      <title>Theme for the Release</title>
      <p>This release provides significant updates to the EPUB transform with full support for font
        embedding and obfuscation. This functionality includes some enhancements to the more general
        map-to-graphic-map processing to make it easier to extend for things other than just
        graphics.</p>
      <p>This release also has the start of support for the 2.x Open Toolkit. The EPUB transform
        should work with both versions 1.8.5 and 2.x, although it has not been tested extensively
        with 2.x versions later than 2.1 at this time. The 2.x version of the preprocessing does not
        include the adjust copy-to processing provided in the 1.8.5 version but the 2.x OT includes
        new functionality to ensure that multiple references to the same topic result in
        uniquely-named HTML files. This new functionality should be sufficient to satisfy the EPUB
        requirement that a given HTML file only be used once from the EPUB navigation structure.
        However, it does not, as far as I know, use @keys values to set the result filename so there
        may be a difference in how result anchors are generated between the 1.8.5 and 2.x versions
        in this release.</p>
      <p>This release also includes a number of  accumulated bug fixes and enhancements in various
        DITA for Publishers and DITA Community plugins.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="section_ggg_vf4_tv">
      <title>Resolved Issues</title>
      <p>These are the most significant issues addressed in this release:</p>
      <ul id="ul_gdd_xf4_tv">
        <li>EPUB issue #57: Items for audio and video files do not produce correct MIME
            types.<p>Video and audio embedding should now work correctly using the DITA Community
              <xmlelem>audio</xmlelem> and <xmlelem>video</xmlelem> markup. </p></li>
        <li>EPUB issue #57: Is `application/svg` the correct media-type for SVG images?<p>Embeded
            SVGs should reflect the correct MIME type.</p></li>
      </ul>
    </section>
  </conbody>
</concept>
