<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<chapter
  id="chapter-id">
  <title>Video Example</title>
  <body>
    <p outputclass="ct">Hitting Basics</p>
    <p outputclass="tx"><ph outputclass="DropCapKE">H</ph><ph>itting in slowpitch is </ph><ph outputclass="ital" xml:lang="en-US">about</ph><ph> the same as hitting in baseball and fastpitch softball. You hold the bat </ph><ph outputclass="ital" xml:lang="en-US">about</ph><ph> the same way; your stance, forward stride, and swing are all </ph><ph outputclass="ital" xml:lang="en-US">about</ph><ph> the same. But if you talk to accomplished veterans of the slowpitch game, they will tell you that hitting in slowpitch is considerably different from hitting in baseball and fastpitch softball, although they are </ph><ph outputclass="ital" xml:lang="en-US">about</ph><ph> the same. And they will also tell you stories about accomplished baseball hitters who couldn’t adapt to slowpitch.</ph></p>
    <p outputclass="tx"><ph>The good news in slowpitch hitting is that you have much more time to hit the ball. The bad news in slowpitch hitting is that you have much more time to hit the ball . . . and thus to swing incorrectly.</ph></p>
    <p outputclass="tx"><ph>If you’re relatively new to slowpitch, studying this chapter will provide you with a solid foundation to become a successful hitter. If you’ve been playing slowpitch softball for several years and are an accomplished hitter, you may choose to skip this chapter, although you’ll miss a point or two that may help you become an even better hitter. Or if you’re currently unsatisfied with your hitting, a careful review of the basics will be a good foundation before you go to chapter 2, “Advanced Hitting.”</ph></p>
    <p outputclass="tx"><ph>Although no single way of hitting is correct for every player, following the basic principles covered in this chapter can increase the odds of your hitting well.</ph></p>
    <p outputclass="tx"><ph>As you read this chapter, have a bat handy and enough space to swing it so that you can try out what is being discussed.</ph></p>
    <p outputclass="No-Paragraph-Style para-style-override-2"/>
    <fig outputclass="image">
<!--      <d4p_video id="E5123_026.mp4" controls="controls" width="640" height="360">
        <source src="images/E5123_026.mp4" type="video/mp4"/>
      </d4p_video>
-->      
      <d4p_video id="E5123_026.mp4" width="640" height="360">
        <d4p_video_poster value="../images/E5123_026_poster.png"/>
        <d4p_video_source value="../images/E5123_026.mp4" type="video/mp4"/>
      </d4p_video>
    </fig>
  </body>
</chapter>
