<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE learningContent
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Learning Content//EN" "learningContent.dtd">
<learningContent id="SEC005_002">
   <title>5.2 The origin of the 3 K radiation</title>
   <learningContentbody>
      <section>
          
          <p>In speaking of the radiation as having a cosmic origin, what do we have in
            mind? Essentially this:</p>
          
          
          <p>In the violent conditions of the early evolution of the Universe, a stage was
            reached where the matter consisted of a plasma of electrons, protons, neutrons, and some
            light nuclei such as helium. There were no atoms as such for the simple reason that
            atoms would have been too fragile to withstand the violence of the collisions that were
            taking place at the temperature that then existed. As electromagnetic radiation passed
            through the plasma, it interacted with the matter, exchanging energy in packets or
            ‘quanta’ of magnitude</p>
          <fig outputclass="Equation">
            <image href="../../media/S357_1_e009i.gif"/>
            <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
         </fig>
          <p>where <i>f</i> is the frequency of the radiation and <i>h</i> is the Planck
            constant.</p>
          <p>The radiation was mainly affected by its collisions with the <i>electrons</i>.
            This is because such collisions cause much bigger energy changes to the photons than
            collisions with the far more massive nucleons (just as a table tennis ball may lose all
            its energy in a collision with another table tennis ball, but will bounce off a
            relatively massive billiard ball with little change in energy). Thus there is a ready
            exchange of energy between the photons and the electrons, in the process of which, the
            radiation acquires the thermal spectrum characterised by the temperature of the
            electrons. The radiation and the electrons tend to come into thermal equilibrium with
            each other, and the electrons are said to have <i>thermalised</i> the
            radiation.</p>
          <p>As the expansion of the Universe proceeded, the temperature of the radiation
            progressively fell, and so did that of the matter. This fall led to important changes in
            behaviour. From the earliest times, the Universe had been opaque to radiation, in the
            sense that it could not travel far before it interacted with the electrons. But as the
            temperature declined and photon energies decreased, a stage was reached where electrons
            could be bound to nuclei to form neutral atoms – atoms that were no longer likely
            to be disrupted in collisions with the reduced-energy photons. Later, the energy of the
            radiation reduced still further to the point where it could not even excite the atomic
            electrons to higher energy states. At this stage, the radiation could no longer be
            strongly absorbed by matter. This being so, the Universe became transparent. This stage
            we call the <i>decoupling</i> of radiation from matter. (You will find that some books
            refer to this stage in the development of the Universe as the
            ‘recombination’ era rather than the decoupling epoch.) It occurs when the
            radiation has cooled down to the point where the most probable photon energy corresponds
            to a temperature of 3000 K.
            This
            occurred some 4 × 10<sup>5</sup> years after the instant of the big bang.
            Thus the radiation we now observe as 3 K radiation is today's cooled-down remnant of
            that 3000 K big bang radiation.</p>
          <p>How confident can we be that this was indeed the origin of the 3 K radiation?
            There are essentially four properties that lead to this conclusion:</p>
          <ol>
            <li>
              <p>As we have already mentioned, the <i>isotropy</i> of the radiation points
                to some global, cosmic origin.</p>
            </li>
            <li>
              <p>The <i>spectrum</i> of the radiation is such that it could only have been
                produced by a sufficiently rapid interaction of the radiation with matter for the
                thermal energy distribution of the particles of matter to be imprinted on the
                radiation. Only in the early dense stages of the Universe were particles and
                radiation interacting fast enough for this to have been achieved within the time
                available.</p>
            </li>
            <li>
              <p>The <i>present temperature</i> of the radiation of only 3 K is lower than
                that of most visible matter currently in the Universe. How could it be so low? The
                only reasonable explanation is that it has been strongly redshifted -indicating that
                it has been travelling towards us over an exceedingly long period of time, i.e. it
                was emitted soon after the big bang.</p>
            </li>
            <li>
              <p>The <i>density of photons</i> corresponding to the 3 K radiation is
                enormous. In fact there are believed to be about 10<sup>9</sup> times as many 3 K
                photons in any large region of the Universe as there are neutrons and protons.
                Clearly this radiation is no mere by-product of an obscure process; it is a
                ubiquitous feature of the Universe. This prompts us to ask at what stage of the
                Universe is radiation likely to have played a dominant role? The answer has to be:
                the violent <i>early</i> Universe.</p>
            </li>
          </ol>
          
        </section>
   </learningContentbody>
</learningContent>