<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<chapter id="d5e2"><title>Preface</title><prolog/><body><p><image href="../images/chapter00.png" width="5in" placement="inline"/></p><p>This book grew out of my experimentation with wikis for online help and
      user assistance and my complete adoration of Google search, which I felt would change forever
      the way that users find information that helps them complete a task, even one as simple as
      slicing a tomato or folding fitted sheets.<fn><p>
          http://www.ehow.com/how_1682_slice-tomato.html,
          http://www.ehow.com/how_6067_fold-fitted-sheet.html</p></fn> Everyday tasks are documented
      on the web by everyday people. The start of this people-centric revolution has been described
      as the second generation of the Web. Web 1.0 was about data and display, but Web 2.0 merges
      data and display with user-centric design and ideas. </p><p>While people debate the cult of
      the amateur<fn><p> Andrew Keen, 2007, The Cult of the Amateur: How Today’s Internet is Killing
          Our Culture, Broadway Business, ISBN: 0385520808.</p></fn> and spread uncertainty and
      doubt, professional writers now have the tools to <indexterm>collaboration<indexterm>with
          audiences</indexterm></indexterm>collaborate with their audience easily for the first time
      in history. How we seize this opportunity and how our audience responds and becomes a part of
      this revolution will determine our success in this new environment.</p><p>Nearly all of the
      discussion in this book surrounds new ideas for documentation, whether you are writing
      documentation as film makers, corporate marketers, technical writers, programmers, or
      managers. Sometimes these “new” ideas uncover age-old truths about communities and people’s
      behavior and habits. Sometimes you have to experiment on your own time with your own dollars
      and tools to prove that a technique is worth an investment. That try-and-see attitude is what
      the cutting edge is all about. </p><p>Beth Kanter<indexterm>Kanter, Beth</indexterm>, a
      trainer who teaches non-profit organizations how to bring social networking to their business,
      compares experiencing social media for the first time to a first-time sexual experience—you
      can’t describe how it feels until you experience it. In the same way, you can’t describe or
      measure the value of a technique or methodology until you try it and analyze your
      results.</p><p>Still, many people describe social media dabbling and experimentation as a
      waste of time. However, Clay <indexterm>Shirky, Clay</indexterm>Shirky states his argument
      against “how can you find the time” as a rallying cry against the mindless hours spent
      watching TV—two hundred billion hours per year in the U.S. alone.<fn><p>
          http://www.shirky.com/herecomeseverybody/2008/04/looking-for-the-mouse.html</p></fn> By
      finding and making the time for this experimental discovery, you may save time and effort
      later while increasing the quality and adding perceived value. Plus, you may find interacting
      with others more fulfilling than the one-way communication offered by your television or other
      media outlets. </p></body></chapter>
