<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:shakespear:dtd:act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-1">
   <title>ACT I</title>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  On a ship at sea: a tempestuous noise of thunder and lightning heard.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter a Master and a Boatswain</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Master</speaker>
            <line>Boatswain!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Boatswain</speaker>
            <line>Here, master: what cheer?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Master</speaker>
            <line>Good, speak to the mariners: fall to't, yarely,</line>
            <line>or we run ourselves aground: bestir, bestir.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Enter Mariners</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Boatswain</speaker>
            <line>Heigh, my hearts! cheerly, cheerly, my hearts!</line>
            <line>yare, yare! Take in the topsail. Tend to the</line>
            <line>master's whistle. Blow, till thou burst thy wind,</line>
            <line>if room enough!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter ALONSO, SEBASTIAN, ANTONIO, FERDINAND,
GONZALO, and others</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALONSO</speaker>
            <line>Good boatswain, have care. Where's the master?</line>
            <line>Play the men.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Boatswain</speaker>
            <line>I pray now, keep below.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>Where is the master, boatswain?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Boatswain</speaker>
            <line>Do you not hear him? You mar our labour: keep your</line>
            <line>cabins: you do assist the storm.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GONZALO</speaker>
            <line>Nay, good, be patient.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Boatswain</speaker>
            <line>When the sea is. Hence! What cares these roarers</line>
            <line>for the name of king? To cabin: silence! trouble us not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GONZALO</speaker>
            <line>Good, yet remember whom thou hast aboard.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Boatswain</speaker>
            <line>None that I more love than myself. You are a</line>
            <line>counsellor; if you can command these elements to</line>
            <line>silence, and work the peace of the present, we will</line>
            <line>not hand a rope more; use your authority: if you</line>
            <line>cannot, give thanks you have lived so long, and make</line>
            <line>yourself ready in your cabin for the mischance of</line>
            <line>the hour, if it so hap. Cheerly, good hearts! Out</line>
            <line>of our way, I say.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GONZALO</speaker>
            <line>I have great comfort from this fellow: methinks he</line>
            <line>hath no drowning mark upon him; his complexion is</line>
            <line>perfect gallows. Stand fast, good Fate, to his</line>
            <line>hanging: make the rope of his destiny our cable,</line>
            <line>for our own doth little advantage. If he be not</line>
            <line>born to be hanged, our case is miserable.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Re-enter Boatswain</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Boatswain</speaker>
            <line>Down with the topmast! yare! lower, lower! Bring</line>
            <line>her to try with main-course.</line>
            <stagedir>A cry within</stagedir>
            <line>A plague upon this howling! they are louder than</line>
            <line>the weather or our office.</line>
            <stagedir>Re-enter SEBASTIAN, ANTONIO, and GONZALO</stagedir>
            <line>Yet again! what do you here? Shall we give o'er</line>
            <line>and drown? Have you a mind to sink?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SEBASTIAN</speaker>
            <line>A pox o' your throat, you bawling, blasphemous,</line>
            <line>incharitable dog!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Boatswain</speaker>
            <line>Work you then.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>Hang, cur! hang, you whoreson, insolent noisemaker!</line>
            <line>We are less afraid to be drowned than thou art.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GONZALO</speaker>
            <line>I'll warrant him for drowning; though the ship were</line>
            <line>no stronger than a nutshell and as leaky as an</line>
            <line>unstanched wench.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Boatswain</speaker>
            <line>Lay her a-hold, a-hold! set her two courses off to</line>
            <line>sea again; lay her off.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter Mariners wet</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Mariners</speaker>
            <line>All lost! to prayers, to prayers! all lost!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Boatswain</speaker>
            <line>What, must our mouths be cold?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GONZALO</speaker>
            <line>The king and prince at prayers! let's assist them,</line>
            <line>For our case is as theirs.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SEBASTIAN</speaker>
            <line>I'm out of patience.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>We are merely cheated of our lives by drunkards:</line>
            <line>This wide-chapp'd rascal--would thou mightst lie drowning</line>
            <line>The washing of ten tides!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GONZALO</speaker>
            <line>He'll be hang'd yet,</line>
            <line>Though every drop of water swear against it</line>
            <line>And gape at widest to glut him.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>A confused noise within:   'Mercy on us!'--
'We split, we split!'--'Farewell, my wife and
children!'--
'Farewell, brother!'--'We split, we split, we split!'</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>Let's all sink with the king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SEBASTIAN</speaker>
            <line>Let's take leave of him.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt ANTONIO and SEBASTIAN</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GONZALO</speaker>
            <line>Now would I give a thousand furlongs of sea for an</line>
            <line>acre of barren ground, long heath, brown furze, any</line>
            <line>thing. The wills above be done! but I would fain</line>
            <line>die a dry death.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  The island. Before PROSPERO'S cell.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter PROSPERO and MIRANDA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MIRANDA</speaker>
            <line>If by your art, my dearest father, you have</line>
            <line>Put the wild waters in this roar, allay them.</line>
            <line>The sky, it seems, would pour down stinking pitch,</line>
            <line>But that the sea, mounting to the welkin's cheek,</line>
            <line>Dashes the fire out. O, I have suffered</line>
            <line>With those that I saw suffer: a brave vessel,</line>
            <line>Who had, no doubt, some noble creature in her,</line>
            <line>Dash'd all to pieces. O, the cry did knock</line>
            <line>Against my very heart. Poor souls, they perish'd.</line>
            <line>Had I been any god of power, I would</line>
            <line>Have sunk the sea within the earth or ere</line>
            <line>It should the good ship so have swallow'd and</line>
            <line>The fraughting souls within her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>Be collected:</line>
            <line>No more amazement: tell your piteous heart</line>
            <line>There's no harm done.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MIRANDA</speaker>
            <line>O, woe the day!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>No harm.</line>
            <line>I have done nothing but in care of thee,</line>
            <line>Of thee, my dear one, thee, my daughter, who</line>
            <line>Art ignorant of what thou art, nought knowing</line>
            <line>Of whence I am, nor that I am more better</line>
            <line>Than Prospero, master of a full poor cell,</line>
            <line>And thy no greater father.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MIRANDA</speaker>
            <line>More to know</line>
            <line>Did never meddle with my thoughts.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>'Tis time</line>
            <line>I should inform thee farther. Lend thy hand,</line>
            <line>And pluck my magic garment from me. So:</line>
            <stagedir>Lays down his mantle</stagedir>
            <line>Lie there, my art. Wipe thou thine eyes; have comfort.</line>
            <line>The direful spectacle of the wreck, which touch'd</line>
            <line>The very virtue of compassion in thee,</line>
            <line>I have with such provision in mine art</line>
            <line>So safely ordered that there is no soul--</line>
            <line>No, not so much perdition as an hair</line>
            <line>Betid to any creature in the vessel</line>
            <line>Which thou heard'st cry, which thou saw'st sink. Sit down;</line>
            <line>For thou must now know farther.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MIRANDA</speaker>
            <line>You have often</line>
            <line>Begun to tell me what I am, but stopp'd</line>
            <line>And left me to a bootless inquisition,</line>
            <line>Concluding 'Stay: not yet.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>The hour's now come;</line>
            <line>The very minute bids thee ope thine ear;</line>
            <line>Obey and be attentive. Canst thou remember</line>
            <line>A time before we came unto this cell?</line>
            <line>I do not think thou canst, for then thou wast not</line>
            <line>Out three years old.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MIRANDA</speaker>
            <line>Certainly, sir, I can.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>By what? by any other house or person?</line>
            <line>Of any thing the image tell me that</line>
            <line>Hath kept with thy remembrance.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MIRANDA</speaker>
            <line>'Tis far off</line>
            <line>And rather like a dream than an assurance</line>
            <line>That my remembrance warrants. Had I not</line>
            <line>Four or five women once that tended me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>Thou hadst, and more, Miranda. But how is it</line>
            <line>That this lives in thy mind? What seest thou else</line>
            <line>In the dark backward and abysm of time?</line>
            <line>If thou remember'st aught ere thou camest here,</line>
            <line>How thou camest here thou mayst.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MIRANDA</speaker>
            <line>But that I do not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>Twelve year since, Miranda, twelve year since,</line>
            <line>Thy father was the Duke of Milan and</line>
            <line>A prince of power.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MIRANDA</speaker>
            <line>Sir, are not you my father?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>Thy mother was a piece of virtue, and</line>
            <line>She said thou wast my daughter; and thy father</line>
            <line>Was Duke of Milan; and thou his only heir</line>
            <line>And princess no worse issued.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MIRANDA</speaker>
            <line>O the heavens!</line>
            <line>What foul play had we, that we came from thence?</line>
            <line>Or blessed was't we did?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>Both, both, my girl:</line>
            <line>By foul play, as thou say'st, were we heaved thence,</line>
            <line>But blessedly holp hither.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MIRANDA</speaker>
            <line>O, my heart bleeds</line>
            <line>To think o' the teen that I have turn'd you to,</line>
            <line>Which is from my remembrance! Please you, farther.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>My brother and thy uncle, call'd Antonio--</line>
            <line>I pray thee, mark me--that a brother should</line>
            <line>Be so perfidious!--he whom next thyself</line>
            <line>Of all the world I loved and to him put</line>
            <line>The manage of my state; as at that time</line>
            <line>Through all the signories it was the first</line>
            <line>And Prospero the prime duke, being so reputed</line>
            <line>In dignity, and for the liberal arts</line>
            <line>Without a parallel; those being all my study,</line>
            <line>The government I cast upon my brother</line>
            <line>And to my state grew stranger, being transported</line>
            <line>And rapt in secret studies. Thy false uncle--</line>
            <line>Dost thou attend me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MIRANDA</speaker>
            <line>Sir, most heedfully.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>Being once perfected how to grant suits,</line>
            <line>How to deny them, who to advance and who</line>
            <line>To trash for over-topping, new created</line>
            <line>The creatures that were mine, I say, or changed 'em,</line>
            <line>Or else new form'd 'em; having both the key</line>
            <line>Of officer and office, set all hearts i' the state</line>
            <line>To what tune pleased his ear; that now he was</line>
            <line>The ivy which had hid my princely trunk,</line>
            <line>And suck'd my verdure out on't. Thou attend'st not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MIRANDA</speaker>
            <line>O, good sir, I do.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>I pray thee, mark me.</line>
            <line>I, thus neglecting worldly ends, all dedicated</line>
            <line>To closeness and the bettering of my mind</line>
            <line>With that which, but by being so retired,</line>
            <line>O'er-prized all popular rate, in my false brother</line>
            <line>Awaked an evil nature; and my trust,</line>
            <line>Like a good parent, did beget of him</line>
            <line>A falsehood in its contrary as great</line>
            <line>As my trust was; which had indeed no limit,</line>
            <line>A confidence sans bound. He being thus lorded,</line>
            <line>Not only with what my revenue yielded,</line>
            <line>But what my power might else exact, like one</line>
            <line>Who having into truth, by telling of it,</line>
            <line>Made such a sinner of his memory,</line>
            <line>To credit his own lie, he did believe</line>
            <line>He was indeed the duke; out o' the substitution</line>
            <line>And executing the outward face of royalty,</line>
            <line>With all prerogative: hence his ambition growing--</line>
            <line>Dost thou hear?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MIRANDA</speaker>
            <line>Your tale, sir, would cure deafness.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>To have no screen between this part he play'd</line>
            <line>And him he play'd it for, he needs will be</line>
            <line>Absolute Milan. Me, poor man, my library</line>
            <line>Was dukedom large enough: of temporal royalties</line>
            <line>He thinks me now incapable; confederates--</line>
            <line>So dry he was for sway--wi' the King of Naples</line>
            <line>To give him annual tribute, do him homage,</line>
            <line>Subject his coronet to his crown and bend</line>
            <line>The dukedom yet unbow'd--alas, poor Milan!--</line>
            <line>To most ignoble stooping.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MIRANDA</speaker>
            <line>O the heavens!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>Mark his condition and the event; then tell me</line>
            <line>If this might be a brother.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MIRANDA</speaker>
            <line>I should sin</line>
            <line>To think but nobly of my grandmother:</line>
            <line>Good wombs have borne bad sons.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>Now the condition.</line>
            <line>The King of Naples, being an enemy</line>
            <line>To me inveterate, hearkens my brother's suit;</line>
            <line>Which was, that he, in lieu o' the premises</line>
            <line>Of homage and I know not how much tribute,</line>
            <line>Should presently extirpate me and mine</line>
            <line>Out of the dukedom and confer fair Milan</line>
            <line>With all the honours on my brother: whereon,</line>
            <line>A treacherous army levied, one midnight</line>
            <line>Fated to the purpose did Antonio open</line>
            <line>The gates of Milan, and, i' the dead of darkness,</line>
            <line>The ministers for the purpose hurried thence</line>
            <line>Me and thy crying self.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MIRANDA</speaker>
            <line>Alack, for pity!</line>
            <line>I, not remembering how I cried out then,</line>
            <line>Will cry it o'er again: it is a hint</line>
            <line>That wrings mine eyes to't.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>Hear a little further</line>
            <line>And then I'll bring thee to the present business</line>
            <line>Which now's upon's; without the which this story</line>
            <line>Were most impertinent.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MIRANDA</speaker>
            <line>Wherefore did they not</line>
            <line>That hour destroy us?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>Well demanded, wench:</line>
            <line>My tale provokes that question. Dear, they durst not,</line>
            <line>So dear the love my people bore me, nor set</line>
            <line>A mark so bloody on the business, but</line>
            <line>With colours fairer painted their foul ends.</line>
            <line>In few, they hurried us aboard a bark,</line>
            <line>Bore us some leagues to sea; where they prepared</line>
            <line>A rotten carcass of a boat, not rigg'd,</line>
            <line>Nor tackle, sail, nor mast; the very rats</line>
            <line>Instinctively had quit it: there they hoist us,</line>
            <line>To cry to the sea that roar'd to us, to sigh</line>
            <line>To the winds whose pity, sighing back again,</line>
            <line>Did us but loving wrong.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MIRANDA</speaker>
            <line>Alack, what trouble</line>
            <line>Was I then to you!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>O, a cherubim</line>
            <line>Thou wast that did preserve me. Thou didst smile.</line>
            <line>Infused with a fortitude from heaven,</line>
            <line>When I have deck'd the sea with drops full salt,</line>
            <line>Under my burthen groan'd; which raised in me</line>
            <line>An undergoing stomach, to bear up</line>
            <line>Against what should ensue.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MIRANDA</speaker>
            <line>How came we ashore?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>By Providence divine.</line>
            <line>Some food we had and some fresh water that</line>
            <line>A noble Neapolitan, Gonzalo,</line>
            <line>Out of his charity, being then appointed</line>
            <line>Master of this design, did give us, with</line>
            <line>Rich garments, linens, stuffs and necessaries,</line>
            <line>Which since have steaded much; so, of his gentleness,</line>
            <line>Knowing I loved my books, he furnish'd me</line>
            <line>From mine own library with volumes that</line>
            <line>I prize above my dukedom.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MIRANDA</speaker>
            <line>Would I might</line>
            <line>But ever see that man!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>Now I arise:</line>
            <stagedir>Resumes his mantle</stagedir>
            <line>Sit still, and hear the last of our sea-sorrow.</line>
            <line>Here in this island we arrived; and here</line>
            <line>Have I, thy schoolmaster, made thee more profit</line>
            <line>Than other princesses can that have more time</line>
            <line>For vainer hours and tutors not so careful.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MIRANDA</speaker>
            <line>Heavens thank you for't! And now, I pray you, sir,</line>
            <line>For still 'tis beating in my mind, your reason</line>
            <line>For raising this sea-storm?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>Know thus far forth.</line>
            <line>By accident most strange, bountiful Fortune,</line>
            <line>Now my dear lady, hath mine enemies</line>
            <line>Brought to this shore; and by my prescience</line>
            <line>I find my zenith doth depend upon</line>
            <line>A most auspicious star, whose influence</line>
            <line>If now I court not but omit, my fortunes</line>
            <line>Will ever after droop. Here cease more questions:</line>
            <line>Thou art inclined to sleep; 'tis a good dulness,</line>
            <line>And give it way: I know thou canst not choose.</line>
            <stagedir>MIRANDA sleeps</stagedir>
            <line>Come away, servant, come. I am ready now.</line>
            <line>Approach, my Ariel, come.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter ARIEL</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARIEL</speaker>
            <line>All hail, great master! grave sir, hail! I come</line>
            <line>To answer thy best pleasure; be't to fly,</line>
            <line>To swim, to dive into the fire, to ride</line>
            <line>On the curl'd clouds, to thy strong bidding task</line>
            <line>Ariel and all his quality.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>Hast thou, spirit,</line>
            <line>Perform'd to point the tempest that I bade thee?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARIEL</speaker>
            <line>To every article.</line>
            <line>I boarded the king's ship; now on the beak,</line>
            <line>Now in the waist, the deck, in every cabin,</line>
            <line>I flamed amazement: sometime I'ld divide,</line>
            <line>And burn in many places; on the topmast,</line>
            <line>The yards and bowsprit, would I flame distinctly,</line>
            <line>Then meet and join. Jove's lightnings, the precursors</line>
            <line>O' the dreadful thunder-claps, more momentary</line>
            <line>And sight-outrunning were not; the fire and cracks</line>
            <line>Of sulphurous roaring the most mighty Neptune</line>
            <line>Seem to besiege and make his bold waves tremble,</line>
            <line>Yea, his dread trident shake.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>My brave spirit!</line>
            <line>Who was so firm, so constant, that this coil</line>
            <line>Would not infect his reason?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARIEL</speaker>
            <line>Not a soul</line>
            <line>But felt a fever of the mad and play'd</line>
            <line>Some tricks of desperation. All but mariners</line>
            <line>Plunged in the foaming brine and quit the vessel,</line>
            <line>Then all afire with me: the king's son, Ferdinand,</line>
            <line>With hair up-staring,--then like reeds, not hair,--</line>
            <line>Was the first man that leap'd; cried, 'Hell is empty</line>
            <line>And all the devils are here.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>Why that's my spirit!</line>
            <line>But was not this nigh shore?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARIEL</speaker>
            <line>Close by, my master.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>But are they, Ariel, safe?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARIEL</speaker>
            <line>Not a hair perish'd;</line>
            <line>On their sustaining garments not a blemish,</line>
            <line>But fresher than before: and, as thou badest me,</line>
            <line>In troops I have dispersed them 'bout the isle.</line>
            <line>The king's son have I landed by himself;</line>
            <line>Whom I left cooling of the air with sighs</line>
            <line>In an odd angle of the isle and sitting,</line>
            <line>His arms in this sad knot.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>Of the king's ship</line>
            <line>The mariners say how thou hast disposed</line>
            <line>And all the rest o' the fleet.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARIEL</speaker>
            <line>Safely in harbour</line>
            <line>Is the king's ship; in the deep nook, where once</line>
            <line>Thou call'dst me up at midnight to fetch dew</line>
            <line>From the still-vex'd Bermoothes, there she's hid:</line>
            <line>The mariners all under hatches stow'd;</line>
            <line>Who, with a charm join'd to their suffer'd labour,</line>
            <line>I have left asleep; and for the rest o' the fleet</line>
            <line>Which I dispersed, they all have met again</line>
            <line>And are upon the Mediterranean flote,</line>
            <line>Bound sadly home for Naples,</line>
            <line>Supposing that they saw the king's ship wreck'd</line>
            <line>And his great person perish.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>Ariel, thy charge</line>
            <line>Exactly is perform'd: but there's more work.</line>
            <line>What is the time o' the day?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARIEL</speaker>
            <line>Past the mid season.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>At least two glasses. The time 'twixt six and now</line>
            <line>Must by us both be spent most preciously.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARIEL</speaker>
            <line>Is there more toil? Since thou dost give me pains,</line>
            <line>Let me remember thee what thou hast promised,</line>
            <line>Which is not yet perform'd me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>How now? moody?</line>
            <line>What is't thou canst demand?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARIEL</speaker>
            <line>My liberty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>Before the time be out? no more!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARIEL</speaker>
            <line>I prithee,</line>
            <line>Remember I have done thee worthy service;</line>
            <line>Told thee no lies, made thee no mistakings, served</line>
            <line>Without or grudge or grumblings: thou didst promise</line>
            <line>To bate me a full year.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>Dost thou forget</line>
            <line>From what a torment I did free thee?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARIEL</speaker>
            <line>No.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>Thou dost, and think'st it much to tread the ooze</line>
            <line>Of the salt deep,</line>
            <line>To run upon the sharp wind of the north,</line>
            <line>To do me business in the veins o' the earth</line>
            <line>When it is baked with frost.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARIEL</speaker>
            <line>I do not, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>Thou liest, malignant thing! Hast thou forgot</line>
            <line>The foul witch Sycorax, who with age and envy</line>
            <line>Was grown into a hoop? hast thou forgot her?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARIEL</speaker>
            <line>No, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>Thou hast. Where was she born? speak; tell me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARIEL</speaker>
            <line>Sir, in Argier.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>O, was she so? I must</line>
            <line>Once in a month recount what thou hast been,</line>
            <line>Which thou forget'st. This damn'd witch Sycorax,</line>
            <line>For mischiefs manifold and sorceries terrible</line>
            <line>To enter human hearing, from Argier,</line>
            <line>Thou know'st, was banish'd: for one thing she did</line>
            <line>They would not take her life. Is not this true?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARIEL</speaker>
            <line>Ay, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>This blue-eyed hag was hither brought with child</line>
            <line>And here was left by the sailors. Thou, my slave,</line>
            <line>As thou report'st thyself, wast then her servant;</line>
            <line>And, for thou wast a spirit too delicate</line>
            <line>To act her earthy and abhorr'd commands,</line>
            <line>Refusing her grand hests, she did confine thee,</line>
            <line>By help of her more potent ministers</line>
            <line>And in her most unmitigable rage,</line>
            <line>Into a cloven pine; within which rift</line>
            <line>Imprison'd thou didst painfully remain</line>
            <line>A dozen years; within which space she died</line>
            <line>And left thee there; where thou didst vent thy groans</line>
            <line>As fast as mill-wheels strike. Then was this island--</line>
            <line>Save for the son that she did litter here,</line>
            <line>A freckled whelp hag-born--not honour'd with</line>
            <line>A human shape.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARIEL</speaker>
            <line>Yes, Caliban her son.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>Dull thing, I say so; he, that Caliban</line>
            <line>Whom now I keep in service. Thou best know'st</line>
            <line>What torment I did find thee in; thy groans</line>
            <line>Did make wolves howl and penetrate the breasts</line>
            <line>Of ever angry bears: it was a torment</line>
            <line>To lay upon the damn'd, which Sycorax</line>
            <line>Could not again undo: it was mine art,</line>
            <line>When I arrived and heard thee, that made gape</line>
            <line>The pine and let thee out.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARIEL</speaker>
            <line>I thank thee, master.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>If thou more murmur'st, I will rend an oak</line>
            <line>And peg thee in his knotty entrails till</line>
            <line>Thou hast howl'd away twelve winters.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARIEL</speaker>
            <line>Pardon, master;</line>
            <line>I will be correspondent to command</line>
            <line>And do my spiriting gently.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>Do so, and after two days</line>
            <line>I will discharge thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARIEL</speaker>
            <line>That's my noble master!</line>
            <line>What shall I do? say what; what shall I do?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>Go make thyself like a nymph o' the sea: be subject</line>
            <line>To no sight but thine and mine, invisible</line>
            <line>To every eyeball else. Go take this shape</line>
            <line>And hither come in't: go, hence with diligence!</line>
            <stagedir>Exit ARIEL</stagedir>
            <line>Awake, dear heart, awake! thou hast slept well; Awake!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MIRANDA</speaker>
            <line>The strangeness of your story put</line>
            <line>Heaviness in me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>Shake it off. Come on;</line>
            <line>We'll visit Caliban my slave, who never</line>
            <line>Yields us kind answer.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MIRANDA</speaker>
            <line>'Tis a villain, sir,</line>
            <line>I do not love to look on.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>But, as 'tis,</line>
            <line>We cannot miss him: he does make our fire,</line>
            <line>Fetch in our wood and serves in offices</line>
            <line>That profit us. What, ho! slave! Caliban!</line>
            <line>Thou earth, thou! speak.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CALIBAN</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Within</stagedir>  There's wood enough within.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>Come forth, I say! there's other business for thee:</line>
            <line>Come, thou tortoise! when?</line>
            <stagedir>Re-enter ARIEL like a water-nymph</stagedir>
            <line>Fine apparition! My quaint Ariel,</line>
            <line>Hark in thine ear.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARIEL</speaker>
            <line>My lord it shall be done.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>Thou poisonous slave, got by the devil himself</line>
            <line>Upon thy wicked dam, come forth!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter CALIBAN</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CALIBAN</speaker>
            <line>As wicked dew as e'er my mother brush'd</line>
            <line>With raven's feather from unwholesome fen</line>
            <line>Drop on you both! a south-west blow on ye</line>
            <line>And blister you all o'er!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>For this, be sure, to-night thou shalt have cramps,</line>
            <line>Side-stitches that shall pen thy breath up; urchins</line>
            <line>Shall, for that vast of night that they may work,</line>
            <line>All exercise on thee; thou shalt be pinch'd</line>
            <line>As thick as honeycomb, each pinch more stinging</line>
            <line>Than bees that made 'em.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CALIBAN</speaker>
            <line>I must eat my dinner.</line>
            <line>This island's mine, by Sycorax my mother,</line>
            <line>Which thou takest from me. When thou camest first,</line>
            <line>Thou strokedst me and madest much of me, wouldst give me</line>
            <line>Water with berries in't, and teach me how</line>
            <line>To name the bigger light, and how the less,</line>
            <line>That burn by day and night: and then I loved thee</line>
            <line>And show'd thee all the qualities o' the isle,</line>
            <line>The fresh springs, brine-pits, barren place and fertile:</line>
            <line>Cursed be I that did so! All the charms</line>
            <line>Of Sycorax, toads, beetles, bats, light on you!</line>
            <line>For I am all the subjects that you have,</line>
            <line>Which first was mine own king: and here you sty me</line>
            <line>In this hard rock, whiles you do keep from me</line>
            <line>The rest o' the island.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>Thou most lying slave,</line>
            <line>Whom stripes may move, not kindness! I have used thee,</line>
            <line>Filth as thou art, with human care, and lodged thee</line>
            <line>In mine own cell, till thou didst seek to violate</line>
            <line>The honour of my child.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CALIBAN</speaker>
            <line>O ho, O ho! would't had been done!</line>
            <line>Thou didst prevent me; I had peopled else</line>
            <line>This isle with Calibans.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>Abhorred slave,</line>
            <line>Which any print of goodness wilt not take,</line>
            <line>Being capable of all ill! I pitied thee,</line>
            <line>Took pains to make thee speak, taught thee each hour</line>
            <line>One thing or other: when thou didst not, savage,</line>
            <line>Know thine own meaning, but wouldst gabble like</line>
            <line>A thing most brutish, I endow'd thy purposes</line>
            <line>With words that made them known. But thy vile race,</line>
            <line>Though thou didst learn, had that in't which</line>
            <line>good natures</line>
            <line>Could not abide to be with; therefore wast thou</line>
            <line>Deservedly confined into this rock,</line>
            <line>Who hadst deserved more than a prison.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CALIBAN</speaker>
            <line>You taught me language; and my profit on't</line>
            <line>Is, I know how to curse. The red plague rid you</line>
            <line>For learning me your language!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>Hag-seed, hence!</line>
            <line>Fetch us in fuel; and be quick, thou'rt best,</line>
            <line>To answer other business. Shrug'st thou, malice?</line>
            <line>If thou neglect'st or dost unwillingly</line>
            <line>What I command, I'll rack thee with old cramps,</line>
            <line>Fill all thy bones with aches, make thee roar</line>
            <line>That beasts shall tremble at thy din.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CALIBAN</speaker>
            <line>No, pray thee.</line>
            <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>
            <line>I must obey: his art is of such power,</line>
            <line>It would control my dam's god, Setebos,</line>
            <line>and make a vassal of him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>So, slave; hence!</line>
            <stagedir>Exit CALIBAN</stagedir>
            <stagedir>Re-enter ARIEL, invisible, playing and singing;
FERDINAND following</stagedir>
            <subhead>ARIEL'S song.</subhead>
            <line>Come unto these yellow sands,</line>
            <line>And then take hands:</line>
            <line>Courtsied when you have and kiss'd</line>
            <line>The wild waves whist,</line>
            <line>Foot it featly here and there;</line>
            <line>And, sweet sprites, the burthen bear.</line>
            <line>Hark, hark!</line>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Burthen (dispersedly, within) Bow-wow</stagedir>
            </line>
            <line>The watch-dogs bark!</line>
            <stagedir>Burthen Bow-wow</stagedir>
            <line>Hark, hark! I hear</line>
            <line>The strain of strutting chanticleer</line>
            <line>Cry, Cock-a-diddle-dow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>Where should this music be? i' the air or the earth?</line>
            <line>It sounds no more: and sure, it waits upon</line>
            <line>Some god o' the island. Sitting on a bank,</line>
            <line>Weeping again the king my father's wreck,</line>
            <line>This music crept by me upon the waters,</line>
            <line>Allaying both their fury and my passion</line>
            <line>With its sweet air: thence I have follow'd it,</line>
            <line>Or it hath drawn me rather. But 'tis gone.</line>
            <line>No, it begins again.</line>
            <stagedir>ARIEL sings</stagedir>
            <line>Full fathom five thy father lies;</line>
            <line>Of his bones are coral made;</line>
            <line>Those are pearls that were his eyes:</line>
            <line>Nothing of him that doth fade</line>
            <line>But doth suffer a sea-change</line>
            <line>Into something rich and strange.</line>
            <line>Sea-nymphs hourly ring his knell</line>
            <stagedir>Burthen Ding-dong</stagedir>
            <line>Hark! now I hear them,--Ding-dong, bell.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>The ditty does remember my drown'd father.</line>
            <line>This is no mortal business, nor no sound</line>
            <line>That the earth owes. I hear it now above me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>The fringed curtains of thine eye advance</line>
            <line>And say what thou seest yond.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MIRANDA</speaker>
            <line>What is't? a spirit?</line>
            <line>Lord, how it looks about! Believe me, sir,</line>
            <line>It carries a brave form. But 'tis a spirit.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>No, wench; it eats and sleeps and hath such senses</line>
            <line>As we have, such. This gallant which thou seest</line>
            <line>Was in the wreck; and, but he's something stain'd</line>
            <line>With grief that's beauty's canker, thou mightst call him</line>
            <line>A goodly person: he hath lost his fellows</line>
            <line>And strays about to find 'em.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MIRANDA</speaker>
            <line>I might call him</line>
            <line>A thing divine, for nothing natural</line>
            <line>I ever saw so noble.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir> It goes on, I see,</line>
            <line>As my soul prompts it. Spirit, fine spirit! I'll free thee</line>
            <line>Within two days for this.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>Most sure, the goddess</line>
            <line>On whom these airs attend! Vouchsafe my prayer</line>
            <line>May know if you remain upon this island;</line>
            <line>And that you will some good instruction give</line>
            <line>How I may bear me here: my prime request,</line>
            <line>Which I do last pronounce, is, O you wonder!</line>
            <line>If you be maid or no?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MIRANDA</speaker>
            <line>No wonder, sir;</line>
            <line>But certainly a maid.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>My language! heavens!</line>
            <line>I am the best of them that speak this speech,</line>
            <line>Were I but where 'tis spoken.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>How? the best?</line>
            <line>What wert thou, if the King of Naples heard thee?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>A single thing, as I am now, that wonders</line>
            <line>To hear thee speak of Naples. He does hear me;</line>
            <line>And that he does I weep: myself am Naples,</line>
            <line>Who with mine eyes, never since at ebb, beheld</line>
            <line>The king my father wreck'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MIRANDA</speaker>
            <line>Alack, for mercy!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>Yes, faith, and all his lords; the Duke of Milan</line>
            <line>And his brave son being twain.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir> The Duke of Milan</line>
            <line>And his more braver daughter could control thee,</line>
            <line>If now 'twere fit to do't. At the first sight</line>
            <line>They have changed eyes. Delicate Ariel,</line>
            <line>I'll set thee free for this.</line>
            <stagedir>To FERDINAND</stagedir>
            <line>A word, good sir;</line>
            <line>I fear you have done yourself some wrong: a word.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MIRANDA</speaker>
            <line>Why speaks my father so ungently? This</line>
            <line>Is the third man that e'er I saw, the first</line>
            <line>That e'er I sigh'd for: pity move my father</line>
            <line>To be inclined my way!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>O, if a virgin,</line>
            <line>And your affection not gone forth, I'll make you</line>
            <line>The queen of Naples.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>Soft, sir! one word more.</line>
            <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>
            <line>They are both in either's powers; but this swift business</line>
            <line>I must uneasy make, lest too light winning</line>
            <line>Make the prize light.</line>
            <stagedir>To FERDINAND</stagedir>
            <line>One word more; I charge thee</line>
            <line>That thou attend me: thou dost here usurp</line>
            <line>The name thou owest not; and hast put thyself</line>
            <line>Upon this island as a spy, to win it</line>
            <line>From me, the lord on't.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>No, as I am a man.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MIRANDA</speaker>
            <line>There's nothing ill can dwell in such a temple:</line>
            <line>If the ill spirit have so fair a house,</line>
            <line>Good things will strive to dwell with't.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>Follow me.</line>
            <line>Speak not you for him; he's a traitor. Come;</line>
            <line>I'll manacle thy neck and feet together:</line>
            <line>Sea-water shalt thou drink; thy food shall be</line>
            <line>The fresh-brook muscles, wither'd roots and husks</line>
            <line>Wherein the acorn cradled. Follow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>No;</line>
            <line>I will resist such entertainment till</line>
            <line>Mine enemy has more power.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Draws, and is charmed from moving</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MIRANDA</speaker>
            <line>O dear father,</line>
            <line>Make not too rash a trial of him, for</line>
            <line>He's gentle and not fearful.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>What? I say,</line>
            <line>My foot my tutor? Put thy sword up, traitor;</line>
            <line>Who makest a show but darest not strike, thy conscience</line>
            <line>Is so possess'd with guilt: come from thy ward,</line>
            <line>For I can here disarm thee with this stick</line>
            <line>And make thy weapon drop.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MIRANDA</speaker>
            <line>Beseech you, father.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>Hence! hang not on my garments.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MIRANDA</speaker>
            <line>Sir, have pity;</line>
            <line>I'll be his surety.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>Silence! one word more</line>
            <line>Shall make me chide thee, if not hate thee. What!</line>
            <line>An advocate for an imposter! hush!</line>
            <line>Thou think'st there is no more such shapes as he,</line>
            <line>Having seen but him and Caliban: foolish wench!</line>
            <line>To the most of men this is a Caliban</line>
            <line>And they to him are angels.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MIRANDA</speaker>
            <line>My affections</line>
            <line>Are then most humble; I have no ambition</line>
            <line>To see a goodlier man.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>Come on; obey:</line>
            <line>Thy nerves are in their infancy again</line>
            <line>And have no vigour in them.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>So they are;</line>
            <line>My spirits, as in a dream, are all bound up.</line>
            <line>My father's loss, the weakness which I feel,</line>
            <line>The wreck of all my friends, nor this man's threats,</line>
            <line>To whom I am subdued, are but light to me,</line>
            <line>Might I but through my prison once a day</line>
            <line>Behold this maid: all corners else o' the earth</line>
            <line>Let liberty make use of; space enough</line>
            <line>Have I in such a prison.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>                It works.</line>
            <stagedir>To FERDINAND</stagedir>
            <line>Come on.</line>
            <line>Thou hast done well, fine Ariel!</line>
            <stagedir>To FERDINAND</stagedir>
            <line>Follow me.</line>
            <stagedir>To ARIEL</stagedir>
            <line>Hark what thou else shalt do me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MIRANDA</speaker>
            <line>Be of comfort;</line>
            <line>My father's of a better nature, sir,</line>
            <line>Than he appears by speech: this is unwonted</line>
            <line>Which now came from him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>Thou shalt be free</line>
            <line>As mountain winds: but then exactly do</line>
            <line>All points of my command.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARIEL</speaker>
            <line>To the syllable.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>Come, follow. Speak not for him.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>