<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net/doctypes/dita/shakespear/dtd/act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-3">
   <title>ACT III</title>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  Before PROSPERO'S Cell.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter FERDINAND, bearing a log</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>There be some sports are painful, and their labour</line>
            <line>Delight in them sets off: some kinds of baseness</line>
            <line>Are nobly undergone and most poor matters</line>
            <line>Point to rich ends. This my mean task</line>
            <line>Would be as heavy to me as odious, but</line>
            <line>The mistress which I serve quickens what's dead</line>
            <line>And makes my labours pleasures: O, she is</line>
            <line>Ten times more gentle than her father's crabbed,</line>
            <line>And he's composed of harshness. I must remove</line>
            <line>Some thousands of these logs and pile them up,</line>
            <line>Upon a sore injunction: my sweet mistress</line>
            <line>Weeps when she sees me work, and says, such baseness</line>
            <line>Had never like executor. I forget:</line>
            <line>But these sweet thoughts do even refresh my labours,</line>
            <line>Most busy lest, when I do it.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter MIRANDA; and PROSPERO at a distance, unseen</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MIRANDA</speaker>
            <line>Alas, now, pray you,</line>
            <line>Work not so hard: I would the lightning had</line>
            <line>Burnt up those logs that you are enjoin'd to pile!</line>
            <line>Pray, set it down and rest you: when this burns,</line>
            <line>'Twill weep for having wearied you. My father</line>
            <line>Is hard at study; pray now, rest yourself;</line>
            <line>He's safe for these three hours.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>O most dear mistress,</line>
            <line>The sun will set before I shall discharge</line>
            <line>What I must strive to do.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MIRANDA</speaker>
            <line>If you'll sit down,</line>
            <line>I'll bear your logs the while: pray, give me that;</line>
            <line>I'll carry it to the pile.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>No, precious creature;</line>
            <line>I had rather crack my sinews, break my back,</line>
            <line>Than you should such dishonour undergo,</line>
            <line>While I sit lazy by.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MIRANDA</speaker>
            <line>It would become me</line>
            <line>As well as it does you: and I should do it</line>
            <line>With much more ease; for my good will is to it,</line>
            <line>And yours it is against.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>Poor worm, thou art infected!</line>
            <line>This visitation shows it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MIRANDA</speaker>
            <line>You look wearily.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>No, noble mistress;'tis fresh morning with me</line>
            <line>When you are by at night. I do beseech you--</line>
            <line>Chiefly that I might set it in my prayers--</line>
            <line>What is your name?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MIRANDA</speaker>
            <line>Miranda.--O my father,</line>
            <line>I have broke your hest to say so!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>Admired Miranda!</line>
            <line>Indeed the top of admiration! worth</line>
            <line>What's dearest to the world! Full many a lady</line>
            <line>I have eyed with best regard and many a time</line>
            <line>The harmony of their tongues hath into bondage</line>
            <line>Brought my too diligent ear: for several virtues</line>
            <line>Have I liked several women; never any</line>
            <line>With so fun soul, but some defect in her</line>
            <line>Did quarrel with the noblest grace she owed</line>
            <line>And put it to the foil: but you, O you,</line>
            <line>So perfect and so peerless, are created</line>
            <line>Of every creature's best!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MIRANDA</speaker>
            <line>I do not know</line>
            <line>One of my sex; no woman's face remember,</line>
            <line>Save, from my glass, mine own; nor have I seen</line>
            <line>More that I may call men than you, good friend,</line>
            <line>And my dear father: how features are abroad,</line>
            <line>I am skilless of; but, by my modesty,</line>
            <line>The jewel in my dower, I would not wish</line>
            <line>Any companion in the world but you,</line>
            <line>Nor can imagination form a shape,</line>
            <line>Besides yourself, to like of. But I prattle</line>
            <line>Something too wildly and my father's precepts</line>
            <line>I therein do forget.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>I am in my condition</line>
            <line>A prince, Miranda; I do think, a king;</line>
            <line>I would, not so!--and would no more endure</line>
            <line>This wooden slavery than to suffer</line>
            <line>The flesh-fly blow my mouth. Hear my soul speak:</line>
            <line>The very instant that I saw you, did</line>
            <line>My heart fly to your service; there resides,</line>
            <line>To make me slave to it; and for your sake</line>
            <line>Am I this patient log--man.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MIRANDA</speaker>
            <line>Do you love me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>O heaven, O earth, bear witness to this sound</line>
            <line>And crown what I profess with kind event</line>
            <line>If I speak true! if hollowly, invert</line>
            <line>What best is boded me to mischief! I</line>
            <line>Beyond all limit of what else i' the world</line>
            <line>Do love, prize, honour you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MIRANDA</speaker>
            <line>I am a fool</line>
            <line>To weep at what I am glad of.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>Fair encounter</line>
            <line>Of two most rare affections! Heavens rain grace</line>
            <line>On that which breeds between 'em!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>Wherefore weep you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MIRANDA</speaker>
            <line>At mine unworthiness that dare not offer</line>
            <line>What I desire to give, and much less take</line>
            <line>What I shall die to want. But this is trifling;</line>
            <line>And all the more it seeks to hide itself,</line>
            <line>The bigger bulk it shows. Hence, bashful cunning!</line>
            <line>And prompt me, plain and holy innocence!</line>
            <line>I am your wife, it you will marry me;</line>
            <line>If not, I'll die your maid: to be your fellow</line>
            <line>You may deny me; but I'll be your servant,</line>
            <line>Whether you will or no.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>My mistress, dearest;</line>
            <line>And I thus humble ever.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MIRANDA</speaker>
            <line>My husband, then?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>Ay, with a heart as willing</line>
            <line>As bondage e'er of freedom: here's my hand.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MIRANDA</speaker>
            <line>And mine, with my heart in't; and now farewell</line>
            <line>Till half an hour hence.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>A thousand thousand!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt FERDINAND and MIRANDA severally</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>So glad of this as they I cannot be,</line>
            <line>Who are surprised withal; but my rejoicing</line>
            <line>At nothing can be more. I'll to my book,</line>
            <line>For yet ere supper-time must I perform</line>
            <line>Much business appertaining.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  Another part of the island.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter CALIBAN, STEPHANO, and TRINCULO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>STEPHANO</speaker>
            <line>Tell not me; when the butt is out, we will drink</line>
            <line>water; not a drop before: therefore bear up, and</line>
            <line>board 'em. Servant-monster, drink to me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRINCULO</speaker>
            <line>Servant-monster! the folly of this island! They</line>
            <line>say there's but five upon this isle: we are three</line>
            <line>of them; if th' other two be brained like us, the</line>
            <line>state totters.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>STEPHANO</speaker>
            <line>Drink, servant-monster, when I bid thee: thy eyes</line>
            <line>are almost set in thy head.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRINCULO</speaker>
            <line>Where should they be set else? he were a brave</line>
            <line>monster indeed, if they were set in his tail.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>STEPHANO</speaker>
            <line>My man-monster hath drown'd his tongue in sack:</line>
            <line>for my part, the sea cannot drown me; I swam, ere I</line>
            <line>could recover the shore, five and thirty leagues off</line>
            <line>and on. By this light, thou shalt be my lieutenant,</line>
            <line>monster, or my standard.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRINCULO</speaker>
            <line>Your lieutenant, if you list; he's no standard.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>STEPHANO</speaker>
            <line>We'll not run, Monsieur Monster.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRINCULO</speaker>
            <line>Nor go neither; but you'll lie like dogs and yet say</line>
            <line>nothing neither.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>STEPHANO</speaker>
            <line>Moon-calf, speak once in thy life, if thou beest a</line>
            <line>good moon-calf.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CALIBAN</speaker>
            <line>How does thy honour? Let me lick thy shoe.</line>
            <line>I'll not serve him; he's not valiant.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRINCULO</speaker>
            <line>Thou liest, most ignorant monster: I am in case to</line>
            <line>justle a constable. Why, thou deboshed fish thou,</line>
            <line>was there ever man a coward that hath drunk so much</line>
            <line>sack as I to-day? Wilt thou tell a monstrous lie,</line>
            <line>being but half a fish and half a monster?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CALIBAN</speaker>
            <line>Lo, how he mocks me! wilt thou let him, my lord?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRINCULO</speaker>
            <line>'Lord' quoth he! That a monster should be such a natural!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CALIBAN</speaker>
            <line>Lo, lo, again! bite him to death, I prithee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>STEPHANO</speaker>
            <line>Trinculo, keep a good tongue in your head: if you</line>
            <line>prove a mutineer,--the next tree! The poor monster's</line>
            <line>my subject and he shall not suffer indignity.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CALIBAN</speaker>
            <line>I thank my noble lord. Wilt thou be pleased to</line>
            <line>hearken once again to the suit I made to thee?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>STEPHANO</speaker>
            <line>Marry, will I kneel and repeat it; I will stand,</line>
            <line>and so shall Trinculo.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter ARIEL, invisible</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CALIBAN</speaker>
            <line>As I told thee before, I am subject to a tyrant, a</line>
            <line>sorcerer, that by his cunning hath cheated me of the island.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARIEL</speaker>
            <line>Thou liest.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CALIBAN</speaker>
            <line>Thou liest, thou jesting monkey, thou: I would my</line>
            <line>valiant master would destroy thee! I do not lie.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>STEPHANO</speaker>
            <line>Trinculo, if you trouble him any more in's tale, by</line>
            <line>this hand, I will supplant some of your teeth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRINCULO</speaker>
            <line>Why, I said nothing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>STEPHANO</speaker>
            <line>Mum, then, and no more. Proceed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CALIBAN</speaker>
            <line>I say, by sorcery he got this isle;</line>
            <line>From me he got it. if thy greatness will</line>
            <line>Revenge it on him,--for I know thou darest,</line>
            <line>But this thing dare not,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>STEPHANO</speaker>
            <line>That's most certain.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CALIBAN</speaker>
            <line>Thou shalt be lord of it and I'll serve thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>STEPHANO</speaker>
            <line>How now shall this be compassed?</line>
            <line>Canst thou bring me to the party?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CALIBAN</speaker>
            <line>Yea, yea, my lord: I'll yield him thee asleep,</line>
            <line>Where thou mayst knock a nail into his bead.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARIEL</speaker>
            <line>Thou liest; thou canst not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CALIBAN</speaker>
            <line>What a pied ninny's this! Thou scurvy patch!</line>
            <line>I do beseech thy greatness, give him blows</line>
            <line>And take his bottle from him: when that's gone</line>
            <line>He shall drink nought but brine; for I'll not show him</line>
            <line>Where the quick freshes are.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>STEPHANO</speaker>
            <line>Trinculo, run into no further danger:</line>
            <line>interrupt the monster one word further, and,</line>
            <line>by this hand, I'll turn my mercy out o' doors</line>
            <line>and make a stock-fish of thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRINCULO</speaker>
            <line>Why, what did I? I did nothing. I'll go farther</line>
            <line>off.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>STEPHANO</speaker>
            <line>Didst thou not say he lied?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARIEL</speaker>
            <line>Thou liest.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>STEPHANO</speaker>
            <line>Do I so? take thou that.</line>
            <stagedir>Beats TRINCULO</stagedir>
            <line>As you like this, give me the lie another time.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRINCULO</speaker>
            <line>I did not give the lie. Out o' your</line>
            <line>wits and bearing too? A pox o' your bottle!</line>
            <line>this can sack and drinking do. A murrain on</line>
            <line>your monster, and the devil take your fingers!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CALIBAN</speaker>
            <line>Ha, ha, ha!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>STEPHANO</speaker>
            <line>Now, forward with your tale. Prithee, stand farther</line>
            <line>off.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CALIBAN</speaker>
            <line>Beat him enough: after a little time</line>
            <line>I'll beat him too.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>STEPHANO</speaker>
            <line>Stand farther. Come, proceed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CALIBAN</speaker>
            <line>Why, as I told thee, 'tis a custom with him,</line>
            <line>I' th' afternoon to sleep: there thou mayst brain him,</line>
            <line>Having first seized his books, or with a log</line>
            <line>Batter his skull, or paunch him with a stake,</line>
            <line>Or cut his wezand with thy knife. Remember</line>
            <line>First to possess his books; for without them</line>
            <line>He's but a sot, as I am, nor hath not</line>
            <line>One spirit to command: they all do hate him</line>
            <line>As rootedly as I. Burn but his books.</line>
            <line>He has brave utensils,--for so he calls them--</line>
            <line>Which when he has a house, he'll deck withal</line>
            <line>And that most deeply to consider is</line>
            <line>The beauty of his daughter; he himself</line>
            <line>Calls her a nonpareil: I never saw a woman,</line>
            <line>But only Sycorax my dam and she;</line>
            <line>But she as far surpasseth Sycorax</line>
            <line>As great'st does least.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>STEPHANO</speaker>
            <line>Is it so brave a lass?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CALIBAN</speaker>
            <line>Ay, lord; she will become thy bed, I warrant.</line>
            <line>And bring thee forth brave brood.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>STEPHANO</speaker>
            <line>Monster, I will kill this man: his daughter and I</line>
            <line>will be king and queen--save our graces!--and</line>
            <line>Trinculo and thyself shall be viceroys. Dost thou</line>
            <line>like the plot, Trinculo?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRINCULO</speaker>
            <line>Excellent.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>STEPHANO</speaker>
            <line>Give me thy hand: I am sorry I beat thee; but,</line>
            <line>while thou livest, keep a good tongue in thy head.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CALIBAN</speaker>
            <line>Within this half hour will he be asleep:</line>
            <line>Wilt thou destroy him then?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>STEPHANO</speaker>
            <line>Ay, on mine honour.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARIEL</speaker>
            <line>This will I tell my master.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CALIBAN</speaker>
            <line>Thou makest me merry; I am full of pleasure:</line>
            <line>Let us be jocund: will you troll the catch</line>
            <line>You taught me but while-ere?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>STEPHANO</speaker>
            <line>At thy request, monster, I will do reason, any</line>
            <line>reason. Come on, Trinculo, let us sing.</line>
            <stagedir>Sings</stagedir>
            <line>Flout 'em and scout 'em</line>
            <line>And scout 'em and flout 'em</line>
            <line>Thought is free.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CALIBAN</speaker>
            <line>That's not the tune.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Ariel plays the tune on a tabour and pipe</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>STEPHANO</speaker>
            <line>What is this same?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRINCULO</speaker>
            <line>This is the tune of our catch, played by the picture</line>
            <line>of Nobody.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>STEPHANO</speaker>
            <line>If thou beest a man, show thyself in thy likeness:</line>
            <line>if thou beest a devil, take't as thou list.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRINCULO</speaker>
            <line>O, forgive me my sins!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>STEPHANO</speaker>
            <line>He that dies pays all debts: I defy thee. Mercy upon us!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CALIBAN</speaker>
            <line>Art thou afeard?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>STEPHANO</speaker>
            <line>No, monster, not I.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CALIBAN</speaker>
            <line>Be not afeard; the isle is full of noises,</line>
            <line>Sounds and sweet airs, that give delight and hurt not.</line>
            <line>Sometimes a thousand twangling instruments</line>
            <line>Will hum about mine ears, and sometime voices</line>
            <line>That, if I then had waked after long sleep,</line>
            <line>Will make me sleep again: and then, in dreaming,</line>
            <line>The clouds methought would open and show riches</line>
            <line>Ready to drop upon me that, when I waked,</line>
            <line>I cried to dream again.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>STEPHANO</speaker>
            <line>This will prove a brave kingdom to me, where I shall</line>
            <line>have my music for nothing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CALIBAN</speaker>
            <line>When Prospero is destroyed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>STEPHANO</speaker>
            <line>That shall be by and by: I remember the story.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRINCULO</speaker>
            <line>The sound is going away; let's follow it, and</line>
            <line>after do our work.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>STEPHANO</speaker>
            <line>Lead, monster; we'll follow. I would I could see</line>
            <line>this tabourer; he lays it on.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRINCULO</speaker>
            <line>Wilt come? I'll follow, Stephano.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  Another part of the island.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter ALONSO, SEBASTIAN, ANTONIO, GONZALO,
ADRIAN, FRANCISCO, and others</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GONZALO</speaker>
            <line>By'r lakin, I can go no further, sir;</line>
            <line>My old bones ache: here's a maze trod indeed</line>
            <line>Through forth-rights and meanders! By your patience,</line>
            <line>I needs must rest me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALONSO</speaker>
            <line>Old lord, I cannot blame thee,</line>
            <line>Who am myself attach'd with weariness,</line>
            <line>To the dulling of my spirits: sit down, and rest.</line>
            <line>Even here I will put off my hope and keep it</line>
            <line>No longer for my flatterer: he is drown'd</line>
            <line>Whom thus we stray to find, and the sea mocks</line>
            <line>Our frustrate search on land. Well, let him go.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside to SEBASTIAN</stagedir>  I am right glad that he's so</line>
            <line>out of hope.</line>
            <line>Do not, for one repulse, forego the purpose</line>
            <line>That you resolved to effect.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SEBASTIAN</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside to ANTONIO</stagedir>  The next advantage</line>
            <line>Will we take throughly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside to SEBASTIAN</stagedir>  Let it be to-night;</line>
            <line>For, now they are oppress'd with travel, they</line>
            <line>Will not, nor cannot, use such vigilance</line>
            <line>As when they are fresh.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SEBASTIAN</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside to ANTONIO</stagedir>  I say, to-night: no more.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Solemn and strange music</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALONSO</speaker>
            <line>What harmony is this? My good friends, hark!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GONZALO</speaker>
            <line>Marvellous sweet music!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter PROSPERO above, invisible. Enter several
strange Shapes, bringing in a banquet;
they dance about it with gentle actions of
salutation; and, inviting the King, &amp;c. to
eat, they depart</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALONSO</speaker>
            <line>Give us kind keepers, heavens! What were these?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SEBASTIAN</speaker>
            <line>A living drollery. Now I will believe</line>
            <line>That there are unicorns, that in Arabia</line>
            <line>There is one tree, the phoenix' throne, one phoenix</line>
            <line>At this hour reigning there.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>I'll believe both;</line>
            <line>And what does else want credit, come to me,</line>
            <line>And I'll be sworn 'tis true: travellers ne'er did</line>
            <line>lie,</line>
            <line>Though fools at home condemn 'em.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GONZALO</speaker>
            <line>If in Naples</line>
            <line>I should report this now, would they believe me?</line>
            <line>If I should say, I saw such islanders--</line>
            <line>For, certes, these are people of the island--</line>
            <line>Who, though they are of monstrous shape, yet, note,</line>
            <line>Their manners are more gentle-kind than of</line>
            <line>Our human generation you shall find</line>
            <line>Many, nay, almost any.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>              Honest lord,</line>
            <line>Thou hast said well; for some of you there present</line>
            <line>Are worse than devils.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALONSO</speaker>
            <line>I cannot too much muse</line>
            <line>Such shapes, such gesture and such sound, expressing,</line>
            <line>Although they want the use of tongue, a kind</line>
            <line>Of excellent dumb discourse.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir> Praise in departing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FRANCISCO</speaker>
            <line>They vanish'd strangely.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SEBASTIAN</speaker>
            <line>No matter, since</line>
            <line>They have left their viands behind; for we have stomachs.</line>
            <line>Will't please you taste of what is here?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALONSO</speaker>
            <line>Not I.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GONZALO</speaker>
            <line>Faith, sir, you need not fear. When we were boys,</line>
            <line>Who would believe that there were mountaineers</line>
            <line>Dew-lapp'd like bulls, whose throats had hanging at 'em</line>
            <line>Wallets of flesh? or that there were such men</line>
            <line>Whose heads stood in their breasts? which now we find</line>
            <line>Each putter-out of five for one will bring us</line>
            <line>Good warrant of.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALONSO</speaker>
            <line>I will stand to and feed,</line>
            <line>Although my last: no matter, since I feel</line>
            <line>The best is past. Brother, my lord the duke,</line>
            <line>Stand to and do as we.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Thunder and lightning. Enter ARIEL, like a
harpy; claps his wings upon the table; and,
with a quaint device, the banquet vanishes</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARIEL</speaker>
            <line>You are three men of sin, whom Destiny,</line>
            <line>That hath to instrument this lower world</line>
            <line>And what is in't, the never-surfeited sea</line>
            <line>Hath caused to belch up you; and on this island</line>
            <line>Where man doth not inhabit; you 'mongst men</line>
            <line>Being most unfit to live. I have made you mad;</line>
            <line>And even with such-like valour men hang and drown</line>
            <line>Their proper selves.</line>
            <stagedir>ALONSO, SEBASTIAN &amp;c. draw their swords</stagedir>
            <line>You fools! I and my fellows</line>
            <line>Are ministers of Fate: the elements,</line>
            <line>Of whom your swords are temper'd, may as well</line>
            <line>Wound the loud winds, or with bemock'd-at stabs</line>
            <line>Kill the still-closing waters, as diminish</line>
            <line>One dowle that's in my plume: my fellow-ministers</line>
            <line>Are like invulnerable. If you could hurt,</line>
            <line>Your swords are now too massy for your strengths</line>
            <line>And will not be uplifted. But remember--</line>
            <line>For that's my business to you--that you three</line>
            <line>From Milan did supplant good Prospero;</line>
            <line>Exposed unto the sea, which hath requit it,</line>
            <line>Him and his innocent child: for which foul deed</line>
            <line>The powers, delaying, not forgetting, have</line>
            <line>Incensed the seas and shores, yea, all the creatures,</line>
            <line>Against your peace. Thee of thy son, Alonso,</line>
            <line>They have bereft; and do pronounce by me:</line>
            <line>Lingering perdition, worse than any death</line>
            <line>Can be at once, shall step by step attend</line>
            <line>You and your ways; whose wraths to guard you from--</line>
            <line>Which here, in this most desolate isle, else falls</line>
            <line>Upon your heads--is nothing but heart-sorrow</line>
            <line>And a clear life ensuing.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>He vanishes in thunder; then, to soft music
enter the Shapes again, and dance, with
mocks and mows, and carrying out the table</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>Bravely the figure of this harpy hast thou</line>
            <line>Perform'd, my Ariel; a grace it had, devouring:</line>
            <line>Of my instruction hast thou nothing bated</line>
            <line>In what thou hadst to say: so, with good life</line>
            <line>And observation strange, my meaner ministers</line>
            <line>Their several kinds have done. My high charms work</line>
            <line>And these mine enemies are all knit up</line>
            <line>In their distractions; they now are in my power;</line>
            <line>And in these fits I leave them, while I visit</line>
            <line>Young Ferdinand, whom they suppose is drown'd,</line>
            <line>And his and mine loved darling.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit above</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GONZALO</speaker>
            <line>I' the name of something holy, sir, why stand you</line>
            <line>In this strange stare?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALONSO</speaker>
            <line>O, it is monstrous, monstrous:</line>
            <line>Methought the billows spoke and told me of it;</line>
            <line>The winds did sing it to me, and the thunder,</line>
            <line>That deep and dreadful organ-pipe, pronounced</line>
            <line>The name of Prosper: it did bass my trespass.</line>
            <line>Therefore my son i' the ooze is bedded, and</line>
            <line>I'll seek him deeper than e'er plummet sounded</line>
            <line>And with him there lie mudded.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SEBASTIAN</speaker>
            <line>But one fiend at a time,</line>
            <line>I'll fight their legions o'er.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>I'll be thy second.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt SEBASTIAN, and ANTONIO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GONZALO</speaker>
            <line>All three of them are desperate: their great guilt,</line>
            <line>Like poison given to work a great time after,</line>
            <line>Now 'gins to bite the spirits. I do beseech you</line>
            <line>That are of suppler joints, follow them swiftly</line>
            <line>And hinder them from what this ecstasy</line>
            <line>May now provoke them to.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ADRIAN</speaker>
            <line>Follow, I pray you.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>