<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net/doctypes/dita/shakespear/dtd/act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-5">
   <title>ACT V</title>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  Before PROSPERO'S cell.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter PROSPERO in his magic robes, and ARIEL</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>Now does my project gather to a head:</line>
            <line>My charms crack not; my spirits obey; and time</line>
            <line>Goes upright with his carriage. How's the day?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARIEL</speaker>
            <line>On the sixth hour; at which time, my lord,</line>
            <line>You said our work should cease.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>I did say so,</line>
            <line>When first I raised the tempest. Say, my spirit,</line>
            <line>How fares the king and's followers?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARIEL</speaker>
            <line>Confined together</line>
            <line>In the same fashion as you gave in charge,</line>
            <line>Just as you left them; all prisoners, sir,</line>
            <line>In the line-grove which weather-fends your cell;</line>
            <line>They cannot budge till your release. The king,</line>
            <line>His brother and yours, abide all three distracted</line>
            <line>And the remainder mourning over them,</line>
            <line>Brimful of sorrow and dismay; but chiefly</line>
            <line>Him that you term'd, sir, 'The good old lord Gonzalo;'</line>
            <line>His tears run down his beard, like winter's drops</line>
            <line>From eaves of reeds. Your charm so strongly works 'em</line>
            <line>That if you now beheld them, your affections</line>
            <line>Would become tender.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>Dost thou think so, spirit?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARIEL</speaker>
            <line>Mine would, sir, were I human.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>And mine shall.</line>
            <line>Hast thou, which art but air, a touch, a feeling</line>
            <line>Of their afflictions, and shall not myself,</line>
            <line>One of their kind, that relish all as sharply,</line>
            <line>Passion as they, be kindlier moved than thou art?</line>
            <line>Though with their high wrongs I am struck to the quick,</line>
            <line>Yet with my nobler reason 'gaitist my fury</line>
            <line>Do I take part: the rarer action is</line>
            <line>In virtue than in vengeance: they being penitent,</line>
            <line>The sole drift of my purpose doth extend</line>
            <line>Not a frown further. Go release them, Ariel:</line>
            <line>My charms I'll break, their senses I'll restore,</line>
            <line>And they shall be themselves.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARIEL</speaker>
            <line>I'll fetch them, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>Ye elves of hills, brooks, standing lakes and groves,</line>
            <line>And ye that on the sands with printless foot</line>
            <line>Do chase the ebbing Neptune and do fly him</line>
            <line>When he comes back; you demi-puppets that</line>
            <line>By moonshine do the green sour ringlets make,</line>
            <line>Whereof the ewe not bites, and you whose pastime</line>
            <line>Is to make midnight mushrooms, that rejoice</line>
            <line>To hear the solemn curfew; by whose aid,</line>
            <line>Weak masters though ye be, I have bedimm'd</line>
            <line>The noontide sun, call'd forth the mutinous winds,</line>
            <line>And 'twixt the green sea and the azured vault</line>
            <line>Set roaring war: to the dread rattling thunder</line>
            <line>Have I given fire and rifted Jove's stout oak</line>
            <line>With his own bolt; the strong-based promontory</line>
            <line>Have I made shake and by the spurs pluck'd up</line>
            <line>The pine and cedar: graves at my command</line>
            <line>Have waked their sleepers, oped, and let 'em forth</line>
            <line>By my so potent art. But this rough magic</line>
            <line>I here abjure, and, when I have required</line>
            <line>Some heavenly music, which even now I do,</line>
            <line>To work mine end upon their senses that</line>
            <line>This airy charm is for, I'll break my staff,</line>
            <line>Bury it certain fathoms in the earth,</line>
            <line>And deeper than did ever plummet sound</line>
            <line>I'll drown my book.</line>
            <stagedir>Solemn music</stagedir>
            <stagedir>Re-enter ARIEL before: then ALONSO, with a
frantic gesture, attended by GONZALO;
SEBASTIAN and ANTONIO in like manner,
attended by ADRIAN and FRANCISCO   they all
enter the circle which PROSPERO had made,
and there stand charmed; which PROSPERO
observing, speaks:</stagedir>
            <line>A solemn air and the best comforter</line>
            <line>To an unsettled fancy cure thy brains,</line>
            <line>Now useless, boil'd within thy skull! There stand,</line>
            <line>For you are spell-stopp'd.</line>
            <line>Holy Gonzalo, honourable man,</line>
            <line>Mine eyes, even sociable to the show of thine,</line>
            <line>Fall fellowly drops. The charm dissolves apace,</line>
            <line>And as the morning steals upon the night,</line>
            <line>Melting the darkness, so their rising senses</line>
            <line>Begin to chase the ignorant fumes that mantle</line>
            <line>Their clearer reason. O good Gonzalo,</line>
            <line>My true preserver, and a loyal sir</line>
            <line>To him you follow'st! I will pay thy graces</line>
            <line>Home both in word and deed. Most cruelly</line>
            <line>Didst thou, Alonso, use me and my daughter:</line>
            <line>Thy brother was a furtherer in the act.</line>
            <line>Thou art pinch'd fort now, Sebastian. Flesh and blood,</line>
            <line>You, brother mine, that entertain'd ambition,</line>
            <line>Expell'd remorse and nature; who, with Sebastian,</line>
            <line>Whose inward pinches therefore are most strong,</line>
            <line>Would here have kill'd your king; I do forgive thee,</line>
            <line>Unnatural though thou art. Their understanding</line>
            <line>Begins to swell, and the approaching tide</line>
            <line>Will shortly fill the reasonable shore</line>
            <line>That now lies foul and muddy. Not one of them</line>
            <line>That yet looks on me, or would know me Ariel,</line>
            <line>Fetch me the hat and rapier in my cell:</line>
            <line>I will discase me, and myself present</line>
            <line>As I was sometime Milan: quickly, spirit;</line>
            <line>Thou shalt ere long be free.</line>
            <stagedir>ARIEL sings and helps to attire him</stagedir>
            <line>Where the bee sucks. there suck I:</line>
            <line>In a cowslip's bell I lie;</line>
            <line>There I couch when owls do cry.</line>
            <line>On the bat's back I do fly</line>
            <line>After summer merrily.</line>
            <line>Merrily, merrily shall I live now</line>
            <line>Under the blossom that hangs on the bough.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>Why, that's my dainty Ariel! I shall miss thee:</line>
            <line>But yet thou shalt have freedom: so, so, so.</line>
            <line>To the king's ship, invisible as thou art:</line>
            <line>There shalt thou find the mariners asleep</line>
            <line>Under the hatches; the master and the boatswain</line>
            <line>Being awake, enforce them to this place,</line>
            <line>And presently, I prithee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARIEL</speaker>
            <line>I drink the air before me, and return</line>
            <line>Or ere your pulse twice beat.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GONZALO</speaker>
            <line>All torment, trouble, wonder and amazement</line>
            <line>Inhabits here: some heavenly power guide us</line>
            <line>Out of this fearful country!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>Behold, sir king,</line>
            <line>The wronged Duke of Milan, Prospero:</line>
            <line>For more assurance that a living prince</line>
            <line>Does now speak to thee, I embrace thy body;</line>
            <line>And to thee and thy company I bid</line>
            <line>A hearty welcome.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALONSO</speaker>
            <line>Whether thou best he or no,</line>
            <line>Or some enchanted trifle to abuse me,</line>
            <line>As late I have been, I not know: thy pulse</line>
            <line>Beats as of flesh and blood; and, since I saw thee,</line>
            <line>The affliction of my mind amends, with which,</line>
            <line>I fear, a madness held me: this must crave,</line>
            <line>An if this be at all, a most strange story.</line>
            <line>Thy dukedom I resign and do entreat</line>
            <line>Thou pardon me my wrongs. But how should Prospero</line>
            <line>Be living and be here?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>First, noble friend,</line>
            <line>Let me embrace thine age, whose honour cannot</line>
            <line>Be measured or confined.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GONZALO</speaker>
            <line>Whether this be</line>
            <line>Or be not, I'll not swear.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>You do yet taste</line>
            <line>Some subtilties o' the isle, that will not let you</line>
            <line>Believe things certain. Welcome, my friends all!</line>
            <stagedir>Aside to SEBASTIAN and ANTONIO</stagedir>
            <line>But you, my brace of lords, were I so minded,</line>
            <line>I here could pluck his highness' frown upon you</line>
            <line>And justify you traitors: at this time</line>
            <line>I will tell no tales.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SEBASTIAN</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  The devil speaks in him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>No.</line>
            <line>For you, most wicked sir, whom to call brother</line>
            <line>Would even infect my mouth, I do forgive</line>
            <line>Thy rankest fault; all of them; and require</line>
            <line>My dukedom of thee, which perforce, I know,</line>
            <line>Thou must restore.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALONSO</speaker>
            <line>If thou be'st Prospero,</line>
            <line>Give us particulars of thy preservation;</line>
            <line>How thou hast met us here, who three hours since</line>
            <line>Were wreck'd upon this shore; where I have lost--</line>
            <line>How sharp the point of this remembrance is!--</line>
            <line>My dear son Ferdinand.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>I am woe for't, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALONSO</speaker>
            <line>Irreparable is the loss, and patience</line>
            <line>Says it is past her cure.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>I rather think</line>
            <line>You have not sought her help, of whose soft grace</line>
            <line>For the like loss I have her sovereign aid</line>
            <line>And rest myself content.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALONSO</speaker>
            <line>You the like loss!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>As great to me as late; and, supportable</line>
            <line>To make the dear loss, have I means much weaker</line>
            <line>Than you may call to comfort you, for I</line>
            <line>Have lost my daughter.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALONSO</speaker>
            <line>A daughter?</line>
            <line>O heavens, that they were living both in Naples,</line>
            <line>The king and queen there! that they were, I wish</line>
            <line>Myself were mudded in that oozy bed</line>
            <line>Where my son lies. When did you lose your daughter?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>In this last tempest. I perceive these lords</line>
            <line>At this encounter do so much admire</line>
            <line>That they devour their reason and scarce think</line>
            <line>Their eyes do offices of truth, their words</line>
            <line>Are natural breath: but, howsoe'er you have</line>
            <line>Been justled from your senses, know for certain</line>
            <line>That I am Prospero and that very duke</line>
            <line>Which was thrust forth of Milan, who most strangely</line>
            <line>Upon this shore, where you were wreck'd, was landed,</line>
            <line>To be the lord on't. No more yet of this;</line>
            <line>For 'tis a chronicle of day by day,</line>
            <line>Not a relation for a breakfast nor</line>
            <line>Befitting this first meeting. Welcome, sir;</line>
            <line>This cell's my court: here have I few attendants</line>
            <line>And subjects none abroad: pray you, look in.</line>
            <line>My dukedom since you have given me again,</line>
            <line>I will requite you with as good a thing;</line>
            <line>At least bring forth a wonder, to content ye</line>
            <line>As much as me my dukedom.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Here PROSPERO discovers FERDINAND and MIRANDA
playing at chess</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MIRANDA</speaker>
            <line>Sweet lord, you play me false.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>No, my dear'st love,</line>
            <line>I would not for the world.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MIRANDA</speaker>
            <line>Yes, for a score of kingdoms you should wrangle,</line>
            <line>And I would call it, fair play.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALONSO</speaker>
            <line>If this prove</line>
            <line>A vision of the Island, one dear son</line>
            <line>Shall I twice lose.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SEBASTIAN</speaker>
            <line>A most high miracle!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>Though the seas threaten, they are merciful;</line>
            <line>I have cursed them without cause.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Kneels</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALONSO</speaker>
            <line>Now all the blessings</line>
            <line>Of a glad father compass thee about!</line>
            <line>Arise, and say how thou camest here.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MIRANDA</speaker>
            <line>O, wonder!</line>
            <line>How many goodly creatures are there here!</line>
            <line>How beauteous mankind is! O brave new world,</line>
            <line>That has such people in't!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>'Tis new to thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALONSO</speaker>
            <line>What is this maid with whom thou wast at play?</line>
            <line>Your eld'st acquaintance cannot be three hours:</line>
            <line>Is she the goddess that hath sever'd us,</line>
            <line>And brought us thus together?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FERDINAND</speaker>
            <line>Sir, she is mortal;</line>
            <line>But by immortal Providence she's mine:</line>
            <line>I chose her when I could not ask my father</line>
            <line>For his advice, nor thought I had one. She</line>
            <line>Is daughter to this famous Duke of Milan,</line>
            <line>Of whom so often I have heard renown,</line>
            <line>But never saw before; of whom I have</line>
            <line>Received a second life; and second father</line>
            <line>This lady makes him to me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALONSO</speaker>
            <line>I am hers:</line>
            <line>But, O, how oddly will it sound that I</line>
            <line>Must ask my child forgiveness!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>There, sir, stop:</line>
            <line>Let us not burthen our remembrance with</line>
            <line>A heaviness that's gone.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GONZALO</speaker>
            <line>I have inly wept,</line>
            <line>Or should have spoke ere this. Look down, you god,</line>
            <line>And on this couple drop a blessed crown!</line>
            <line>For it is you that have chalk'd forth the way</line>
            <line>Which brought us hither.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALONSO</speaker>
            <line>I say, Amen, Gonzalo!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GONZALO</speaker>
            <line>Was Milan thrust from Milan, that his issue</line>
            <line>Should become kings of Naples? O, rejoice</line>
            <line>Beyond a common joy, and set it down</line>
            <line>With gold on lasting pillars: In one voyage</line>
            <line>Did Claribel her husband find at Tunis,</line>
            <line>And Ferdinand, her brother, found a wife</line>
            <line>Where he himself was lost, Prospero his dukedom</line>
            <line>In a poor isle and all of us ourselves</line>
            <line>When no man was his own.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALONSO</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>To FERDINAND and MIRANDA</stagedir>  Give me your hands:</line>
            <line>Let grief and sorrow still embrace his heart</line>
            <line>That doth not wish you joy!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GONZALO</speaker>
            <line>Be it so! Amen!</line>
            <stagedir>Re-enter ARIEL, with the Master and Boatswain
amazedly following</stagedir>
            <line>O, look, sir, look, sir! here is more of us:</line>
            <line>I prophesied, if a gallows were on land,</line>
            <line>This fellow could not drown. Now, blasphemy,</line>
            <line>That swear'st grace o'erboard, not an oath on shore?</line>
            <line>Hast thou no mouth by land? What is the news?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Boatswain</speaker>
            <line>The best news is, that we have safely found</line>
            <line>Our king and company; the next, our ship--</line>
            <line>Which, but three glasses since, we gave out split--</line>
            <line>Is tight and yare and bravely rigg'd as when</line>
            <line>We first put out to sea.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARIEL</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside to PROSPERO</stagedir>  Sir, all this service</line>
            <line>Have I done since I went.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside to ARIEL</stagedir>  My tricksy spirit!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALONSO</speaker>
            <line>These are not natural events; they strengthen</line>
            <line>From strange to stranger. Say, how came you hither?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Boatswain</speaker>
            <line>If I did think, sir, I were well awake,</line>
            <line>I'ld strive to tell you. We were dead of sleep,</line>
            <line>And--how we know not--all clapp'd under hatches;</line>
            <line>Where but even now with strange and several noises</line>
            <line>Of roaring, shrieking, howling, jingling chains,</line>
            <line>And more diversity of sounds, all horrible,</line>
            <line>We were awaked; straightway, at liberty;</line>
            <line>Where we, in all her trim, freshly beheld</line>
            <line>Our royal, good and gallant ship, our master</line>
            <line>Capering to eye her: on a trice, so please you,</line>
            <line>Even in a dream, were we divided from them</line>
            <line>And were brought moping hither.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARIEL</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside to PROSPERO</stagedir>          Was't well done?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside to ARIEL</stagedir>  Bravely, my diligence. Thou shalt be free.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALONSO</speaker>
            <line>This is as strange a maze as e'er men trod</line>
            <line>And there is in this business more than nature</line>
            <line>Was ever conduct of: some oracle</line>
            <line>Must rectify our knowledge.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>Sir, my liege,</line>
            <line>Do not infest your mind with beating on</line>
            <line>The strangeness of this business; at pick'd leisure</line>
            <line>Which shall be shortly, single I'll resolve you,</line>
            <line>Which to you shall seem probable, of every</line>
            <line>These happen'd accidents; till when, be cheerful</line>
            <line>And think of each thing well.</line>
            <stagedir>Aside to ARIEL</stagedir>
            <line>Come hither, spirit:</line>
            <line>Set Caliban and his companions free;</line>
            <line>Untie the spell.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit ARIEL</stagedir>
            <line>How fares my gracious sir?</line>
            <line>There are yet missing of your company</line>
            <line>Some few odd lads that you remember not.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter ARIEL, driving in CALIBAN, STEPHANO
and TRINCULO, in their stolen apparel</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>STEPHANO</speaker>
            <line>Every man shift for all the rest, and</line>
            <line>let no man take care for himself; for all is</line>
            <line>but fortune. Coragio, bully-monster, coragio!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRINCULO</speaker>
            <line>If these be true spies which I wear in my head,</line>
            <line>here's a goodly sight.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CALIBAN</speaker>
            <line>O Setebos, these be brave spirits indeed!</line>
            <line>How fine my master is! I am afraid</line>
            <line>He will chastise me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SEBASTIAN</speaker>
            <line>Ha, ha!</line>
            <line>What things are these, my lord Antonio?</line>
            <line>Will money buy 'em?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>Very like; one of them</line>
            <line>Is a plain fish, and, no doubt, marketable.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>Mark but the badges of these men, my lords,</line>
            <line>Then say if they be true. This mis-shapen knave,</line>
            <line>His mother was a witch, and one so strong</line>
            <line>That could control the moon, make flows and ebbs,</line>
            <line>And deal in her command without her power.</line>
            <line>These three have robb'd me; and this demi-devil--</line>
            <line>For he's a bastard one--had plotted with them</line>
            <line>To take my life. Two of these fellows you</line>
            <line>Must know and own; this thing of darkness!</line>
            <line>Acknowledge mine.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CALIBAN</speaker>
            <line>I shall be pinch'd to death.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALONSO</speaker>
            <line>Is not this Stephano, my drunken butler?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SEBASTIAN</speaker>
            <line>He is drunk now: where had he wine?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALONSO</speaker>
            <line>And Trinculo is reeling ripe: where should they</line>
            <line>Find this grand liquor that hath gilded 'em?</line>
            <line>How camest thou in this pickle?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TRINCULO</speaker>
            <line>I have been in such a pickle since I</line>
            <line>saw you last that, I fear me, will never out of</line>
            <line>my bones: I shall not fear fly-blowing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SEBASTIAN</speaker>
            <line>Why, how now, Stephano!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>STEPHANO</speaker>
            <line>O, touch me not; I am not Stephano, but a cramp.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>You'ld be king o' the isle, sirrah?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>STEPHANO</speaker>
            <line>I should have been a sore one then.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALONSO</speaker>
            <line>This is a strange thing as e'er I look'd on.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Pointing to Caliban</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>He is as disproportion'd in his manners</line>
            <line>As in his shape. Go, sirrah, to my cell;</line>
            <line>Take with you your companions; as you look</line>
            <line>To have my pardon, trim it handsomely.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CALIBAN</speaker>
            <line>Ay, that I will; and I'll be wise hereafter</line>
            <line>And seek for grace. What a thrice-double ass</line>
            <line>Was I, to take this drunkard for a god</line>
            <line>And worship this dull fool!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>Go to; away!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALONSO</speaker>
            <line>Hence, and bestow your luggage where you found it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SEBASTIAN</speaker>
            <line>Or stole it, rather.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt CALIBAN, STEPHANO, and TRINCULO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>Sir, I invite your highness and your train</line>
            <line>To my poor cell, where you shall take your rest</line>
            <line>For this one night; which, part of it, I'll waste</line>
            <line>With such discourse as, I not doubt, shall make it</line>
            <line>Go quick away; the story of my life</line>
            <line>And the particular accidents gone by</line>
            <line>Since I came to this isle: and in the morn</line>
            <line>I'll bring you to your ship and so to Naples,</line>
            <line>Where I have hope to see the nuptial</line>
            <line>Of these our dear-beloved solemnized;</line>
            <line>And thence retire me to my Milan, where</line>
            <line>Every third thought shall be my grave.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALONSO</speaker>
            <line>I long</line>
            <line>To hear the story of your life, which must</line>
            <line>Take the ear strangely.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PROSPERO</speaker>
            <line>I'll deliver all;</line>
            <line>And promise you calm seas, auspicious gales</line>
            <line>And sail so expeditious that shall catch</line>
            <line>Your royal fleet far off.</line>
            <stagedir>Aside to ARIEL</stagedir>
            <line>My Ariel, chick,</line>
            <line>That is thy charge: then to the elements</line>
            <line>Be free, and fare thou well! Please you, draw near.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <epilogue id="act-5-epilog">
      <title>EPILOGUE</title>
      <epilogue-body>
         <speech>
            <speaker>[PROSPERO]</speaker>
            <line>Now my charms are all o'erthrown,</line>
            <line>And what strength I have's mine own,</line>
            <line>Which is most faint: now, 'tis true,</line>
            <line>I must be here confined by you,</line>
            <line>Or sent to Naples. Let me not,</line>
            <line>Since I have my dukedom got</line>
            <line>And pardon'd the deceiver, dwell</line>
            <line>In this bare island by your spell;</line>
            <line>But release me from my bands</line>
            <line>With the help of your good hands:</line>
            <line>Gentle breath of yours my sails</line>
            <line>Must fill, or else my project fails,</line>
            <line>Which was to please. Now I want</line>
            <line>Spirits to enforce, art to enchant,</line>
            <line>And my ending is despair,</line>
            <line>Unless I be relieved by prayer,</line>
            <line>Which pierces so that it assaults</line>
            <line>Mercy itself and frees all faults.</line>
            <line>As you from crimes would pardon'd be,</line>
            <line>Let your indulgence set me free.</line>
         </speech>
      </epilogue-body>
   </epilogue>
</act>