<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<chapter
  id="d5e2">
  <title>Wikis and Open Documentation Systems</title>
  <prolog/>
  <body>
    <p><image
        href="images/chapter06.png"
        id="image_1eaabc02-b507-433f-a667-5d32540ef502"
        width="5in"/></p>
    <epigram>Your wiki is not Wikipedia.&#8232;—Stewart Mader</epigram>
    <p>The recent explosion of wikis hosted on the Internet and the extreme success of Wikipedia,
      the largest online reference encyclopedia, has led to discussions about where a wiki might fit
      into technical documentation. Originally created in 1995 for making quick web pages, wiki
      means “quick” in Hawaiian and is now synonymous with collaborative authoring. Over 90 wiki
      applications are available, and most offer cross-platform, cross-browser pages. Wikis
      encourage collaboration because they allow any one with the right permissions to edit any web
      page, and many wikis can even reconcile differences when two authors edit the same article at
      the same time. </p>
    <p>Wikis represent a shift towards living, breathing, changing documentation, and not all
      writers are certain of their value or place in <indexterm>technical documentation<indexterm
          >wikis and</indexterm></indexterm>technical deliverables. I believe that wikis encourage
      crowd-sourcing, or delegating work to a large group of semi-organized individuals (a crowd),
      and help writers see customers’ view points. Customers might expect a wiki when a customer
        <indexterm>forums<indexterm>compared to wikis</indexterm></indexterm>forum does not provide
      enough information to answer their questions or when scrolling through multiple answers on a
      forum becomes tedious. </p>
    <p>Wikis are good for project management and communication, for information gathering and
      collection of source material, and for content delivery. Wikis can be either the source of
      your content or the published deliverable from another source. This chapter talks about both
      sourcing models and also contains a roundtrip discussion, where the content goes to a wiki and
      the wiki articles come back to a source file to be modified again and again. </p>
    <p>Using wikis for project <indexterm>wikis<indexterm
        >enterprise</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm>wikis<indexterm>collaboration
        in</indexterm></indexterm>collaboration is an important model and one that is prevalent in
      today’s workplace. Scott Abel, creator of The Content Wrangler, and Stewart Mader, author of
      Wikipatterns and wiki adoption consultant, recently collaborated on some research into wiki
      use in the enterprise, producing a report titled “Why Businesses Don’t Collaborate.”<fn>
        <p>
          http://www.scribd.com/doc/16336782/Why-Businesses-Dont-Collaborate-Meeting-Management-Group-Input-and-Wiki-Usage-Survey-Results</p>
      </fn> In their report they discuss uses of the enterprise wiki, which is a wiki behind a
      corporate firewall. The security layer for this type of wiki is based on the credentials
      already established for company email and the company network. By using the enterprise wiki
      rather than relying on email for tasks like distributing meeting agendas and posting meeting
      minutes, people save time, work together, and distribute updates and information more easily.
      One responder to the survey noted, “I’ve found that people are much more likely to participate
      when they can just go update wiki pages vs. reviewing formal/traditional documents.” </p>
    <p>I also believe that wikis are not always the best-fit application, depending on the business
      needs for the wiki. Some disadvantages for wikis include:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>Portability: A wiki often is run from a server and even though web servers are becoming
        smaller and smaller on disk, gathering up all the pieces to create a portable wiki may not
        be practical.</li>
      <li>Connectivity requirements: Wikis are often online-only content, so people cannot browse a
        wiki on an airplane, for example.</li>
      <li>Access control choices and implications: People’s perceptions of wikis are that they
        should be open for editing, but if you want to use a wiki just to enable <indexterm
            >collaboration<indexterm>wikis and</indexterm></indexterm>comments, you might not meet
        some users expectations.</li>
      <li>Output deliverables: Many wikis offer output formats ranging from PDF to content for a
        mobile smartphone, but those may not meet your users standards for output quality.</li>
    </ul>
    <p>In March and April of 2008, 493 people responded to a survey from the Center for Information
      Development Management that asked about publishing practices and information management
      techniques. More than half of the respondents said they use wikis internally but just 9% use
      wikis for externally facing documents.<fn>
        <p> http://www.cidmblog.com/?q=node/33</p>
      </fn> My interpretation is that we are getting more practice using wikis for project
      management and internal collaboration, but we are not yet replacing traditional <indexterm
        >help, online<indexterm>compared to wikis</indexterm></indexterm>help systems with wikis. </p>
    <p>Wiki<indexterm>wikis<indexterm>comparison to online help</indexterm></indexterm> applications
      offer many advantages over traditional HTML publication methods. From Microsoft’s early
      WinHelp to Compiled HTML Help format (CHM)<indexterm>CHM</indexterm> to the open source
      Eclipse help<indexterm>Eclipse help</indexterm>, we have seen a growing demand for user
      assistance systems designed to be cross-platform and network friendly. Many wikis use wikitext
      for editing, a simplified markup language that is often an alternative to HTML coding. There
      are also some pitfalls to avoid when using wikitext<indexterm>wikitext<indexterm
          >example</indexterm></indexterm> instead of traditional <indexterm>HTML<indexterm>used in
          wikis</indexterm></indexterm>HTML markup, however. For example, wikitext is not exactly
      the same for every engine so learning one wikitext syntax is not transferable to another wiki.
      Some wikitext is <indexterm>HTML<indexterm>used in wikis</indexterm></indexterm>HTML-based,
      other wikitext is text-based. </p>
    <p>Following are some ways that <indexterm>technical documentation<indexterm>wikis
          and</indexterm></indexterm>wikis are different from traditional user assistance systems. </p>
    <ul>
      <li>Editing: The “wikitext” markup used by many wikis is meant to be simple and easy to
        use</li>
      <li>Linking: Many wikis allow page-name-based linking to other wiki pages, or simple HTML
        linking methods</li>
      <li>Subscribing options: RSS<indexterm>RSS (Really Simple Syndication)<indexterm>subscribing
            to wikis</indexterm></indexterm> feeds for recent changes, “watch” pages for edits</li>
      <li>Searching:<indexterm>wikis<indexterm>searching in</indexterm></indexterm> Search<indexterm
            >search<indexterm>in wikis</indexterm></indexterm> engine technology often is
        included</li>
      <li>Scalability: Many pages edited by many authors </li>
      <li>Access control: Registration and logins can control authoring privileges</li>
    </ul>
    <p>To quote the introduction to the CommonCraft video instructions for wikis, “wiki web sites
      are easy to use, but hard to describe.” I recommend their video, Wikis in Plain English, for
      an introduction to wikis and how they work in less than four minutes’ time.<fn>
        <p> http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-dnL00TdmLY</p>
      </fn></p>
    <p>Learning about different <indexterm>wikis<indexterm>learning
      about</indexterm></indexterm>wikis and how they work should involve hands-on exercises as well
      as reading and watching videos about wikis. Many wikis offer a sandbox area so that you can
      see the editor and try your hand at wiki editing.</p>
    <p> shows a troubleshooting page on the <indexterm>One Laptop per Child<indexterm
          >wiki</indexterm></indexterm>One Laptop per Child wiki at wiki.laptop.org. It has a table
      of contents advance organizer feature built in to the wiki page, a graphic, navigation in the
      sidebar, and a visible search form. The tabs at the top are prominent features of the wiki,
      enabling users to discuss, edit, and view a history of the page. </p>
    <p>wiki.laptop.org while displaying a page</p>
    <p>Even without logging in, a user can click the edit tab in this particular wiki. When you
      click the edit tab, you see a new interface that shows the editor window. In , the wikitext is
      text-based. For example, the three equals signs in a row (===) on each end of a phrase
      indicate a heading. </p>
    <p>wiki.laptop.org while editing a page</p>
    <p>The website wikimatrix.org, a comprehensive tool that describes wiki applications and lets
      you run side-by-side comparisons, uses the following categories to evaluate wikis:</p>
    <p>When evaluating <indexterm>evaluation<indexterm>of wiki
      applications</indexterm></indexterm>wikis, just like any technology tools, you should first
      decide the business needs and use cases for the wiki. After gathering use cases, determine the
      fit for the list of wiki applications that meet your business objectives and use cases. </p>
    <p>Another practical consideration for selecting a wiki application is whether it uses a
        <indexterm>wikis<indexterm>database-driven</indexterm></indexterm>database to serve up the
      content. If you need access to the content for repurposing, versioning, backing up, or
      translating, how easy is it to get access to the data structures? Are you more comfortable
      with database commands or file copy commands and automation? </p>
    <p>You want to determine the license that you use for the content created on your <indexterm
          >wikis<indexterm>licensing content</indexterm></indexterm>wiki so that you can decide if
      creating new deliverables from the wiki source and sharing the content is allowed. </p>
    <p>The editing syntax for wikis varies widely. Some use HTML and some use <indexterm
          >wikis<indexterm>syntax</indexterm></indexterm>wikitext for editing. Wikitext is a markup
      language that usually simplifies the markup further than just HTML, using conventions such as
      asterisks * for bullets and square brackets [] to indicate linked text. Will your users tend
      to spend time in a WYSIWYG editor, or will they be more comfortable in a particular
        wikitext<indexterm>wikitext<indexterm>varied syntax</indexterm></indexterm>, and if so, what
      wikitext do they already know? Do most of your users already know rudimentary HTML<indexterm
          >HTML<indexterm>used in wikis</indexterm></indexterm> markup?</p>
    <p>How about <indexterm>wikis<indexterm>scripting support</indexterm></indexterm>scripting
      support within the wiki? Some wiki applications enable programmatic solutions within a page,
      such as creating a table of contents automatically or enabling embedded pages within pages.
      Are you going to have editors who will want advanced features that scripting offers, such as
      embedded expanding tables of contents or publishing items from an RSS feed? Scripts may solve
      some web publishing problems, but for a casual wiki editor, scripted instructions add to the
      complexity of viewing the wikitext. </p>
    <p>Like HTML help systems, wiki syntax should give you the ability to easily link to other wiki
      pages and to external sources. Be aware of how difficult or easy it is to link to non-wiki
      resources with the wiki markup offered by the wiki application you are evaluating.</p>
    <p>An added benefit of wikis is the ability to subscribe to RSS feeds that enable you or other
      wiki users to “watch” what pages are being edited. Find out the granularity of what changes
      you can be notified on—is it per article, per page, per category, per section? </p>
    <p>While setting up search engines within a traditional help system is often difficult, most
      wiki applications build in easy search mechanisms within the body of the wiki. Find out if you
      can integrate another search engine with the wiki application or if you must use the one
      shipped with the wiki. </p>
  </body>
  <subsection
    id="d5e226">
    <title>Starting or reinvigorating a wiki</title>
    <body>
      <p>A wiki is not always the answer to the question being asked. One of my favorite quotes
        about a <indexterm>communities<indexterm>wikis supporting</indexterm></indexterm>wiki is
        from a blog article in which the author told a story about how starting a wiki was in
        reality just a procrastination attempt—put off the real work of collaborating and
        cooperating with each other by distracting yourself with wiki application research and
        selection and installation.<fn>
          <p> http://www.hacknot.info/hacknot/action/showEntry?eid=71</p>
        </fn> It’s so true that the hardest part about working on a wiki is not writing the content
        but building the trust and relationships that will ensure the wiki continues to grow and
        thrive. So if you are ready to work on growing wiki use<indexterm>adopting wikis in
          documentation process</indexterm>, and not just installing wiki software, here are an some
        best practices for building your wiki. </p>
    </body>
    <subsection
      id="d5e242">
      <title>Conduct an audience analysis</title>
      <prolog>
        <metadata>
          <keywords>
            <indexterm>social media<indexterm>audience analysis</indexterm></indexterm>
            <indexterm>audience analysis</indexterm>
            <indexterm>audience analysis</indexterm>
          </keywords>
        </metadata>
      </prolog>
      <body>
        <p>Just like with other information deliverables, knowing your audience is an important part
          of running a <indexterm>wikis<indexterm>audience analysis for</indexterm></indexterm>wiki.
          For example, WoWwiki.com is a popular wiki run by the community for a popular game,
            <indexterm>World of Warcraft</indexterm><indexterm>communities<indexterm>World of
              Warcraft</indexterm></indexterm>World of Warcraft. This particular wiki’s community
          wants strategy articles and reference information for their wiki; users’ technical or
          how-to questions or discussions are roundly dismissed, and the community shapes the wiki
          in the way they want it to be.<fn>
            <p> Based on my notes from a 2008 SXSWi panel, Edit Me: How Gamers are Adopting the Wiki
              Way.
              http://justwriteclick.com/2008/03/16/stories-from-sxswi-2008-edit-me-how-gamers-are-adopting-the-wiki-way/</p>
          </fn> So, before starting a wiki, offer a survey or talk to customers about their hopes
          and expectations.</p>
      </body>
    </subsection>
    <subsection
      id="d5e269">
      <title>Build a wiki style guide</title>
      <prolog>
        <metadata>
          <keywords>
            <indexterm>style guidance</indexterm>
          </keywords>
        </metadata>
      </prolog>
      <body>
        <p>You may already have a <indexterm>wikis<indexterm>style
            guidance</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm>content<indexterm>style
              guidelines</indexterm></indexterm>style guide for your writing deliverables. You may
          have a list of preferred action words for tasks and steps, or a description of how you
          capitalize headings or the titles of wiki pages, to standardize your wiki’s URLs. Embed
          your wiki style guide directly on the wiki itself as a wiki page. Make sure that your own
          contributions consistently follow a style guide. </p>
        <p>A style guide can also describe which <indexterm>wikis<indexterm
            >categories</indexterm></indexterm>categories are helpful in your wiki, and some of the
          background decisions for choosing those categories. As an example, the OLPC Wiki has a
          Style Guide page<fn>
            <p> http://wiki.laptop.org/go/Style_guide</p>
          </fn> that helps new contributors understand the structure and organization of the wiki.
          The Firefox Support Knowledge Base has a comprehensive style guide<fn>
            <p> http://support.mozilla.com/en-US/kb/Style+Guide</p>
          </fn> that also refers contributors to Sun Microsystem’s style guide, <ph>Read Me First! A
            Style Guide for the Computer Industry</ph>. If contributors do not follow the style
          guide, even with reminders, decide if you want to edit the text to match the style guide
          or if the community will accept the text without strict adherence to a style guide.</p>
        <p>Another way of defining style is determining a “<indexterm>wikis<indexterm
              >voice</indexterm></indexterm>voice” for your wiki. Decide ahead of time the types of
          information and word choices that the wiki pages reflect. Refer to Chapter 7, “Finding
          your Voice,” for more suggestions and style guidance.</p>
      </body>
    </subsection>
    <subsection
      id="d5e309">
      <title>Offer wiki how-to guides or training sessions</title>
      <body>
        <p>Wiki <indexterm>wikis<indexterm>tutorials</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm
            >training</indexterm>tutorials give new users a chance to learn in a safe environment,
          one in which they can explore and experiment and not worry about harming the wiki. A
          tutorial or just a page with some simple how-to steps might be sufficient. Offer a
          “sandbox” area or single page in your wiki where people can try out the interface and
          practice writing the wikitext knowing that their changes are not permanent.</p>
        <p>Another way to help users get comfortable making edits is to purposely leave typos in
          certain pages, giving users a chance to correct small areas before attempting to revise an
          article or add a new article. </p>
        <p>A how-to guide may be helpful for describing common tasks, such as starting an editable
          section or starting a new page. Even an experienced wiki user might need a short how-to
          guide on the basics if the wiki application is unfamiliar.</p>
        <p>If your wiki seems to be intimidating to some, or if your customer base is not already
          familiar with the wikitext<indexterm>wikitext<indexterm>training</indexterm></indexterm>
          you are using, you may want to offer webinars or training sessions to help boost people’s
          confidence in contributing to the wiki. If your wiki is only for an internal audience, you
          could offer informal brown bag lunches to demonstrate how to edit the wiki or add pages.
          At Webworks.com, a company that develops content conversion and deployment solutions, they
          held a brown bag lunch for the entire company before the wiki was rolled out, and all but
          one of the employees have made edits on the wiki.</p>
      </body>
    </subsection>
    <subsection
      id="d5e332">
      <title>Set rules for arbitration</title>
      <prolog>
        <metadata>
          <keywords>
            <indexterm>wikis<indexterm>rules for arbitration</indexterm></indexterm>
            <indexterm>rules for arbitration</indexterm>
          </keywords>
        </metadata>
      </prolog>
      <body>
        <p>Depending on the subject matter of your <indexterm>policies, social computing<indexterm
              >wiki arbitration</indexterm></indexterm>wiki, you may have controversial articles
          that get a lot of discussion or <indexterm>collaboration<indexterm>wikis
            and</indexterm></indexterm>comments, or rounds of aggressive edits in which one
          contributor is pitted against another for the “truth” or being “right.” When this type of
          standoff happens, it is best to have rules for arbitration to determine which edit is the
          edit that remains. Sometimes a community leader will step into this role, but sometimes
          your company will have to take a stand. Either way, be sure to have a written policy
          available on the <indexterm>wikis<indexterm>policies</indexterm></indexterm>wiki to set
          expectations. Experienced contributors want to know the rules of engagement and the
          expectations of the community.</p>
        <p>You may also determine that a particular wiki’s architecture model allows for only one
          wiki article per topic, but multiple wiki articles could be true for each topic. For
          example, collaborations for online textbooks do not use the one-article-per-topic model
          for their <indexterm>collaboration<indexterm>online
          textbooks</indexterm></indexterm>collaborative authoring environments. Instead, they allow
          multiple authors to write more than one conclusive article, such as describing how the
          American Civil War started. When the textbook is compiled for printing or PDF<indexterm
            >PDF, as wiki output</indexterm> creation, a “lens,” or specialized content filter,
          determines which article is included in the textbook. Some wiki applications will enable
          this <indexterm>content<indexterm>filtering</indexterm></indexterm>filtering capability so
          that readers can devise their own lenses for the content, but more often, only one wiki
          page “wins” the battle for being the true article on the wiki.</p>
      </body>
    </subsection>
    <subsection
      id="d5e371">
      <title>Differentiate “warranted” content</title>
      <prolog>
        <metadata>
          <keywords>
            <indexterm>wikis<indexterm>warranted content</indexterm></indexterm>
            <indexterm>warranted content</indexterm>
          </keywords>
        </metadata>
      </prolog>
      <body>
        <p>Many <indexterm>wikis<indexterm>content models</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm
              >content<indexterm>warranted</indexterm></indexterm>wiki users are following a
            <indexterm>publishing<indexterm>wiki content</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm
              >publishing<indexterm>models</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm>publishing<indexterm
              >internal content to external content</indexterm></indexterm>publishing model that
          clearly designates an area of the <indexterm>technical documentation<indexterm>wikis
              and</indexterm></indexterm>wiki that is tested, warranted, vetted, and company-backed.
          A common model for many groups is to have an internal <indexterm>wikis<indexterm
              >publishing models</indexterm></indexterm>wiki where drafts are published and
          discussion occurs, and an external wiki that houses the content that is considered
          “warranted.” For example, <indexterm>FLOSS Manuals<indexterm
          >wiki</indexterm></indexterm>FLOSS Manuals has a “<indexterm>wikis<indexterm>write
              area</indexterm></indexterm>Write” area where all content remains while it is still in
          draft stage and a “<indexterm>wikis<indexterm>read area</indexterm></indexterm>Read” area
          to which wiki pages are published when the content is ready. A small group of writers with
          “Maintainer” privileges has the capability to move content from the “Write” area to the
          “Read” area.</p>
        <p><indexterm>Dyer, Lisa</indexterm>Lisa Dyer, a development manager at Lombardi Software,
          uses a similar model in maintaining three wikis. The <indexterm>collaboration<indexterm
              >internal</indexterm></indexterm>internal-only wiki is used by developers, business
          analysts, quality testers, and information developers to write, display, and discuss use
          cases, test plans, and other software documentation artifacts. Guaranteed, tested content
          is published to an external-facing wiki, and only information developers have full control
          over editing the wiki pages. Customers, using their support ID to log on to the wiki, can
          leave <indexterm>collaboration<indexterm>wikis and</indexterm></indexterm>comments on the
          pages but cannot directly edit the <indexterm>content<indexterm
            >wiki</indexterm></indexterm>content. In a third wiki, Lombardi’s technical services
          employees can edit articles and customers can view this content as well, but the
          disclaimer on the wiki states that the content is not tested and following the
          instructions may or may not have expected results. You can read more about their wiki
          model in “Using Structured Wikis in Software Engineering” from WikiSym 2008.<fn>
            <p>
              http://www.wikis4se.org/lib/exe/fetch.php/2008:wikis4se-2008-using_structured_wikis_in_software_engineering.pdf</p>
          </fn></p>
      </body>
    </subsection>
    <subsection
      id="d5e450">
      <title>Integrate the wiki with other content</title>
      <body>
        <p><indexterm>content<indexterm>combining</indexterm></indexterm>Although<indexterm>help,
              online<indexterm>integrating wikis with</indexterm></indexterm> some <indexterm
            >technical documentation<indexterm>wikis and</indexterm></indexterm>people find that
            a<indexterm>content<indexterm>wiki</indexterm></indexterm> wiki is sufficient for
          delivering the <indexterm>content<indexterm>integrating</indexterm></indexterm>information
          a customer needs, a wiki alone is not sufficient for many audiences and products. If you
          produce a wiki in addition to other deliverables for a product, you need to integrate the
          wiki with the documentation set so that it looks like the rest of your documentation,
          follows your style requirements, and is included in search and indexing tools. If you need
          to set the wiki apart because it is unvetted content, or because it contains only
          tutorials or specialized content, it still should follow corporate guidelines for visual
          style. </p>
        <p>If a wiki’s look and feel is widely different from other deliverables, the wiki may
          appear like an afterthought or unneeded part of the documentation set. <indexterm>Johnson,
            Tom</indexterm>Tom Johnson, on idratherbewriting.com, also found that the scope of the
            search<indexterm>search<indexterm>in wikis</indexterm></indexterm> boxes is an important
          usability aspect of integrating the wiki with other content in your documentation set. Tom
          voices his concerns about user assistance that is fragmented and in too many locations
          without a unifying search or theme.<fn>
            <p>
              http://www.idratherbewriting.com/2008/02/06/a-web-20-documentation-idea-gone-wrong/</p>
          </fn> When users are within a stand-alone help system, they may not know that a wiki
          exists. Finding ways to expand the user assistance system to include the wiki or support
            <indexterm>forums<indexterm>searching through online help</indexterm></indexterm>forums
          in a search would help direct readers to the conversation-based content. </p>
        <p>You may find that you can single-source to initially build a wiki. Webworks.com offers
          publishing to wikitext from multiple types of source files. One XML-based standard for
          technical documentation, the Darwin Information Typing Architecture (DITA), enables the
          DITA2Wiki <indexterm>open source<indexterm>DITA2Wiki</indexterm></indexterm>open source
          project which offers a framework to use DITA source files to populate a wiki. Other
          projects such as the Mylyn <indexterm>MediaWiki<indexterm>transform to
            DITA</indexterm></indexterm>MediaWiki to DITA project<fn>
            <p> http://greensopinion.blogspot.com/2008/11/mylyn-wikitext-targets-oasis-dita.html</p>
          </fn> have found ways to transform wikitext<indexterm>wikitext<indexterm>transform from
              XML</indexterm></indexterm> into XML files. Another workflow is to author in a wiki
          and output PDF<indexterm>PDF, as wiki output</indexterm> files as books from the wiki.
            <indexterm>wikislices</indexterm>Wikislices are another method for extracting a book
          from a specific set of wiki pages. But wiki integration could also mean supplying a wiki
          with updated articles but then use a <indexterm>wikis<indexterm
            >slicing</indexterm></indexterm>wikislicing technique to pull those articles back into
          user assistance that is delivered in another way. </p>
        <p>Another aspect of integrating a wiki with other content is ensuring that an online
          identity is associated with the wiki. For example, if a login ID is already required for
          access to your customer support website, perhaps your wiki could use the same login
          credentials, lending credibility to the wiki because only supported customers could edit
          the content.</p>
      </body>
    </subsection>
    <subsection
      id="d5e533">
      <title>Ensure that your wiki has original content</title>
      <body>
        <p>Let your wiki community know that you are fully committed to the wiki by offering
            <indexterm>content<indexterm>wiki</indexterm></indexterm>original articles found nowhere
          else. Knowing that the wiki is dynamic and original will entice readers to continue to
          visit it. Even more enticing would be to feature a community member’s contribution on a
          regular basis. This best practice works well when the wiki is just a part of your overall
            <indexterm>technical documentation<indexterm>wikis
          and</indexterm></indexterm>documentation set. If your wiki is the sole source of end-user
          documentation, then the wiki itself is all “original” content, meaning, its content cannot
          be found in other publications.</p>
      </body>
    </subsection>
    <subsection
      id="d5e547">
      <title>Beware of spammers, and back up often</title>
      <prolog>
        <metadata>
          <keywords>
            <indexterm>wikis<indexterm>spammers</indexterm></indexterm>
            <indexterm>spammers</indexterm>
          </keywords>
        </metadata>
      </prolog>
      <body>
        <p>You want to constantly check the wiki for edits or <indexterm>collaboration<indexterm
              >wikis and</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm>comments<indexterm
            >spam</indexterm></indexterm>comments that do not look genuine or well-meaning. You can
          reverse those changes if they happen. Spammers will not target your wiki for long once
          they understand that their efforts are futile. </p>
        <p>You can protect your wiki from spam-based changes by requiring users who make edits or
            <indexterm>collaboration<indexterm>wikis and</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm
              >comments<indexterm>spam</indexterm></indexterm>comments to solve a math sum in a web
          form or enter a text string from a graphic before submitting a comment. Tools such as
            Captcha<fn>
            <p> http://www.captcha.net/</p>
          </fn> have this type of requirement and are prevalent and effective. Some wikis allow you
          to block, redirect, or ban users or even IP addresses.</p>
        <p>Wiki <indexterm>wikis<indexterm>vandalism</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm>vandalism,
            wiki</indexterm>vandalism is different from wiki spam. Typically a vandal’s intent is to
          disrupt the community or personally annoy or distract a particular community member.
          Again, immediate reversal of the vandalism and backup of your wiki can often stop vandals.
          Vandalism is rare and is not typical for most wiki communities. An active community can
          also help you keep unwanted content and spam out of your wiki. Rather than expending
          energy preventing vandalism, work harder on building your community and encouraging
          contributors.</p>
      </body>
    </subsection>
    <subsection
      id="d5e589">
      <title>Keep updating content </title>
      <body>
        <p>The point of having a wiki is to enable constant editing and adding of new <indexterm
              >content<indexterm>up-to-date</indexterm></indexterm>content. Users expect wikis, more
          than most forms of documentation, to have timely and frequent updates, and most wiki tools
          offer a timeline of <indexterm>content<indexterm>wiki</indexterm></indexterm>changes so
          users can easily view the latest edits and additions. </p>
        <p>If your product’s release schedule does not typically have regular updates, you may find
          that a wiki is not a good match for your product documentation, and you might look
          elsewhere for customer conversations. </p>
        <p>GigaSpaces technical writer Gilad David <indexterm>Maayan, Gilad David</indexterm>Maayan
          says “we weren’t updating our <indexterm>help, online<indexterm>compared to
              wikis</indexterm></indexterm>help pages as often as we would have liked,” in a case
          study published on the <indexterm>Atlassian Confluence</indexterm>Atlassian web site.<fn>
            <p> http://www.atlassian.com/software/confluence/casestudies/gigaspaces.jsp</p>
          </fn> He moved their online help content to a wiki to gain more frequent updates, more
          contributors, improved searching, finding, and a better overall user experience.</p>
      </body>
    </subsection>
    <subsection
      id="d5e623">
      <title>Become a member of the community</title>
      <body>
        <p>If you are willing to share your professional identity with customers, you lend
          credibility to your intention to become part of their <indexterm>communities<indexterm
              >participation in</indexterm></indexterm>community. In some cases, depending on the
          wiki and the corporate culture, you might not want to insert yourself too much into the
          community that is building up. For example, a developer of a game might be attacked if he
          or she tries to defend design decisions made in the game by writing wiki articles. Plus,
          if writing strategy articles is not part of a developer’s job description and the wiki
          community members prefer that the developer continue to develop features, article writing
          might be a perceived waste of resources. If instead the developer makes a useful comment
          on a wiki page, he or she is still contributing to the community but in a way that the
          community would embrace instead of attack.</p>
      </body>
    </subsection>
    <subsection
      id="d5e632">
      <title>Maintain categories</title>
      <body>
        <p>Many technical writers excel in creating indexes and keywords, including inferring other
          terms that people might want to use. With <indexterm>wikis<indexterm
              >categories</indexterm></indexterm>categories on a wiki, you can organize in many
          ways, beyond keywords. Although you do not want to over-organize a wiki and risk
          discouraging community contributions, you can suggest categories, tags,<indexterm
              >tagging<indexterm>wiki content</indexterm></indexterm> and keywords to a contributor
          just as you would to a co-worker. However be prepared to accept if they don’t want to use
          them. Ease of use and low barriers to entry may be more valuable than strict rules about
          consistency.</p>
      </body>
    </subsection>
    <subsection
      id="d5e646">
      <title>Watch recent changes</title>
      <body>
        <p>If you want to become an active contributor to a wiki, you should keep an eye on the
          recent changes page, either by RSS<indexterm>RSS (Really Simple Syndication)<indexterm
              >subscribing to wikis</indexterm></indexterm> or email notification. This practice
          gives you an idea of what areas are being heavily revised and also what areas might be
          under contentious debate.</p>
        <p>You also want to watch certain pages, such as pages that you start or edit, to see how
          your changes are interpreted and whether activity happens on your page. In the case of the
          One Laptop per Child<indexterm>One Laptop per Child<indexterm>wiki</indexterm></indexterm>
          simple user guide, I watched the wiki page that contained the user guide content and was
          pleasantly surprised when Walter Bender, the president of development<indexterm
            >development</indexterm> for the project at that time, <indexterm>One Laptop per
              Child<indexterm>collaboration</indexterm></indexterm>contributed <indexterm>One Laptop
            per Child<indexterm>user guide edits</indexterm></indexterm>edits from his wealth of
          experience in deploying the laptops.</p>
      </body>
    </subsection>
    <subsection
      id="d5e675">
      <title>Expect small percentages of contributors and value them highly</title>
      <body>
        <p>As with other types of online <indexterm>communities<indexterm>statistics
              about</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm>communities<indexterm>participation
              in</indexterm></indexterm>communities, you will not have hundreds of content
          contributors. Realistically, you might have a core group of about five contributors for
          most types of information products. Several sets of research provide insight into this
          pattern. </p>
        <p>Jakob Nielsen wrote “<indexterm>participation<indexterm
            >inequality</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm>content<indexterm>user-generated</indexterm></indexterm>Participation
          inequality: Encouraging more users to participate”<fn>
            <p> http://www.useit.com/alertbox/participation_inequality.html</p>
          </fn>
          <indexterm>content<indexterm>contributions, statistics about</indexterm></indexterm>in
          2006 to describe the 90% lurker/9% small <indexterm>content<indexterm
              >community-generated</indexterm></indexterm>contribution/1% large <indexterm
              >communities<indexterm>content contributed by</indexterm></indexterm>contribution
          findings of the research he had completed on online user forum participation. He studied
          email <indexterm>mailing lists<indexterm>contributions to</indexterm></indexterm>lists,
          online <indexterm>forums<indexterm>contributions to</indexterm></indexterm>forums, and
          newsgroups, which are the natural predecessors of wikis. His article concludes with
          suggestions on how to move those numbers slightly either towards more contributors or
          towards more lurkers and fewer elite contributors (which may also be a desired result).
          His first suggestion is to recognize that these numbers have been observed for years and
          that you can’t really change these values by much—perhaps by only a few tenths of a
          percent. </p>
        <p>Nielsen’s suggestions include ideas that are easily transferred to user assistance or to
          wiki contributions. First, make it easy to contribute quickly, such as offering star
          rating capability instead of only a web form. The ability to rate an article is included
          in many online help systems, and exposing the <indexterm>help, online<indexterm>rating
              topics</indexterm></indexterm>ratings to the reader helps to determine how “well-worn”
          a help topic is. With forum software you can also determine the value of a community
          member’s contributions based on reputation systems.</p>
        <p>Another suggestion is to make <indexterm>participation<indexterm>as a side
              effect</indexterm></indexterm>participation a side effect. I’ve explored this idea in
          a blog post, looking for ideas on how to make a user assistance system show the fine lines
          of wear, like a cookbook that falls open to your favorite recipe because the binding has
          been flattened on your kitchen countertop.<fn>
            <p> http://justwriteclick.com/2008/05/28/can-online-help-show-read-wear/</p>
          </fn> This indicator of use is called “read wear.” Here are some of the ideas to indicate
          “read wear” that I came up with and people who commented on my blog entry added to. </p>
        <ul>
          <li>Model a wiki‘s “most active pages” feature, which shows the page with the most edits.
            However, the page with the most edits may be more controversial than truthful, so the
            most popular pages might be more useful.</li>
          <li>When a user searches, show the <indexterm>search<indexterm
              >relevance</indexterm></indexterm>most searched-for terms. Users might connect
            concepts more easily when they understand what others are searching for. </li>
          <li>Show the most recently viewed knowledge base articles or most popular articles. I
            found that useful in the past when searching through BMC Software’s rich knowledge base.
            Just as CNN and other news sites offer a list of the <indexterm>help, online<indexterm
                >most emailed topics</indexterm></indexterm>most <indexterm>email<indexterm
                >tracking</indexterm></indexterm>emailed stories per hour, you could show the most
              emailed<indexterm>help, online<indexterm>emailing topics</indexterm></indexterm>
            online help topics. </li>
          <li>Use <indexterm>tagging<indexterm>online help</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm
                >content<indexterm>tagging</indexterm></indexterm>tag <indexterm>clouds,
              tag</indexterm>clouds to display read wear as well, with the largest tag indicating
            the highest number of topics on that subject that users have tagged.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>I found that popularity, time spent on the page, rating on a page, and number of edits on
          a page are the strongest to weakest indicators of read wear for an online content
          system.</p>
        <p>Nielsen also encourages the use of <indexterm>content<indexterm>templates
            for</indexterm></indexterm>templates and draft content so that users don’t have to start
          from a blank page. I know a writer who pre-filled as many technical articles with as much
          information as he could before sending the draft copies to his Subject Matter Expert
          (SME). The SME, a recognized programmer who built software for electronic keyboards,
          happily added content into the pre-filled articles.</p>
        <p>Nielsen also says to <indexterm>forums<indexterm>rewarding participation
            in</indexterm></indexterm>reward, but not over-reward, participants, and he encourages
          the use of a reputation system. I especially like the idea of moderate rewards for
          participation so that dominant profiles do not take over the community. Balance is key,
          along with recognizing that you won’t overcome the community makeup.</p>
        <p>Growing your community should also contribute to the growth of <indexterm
              >participation<indexterm>growing</indexterm></indexterm>participation. Andy
            Oram<indexterm>Oram, Andy</indexterm>’s study<fn>
            <p>
              http://www.onlamp.com/pub/a/onlamp/2006/07/06/rethinking-community-documentation.html</p>
          </fn> of why people contribute documentation to free and <indexterm>open source<indexterm
              >contributions to</indexterm></indexterm>open source software projects shows that
          building communities is the clear winner. </p>
        <p>Applying the 90-9-1 rule makes the <indexterm>communities<indexterm
            >growing</indexterm></indexterm>growth of a <indexterm>wikis<indexterm>participation,
              increasing</indexterm></indexterm>community concrete. For example, if you start with 3
          writers out of 300 wiki participants and grow the community to 3,000 wiki participants,
          it’s possible to have 30 contributing heavily to your wiki project if the 1% large
          contribution number holds throughout the community’s growth.</p>
        <p>Some wiki examples show variances in these percentages, but as described earlier, certain
          best practices can shift the participant percentages. Following are two examples of wikis
          that have had their participation percentage values studied.</p>
        <p>Wikipedia Contributors<indexterm>Wikipedia</indexterm>
        </p>
        <p> The article “Who Writes Wikipedia” by Aaron <indexterm>Swartz, Aaron</indexterm>Swartz
          discusses the claims made by Jimbo Wales that on Wikipedia, “over 50% of all the edits are
          done by just .7% of the users ... 524 people.” Aaron Swartz describes the story he saw
          from his studies as follows:</p>
        <lq>
          <p>“When you put it all together, the story become [sic] clear: an outsider makes one edit
            to add a chunk of information, then insiders make several edits tweaking and
            reformatting it. In addition, insiders rack up thousands of edits doing things like
            changing the name of a category across the entire site—the kind of thing only insiders
            deeply care about. As a result, insiders account for the vast majority of the edits. But
            it’s the outsiders who provide nearly all of the content.” <fn>
              <p> http://www.aaronsw.com/weblog/whowriteswikipedia</p>
            </fn></p>
        </lq>
        <p><indexterm>MSDN</indexterm>MSDN Community Content Contributors</p>
        <p>Although not precisely a <indexterm>technical documentation<indexterm>wikis
              and</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm>wikis, examples<indexterm
            >MSDN</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm>community-generated content<indexterm>MSDN as
              example of</indexterm></indexterm>wiki, the Microsothat are wiki-like. According to
          the site as of December 20, 2007,<fn>
            <p> http://msdn2.microsoft.com/en-us/library/default.aspx</p>
          </fn> 1866 edits out of 10851 total edits were made by the top five contributors (three of
          whom are Microsoft employees). That percentage is slightly above 1% at 1.72%. Looking
          again on April 14, 2009, there are two Microsoft employees in the top five. There were
          over 6000 contributions from the top five contributors out of 31615 total edits, but a
          contribution can be a comment or a topic so it’s more difficult to measure contribution
          percentages.</p>
      </body>
    </subsection>
    <subsection
      id="d5e877">
      <title>Recruit other internal reviewers </title>
      <body>
        <p>Although most online communities strictly adhere to the 90-9-1 rule (where only 1 percent
          of the community contributes content), you can shift those numbers slightly by recruiting
          others in your company to offer their perspectives to the wiki and do minor edits and
          upkeep when needed. Have someone from customer support keep an eye on the recent changes
          or <indexterm>collaboration<indexterm>wikis and</indexterm></indexterm>comments
            RSS<indexterm>RSS (Really Simple Syndication)<indexterm>subscribing to
            wikis</indexterm></indexterm> feed and also ask a marketing or sales representative to
          do the same.</p>
      </body>
    </subsection>
    <subsection
      id="d5e891">
      <title>Do not expect a wiki to fix other broken areas</title>
      <body>
        <p>A wiki is an open documentation system that may reveal flaws in the system faster than
          you might like. Also, wiki collaboration can be a tricky balancing act, and if your
          writing team does not already collaborate and share well, a wiki may cause battles over
          who can see and edit which content items, and lead to other technology-based secrecy
          problems that can undermine the spirit of the wiki.</p>
      </body>
    </subsection>
    <subsection
      id="d5e896">
      <title>Do not build a wiki if customers do not want it</title>
      <body>
        <p>If your customers have not requested a wiki, there’s no need to build one or coerce them
          into thinking they need one. Instead, “wiki-fy” your documentation set by thinking about
          other aspects of wikis that you could adopt without actually using a wiki. How about a
          comment or a <indexterm>help, online<indexterm>rating topics</indexterm></indexterm>rating
          form on each help topic? Or, set up a method of ensuring that customers or service
          personnel get credit and perhaps a byline when they make significant contributions? Also
          realize that your customers may not know all of the features that a wiki could give them,
          such as notifications on content changes. </p>
      </body>
    </subsection>
    <subsection
      id="d5e905">
      <title>Wiki round tripping</title>
      <prolog>
        <metadata>
          <keywords>
            <indexterm>round tripping, wiki</indexterm>
          </keywords>
        </metadata>
      </prolog>
      <body>
        <p><indexterm>wikis<indexterm>single-sourcing content</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm
              >content<indexterm>round tripping</indexterm></indexterm>Single-sourcing—<indexterm
              >wikis<indexterm>round tripping</indexterm></indexterm>writing once and <indexterm
              >publishing<indexterm>wiki content</indexterm></indexterm>publishing the <indexterm
              >content<indexterm>single-sourcing</indexterm></indexterm>content to many different
          formats—has been a popular documentation method for many years now. Many technical writers
          already write in a single-sourcing<indexterm>single-sourcing</indexterm> environment and
          wonder if a wiki is yet another output. I’d suggest different approaches for wiki as
          source and wiki as output, depending on the type of content and the community that you
          expect to contribute to the wiki. </p>
        <p>Wiki round tripping is the conversion from source to wiki and back. It may mean
          processing information files in XML or XHTML, generating output to a wiki in wikitext,
          collecting the changes on the wiki, and folding them back into the source files,
          effectively taking the content on a trip around from source to wiki to source. Here are
          some suggestions for methods that may work. </p>
        <ul>
          <li>True round tripping in a wiki is feasible, if you don’t mind edits coming through the
            wiki back into your source. This type of round trip essentially means that the wiki is a
            source of content. </li>
          <li>A round trip in which the wiki is the continual output would mean that every time you
            publish the single source, you publish to a wiki. In this type of round trip, the
            ability to view a revision history is essential for the wiki community to understand
            what changed after the “publishing round trip event” occurred.</li>
          <li>A round trip in which the wiki is static and published as-is to another format, such
            as a book or PDF<indexterm>PDF, as wiki output</indexterm>, is yet another model. </li>
          <li>You can populate a wiki with content that is written in an easy-to-use authoring
            system with which your writers are familiar. This method is an excellent way to get an
            active wiki up and running. However, if you intend for the wiki to be more than just a
            fancy <indexterm>help, online<indexterm>compared to wikis</indexterm></indexterm>help
            system with comments, and you want to allow for community edits, then your wiki becomes
            the source from that initial publishing point onward. </li>
        </ul>
        <p>Another idea in the wiki round tripping arena is using DITA<indexterm>DITA</indexterm> as
          an in-between authoring-source-and-wiki-storage mechanism. At <indexterm>IBM<indexterm
              >BlueBooks wiki</indexterm></indexterm>IBM, they have successfully converted
          unstructured FrameMaker chapters into DITA topics and then used XSLT to write to
            <indexterm>MediaWiki<indexterm>from FrameMaker to</indexterm></indexterm>MediaWiki for
          an internal wiki used by their 60,000 services personnel to document complex and specific
          configurations for optimal performance or for best practices. These special documents are
          called RedBooks, and the BlueBooks wiki uses RedBooks content to allow experts to
          collaborate with each other on revisions of existing content. DITA serves as a data
          conduit, allowing the information to flow into the wiki.</p>
        <p>Round tripping wiki content might be necessary only if you cannot adjust to the wiki as
          your authoring environment. You might have business reasons for protecting the content by
          strictly limiting authors, or you might be able to gain efficiencies or get a particular
          output by using an already-familiar authoring tool. </p>
        <p>Business cases for round tripping include the need to tap into an existing technical
          person already recognized in the field by allowing their wiki edits to return to the
          single-sourced content, the need for high-quality print output from a source other than
          the wiki, and the need to keep the tool “experts” within the non-wiki tool with which they
          are familiar. Other considerations include the volume of edits, the need for semantic
          markup, the amount of “workaround” documentation that might cause contention on an
          external wiki, and the audience itself. </p>
      </body>
    </subsection>
    <subsection
      id="d5e976">
      <title>Single-sourcing in XML and repurposing the content</title>
      <body>
        <p>Wikis can be sourced from other files or document types, including XML schemas like
            DITA<indexterm>DITA</indexterm>. If you use single-sourced content to populate or seed a
          wiki initially, you may also consider round tripping the content. If you’re trying to make
          a help system that looks like a wiki, but you are not taking advantage of the
          collaborative and crowdsourcing<indexterm>crowdsourcing</indexterm> aspects of a wiki, you
          just have a help system on the web. Also, the source files from which you created the wiki
          become effectively dead content if you go to the wiki and never re-connect back to the
          source files.</p>
        <p>But there are content models that work well with a wiki as the published output from XML
          source. You can use the wiki as a deliverable, and use it not for editing but to collect
          end-user comments and offer notifications. </p>
        <p>You may have another wiki published from XML source where only consultants have editing
          capabilities. A few people would contribute to that type of wiki and edit the articles
          that are pre-seeded by an information development team. In a wiki for such a focused
          audience, technical debate about scenarios and implementations may occur. Any edits to
          wiki pages would be manageable to manually change in your XML source files. </p>
        <p>If your wiki becomes the single source, and you output <indexterm>wikis<indexterm>PDF
              output from</indexterm></indexterm>PDFs or <indexterm>wikislices</indexterm>wikislices
          from it, be aware that wiki syntax<indexterm>wikis<indexterm
            >syntax</indexterm></indexterm> is, for many, a step backwards to the days of manual
          markup and may not be as quick and efficient as today’s authoring tools. You may be
          limited to only the subset of HTML markup that the wiki allows, or you may have access to
          complex macros, but at the cost of having to learn the macro language for the wiki
          application and perhaps teach other users. </p>
      </body>
    </subsection>
    <subsection
      id="d5e1005">
      <title>Understanding wiki patterns and wiki structures</title>
      <body>
        <p>Wikipatterns.com is an extremely useful site to help you start <indexterm>wikis<indexterm
              >patterns</indexterm></indexterm>wiki writing or maintenance. The book of the same
          name gives insights into wiki adoption and offers valuable case studies. Wiki patterns and
          other design patterns originate conceptually from architecture patterns. For example, an
          entryway pattern, be it arched tile, cobblestone, or a simple wooden gate with a dirt
          floor, offers a solution to the problem or question at hand, which is, “How do I enter
          this structure?” For a wiki, a comparison to an entryway pattern might be the welcoming
          pattern, where a current wiki contributor leaves a note on a new wiki contributor’s
            “<indexterm>wikis<indexterm>talk pages</indexterm></indexterm>talk” page or drops them a
          welcoming email after their first edit.</p>
        <p>Wiki patterns help you understand the people patterns and adoption patterns for the wiki.
          One adoption anti-pattern is Too much structure.<fn>
            <p> http://wikipatterns.com/display/wikipatterns/Too+much+structure</p>
          </fn> When you overload a wiki with strict guidelines or lots of empty pages, trying to
          get people to contribute, you may notice that the wiki does not grow organically like you
          hoped. In Wikipatterns, Stewart Mader suggests, “A wiki will evolve into the optimal
          organization of information as people use it, and it’s better to adjust the structure
          based on the content, instead of the other way around.” If a wiki is meant to be a content
          deliverable, strict hierarchy may work just fine to help readers find content. But a wiki
          that you expect to have contributions to should have the flexibility to grow as the
          community sees fit. </p>
      </body>
    </subsection>
    <subsection
      id="d5e1025">
      <title>Inheriting or maintaining a large wiki</title>
      <body>
        <p>Some wikis are already in place and in a certain state by the time you are introduced to
          them. How can you begin work on a large wiki, and what are some areas where you can help
          by contributing to wiki content?</p>
        <p>With the <indexterm>One Laptop per Child<indexterm>wiki</indexterm></indexterm>OLPC wiki,
          an individual contributor, David <indexterm>Farning, David</indexterm>Farning, went
          through the wiki and found the following categories. It’s an accurate content analysis
          based on my experience with the wiki. It was impressive and also helped explain my initial
          bewilderment at how to wrap my arms around the entire wiki.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Philosophy</li>
          <li>Contributing</li>
          <li>Creating</li>
          <li>Curating</li>
          <li>Projects</li>
          <li>Deliverable</li>
          <li>In progress</li>
          <li>Ideas</li>
          <li>Management</li>
        </ul>
        <p>After the volunteer came up with these categories, he asked SJ <indexterm>Klein,
            SJ</indexterm>Klein, director of community content<indexterm>community-generated
              content<indexterm>contributions to</indexterm></indexterm> and long-time Wikipedian,
          if he thought the wiki needed structure. SJ Klein said that a wiki is purposefully without
          hierarchy (flat), especially for projects, to not force a parent or sibling sense for
          projects. He also said, however, that if you have a specific tree hierarchy in mind, feel
          free to develop the idea in some temporary space. So, when you are working on a large
          wiki, if you have some good ideas about organization, set them up and then ask for
          community feedback. </p>
        <p>Here are a few more ideas for starting out in a large wiki environment:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Although the task might seem similar to starting a large writing project, I have found
            that wiki editing has some subtle differences because of the collaboration and community
            “vibe” already present behind the pages. You have to work to figure out that vibe, and
            then determine your course. New people must get a feel for the community so that they
            can figure out who they might irritate or please by editing a topic and whether they
            have the confidence to provide correct content.</li>
          <li>Figure out your role within the wiki community. It might take a while for you to get
            to know who’s there, what <i>their</i> roles are, and where you might best fit in.
            Introduce yourself with your profile<indexterm>profile, online</indexterm> page,
            following the wiki pattern, <indexterm>MySpace<indexterm>wiki
              pattern</indexterm></indexterm>MySpace.<fn>
              <p> http://www.wikipatterns.com/display/wikipatterns/MySpace</p>
            </fn></li>
          <li>Just like a newbie on a writing team, find out if there’s some “grunt work” that you
            can do to get your feet wet and to gain the community’s trust.</li>
          <li>Deletions in a wiki can incur some wrath, so they seem risky to do when you are
            starting out. If you do think some content should be deleted, contact the original
            author or the big contributors and ask whether you can mark it for deletion. Then, mark
            it and hope that someone else (a wiki administrator) determines that it should be
            deleted.</li>
          <li>Start small by <indexterm>tagging<indexterm>wiki
            content</indexterm></indexterm>tagging or applying templates. Those tasks help you get a
            feel for the bigger picture.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>If you want to coach others who come to your <indexterm>wikis<indexterm>collaboration
              in</indexterm></indexterm>wiki looking to do editing, you might look at the
          Mozillazine Knowledge Base’s guidelines on their About page.<fn>
            <p> http://kb.mozillazine.org/MozillaZine_Knowledge_Base:About</p>
          </fn> For writers who want to come in and “make big changes,” their wiki states “If you
          want to propose changes that affect a number of articles, for example a new categorization
          system or a generally reformatting of a class of articles, you should make your suggestion
          at [the wiki page] Knowledge Base changes. Doing so will give other editors and chance to
          give their opinions on the proposal. Even if you don’t think your change will be
          implemented, we’re still interested in hearing your opinions.”<fn>
            <p> http://kb.mozillazine.org/Knowledge_Base_changes</p>
          </fn> I appreciate this informative and welcoming statement because it helps contributors
          understand the way to approach their large wiki and its community members.</p>
      </body>
    </subsection>
  </subsection>
  <subsection
    id="d5e1115">
    <title>Alternatives when a wiki is not the right match </title>
    <body>
      <p>If you determine that business objectives do not warrant a conversation or community-based
        documentation, such as a wiki or customer-focused blog, you might consider different ways of
        implementing the changes to your current documentation output or methods.</p>
    </body>
    <subsection
      id="d5e1119">
      <title>Online help possibilities</title>
      <body>
        <p>If you are evaluating tools for <indexterm>wikis<indexterm>comparison to online
              help</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm>content<indexterm>online
            help</indexterm></indexterm>online help, you may want to seek out online help tools that
          integrate <indexterm>comments<indexterm>in help</indexterm></indexterm>comments,
          community, or <indexterm>conversations<indexterm
          >enabling</indexterm></indexterm>conversation within the documentation.</p>
        <p>An important first step may be to get your user assistance on the Internet. If your
            <indexterm>help, online<indexterm>searching within</indexterm></indexterm>online help is
          not <indexterm>search<indexterm>online help and</indexterm></indexterm>searchable because
          it is not on the Internet, consider ways to put it online rather than offline.<indexterm
            >help, online<indexterm>integrating conversations in</indexterm></indexterm></p>
        <p>Consider a <indexterm>help, online<indexterm>feedback
          tools</indexterm></indexterm>feedback server or Javascript solution that offers tools that
          enable <indexterm>comments<indexterm>in help</indexterm></indexterm>comments and other
          social web integrations. You may want to implement a rating system for each help topic or
          a comment form for each topic. Wiki applications already provide these features, but you
          may be able to integrate a rating system using existing web content tools.</p>
        <p>If you decide to share the contents of your online <indexterm>help, online<indexterm
              >licensing</indexterm></indexterm>help by licensing it with a <indexterm>Creative
            Commons license</indexterm>Creative Commons license, you could embed the CC image at the
          bottom of each page and change the licensing information page in your online help. </p>
        <p>The following table offers some questions to ask about your online help system to look
          for possibilities for integrating conversations or communities.</p>
      </body>
    </subsection>
  </subsection>
  <subsection
    id="d5e1185">
    <title>Talking with writers of wikis</title>
    <body>
      <p>You can learn from writers who document their products with wikis. This interview is with
          <indexterm>Elling, Dee</indexterm>Dee Elling, who maintains a wiki about CodeGear for
        Embarcadero. While researching my STC <i>Intercom</i> article about wikis and technical
          documentation<fn>
          <p> https://www.stc.org/intercom/PDFs/2007/20070910_16-19.pdf</p>
        </fn>, I interviewed Dee Elling via phone and email because she left a helpful comment on my
        talk.bmc.com blog entry about a DITA<indexterm>DITA</indexterm> and wiki combo. Dee’s the
        manager of the documentation group at CodeGear and she blogs at
        http://blogs.codegear.com/deeelling/.</p>
      <p>Interview about wikis for technical documentation with Dee Elling of Embarcadero</p>
      <p><i>July 26th, 2007 </i></p>
      <p><ph>Anne</ph>: What are some of the factors for selecting a wiki software package?</p>
      <p><ph>Dee</ph>: <i>I’ve encountered hesitation from some writers about using a markup
          interface. Many writers preferred a Word-like GUI interface, such as
          Confluence</i><indexterm>Confluence</indexterm><i> provides. Another consideration is
          cost, since there is not always a budget for new systems; at CodeGear we use
          </i><indexterm>MediaWiki<indexterm>at CodeGear</indexterm></indexterm><i>MediaWiki.
          Primarily we manage internal information such as schedules and doc plans; lately we are
          collaborating with engineers to write FAQs and release notes.</i></p>
      <p><i>At my previous employer, one engineering team was writing the documentation themselves
          on the wiki (using outlines provided by the writer), and the writer cleaned it up and
          converted it to PDF</i><indexterm>PDF, as wiki output</indexterm><i> for distribution with
          the product. That is a great use case which I believe could seed the
          adoption</i><indexterm>adopting wikis in documentation process</indexterm><i> of wikis
          into the documentation process, especially in companies where there are limited doc
          resources.</i></p>
      <p><i>At CodeGear I can post copyrighted material to our Developer Network. The Developer
          Network technology allows comments on postings, which is not the same as wiki but a good
          start. Since joining, I have started to post traditional doc content as “articles” there.
          I’ve already fixed a few doc issues due to rapid customer feedback! We are also working on
          a design to make the website interface more wiki-like.</i></p>
      <p><ph>Anne</ph>: How do you get legal approval for such an open-edit site?</p>
      <p><ph>Dee</ph>: <i>At my previous company I never got to the stage of implementing a public
          wiki. However I had many discussions about the legal aspects related to the product
          documentation. The legal aspects seem complex, but lawyers can write new terms for new
          situations.</i></p>
      <p><i>At CodeGear the issue will involve intellectual property, but the user base is so active
          on the internet that there are few “secrets”. More important will be the issue of
          releasing information too soon or otherwise getting in trouble with SOX compliance. (That
          makes my head spin!)</i></p>
      <p><ph>Anne</ph>: What are the considerations when choosing where the wiki is hosted?</p>
      <p><ph>Dee</ph>: <i>Cost and reliability are factors, but most important is buy-in from the IT
          department, who would likely manage the hosting.</i></p>
      <p><ph>Anne</ph>: Which types of products are best targeted for a wiki?</p>
      <p><ph>Dee</ph>: <i>Complex software products are a good example. There is so much flexibility
          in software and product documentation cannot cover every use case. The wiki lets
          </i><indexterm>collaboration<indexterm>with customers</indexterm></indexterm><i>customers
          add content that is relevant to their own use cases, and that will benefit others.</i></p>
      <p><ph>Anne</ph>: How can you encourage your users to contribute?</p>
      <p><ph>Dee</ph>: <i>Keeping up a dialog with the customers is helpful. If you respond to them,
          a dialog develops, and they are more likely to contribute again.</i></p>
      <p><ph>Anne</ph>: What are some of the success factors for the wikis that contain technical
        documentation?</p>
      <p><ph>Dee</ph>: <i>Does it result in more positive feedback from customers? Do customers help
          each other and contribute to strengthening the installed base? Does it increase product
          visibility and mindshare in the market? Is it perceived as a strategic advantage over
          competitors? Does it cut down on tech support phone calls?</i></p>
      <p><ph>Anne</ph>: What traps should be avoided?</p>
      <p><ph>Dee</ph>: <i>The trap of not responding or not paying attention. Writers must
          diligently track the “living documents” they have created, and they must truly
          collaborate. If customers contribute and their contributions go unrecognized, they may
          think that the company is not fully supporting them.</i></p>
      <p><i>Public wiki documentation must be actively managed and that takes more writer effort
          than in the past, when documents were forgotten as soon as they went to manufacturing.
          Contrary to the fear that with wikis you don’t need writers anymore, I believe that with
          wikis the role of the writer will grow.</i></p>
    </body>
  </subsection>
  <subsection
    id="d5e1333">
    <title>Wiki examples</title>
    <body>
      <p>This section contains examples of some of the highest profile wikis in use today for
        technical documentation, targeting end-users of a product or service, or assisting
        developers in their tasks. Although only a small number of technical documentation wikis are
        publicly available, I believe that many more wikis are used internally in companies to
        enhance <indexterm>collaboration<indexterm>internal</indexterm></indexterm>collaboration
        within a company.</p>
    </body>
    <subsection
      id="d5e1342">
      <title>Adobe Labs</title>
      <body>
        <p>labs.adobe.com/wiki</p>
        <p>The Adobe Labs <indexterm>wikis, examples<indexterm>Adobe
          Labs</indexterm></indexterm>wiki (see ) targets developers using Adobe technology and is
          one of the top wikis for daily-use statistics according to Alexa rank.<fn>
            <p> http://www.alexa.com/site/ds/top_sites?ts_mode=global&amp;lang=none&amp;page=1</p>
          </fn> This example shows how a <indexterm>communities<indexterm>wikis
              supporting</indexterm></indexterm>community can build up around a wiki—developers
          helping other developers accomplish a specific task. This type of wiki can help build
          communities of practice more quickly than at any time prior to the introduction of wiki
          te</p>
      </body>
    </subsection>
    <subsection
      id="d5e1363">
      <title>he </title>
      <prolog>
        <metadata>
          <keywords>
            <indexterm>Apache</indexterm>
          </keywords>
        </metadata>
      </prolog>
      <body>
        <p>wiki.apache.org</p>
        <p>Apache <indexterm>wikis, examples<indexterm>Apache</indexterm></indexterm>is a collection
          of <indexterm>open source<indexterm>Apache</indexterm></indexterm>open source tools that
          run the majority of web servers on the Internet. Apache is one of the best-known
          successful open source software examples, and it is a natural choice for its documentation
          to be available in a wiki (see ), open to all for editing and contribution.</p>
      </body>
    </subsection>
    <subsection
      id="d5e1384">
      <title>eBay </title>
      <prolog>
        <metadata>
          <keywords>
            <indexterm>eBay wiki</indexterm>
          </keywords>
        </metadata>
      </prolog>
      <body>
        <p>wiki.ebay.com</p>
        <p>In 2006, eBay created a <indexterm>wikis, examples<indexterm
          >eBay</indexterm></indexterm>wiki (see ) so that sellers could help other sellers and to
          cut down on customer support calls.<fn>
            <p> http://www.forbes.com/markets/2006/06/14/ebay-0614markets04.html</p>
          </fn> This wiki should have worked well for many reasons. First of all, sellers are
          already trying to promote themselves and their stores, so contributing content helps them
          stand out in the crowded marketplace. Also, because a grading system is already motivating
          sellers, they are accustomed to online rating systems that also motivate them to continue
          and enhance their wiki contributions. However, eBay discontinued support for the wiki and
          now hosts it at ebaywiki.jot.com. No active contributions are sought, and the wiki
          articles are only retrievable, not writeable.</p>
      </body>
    </subsection>
    <subsection
      id="d5e1403">
      <title>Microso</title>
      <body>
        <p>msdn2.microsoft.com/en-us/library/default.aspx</p>
        <p>Microsoft’s Developer Network (MSDN), , has been watched closely as one of the first
          forays into community-contributed content, but as it has evolved over the last few years,
          it barely qualifies as a wiki by most wiki standards.<fn>
            <p>
              http://searchwindevelopment.techtarget.com/news/article/0,289142,sid8_gci1211391,00.html</p>
          </fn> Rather than allowing any article to be edited, MSDN allows only certain highly
          structured <indexterm>content<indexterm
          >community-generated</indexterm></indexterm>contributions such as code examples. The
          system strongly types the information to be entered in a web form. Also, the MSDN wiki’s
          top contributors are Microsoft employees rather than outsiders to the company. Still, many
          contributions are made to the wiki-like system, and it is important to watch and learn
          from large-scale <indexterm>content<indexterm
          >user-generated</indexterm></indexterm>deployments of user-generated </p>
      </body>
    </subsection>
    <subsection
      id="d5e1425">
      <title>nDS </title>
      <body>
        <p>www.opends.org/wiki</p>
        <p>The <indexterm>OpenDS</indexterm>OpenDS <indexterm>wikis, examples<indexterm
              >OpenDS</indexterm></indexterm>wiki (see ) was created because of the open source
          nature of the OpenDS product, and the wiki is the only source of documentation for the
          product. Three writers are paid to maintain it, just as any technical writer is paid to
          create and maintain documentation in any other tool. The writer Ragan <indexterm>Haggard,
            Ragan</indexterm>Haggard has presented a few times<fn>
            <p> https://www.opends.org/wiki/page/RHaggard</p>
          </fn> on his experience with wikis for documentation, and he likes the easy access and
          simple interface that the wiki, which uses the <indexterm>MediaWiki<indexterm>for OpenDS
              wiki</indexterm></indexterm>MediaWiki application, offers. However, community
          participation has not been growing. This type of response has been common for wiki
          roll-outs related to product documentation—apathy is more prevalent than any type of
          vanda</p>
      </body>
    </subsection>
    <subsection
      id="d5e1454">
      <title>Cisco </title>
      <body>
        <p>docwiki.cisco.com</p>
        <p>After <indexterm>Cisco</indexterm><indexterm>wikis, examples<indexterm
            >Cisco</indexterm></indexterm>Cisco first rolled out a customer support wiki and
          experienced some success with it, the Cisco documentation team was asked to create a wiki
          for end-user documentation, shown in . It is still a young wiki for external use, and
          Cisco conducted a careful pilot project, allowing internal-only access, before releasing
          the wiki for external use.</p>
      </body>
    </subsection>
  </subsection>
  <subsection
    id="d5e1468">
    <title>Wiki wrap up</title>
    <body>
      <p>While organizing the content and picking the right tool are important, there are many other
        implications when using a wiki for information delivery. Understand that the 90-9-1 rule
        means you will have a small club of one-percenters, and that one-percenter may be you. The
        community built around the wiki is as important or more important than the tool used to
        build the wiki. Because wikis are not like traditional documentation, strict style guidance
        and strict hierarchies may not work for the community that embraces the wiki. </p>
    </body>
  </subsection>
</chapter>
