<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<chapter
  id="d5e2"><title><ph>Easter Seals Internet Public Discourse Policy</ph></title><prolog><metadata
        ><keywords>
        <indexterm>Easter Seals Internet Public Discourse Policy</indexterm>
        <indexterm>policies, social computing<indexterm>Easter Seals</indexterm></indexterm>
        <indexterm>Easter Seals</indexterm>
      </keywords></metadata></prolog><body><p><indexterm>blogs<indexterm>Easter
        Seals</indexterm></indexterm><ph>Easter Seals Internet Public Discourse </ph><indexterm
          >blogging<indexterm>policy</indexterm></indexterm><ph>Policy SECTION III PART I-9 Approved
        by board: July 14, 2007</ph></p><p><ph>The Internet Public Discourse policy applies to
        Easter Seals headquarters and to Affiliates.</ph></p><p><ph>Easter Seals has always
        encouraged staff and volunteers to be champions on behalf of the organization by spreading
        the word about Easter Seals’ work in providing life-changing solutions that help all people
        with disabilities have equal opportunities to live, learn, work and play.</ph></p><p><ph>The
        rapidly growing phenomenon of blogging, social networks and other forms of online electronic
        publishing are emerging as unprecedented opportunities for outreach, information-sharing and
        advocacy.</ph></p><p><ph>Easter Seals encourages staff members and volunteers to use the
        Internet to blog and talk about our organization, our services and your work. Our goals
        are:</ph></p><ul><li><ph>To connect with and provide help and hope to children and adults
          with disabilities and the families who love them;</ph></li><li><ph>To encourage support of
          Easter Seals’ services and programs; and</ph></li><li><ph>To share the expertise of Easter
          Seals’ staff and volunteers.</ph></li></ul><p><ph>Whether or not an Easter Seals staff
        member or volunteer chooses to create or participate in a blog or online
        community</ph><indexterm>online community</indexterm><ph> on their own time is his or her
        own decision. However, it is in Easter Seals’ interest that staff and volunteers understand
        the responsibilities in discussing Easter Seals in the public square known as the World Wide
        Web.</ph></p><p><ph>Guidelines for Easter Seals Bloggers</ph></p><p><ph>1. Be Responsible.
        Blogs, wikis, photo-sharing and other forms of online dialogue (unless posted by authorized
        Easter Seals personnel) are individual interactions, not corporate communications. Easter
        Seals staff and volunteers are personally responsible for their posts.</ph></p><p><ph>2. Be
        Smart. A blog or community post is visible to the entire world. Remember that what you write
        will be public for a long time – be respectful to the company, employees, clients, corporate
        sponsors and competitors, and protect your privacy.</ph></p><p><ph>3. Identify Yourself.
        Authenticity and transparency are driving factors of the blogosphere. List your name and
        when relevant, role at Easter Seals, when you blog about Easter Seals-related
      topics.</ph></p><p><ph>4. Include a Disclaimer. If you blog or post to an online forum in an
        unofficial capacity, make it clear that you are speaking for yourself and not on behalf of
        Easter Seals. If your post has to do with your work or subjects associated with Easter
        Seals, use a disclaimer such as this: “The postings on this site are my own and don’t
        represent Easter Seals’ positions, strategies or opinions.” This is a good practice but does
        not exempt you from being held accountable for what you write.</ph></p><p><ph>5. Respect
        Privacy of Others. Don’t publish or cite personal details and photographs about Easter Seals
        clients, employees, volunteers, corporate partners or vendors without their permission. Any
        disclosure of confidential information will be subject to the same Easter Seals personnel
        policies that apply to wrongful dissemination of information via email, conversations and
        written correspondence.</ph></p><p><ph>6. Write What You Know. You have a unique perspective
        on our organization based on your talents, skills and current responsibilities. Share your
        knowledge, your passions and your personality in your posts by writing about what you know.
        If you’re interesting and authentic, you’ll attract readers who understand your specialty
        and interests. Don’t spread gossip, hearsay or assumptions.</ph></p><p><ph>7. Include Links.
        Find out who else is blogging about the same topic and cite them with a link or make a post
        on their blog. Links are what determine a blog’s popularity rating on blog search engines
        like Technorati. It’s also a way of connecting to the bigger conversation and reaching out
        to new audiences. Be sure to also link to easterseals.com</ph></p><p><ph>8. Be Respectful.
        It’s okay to disagree with others but cutting down or insulting readers, employees, bosses
        or corporate sponsors and vendors is not. Respect your audience and don’t use obscenities,
        personal insults, ethnic slurs or other disparaging language to express yourself.</ph></p><p
        ><ph>9. Work Matters. Ensure that your blogging doesn’t interfere with your work
        commitments. Discuss with your manager if you are uncertain about the appropriateness of
        publishing during business hours.</ph></p><p><ph>10. Don’t Tell Secrets. The nature of your
        job may provide you with access to confidential information regarding Easter Seals, Easter
        Seals beneficiaries, or fellow employees. Respect and maintain the confidentiality that has
        been entrusted to you. Don’t divulge or discuss proprietary information, internal documents,
        personal details about other people or other confidential
  material.</ph></p></body></chapter>
