<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<chapter
  id="d5e2"><title>Commenting and Connecting with Users</title><abstract>
    <p
      outputclass="intro-quote">The biggest mistake is believing there is one right way to listen,
      &#8232;to talk, to have a conversation - or a relationship. &#8232;—Deborah Tannen</p>
    <p
      outputclass="intro-quote">It was impossible to get a conversation going, &#8232;everybody was
      talking too much.&#8232;—Yogi Berra</p>
  </abstract>
  <prolog/>
  <body>
    <p>There are new social computing tools being invented all the time, and traditional websites
      are also finding ways to incorporate tagging, sharing, and other collaboration helpers in
      their content. <indexterm>conversations<indexterm>blogs</indexterm></indexterm>Blogs have led
      the way. <indexterm>blogs<indexterm>description of</indexterm></indexterm>Blogs, short for
      weblogs, are websites with reverse chronological entries (listing them from newest to oldest).
      Topics range from personal to professional, offering galleries of photography or comics, and
      can be written, audio, or video entries. </p>
    <p>When <indexterm>content<indexterm>blogs</indexterm></indexterm>blogging, realize first and
      foremost that a conversation doesn’t have to be a direct connection between writer and
      customer. You can blog about your area of expertise which shows the customer your passion for
      your work, which translates into high quality products or services from you when representing
      your company on a blog. A blog entry can offer a link opportunity for a customer to connect to
      you. </p>
    <p>Also think about how you can help customers connect with each other in comments or in
      trackbacks, which notify the original blog author that you have linked to a particular entry.
      This section discusses ideas for starting conversations, building on the stages of listening,
      participating, and offering a platform. </p>
  </body>
  <subsection
    id="d5e29">
    <title>Listening and monitoring conversations </title>
    <body>
      <p>Because they are typically fast readers and collectors of information, writers are often
        excellent blog monitors and can easily handle multiple notifications from news feeds or
          RSS<indexterm>RSS (Really Simple Syndication)<indexterm>listening to conversation
            through</indexterm></indexterm> subscriptions. If the technical writer is also
        maintaining a blog and online presence<indexterm>presence, online</indexterm>, commenting on
        others blogs in the field is a great way to join the conversation. Also consider joining or
        moderating a customer <indexterm>forums<indexterm>participating
          in</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm>forums<indexterm
        >moderating</indexterm></indexterm>forum or board. If your product is sold on a website like
        amazon.com, you can find conversations going on in the reviews and review comments as well
        as blog entries. </p>
    </body>
    <subsection
      id="d5e50">
      <title>Reading and commenting on blogs</title>
      <body>
        <p>I believe the best <indexterm>blogs<indexterm>starting</indexterm></indexterm>starting
          point for blogging<indexterm>blogs<indexterm>commenting on</indexterm></indexterm> is to
          read <indexterm>blogs<indexterm>reading</indexterm></indexterm>blogs. Follow the ones that
          interest you personally and professionally by using an RSS feed reader<indexterm>feed
            readers</indexterm> such as Bloglines<indexterm>Bloglines</indexterm> or <indexterm
              >Google<indexterm>Reader</indexterm></indexterm>Google Reader. As you begin reading
          and collecting subscriptions to blogs, you will notice the discussions in the <indexterm
              >comments<indexterm>on blog posts</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm>comments<indexterm
              >on blog posts</indexterm></indexterm>comments. Once you feel confident and interested
          enough in a topic or post that you can contribute a <indexterm>conversations<indexterm
              >joining</indexterm></indexterm>comment, write your comment, and make that connection.
          If beginning even an internal-audience blog is intimidating, consider your first foray
          into blogging to be commenting on other’s internal blogs. And you certainly should read
          blogs often before beginning to write for one yourself to get a sense of style, tone, and
          voice. </p>
      </body>
    </subsection>
  </subsection>
  <subsection
    id="d5e95">
    <title>Starting and maintaining a blog </title>
    <body>
      <p>Starting a blog may seem overwhelming at first. Not only do you have to choose a tool and
        platform with which to start, you must also begin the daunting task of writing and
        maintaining regular posts. The Groundswell<indexterm>Groundswell</indexterm> authors say
        that a good measure of whether you have the stamina and energy to keep up with regular
        blogging is to <indexterm>blogging<indexterm>practicing</indexterm></indexterm>try to write
        five entries. If you cannot sustain the writing effort for the time it takes to write five
        entries, you should reconsider whether you can keep up with a blog’s needs.</p>
    </body>
    <subsection
      id="d5e108">
      <title>Choosing a blog platform</title>
      <prolog>
        <metadata>
          <keywords>
            <indexterm>blogging<indexterm>platforms</indexterm></indexterm>
            <indexterm>platforms</indexterm>
          </keywords>
        </metadata>
      </prolog>
      <body>
        <p>I was fortunate when just starting blogging because the blogging tool was already
          selected. All I had to do was get registered and start writing. I could also practice with
          the blogging interface itself, learning what I liked and disliked in a blogging engine.
          Because the engine choices were out of my hands in my early blog writing attempts (the
          internal BMC blogs were maintained on a Sun<indexterm>Sun Microsystems<indexterm>blogging
              platform</indexterm></indexterm> blogging platform), I did not have the added pressure
          of evaluating<indexterm>evaluation<indexterm>of blogging engines</indexterm></indexterm>
          tools.</p>
        <p>If the blog platform is not already selected for you, compare blog platforms at
            <indexterm>weblogmatrix.org</indexterm><indexterm>blogging<indexterm
            >tools</indexterm></indexterm>weblogmatrix.org to assist in your selection process. The
          system requirements for the platform may eliminate some. Another consideration for
          choosing a blog platform is the ability to connect to the audience you want to converse
          with using comments and link notifications called trackbacks. Trackback notifications are
          given to the blogger when you link to their blog entry, but typically only work within the
          same blogging system. For example, <indexterm>WordPress</indexterm>WordPress blogs cannot
          notify Blogger blogs about a link to an entry, so the intended trackback does not appear
          near the comments on the entry. Spam prevention and comment moderation are also important
          features to include in your analysis. </p>
        <p>If you need to design a theme for the blog to match your company’s brand, you also want
          to study the ease with which you can modify the templates yourself or contract for visual
          design work on a particular blog platform.</p>
        <p>The basic expectations that readers have for a blog are comments, subscriptions, and easy
          linking to individual entries. Without a subscription system, like an RSS or Atom feed, a
          website cannot be a blog. </p>
      </body>
    </subsection>
    <subsection
      id="d5e143">
      <title>Continuity of posts</title>
      <body>
        <p>When I first proposed that I start a blog for BMC Software, my role was writing solutions
          documentation for combinations of products that solved specific business needs. My
          proposal was accepted immediately because of the type of customer we were trying to reach
          with our particular type of writing assignments. Blogging about my experiences while I
          learned about ITIL (the IT (Information Technology) Infrastructure Library) and Business
          Service Management would help others learn with me. This type of “learn with me” message
          was a good match for the blog medium. </p>
        <p>Before writing the proposal, I walked across to a fellow technical writer’s office who I
          knew was a blogger with a decent following and asked her, how many posts a week would I
          need to promise in order to keep a set of readers? She said two a week at a minimum with
          three a week being ideal. I wrote into the proposal that I would write a minimum of two
          posts a week which would be about four hours or ten percent of my time. I kept that
          schedule up, aiming for a Tuesday and Thursday post, and was one of the more prolific
          bloggers on the site. A few months after launching talk.bmc.com, they instituted a policy
          that you had to have at least one blog update every two months or your blog would be taken
          off the site. This type of requirement is a good idea for corporate sites that want
          committed bloggers and dynamic content.</p>
        <p>My initial work in blogging was internal to BMC Software, which limited my potential
          readers, but helped me focus my audience. I could practice my voice and write limited
          topics while finding what I liked about blogging and where the rewards might be so that I
          could justify the time and effort I was investing. I learned about post and commenting
          frequency, where comments came from, how to respond, and how to grow readership. </p>
        <p>After getting comfortable with and learning from my internal blog experience, I next
          began blogging externally on the talk.bmc.com site, using the Plone engine already set up
          for us. Because <indexterm>moderation<indexterm>blog
          comments</indexterm></indexterm>comments were moderated by other BMC staffers, I did not
          have to worry about spam deletion and comment moderation; I could focus on researching and
          writing entries. If your company offers any blogging platform, I highly recommend that you
          take an experimental path for learning about blogging and determining if there is a return
          on investment<indexterm>return on investment (ROI)<indexterm
            >blogging</indexterm></indexterm> (or <indexterm>reach and influence (R and
            I)</indexterm>Reach and Influence) equation that will work for your blogging
          efforts.</p>
        <p>If you want to take a break from blogging but still have fresh blog posts on your site,
          you could write posts ahead of time and set them for a publish date in the future. If you
          can’t take the time to get that far ahead in publishing you can also ask for <indexterm
              >blogs<indexterm>guest contributors</indexterm></indexterm>guest posts. This technique
          works well for planned extended leaves such as maternity leave or for avoiding burnout. In
          my case, when I was out raising babies, I wanted the voice to be genuine rather than some
          sort of newsletter publishing while I was unavailable for blog comments and so on. So in
          planning for my leave, I wrote to about twenty of my colleagues and asked them to write a
          blog entry about a very specific topic, selecting ones that I knew were interesting to
          them or that they had written email messages about previously. I managed to get about ten
          posts this way. I introduced each post with a short introduction to the guest blogger and
          a note to let the reader know that I was on an extended leave. The supportive talk.bmc.com
          team published them for me on a weekly schedule. This technique proved to be an effective
          bridge of content, and I did not lose readership during that time.</p>
      </body>
    </subsection>
    <subsection
      id="d5e174">
      <title>Blog examples</title>
      <body>
        <p>National Instruments’ “<indexterm>blogs, examples<indexterm>technically speaking
              (National Instruments)</indexterm></indexterm>technically speaking” blog</p>
        <p> shows a group blog written by the technical writers at <indexterm>blogs,
              examples<indexterm>National Instruments</indexterm></indexterm>National Instruments
          that offers customers a view into the daily life of a technical writer. It includes a
          website that provides stories of the daily work done at National Instruments. Some of
          these technical writers worked in Shanghai for a year or so, as US employees, which
          offered an overseas perspective on their daily work.</p>
        <p>lvtechspeak.blogspot.com</p>
        <p>Embarcadero: “CodeGear Information Development” blog</p>
        <p>Direct <indexterm>conversations<indexterm>joining</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm
            >blogs, examples<indexterm>Embarcadero</indexterm></indexterm>conversations are likely
          to occur between bloggers who are online help writers and their audience. An excellent
          example of such a <indexterm>conversations<indexterm>with customers,
            examples</indexterm></indexterm>conversation occurred between Dee Elling, a technical
          publication manager at Borland, and her group of Delphi programmers when she posted a
          “Help on Help” blog entry (). Dee has bravely and calmly answered their <indexterm
              >comments<indexterm>on blog posts</indexterm></indexterm>questions, reminding them
          that their priorities are the same. She has built a bridge to ensure customers that she
          hears their concerns about a lack of examples. She is participating in online
          conversations. She says that some of the more abrasive responses are caused by pent-up
          frustration over a long-ago acquisition of her product, which created a heartbreak in the
          community that still resonates with members today.</p>
        <p>blogs.embarcadero.com/deeelling</p>
        <p><indexterm>Atlassian Confluence</indexterm>Atlassian Confluence<indexterm
            >Confluence</indexterm>: A technical writer’s blog </p>
        <p><indexterm>conversations<indexterm>with customers,
          examples</indexterm></indexterm>Customers seeking technical support for a
            Confluence<indexterm>Confluence</indexterm> product have commented on Sarah <indexterm
            >Maddox, Sarah</indexterm>Maddox’s blog shown in . They know that she is a technical
          writer at Confluence, and they have come to expect a quicker response from her
          personal/professional blog than from other traditional channels. And sure enough, she
          delivers on their expectations. </p>
        <p>ffeathers.<indexterm>blogs, examples<indexterm>ffeathers - a technical writer's
              blog</indexterm></indexterm>wordpress.com</p>
      </body>
    </subsection>
  </subsection>
  <subsection
    id="d5e248">
    <title>Providing infrastructure for &#8232;customer blogs</title>
    <body>
      <p>In many organizations, the technical publication department will not take the lead in
        designing or providing <indexterm>blogs<indexterm
        >infrastructure</indexterm></indexterm>infrastructure for customer <indexterm
            >blogs<indexterm>customer</indexterm></indexterm>blogs. This type of service is better
        performed by the website management department, marketing, or sales department, which can
        track generated leads more easily, or by the customer support department, which has a
        business goal of customers helping other customers. Sometimes a valuable internal
        communications device is started by someone on their own time with a server under their
        desk. For inspiration, read Groundswell for case studies such as the Best Buy internal blog
          <indexterm>blogs<indexterm>platforms</indexterm></indexterm>platform for employees.</p>
    </body>
  </subsection>
  <subsection
    id="d5e267">
    <title>Integrating user content into your user assistance</title>
    <body>
      <p><i>Mashup</i>
        <indexterm>content<indexterm>integrating</indexterm></indexterm>typically refers to websites
        or applications that combine data from different sources in new ways. You could think of
        integration of user contributions into your <indexterm>help, online<indexterm>creating from
            wiki pages</indexterm></indexterm>user assistance as a mashup in itself. An example of a
          <indexterm>content<indexterm>combining</indexterm></indexterm>mashup that could be used in
          <indexterm>help, online<indexterm>mashups in</indexterm></indexterm>user assistance is a
          <indexterm>wikislices</indexterm><indexterm>wikis<indexterm
          >slicing</indexterm></indexterm><i>wikislice</i>, which repurposes a part of a <indexterm
            >content<indexterm>wiki</indexterm></indexterm>wiki as an ebook<indexterm>ebooks
          (PDF)</indexterm> (PDF<indexterm>PDF, as wiki output</indexterm>) or in an online help
        system. A wikislice is a selected cross-section of a wiki, created by wiki editors
        selectively extracting content on a particular group of articles for different audiences or
        deliverables. The sample wikislices on Wikipedia<fn><p>
            http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:WikiProject_Wikislice </p></fn> contain content
        related to mathematics, chemistry, and physics, to name a few subjects. A wikislice can be
        downloaded to consume offline, so an Internet connection is not necessary once the content
        is local. And because the wikislice can be styled differently from the wiki as a whole, it
        can benefit from a more readable format, and its content can be more easily digestible and
        organized than the vast expanse of a well-populated wiki. </p>
      <p>A project called <indexterm>InfoSlicer</indexterm>InfoSlicer<fn><p>
            http://activities.sugarlabs.org/en-US/sugar/addon/4042</p></fn> is housed on the
          <indexterm>open source<indexterm>InfoSlicer</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm>open
            source<indexterm>SugarLabs</indexterm></indexterm>SugarLabs website, host site for the
        developers of the <indexterm>Sugar learning platform</indexterm>Sugar learning platform. A
        team created InfoSlicer to help teachers create curriculum by downloading and re-mixing
        Wikipedia articles. For example, if a teacher wants to teach students about the African
        continent, they can download articles about animals, clothing, civil structures, and
        traditions that are native to countries in Africa, then combine them into one set of
        articles. The Darwin Information Typing Architecture (DITA) is the technology that combines
        the data since the underlying organization layer is a DITA map structure.</p>
      <p>InfoSlicer for creating wikislices</p>
      <p>To use some slice of a wiki as part of your online help system, you could set up a plug-in
        that queries the wiki’s database or source content for specific articles at specific
          publishing<indexterm>publishing<indexterm>wiki content</indexterm></indexterm> times. You
        need to ensure that the <indexterm>communities<indexterm>content contributed
          by</indexterm></indexterm>community would welcome such remixes of their contributed
        content, and that the wiki content licensing allows you to republish the content as part of
        your static user assistance system. </p>
      <p>Following are tools and techniques that can enable a mashup of wiki<indexterm
            >wikis<indexterm>exporting content</indexterm></indexterm> and user assistance:</p>
      <ul>
        <li><indexterm>MWDumper</indexterm>MWDumper, available at download.wikimedia.org/tools, is a
          tool that extracts sets of pages from a <indexterm>MediaWiki<indexterm>exporting
              from</indexterm></indexterm>MediaWiki dump file. You write your own filters to ensure
          you get the pages you want. Your information architecture should use certain templates
          that you would pre-select as the topics to be filtered and exported from MediaWiki.
          Prerequisites are the Java SDK and access to the database running the MediaWiki
          installation.</li>
        <li>You can use a Special:Export box for MediaWiki pages that enables you to export a set of
          pages based on a category name. On any MediaWiki installation, you can enter the root
          domain URL plus /Sple, go to http://www.wikihow.com/Special:Export and enter Work-World as
          the category. You’ll get a list of the subcategories. Select the options and save the
          file. You can then download the resulting XML file.</li>
        <li>If the structure of the content is easily determined (such as a heading followed by only
          paragraph text), you might consider screen-scraping, which can be done with scripting
          programs. For more complex topics, such as tasks with embedded graphics, this approach may
          not work well because it is difficult to capture multiple embedded files with a screen
          scraping process.</li>
        <li>You can also do direct database calls to the wiki database layer. There is a connection
          that allows users to use Microsoft Word to edit the wiki database layer directly using a
          subset of DITA<indexterm>DITA</indexterm> markup tags.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>If you’re thinking about mashing up your wiki content with your user assistance content,
        consider the following guidelines:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>Ensure that the content is licensed for use in a new deliverable. <indexterm>Creative
            Commons license</indexterm>Creative Commons licenses allow for share and share alike,
          meaning that anything created from your shared content must also be shared content itself.
          The ramification of choosing content with this license is that your resulting content also
          has to be shareable. You would also have to attribute the source. GNU Public License has
          more documentation-friendly terms in it, but it requires that resulting content be
          licensed with the same terms. </li>
        <li>Design the wiki with specific tags in mind for collection. Let wiki contributors know
          that articles tagged in a certain way will be incorporated into the online help.</li>
        <li>Query the database for categories, specific tags, or templates, and create a
            DITA<indexterm>DITA</indexterm> map or similar structure for re-assembling the
          content.</li>
        <li>Using a DITA<indexterm>DITA</indexterm> map or similar structure as a query, get the
          content out of the wiki database, and then turn it into HTML files (or whatever format is
          needed by the user assistance/help authoring tool). Import files into the help authoring
          tool and recompile the help. </li>
      </ul>
      <p>Other ways to integrate user content into your user assistance include using
          screencasts<indexterm>screencasts</indexterm> created by users, searching Google for the
        most helpful troubleshooting articles related to your product and asking permission to
        re-post those, and incorporating wiki articles with the author’s permission and proper
        licensing agreements in place. These suggestions are just a few techniques that might work
        for your content. </p>
    </body>
    <subsection
      id="d5e406">
      <title>Introducing comment and feedback systems in user assistance</title>
      <prolog>
        <metadata>
          <keywords>
            <indexterm>comments<indexterm>enabling</indexterm></indexterm>
            <indexterm>enabling</indexterm>
          </keywords>
        </metadata>
      </prolog>
      <body>
        <p><indexterm>help, online<indexterm>comments in</indexterm></indexterm>Help authoring tools
          provide user feedback tools right inside of the topics that you author with the tool. Even
          a simple link to an email address on each help page so that readers can send email to a
          centralized mailbox in the department gives your readers a way to give feedback. If you
          want to structure the feedback, add a web form with specific fields to be filled out
          before a reader can send it. The <indexterm>help, online<indexterm>feedback
              tools</indexterm></indexterm>feedback mechanism can send the form via <indexterm
              >email<indexterm>using for customer feedback</indexterm></indexterm>email. Google
          Forms can populate a Google Spreadsheet with results even as the responses are still
          coming in. Comments and feedback systems can be incorporated into many online help
          outputs. Jive Software and JS-Kit are two such offerings. Also, be sure you can track on
          which pages people are choosing to initiate the comment or response mechanism of your
          choice. </p>
        <p>You may find ways to discover what your readers are doing without requiring their
          participation to do so, like Will Hill’s “read-wear” phrase and concept discussed in
          Chapter 6.<fn><p> http://www.useit.com/alertbox/participation_inequality.html</p></fn>
        </p>
      </body>
    </subsection>
    <subsection
      id="d5e435">
      <title>Moderating or participating in online forums</title>
      <prolog>
        <metadata>
          <keywords>
            <indexterm>comments<indexterm>enabling</indexterm></indexterm>
            <indexterm>enabling</indexterm>
          </keywords>
        </metadata>
      </prolog>
      <body>
        <p>Professional writers who have mastered the product they document are natural respondents
          to online <indexterm>discussions about content<indexterm>in
            forums</indexterm></indexterm>forum<indexterm>moderation<indexterm
            >forums</indexterm></indexterm> questions. The best approach is to read the <indexterm
              >forums<indexterm>participating in</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm>forums<indexterm
              >moderating</indexterm></indexterm>forum regularly for a while to get a sense of the
            <indexterm>conversations<indexterm>joining</indexterm></indexterm>community that exists,
          how often people post, the amount of time it typically takes for questions to be answered,
          and the key contributors to the site. After you gain a feel for the appropriate approach,
          style, and tone for your messages, start by answering questions, and be sure to disclose
          your employer. </p>
        <p>Consider becoming a moderator only after you have been a participant for a while. Most
          online <indexterm>communities<indexterm>participation
          in</indexterm></indexterm>communities do not recognize any sense of entitlement that you
          may have because of your employer. Instead, you must earn the <indexterm
              >communities<indexterm>trust within</indexterm></indexterm>community’s trust and offer
          real help, even if you only provide links to your online help. Teaching the community to
          fish (for information) feeds them longer than just answering questions without citing how
          you learned the information yourself.</p>
      </body>
    </subsection>
    <subsection
      id="d5e479">
      <title>Instant messaging and responses</title>
      <body>
        <p>You have probably noticed that many websites now contain “<indexterm>Live
            Help</indexterm><indexterm>help, live</indexterm>Live Help” links. If your corporate
          site includes such links, you might find out how the live help is staffed and volunteer to
          be a staffer for an hour or longer, exchanging instant messages with real customers. </p>
        <p>Interesting examples exist of scripted response programs written for frequently asked
          questions, using artificial intelligence stored in knowledge reserves, dictionaries, or
          other reference materials such as concordances to guess at a needed response. For example,
          IRC has a helper robot called IRCza that is natural language artificial intelligence chat
          robot for IRC.<fn><p> http://timberfrog.com/icqza/irczafaq.html</p></fn> AOL Instant
          Messenger offers AIMbots, which can tell you when movies are going to show. According to
          the paper “Using Instant Messaging to Provide an Intelligent Learning Environment,”
            <indexterm>Artificial Intelligence Markup Language (AIML)</indexterm>Artificial
          Intelligence Markup Language (AIML)<fn><p>
            http://www.alicebot.org/TR/2001/WD-aiml/</p></fn> is an XML-compliant language that
          facilitates the creation of “<indexterm>chatbots</indexterm>chatbots” with various
          personalities and kinds of knowledge. By connecting the chatbot to a support knowledge
          base of frequent responses, you might be able to offer a virtual conversation with
          responses to a customer.</p>
      </body>
    </subsection>
    <subsection
      id="d5e505">
      <title>Writing reviews </title>
      <body>
        <p><indexterm>social shopping</indexterm>Social shopping involves researching reviews and
          community member recommendations before or while making a purchase. To encourage and
          participate in social shopping, you could read a book that is related to the types of
          problems your customers solve with your product, then go to amazon.com and write a book
          review for a book related to your product or expertise that your company provides. Or, you
          could perform a search on amazon.com using keywords that are helpful to your users to get
          a sense of who else is reading and reviewing those books and what problems they’re
          solving.</p>
      </body>
    </subsection>
    <subsection
      id="d5e511">
      <title>Integrating social tagging</title>
      <prolog>
        <metadata>
          <keywords>
            <indexterm>tagging<indexterm>sites</indexterm></indexterm>
            <indexterm>sites</indexterm>
          </keywords>
        </metadata>
      </prolog>
      <body>
        <p>You may want to be a <indexterm>content<indexterm>tagging</indexterm></indexterm>tag
          maintainer for your product, by offering tag sets related to your product or service on
          popular social <indexterm>content<indexterm>bookmarking</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm
            >bookmarking, social</indexterm>bookmarking<indexterm>social bookmarking</indexterm> and
          tagging sites such as digg.com<indexterm>digg.com</indexterm> and delicious.com<indexterm
            >delicious.com</indexterm>. Keep an eye on community members who use your products and
          observe what tags they use as well. </p>
        <p>Tagging involves a skill that many technical writers have—determining which keywords best
          describe a link or image for retrieval later. Social bookmarking sites like delicious.com
          and digg.com<indexterm>digg.com</indexterm> use tagging, or keywords, to help users find
          their links later or group them into categories. What is more advanced and social about
          tagging or social bookmarking is that the tags that others use and the content that they
          have tagged are usually visible to anyone. </p>
        <p>There are literally hundreds of <indexterm>communities<indexterm>social bookmarking
              and</indexterm></indexterm>social bookmarking or tagging sites, but the
          writerriver.com, digg.com, and delicious.com sites are particularly useful to technical
          communication.</p>
        <p>You may find other social bookmarking sites are useful for your particular users, such as
          reddit.com, stumbleupon.com, and furl.com.</p>
      </body>
    </subsection>
    <subsection
      id="d5e554">
      <title>Sharing photos and videos for explanation or assistance</title>
      <prolog>
        <metadata>
          <keywords>
            <indexterm>photos</indexterm>
            <indexterm>video<indexterm>sharing</indexterm></indexterm>
            <indexterm>sharing</indexterm>
          </keywords>
        </metadata>
      </prolog>
      <body>
        <p>At sites such as Screencast.com<fn><p> http://screencast.com/</p></fn> and IgniteCAST,<fn
              ><p> http://www.ignitecast.com</p></fn> users can use a desktop tool to capture
          screenshots or screencasts, which are videos showing the computer screen that are often
          narrated with a voice script to explain what is happening on the screen. The related
          website hosts the image or video files for playback. Photos may be the best solution to
          showing sequential instructions rather than writing them out, or even using complicated 3D
          modeling software. For example, a Lego fan posted instructions for building a
            refrigerator<fn><p>
            http://www.flickr.com/photos/nolnet/3184800280/in/photostream/</p></fn> with Legos by
          laying out the Lego pieces, taking photos, and putting the whole collage together with
          some text for instructions.<fn><p>
              http://www.flickr.com/photos/28119014@N06/3185664328</p></fn></p>
        <p><indexterm>Sun Microsystems<indexterm>platform</indexterm></indexterm>Sun Microsystems
          offers a platform for video uploads and screencasts at slx.sun.com/media where anyone with
          a Sun login (employee or external customer) can upload video messages or screencasts to
          share with the community.</p>
        <p>slx.sun.com/media</p>
        <p>Instructions for building a Lego refrigerator </p>
        <p>Photo of resulting Lego refrigerator</p>
      </body>
    </subsection>
  </subsection>
</chapter>
