<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<chapter
  id="d5e2">
  <title>Finding Your Voice</title>
  <prolog/>
  <body>
    <p><image
        href="images/chapter07.png"
        id="image_b279aa87-ef83-4d89-8369-5e1e0d720b7a"
        width="5in"/></p>
    <epigram>Writing gives you the illusion of control, <br/>and then you realize it’s just an
      illusion, <br/>that people are going to bring their own stuff into it.<br/>—David
      Sedaris</epigram>
    <p>Standing out in the attention-hungry blogosphere means you must write better than most of the
      crowd. Not only must you <i>write</i> better than the crowd, you must also <i>communicate</i>
      better. This chapter describes best practices for writing when using <indexterm>social
          media<indexterm>audience analysis</indexterm></indexterm>social applications and
      communicating with people who prefer to obtain their technical information through the social
      web.</p>
    <p>As Brian Clark on the Copyblogger site writes, when “writing specifically with the social
      media audience in mind, understand the mentality and what they’re looking to get from Digg,
      Netscape, Reddit, StumbleUpon, and so on, and appeal to that desire.” </p>
  </body>
  <subsection
    id="d5e26">
    <title>Style guide </title>
    <body>
      <p>For the most <indexterm>social media<indexterm>style of
        writing</indexterm></indexterm>part, “conversation” is a less formal <indexterm
            >blogging<indexterm>style</indexterm></indexterm>style of writing than technical writers
        are used to. You may need to write a separate <indexterm>content<indexterm>style
            guidelines</indexterm></indexterm>style guide for blog, screencast, or tutorial
        deliverables, or a subsection of your current corporate style guide could discuss the
        special rules that apply when writing for social web media and audiences.</p>
      <p>An excellent style guide<indexterm>style guidance</indexterm> for online blog articles
        comes from A List Apart, a collection of essays and articles for web developers who are
        experts in CSS (Cascading Style Sheets).<fn>
          <p> http://www.alistapart.com/contribute/styleguide/</p>
        </fn> Informality is not the first goal of the style guide, but rather clarity, audience
        consideration, and links to definitions for those readers who are well-versed in code but
        may not be familiar with the vocabulary of an industry expert in visual design or any
        specialty the blog’s author discusses.</p>
      <p>A <indexterm>minimalist documentation</indexterm>minimalist, clean style in your writing is
        best for reading on the web. Brevity may seem curt when speaking to someone, but if the
        writing is more clear when brief, don’t think you need to embellish the writing with lots of
        small talk or jokes.</p>
      <p> A sense of humor can come through as part of your personality, as long as the humor
        matches your audience. A classy, clever sense of humor will be welcomed by the types of
        readers who read blogs for information, and you can tailor that sense of humor (and adjust
        your definitions of classy and clever). </p>
      <p>You do not need to use the formal trademark and registered trademark symbols on first use
        when writing for online content like a blog. It’s more difficult to determine where the
        “first use” occurred anyway. But do be respectful of brand names and company names.</p>
      <p>Many times people assume that writing for the social web automatically calls for a more
        informal style in writing. Some might even predict that our communications in the future
        will include “text speak,” or shortcuts and slang in the English language often used on
        mobile devices where it’s faster to type short phrases and use numbers or single letters
        with phonetic pronunciation. <indexterm>Self, Tony</indexterm>Tony Self ponders this issue
        in “What if Readers Can’t Read?”<fn>
          <p> http://www.hyperwrite.com/Articles/showarticle.aspx?id=84</p>
        </fn> I think that professional writers should stand above that crowd and instead adopt a
        strict adherence to correct grammar and traditional spellings; however, a casual,
        speaking-like style in your writing is perfectly acceptable and likely preferred in most
        communications. </p>
      <p><indexterm>Redish, Ginny</indexterm>Ginny Redish’s book, <i>Letting Go of the Words:
          Writing Web Content that Works</i>, talks about a casual but concise writing style. </p>
      <p><indexterm>Microsoft<indexterm>guidelines for tone in
        communication</indexterm></indexterm>Microsoft’s most recent style guide, available online,
        requires a specific tone and voice:</p>
      <lq>
        <p> “Use the Microsoft® Windows® tone to inspire confidence by communicating to users on a
          personal level by being accurate, encouraging, insightful, objective, and user focused.
          Don’t use a distracting, condescending (example: “Just do this...”), or arrogant tone.
          Avoid the extremes of the “machine” voice (where the speaker is removed from the language)
          and the “sales rep” voice (where the writing tries to sell us something, to cajole us, to
          cheer us up, to gloss over everything as ‘simple.’)” <fn>
            <p> http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/aa974175.aspx</p>
          </fn></p>
      </lq>
      <p>These are excellent guidelines to follow when establishing your own balance between casual
        and formal.</p>
    </body>
    <subsection
      id="d5e94">
      <title>Open and honest</title>
      <body>
        <p>The social media audience expects open communication and honesty. Much like the general
          web-reading audience, this audience has little time or patience for messages that are not
          directly related to their task at hand. Plus, any exaggeration or vague references can be
          commented on or edited immediately, so be as honest and open as you can in your
          communication. </p>
        <p>At BMC Software, I was instructed by the <indexterm>talk.bmc.com
          site</indexterm>talk.bmc.com blog team to make my blog sound like I was standing beside
          the customers, solving problems similar to their own. I was encouraged to be honest and
          open about weaknesses and gaps in my own knowledge about Business Service Management, one
          of our core corporate competencies. In a blog, it does not help the reader if you write
          about things you don’t know. However, you can talk about your own learning journey, and
          one of your readers may be at the same level of knowledge that you were when you started
          out. You can only be a “newbie” for a while, and it’s valuable to capture that experience
          and learning path on a blog. </p>
        <p>I was also guided to the Cluetrain Manifesto and encouraged to advocate its principles
          through blogging for BMC Software. Here is a powerful quote from the manifesto that
          strongly states the need for companies and their employees to be direct in their
          communications with each other:</p>
        <lq>
          <p>“...learning to speak in a human voice is not some trick, nor will corporations
            convince us they are human with lip service about ‘listening to customers.’ They will
            only sound human when they empower real human beings to speak on their
            behalf....employees are getting hyperlinked even as markets are. Companies need to
            listen carefully to both. Mostly, they need to get out of the way so intranetworked
            employees can converse directly with internetworked markets.” <fn>
              <p> http://www.cluetrain.com/</p>
            </fn></p>
        </lq>
        <p>So, does openness and honesty also require or dissolve into negativity? I don’t believe
          so. You can be honest about a problem without complaining about it or casting it in a
          negative light. You can strike a balance, though, so that you do not sound overly
          enthusiastic or plainly ignorant of certain problems. You cannot, however, be open to the
          point of violating any<indexterm>blogs<indexterm>policy</indexterm></indexterm> policy
          agreement that you’ve made with your company. </p>
        <p>What about <indexterm>discussions about content<indexterm>transparency
            of</indexterm></indexterm>transparency? What does that mean exactly? Transparency in
          written communications usually means that nothing crucial is hidden from view, and it also
          usually prescribes a straightforward, no-nonsense, sensible communication style. Secrecy
          is not tolerated or expected from a writer using social media tools or the Internet in
          general. Know your company policies for trade secrets and other private information, and
          know when it is appropriate to talk about products still in development. The trigger for
          when you can write about something may vary from company to company, depending on whether
          generating buzz or excitement is part of the business goals of using social media for
          messaging.</p>
        <p>Transparent, clear, and authentic writing is a powerful tool for convincing others of
          your point of view, but it is also important for building trust with your audience. This
          trust and belief in the accuracy of your documentation is crucial for creating successful
          relationships with readers through any social media communication.</p>
      </body>
    </subsection>
    <subsection
      id="d5e128">
      <title>Personal and professional</title>
      <body>
        <p>When writing for social media, you have to present yourself as a real person. Writing in
          anonymity won’t work in most social media situations. Readers are interested in the person
          behind the writing, who you work for, why you started writing, and how you came to know
          the information that you know. Your identity and reputation precede all that you say
          online because it is generally easy to gather enough information to form an opinion of
          you. Typically you link from your front page to a page that describes you and your
          interests and perhaps the reasons why you write a <indexterm>blogs<indexterm
              >professionalism in</indexterm></indexterm>blog.</p>
        <p>People seeking information on social media outlets are naturally drawn to seek a
          relationship with the person providing the information. They want to get to know you. Give
          them some information to put a face with a name, including a professional picture that
          reflects your style. Recently there has been much importance placed on building a personal
            <indexterm>brands<indexterm>personal</indexterm></indexterm>brand. Although your goal
          might be to merely enable conversations instead of trying to stand out at your company, be
          aware that your writing represents you as an individual as much or even more than it
          represents your company. </p>
        <p>Although you should insert your personality into your social media communications,
          especially for blogs, forums, and presence content such as microblogs, you need to strike
          a balance. You must consider your own privacy as well as that of your family members, your
          co-workers, and anyone that might be part of or affected by a personal story you share. </p>
        <p>But also be aware of the discomfort that some people may have with expressions of
          political views, sexual preferences, and religion. What seems innocent and harmless to you
          may be a red flag to someone from a different culture or age group. Use good judgment and
          as always, know your audience. </p>
      </body>
    </subsection>
    <subsection
      id="d5e148">
      <title>Telling a story</title>
      <body>
        <p>It’s important to share personal stories, especially if you are passionate about
          something in your company or your work life. If a <indexterm>blogs<indexterm>storytelling
              in</indexterm></indexterm>story effectively relays that passion in a “sticky” way, the
          story remains with the reader. For example, I shared a personal story about getting an eye
          injury from a piñata bat striking my eye at a children’s birthday party.<fn>
            <p> http://justwriteclick.com/2009/01/28/arrrrrrr-mateysarrrrrrr-mateys/</p>
          </fn> I related the entire experience back to my chosen profession of providing web-based
          information and linked to accessibility guidelines in place for low vision people who want
          to get information from websites. Because it was such an unusual incident, and it related
          to me and my family, including my children, some might consider it risky to relate such a
          story on a blog. But if the story helps someone remember to enter ALT tags on images so
          that a screen reader can help someone with low vision understand a web page, and if the
          story shares in a professional way without too much detail, I believe it has a place on a
          blog.</p>
      </body>
    </subsection>
    <subsection
      id="d5e162">
      <title>Snappy titles</title>
      <body>
        <p>To encourage readers to go beyond skimming headlines and click through to your content,
          you should borrow some advice from copywriting and journalism schools. Although titles
          should be accurate and convey the correct information, you also have some freedom to
          create titles that are more enticing. </p>
        <p>Copyblogger author Brian Clark talks about the Swipe File, a collection of headline
          templates that capture the readers’ attention in two separate blog posts.<fn>
            <p> , </p>
          </fn> He suggests going beyond the common “How to” and “List of” titles to formulas for
          headline writing. While you don’t need to sprinkle copywriting throughout your <indexterm
            >technical documentation<indexterm>titles</indexterm></indexterm>technical
          documentation, you may want to study these types of headlines and determine if they might
          work for your social web writing efforts. Writing an enticing, attention-grabbing headline
          takes practice but may make a difference in number of visitors.</p>
      </body>
    </subsection>
  </subsection>
  <subsection
    id="d5e177">
    <title>Publishing strategies</title>
    <body>
      <p>You are a <indexterm>social media<indexterm>publishing</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm
            >publishing<indexterm>blog posts</indexterm></indexterm>publisher each time your
          <indexterm>content<indexterm>publishing strategies</indexterm></indexterm>content goes on
        the web. You need to shift your thinking away from print writing towards web writing, and
        you may need to think about publishing strategies before you write a single paragraph. When
        I first started blogging, writing two posts a week was my intention. This strategy meant I
        also needed to determine the spacing and timing for those two posts. This section discusses
        some of the considerations when blogging and <indexterm
        >microblogging</indexterm>microblogging for publishing. </p>
    </body>
    <subsection
      id="d5e198">
      <title>Timing </title>
      <body>
        <p>Daily <indexterm>publishing<indexterm>timing</indexterm></indexterm>newspapers are
          typically available in the morning, but the constant availability of today’s news makes
          the idea of waiting until breakfast time to get your news ludicrous. Because the social
          web encompasses the world, people in different time zones wake up at different hours of
          your daytime and scan the social web for information and updates. For Twitter posts, you
          can set the time that a <indexterm>publishing<indexterm>Twitter
            posts</indexterm></indexterm>Twitter update is published using a site like <indexterm
              >Twitter<indexterm>publishing posts</indexterm></indexterm>TweetLater.com. You can
          publish when you believe your readers are first reading their information or you can time
          the publishing to catch them later in the afternoon or evening, but also realize that the
          earth is round and you may need to post multiple times to set your message timing around
          the globe. </p>
        <p>On her WordPress <indexterm>blogs<indexterm>publishing</indexterm></indexterm>blog,
          Lorelle <indexterm>VanFossen, Lorelle</indexterm>VanFossen has an excellent post titled
          “When is the Best Time and Day to Publish a Blog Post.”<fn>
            <p>
              http://lorelle.wordpress.com/2008/12/03/when-is-the-best-time-and-day-to-publish-a-blog-post/</p>
          </fn> She writes about analyzing when your readers tend to read posts and when they tend
          to <indexterm>blogs<indexterm>commenting on</indexterm></indexterm>comment on posts. Use
          analytics on your web site, blog, or wiki to find out when people read the content, and
          then time the publishing of your content so that it matches when your readers are seeking
          updates or searching for answers. Some bloggers have even set up specific “open comment”
          times, such as on Tuesday evenings. Readers know they can go to the blog site at that time
          and post <indexterm>comments<indexterm>timing on blog
          posts</indexterm></indexterm>comments and get immediate responses from other readers and
          the blogger. </p>
      </body>
    </subsection>
    <subsection
      id="d5e241">
      <title>Search engine optimization</title>
      <body>
        <p>In the <indexterm>search<indexterm>optimization</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm
              >search<indexterm>rankings</indexterm></indexterm>economy of web <indexterm
              >content<indexterm>searching for</indexterm></indexterm>content, you are paid in links
          to your content (which indicate your reputation) and in attention (which is indicated by
          the number of page views your site receives). Both of these “currencies” can be optimized
          and are part of a <indexterm>blogs<indexterm>search engine
            optimization</indexterm></indexterm>search engine optimization (SEO) strategy. Most
          blogs already follow many of the basic rules for optimization—content is updated often and
          tagged with keywords; natural, readable URLs are used; importance is placed on the first
          paragraph, heading, and title text; and the content is text-heavy so that it is not hidden
          behind Flash introductions or video. However, because buzz generation is not the main
          business goal for most documentation, search engine optimization is probably not important
          enough to make you switch your online <indexterm>help, online<indexterm
              >finding</indexterm></indexterm>help engine to a blog engine. But you should evaluate
          the <indexterm>HTML<indexterm>evaluating for search engine
            optimization</indexterm></indexterm>HTML that is generated from your online help tool to
          ensure that it can be optimized so that it can be found.</p>
        <p>Another key to optimization is to ensure that your domain name is reserved for several
          years, not just one year at a time. To search engines, this indicates that your content
          will be available for a while and is valuable enough to keep archived. You should also
          ensure that your content is registered with search engines. There are many search engine
          submission sites, such as <indexterm>addme.com</indexterm>addme.com. </p>
        <p>SEO techniques are constantly changing. <indexterm>Google<indexterm>Help Center for web
              masters</indexterm></indexterm>Google has a Help Center for web masters<fn>
            <p> http://google.com/support/webmasters/</p>
          </fn> that contains information about how Google works, and you may want to look for
          similar information from other search engines. </p>
      </body>
    </subsection>
    <subsection
      id="d5e291">
      <title>Submitting to social bookmarking sites</title>
      <body>
        <p>You should make your <indexterm>content<indexterm
            >sharing</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm>content<indexterm
            >bookmarking</indexterm></indexterm>content share-able—blog-able, tweet-able, and
          tag-able—because you enable others to promote the content for you. I may owe the entire
          genesis of the writing of this book to a single <indexterm>social
            bookmarking</indexterm><indexterm>bookmarking, social</indexterm>bookmarking event by a
          co-worker of mine at BMC Software. On my blog at <indexterm>talk.bmc.com
          site</indexterm>talk.bmc.com, I had interviewed a fellow technical writer about working on
          a wiki for a cell phone manufacturer. Will <indexterm>Hurley, William
            (whurley)</indexterm>Hurley submitted it to digg.com as a story because he found it
          interesting. About a month later I had an inquiry from the editor of <i>Intercom</i>
          magazine, the magazine for the members of the Society for Technical Communication, asking
          if I could write an article about wikis in technical publications. I obliged and it was
          the start of a great research and experimental phase, thanks to the social tagging of that
          article on digg.com. </p>
        <p>You might find it useful as a publishing strategy to tag your content for social
          bookmarking sites. Other users may follow suit and your keywords will have multiple
          submissions that will help them stand out in the crowd.</p>
      </body>
    </subsection>
    <subsection
      id="d5e321">
      <title>Finding your audio voice</title>
      <body>
        <p>You may also find <indexterm>content<indexterm>audio</indexterm></indexterm>that text
          alone will not help your message reach as far. When I was at BMC Software, the
          coordinators of the <indexterm>talk.bmc.com site</indexterm>talk.bmc.com site decided to
          do two separate podcasts with the two most popular bloggers on the site—Steve Carl and me.
          It was my first <indexterm>podcasts<indexterm>author's experience
            with</indexterm></indexterm>podcast and I was extremely nervous but very excited about
          learning a new way of communicating. I chose to go to a home-based recording studio in
          south Austin, with padded walls and excellent microphones. We had a fun time, and I truly
          felt comfortable with my interviewer Ynema <indexterm>Mangum, Ynema</indexterm>Mangum.
          Four years later I learned that podcast was the one that fellow technical writer and
          blogger <indexterm>Johnson, Tom</indexterm>Tom Johnson heard first, before he started to
          read my blog at talk.bmc.com. Since Tom was interested in podcasting, and because podcasts
          were a more “unusual” form of communication for technical writers, the podcast came to his
          attention first. Be on the lookout for similar technologies or publishing venues that
          might help your other deliverables gain attention.</p>
      </body>
    </subsection>
    <subsection
      id="d5e344">
      <title>Link to your work </title>
      <body>
        <p>While I was blogging for BMC Software, I was also writing white papers that described
          complex cross-product solutions to particular business problems. I liked to write a blog
            entry<fn>
            <p> http://talk.bmc.com/blogs/blog-gentle/anne-gentle/eating-own-dog-food</p>
          </fn> talking about the white paper and the problems it described and then link to the
          white paper download site once it was available on the bmc.com site. On a corporate
            <indexterm>blogs<indexterm>linking other work to</indexterm></indexterm>blog, this type
          of linking helps to show that your first priority is your work, and that your work is
          relevant to the types of problems your readers face.</p>
      </body>
    </subsection>
  </subsection>
  <subsection
    id="d5e357">
    <title>Idea generation </title>
    <body>
      <p>Three basic steps can get you started with social technologies and documentation:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>1 Listen </li>
        <li>2 Join </li>
        <li>3 Provide a platform</li>
      </ul>
    </body>
    <subsection
      id="d5e368">
      <title>Listen to the conversation</title>
      <body>
        <p>This section gives ideas for reading, listening, and <indexterm>social media<indexterm
              >monitoring conversations</indexterm></indexterm>monitoring online discussions about
          your product that you document, the company you work for, or the typical users and
          personas for your product or service.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>To find social media content related to your company, search for your product names
            and company name on sites where Web 2.0 conversations occur. Use a Yahoo<indexterm
              >Yahoo</indexterm> Pipes Social Media setup to monitor the conversations about your
            product in the blog world, on Twitter<indexterm>Twitter<indexterm>searching
                within</indexterm></indexterm>, and so on. A pre-configured Yahoo Pipe is available
            that you can use to find out more about what is being said about your company or
              product.<fn>
              <p> http://www.churchofthecustomer.com/blog/2008/04/keeping-up-with.html</p>
            </fn></li>
          <li>Sign up for notifications on customer support <indexterm>forums<indexterm>getting
                notifications on</indexterm></indexterm>forums that are relevant to your area of
            expertise on your product. Monitor the forum and step in to help whenever you can. Look
            for conversations on email <indexterm>mailing lists<indexterm
              >monitoring</indexterm></indexterm>lists beyond your company’s customer support
            forums, such as a Yahoo<indexterm>Yahoo</indexterm> Group dedicated to your product.
            Point to your online help systems when appropriate.</li>
          <li>Use Technorati and <indexterm>BlogPulse</indexterm>BlogPulse to <indexterm
                >blogs<indexterm>monitoring</indexterm></indexterm>monitor keywords that are
            pertinent to your company and products as well as your competitors. Use Search Engine
            Optimization (SEO) keywords tools like SEMRush and the Google <indexterm
                >Google<indexterm>AdWords</indexterm></indexterm>AdWords Keyword tool to study and
            research relevant keywords.</li>
          <li>Constantly read and monitor <indexterm>comments<indexterm
              >monitoring</indexterm></indexterm>comments on articles in wikis and support forums
            related to your products. Often the true value to the customer is in the discussion on
            an article or post about strategy or best practices, and not in the item itself.
            Questions are asked and answered, and nuance is explored and interpreted through
            conversation.</li>
        </ul>
      </body>
    </subsection>
    <subsection
      id="d5e427">
      <title>Join the conversation </title>
      <body>
        <p>Once you <indexterm>forums<indexterm>participating in</indexterm></indexterm>are adept at
          listening and understanding the <indexterm>discussions about content<indexterm>in
              wikis</indexterm></indexterm>conversation and <indexterm>communities<indexterm
              >participation in</indexterm></indexterm>community building going on, you can join in
          by talking to others or providing information on a community site.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Start a Flickr photo set that contains photos<indexterm>photos</indexterm> of your
            product in use. If your product is software, perhaps use screen captures. Be sure to
            offer navigation hints for how to open a dialog box or set up a particular view. For
            hardware, photos are especially helpful for providing how-to information, such as
            opening the case on a computer, inserting an SD card, changing a battery, or loading an
            ink cartridge. </li>
          <li>Post screencasts<indexterm>screencasts</indexterm> on <indexterm>You
            Tube</indexterm>You Tube or a higher-resolution video<indexterm>video<indexterm
                >sharing</indexterm></indexterm> site like Vimeo or Viddler. Screencasts are video
            tutorials that take video of your screen while a voice over explains the task being
            accomplished. If operating your hardware product has a tricky physical task, you might
            post a video of someone performing that task.</li>
          <li>Future-proof a <indexterm>content<indexterm>tagging</indexterm></indexterm>helpful set
            of <indexterm>tagging<indexterm>URLs</indexterm></indexterm>URLs by creating
            delicious.com tag sets that describe how-to information about your product. Even if you
            add additional tagged URLs, delicious.com groups them by tag so people get the latest
            set of URLs along with your notes about the links.</li>
          <li>Start a blog at your company, or assist in writing entries as a guest or a regular
            contributor for an existing blog at your company.</li>
          <li>Offer <indexterm>comments<indexterm>on blog posts</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm
                >blogs<indexterm>commenting on</indexterm></indexterm>comments on a customer blog
            when the blogger writes an entry that is relevant to your product. When a customer finds
            your blog, respond to comments quickly with an answer or simple acknowledgement.</li>
          <li>Contact a customer and ask if you could interview him or her for a podcast<indexterm
                >podcasts<indexterm>requesting from a customer</indexterm></indexterm>. You can post
            the podcast on your blog as an MP3 file or host it on one of the podcast websites.</li>
          <li>Request that a customer write a Wikipedia<indexterm>Wikipedia</indexterm> entry about
            your product’s technical concepts or submit one yourself. But be aware that Wikipedia
            does not accept articles for commercial products because articles must pass its
            notability test. Before submitting to Wikipedia on behalf of your company, refer to
            Wikipedia’s list of policies.<fn>
              <p> http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Policies_and_guidelines</p>
            </fn> For example, ASI’s solution architect, Jay McCormack, submitted an article
            defining “friendraising.” Friendraising is the practice of online event-based fund
            raising using social networking and viral marketing techniques. In less than an hour
            after his submission, the Wikipedia community had altered the article presenting a much
            more cynical view of the term, plus marked it for deletion identifying it as a neologism
            without reliable sources and verifiability.<fn>
              <p> http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Friendraising&amp;action=history</p>
            </fn> The article has survived for more than a year, though.</li>
          <li>Set up a Facebook<indexterm>Facebook</indexterm> group or a LinkedIn<indexterm
              >LinkedIn</indexterm> group after determining where your users are most likely to join
            in. Building this type of group on an existing platform helps you connect customers to
            each other with minimal effort.</li>
        </ul>
      </body>
    </subsection>
    <subsection
      id="d5e518">
      <title>Provide a platform for conversation</title>
      <body>
        <p>Even though only about 1% of people in an online community will offer contributions to an
          online community, you may find that it makes sense to provide a platform especially for
          them and the other community members who will benefit from their contributions. Here are
          some ideas.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Provide a user group email <indexterm>mailing lists<indexterm
              >creating</indexterm></indexterm>list using Yahoo<indexterm>Yahoo</indexterm> Groups,
            Google Groups, or any of the multiple choices for email lists, or ask a known user
            community member to do so. Realize though that mailing lists are one technology that can
            make group work more difficult. As Clay <indexterm>Shirky, Clay</indexterm>Shirky
            eloquently explains in “Group as User: Flaming and the Design of Social Software,”<fn>
              <p> http://www.shirky.com/writings/group_user.html</p>
            </fn> mailing lists can have the most difficulty with signal-to-noise ratio because
            members have difficulty obeying rules of conduct when there is so much communal
            attention (both positive and negative) available. When the list is large, the problem is
            more difficult to manage.</li>
          <li>Your online <indexterm>help, online<indexterm>comments in</indexterm></indexterm>help
            system or a wiki based on user assistance content could provide a <indexterm
                >comments<indexterm>in help</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm>comments<indexterm>in
                help</indexterm></indexterm>commenting platform for customers.</li>
          <li>Provide a full-fledged wiki with editing enabled to give customers a chance to write
            or edit pre-seeded articles.</li>
          <li>Offer a video<indexterm>video<indexterm>sharing</indexterm></indexterm> and multimedia
            sharing plems does at http://sunfeedroom.sun.com.</li>
          <li>Give your users a blogging <indexterm>blogs<indexterm
              >platforms</indexterm></indexterm>platform by either building a planet blog (a
            collection of blog entries from different bloggers using aggregated feeds) or by hosting
            customer blog entries on a web site. </li>
          <li>Build a social networking<indexterm>social networking<indexterm>integrating with
                documentation</indexterm></indexterm> community using hosted software like Ning.com
            (an online platform for people to create their own social websites and social networks)
            to allow customers to communicate with each other and your company’s employees.</li>
        </ul>
      </body>
    </subsection>
  </subsection>
  <subsection
    id="d5e579">
    <title>Living and working with conversation and community</title>
    <body>
      <p><indexterm>Mader, Stewart</indexterm>Stewart Mader’s consulting brand is called “Future
        Changes” and I like this turn of phrase. It can either describe changes in the future or
        offer a mere statement of fact that the future changes. The future of education, of business
        and technical communications, has changed, is changing, and will change. Right now it seems
        like the number of social media tools is on a constant upward trend, but social methods for
          <indexterm>technical documentation<indexterm>changes
        in</indexterm></indexterm>documentation may take a place in an overall content strategy as
        another publishing mechanism. It’s exciting to see how it evolves over time.</p>
      <p>In the workplace, I have always surrounded myself with people who are smart, professional,
        and have an eye on the future. Collaboration, innovation, and creativity are high priorities
        in my work environment. At BMC Software I sought out new areas for communication when my job
        description charged me with doing so. I was fortunate to find people who were breaking new
        ground at <indexterm>talk.bmc.com site</indexterm>talk.bmc.com. As an indicator of their
        forward-thinking career paths, some of the people experimenting with blogs and podcasts in
        2005 are now working on cloud computing solutions. Others are inventing remote video
        interviewing techniques and creating media channels where there were none previously. </p>
      <p>People ask me, where should we start with these conversational and connective methods? In
        2005, I started with blogging behind the firewall. But in 2009, writing <indexterm
            >Twitter<indexterm>starting point</indexterm></indexterm>Twitter posts with protected
        updates might be a good starting point. </p>
      <p>People also want to know, where should my team start conversations? Or where should we
        focus our time if we do start? In this book, I talk about phases: Listen, Participate,
        Share, and Build a platform. I think you should start with listening and monitoring what’s
        already being said. Next, start commenting on blogs, blogging, or even microblogging
        yourself. A small step towards blogging is to blog on an internal site, behind your
        firewall, to limit your audience if that makes you more comfortable. I’d recommend trying
        out tools that are already installed that you don’t have to maintain and install yourself.
        For example, I started my blog at justwriteclick.com on wordpress.com and paid $10 a year to
        map my domain name. When I knew WordPress was a good fit for me and my blogging and site
        needs, I went ahead and found a host provider and installed WordPress on the server myself. </p>
      <p>Sharing content is the next step, and you can learn so much by sharing content and talking
        with others about it. Full time, continuous engagement with a user community while sharing
        content must be preceded by real relationship building with users. These steps require that
        you know your companies social media strategy, which may be a content strategy with a social
        media delivery mechanism. </p>
      <p>The final step is providing a platform for users. These steps take time but you will learn
        valuable lessons along the way and hopefully avoid any stumbling or disastrous results. It’s
        okay to fail, though. You learn new lessons with each attempt and approach. And you meet
        people, have ongoing conversations, and help build online communities along the way.</p>
    </body>
  </subsection>
</chapter>
