<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<chapter
  id="d5e2">
  <title>Towards the Future of Documentation</title>
  <shortdesc>Tell me… and I will forget. Show me… and I will remember. &#8232;Involve me… and I
    will understand.&#8232;—Confucius</shortdesc>
  <prolog/>
  <body>
    <p>As writers and content creators we are witnesses to the age of information shifting to the
      age of interaction. One week of content from the New York Times contains as much information
      as a person could get in a lifetime in the 18th century, according to information architect
      Richard Saul <indexterm>Wurman, Richard Saul</indexterm>Wurman in <i>Information Anxiety,</i>
      written in 1989. The speed at which we access this information is constantly improving—with
      fiber optic technology you can receive an amount of information equal to 10 full CDs per
      second. Filling a CD with that much text would take twelve years typing 100 words per minute!
      The only way people can handle this much information is to build relationships and act as
      filters for each other.</p>
    <p>Some content creators do not yet see a link between <i>online help</i> and the blogs, wikis,
      and forum posts with which users are finding <i>help online</i>, ironically. I have seen in
      writers’ email lists such quotes as “Sorry, I absolutely refuse to discuss anything, even
      cats, on a blog!” or “I’d rather not trust an encyclopedia that would accept me as a
        <indexterm>community-generated content<indexterm>distrust
      of</indexterm></indexterm>contributor.” Even if the Groucho Marx reference was meant in jest,
      how can we learn from the age-old
        <indexterm>content<indexterm>community-generated</indexterm></indexterm>community behaviors
      that are now being applied to documentation?</p>
    <p>Documentation as conversation means getting closer to users and helping them perform well.
        <indexterm>user-centered design</indexterm>User-centered design has been touted as one of
      the most important ideas developed in the last twenty years of workplace writing.<fn><p>
          http://owl.english.purdue.edu/owl/resource/624/01/</p></fn>
      <indexterm>Web 2.0<indexterm>role in user-centered design</indexterm></indexterm>Web 2.0 gives
      users a chance to interact with information and other users. </p>
    <p>Now, writers can take the idea of user-centered design a step further by starting
      conversations with users and enabling user assistance in interactions. Writers have more
      conversation-starting tools at their disposal than at any other time in history. Tools may
      include blogs, wikis, forums, and social networking sites, but may also involve photos, simple
      stick figure illustrations, videos, virtual worlds, or instant messaging<indexterm>instant
        messaging (IM)</indexterm>.</p>
  </body>
  <subsection
    id="d5e51">
    <title>How people communicate about technical topics today </title>
    <body>
      <p>The increasing complexity of what we want to do with technology has driven us to talk to
        people through various methods in order to make gadgets work, or software function. How has
        changing technology affected how these conversations are held? An example of how technical
        documentation has changed over the years is sewing patterns. Historically, people talked
        face to face to teach others how to sew a quilt for a bed cover, for example. Next, the
        patterns were written down, and the advent of printing meant that patterns could be produced
        for anyone in their home. Today’s quilting instructions are not only disseminated on the
        Internet, but people everywhere write instructions to each other on <indexterm>mailing
            lists<indexterm>community-based content</indexterm></indexterm>mailing lists and forums,
        quilters are writing <indexterm>blogs<indexterm>reduction of publishing
          costs</indexterm></indexterm>blogs,<fn><p> My mom writes a quilting blog at
            quilterjan.blogspot.com and has over 30,000 hits in the 15 months she has been writing.
          </p></fn> and online
        <indexterm>communities<indexterm>quilting</indexterm></indexterm>communities are forming
        around the passion for quilts and quilting.</p>
      <p>Over the years, the <indexterm>conversations<indexterm>cost of</indexterm></indexterm>cost
        of <indexterm>conversations<indexterm>ease of</indexterm></indexterm>conversation has
        dropped across a number of areas. We have gone from the need to design, then write, and then
        go through a long, sometimes arduous publishing<indexterm>publishing<indexterm>changes
            in</indexterm></indexterm> process (that was out of reach for ordinary people) to
        print-on-demand services and other “instant” methods for publication. With
            <indexterm>blogging<indexterm>microblogging</indexterm></indexterm>microblogging
        services like Twitter, you can merely have a thought, decide to express it, type it on your
          smartphone<indexterm>iPhone</indexterm>, and immediately push it out to all your
        followers. It’s a searchable piece of content and can even be re-used as a sidebar on a
        “macro” blog. Communication is immediate and filtered as the recipient requests.</p>
    </body>
  </subsection>
  <subsection
    id="d5e99">
    <title>Anticipating actions and questions</title>
    <body>
      <p>As a professional writer entering the wiki world, I had to determine my goals for designing
        documentation that would be part of a
            <indexterm>conversations<indexterm>community</indexterm></indexterm>conversation within
        a community. I learned that conversations are typically measured in three areas within an
        enterprise: public relations, customer support, and sales and marketing. With this framework
        in mind, I determined that my best fit was in the customer support area for One Laptop per
          Child<indexterm>One Laptop per Child<indexterm>author's experience
          with</indexterm></indexterm> when I volunteered to write documentation for parents,
        teachers, and students using the sturdy hardware and open source education platform. An open
        source project or platform means that the goods and knowledge that built it are freely
        available to copy, distribute, and modify so that it can be shared with others, even the
        source code. </p>
      <p>When you start supporting customers, especially for technical information, you want to
        analyze their tasks and anticipate their questions. In <i>The 4-Hour Workweek</i>, Timothy
          <indexterm>Ferriss, Timothy</indexterm>Ferriss says that the first web page you create
        when automating the business of selling a product or service should be <i>a list of actual
          asked questions</i>. He says you should build up your list of questions over time as you
        answer the questions yourself. </p>
      <p>This type of do-it-yourself approach is excellent for producing documentation like the
          horse-training<indexterm>training</indexterm> books touted as best in class by Kathy
          <indexterm>Sierra, Kathy</indexterm>Sierra. Kathy Sierra is a master trainer, creator of
        the HeadFirst series, and authored the Creating Passionate Users <indexterm>blogs,
            examples<indexterm>Creating Passionate Users</indexterm></indexterm>blog. According to
        her, books that embed questions right within the instructions are “the best user manuals
        EVER.” Her blog entry on “Creating Passionate Users,”<fn><p>
            http://headrush.typepad.com/creating_passionate_users/2006/09/how_to_get_user.html</p></fn>
        states that a good manual for a complex product should include at least five distinct
        sections: Reference Guide, Tutorial, Learning/Understanding, Cookbook/Recipe, and Start
        Here. Her detailed descriptions of each section describe, in essence, John Carroll’s basic
        concepts of <indexterm>minimalist documentation</indexterm>minimal documentation.<fn><p>
            Minimalism was first described by John <indexterm>Carroll, John</indexterm>Carroll as an
            instructional design philosophy at the IBM Watson Research Center in the 1980s,
            presented in his book <ph>The Nurnberg Funnel</ph>.</p></fn> And the principles of
        minimal documentation play a major role in creating documentation that fits into user
        conversation. Minimalist principles encourage both writer and instructor to:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>Get the user up and running quickly</li>
        <li>Let the user think and improvise</li>
        <li>Focus on real work and real goals</li>
        <li>Make use of user’s prior knowledge</li>
        <li>Use error recognition and error recovery as learning helpers</li>
      </ul>
      <p>Kathy Sierra seems to be describing manuals that support popular consumer products, like
        TiVo digital video recorders or MOTORAZR mobile phones. Learning about consumer products may
        inspire more passion and excitement in writers, both amateur and professional, than writing
        about products that are used in the workplace (and perhaps for boring or dirty jobs). Others
        may be passionate and inspired by open source products. Still others may enjoy documenting
        medical devices. And, for the most part, the documents that writers are paid to write are
        for products that help people do their jobs. So although Sierra’s outline does not seem
        widely applicable for all technical documents, it makes one wonder just how these types of
        sections could be worked into the existing documents. Would any particular audience
        appreciate sections that have the type of information that she’s talking about? Most likely
        the answer is yes. And wouldn’t we all like to be a little more passionate about the tools
        we use every day?</p>
      <p>In addition to finding passion in the tasks users do, writers should be applying customer
        support data, to help them keep up with changes in questions as time goes on and as releases
        go out the door. Much like the most popular
          <indexterm>Google<indexterm>search</indexterm></indexterm>Google
            search<indexterm>search<indexterm>relevance</indexterm></indexterm> hits, the most
        frequently accessed questions and answers should rise to the top of a customer support
        knowledge base. Interviewing those who spend the most time on the phone or in the field with
        customers gives us valuable insight into the questions that are currently being asked.</p>
    </body>
    <subsection
      id="d5e180">
      <title>Expectations for documentation have shifted</title>
      <body>
        <p><indexterm>technical documentation<indexterm>expectations
          for</indexterm></indexterm>Technology is pervasive in developed countries in all parts of
          life—home life, school life, and work life. As a result, expectations for technical
          documentation are shifting. Prior to the Internet, people would carefully store printed
          manuals on a bookshelf for reference. Today, people use a search engine as their starting
          point for troubleshooting a device. For example, I still see click-throughs from people
          searching for “BMC Performance Manager” nearly two years after posting blog entries about
          the BMC Software product “Performance Manager.” The small book that comes with a consumer
          device may still be the best place to look for assistance, especially because of the
          multiple translations available for international audiences. Yet a visual, video-loving
          user may search on You Tube for troubleshooting advice. And others might just use the
          interface itself until they figure it out. Still others might consider a friend or
          co-worker the best source of technical expertise, so documentation is rarely used by the
          inquirer (although certainly the expert friends or co-workers are intimately familiar with
          their favorite sources of technical information.)</p>
      </body>
    </subsection>
    <subsection
      id="d5e189">
      <title>Search may affect delivery and presentation methods</title>
      <body>
        <p><indexterm>content<indexterm>searching for</indexterm></indexterm>Search technology and
          its application by users has changed the face and entry point to <indexterm>technical
              documentation<indexterm>searching</indexterm></indexterm>technical documentation. The
          entry point is the page your user lands on first, also called a landing page. Sometimes
          landing pages are text-heavy and feature-focused rather than task-oriented. Search forms
          and entering a couple of keywords are more often the starting point for users reading
          online help.</p>
        <p>How many times have you heard someone say, “I found the following
              Microsoft<indexterm>Microsoft<indexterm>Knowledge Base,
            searching</indexterm></indexterm> Knowledge Base article using a Google
              search<indexterm>search<indexterm>accessing documentation
            through</indexterm></indexterm>” (or have said the same thing yourself)? Microsoft has
          built excellent content in their Knowledge Base, but a competitor’s search engine often
          brings users to the site. Although the Knowledge Base must have a search engine available
          to visitors (much like a manual of some sort is still required for many consumer
          products), when a visitor finds the content by using another search engine, all the
          resources, time, and money spent on providing a search engine on that Knowledge Base were
          wasted. The company experiences zero return on investment<indexterm>return on investment
              (ROI)<indexterm>search implementation</indexterm></indexterm> for the
              <indexterm>search<indexterm>investment in</indexterm></indexterm>search engine, but
          total return on investment on the <indexterm>return on investment (ROI)<indexterm>content
              development</indexterm></indexterm>content itself. </p>
        <p>Search relevance has to do with Google’s secret algorithms and the calculations used for
          ranking by any search engine. This relevance brings a user to your content when they are
          seeking an answer to a specific question. If your help system does not follow Google’s
          basic Webmaster guidelines,<fn><p>
            http://www.google.com/support/webmasters/?hl=en</p></fn> it may not be found as often as
          blog entries on the same topic. For example, Google indicates that fewer than 100 links
          from a sitemap are ideal, and warns that not every search engine spider searches dynamic
          pages with multiple parameters in the URL. You may have noticed that a recently
              <indexterm>content<indexterm>up-to-date</indexterm></indexterm>updated blog entry or
          wiki page tends to have more links to its entries by Google. A commenter notes this in a
          comment on the blog entry in the Britannica <indexterm>blogs<indexterm>search
              rankings</indexterm></indexterm>blog.<fn><p>
              http://www.britannica.com/blogs/2008/11/the-fast-food-information-age-we-are-what-we-read/</p></fn>
          “Perhaps another idea would be to ask Google WHY the social media (i.e. Wikipedia) entry
          for a topic ranks so much higher than the vetted, Britannica entry?”</p>
        <p>Secret algorithms or not, as a writer you need to understand your user’s entry points.
          Search is important to conversational documentation because of the importance search
          engines place on frequently-updated content. If your user assistance system is offline or
          infrequently updated, your users may not find answers by searching with popular search
          engines. For example, Google gives a higher
              <indexterm>search<indexterm>rankings</indexterm></indexterm>search ranking to more
          oft-updated content. </p>
        <p><indexterm>help, online<indexterm>searching
            within</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm>help,
            online<indexterm>finding</indexterm></indexterm>Naturally, you know your audience best.
          If they do not require online access to use your product, they may not search for answers
          to questions in a search engine. </p>
        <p>Merely using a blog or <indexterm>wikis<indexterm>search
            relevance</indexterm></indexterm>wiki as a holding place for content may improve the
          search ranking. You may think that your users will search within the help in the product
          itself, but you may find, as the Britannica blog writer did, that between 90 and 98% of
          library users in 2008 assumed they could get all relevant information on a subject by
          simply searching on Google. </p>
        <p>If these results are also true for users of the product that you document, then you need
          to try to get search words pointing to your online user assistance. A good first step is
          to ensure that your online user assistance is available on the Internet to be found by
          search engines. Also find out what your users search for, and then determine how you want
          to improve the ranking of those searches. Perhaps you want to integrate user-generated
          content into your user assistance if search engines tend to value those entries more than
          others. </p>
        <p>You can also place a carefully-crafted search index as the entry point to
              <indexterm>content<indexterm>community-generated</indexterm></indexterm>community
          content. Adobe created a Google Custom Search Engine as a front-end to community content
          and hand-selected the most useful community offerings such as blogs and video tutorials at
          community.adobe.com. By indexing only the highest-quality outside resources, Adobe helps
          build trust with the readers that use the search hits to find information.</p>
      </body>
    </subsection>
  </subsection>
  <subsection
    id="d5e282">
    <title>Types of writing influenced by the social web</title>
    <prolog>
      <metadata>
        <keywords>
          <indexterm>social media<indexterm>influence on technical
            documentation</indexterm></indexterm>
          <indexterm>influence on technical documentation</indexterm>
        </keywords>
      </metadata>
    </prolog>
    <body>
      <p>In February, 2008, STC President Linda <indexterm>Oestriech, Linda</indexterm>Oestriech
        stated in a podcast<indexterm>podcasts<indexterm>Tech Writer Voices</indexterm></indexterm>
        on Tech Writer Voices<fn><p>
            http://www.idratherbewriting.com/2008/02/05/interview-with-stc-president-linda-oestreich-the-direction-the-stc-is-heading/</p></fn>,
        “We aren’t the technical writers of the 70s.” I might add that we aren’t even the technical
        writers of the 90s. How have <indexterm>technical documentation<indexterm>changes
            in</indexterm></indexterm>changing technology and expectations influenced technical
        communication and writing today compared to 10 or 30 years ago?</p>
      <p>Many have been wondering about the state of technical communications and looking to the
        history of it for insight. For example, Jared Spool, a usability consultant, describes a
        past when technical people and engineers expected to learn every detail about a product and
        had no expectations of simply being able to pick something up and know how to use it. He
        describes how the user manuals weighed more than the product itself (and this was when
        computers filled a room). In those days, he says users invested enough in the technology
        that they wanted to learn the product, and started with reading the manuals.<fn><p>
            http://www.uie.com/brainsparks/2007/05/16/where-did-technical-writing-go/</p></fn>
      </p>
      <p>In contrast, Kathy <indexterm>Sierra, Kathy</indexterm>Sierra describes a successful manual
        today as a page-turner—user-friendly, one that users learn from, one that pushes users to
        higher levels of understanding by being motivating as well informational. Technical writers
        can deliver that user manual in the right corporate environment, or publishers can hire
        writers to deliver that user manual for sale in bookstores. </p>
      <p>Technical communication is not just about writing, and has always spanned multiple areas of
        expertise. User interface design and usability play a large part in communicating technical
        information so that users can do neat things with a technical product. Because our audiences
        use technology more often, but also demand simplicity and elegance, many products have
        become easier and more intuitive to use. As more products are available in a global
        marketplace, words are increasingly substituted with images and illustrations.
            Video<indexterm>video<indexterm>communicating technical topics
          with</indexterm></indexterm> editors and video producers are technical communicators as
        they develop training<indexterm>training</indexterm> courses. The market for words and
        printed books still exists, but favors “missing manuals,” guides for dummies, and other
        books that teach or instruct. </p>
    </body>
  </subsection>
  <subsection
    id="d5e330">
    <title>Defining conversation </title>
    <body>
      <p>Conversation<indexterm>conversations<indexterm>defining</indexterm></indexterm> as a
        discourse is nearly undefinable since it spans so many speech events and environments from
        informal to formal, intimate to public, and argumentative to collaborative, plus many more
        in a spectrum. But certain contexts for
            <indexterm>conversations<indexterm>joining</indexterm></indexterm>conversation are
        useful for <indexterm>technical documentation<indexterm>benefiting from
            conversation</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm>technical
            documentation<indexterm>conversations within</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm>social
            media<indexterm>technical writers and</indexterm></indexterm>documentation, such as the
        communities of practice that allow users to participate in conversations that Nicky
          <indexterm>Bleiel, Nicky</indexterm>Bleiel describes as “Convergence Technical
        Communication” in an article for The Content Wrangler.<fn><p>
            http://www.thecontentwrangler.com/article/convergence_technical_communication_strategies_for_incorporating_web_20/</p></fn></p>
      <p>Imagine that you are assigned to answer customer support calls at a mobile phone network
        supplier for a day. You would establish a connection with each customer, put a name with a
        voice or face or email address, and from a quick customer database search, you know who the
        customer works for and what that customer’s role is in their company. Thanks to your
        company’s call log, you might know the exact problem each customer is wrestling with and be
        able to pinpoint the information they need to solve their problems. </p>
      <p>If writers had that much information every time they started writing a new document,
        section, or topic, they could be more effective for one individual customer. But technical
        guides usually need to help hundreds of such customers. So imagine instead that you are
        reading a deep technical debate in the discussion area of a wiki, on a customer’s blog, or a
        140-character Twitter post. How would you rewrite your documentation to answer that users’
        exact question, and then make the information accessible to any user? And, can you step into
        the conversation by posting a response that gives that user the right information at the
        right time?</p>
    </body>
    <subsection
      id="d5e368">
      <title>Asynchronous conversations</title>
      <body>
        <p>Nearly all <indexterm>technical documentation<indexterm>benefiting from
              conversation</indexterm></indexterm>documentation can be considered an
            asynchronous<indexterm>asynchronous conversation</indexterm>
          <indexterm>conversations<indexterm>asynchronous</indexterm></indexterm>conversation
          between reader and writer, meaning that the messages can be written or received at any
          time regardless of the sender or receiver’s schedule. The reader is an audience that the
          writer has considered before determining what to write. As Ginny Redish<indexterm>Redish,
            Ginny</indexterm> says in her book, <i>Letting Go of the Words: Writing Web Content that
            Works</i>, writers can relate to solving the issues of “helping people get just what
          they need, when they need it, in the amount they need, as quickly as possible.” Good
          information chunking and organizing practices create a just-in-time conversation to help
          someone, somewhere accomplish his or her goals.</p>
        <p><indexterm>Hyde, Adam</indexterm>Adam Hyde, founder of <indexterm>FLOSS
              Manuals<indexterm>collaborative
              writing</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm>collaboration<indexterm>FLOSS
              Manuals</indexterm></indexterm>FLOSS Manuals, finds that conversation has a clear and
          direct value in the in-person events called Book Sprints that serve to create content from
          outlines in a short period of time, such as a week. He perceives that the
              <indexterm>conversations<indexterm>in-person</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm>conversations<indexterm>Book
              Sprints</indexterm></indexterm>conversation takes place on at least four
              <indexterm>conversations<indexterm>levels
              of</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm>content<indexterm>collaboration in
              creating</indexterm></indexterm>levels: </p>
        <ul>
          <li>In the room: With all participants seated around the same table conversations need to
            be fostered. Unlike traditional writing processes, this is a noisy environment and
            chatter should be encouraged. It is through these across-the-table conversations that
            the participants are harmonizing their ideas about what they are writing.</li>
          <li>In the text: The texts themselves are conversations. Do not be protective about the
            content you contribute­—encourage others to read it, change it, delete it etc. The
            continual combing through of the content by many eyes is a fundamental tenet of Free
            Software and serves equally well in this environment. This constant changing is itself a
            conversation happening in the text and it is essential for improving and harmonizing the
            content.</li>
          <li>Outside the room: Be in touch with people outside the room and ask for their take on
            the texts. It is important to know if the texts really are going in a direction that can
            be understood by people that have not been privy to the conversations in the Book Sprint
            room. Encourage remote participants to feed back into the conversation via
              <indexterm>Internet Relay Chat
                (IRC)</indexterm><indexterm>conversations<indexterm>Internet Relay Chat
                (IRC)</indexterm></indexterm>Internet Relay Chat (<indexterm>IRC (Internet Relay
              Chat)</indexterm>IRC), email, editing, and the FLOSS Manuals web chat.</li>
          <li>With the reader: When writing, use a direct and friendly and conversational voice. One
            trick to getting disk jockeys to relax and sound ‘normal’ on air is to cut out a picture
            of a face, stick it to the microphone and ask the DJ to talk ‘to’ that person. This
            works. We have not tried this approach yet in Book Sprints, however the same effect can
            be achieved by thinking of the reader as someone you know well and respect. Write to
            that person as if you were explaining something you know they don’t understand. </li>
        </ul>
      </body>
    </subsection>
    <subsection
      id="d5e441">
      <title>Agile development and conversations for collaboration</title>
      <prolog>
        <metadata>
          <keywords>
            <indexterm>development</indexterm>
          </keywords>
        </metadata>
      </prolog>
      <body>
        <p><indexterm>conversations<indexterm>Agile development
            and</indexterm></indexterm>Agile<indexterm>Agile development</indexterm>
            development<indexterm>development</indexterm> techniques may involve writing user
          stories that can be developed and designed within a “sprint” or iteration that may be as
          short as two weeks. Teams applying this type of development strive to develop robust
          software rapidly, including testing and documenting it, so that the new story can be
          played out immediately after the end of the iteration. By leveraging the Agile user story,
          which should be user-centric and task-oriented, writers can put themselves into the place
          of a customer. Because Agile development encourages developers to write the user story
          while developing the product, the goal is to match the user’s expectations quickly. In
          some ways, Agile development lends itself well to <indexterm>Web 2.0<indexterm>fit with
              Agile development</indexterm></indexterm>Web 2.0 tools and pushes the user story that
          may be told with social web tools such as blogs or wikis towards the development phase
          rather than the post-release phase. </p>
        <p>If we can get closer to the users by finding out their documentation needs, we can better
          understand their product needs. Then, we can help build in solutions to these needs during
          the design of our products, moving ourselves closer to the design stages rather than
          relegating documentation as an afterthought of development. Collaboration with users can
          go a long way towards collaboration in the workplace during product design. </p>
      </body>
    </subsection>
  </subsection>
  <subsection
    id="d5e465">
    <title>Reasons for moving content towards the social web</title>
    <body>
      <p>As Harry Miller at <indexterm>content<indexterm>moving to social
          web</indexterm></indexterm>Microsoft pondered in a podcast in mid-2000, what if a user
        guide had to read like an Instant Messaging, or IM,<indexterm>IM (Instant
          Messaging)</indexterm>
        <indexterm>conversations<indexterm>instant
        messaging</indexterm></indexterm>conversation—quick, real-time questions and fast answers,
        tailored to nearly every potential customer situation?<fn><p>
            http://blogs.msdn.com/harrymiller/archive/2007/07/16/the-im-model-of-tech-writing.aspx</p></fn>
        We may be seeing the birth of such a user’s guide with Twitter’s popularity as a customer
        care platform and the <indexterm>Twitter<indexterm>user growth
        rate</indexterm></indexterm>Twitter user base growing at a rate of over 30% in one month
        (February 2009).<fn><p>
            http://siteanalytics.compete.com/facebook.com+twitter.com/?metric=uv</p></fn></p>
      <p>Different users have different <indexterm>technical documentation<indexterm>expectations
            for</indexterm></indexterm>expectations and needs for documentation. Some users expect
        precise answers from a user guide. Some want to impress people with their knowledge and
        efficiency. Others might have a particular aversion to truly learning a product because they
        use the product only once every other month to perform a specific (perhaps boring) task. The
        manual that you write might not respond to all of these needs just yet. But if you keep
        enabling conversations with users, your documentation can anticipate questions and give
        answers so responsively that your users might wonder if there’s a ghost in the machine. But
        even if your documentation can’t “talk back” to your users, it can help users talk to each
        other and make connections that help them do their jobs well, play with technology at home,
        or learn something new in a classroom setting. Instead of concentrating on single sourcing
        methods or the tools of the trade, think about <indexterm>technical
            documentation<indexterm>benefiting from
        conversation</indexterm></indexterm>documentation and user assistance as a multiple-channel
        communication device, perhaps with the help of some social technology applications.</p>
      <p>Many skills that are valuable in delivering traditional user assistance are easily
        transferable to social network integration for user assistance. These skills include:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>Excellent communication</li>
        <li>Concise writing</li>
        <li>Good design</li>
        <li>Planning</li>
      </ul>
    </body>
    <subsection
      id="d5e518">
      <title>Pack carefully when moving content towards conversation </title>
      <body>
        <p>Technical writers have plenty of good reasons to avoid actual
              <indexterm>conversations<indexterm>enabling</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm>conversations<indexterm>avoiding</indexterm></indexterm>conversations
          with customers. We are not usually trained to handle an angry customer or to troubleshoot
          the product at the technical level that is necessary. But technical writers are typically
          good at learning quickly and applying technology to solve problems. You might think that
          social media or social networking is meant only for young people, or that only a person
          with too much spare time appreciates things like social bookmarking or Second Life. But
          these technologies do not belong only to the young, the technically savvy, or the
          extremely extroverted. The demographics for both Facebook and Twitter users show trends
          towards an aging group. The fastest growing demographic group for Facebook in February
          2009 includes people over the age of 35<fn><p>
              http://www.facebook.com/press/info.php?statistics</p></fn> and more than 40% of
          Twitter users are age 35–49.</p>
        <p>Technical communicators are already skilled in many of these technologies and just have
          to learn to apply them to communication with users. Welcome and seek out internal coaching
          in the area of customer communications, though. Missteps may cause setbacks in your plans
          to enable customer connections with your documentation. Also, ensure that your plans mesh
          with an overall corporate social media strategy. </p>
      </body>
    </subsection>
  </subsection>
  <subsection
    id="d5e537">
    <title>Social media, social networking, and now the social web</title>
    <body>
      <p><indexterm>social media<indexterm>defining</indexterm></indexterm>Social media is still
        being defined, but over the past few years, more people have weighed in on the definition.
        It’s an interesting use of social media to study the definition of social media. For
        example, the Wikipedia<indexterm>Wikipedia</indexterm> entry about social media points to
        the popular tech blogger Robert Scoble’s blog post about social media in which he defined
        social media as news media pitting old media against new media. But even though social media
        is compared to newspapers and journalism, technical writers can think of themselves as
        interviewers and journalists. A journalism background may help you see ways to present
        information in a news-delivery style. <indexterm>Abel, Scott</indexterm>Scott Abel, creator
        of The <indexterm>Content Wrangler, The</indexterm>Content Wrangler website and community,
        has a journalism background and purposely runs The Content Wrangler site more like a
        magazine than a blog.</p>
      <p>Many companies invest in social media projects through their marketing or advertisement
        departments. Technical writers, however, should not dismiss the application of social media
        to their deliverables because it appears at first glance to be more of a marketing function
        or a method of building up a brand. </p>
      <p>Social media, social networking, and the social web are related concepts but separately
        defined from Web 2.0. As social media researcher <indexterm>boyd, danah</indexterm>danah
        boyd, (she prefers no capitalization of her name), points out in a talk at the Microsoft
        Research Tech Fest called, Social Media is Here to Stay… Now What? Web 2.0 has different
        meanings for technologists, businesses, and users. She also says, “Social media is the
        latest buzzword in a long line of buzzwords.”<fn><p>
            http://www.danah.org/papers/talks/MSRTechFest2009.html</p></fn></p>
      <p>No matter what the preferred term is, those of us researching social aspects of information
        dissemination can find many applications beyond news reporting and brand building for social
        media. The next chapter explores some of the basics and then dives into examples of web
        applications that enable social media.</p>
    </body>
  </subsection>
</chapter>
