<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<chapter
  id="d5e2"><title>Defining a Writer’s Role with the Social Web</title><shortdesc>The more original
    a discovery, &#8232;the more obvious it seems afterwards.&#8232;—Arthur
    Koestler</shortdesc><prolog/><body><p>As a writer, you need to find the correct value
      proposition for your work and determine whether your role is an enabler of conversation or an
      instigator of conversation. In a world of rock star coders, you want to find out whether you
      are a sage on stage or a stage hand. Or perhaps your evaluation will determine that no social
      media action is the correct action.</p><p>You might already be aware of the challenges of
      introducing Web 2.0 or community-driven content in an enterprise environment. Many people are
      skeptics, asking for proof of the efficacy of the methods. This chapter discusses strategies
      for determining your role and offers strategies for a phased approach to integrating the
      social web in your writing. </p></body><subsection
    id="d5e10"><title>Challenges and opportunities</title><body><p>Once you get enthusiastic about a
        particular social networking tool or medium, you may find that you spend an inordinate
        amount of time on the site or reviewing the tools used for the site. Be aware of your
        priorities, and be cautious of portraying a tool as a time-wasting, productivity-sucking
        black hole before others can give it a chance. Remember that your online <indexterm
          >presence, online</indexterm>presence records the amount of time and the time of day that
        you work with a tool. You can avoid too much of a good thing if you’re smart about your time
        allocation. You might need to participate in an online community after normal business hours
        to ensure that the community trusts you to do your “real” job first and experimentation
        second.</p><p>It’s important to find a balance between allowing an individual’s authentic
        voice to speak on behalf of an organization and the requirements of institutional messaging
        and <indexterm>brands<indexterm>preserving</indexterm></indexterm>brand preservation. Be
        sure to follow all related corporate <indexterm>policies, social computing<indexterm
            >following</indexterm></indexterm>policies and study the messaging that your company
        prefers to maintain. </p><p>It’s also possible that you are ahead of the curve and need to
        help others see ways to apply social technologies for the company. You could get involved in
        a community related to personal interests outside of work to understand how social
        technologies can be applied before attempting to apply what you’ve learned at work. This
        approach works well especially if your organization is extra-conservative or if there is no
        demand for content with social connections yet for your company.</p><p>What about the
        ubiquitous argument, “Sorry, but we just don’t have the resources for this type of project”?
        You might need to barter for resources or entice someone’s time and skills off the clock.
        Think of the reasons that people are motivated to contribute to a project, such as
        recognition or respect, and see what you can offer in return. Also realize that if the
        resources truly are not available but you think you can save time and money with social or
        community content<indexterm>community-generated content<indexterm>contributions
            to</indexterm></indexterm>, you need to have a strategy and be able to prove return on
        the investment in time and money. </p><p>Return on <indexterm>return on investment
            (ROI)<indexterm>proving</indexterm></indexterm>investment<indexterm>return on investment
            (ROI)<indexterm>measuring</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm>return on investment
            (ROI)<indexterm>content development</indexterm></indexterm> is notoriously hard to
        measure because of the difficulty in determining what to measure and how to measure.
      </p></body><subsection
      id="d5e54"><title>Taking stock of current communities and conversations</title><body><p>Before
          you jump in and risk embarrassing yourself or your team or, worse yet, angering customers
          or internal departments, with the absolute worst risk of being fired, you need to analyze
          and understand the <indexterm>communities<indexterm>writer's role
            in</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm>communities<indexterm>existing</indexterm></indexterm>communities
          that already exist within your company or externally and learn how to interact or stand
          back. As writers, we need to figure out whether we would be welcomed as members of the
          community or whether we should instead try to enable the conversation through our
          deliverables. Based on the size of your particular community base, you may decide to
          immerse yourself in the <indexterm>communities<indexterm>participation
            in</indexterm></indexterm>community, to become a part of the conversation, and make your
          customers feel like you are helping them solve problems. </p><p>Realize that there are
            <indexterm>grassroots communities for products</indexterm>grassroots<indexterm
            >grassroots efforts</indexterm>
          <indexterm>communities<indexterm>grassroots</indexterm></indexterm>communities related to
          commercial products. For example, the XMFan site<fn><p> http://xmfan.com/</p></fn> was
          started by regular people who are fans of XM Radio. Another example is the IKEAFans<fn><p>
              http://ikeafans.com/</p></fn> site offers support help and an “IKEApedia” area with
          assembly manuals included. When approaching a <indexterm>conversations<indexterm
              >enabling</indexterm></indexterm>community started outside of the company, though, be
          cautious of whether you would be considered an intruder or outsider. </p><p>An excellent
          example of a writer offering their community involvement back with improvements to content
          is the lead writer for Adobe InDesign and InCopy products, Bob <indexterm>Bringhurst,
            Bob</indexterm>Bringhurst. He writes a blog at blogs.adobe.com/indesigndocs/ with
          announcements, buried treasures, and bonus documentation, to name a few categories. He is
          active on the user forums and uses his blog to talk to community members and link to
          others’ blogs, such as this InDesign link round up entry.<fn><p>
              http://blogs.adobe.com/indesigndocs/2009/05/best_indesign_links_of_may.html</p></fn>
        </p><p>You could follow different models for participation in communities—use the technical
          writer as personality and deliverer of content, a “sage on stage” model where the writer
          instigates participation opportunities, or involve the technical writer as a bystander of
          the conversation. In the second model, the writer is more like a stage hand who needs to
          understand the inner workings of the community theater to put on a good show. We can
          enable conversation through our user assistance without being the star of the show. A
          third model of participation is to listen to many communities and learn from the
          interactions of others, bringing that knowledge back into the technical documentation or
          passing it to the appropriate groups at your company. </p><p>Anne Zelenka<indexterm
            >Zelenka, Anne</indexterm> has written about the <i>information age</i> versus the
            <indexterm>connectivity age</indexterm><i>connectivity age</i> on the Web Worker
            Daily<indexterm>Web Worker Daily</indexterm> web site.<fn><p>
              http://gigaom.com/2007/10/06/from-the-information-age-to-the-connected-age/</p></fn> I
          believe this distinction is an important one for the participation models that writers can
          choose. Are you an information worker or a connection worker, and does your corporate
          culture support you more in one model or another? Anne likens the building of
            Microsoft<indexterm>Microsoft<indexterm>"information age"
            example</indexterm></indexterm> as an example of the information age. The currency is
          always monetary, and the information that Microsoft created begat monolithic software.
          Google, on the other hand, has built a <indexterm>Google<indexterm>business
              model</indexterm></indexterm>business model based on human behavior to make products
          that use attention, such as Adwords, turn into monetized goods. If you can find a way to
          turn attention to your online help with <indexterm>conversations<indexterm
              >locating</indexterm></indexterm>conversation or community inclusion, you have moved
          your user assistance into the connected age. Take note of where your company already
          exhibits movement towards the connected age. </p><p>If you have observed that most user
            <indexterm>communities<indexterm>content contributed
          by</indexterm></indexterm>communities do not publish comprehensive tomes, you are correct.
          As Andy Oram<indexterm>Oram, Andy</indexterm> of O’Reilly Media says, people who respond
          to email <indexterm>mailing lists<indexterm>community-based
            content</indexterm></indexterm>lists do not even think that they are writing
            documentation.<fn><p>
              http://www.oreillynet.com/onlamp/blog/2007/01/why_do_you_contribute_to_commu.html
            </p></fn> However, because a search can find the information, and the information can
          answer someone’s question later, it actually is documentation. As Darren
            Barefoot<indexterm>Barefoot, Darren</indexterm> said in his talk “Everyone’s a technical
          writer” at <indexterm>DocTrain West conference</indexterm>DocTrain West in spring 2008,
          the “people formerly known as the audience” are already documenting your products in ways
          you could never hope to cover yourself with a team of technical
      writers.</p></body></subsection><subsection
      id="d5e173"><title>Instigator or enabler of conversation</title><body><p>An <indexterm
            >technical documentation<indexterm>integrating with community-based
            content</indexterm></indexterm>instigator provides a starting point for a <indexterm
              >conversations<indexterm>instigating</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm
              >conversations<indexterm>enabling</indexterm></indexterm>conversation, perhaps by
          communicating a controversial decision or a highly debated strategic choice. A writer in
          an instigator role should know customers’ business needs and be well-connected with those
          he or she plans to talk to online. </p><p>An enabler of conversation understands the
          underlying concepts of a product or service well enough to help others understand those
          concepts as well. An enabler gives a community the authority to make decisions or provides
          patterns that help a community develop and grow. </p><p>Whether you’re an instigator or
          enabler, you can repeatedly gather knowledge from <indexterm>technical
              documentation<indexterm>benefiting from
          conversation</indexterm></indexterm>communities and conversation, then bring it back and
          incorporate what you’ve learned into the documentation. Ideally you’ll “give back” to the
            <indexterm>content<indexterm>community-generated</indexterm></indexterm>communities that
          provided the knowledge to you by continually improving the content offerings. </p><p>It
          may seem that an extrovert would be the instigator of conversations in documentation, and
          an introvert would be the enabler of the conversations. Introversion and extroversion
          refer to how a person draws energy—either from an external source such as interaction with
          other people, or from an internal source, such as their own thoughts and imagination.
          However, in the realm of social media, introverts often find online social networking
          provides the right balance of encouragement to reach out along with the ability to turn
          off the stream of constant communication and regroup for a period of time. Therefore, the
          role of an instigator does not need to be reserved for an extrovert. An extroverted
          instigator may not be a good blogger, for example, because good writing often requires
          introspection and reflection. But either personality type can take on either role and do
          the tasks within each role. </p></body></subsection></subsection><subsection
    id="d5e208"><title>Building a strategic plan for conversation and community
      integration</title><body><p>As with all technical documentation projects, you should plan
        before implementing any changes to your documentation or approach. However, when trying out
        social media tools, you need to be willing to spend time experimenting. Grassroots<indexterm
          >grassroots efforts</indexterm> efforts that fly under management<indexterm>management
          buy-in</indexterm>’s radar for a while might give you the biggest payback. </p><p>Beth
          Kanter<indexterm>Kanter, Beth</indexterm>, a social media consultant to non-profits,
        describes participation in social media as having five <indexterm>social media<indexterm
            >phases for implementing</indexterm></indexterm>phases: listen, participate, generate
        buzz, share content, and create community.<fn><p>
            http://beth.typepad.com/beths_blog/2008/10/how-much-time-d.html</p></fn> A
        simplification for our approach involves four phases: </p><ul><li>First, listen. </li><li
          >Second, participate in the conversations (and continue to listen). </li><li>Third, share
          content.</li><li>Fourth, lead the way by offering a platform for conversations to
          occur.</li></ul><p>A conversation enabler will work best in the first two phases. A
        conversation instigator can work in all the phases. I believe this phased approach yields
        better results than jumping straight to offering a platform. You may notice that I skipped
        over <indexterm>Kanter, Beth</indexterm>Beth Kanter’s third phase where she suggests that
        you should generate buzz. I don’t think that generating buzz or media attention is
        necessarily the realm of <indexterm>technical documentation<indexterm>integrating with
            community-based content</indexterm></indexterm>technical documentation, though it might
        be if you’re a lone writer bridging the gap in technical marketing documentation.
      </p></body><subsection
      id="d5e250"><title>Listening phase</title><body><p>In their ebook, <indexterm>Social Media
            Marketing Playbook (Getting to First Base) ebook</indexterm>Social Media Marketing
          Playbook, Darren Barefoot and Julie <indexterm>Szabo, Julie</indexterm>Szabo believe that
          technical writers are excellent blog monitors and can easily handle multiple notifications
          from reading multiple news feeds or RSS subscriptions. If the technical writer is also
          maintaining a blog and online presence, <indexterm>communities<indexterm>listening to
              conversations in</indexterm></indexterm>commenting on others’ blogs in the field is a
          great way to join the <indexterm>conversations<indexterm>listening
            to</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm>conversations<indexterm>following through
              syndication</indexterm></indexterm>conversation, but <indexterm>blogs<indexterm
              >commenting on</indexterm></indexterm>commenting on blogs moves into the participation
          phase. </p><p>Tools for listening are subscription tools such as RSS feed readers,
            <indexterm>Google<indexterm>Alerts</indexterm></indexterm>Google Alerts, <indexterm
              >search<indexterm>in Twitter</indexterm></indexterm>search.twitter.com, <indexterm
            >Technorati</indexterm>Technorati, and Yahoo Pipes.</p><p>Another way to listen is to
          spend a day with technical support listening to their calls. This literal listening
          exercise can be eye opening if you’ve never spent a day on the customer line before.</p><p
          >If your product is sold on a website like amazon.com, you can also find conversations in
          the reviews, review comments, and blog entries.</p></body></subsection><subsection
      id="d5e299"><title>Participation phase</title><body><p>In this phase, you can blog
            and<indexterm>comments<indexterm>on blog posts</indexterm></indexterm>
          <indexterm>conversations<indexterm>joining</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm>blogging<indexterm>commenting</indexterm></indexterm>comment
          on blogs. The authors of the book <i>Groundswell</i>, Charlene <indexterm>Li,
            Charlene</indexterm>Li and Josh <indexterm>Bernoff, Josh</indexterm>Bernoff, suggest
          that you write five entries to see if you have the ability to stick with regular
            <indexterm>blogging<indexterm>regularly</indexterm></indexterm>blogging. Internal
          blogging is also a good starting point, where the blog can only be read behind a corporate
          firewall. Other participation ideas include:</p><ul><li>Find a wiki and contribute. Start
            with small tasks such as editing or tagging. </li><li>Offer a comment mechanism built
            into your <indexterm>help, online<indexterm>conversation-based tools
              in</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm>help, online<indexterm>comments
              in</indexterm></indexterm>help system.</li><li>Offer a <indexterm>help,
                online<indexterm>surveys in</indexterm></indexterm>survey on your help system.
            </li><li>Start tagging sites relevant to your product on delicious.com, reddit.com, or
            stumbleupon.com.</li><li>Offer a live chat or take a turn staffing the live chat if you
            have the knowledge.</li><li>Consider joining or <indexterm>moderation<indexterm
                >forums</indexterm></indexterm>moderating a <indexterm>communities<indexterm
                >participation in</indexterm></indexterm>customer forum or <indexterm
                >boards<indexterm>message</indexterm></indexterm>board that has private messaging
            where one-on-one conversations can occur. </li></ul></body></subsection><subsection
      id="d5e373"><title>Content sharing phase</title><body><p>The content sharing phase may be as
          simple to implement as adding a <indexterm>Creative Commons license</indexterm>Creative
          Commons <indexterm>content<indexterm>licensing</indexterm></indexterm>license to your
          content to allow for share and share alike. Licensing your content with a Creating Commons
          license declares that your content is reusable and describes the conditions and
          circumstances for that reuse. There are different licenses available for you (or your
          legal department at your company) to review. Instead of reserving all rights to your
          documentation, you reserve some rights, but also free the content to be used by others.
          For example, the Adobe help content offered with the Technical Communication Suite has a
          Creative Commons license, Attribution Non-Commercial Share Alike, as indicated by this
          icon:</p><p>On the creativecommons.org web site, you can answer straight forward questions
          to determine the license you want for your content, such as do you want to allow
          commercial uses of your work, do you want to allow modifications of your work (with or
          without others share alike on content created from your work), and the jurisdiction of
          your license. Licensing your content lets you share your content. </p><p>Another way to
          share your content is to offer an RSS feed that someone could embed in a sidebar or
          another location in a web page. A web service like dapper.net can help you make RSS feeds
          from any web page. </p><p>You can share content by uploading photos or screenshots to a
            <indexterm>photos</indexterm>photo sharing site such as Flickr, or you could upload
          videos or <indexterm>screencasts</indexterm>screencasts to You Tube or Vimeo. Beyond
          photos and videos, a great example of sharing content is the Autodesk Civil Engineering
            Community.<fn><p> http://civilcommunity.autodesk.com/content/</p></fn> Users can join
          the community and download templates, styles or shapes. </p></body></subsection><subsection
      id="d5e403"><title>Platform or stage phase</title><body><p>If the first three phases yielded
            <indexterm>content<indexterm>platforms for</indexterm></indexterm>connections and a
          sense of community that you could tap for growing community-based documentation, your
          final phase might be to create a <indexterm>communities<indexterm>wikis
              supporting</indexterm></indexterm>wiki for your product, either as a supplement to
          your documentation or as the new home of your entire user assistance content. </p><p
          >Alternatively, if users and customers have enough to say about your product that you
          think it would be helpful to the community to host a blog, the result of the first two
          phases might be to offer a blogging platform. </p><p>You might find that a forum becomes a
          platform for developers to collaborate with each other on projects. The <indexterm
              >communities<indexterm>EMC</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm>communities<indexterm
              >examples of online</indexterm></indexterm>EMC Community offers blogs, forums, and
          social media opportunities on platforms such as Facebook and Flickr in one community site
          at emc.com/community. </p><p>Another example of a social media plaat sun.com/communities.
          Two writers, Gail <indexterm>Chappell, Gail</indexterm>Chappell and Cindy <indexterm
            >Church, Cindy</indexterm>Church, presented their experience with Sun at the 2008
            <indexterm>STC Summit</indexterm>STC Summit. Both their product and their <indexterm
            >social media<indexterm>audience analysis</indexterm></indexterm>audience were a good
          match for providing a platform for documentation through a wiki. Their audience was
          college-age developers in school plus industry-savvy developers in the workforce, both
          busily coding enterprise applications using <indexterm>open source<indexterm>NetBeans
              Ruby</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm>NetBeans Ruby</indexterm>NetBeans Ruby. It’s a
          free, open-source software tool for creating Ruby language programs and part of the
          NetBeans integrated development environment. </p><p>For their case study, contributions
          from the community were welcomed, both for the product and the documentation. The wiki did
          not take off as a platform for community-generated content as you might think, though.
          They used the <indexterm>open source<indexterm>wikis for</indexterm></indexterm>wiki for
          providing drafts of documentation and delivering info quickly. Content on the wiki did not
          need to be perfect or in a strict template. Once a draft was posted to the wiki, writers
          then posted a message to the user forum to let them know they could review it. Once the
          content was reviewed and vetted, writers transferred it to the main website instead of the
          wiki. One lesson to learn from their experience is that even though the writers provided a
          platform for community content, the model that was most valuable was using the wiki for
          drafting content then transferring the content to a non-platform-based
        deliverable.</p></body></subsection><subsection
      id="d5e461"><title>Putting it all together</title><body><p>During any phase you can consider
          the level of your content itself. Any one of these levels may fit your business needs, but
          you can use the following table as a roadmap towards using social documentation to further
          more and more business needs.</p></body></subsection></subsection><subsection
    id="d5e466"><title>The documentation environment</title><body><p>What is the lifecycle of the
        products that you document? If your company releases products often, your users may expect
        documentation updates every release. A wiki may be the best way to fulfill this expectation.
        If the product releases only once every other year, you can invest in conversations during
        those longer release cycles by using a different format, such as customer <indexterm
          >discussions about content<indexterm>in forums</indexterm></indexterm>forums, blogs, or
        podcasts.</p><p>What are the current technical publications deliverables? If your team still
        relies heavily on printed documentation, you might not have an efficient method for getting
        feedback from or conversing with customers. If you continue to deliver printed
        documentation, you will want to find online methods for enabling conversation and community.
        If you do not already have a method for gathering feedback on printed documentation,
        investigate the costs and returns of sending printed-format surveys or
      questionnaires.</p></body><subsection
      id="d5e477"><title>Documentation survey to analyze audiences </title><prolog><metadata
            ><keywords>
            <indexterm>audience analysis</indexterm>
            <indexterm>surveys</indexterm>
          </keywords></metadata></prolog><body><p>Surveys are yet <indexterm>technical
              documentation<indexterm>getting feedback</indexterm></indexterm>another conversation
          point with your audience, especially if you have an integrated survey system tied into
          your <indexterm>help, online<indexterm>surveys in</indexterm></indexterm>help system, such
          as a rating system or comment system. Collecting and analyzing <indexterm>social
              media<indexterm>surveys of use</indexterm></indexterm>survey data is a proven method
          for discovering the communities your readers already use to find answers. You can survey
          your <indexterm>technical documentation<indexterm>analyzing
            audiences</indexterm></indexterm>audience in several ways, even inexpensively using
          services like surveymonkey.com. <indexterm>Google<indexterm
          >Forms</indexterm></indexterm>Google Forms are easy to design, and when someone fills out
          the form, the data automatically goes into a Google Spreadsheet as it is collected so you
          can see partial results before the survey is closed. If you do not want to expend
          resources sending out your own survey, find ways to add a question or two to surveys that
          are already sent to your customers.</p><p>Go beyond a documentation survey into a social
          media usage survey as described in the next section. </p></body></subsection><subsection
      id="d5e514"><title>Determining if your customers would like a conversation </title><body><p
          >Look at the specific problems that your technical publications group is trying to solve
          or has had feedback about, and analyze whether applying some of the <indexterm>social
              networking<indexterm>integrating with documentation</indexterm></indexterm>social
          networking or notifications technology would help solve those problems. Customers cannot
          always articulate their needs in specific requests for a certain deliverable like a wiki.
          Keep in mind that the terms “RSS feeds” and “wiki” may not be familiar to your customers.
          If you asked them, “Would you like to know when new items are added to the help system?”,
          they would probably respond positively. Also consider the prospect who is not yet a
          customer. What conversation or community techniques can build relationships that help with
          converting a prospect to a customer?</p><p>Analyze your audience to determine their pain
          points. Ask questions or conduct a survey, and be sure to understand the demographic
          information. While gender and age are not always good indicators of an individual’s
          behavior online, research indicates that men use certain social media tools like
            <indexterm>Twitter<indexterm>user demographics</indexterm></indexterm>Twitter
          differently than women do.<fn><p>
              http://www.iq.harvard.edu/blog/netgov/2009/06/hbs_research_twitter_oligarchy.html</p></fn>
          Different age groups might have different answers for your survey, or not. A <indexterm
            >surveys</indexterm>survey run by two technical writers at Sun had an audience
            of<indexterm>Sun Microsystems<indexterm>survey for shifting
            priorities</indexterm></indexterm> programmers, most of whom were male. The writers
          wondered if age differences would result in a different “wish list” for video or
            screencasts<indexterm>screencasts</indexterm>. They found that no matter the age, all of
          the programmers wanted pretty much the same thing—examples and a web celebrity of sorts to
          listen to and learn from. Using the information they gained from the survey, the writers
          could provide a business case for shifting their priorities in a release from traditional
          online help to videos and screencasts.</p><p>The book <i>Groundswell</i><indexterm
            >Groundswell</indexterm> offers a Social <indexterm>Groundswell Social Technographics
            tool</indexterm>Technographics tool.<fn><p>
              http://www.forrester.com/Groundswell/profile_tool.html</p></fn> is an <indexterm
              >communities<indexterm>demographics</indexterm></indexterm>example of the results for
          U.S.-based women aged 35-44.</p><p>Data from Forrester Research Technographics
            surveys<indexterm>surveys</indexterm></p><p>Creators are at the top of the ladder
          because they create content such as blog entries or videos. Critics are most likely to
          respond to others on email <indexterm>mailing lists<indexterm>contributions
            to</indexterm></indexterm>lists or <indexterm>forums<indexterm>contributions
              to</indexterm></indexterm>forums. At the bottom of the ladder are Inactives, those who
          do not create or consume social content. If your study shows that many of your customers
          are Inactives, you may not need <indexterm>social media<indexterm>surveys of
              use</indexterm></indexterm>social media integration to serve your customer’s
          information needs.</p></body></subsection><subsection
      id="d5e586"><title>Determining your role in the conversation</title><body><p>You can ask
          several questions to help discover if you are an enabler of conversation, an instigator,
          or both. Depending on the number of users of the products that you document, there may be
          a place for the technical writer in the <indexterm>communities<indexterm>participation
              in</indexterm></indexterm>community. For wiki documentation especially, it is
          important that you become a conversation starter, unless there’s a large community base
          already. Several factors influence<indexterm>influence, measuring</indexterm> this
          determination: </p><ul><li>Is the <indexterm>communities<indexterm>writer's role
                in</indexterm></indexterm>community small, and if so, can you easily become like the
            community members? Or is there a conflict of interest that might prevent you from direct
            communications? </li><li>What <indexterm>communities<indexterm>motivations
                of</indexterm></indexterm>motivates the community to use your product? If community
            members are passionate about your product because they selected it, the conversation may
            be easy to start and continue. If the product was purchased by upper management and
            implemented by community members, you might be more effective as a conversation enabler
            than a starter/joiner. </li><li>Is the community getting paid to implement the product?
            If so, will they view your presence<indexterm>presence, online</indexterm> as
            competition? In this type of situation, it might be better to enable
            conversation.</li><li>Has another department in your company started a <indexterm
                >conversations<indexterm>instigating</indexterm></indexterm>conversation? If other
            departments internally are in fact responsible for responding, be careful about how your
            involvement might be interpreted. Talk to others internally before inserting yourself as
            a community member or you may appear to be strong-arming others. A slow, easy beginning
            is best, and practice and hands-on experience are your most valuable assets.
          </li></ul><p>Whether you’re enabling a conversation or are part of the conversation, it’s
          important to be professional but also personable and genuine. </p><p>Also expect to face
          the inevitable negativity or conflict that can occur within a community. You should face
          it, communicate openly, overcome the negative discussions, and do not purposely avoid
          negative situations. </p></body></subsection><subsection
      id="d5e629"><title>Corporate policies for social sites</title><body><p>Read your corporate
            blogging<indexterm>blogging<indexterm>policy</indexterm></indexterm> policy or public
          discourse policy or <indexterm>social networking<indexterm
            >policies</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm>social media<indexterm
            >policies</indexterm></indexterm>social networking policy. If your company does not have
          such policies, thoroughly research the examples from IBM and <indexterm>policies, social
              computing<indexterm>Sun Microsystems</indexterm></indexterm>Sun<indexterm>Sun
              Microsystems<indexterm>social computing policy</indexterm></indexterm>, and consider
          whether they fit your corporate culture and how you might adjust them as needed. </p><p
            ><indexterm>IBM<indexterm>social computing policy</indexterm></indexterm>IBM has a
            <indexterm>policies, social computing<indexterm
            >following</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm>policies, social computing<indexterm
              >IBM</indexterm></indexterm>policy<fn><p>
              http://www.ibm.com/blogs/zz/en/guidelines.html</p></fn> that is considered to be the
          “gold standard” for these types of guidelines for employees. Sun is a known leader in this
          area and their policy<fn><p> http://www.sun.com/aboutsun/media/blogs/policy.html</p></fn>
          has been adapted and referenced for years. For non-profit organizations, Appendix B
          contains the policy for online discussion from Easter Seals which encompasses many
          different types of online publishing areas.<fn><p>
              http://beth.typepad.com/beths_blog/2008/04/nonprofit-blogg.html</p></fn>
        </p><p>These policies have many commonalities for trust-worthy, valuable online
          representation. The policies give you advice like: be genuine, always identify yourself
          and the company you represent, be professional, talk about what you know, cite sources and
          acknowledge others’ contributions, obey copyright laws, offer value, don’t pick fights,
          and respect your audience. All of these policies ask that the person abide by the policy
          and use good judgement in all their online interactions. </p><p>Additionally, study your
          corporate culture to determine how much openness and transparency already exist. Look for
          areas where transparency and openness are rewarded and not feared. Find ways to mitigate
          the risks that you may take by attempting transparency in your communications.</p><p>Do
          not contribute if your contribution could be interpreted as interrupting “real” work (such
          as posting long responses during work hours). </p></body></subsection><subsection
      id="d5e690"><title>Analyzing benefits from social media methods</title><body><p>User
          expectations and corporate culture play an important role in <indexterm
              >evaluation<indexterm>of feasibility of using social
          media</indexterm></indexterm>evaluating whether your products and documentation set could
            <indexterm>social media<indexterm>benefits of using</indexterm></indexterm>benefit from
          social networking and conversation either with staff members or with customers. Products
          that contain elements of <indexterm>open source<indexterm>wikis
            for</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm>open source<indexterm>documentation
              expectations</indexterm></indexterm>open source, which gives the user access to the
          source code, will have expectations of open documentation that come with source files that
          customers can edit or remix themselves. If products are not open source, but users are
          accustomed to early revisions of the documentation, they may have their expectations for
          content already set. A writer in an enabler role would do well to keep up with user
          expectations and analyze the conversations occurring about the social media tools in
          use.</p></body></subsection><subsection
      id="d5e713"><title>Defining business objectives </title><body><p>The book <i>Groundswell</i>
          discusses a four-step approach to getting corporations into <indexterm
              >conversations<indexterm>business objectives of</indexterm></indexterm>conversations:
          People, Objectives, Strategy, and Technology. I believe this approach can apply for
          technical publications and <indexterm>social media<indexterm>alignment with business
              objectives</indexterm></indexterm>social media as well. The business objectives that
          your department typically aligns with are your objectives for any social web exploration
          as well. I especially appreciate that the technology research and decision is the last one
          in their approach.</p><p>Before you attempt direct conversation with customers or try to
          enable more customer-to-customer interaction, ask yourself what you hope to achieve.
          Articulate the business goals so that you can communicate them to your manager and others.
          Also, examine how realistic your goals are given the time and resources that you have
          available. Keep in mind that you may have to use your own time and resources initially to
          prove the value of your proposal before you can gain the confidence of those who measure
          business value and make decisions. Many of the Groundswell case studies involved a couple
          of guys and an under-the-radar server installation.</p><p>To discover where you might gain
          business perspectives in different areas, such as Operations or Finance, look at the
          metrics in . </p><p>Leave flex room in your social media business strategies for
          unintended consequences, where a group of users may not want “how to” information coming
          from a social deliverable, perhaps they want reference information that they can add to
          instead. Or perhaps your users are not interested in status updates that answer “What are
          you doing,” but instead want to know “Where are you?”</p></body></subsection><subsection
      id="d5e737"><title>Agile product development and the agile writer</title><prolog><metadata
            ><keywords>
            <indexterm>Agile development</indexterm>
          </keywords></metadata></prolog><body><p>What development method does your team use? Agile
          development refers to a group of software development methods that incorporate user
          involvement into development. On an Agile team you use time-boxed iterations to deliver
          small features of potentially shippable software at the end of each iteration. Central to
          many Agile shops are Scrum project management and self-organizing teams with
          cross-functional team members, including technical writers embedded on development teams.
          The way software is developed usually influence<indexterm>influence,
          measuring</indexterm>s the way that the technical publications team works, and Agile
          methods may lead to bigger changes than most. If you work in an Agile development
          environment, however, your team has probably already had to adjust the publication release
          cycles, information development methods, and the amount of documentation that is promised
          with each release, depending on the staffing challenges that you face because of Agile
          adaptations. </p><p>Sarah <indexterm>Maddox, Sarah</indexterm>Maddox has two wonderful
          blog posts in which she discusses her typical day as a technical writer working on an
          Agile development<indexterm>development</indexterm> team.<fn><p>
              http://ffeathers.wordpress.com/2008/01/20/the-agile-technical-writer/,
              http://ffeathers.wordpress.com/2008/01/26/the-agile-technical-writer-ii/</p></fn> Much
          of her work involves IM<indexterm>IM (Instant Messaging)</indexterm> conversations and
          editing in a wiki<indexterm>wikis<indexterm>in Agile development
            process</indexterm></indexterm> environment, using the wiki product that she documents
          as the documentation deliverable. </p><p>Mike <indexterm>Wethington,
          Mike</indexterm>Wethington, a technical publications manager and scrum master at Troux
          Technologies, says that the days are gone of introverted technical writers expecting to be
          handed specifications and isolate themselves while they write the documentation. Agile
          methods require internal team communication that resembles a conversation, with daily team
          standup meetings and collaboration with team members on writing tasks. The tools of the
          social web are critical to the speed, efficiency, and focus that a disciplined Agile team
          must have in order to succeed.</p></body></subsection></subsection><subsection
    id="d5e772"><title>Identifying key communicating team members</title><body><p>For those who are
        interested in being a representative voice for your department, for the technical
        documentation, or for the product itself, determine the methods that team members can use to
        begin <indexterm>conversations<indexterm>joining</indexterm></indexterm>conversations. Each
        team member should have a consistent, professional, and approachable online persona. Search
        for your first and last name on Google and other search engines and try to envision what you
        represent to customers, both internal and external to your company.</p><p>Examine existing
        community starting points for your customer base. Begin the conversations in a
        non-intimidating manner, such as commenting on blog posts. Always represent yourself
        honestly, and determine your standard disclaimer and when you will apply a disclaimer. For
        example, you need to identify yourself as a corporate representative when the blog post
        addresses a topic specific to your company.</p><p>For some team members, nothing could be
        more terrifying than losing anonymity while writing technical documentation. Because
        identifying oneself online can have negative consequences, do not require this type of
        involvement as a term of employment for existing employees. Writers may want to maintain two
        personas online, a personal one and a professional one. Behind-the-scenes and connector
        roles do not require the loss of anonymity or privacy. And rather than being directly
        involved in the conversations, writers can facilitate conversations and community by
        incorporating them into the documentation system. </p></body><subsection
      id="d5e786"><title>Piloting and testing internal solution first</title><body><p>It is very
          easy to stumble while practicing the art of conversation and community, so you might want
          to try internal conversations first. For example, start an internal wiki<indexterm
              >wikis<indexterm>collaboration in</indexterm></indexterm> so that you and your team
          can become accustomed to the new way of working and communicating. </p><p>Stewart Mader,
          author of <i>Wikipatterns </i>touts the value and necessity of using a pilot project to
          start wikis, and I believe this approach would work best for implementing any type of
          social media. This technology is still relatively experimental, and you should allow your
          team to experiment to find the strengths and weaknesses of a new delivery mechanism or
          community system.</p></body></subsection></subsection><subsection
    id="d5e800"><title>Managing these conversational, connective, community methods</title><body><p
        >As with the introduction of any new technology, you should ask yourself whether it is
        necessary? What criteria make this conversation-based implementation important at this point
        in the product’s lifecycle? How can you make it a priority? You need to be able to write a
        business case for the cost savings or time savings that could occur based on the
        conversation-based implementation that you are considering. Find out what business areas
        need the most work right now. Understand your department’s place in the organization—are you
        more helpful to marketing and pre-sales efforts or to technical support? Does your audience
        consist mostly of internal consultants, and if so, what are their biggest hurdles? How could
        conversation-based or community-based content help them meet their goals?</p><p>Also
        consider that your manager has access to more information than you do and may understand the
        current customer climate and community better than you do. Without the necessary tools and
        information, you cannot easily build relationships, and relationship building should
        probably start with your team’s and manager’s buy-in. </p></body><subsection
      id="d5e806"><title>What if your manager doesn’t see any value in social media for tech
        pubs?</title><body><p>If your <indexterm>management buy-in</indexterm>manager does not see
          any value in implementing<indexterm>social media<indexterm>proving
              effectiveness</indexterm></indexterm> social media, continue to try to show the value
          of it with examples from other companies or other areas of your own company until you can
          make a business case that speaks to your manager. If you strongly believe that a
          conversational approach is the right direction for your documentation, try some
            grassroots<indexterm>grassroots efforts</indexterm> efforts yourself until you can prove
          its worth and value, either with a few great anecdotes or hard numbers that prove the
          return on the time invested. Also realize that <i>ROI </i>can stand for <indexterm>risk of
            inaction (ROI)</indexterm>Risk Of Inaction. If <i>not</i> starting a conversation is
          more risky than starting one, that perception may sway your manager to try out a pilot
          project and experiment with social bookmarking<indexterm>social bookmarking</indexterm>,
            <indexterm>forums<indexterm>moderating</indexterm></indexterm>forum moderation,
          screencasting, or other areas that make sense in your business environment.</p><p>Part of
          implementing your chosen solution for integrating conversation or community into your user
          assistance is also recording lessons learned (what worked well, what did not succeed) and
          analyzing what you might adjust. Be sure to present metrics for measuring the success of
          your implementation. </p></body></subsection><subsection
      id="d5e841"><title>Time to allocate for these efforts</title><body><p>All questions about
          using <indexterm>social media<indexterm>time commitment</indexterm></indexterm>social
          media technologies distill to the single question, “How much time does all this take?”
          Beth Kanter has some ideas. She says that each rung of the ladder involves more and more
          time. Expect to allocate 5 hours a week to listen, 10 hours a week to participate, and 20
          hours a week to provide a platform for sharing content. For community <indexterm
              >communities<indexterm>growing</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm>communities<indexterm
              >building</indexterm></indexterm>building, expect the tasks to consume at least 25
          hours of a team’s work week. You likely don’t need to add the listening hours to the
          participating hours once you are building a community, though if each of those tasks
          remains important and gives good return on the time spent, then the time adds up to sixty
          hours a week. These time estimates may add up so that you realize you need more than one
          person assigned to this type of effort. In short, these tasks can easily become a full
          time job. The size and growth rate of the community will also dictate the number of hours
          needed to address their needs. Compare the time needed to welcome two or three people to
          an online community per day to welcoming over one hundred new members each day.
        </p></body></subsection><subsection
      id="d5e860"><title>Measuring conversation effectiveness</title><body><p><indexterm
              >metrics<indexterm>social media implementation</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm
              >metrics<indexterm>blogging influence</indexterm></indexterm>Metrics and <indexterm
            >social media<indexterm>proving effectiveness</indexterm></indexterm>social media mix
          like oil and water with interesting lava-lamp-like configurations as a result. In a
          corporate environment, someone has to pay the blogger’s bills or the podcaster’s
          bandwidth, and more importantly, decide that the <indexterm>conversations<indexterm>cost
              of</indexterm></indexterm>cost of the hours spent working on social media efforts is
          worth giving up other deliverables. So effectiveness, return on investment<indexterm
            >return on investment (ROI)<indexterm>measuring</indexterm></indexterm>, and metrics all
          come up continually.</p><p>When you are trying to <indexterm>blogs<indexterm>measuring
              effectiveness of</indexterm></indexterm>measure effectiveness, be sure that you are
          using the right <indexterm>metrics<indexterm>Reach and
          Influence</indexterm></indexterm>metric. For example, instead of measuring the <indexterm
            >return on investment (ROI)<indexterm>blogging</indexterm></indexterm>Return on
          Investment of <indexterm>evaluation<indexterm>of blog
            effectiveness</indexterm></indexterm>blogging<indexterm>blogging<indexterm>Reach and
              Influence</indexterm></indexterm>, try to gauge the <indexterm>reach and influence (R
            and I)</indexterm>Reach and Influence (R and I) of blogging. Influence rather than
          Investment offers measurable analytics to use when investigating a blog’s contribution to
          the bottom line. If you are seeking an independent blogger to sponsor or give ads to, you
          may use these measures. Also, when you analyze your corporate blog site and measure
          effectiveness of corporate bloggers, use these same principles. An article on the
          Marketing Sherpa site<fn><p>
            http://www.marketingsherpa.com/article.html?ident=30044</p></fn> provides the following
          factors to use when evaluating and measuring the <indexterm>metrics<indexterm>conversation
              effectiveness</indexterm></indexterm>effectiveness of a blogger’s <indexterm
              >blogs<indexterm>influence of</indexterm></indexterm>influence:</p><ul><li><indexterm
                >metrics<indexterm>traffic, blog</indexterm></indexterm>Traffic: Visitors and page
            hits, but don’t trust it alone.</li><li><indexterm>metrics<indexterm>RSS feed
                subscriptions</indexterm></indexterm>RSS<indexterm>RSS (Really Simple
                Syndication)<indexterm>measuring reader loyalty</indexterm></indexterm> feed
            subscriptions: Subscribers measure return visits and may indicate loyalty to the
            blog.</li><li>Inbound links: <indexterm>metrics<indexterm>inbound
              links</indexterm></indexterm>How often do other bloggers or other websites link to
            this blog?</li><li><indexterm>search<indexterm>measure of blog
              effectiveness</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm>search<indexterm>rankings</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm>metrics<indexterm>search
                position</indexterm></indexterm>Search position, part one: Keywords for company
            brand and keywords.</li><li>Search position, part two: Keywords for the blogger’s
              <indexterm>brands<indexterm>in search, as a measure of blog
              influence</indexterm></indexterm>brand (fame level).</li><li>Voice: <indexterm
                >metrics<indexterm>voice</indexterm></indexterm>Does the person blogging<indexterm
                >blogging<indexterm>Reach and Influence</indexterm></indexterm> represent the
            promise of an online experience that you can “hear” and appreciate?</li></ul><p>To these
          factors, I would add the number and frequency of <indexterm>comments<indexterm>on blog
              posts</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm>comments<indexterm>on blog
            posts</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm>blogs<indexterm>commenting
            on</indexterm></indexterm>comments on posts. Plus, the variety of the commenters’ voices
          can show the type of audience the blogger has gained. When you measure these factors,
          rephrase the Return on Investment (ROI) question as an investment in Influence. In your
          environment, how can you prove that Influence is worth investing in?</p><p>After you have
          determined that time and resources should be invested in order to increase influence, how
          do you find the time for this “extra” work? Is it really extra? You can shape your role by
          studying the desired outcome and the values you place on influence. You may find a role as
          enabler or <indexterm>content<indexterm>curators of</indexterm></indexterm>curator yields
          better results than a role of content contributor.</p><p>If your measurements are proving
          the value, showing time or <indexterm>return on investment (ROI)<indexterm
              >proving</indexterm></indexterm>costs savings should be straightforward. Look for real
          sales or connections made as a result of a blog entry or a <indexterm>wikis<indexterm
              >measuring effectiveness</indexterm></indexterm>wiki article or a customer support
          forum post. For example, compare money spent on a marketing and public relations campaign
          with the cost of a few hours of a technical writer’s time writing a blog entry.</p><p>And
          how about the opposite question: if everyone else writes the content, which should save
          writers <indexterm>social media<indexterm>time commitment</indexterm></indexterm>time,
          what do they do with the time saved to continue to add value? Edit like a magazine
          publisher? Become a curator of content? Or a <indexterm>manager,
            community</indexterm><indexterm>community manager</indexterm><indexterm
              >communities<indexterm>managing</indexterm></indexterm>community manager? <indexterm
            >Bailie, Rahel</indexterm>Rahel Bailie, content strategist and founder of Intentional
          Design, believes this is the new role for technical writers, saying “To be able to
          leverage User Generated Content, an organization needs to have a community from which to
          draw information and opinions, and those communities need <indexterm>moderation<indexterm
              >community</indexterm></indexterm>moderators. Community management, a relatively new
          career track, seems to be a logical next step for content developers.”<fn><p>
              http://www.enewsbuilder.net/techcommanager/e_article001389770.cfm?x=b11,0,w</p></fn>
        </p></body></subsection><subsection
      id="d5e1053"><title>Measuring whether a documentation conversation works </title><body><p>This
          question, “But does documentation as conversation work?” stems from the <indexterm
              >metrics<indexterm>social media implementation</indexterm></indexterm>measurability
          equation. Those who are interested in website metrics and analytics often want some fancy
          tool to take care of the measurements for them. But, in reality, it is extremely difficult
          to know what measuring stick you can use on a blog entry, for example, or the value of a
          well-stocked wiki. Measuring community involvement is often discussed in fuzzy vague terms
          and not hard numbers. So, if you apply conversation or community methods to <indexterm
            >technical documentation<indexterm>measuring effectiveness
          of</indexterm></indexterm>documentation, how do you prove it is working? And how do you
          prove the level to which it’s working and whether it outpaces conventional user assistance
          methods? </p><p>Website analytical tools like <indexterm>metrics<indexterm>Google
              Analytics</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm>Google<indexterm>Analytics</indexterm></indexterm>Google
          Analytics help you count numbers of visitors, and the tools are getting more sophisticated
          about measuring how long each visitor stays. Also, they are better able to track the path
          that users take through a help system, which can help you measure their effectiveness.
          Plus, Google’s <indexterm>help, online<indexterm>tracking
            keywords</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm>help, online<indexterm
            >finding</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm>Google<indexterm>keyword
            tracking</indexterm></indexterm>keyword tracking is extremely helpful for indicating
          which <indexterm>search<indexterm>keywords</indexterm></indexterm>keywords are most
          searched for and may help you analyze which <indexterm>metrics<indexterm
              >keywords</indexterm></indexterm>keywords are most efficient for letting a user figure
          out the answer and move on. Time spent on a page may or may not be a good measurement for
          effectiveness of a help system, but findability<indexterm>findability</indexterm> of your
          help system is measurable. You can also ask your audience if their participation in
          conversation or community has prevented them from leaving a company or abandoning a
          product from a particular company. Often we don’t measure in the sense of preventing a
          negative result.</p><p><indexterm>community equity</indexterm>Community equity is an
          emerging research area that measures the value that an individual brings as a member of an
          online community. Peter Reiser at Sun Microsystems has developed a method and algorithm
          for calculating a member’s community equity based on information offerings and personal
          interactions with others. His team also created widgets that help people see other members
          equity ratings and central areas of expertise. By reading, rating, contributing, tagging,
          and editing, a person increases their <indexterm>information equity</indexterm>information
          equity. Personal equity is calculated based on connections, reputation, and collaborative
          efforts. The values “age” and decrease to zero over time so there is a “freshness” to the
          values. Peter Reiser’s project is now available as an <indexterm>open source<indexterm
              >community equity project</indexterm></indexterm>open source project.<fn><p>
              http://kenai.com/projects/community-equity</p></fn> These individual visual measures
          of a community member’s contributions may help you measure the overall value of a
          community.</p><p>In the SXSW Interactive panel presentation titled “Social Media Metrics:
          Where are they?”<fn><p>
              http://2008.sxsw.com/interactive/programming/panels_schedule/?action=show&amp;id=IAP060474</p></fn>
          the producer for talk.bmc.com community content<indexterm>community-generated
              content<indexterm>developing</indexterm></indexterm>, Ynema <indexterm>Mangum,
            Ynema</indexterm>Mangum, noted a <indexterm>metrics<indexterm>case
            study</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm>help, online<indexterm
            >measuring</indexterm></indexterm>measurement case study of a single blog entry written
          by <indexterm>Hurley, William (whurley)</indexterm>William Hurley (known as Whurley)
          titled “20 Reasons Why Microsoft Loves Open Source.” Whurley’s blog entry it was intended
          to draw attention and managed to get on the front page of active online communities such
          as Slashdot and Digg. It could cost $800,000 dollars to gain similar media coverage. That
          is one method to measure conversations, though <indexterm>whurley (William
            Hurley)</indexterm>Whurley’s use of conflict journalism and sensationalist shots at
          competitors does not fit nicely into our usual methods of delivering quality information
          in a timely manner. </p><p>So, how could you measure whether a technical publication-based
          conversation is working? My first suggestion is to go to the usual metrics that technical
          publication uses to provide value—for example, lowered support costs. Or, perhaps it is
          not Return on Investment you need to measure but <indexterm>risk of inaction
            (ROI)</indexterm><indexterm>metrics<indexterm>risk of
          inaction</indexterm></indexterm>Risk of Inaction. If your competitors all use wikis or
            <indexterm>help, online<indexterm>conversation-based tools
            in</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm>help, online<indexterm>comments
            in</indexterm></indexterm>help systems with <indexterm>comments<indexterm>on blog
              posts</indexterm></indexterm>comments and other conversation-based, community-based
          user assistance tools, your team should evaluate their use for your deliverables as well.
          Just as competing products need to keep up with each other’s features, I think that we
          need to keep an eye on competitor’s conversations and determine if there’s a perceived
          value your company should match.</p></body></subsection><subsection
      id="d5e1174"><title>Determining fit in the organization and community</title><prolog><metadata
            ><keywords>
            <indexterm>communities<indexterm>content contributed by</indexterm></indexterm>
            <indexterm>content contributed by</indexterm>
          </keywords></metadata></prolog><body><p>You should try to match your contribution with
          your role in your company. For example, if you generally add value by decreasing customer
          support calls, then look to the support communities for ideas. If you assist the services
          or field personnel in getting their jobs done, find a way to tap into that community base.
          If your documentation is a sales-winning essential part of the product, get yourself close
          to the sales and marketing department’s conversations with customers. </p><p><indexterm
              >conversations<indexterm>joining</indexterm></indexterm>Matching up your strengths and
          experience to the conversations helps you avoid stepping on toes or stumbling into
          conversations where you do not have the tools, background, or correct messaging to deal
          with the situation correctly. Other departments may be able to help if a customer becomes
          angry or you witness an outburst between two community members. Clay <indexterm>Shirky,
            Clay</indexterm>Shirky has an excellent essay titled “Group as User: Flaming and the
          Design of Social Software” that describes cooling-off techniques, rating, karma, and ways
          to harness the “performance” effect for good purposes instead of only negative
          distractions. But brand protection, public relations, and crisis communications are likely
          better left to a professional trained in those areas, and you should find someone at your
          company who can help in those areas. You should also be ready to escalate the information
          to the right group when you observe a conversation that another organization within your
          company should handle.</p></body></subsection><subsection
      id="d5e1192"><title>Grassroots efforts</title><body><p>Grassroots efforts are defined by an
          unofficial group starting a project without authority or hierarchy but with organic growth
          and natural networking tendencies. When a few friends or coworkers who share a common
          vision or goal start on an effort that grows beyond their expectations, that would be a
            grassroots<indexterm>grassroots efforts</indexterm> effort. </p><p>Another term that is
          used rather than grassroots<indexterm>grassroots efforts</indexterm> is <indexterm
            >groundswell</indexterm>groundswell, from the book by the same name. In this context, a
          groundswell is “a social trend in which people use technologies to get the things they
          need from each other rather than from traditional institutions like corporations.” It is
          also described more simply as a change in public opinion that is broad and far-reaching.
          Writers can build a groundswell because they know the product well, can help people make
          connections with each other with social technologies, and can write well enough to
          convince others of the basic value of the product. Writers may also already know community
          members who might be willing to help with a few tasks, or at least be willing to review
          write-ups. With a publishing platform like a blog or a wiki, writers enable conversations
          to take place that may not have had a place to occur.</p><p>Writers at a mobile phone
          designer and manufacturer who wanted to experiment with a wiki decided to go through the
          correct channels for a legal disclaimer by simply requesting revisions to the legal
          verbiage in their existing online help disclaimer. They were pleasantly surprised when
          their legal department was helpful and encouraged their experiment. Then the writers
          created a <indexterm>MediaWiki<indexterm>at mobile phone
            manufacturer</indexterm></indexterm>MediaWiki installation, pre-seeded it with content
          from their user guide, and waited to see if users would find it and edit it. </p><p
          >Interestingly, a few years after this experimental wiki, it turns out, another wiki built
          by end-users of the cell phone they intended to document and build a community around,
          became “the” source for information and user-to-user communication about the phone and
          tips and tricks. In that case, while the company wiki was helpful, the external community
          wiki was more visited and edited. I think their experiment showed their relative naivete
          about the power of community building rather than web page building.</p><p>Another term
          related to grassroots is astroturf, which is a group that wants to be known as grassroots
          but is conceived, created, and sometimes funded by a corporation or lobby. Full disclosure
          of the backing behind your efforts is the best course of action to avoid distrust or
          suspicion later when someone reveals the origin of the group and the underlying
          motivations. </p></body></subsection><subsection
      id="d5e1218"><title>Recruiting others by proving the value</title><body><p>Once you have a few
          success stories to tell, share them with anyone who shows an interest. This <indexterm
            >storytelling</indexterm>storytelling is at the heart of a grassroots movement. These
          blog entries and interviews with wiki maintainers are examples of storytelling that you
          can do within your organization.</p><p>At the “Social Media Metrics, Where are they?”
          panel discussion at SXSW Interactive in March 2008, Ynema Mangum presented a chart showing
          the CXO “X-factor” for influential <indexterm>metrics<indexterm>influential for
              business</indexterm></indexterm>metrics for each area of a large business, where the X
          might be replaced by Operations (COO), Technology (CTO), Finance (CFO), and so forth. The
          X-factor is their business area of expertise and indicates their role in the
          company.</p><p>Once you have determined what you’d like to achieve, consider the direction
          of the conversation and how many participants it will have. Sarah <indexterm>O’Keefe,
            Sarah</indexterm>O’Keefe at Scriptorium Publishing has an excellent white paper titled
          “Friend or Foe? Web 2.0 in Technical Communication”<fn><p>
              http://www.scriptorium.com/whitepapers/web2/</p></fn> that describes the one-to-one,
          one-to-many, many-to-many, and many-to-one directional communication occurring
          today.</p><p>If you want to encourage generated content, start slowly. You might seek
          business objectives at different levels, depending on your goals and the business areas
          you aim to influence.</p></body></subsection></subsection></chapter>
