<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<chapter
  id="d5e2"><title>Preface</title><prolog/><body><p><image
        href="images/chapter00.png"
        width="5in"/></p><p>This book grew out of my experimentation with wikis for online help and
      user assistance and my complete adoration of Google search, which I felt would change forever
      the way that users find information that helps them complete a task, even one as simple as
      slicing a tomato or folding fitted sheets.<fn><p>
          http://www.ehow.com/how_1682_slice-tomato.html,
          http://www.ehow.com/how_6067_fold-fitted-sheet.html</p></fn> Everyday tasks are documented
      on the web by everyday people. The start of this people-centric revolution has been described
      as the second generation of the Web. Web 1.0 was about data and display, but Web 2.0 merges
      data and display with user-centric design and ideas. </p><p>While people debate the cult of
      the amateur<fn><p> Andrew Keen, 2007, The Cult of the Amateur: How Today’s Internet is Killing
          Our Culture, Broadway Business, ISBN: 0385520808.</p></fn> and spread uncertainty and
      doubt, professional writers now have the tools to <indexterm>collaboration<indexterm>with
          audiences</indexterm></indexterm>collaborate with their audience easily for the first time
      in history. How we seize this opportunity and how our audience responds and becomes a part of
      this revolution will determine our success in this new environment.</p><p>Nearly all of the
      discussion in this book surrounds new ideas for documentation, whether you are writing
      documentation as film makers, corporate marketers, technical writers, programmers, or
      managers. Sometimes these “new” ideas uncover age-old truths about communities and people’s
      behavior and habits. Sometimes you have to experiment on your own time with your own dollars
      and tools to prove that a technique is worth an investment. That try-and-see attitude is what
      the cutting edge is all about. </p><p>Beth Kanter<indexterm>Kanter, Beth</indexterm>, a
      trainer who teaches non-profit organizations how to bring social networking to their business,
      compares experiencing social media for the first time to a first-time sexual experience—you
      can’t describe how it feels until you experience it. In the same way, you can’t describe or
      measure the value of a technique or methodology until you try it and analyze your
      results.</p><p>Still, many people describe social media dabbling and experimentation as a
      waste of time. However, Clay <indexterm>Shirky, Clay</indexterm>Shirky states his argument
      against “how can you find the time” as a rallying cry against the mindless hours spent
      watching TV—two hundred billion hours per year in the U.S. alone.<fn><p>
          http://www.shirky.com/herecomeseverybody/2008/04/looking-for-the-mouse.html</p></fn> By
      finding and making the time for this experimental discovery, you may save time and effort
      later while increasing the quality and adding perceived value. Plus, you may find interacting
      with others more fulfilling than the one-way communication offered by your television or other
      media outlets. </p></body><subsection
    id="d5e40"><title>What’s in this book</title><body><p>Use this book to help you experiment with
        and explore social media techniques, and to analyze and interpret the results. It offers
        descriptions and definitions for the technologies and publishing methods that make up this
        new way of thinking about content. </p><p>After defining the areas that social media and
        social networking encompass, the book provides ideas for defining your role as a content
        author or provider. Next, you can find planning and implementation suggestions and advice as
        well as considerations for choosing your role and goals as a writer or provider of content.
        </p><p>This book also includes a chapter on measuring the effectiveness of these
        experimental areas as well as proving their value to various stakeholders. Finally, you can
        find specific ideas for integrating conversation, community, and collaboration into
        documentation. </p><p>In this book you can learn about enabling conversation and community
        in your documentation using <indexterm>social networking<indexterm>integrating with
            documentation</indexterm></indexterm>social media and social networking. The definition
        of documentation ranges from the standard email message on a mailing list, to a
        140-character microblog post, to an exhaustively examined and discussed forum post or wiki
        article, to a traditional online help file, to the trusty dog-eared manual or often-opened
        PDF file. </p><p>What does it mean to enable a conversation, and how do you assess Web 2.0
        tools and strategies such as wikis and blogs? In the landscape of technology products, the
        consumption of technical topics is often distilled to finding the right answer quickly, to
        solving the problem, and moving on. End-users do not necessarily care about the source of
        the information or whether it was written by a professional; they judge the information
        solely on its ability to solve their immediate problem. </p><p>So if you are a professional
        writer, how do you fit into a landscape in which content must be constantly available and
          <indexterm>content<indexterm>up-to-date</indexterm></indexterm>up-to-date, where blog
        entries get more visitors than your help pages? How do you ensure that your content has the
        same or better value than content from a myriad of online sources? If you are a developer
        who wants to ensure that users have a good experience and get the answers they need, how do
        you respond to their questions naturally or presciently? If you are a content creator, such
        as a filmmaker or game designer, how do you ensure that you are entering the conversation
        and enabling community in your communications?</p><p>To answer these questions, and to help
        writers determine which <indexterm>social networking<indexterm
        >tools</indexterm></indexterm>social networking tools might help them communicate technical
        information to their end-users, this book examines the categories of social media and
        networking tools and provides pointers for evaluating each newcomer or old
      standby.</p></body><subsection
      id="d5e72"><title>Finding out more about related software, services, and sites </title><body
          ><p>In the spirit of contributed, free, and open sharing, links to all of the websites
          mentioned in this book are collected on &#8232;delicious.com/annegentle/conversation and
            delicious.com<indexterm>delicious.com</indexterm>/annegentle/community. Participate in
          the building of this book’s future by adding new relevant URLs to delicious.com, using the
          tags <i>conversation</i> or <i>community</i>, and by adding me to your
      network.</p></body></subsection><subsection
      id="d5e85"><title>About Anne Gentle</title><body><p>I’m a senior technical writer who started
          blogging in 2005 for a corporate conversation at talk.bmc.com for BMC Software. I now work
          as a senior technical writer at Advanced Solutions International and write a professional
          blog about writing, wikis, and information design at <indexterm>blogs, examples<indexterm
              >Just Write Click</indexterm></indexterm>JustWriteClick.com. </p><p>I became
          interested in using wikis for documentation and decided that a hands-on apprenticeship
          would be the most efficient way to learn about wikis. I have been volunteering for the One
          Laptop per Child<indexterm>One Laptop per Child<indexterm>author's experience
              with</indexterm></indexterm> project, writing end-user documentation for children,
          parents, and teachers across the world<indexterm>XO laptop</indexterm>, using open
            source<indexterm>open source<indexterm>One Laptop per Child</indexterm></indexterm>
          software that could change the way education happens in under-developed and under-served
          nations. FLOSS Manuals, a toolset and community dedicated to writing free documentation
          for free software, shaped many of my experiences with community
      documentation.</p></body></subsection><subsection
      id="d5e109"><title>Acknowledgments</title><body><p>I work a 30-hour work week so that not only
          can I spend my time pursuing interesting projects, but I can also work a longer “mom
          shift” in the afternoons and evenings. Without nap time, early bedtime routines for my
          kids, truly-caring child care, and above all, a wonderful husband, I never could have
          written this book, nor would I have learned the lessons that enabled me to write it.
          </p><p>I offer special thanks and gratitude to my husband Paul for encouraging me. His
          involvement in the distributed.net community brought us to Austin, and showed me the power
          of volunteers sharing a common cause. </p><p>My good friend Kelly Holcomb skillfully
          edited the first drafts of this book. She read it, edited it, and asked wise questions in
          the margins, which compelled me to answer them. </p><p>I owe a huge debt for the education
          I have received from <indexterm>FLOSS Manuals<indexterm>author's experience
              with</indexterm></indexterm>FLOSS Manuals founder <indexterm>Hyde,
          Adam</indexterm>Adam Hyde and <indexterm>SugarLabs</indexterm>SugarLabs coordinator David
            <indexterm>Farning, David</indexterm>Farning. They both read extremely early drafts of
          this book and encouraged me throughout the process. Adam generously contributed most of
          the content about Book Sprints. Working with him has been inspirational. He has assembled
          a great crew at FLOSS Manuals, which connected me with Patrick Davison, who did the
          interior and cover designs for the book. And without FLOSS Manuals I might not have met
          Andy <indexterm>Oram, Andy</indexterm>Oram, who graciously read the book, offered
          guidance, and wrote an insightful foreword.</p><p><i>Thanks to “ThisParticularGreg,” “J.E.
            Theriot,” “krossbow,” and “Pathfinder Linden” for their photographs and for making their
            photographs available on flickr.com under a Creative Commons License. Thanks to “nolnet”
            for giving me permission to use photos of his Lego refrigerator.</i></p><p><i>Thanks to
            Dee Elling for permission to use my interview with her and for the lessons learned that
            she shared with me. </i></p><p><i>Scott Abel, Sarah O’Keefe, Alan Porter, and Will
            Sansbury read a hack of a draft and offered wonderful insights from their varied
            perspectives. I learned from each of them even while editing the book based on their
            feedback. Without their collective knowledge, wisdom, and experiences plus generously
            giving their time to read and offer comments, this book would not be as useful to all of
            us. </i></p></body></subsection></subsection></chapter>
