<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<chapter id="d5e2"><title><ph>Glossary</ph></title><prolog/><body><p><indexterm>Agile development</indexterm>Agile development </p><p>A software development methodology that develops software rapidly with multiple tight iterations, or development cycles (2–3 weeks). Each iteration includes design, development, test, and documentation of a subset of the product’s features. Each iteration should result in a potentially deliverable product.</p><p>Atom</p><p>An XML standards, similar to RSS, used for syndication. (See also Syndication.)</p><p>Barcamp</p><p>A user-focused conference where the content is provided by participants. The “bar” in the name refers not to the place it is held but to the hacker term “foobar,” as an opposing camp for Tim O’Reilly’s Foo Camp—an invitation-only event. Barcamp includes people with similar interests in open source and technology.</p><p>Blog</p><p>An online web site where entries are typically chronologically listed. The term comes from a contraction of the term “weblog.”</p><p>Blogosphere </p><p>A term that describes the interconnected world of blogs, bloggers, and their culture.</p><p>Book Sprint</p><p>An event for collaborative authoring that typically starts with an outline and results in a book by the end of a set period of time, usually about a week. Usually set in one location at one time, but remote collaborators can also participate.</p><p>Bookmarking </p><p>Saving a web address for later retrieval and reading, similar to placing a piece of paper between pages to mark that spot for reading a book. (See also social bookmarking.)</p><p>Bots, robots</p><p>Software that automatically <indexterm>search<indexterm>bots</indexterm></indexterm>searches the web for specific content on command. </p><p>Community</p><p>A <indexterm>communities<indexterm>definition of</indexterm></indexterm>group of people with similar interests or goals. An online community typically has a central location online to share these interests.</p><p><indexterm>manager, community</indexterm>Community manager</p><p>An emerging role still being defined that involves communication with the community, encouraging community members, advocating for the community, and promoting awareness.</p><p>Content curator</p><p>A curator is typically the custodian of a collection of art or historic objects; for content curation the person’s role is to manage, administer, and generally take care of content.</p><p><indexterm>Creative Commons license</indexterm>Creative Commons license</p><p>Gives permission for six types of use of a created body of work, allowing for the author to retain copyright but also authorize different uses of the materials.</p><p>Crowdsourcing</p><p>Offering a task to a large group, typically outside of a company so it is similar to outsourcing but instead gives the work to a large group of people.</p><p>Curating</p><p>Organizing and maintaining a collection.</p><p>DITA (Darwin Information Typing Architecture)</p><p>An XML-based extensible architecture for creating technical documentation. With it you write strongly-typed topics of concept, task, and reference. </p><p>DITA map</p><p>A DITA map structure organizes DITA topics so that the XML-based topics can be transformed with XSLT into information deliverables.</p><p>Enabler </p><p>A role for providing for conversation. An enabler of conversation understands the underlying concepts of a product or service well enough to help others make those connections intelligently as well. </p><p>Flame wars </p><p>A heated argument online that results in back-and-forth discussion including insults and angry remarks.</p><p>FLOSS Manuals</p><p><indexterm>FLOSS Manuals<indexterm>defined</indexterm></indexterm>Both a community and web-based collaboration tool created in 2007 by <indexterm>Hyde, Adam</indexterm>Adam Hyde for the purpose of providing free documentation for free software. FLOSS in the name is an acronym for Free Libre <indexterm>open source<indexterm>FLOSS Manuals</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm>open source<indexterm>open documentation contributions</indexterm></indexterm>Open Source Software.</p><p><indexterm>folksonomy</indexterm>Folksonomy </p><p>A classification system using tags created by members of an online community, or everyday folks. Plays off the word “taxonomy” which is the formal practice and science of classifying items.</p><p><indexterm>forums<indexterm>definition</indexterm></indexterm>Forum</p><p>A message board system used online for public or member-only discussion and debate on topics.</p><p>FrameMaker</p><p>A word processing and publishing software product from Adobe, often used in technical documentation for large documents.</p><p>Gift economy</p><p>A bartering system of efforts traded in exchange for altruistic gains.</p><p>Going viral </p><p>Spreading a video, image or text by using Internet web sites or email messages and word of mouth so that it becomes extremely popular.</p><p><indexterm>groundswell</indexterm>Groundswell </p><p>A social trend in which people use technologies to get the things they need from each other rather than from traditional institutions like corporations.</p><p>Haptic</p><p>Using feedback of a sensory nature for user interfaces such as touch or tactile sensations or orientation of a device in space. Examples are touchscreen keyboards and the Nintendo <indexterm>Wii</indexterm>Wii controller causing a “bump” sensation when moving the cursor over a button.</p><p><indexterm>Twitter<indexterm>hashtags</indexterm></indexterm>Hashtag</p><p>Words or phrases prefixed with a hash symbol (#) used specifically on Twitter to identify content for later searches, grouping, and retrieval. An example is the #stc09 hashtag used to indicate that a Twitter update was about the STC Summit in 2009.</p><p>Instant Messaging (IM)</p><p>A form of online chat that enables real-time messages sent back and forth between two or more people. Typically an IM client is used to enable the chat. Some clients support text messages only while others enable video and audio streaming in addition to text.</p><p><indexterm>Internet Relay Chat (IRC)</indexterm>Internet Relay Chat (IRC)</p><p>A chat network protocol on the Internet that enables synchronous communication by typing text in hosted channels.</p><p>Instigator </p><p>A role for starting conversations, an instigator provides a starting point for discussion, perhaps by offering a controversial opinion or a highly debated strategic choice.</p><p>Mashup</p><p>An online application or tool that combines data or content from multiple sources to give a new perspective or service.</p><p><indexterm>MediaWiki<indexterm>definition</indexterm></indexterm>MediaWiki</p><p>A web-based wiki software application. Its most well-known use is for the online encyclopedia Wikipedia.</p><p>Microblog, <indexterm>microblogging</indexterm><indexterm>blogging<indexterm>microblogging</indexterm></indexterm>microblogging</p><p>Brief text-based entries that are smaller than normal blog posts. As an example, it describes Twitter posts with their 140-character per post limitation.</p><p><indexterm>One Laptop per Child<indexterm>described</indexterm></indexterm>Open source</p><p>A method for distributing software that guarantees anyone who uses that software the right to use, modify, and re-distribute the software and its source code freely. Usually, open source software must be re-distributed under the same terms it was originally distributed. Typically open source projects are built and maintained by volunteers. Well-known examples of open source projects include the Apache web server and the Firefox web browser.</p><p>One Laptop per Child (OLPC)</p><p>A US-based non-profit organization whose mission is to provide affordable, rugged education devices to children in developing countries.</p><p>PDF (Portable Document Format)</p><p>A file format developed by Adobe that preserves all printed page formatting for electronic viewing and distribution.</p><p><indexterm>podcasts<indexterm>defined</indexterm></indexterm>Podcast</p><p>An audio recording that is broadcast on the Internet. Often uses RSS for subscribing to updates.</p><p><indexterm>round tripping, wiki</indexterm>Round tripping</p><p>The act of taking content from one application, such as DITA XML into another, such as a wiki, and then back again to the original content files.</p><p>RSS</p><p>RSS stands for Really Simple Syndication. See also Syndication.</p><p><indexterm>screencasts</indexterm>Screencasting </p><p>A recording of your screen while you are doing a computer task on-screen that may include narrative instructions or explanation of the software being used.</p><p><indexterm>screen scraping</indexterm>Screen scraping </p><p>Extracting data, typically HTML, from a web page programmatically.</p><p>Search Engine Optimization (SEO) </p><p>The process of improving ranking of content by search engines and the number of click-throughs to a website. Typically involves optimizing use of keywords and eliminating barriers to automated indexing activities performed by search engines. </p><p><indexterm>social bookmarking</indexterm>Social bookmarking</p><p>The practice of sharing web addresses for storage and retrieval with others. First coined by the site delicious.com, which incorporates tagging and a folksonomy for applying metadata to bookmarks.</p><p><indexterm>social networking<indexterm>defined</indexterm></indexterm>Social networking </p><p>The practice of connecting and communicating with people who share interests or common goals. Social networking sites enable this communication and sharing online.</p><p><indexterm>social shopping</indexterm>Social shopping</p><p>A method of offering social interactions or communications revolving around e-commerce websites using techniques such as product reviews or forums embedded within the shopping experience.</p><p>Social tagging </p><p>Assigning keywords for a blog entry, link, photo, or video, and then sharing them with the community online or a select network of other users of the website. (See also tagging.)</p><p>Social web</p><p>Describes people applying technology with the World Wide Web in a community or socially interactive manner using reputation, identity, presence, relationships, grouping, communication, and sharing to accomplish tasks or projects.</p><p>Social weather</p><p>A multi-dimensional visualization of the relative attitude of a community or group.</p><p>Syndication </p><p>Supplying content such as text, images, video, or audio, for consumption, reuse, and integration with other material via a subscription feed. RSS and Atom are XML standards that support syndication.</p><p>Tag cloud</p><p>A visual method of displaying tags (keywords) that are used most often. Tag clouds use a larger font size or bold to indicate which tags are associated with the largest number of references or most recently accessed reference.</p><p>Tagging</p><p>The act of assigning a keyword to a particular item such as a blog entry, link, photo, or video.</p><p>Trackback</p><p>Offers a method for  tracking links to content by sending a notification to another site, typically a blog, when one entry links to another entry. Often, snippets of text from the blog content are included with the trackback link and notification.</p><p><indexterm>Twitter<indexterm>tweets</indexterm></indexterm>Tweet</p><p>A single post on Twitter, or when used as a verb, the act of posting an update to Twitter. (See also Twitter.)</p><p><indexterm>Twitter<indexterm>tweetups</indexterm></indexterm>Tweetups </p><p>A real-world meeting enabled by using Twitter for inviting, communicating, and responding about the event. Substitutes Tweet for Meet in the term “meet up.”</p><p><indexterm>Twitter<indexterm>described</indexterm></indexterm>Twitter</p><p>A web application that enables you to post 140-character microentries from the web or from a mobile phone answering the question, “What are you doing?”</p><p><indexterm>unconferences</indexterm>Unconference </p><p>A user-driven conference facilitated by organizers, but with the content of the conference shaped by the attendees around a theme or purpose.</p><p>Vlog, video log</p><p>A word play of the term “blog,” it describes video publications that are syndicated and subscribed to similar to a blog.</p><p>Web 2.0</p><p>The second version of the World Wide Web where interaction and collaboration takes precedence over static data.</p><p><indexterm>whuffie</indexterm>Whuffie</p><p>The ephemeral, reputation-based currency invented by Cory Doctorow in his sci-fi novel, <i>Down and Out in the Magic Kingdom</i>.</p><p>Wiki</p><p>A collaborative web site where pages can be edited and added to by contributors.</p><p><indexterm>wikislices</indexterm>Wikislice </p><p>A cross-section of selected wiki pages collected together to form a new deliverable. </p><p>Wikitext </p><p>A markup language used to create the web pages that make up a wiki. Often it is a simplified, ASCII-based alternative to HTML coding.</p><p>Wiki patterns</p><p>Offers known solutions to known problems when trying to increase wiki adoption in a pattern format shaped after architectural patterns. Coined by Stewart Mader and described in his book, <i>Wikipatterns</i>.</p><p><indexterm>WordPress</indexterm>WordPress</p><p>An open source blog publishing application.</p><p>XHTML</p><p>A standard called eXtensible HyperText Markup Language that makes HTML conform to more strict XML rules.</p><p>XML</p><p>A standard called eXtensible Markup Language that imposes structure on a document through tags indicated with brackets and text. </p><p>XSLT</p><p>A standard called eXtensible Stylesheet Language Transformations that enables processing XML files into other formats such as HTML or PDF without changing the original XML file.</p></body></chapter>