<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<chapter
  id="d5e2"><title>Community and Documentation</title><shortdesc>The scale of the global community
    that is going to be able to participate in all sorts of discovery and innovation is something
    that the world has simply never seen before.&#8232;—Thomas Friedman, The World is
    Flat</shortdesc><prolog/><body><p>This chapter explores the idea that a small group of people
      who have a sense of belonging in an online community may provide content much like a technical
      writer does. Regardless of their background, education, or training, more people are becoming
      providers of technical information on the web. The gift economy, where altruism motivates
      contributions more than monetary gain, is partially responsible for this shift. <indexterm
        >Anderson, Chris</indexterm>Chris Anderson, author of <i>The Long Tail</i>, also wrote the
      article, “Free! Why $0.00 Is the Future of Business” for Wired<indexterm>Wired</indexterm>
        magazine<fn><p>
        http://www.wired.com/techbiz/it/magazine/16-03/ff_free?currentPage=all</p></fn> in February
      of 2008. In the article he describes a taxonomy<indexterm>taxonomy</indexterm> of “free” that
      contains many models including the gift economy. In <i>Naked Conversations</i>, bloggers
        <indexterm>Scobel, Robert</indexterm>Robert Scobel and <indexterm>Israel,
      Shel</indexterm>Shel Israel state “Altruism turns people on even more than making money.”
      Combine these altruistic motivations with a publishing system that has a low barrier to entry
      and you get a whole new way of working and writing. </p><p>If anyone can be a writer, what
      communities of writers have formed, and what have they accomplished? Why would you leverage
      someone’s sense of community belonging for documentation instead of hiring professional
      writers? How do you form communities online and in the real world? </p><p><indexterm
          >communities<indexterm>definition of</indexterm></indexterm><i>Community</i> has many
      definitions, but an <i>online community</i> has specific elements that shape its definition.
      From a blog entry by Forrester Research analyst Jeremiah <indexterm>Owyang,
        Jeremiah</indexterm>Owyang comes this definition: “An online community is: Where a group of
      people with similar goals or interests connect and exchange information using web tools.”<fn
          ><p> http://www.web-strategist.com/blog/2007/12/28/defining-the-term-community/</p></fn>
      As you might expect from a community researcher, Owyang says that his Twitter followers helped
      him shape that definition. Howard <indexterm>Rheingold, Howard</indexterm>Rheingold defines a
      virtual <indexterm>communities<indexterm>virtual</indexterm></indexterm>community<indexterm
        >virtual communities</indexterm> in his book, <i>The Virtual Community</i>, as “when people
      carry on public discussions long enough, with sufficient human feeling, to form webs of
      personal relationships.” Think of the online communities you belong to. You know there are
      common elements of discussion, agreement, core values, and unifying goals that help you
      identify it as a community. Relationships are the makeup of communities. Connections with each
      other establish relationships. Not all relationships in a community have to be positive­—even
      contentious debate can help a community meet its goals as long as the relationships remain
      respectful and intact after discussions.</p><p>Although in-person <indexterm
          >collaboration<indexterm>in-person</indexterm></indexterm>collaboration is an aspect of
      communities and documentation, much communication happens only online until community members
      meet at a conference or a networking event. Much of the communication that helps you feel like
      you know a person in the community happens online long before a face-to-face meeting. It’s
      that in-person or online conversation and public discourse that forges the relationships that
      create a community. </p><p>Sometimes the tools that help create the connections are mistaken
      for the community itself. Community is built from the connections, not the tools. For example,
      a blog with <indexterm>comments<indexterm>on blog posts</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm
          >comments<indexterm>on blog posts</indexterm></indexterm>comments might constitute a
      conversation, but it does not constitute the community itself. This distinction is important
      for a few reasons. First, it can help you choose which tools you can use to form a community.
      Second, it can help you understand why you might not have a community on your hands, yet, even
      though the right tools are in place. And, it can help you understand why a wiki has few edits
      yet many hits. Perhaps the sense of belonging to a community with a specific purpose and set
      of goals and the motivations that follow are not yet present. Or perhaps the technology layers
      are not familiar, so people don’t feel comfortable in an online community until they make
      sense of the tools for communication and interaction. </p></body><subsection
    id="d5e91"><title>Motivations for writers and online communities</title><body><p>Why are any of
        us interested in documenting a complex product or process? It’s possible that the core of
        our motivation is recognition or reward, measured in terms of money or success. Or maybe we
        think that writing and communicating with text, images, audio, or video is a great way to
        make a living. But, an underlying motivator for many technical writers is the desire to help
        others learn. By teaching, you learn twice. By joining a community, being a community
        member, and looking for places where you can either contribute or motivate others to
        contribute, you are empowering <indexterm>collaboration<indexterm>with
          audiences</indexterm></indexterm>collaborative efforts unlike any seen in the past. What I
        am observing more is that community members who do not have a writing role still want to
        write or communicate information about the product or service.</p><p>I can identify with the
        desire to help people through my work with the One Laptop per Child project<indexterm>One
          Laptop per Child<indexterm>author's experience with</indexterm></indexterm>. My kids and
        the kids in my son’s preschool classroom inspired me to work for the first time on an open
        source project. My first experience with Sugar, the open source operating system for the
        laptop, was an emulation on my laptop, and I was floored by its elegance and simplicity,
        created by a community of developers and usability experts giving their time to the project.
        I was inspired by the high quality of their offering and wanted the documentation to match
        it.</p><p>I have found my volunteer work to be invaluable as a learning experience and
        exercise in connecting to others. But I will also admit that one of my motivations has been
        to experiment with publishing and book promotion, with an idea in the back of my head that
        FLOSS Manuals could hit upon a huge bestselling book idea. </p><p>Before the OLPC Book
        Sprint in August, the FLOSS Manuals community had quite a nice discussion about money and
        free documentation. Income from book sales is typically used to further fund <indexterm
          >FLOSS Manuals<indexterm>goals</indexterm></indexterm>FLOSS Manuals’ goals as a non-profit
        community—invest your gains to further your aims.</p><p>So while writers are accustomed to
        earning money directly for writing, they might find that they are motivated not by the money
        itself but by the additional activities the money can fund. For example, profits from a Book
        Sprint can be used to fund future Book Sprints.</p></body><subsection
      id="d5e119"><title>New roles for writers</title><body><p>One of the roles I learned about
          while writing for a wiki is “<indexterm>manager, community</indexterm><indexterm>community
            manager</indexterm><indexterm>communities<indexterm>managing</indexterm></indexterm>community
          manager.” In many wiki environments, the writer can be the “content <indexterm
              >content<indexterm>curators of</indexterm></indexterm>curator,” someone who assembles
          collections based on themes. But if your goal is to build and grow a wiki, you need to
          build and grow the community for it first. People who feel they are part of a community
          may share knowledge as the community becomes a <indexterm>communities<indexterm>of
              practice</indexterm></indexterm>community of practice. Clay <indexterm>Shirky,
            Clay</indexterm>Shirky, in his talk about his book, <i>Here Comes Everybody</i>,<fn><p>
              http://cyber.law.harvard.edu/interactive/events/2008/02/shirky</p></fn> explains how
          quickly a community of practice can form now that online tools speed up the process of
          teaching specific techniques and learning them from others. A community of practice uses
          people as conduits to transfer knowledge. As those who study knowledge management have
          learned, workers spend a third of their time searching for information, and workers are
          five times more likely to turn to experienced co-workers for information rather than
          reading a book, thereby shortening their learning curve and hopefully avoiding mistakes.
          </p><p>You have probably heard of the phrase “train the trainer.” You may even imagine
          that your role as a writer is to write to the person who reads enough to learn a product
          inside and out and become the in-house expert for it. As an extension of that writer’s
          role of training the trainer, a writer may become a leader within the online <indexterm
              >communities<indexterm>writer's role in</indexterm></indexterm>community, teaching
          other community members. This trainer role may be highly motivating to some.</p><p
          >Particular types of users are more likely to seek out online <indexterm
              >communities<indexterm>participation in</indexterm></indexterm>communities for
          information—competent performers, proficient performers, and expert performers, as defined
          by Dreyfus and Dreyfus in <i>Mind over Machine</i>. In their “Model of Skill Acquisition,”
          these types of users are separated from the novices and advanced beginners, who represent
          the first two stages in the model. Advanced users are more likely to demand useful
          examples, instructions for getting results or achieving a specific goal, and advanced
          troubleshooting information. </p><p>When managing a community of experts, realize that the
          rules of the community can make entry difficult. Consider that some <indexterm
              >communities<indexterm>rules</indexterm></indexterm>communities have an unspoken “no
          whining” rule, which creates a very different atmosphere than a community that has a
          “there are no dumb questions” philosophy. </p></body></subsection><subsection
      id="d5e177"><title>Free as in freedom documentation</title><body><p>Why do people contribute
          to documentation for no payment or even unknowingly, since they don’t consider themselves
          to be writers? Andy Oram<indexterm>Oram, Andy</indexterm>, senior editor at O’Reilly
          Media, studied contributions to documentation by surveying people who contribute to online
          forums, email <indexterm>mailing lists<indexterm>contributions
          to</indexterm></indexterm>lists, or wikis. His “Why Do People Write Free Documentation?
          Results of a Survey”<fn><p>
              http://www.onlamp.com/pub/a/onlamp/2007/06/14/why-do-people-write-free-documentation-results-of-a-survey.html?page=1</p></fn>
          report contains many findings, some of which are surprising:</p><ul><li>People generally
            don’t think that they were contributing to documentation.</li><li>People don’t think of
            themselves as writers, despite the fact that the communication is written.</li></ul><p
          >Because the people surveyed were not paid directly for their written contributions, their
          contributions could be considered free as in “no-cost.” In <indexterm>open
              source<indexterm>open documentation contributions</indexterm></indexterm>open source
          circles, “free” can mean “freedom” rather than “no cost.” “Free” documentation, however,
          represents a shift away from these two definitions. </p><p>The email/Internet/search
          engine infrastructure that is in place enables all of us to feel like we are getting and
          giving information for free. In reality, a small group of people who have computers and
          pay $40 per month for high speed Internet access offer their time and knowledge in
          information exchanges in the hope that they will be repaid by others’ time and knowledge,
          through recognition, by achieving a sense of belonging, or by gaining back time through
          efficiency gains. These <indexterm>communities<indexterm>motivations
            of</indexterm></indexterm>motivations for contribution (reciprocity, reputation,
          attachment, and efficiency) in any online <indexterm>communities<indexterm>participation
              in</indexterm></indexterm>community are documented by Peter Kollack in his paper, The
          Economies of Online <indexterm>collaboration<indexterm>motivations
            for</indexterm></indexterm>Collaboration.<fn><p>
              http://www.sscnet.ucla.edu/soc/faculty/kollock/papers/economies.htm</p></fn>
        </p><p>For some, payment is in yet another free, no-cost form. Perhaps you could even go so
          far as to say that their payment is in happiness. <indexterm>Hunt, Tara</indexterm>Tara
            Hunt<indexterm>Tara Hunt</indexterm>, author of <i>The </i><indexterm>Whuffie Factor,
            The</indexterm><i>Whuffie Factor</i> and blogger at horsepigcow.com discusses the
          happiness factor in a 197-slide deck (offered for free!).<fn><p>
              http://www.slideshare.net/missrogue/happiness-as-your-business-model-414463</p></fn>
          The following four items represent what Tara calls pillars of happiness:</p><ul><li
            >Autonomy: Give people the ability to personalize their experience, offer choices, be
            open and transparent. </li><li>Competence: Let people feel like they’re good at what
            they do. </li><li>Relatedness: People want to connect with others in similar situations.
            </li><li>Self-esteem: People who are confident in their knowledge or relationships have
            self-esteem. </li></ul></body></subsection><subsection
      id="d5e253"><title>Joining a community</title><body><p>This new <indexterm
              >collaboration<indexterm>economy of</indexterm></indexterm>collaborative economy will
          affect technical writers who are paid for <indexterm>social media<indexterm>community
              involvement</indexterm></indexterm>documentation. Part of the new role for writers in
          Web 2.0 is becoming a community member, being a contributor, and being a reader of
          contributions from other community members. </p><p><indexterm>communities<indexterm
              >conversations in</indexterm></indexterm>Community membership is a hands-on activity
          that you do best when you have practice at it. It is not easy to get experience, but it is
          necessary. You must read the online arguments (flame wars) and observe other’s reactions
          to know how to handle them better each time they happen. You can observe leadership
          passing hands and the delegation that occurs. But observation does not always teach you
          how to step into a leadership role or delegate well.</p><p>You can learn the ebb and flow
          of a <indexterm>communities<indexterm>measuring conversations
            in</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm>conversations<indexterm>measuring "social
              weather"</indexterm></indexterm>conversation and become a meteorologist for the
            “<indexterm>social weather</indexterm>social weather” that’s ongoing in a community. For
          an example of social weather, do what Clay <indexterm>Shirky, Clay</indexterm>Shirky
          writes in his description of the course with the same name at New York University. Simply
          make some observations next time you walk into a restaurant. Is it noisy or quiet? Slow or
          busy? Are there couples or groups dining? In a restaurant you have visual and auditory
          cues to give your inner meteorologist a chance to assess the social weather. In an online
          community, you need to understand the cues that occur in writing, in emoticons, and in
          frequency and intensity of updates to content. In the presentation “Blogs and the social
          weather” at the Internet Research 3.0 conference in October 2002, Alex Halavais describes
          a deep dive analysis of bloggers’ discourse.</p><lq><p><i> “By measuring changes in word
              frequency within a large set of popular blogs over a period of four weeks, and
              comparing these changes to those in the ‘traditional’ media represented on the web, we
              are able to come to a better understanding of the nature of the content found on these
              sites. This view is further refined by clustering those blogs that carry similar
              content. While those who blog may not be very representative of the public at large,
              charting discourse in this way presents an interesting new window on public opinion.”
              </i><indexterm>Halavais, Alan</indexterm><fn><p>
                http://aoir.org/2002/program/halavais2.html</p></fn></p></lq><p>While this concept
          may sound new and exciting, it is quite 20th century. Analyzing newspaper content to
          determine public opinion was researcher A.A.<indexterm>blogs<indexterm>analyzing
              conversations in</indexterm></indexterm>Tenney’s original concept<fn><p> Tenney, A. A.
              (1912). The scientific analysis of the press. Independent 73:895-898.</p></fn> in
          1912.</p><p>So what are some ideas for keeping the <indexterm>social
          weather</indexterm>social weather sunny and clear in a community? <indexterm>Hunt,
            Tara</indexterm>Tara Hunt’s pillars of happiness are a good set of guidelines for
          testing your social deliverables for helping users and contributors. When community
          members can voice an opinion, give an honest review, and build an article or a diagram or
          a picture or a video, perhaps by taking on a writing role, they feel autonomous and
          happiness follows. Kathy Sierra calls creating competent users “helping users kick ass,”
          and she has written valuable blog entries about how to do that.<fn><p>
              http://headrush.typepad.com/</p></fn> In the area of relatedness, a writer doesn’t
          necessarily have to be a community member to enable people to talk to each other and meet
          in person more easily. Organizing tweetups (in-person gatherings for <indexterm
              >Twitter<indexterm>tweetups</indexterm></indexterm>Twitter users) or user group
          meetings are an extension of the community manager role, enabling people to feel related
          to one another. Documentation that enables relatedness, such as helping wiki writers talk
          to each other via comments or “<indexterm>wikis<indexterm>talk
            pages</indexterm></indexterm>talk” pages contributes to that pillar of happiness. </p><p
          >I found that after moving OLPC content to the FLOSS Manuals wiki, I still communicated
          project information via the OLPC wiki at wiki.laptop.org. When I organized the Book
          Sprint, I used a particular request page on the wiki to invite community members to the
          event. Volunteers then contacted me through my wiki “Talk” page which sent an email
          notification to the email address I had designated while still keeping our discussion open
          for any project contributor to see. </p></body></subsection><subsection
      id="d5e335"><title>Growing a community</title><body><p>Create guidelines and a central purpose
          for the community if you are going to <indexterm>communities<indexterm
              >building</indexterm></indexterm>grow one organically. For example, some online
            <indexterm>communities<indexterm>growing</indexterm></indexterm>communities subscribe to
          one overarching rule: No whining. Others may set a basic rule like: The only dumb question
          is the one unasked. These two communities will attract different members. Also, after you
          identify an established community you want to join, realize that it may take a direction
          that you hadn’t considered by changing its goals or changing some of its rules or culture.
          </p><p>Rather than trying to single-handedly grow the community, delegate to and recruit
          from the established community members for tasks that are not in your area.</p><p
            ><indexterm>communities<indexterm>patterns</indexterm></indexterm>Communities may have
            <indexterm>wikis<indexterm>patterns</indexterm></indexterm>patterns and anti-patterns
          much like the wiki patterns that Stewart <indexterm>Mader, Stewart</indexterm>Mader
          identified in his book of the same name. In online communities, people can block progress
          on community projects such as coding open source software. For example, someone might
          offer to address a bug but then doesn’t. The lack of follow-through becomes a block for
          anyone else who wants to make progress on the bug. Lack of documentation can also hamper
          community efforts. Ever-changing or ambiguous licensing of code may cause a community to
          abandon it if the license is not easy to use or not in line with the community’s vision.
          </p><p>Realize that benevolent dictatorship may not be the correct approach for a
          community. A benevolent dictatorship usually involves one leader who maintains a stance of
          always doing what’s best for the community, but maintains control over all decisions. Keep
          a balance as you foster community interaction, especially if you become a leader. Realize
          that everyone can have a role or several roles at once, both leading and following. </p><p
          >Software management books author Gerald <indexterm>Weinberg, Gerald</indexterm>Weinberg
          once said, “No matter what the problem is, it’s always a people problem.” Remember that
          technology layers cannot fix basic <indexterm>communities<indexterm>trust
              within</indexterm></indexterm>trust issues or bad behavior. Rather than adding
          administration layers, complex access control lists, or even check-ins, talk through the
          people problems. And if you are the benevolent dictator, be ready to allow the community
          to self-govern if that is the right direction for it.</p></body></subsection></subsection><subsection
    id="d5e378"><title>Real-world events</title><prolog><metadata><keywords>
          <indexterm>events</indexterm>
        </keywords></metadata></prolog><body><p>One reason people join an online <indexterm
            >communities<indexterm>in-person interaction</indexterm></indexterm>community is the
        in-person interaction that can happen at professional conferences or networking <indexterm
            >communities<indexterm>events</indexterm></indexterm>events. They may join a community
        related to their profession or to the tools needed for their job, or a community related to
        a fun recreational interest. It follows that people want to meet others in person at
        meetings and gatherings. These events not only enable you to communicate with your company’s
        customers; events help the customers meet and talk to each other. User groups and focus
        groups are examples of real-world meetings that have a single goal in mind. <indexterm
          >unconferences</indexterm>Unconferences, <indexterm>barcamp</indexterm><ph>barcamps</ph>,
        and <indexterm>meetups</indexterm>meetups are another type of real-world event where people
        with similar interests and goals meet to share information. A newly-defined event called a
          <indexterm>Book Sprint</indexterm>Book Sprint borrows from these camp concepts to create a
        one-week event of collaborative authoring that generates a book. </p></body><subsection
      id="d5e410"><title>Unconferences, barcamps, and meetups</title><body><p>An unconference or
            <indexterm>conversations<indexterm>barcamp</indexterm></indexterm>barcamp is usually
          defined by its lack of definition. The morning of the event, attendees gather at one place
          in front of a white board or poster and offer to share their knowledge in presentations or
          demonstrations. The unconference has no agenda until session ideas are placed on a white
          board, often using Post-it notes, in certain time slots so that participants can find
          sessions to attend. Sometimes a wiki page can help shape the agenda before the event, but
          the board at the event is the “final” schedule. </p><p>A meetup is a prearranged group
          meeting and the online social networking site meetup.com facilitates organizing those
          meetings. A combination of meetup and <indexterm>Twitter<indexterm
            >tweetups</indexterm></indexterm>Twitter, a Tweetup is an in-person meeting organized
          using Twitter for publicity and invites. Sometimes these events are intended for casual
          entertaining, other times they are organized for professional networking. The main point
          of these types of gatherings is to take advantage of the higher fidelity conversations
          that in-person events offer.</p><p>How can you plan for such a purposely impromptu event
          such as an unconference? First you have to realize that the attendees are going to make or
          break the event. I had little experience with planning an unconference when I was asked to
          plan one that would take place during the 2008 DocTrain West conference. With the
          encouragement and help of one person who was certainly going to attend, I was able to grow
          the invitation list with like-minded individuals. We ended up with some of the most
          interesting attendees, and one person said it was the most useful session of the
          conference to him, a compliment considering that the unconference was embedded within a
          highly valuable conference with a devoted group of
    attendees.</p></body></subsection></subsection><subsection
    id="d5e428"><title>Book Sprints</title><body><p>A <indexterm>FLOSS Manuals<indexterm>Book
            Sprints</indexterm></indexterm>Book Sprint is <indexterm>content<indexterm>collaboration
            in creating</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm>collaboration<indexterm>authoring
            and</indexterm></indexterm>collaborative authoring, in a short time such as 3–4 months,
        with the express goal of <indexterm>technical documentation<indexterm>collaborative
            authoring</indexterm></indexterm>publishing a book. That sums up the goal of the Book
        Sprint as devised by Tomas Krag, whose interests lie in the use of technology for developing
        nations and who was much more interested in the distribution of content and ideas than
        protecting his rights as an author. <indexterm>Hyde, Adam</indexterm>Adam Hyde, founder of
        FLOSS Manuals, was keen to explore the idea of an extreme Book Sprint, which compresses the
        authoring and production of a print-ready book into a week-long sprint. The first year after
        the birth of the Book Sprint concept, Adam and FLOSS Manuals experimented with several
        models of the sprint.</p><p>An entire Book Sprints book is available on the FLOSS Manuals
        website, offering how-to guidance for running your own Book Sprint. This section re-uses
        some of that content to spread the Book Sprint ideas and concepts as a collaboration
        technique. </p></body><subsection
      id="d5e457"><title>Book Sprint planning</title><body><p><indexterm>discussions about
              content<indexterm>in Book Sprints</indexterm></indexterm>Although the goal of the Book
          Sprint is to produce a book in one week, the planning of the event often determines its
          success. This section details some of the planning you should do in advance of the Book
          Sprint dates. Although a FLOSS Manuals Book Sprint uses the FLOSS Manuals wiki tool, you
          can use this advice with any collaborative authoring tool. </p><p>Scope</p><p>What topics
          will the book cover?</p><p>When determining the <indexterm>content<indexterm>scope of, for
              Book Sprints</indexterm></indexterm>scope of a book, you might experience a “chicken
          and egg” scenario. You might want to plan the scope and then invite people to attend, but
          at the same time you may wonder whether it is better to invite people to attend and then
          let them decide the scope. <indexterm>Hyde, Adam</indexterm>Adam Hyde thinks that you can
          strike a balance. You can decide on the overall topic of a book, such as an existing
          software product, before inviting anyone. The writers participating in the sprint can then
          help brainstorm the details of the content. It’s easier to motivate people if they have
          input early in the process.</p><p>Target Audience</p><p>Along with the scope comes the
          target audience, and one decision certainly shapes the other.</p><p>Who do you want to
          read the book? What are the job titles they hold? What organizations or groups do they
          belong to? Are they students in a college or industry professionals in the workforce? What
          other publications might they read, or what subject matter should they already be familiar
          with? What is their general level of computer literacy? What operating systems are they
          most commonly using?</p><p>Answering these questions should also help you identify
          potential participants in the Book Sprint as writers, editors, or technicians who can
          serve as subject matter experts.</p><p>Ideally, you can include a person from the target
          audience in the sprint as a document tester. For example, if the target audience is
          “newbies,” then invite someone who is new to the product. Instead of trying to imagine the
          level at which to write the material, you will find more value in having a member of your
          target audience in the room to look the experts in the eye and say “I don’t understand
          what that means.” The experts may then have to recalibrate their tone. This is not to say
          that the target audience member is always right, but the experts have to justify their
          position when challenged, which leads to better content.</p><p>Invitations</p><p>An
          important first decision when planning an event is whether you will select and invite a
          limited number of attendees or let the attendee list grow by allowing those initially
          invited to invite others<indexterm>invitations to in-person events</indexterm>. After you
          determine your core set of participants, choose a date and location that should work well
          for most of them. After you set a date and location for the core set of participants, you
          can open the event up to others. </p><p>With the FLOSS Manuals OLPC and <indexterm
            >SugarLabs</indexterm>SugarLabs Book Sprint, we had a last-minute request to attend the
          Book Sprint from a journalist located in the UK. Although she didn’t have firsthand
          experience with the XO laptop, she was interested in the <indexterm>One Laptop per
              Child<indexterm>Book Sprint</indexterm></indexterm>One Laptop per Child project and
          wanted to attend the Book Sprint in order to write a freelance journalist article about
          the experience. Although we were intrigued and flattered, we declined her request to
          attend because we wanted writers who could contribute immediately and also wanted to avoid
          distractions for the other attendees and participants. It turned out to be the right
          decision for all involved since we were a very focused group. </p><p>Draw up the
          outline</p><p>You perform two types of planning for a Book Sprint: planning the content
          and planning the event itself.</p><p>A <indexterm>content<indexterm
              >topic-oriented</indexterm></indexterm>topic-oriented, <indexterm>content<indexterm
              >single-sourcing</indexterm></indexterm>single-sourcing approach to content means that
          each chapter is a standalone piece of content that can be reused in many different
          remixes. This approach also means that the content can be used in a printed book, a PDF
          file, a collection of browse-able HTML files, or embedded in a website as if it were
          directly created in that web site. Planning with reuse in mind is important to the success
          of the sprint. </p><p>You should choose reusable content that can be completed in the
          allotted time for the Book Sprint. Part of the time spent in a Book Sprint is reusing or
          rewriting what else has been written on the topic. Identifying content that is already
          written ahead of time is part of your planning process. What books, websites, or wikis
          already discuss the technology on which Book Sprint focuses? Can you re-use any of that
          content based on their licensing of the content?</p><p>After you have a proposed audience
          and scope for a Book Sprint, take the time to talk about your ideas with others who are
          interested in reading the content. Make sure you have buy-in for the audience and scope
          for which you are planning, and revise as necessary until you feel ready to start
          outlining the book. In a few Book Sprints, the outline was completed the Sunday just
          before the week of the sprint.</p><p>Reuse existing content</p><p>After you have created
          the outline, you should spend time finding as much existing content as possible.
            <indexterm>content<indexterm>reusable</indexterm></indexterm>Re-use, re-use, re-use.
          Search the web and book stores for related content and write to each of the authors asking
          if you can re-use their content. </p><p>If material is available and it is under a liberal
          license—the same as the one as you want to use—ethical and fair treatment of the content
          means writing to the authors not to ask their permission but to ask for their “blessing”
          or endorsement to re-use the content. Many of those authors like to know where their
          content is re-used, and you might find that you have a new, enthusiastic contributor
          coming on board as the result of your communication. At the very least they will probably
          tell other people about your project and that provides good outreach for you.</p><p
          >Getting existing material is important not just because it can contribute to the total
          content of the book but because it is motivating for the writers to see that some of the
          work has already been done before they start. The writers might throw most of it out but
          by then the content has already had its motivating effect.</p></body></subsection><subsection
      id="d5e541"><title>Book Sprint logistics </title><body><p>You need to plan the dates,
          location, and participants in the sprint before you get very far. Either the dates and
          location are determined by the participants, or who participates will determine where and
          when the event takes place. In either situation, you need to consider some basic issues.
          Location and date selection depend on each other because some locations are not going to
          be available for certain dates. Travel time, distance, and cost as well as visa
          considerations are also part of the equation. If participants need a visa to come to the
          U.S. for such an event, at least a month lead time is necessary. </p><p>Transportation
          </p><p>How will everyone get there? Will you find the funds for travel or will the
          participants need to cover some or all of their travel expenses themselves? Travel costs
          are often the largest expense. The following sections provide an example of the travel
          expenses for a Book Sprint with about ten to twelve participants in Austin, Texas.</p><p
            ><i>Airfare</i>:</p><ul><li>Airfare from Amsterdam $1000</li><li>Airfare (for two
            people) from Boston $800</li><li>Airfare from Wisconsin $400</li><li>Total airfare
            $2200</li></ul><p>Six additional participants were all within driving distance of
          Austin. We did not have to pay for parking at the host location, and we did not reimburse
          mileage for driving, which would change the total travel costs.</p><p><i>Car
          rental</i>:</p><ul><li>Two cars, $100 per for a week, $200 total</li></ul><p>We did not
          rent cars for this Book Sprint. Driving people around once they were in Austin was my duty
          as a host and logistics coordinator, but we could have rented one or two cars (at about
          $100 each) for the week and made our lives much easier. Good logistics planning allows
          writing to be the focus of the week.</p><p>Location and other venues </p><p>The venue
          needs to have a single table where everyone can work. The sprinters need ample power
          sockets (or lots of extension cables), and you need a good Internet connection, preferably
          wireless. All-hours access to the building or room itself is helpful. Some host locations
          may want all participants to sign a release so that the host is not liable for damage or
          injury. Signing a release should be fine—nearly all of the planning is based on good faith
          in others anyway, so suing when the location is typically donated would be poor
          form.</p><p><i>Location</i> costs: $0 </p><p>Accommodations </p><p>Where will everyone
          sleep? Will they pay for their own accommodation or will you find funds for it? Is the
          accommodation sufficiently close to the Book Sprint venue so that participants don’t waste
          energy and time traveling every day? Do heavy snorers, smokers, or light sleepers need
          their own room? Do you need to have a space to prepare and cook meals? </p><p>The hotel
          rate was a corporate rate and in total it was $1333 for five nights with two of the rooms
          shared by four participants. The hotel was within walking distance of the sprint
          location.</p><p>Food </p><p>What is everyone going to eat and who will pay for it? Are
          there any special food requirements? Who is going to make the food? Where will you get the
          food? Can participants get a quick snack and caffeinated beverages as needed? Is everyone
          comfortable with alcohol and if so, what do they drink?</p><p>The best estimate is based
          on a per diem for the host city. Austin is $38 a day using a less expensive corporate rate
          for example, so the total would be $950 to provide all the food.</p><p>Fun </p><p>Is there
          anything nearby for some fun time out? It’s important to let the <indexterm
              >communities<indexterm>in-person interaction</indexterm></indexterm>team spend time
          together having fun. The Book Sprint is intended to be a fun event that encourages more
          collaborative efforts long after the intense week is done. The event can be as simple as a
          cookout or a hike for some sightseeing. Be sure to incorporate fun into the plan. It’s
          important to allow time for relationship building.</p></body></subsection><subsection
      id="d5e602"><title>Book Sprint budget</title><body><p>For the Austin-based Book Sprint, the
          costs totaled about $5000. We raised money by asking for donations from each of the
          participating organizations (RedHat, <indexterm>One Laptop per Child<indexterm>Book
              Sprint</indexterm></indexterm>OLPC, and <indexterm>SugarLabs</indexterm>SugarLabs),
          and FLOSS Manuals covered the remaining cost.</p><p>The total cost is comparable to hiring
          a contract technical writer for a specific deliverable, yet the results from the
          collaborative authoring effort generated more interest in the projects, and the quality
          was quite high. </p></body></subsection><subsection
      id="d5e616"><title>If there are online communities already, why hold a face-to-face meeting?
        </title><body><p>In an article published in STC <i>Intercom</i> January 2009, titled
          “Embrace the ‘Un’—When the Community Runs the <indexterm>communities<indexterm
              >events</indexterm></indexterm>Event,” Janet <indexterm>Swisher,
          Janet</indexterm>Swisher relates a story about the <indexterm>technical
              documentation<indexterm>collaborative authoring</indexterm></indexterm>One Laptop per
          Child and <indexterm>SugarLabs</indexterm>SugarLabs Book Sprint in which she was a
            participant.<fn><p>
              http://justwriteclick.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2009/01/embracetheunnoad.pdf</p></fn>
          While editing, she came across a wiki page that contained an embedded note saying
            “<indexterm>One Laptop per Child<indexterm>collaboration</indexterm></indexterm>confirm
          with Walter”—Walter Bender, founding member of the MIT Media Lab and a fellow Book Sprint
          writer who has unique first-hand knowledge and experience with the XO laptop created by
          OLPC. Janet walked over to Walter and asked the question that was listed on the wiki page.
          Without the <indexterm>collaboration<indexterm>in-person</indexterm></indexterm>in-person
          nature of the Book Sprint, this interaction may have taken a day or two via email,
          assuming that Walter could make an email a priority. </p><p>Although extroverts prefer an
          in-person meeting for authoring documentation, there are also good business reasons for
          enhancing the<indexterm>collaboration<indexterm>authoring and</indexterm></indexterm>
          collaboration and <indexterm>conversations<indexterm>Book
          Sprints</indexterm></indexterm>communication by holding an in-person event: </p><ul><li
            >Forging relationships that will help with ongoing writing projects and information
            seeking </li><li>Keeping people motivated to continue contributing to the project
            </li><li>Offering a strategy for updating and maintaining the documentation because a
            community has been created around both the event and the content itself </li></ul><p>The
          community feeling that you build during a Book Sprint project can carry the momentum from
          the project forward, giving people the urge to work on the book in coming weeks and
          leaving them with the feeling they’d like to work together again in the future. It also
          creates evangelists for the projects and generates excitement.</p><p>Remote contributions
          to a Book Sprint </p><p>Remote participation in a Book Sprint can occur, but it is
          supplemental to the actual event. In the case of the August 2008 FLOSS Manuals Book
          Sprint, we had a daily conference call so that remote participants could report their
          status and any blocks to their writing. We had a constant communication channel open on
            <indexterm>IRC (Internet Relay Chat)</indexterm>IRC (<indexterm>Internet Relay Chat
            (IRC)</indexterm>Internet Relay Chat). The founder of FLOSS Manuals, <indexterm>Hyde,
            Adam</indexterm>Adam Hyde, was always available for technical questions in the sprint
          room, plus the main FLOSS Manuals developer Aleksandar <indexterm>Erkalovic,
            Aleksandar</indexterm>Erkalovic was at the ready in Croatia to fix or explain any issues
          we found while sprinting.</p><p>The experience of the <indexterm>FLOSS Manuals<indexterm
              >collaborative writing</indexterm></indexterm>FLOSS Manuals sprints is that the
          majority of the work occurs in the “real space” of the sprint. There have been exceptions
          to this. The <i>Introduction to the Command Line</i> sprint held in <indexterm
              >collaboration<indexterm>Book Sprints</indexterm></indexterm>collaboration with the
          Free Software Foundation is an example where there were few real-space participants and
          many remote participants. Whichever way the participation is split, remote contributions
          are very important, and it’s absolutely necessary to devise a plan to coordinate the real
          space and remote contributions. </p><p>There are excellent tools for assisting with
          communication for remote contributors. We have used phone conferences (either Voice Over
          Internet Protocol (VOIP) or “real” phones), but in general these are not as effective for
          ongoing <indexterm>collaboration<indexterm>FLOSS
          Manuals</indexterm></indexterm>collaboration as text-based communication. A persistently
          open text-based chat is good for “ambient” remote communication, and better suited for
            <indexterm>collaboration<indexterm>Book Sprints</indexterm></indexterm>collaboration
          with remote participants over a day, a week, or longer. Voice chat seems to put too much
          focus on immediate activities, and there are often dreary moments when participants are
          trying to think of something to say. </p><p>However, quick conference calls can be very
          effective to help the real-space Book Sprint team realize that they are not working in
          isolation and that active, real people somewhere else on the planet care about what they
          are doing and want to help. They can give a motivating boost but are not absolutely
          necessary for coordinating work. </p><p>FLOSS Manuals provides the following tools for
          online communication among contributors: a chat widget online, IRC, <indexterm
              >email<indexterm>notifications</indexterm></indexterm>email notifications of changes
          to a topic, and a comparison page showing the changes from one contribution to the
          next.</p><p>Online chat widget</p><p>To chat with others while contributing to a book, we
          have provided a little inline chat window. You can see it on the right of all pages in the
          WRITE section of FLOSS Manuals website and it is also present in the editing pages. It is
          a simple mechanism requiring no extra plug-ins to work in your browser. The chat actually
          works by sending messages to the FLOSS Manuals <indexterm>IRC (Internet Relay
            Chat)</indexterm>IRC <indexterm>conversations<indexterm>Internet Relay Chat
              (IRC)</indexterm></indexterm>(<indexterm>Internet Relay Chat (IRC)</indexterm>Internet
          Relay Chat) channel. This chat is for communicating briefly about anything that comes to
          mind. The text format is short, and there is no history or ability to scroll back. The
          online chat is one chat room; there is no provision (yet) for chatting on a book-specific
          basis. All <indexterm>comments<indexterm>in chat</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm
              >comments<indexterm>in chat</indexterm></indexterm>comments are out in the open for
          all to see and remain there until someone else starts a discussion and forces your
          comments off the page. </p><p>For more elaborate conversations that you want to record, or
          for private messaging, you should use an IRC client when working on open source projects
          because many participants and subject matter experts use that same tool. For other
          projects, there may be a preferred enterprise <indexterm>conversations<indexterm>instant
              messaging</indexterm></indexterm>instant messaging tool, or a real-time chat or video
          capability that you can use. shows the FLOSS Manuals chat widget in action while someone
          is editing a chapter.</p><p>FLOSS Manuals chat widget</p></body></subsection><subsection
      id="d5e761"><title>IRC (Internet Relay Chat)</title><prolog><metadata><keywords>
            <indexterm>IRC (Internet Relay Chat)</indexterm>
          </keywords></metadata></prolog><body><p>IRC is an “old school” technology. Its “Channels”
          are mainly inhabited by geeks, especially free-software geeks. For chat, it’s a good
          technology because it requires very little bandwidth: if you are on a slow connection it
          works quite well. IRC chat rooms or channels are contained within “IRC Networks.” FLOSS
          Manuals uses the Freenode IRC network, one of the oldest and most popular. Anyone can
          create a chat room on the Freenode network, and the FLOSS Manuals chat room most
          frequently used is #flossmanuals. The web-based chat mentioned above connects to that main
          channel. </p><p>To use the IRC chat rooms, you need to have an IRC client installed or a
          browser plug-in installed. The server information is irc.freenode.net. After you connect
          to the server, you can join a chat room. There are other real-time-chat options available
          such as Campfire and Etherpad. The persistent, synchronous conversations and discussions
          groups can have with these tools are extremely valuable when pulling off a Book
          Sprint.</p><p>Notifications </p><p>Every book in FLOSS Manuals has an email notification
          feature and live visual notifications of who is editing. By subscribing to <indexterm
              >email<indexterm>notifications</indexterm></indexterm>email notifications, you get
          email every time a change is made in that book. These notifications also link to a “diff”
          view that shows the recent changes and highlights the differences. Both types of
          notifications are great during Book Sprints for keeping an eye on who is doing what. If
          someone changes something you have written, you can see the change and contact them if
          necessary to discuss the change. </p><p>In the editing interface () you can see who is
          editing any chapter. This view is useful for seeing how much activity is going on but it
          also helps coordinate contributions.</p><p>Editing notifications</p></body></subsection><subsection
      id="d5e783"><title>Book Sprints outside of free software</title><body><p>With communication
          tools assisting the authoring and an authoring tool that enables quick authoring and
          edits, you can accomplish the goal of a book in five days. <indexterm>IBM<indexterm
              >RedBooks</indexterm></indexterm><indexterm>collaboration<indexterm>IBM</indexterm></indexterm>IBM
          has been holding similar in-person events with their RedBooks projects for years. They
          would give subject matter experts a half-day of training in FrameMaker, have them
            <indexterm>technical documentation<indexterm>collaborative
            authoring</indexterm></indexterm>collaboratively outline a RedBook, and then send them
          on their separate ways after a week of authoring and in-person discussions. Some RedBooks
          have moved content into a wiki for internal collaboration.<fn><p>
              http://www.slideshare.net/almondjoy/redbooks-wiki-central-texas-dita-ug-presentation</p></fn></p><p>Think
          of an Agile development team with an embedded writer, meaning that a team consists of
          developers, designers, testers, and writers. Accomplishing a user story about
          documentation may benefit from the advice given in this section about Book Sprints. The
          entire team may decide to use a wiki and collaborate on a book-like project for an
          iteration. You could use your planning day to outline the deliverable, determine the
          audience, and invite others to share in the fun of accomplishing a book delivery in a
          time-boxed manner.</p></body></subsection></subsection></chapter>
