<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:topic" "topic.dtd">
<topic
  id="topic-id">
  <title>Conversation and Community</title>
  <body>
    <p>Copyright © 2009 Anne Gentle</p>
    <p>With the exceptions noted below, this work is licensed under the Creative Commons
      Attribution-Noncommercial 3.0 Unported License. To view a copy of this license, visit
      http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/. You can also find a copy in Appendix A.</p>
    <p>The cover and XML Press logo are Copyright © 2009 XML Press, All Rights Reserved. The policy
      example in Appendix B is reprinted by permission of the copyright holder and may not be copied
      without their permission. </p>
    <p>Editor: Kelly Holcomb</p>
    <p>Reviewers: Scott Abel, Sarah O’Keefe, Alan Porter, Will Sansbury</p>
    <p>Cover and Page Designs: Patrick Davison</p>
    <p><image
        href="images/ccbync.png"/></p>
    <p>Disclaimer</p>
    <p>The information in this book is provided on an “as is” basis, without warranty. While every
      effort has been taken by the author and XML Press in the preparation of this book, the author
      and XML Press shall have neither liability nor responsibility to any person or entity with
      respect to any loss or damages arising from the information contained in this book.</p>
    <p>This book contains links to third-party web sites that are not under the control of the
      author or XML Press. The author and XML Press are not responsible for the content of any
      linked site. Inclusion of a link in this book does not imply that the author or XML Press
      endorses or accepts any responsibility for the content of that third-party site.</p>
    <p>Trademarks</p>
    <p>XML Press and the XML Press logo are trademarks of XML Press.</p>
    <p>All terms mentioned in this book that are known to be trademarks or service marks have been
      capitalized as appropriate. Use of a term in this book should not be regarded as affecting the
      validity of any trademark or service mark.</p>
    <p>XML Press</p>
    <p>Fort Collins, CO 80528</p>
    <p>http://xmlpress.net</p>
    <p>First Edition</p>
    <p>ISBN: 978-0-9822191-1-9</p>
    <p>Printed in the United States of America</p>
  </body>
</topic>
