<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "http://docs.oasis-open.org/dita/v1.1/OS/dtd/concept.dtd">
<concept id="conceptId">
  <title>DITA2InDesign Project</title>
  <prolog>
    <critdates>
      <created date="2008-01-31"/>
      <revised modified="2008-02-07"/>
    </critdates>
  </prolog>
  <conbody>
    <p>The DITA2InDesign project is an open-source, community-based project to develop a plug-in for
      the <xref scope="external" type="html">DITA Open Toolkit</xref> that enables the publishing of
      DITA-based content using the Adobe InDesign CS3 product.</p>
    <p>The project was started by, and is currently being managed by, Eliot Kimber of <xref
        scope="external" format="html" href="http://www.reallysi.com">Really Strategies, Inc.</xref>
      (ekimber at reallysi dot com, user DrMacro on SourceForge).</p>
    <p>The project's SourceForge project page is: <xref
        href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/dita2indesign" format="html" scope="external"
        >http://sourceforge.net/projects/dita2indesign</xref></p>
    <p>
      <note>
        <p>Because of severe limitations in InDesign CS2's XML scripting support, this project is
          only intending to provide scripts for InDesign CS3 or later. The difference in ease of
          scripting between CS2 and CS3 is dramatic. It would be prohibitively difficult to
          implement the needed functionality in CS2 whereas with CS3 it should be fairly
          straightforward.</p>
      </note>
    </p>
  </conbody>
  <concept id="current-status">
    <title>Current Status</title>
    <conbody>
      <p>As of 1 Feb 2008 the project is in the initial startup phase, consisting of a call for
        participation and some initial design ideas and identification of implementation tasks. The
        project code library includes a small amount of XSLT code that demonstrates the general
        processing approach for the XML-to-XML-for-import-to-InDesign component.</p>
      <p>A this time the project is a "spare time" activity for those involved and therefore there
        is no implementation schedule more precise than "as soon as we can". </p>
    </conbody>
  </concept>
  <concept id="call-for-participation">
    <title>Call for Participation</title>
    <conbody>
      <p>This is a community-supported project. The project needs the following contributions:<ul>
          <li>XSLT developers to contribute to the DITA-to-XML-for-import-to-InDesign transforms</li>
          <li>InDesign JavaScript developers to contribute to the InDesign XML import scripts</li>
          <li>InDesign layout designers to contribute to the design of InDesign templates to be used
            for laying out the imported DITA content.</li>
          <li>Writers to contribute to the project User Guide documentation</li>
          <li>Testers to test the plugin as it is developed</li>
        </ul></p>
      <p>If you would like to participate as a developer, simply contact Eliot (see contact info
        above) with your SourceForge user ID. </p>
      <p>If you would like to contribute InDesign templates you can forward them to Eliot. All
        donated templates will be fully attributed although they must be provided with an
        appropriate open source license that allows unrestricted derivative use of the templates. In
        particular, it must be allowable for users of the plug-in to use the templates for documents
        sold as parts of products or to be included with or used by commercial products that use
        this plug-in. </p>
    </conbody>
  </concept>
  <concept id="contributors">
    <title>Contributors</title>
    <conbody>
      <p>The following companies and individuals have contributed materials or development time to
        this project:</p>
      <ul>
        <li><xref href="http://www.comtech-serv.com" scope="external" format="html">Comtech
            Services, Inc.</xref></li>
        <li><xref href="http://www.reallysi.com" scope="external" format="html">Really Strategies,
            Inc.</xref></li>
      </ul>
    </conbody>
  </concept>
</concept>
