<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net/doctypes/dita/shakespear/dtd/act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-5">
   <title>ACT V</title>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  Fields between Dartford and Blackheath.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter YORK, and his army of Irish, with drum
and colours</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>From Ireland thus comes York to claim his right,</line>
            <line>And pluck the crown from feeble Henry's head:</line>
            <line>Ring, bells, aloud; burn, bonfires, clear and bright,</line>
            <line>To entertain great England's lawful king.</line>
            <line>Ah! sancta majestas, who would not buy thee dear?</line>
            <line>Let them obey that know not how to rule;</line>
            <line>This hand was made to handle naught but gold.</line>
            <line>I cannot give due action to my words,</line>
            <line>Except a sword or sceptre balance it:</line>
            <line>A sceptre shall it have, have I a soul,</line>
            <line>On which I'll toss the flower-de-luce of France.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter BUCKINGHAM</stagedir>
            <line>Whom have we here? Buckingham, to disturb me?</line>
            <line>The king hath sent him, sure: I must dissemble.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>York, if thou meanest well, I greet thee well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>Humphrey of Buckingham, I accept thy greeting.</line>
            <line>Art thou a messenger, or come of pleasure?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>A messenger from Henry, our dread liege,</line>
            <line>To know the reason of these arms in peace;</line>
            <line>Or why thou, being a subject as I am,</line>
            <line>Against thy oath and true allegiance sworn,</line>
            <line>Should raise so great a power without his leave,</line>
            <line>Or dare to bring thy force so near the court.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  Scarce can I speak, my choler is so great:</line>
            <line>O, I could hew up rocks and fight with flint,</line>
            <line>I am so angry at these abject terms;</line>
            <line>And now, like Ajax Telamonius,</line>
            <line>On sheep or oxen could I spend my fury.</line>
            <line>I am far better born than is the king,</line>
            <line>More like a king, more kingly in my thoughts:</line>
            <line>But I must make fair weather yet a while,</line>
            <line>Till Henry be more weak and I more strong,--</line>
            <line>Buckingham, I prithee, pardon me,</line>
            <line>That I have given no answer all this while;</line>
            <line>My mind was troubled with deep melancholy.</line>
            <line>The cause why I have brought this army hither</line>
            <line>Is to remove proud Somerset from the king,</line>
            <line>Seditious to his grace and to the state.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>That is too much presumption on thy part:</line>
            <line>But if thy arms be to no other end,</line>
            <line>The king hath yielded unto thy demand:</line>
            <line>The Duke of Somerset is in the Tower.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>Upon thine honour, is he prisoner?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Upon mine honour, he is prisoner.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>Then, Buckingham, I do dismiss my powers.</line>
            <line>Soldiers, I thank you all; disperse yourselves;</line>
            <line>Meet me to-morrow in St. George's field,</line>
            <line>You shall have pay and every thing you wish.</line>
            <line>And let my sovereign, virtuous Henry,</line>
            <line>Command my eldest son, nay, all my sons,</line>
            <line>As pledges of my fealty and love;</line>
            <line>I'll send them all as willing as I live:</line>
            <line>Lands, goods, horse, armour, any thing I have,</line>
            <line>Is his to use, so Somerset may die.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>York, I commend this kind submission:</line>
            <line>We twain will go into his highness' tent.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter KING HENRY VI and Attendants</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Buckingham, doth York intend no harm to us,</line>
            <line>That thus he marcheth with thee arm in arm?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>In all submission and humility</line>
            <line>York doth present himself unto your highness.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Then what intends these forces thou dost bring?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>To heave the traitor Somerset from hence,</line>
            <line>And fight against that monstrous rebel Cade,</line>
            <line>Who since I heard to be discomfited.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter IDEN, with CADE'S head</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IDEN</speaker>
            <line>If one so rude and of so mean condition</line>
            <line>May pass into the presence of a king,</line>
            <line>Lo, I present your grace a traitor's head,</line>
            <line>The head of Cade, whom I in combat slew.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>The head of Cade! Great God, how just art Thou!</line>
            <line>O, let me view his visage, being dead,</line>
            <line>That living wrought me such exceeding trouble.</line>
            <line>Tell me, my friend, art thou the man that slew him?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IDEN</speaker>
            <line>I was, an't like your majesty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>How art thou call'd? and what is thy degree?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IDEN</speaker>
            <line>Alexander Iden, that's my name;</line>
            <line>A poor esquire of Kent, that loves his king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>So please it you, my lord, 'twere not amiss</line>
            <line>He were created knight for his good service.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Iden, kneel down.</line>
            <stagedir>He kneels</stagedir>
            <line>Rise up a knight.</line>
            <line>We give thee for reward a thousand marks,</line>
            <line>And will that thou henceforth attend on us.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IDEN</speaker>
            <line>May Iden live to merit such a bounty.</line>
            <line>And never live but true unto his liege!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Rises</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Enter QUEEN MARGARET and SOMERSET</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>See, Buckingham, Somerset comes with the queen:</line>
            <line>Go, bid her hide him quickly from the duke.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>For thousand Yorks he shall not hide his head,</line>
            <line>But boldly stand and front him to his face.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>How now! is Somerset at liberty?</line>
            <line>Then, York, unloose thy long-imprison'd thoughts,</line>
            <line>And let thy tongue be equal with thy heart.</line>
            <line>Shall I endure the sight of Somerset?</line>
            <line>False king! why hast thou broken faith with me,</line>
            <line>Knowing how hardly I can brook abuse?</line>
            <line>King did I call thee? no, thou art not king,</line>
            <line>Not fit to govern and rule multitudes,</line>
            <line>Which darest not, no, nor canst not rule a traitor.</line>
            <line>That head of thine doth not become a crown;</line>
            <line>Thy hand is made to grasp a palmer's staff,</line>
            <line>And not to grace an awful princely sceptre.</line>
            <line>That gold must round engirt these brows of mine,</line>
            <line>Whose smile and frown, like to Achilles' spear,</line>
            <line>Is able with the change to kill and cure.</line>
            <line>Here is a hand to hold a sceptre up</line>
            <line>And with the same to act controlling laws.</line>
            <line>Give place: by heaven, thou shalt rule no more</line>
            <line>O'er him whom heaven created for thy ruler.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SOMERSET</speaker>
            <line>O monstrous traitor! I arrest thee, York,</line>
            <line>Of capital treason 'gainst the king and crown;</line>
            <line>Obey, audacious traitor; kneel for grace.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>Wouldst have me kneel? first let me ask of these,</line>
            <line>If they can brook I bow a knee to man.</line>
            <line>Sirrah, call in my sons to be my bail;</line>
            <stagedir>Exit Attendant</stagedir>
            <line>I know, ere they will have me go to ward,</line>
            <line>They'll pawn their swords for my enfranchisement.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Call hither Clifford! bid him come amain,</line>
            <line>To say if that the bastard boys of York</line>
            <line>Shall be the surety for their traitor father.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit BUCKINGHAM</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>O blood-besotted Neapolitan,</line>
            <line>Outcast of Naples, England's bloody scourge!</line>
            <line>The sons of York, thy betters in their birth,</line>
            <line>Shall be their father's bail; and bane to those</line>
            <line>That for my surety will refuse the boys!</line>
            <stagedir>Enter EDWARD and RICHARD</stagedir>
            <line>See where they come: I'll warrant they'll</line>
            <line>make it good.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter CLIFFORD and YOUNG CLIFFORD</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>And here comes Clifford to deny their bail.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLIFFORD</speaker>
            <line>Health and all happiness to my lord the king!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Kneels</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>I thank thee, Clifford: say, what news with thee?</line>
            <line>Nay, do not fright us with an angry look;</line>
            <line>We are thy sovereign, Clifford, kneel again;</line>
            <line>For thy mistaking so, we pardon thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLIFFORD</speaker>
            <line>This is my king, York, I do not mistake;</line>
            <line>But thou mistakest me much to think I do:</line>
            <line>To Bedlam with him! is the man grown mad?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Ay, Clifford; a bedlam and ambitious humour</line>
            <line>Makes him oppose himself against his king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLIFFORD</speaker>
            <line>He is a traitor; let him to the Tower,</line>
            <line>And chop away that factious pate of his.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>He is arrested, but will not obey;</line>
            <line>His sons, he says, shall give their words for him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>Will you not, sons?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EDWARD</speaker>
            <line>Ay, noble father, if our words will serve.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD</speaker>
            <line>And if words will not, then our weapons shall.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLIFFORD</speaker>
            <line>Why, what a brood of traitors have we here!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>Look in a glass, and call thy image so:</line>
            <line>I am thy king, and thou a false-heart traitor.</line>
            <line>Call hither to the stake my two brave bears,</line>
            <line>That with the very shaking of their chains</line>
            <line>They may astonish these fell-lurking curs:</line>
            <line>Bid Salisbury and Warwick come to me.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter the WARWICK and SALISBURY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLIFFORD</speaker>
            <line>Are these thy bears? we'll bait thy bears to death.</line>
            <line>And manacle the bear-ward in their chains,</line>
            <line>If thou darest bring them to the baiting place.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD</speaker>
            <line>Oft have I seen a hot o'erweening cur</line>
            <line>Run back and bite, because he was withheld;</line>
            <line>Who, being suffer'd with the bear's fell paw,</line>
            <line>Hath clapp'd his tail between his legs and cried:</line>
            <line>And such a piece of service will you do,</line>
            <line>If you oppose yourselves to match Lord Warwick.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLIFFORD</speaker>
            <line>Hence, heap of wrath, foul indigested lump,</line>
            <line>As crooked in thy manners as thy shape!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>Nay, we shall heat you thoroughly anon.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLIFFORD</speaker>
            <line>Take heed, lest by your heat you burn yourselves.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Why, Warwick, hath thy knee forgot to bow?</line>
            <line>Old Salisbury, shame to thy silver hair,</line>
            <line>Thou mad misleader of thy brain-sick son!</line>
            <line>What, wilt thou on thy death-bed play the ruffian,</line>
            <line>And seek for sorrow with thy spectacles?</line>
            <line>O, where is faith? O, where is loyalty?</line>
            <line>If it be banish'd from the frosty head,</line>
            <line>Where shall it find a harbour in the earth?</line>
            <line>Wilt thou go dig a grave to find out war,</line>
            <line>And shame thine honourable age with blood?</line>
            <line>Why art thou old, and want'st experience?</line>
            <line>Or wherefore dost abuse it, if thou hast it?</line>
            <line>For shame! in duty bend thy knee to me</line>
            <line>That bows unto the grave with mickle age.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALISBURY</speaker>
            <line>My lord, I have consider'd with myself</line>
            <line>The title of this most renowned duke;</line>
            <line>And in my conscience do repute his grace</line>
            <line>The rightful heir to England's royal seat.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Hast thou not sworn allegiance unto me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALISBURY</speaker>
            <line>I have.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Canst thou dispense with heaven for such an oath?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALISBURY</speaker>
            <line>It is great sin to swear unto a sin,</line>
            <line>But greater sin to keep a sinful oath.</line>
            <line>Who can be bound by any solemn vow</line>
            <line>To do a murderous deed, to rob a man,</line>
            <line>To force a spotless virgin's chastity,</line>
            <line>To reave the orphan of his patrimony,</line>
            <line>To wring the widow from her custom'd right,</line>
            <line>And have no other reason for this wrong</line>
            <line>But that he was bound by a solemn oath?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>A subtle traitor needs no sophister.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Call Buckingham, and bid him arm himself.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>Call Buckingham, and all the friends thou hast,</line>
            <line>I am resolved for death or dignity.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLIFFORD</speaker>
            <line>The first I warrant thee, if dreams prove true.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>You were best to go to bed and dream again,</line>
            <line>To keep thee from the tempest of the field.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLIFFORD</speaker>
            <line>I am resolved to bear a greater storm</line>
            <line>Than any thou canst conjure up to-day;</line>
            <line>And that I'll write upon thy burgonet,</line>
            <line>Might I but know thee by thy household badge.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Now, by my father's badge, old Nevil's crest,</line>
            <line>The rampant bear chain'd to the ragged staff,</line>
            <line>This day I'll wear aloft my burgonet,</line>
            <line>As on a mountain top the cedar shows</line>
            <line>That keeps his leaves in spite of any storm,</line>
            <line>Even to affright thee with the view thereof.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLIFFORD</speaker>
            <line>And from thy burgonet I'll rend thy bear</line>
            <line>And tread it under foot with all contempt,</line>
            <line>Despite the bear-ward that protects the bear.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YOUNG CLIFFORD</speaker>
            <line>And so to arms, victorious father,</line>
            <line>To quell the rebels and their complices.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD</speaker>
            <line>Fie! charity, for shame! speak not in spite,</line>
            <line>For you shall sup with Jesu Christ to-night.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YOUNG CLIFFORD</speaker>
            <line>Foul stigmatic, that's more than thou canst tell.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD</speaker>
            <line>If not in heaven, you'll surely sup in hell.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt severally</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  Saint Alban's.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Alarums to the battle. Enter WARWICK</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Clifford of Cumberland, 'tis Warwick calls:</line>
            <line>And if thou dost not hide thee from the bear,</line>
            <line>Now, when the angry trumpet sounds alarum</line>
            <line>And dead men's cries do fill the empty air,</line>
            <line>Clifford, I say, come forth and fight with me:</line>
            <line>Proud northern lord, Clifford of Cumberland,</line>
            <line>Warwick is hoarse with calling thee to arms.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter YORK</stagedir>
            <line>How now, my noble lord? what, all afoot?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>The deadly-handed Clifford slew my steed,</line>
            <line>But match to match I have encounter'd him</line>
            <line>And made a prey for carrion kites and crows</line>
            <line>Even of the bonny beast he loved so well.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter CLIFFORD</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Of one or both of us the time is come.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>Hold, Warwick, seek thee out some other chase,</line>
            <line>For I myself must hunt this deer to death.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Then, nobly, York; 'tis for a crown thou fight'st.</line>
            <line>As I intend, Clifford, to thrive to-day,</line>
            <line>It grieves my soul to leave thee unassail'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLIFFORD</speaker>
            <line>What seest thou in me, York? why dost thou pause?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>With thy brave bearing should I be in love,</line>
            <line>But that thou art so fast mine enemy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLIFFORD</speaker>
            <line>Nor should thy prowess want praise and esteem,</line>
            <line>But that 'tis shown ignobly and in treason.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>So let it help me now against thy sword</line>
            <line>As I in justice and true right express it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLIFFORD</speaker>
            <line>My soul and body on the action both!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>A dreadful lay! Address thee instantly.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>They fight, and CLIFFORD falls</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLIFFORD</speaker>
            <line>La fin couronne les oeuvres.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Dies</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>Thus war hath given thee peace, for thou art still.</line>
            <line>Peace with his soul, heaven, if it be thy will!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Enter YOUNG CLIFFORD</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YOUNG CLIFFORD</speaker>
            <line>Shame and confusion! all is on the rout;</line>
            <line>Fear frames disorder, and disorder wounds</line>
            <line>Where it should guard. O war, thou son of hell,</line>
            <line>Whom angry heavens do make their minister</line>
            <line>Throw in the frozen bosoms of our part</line>
            <line>Hot coals of vengeance! Let no soldier fly.</line>
            <line>He that is truly dedicate to war</line>
            <line>Hath no self-love, nor he that loves himself</line>
            <line>Hath not essentially but by circumstance</line>
            <line>The name of valour.</line>
            <stagedir>Seeing his dead father</stagedir>
            <line>O, let the vile world end,</line>
            <line>And the premised flames of the last day</line>
            <line>Knit earth and heaven together!</line>
            <line>Now let the general trumpet blow his blast,</line>
            <line>Particularities and petty sounds</line>
            <line>To cease! Wast thou ordain'd, dear father,</line>
            <line>To lose thy youth in peace, and to achieve</line>
            <line>The silver livery of advised age,</line>
            <line>And, in thy reverence and thy chair-days, thus</line>
            <line>To die in ruffian battle? Even at this sight</line>
            <line>My heart is turn'd to stone: and while 'tis mine,</line>
            <line>It shall be stony. York not our old men spares;</line>
            <line>No more will I their babes: tears virginal</line>
            <line>Shall be to me even as the dew to fire,</line>
            <line>And beauty that the tyrant oft reclaims</line>
            <line>Shall to my flaming wrath be oil and flax.</line>
            <line>Henceforth I will not have to do with pity:</line>
            <line>Meet I an infant of the house of York,</line>
            <line>Into as many gobbets will I cut it</line>
            <line>As wild Medea young Absyrtus did:</line>
            <line>In cruelty will I seek out my fame.</line>
            <line>Come, thou new ruin of old Clifford's house:</line>
            <line>As did AEneas old Anchises bear,</line>
            <line>So bear I thee upon my manly shoulders;</line>
            <line>But then AEneas bare a living load,</line>
            <line>Nothing so heavy as these woes of mine.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit, bearing off his father</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Enter RICHARD and SOMERSET to fight. SOMERSET
is killed</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD</speaker>
            <line>So, lie thou there;</line>
            <line>For underneath an alehouse' paltry sign,</line>
            <line>The Castle in Saint Alban's, Somerset</line>
            <line>Hath made the wizard famous in his death.</line>
            <line>Sword, hold thy temper; heart, be wrathful still:</line>
            <line>Priests pray for enemies, but princes kill.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Fight: excursions. Enter KING HENRY VI, QUEEN
MARGARET, and others</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Away, my lord! you are slow; for shame, away!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Can we outrun the heavens? good Margaret, stay.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>What are you made of? you'll nor fight nor fly:</line>
            <line>Now is it manhood, wisdom and defence,</line>
            <line>To give the enemy way, and to secure us</line>
            <line>By what we can, which can no more but fly.</line>
            <stagedir>Alarum afar off</stagedir>
            <line>If you be ta'en, we then should see the bottom</line>
            <line>Of all our fortunes: but if we haply scape,</line>
            <line>As well we may, if not through your neglect,</line>
            <line>We shall to London get, where you are loved</line>
            <line>And where this breach now in our fortunes made</line>
            <line>May readily be stopp'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter YOUNG CLIFFORD</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YOUNG CLIFFORD</speaker>
            <line>But that my heart's on future mischief set,</line>
            <line>I would speak blasphemy ere bid you fly:</line>
            <line>But fly you must; uncurable discomfit</line>
            <line>Reigns in the hearts of all our present parts.</line>
            <line>Away, for your relief! and we will live</line>
            <line>To see their day and them our fortune give:</line>
            <line>Away, my lord, away!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  Fields near St. Alban's.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Alarum. Retreat. Enter YORK, RICHARD, WARWICK,
and Soldiers, with drum and colours</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>Of Salisbury, who can report of him,</line>
            <line>That winter lion, who in rage forgets</line>
            <line>Aged contusions and all brush of time,</line>
            <line>And, like a gallant in the brow of youth,</line>
            <line>Repairs him with occasion? This happy day</line>
            <line>Is not itself, nor have we won one foot,</line>
            <line>If Salisbury be lost.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD</speaker>
            <line>My noble father,</line>
            <line>Three times to-day I holp him to his horse,</line>
            <line>Three times bestrid him; thrice I led him off,</line>
            <line>Persuaded him from any further act:</line>
            <line>But still, where danger was, still there I met him;</line>
            <line>And like rich hangings in a homely house,</line>
            <line>So was his will in his old feeble body.</line>
            <line>But, noble as he is, look where he comes.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter SALISBURY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALISBURY</speaker>
            <line>Now, by my sword, well hast thou fought to-day;</line>
            <line>By the mass, so did we all. I thank you, Richard:</line>
            <line>God knows how long it is I have to live;</line>
            <line>And it hath pleased him that three times to-day</line>
            <line>You have defended me from imminent death.</line>
            <line>Well, lords, we have not got that which we have:</line>
            <line>'Tis not enough our foes are this time fled,</line>
            <line>Being opposites of such repairing nature.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>I know our safety is to follow them;</line>
            <line>For, as I hear, the king is fled to London,</line>
            <line>To call a present court of parliament.</line>
            <line>Let us pursue him ere the writs go forth.</line>
            <line>What says Lord Warwick? shall we after them?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>After them! nay, before them, if we can.</line>
            <line>Now, by my faith, lords, 'twas a glorious day:</line>
            <line>Saint Alban's battle won by famous York</line>
            <line>Shall be eternized in all age to come.</line>
            <line>Sound drums and trumpets, and to London all:</line>
            <line>And more such days as these to us befall!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>