<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net/doctypes/dita/shakespear/dtd/act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-4">
   <title>ACT IV</title>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  The coast of Kent.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Alarum. Fight at sea. Ordnance goes off. Enter a
Captain, a Master, a Master's-mate, WALTER WHITMORE,
and others; with them SUFFOLK, and others, prisoners</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Captain</speaker>
            <line>The gaudy, blabbing and remorseful day</line>
            <line>Is crept into the bosom of the sea;</line>
            <line>And now loud-howling wolves arouse the jades</line>
            <line>That drag the tragic melancholy night;</line>
            <line>Who, with their drowsy, slow and flagging wings,</line>
            <line>Clip dead men's graves and from their misty jaws</line>
            <line>Breathe foul contagious darkness in the air.</line>
            <line>Therefore bring forth the soldiers of our prize;</line>
            <line>For, whilst our pinnace anchors in the Downs,</line>
            <line>Here shall they make their ransom on the sand,</line>
            <line>Or with their blood stain this discolour'd shore.</line>
            <line>Master, this prisoner freely give I thee;</line>
            <line>And thou that art his mate, make boot of this;</line>
            <line>The other, Walter Whitmore, is thy share.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Gentleman</speaker>
            <line>What is my ransom, master? let me know.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Master</speaker>
            <line>A thousand crowns, or else lay down your head.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Master's-Mate</speaker>
            <line>And so much shall you give, or off goes yours.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Captain</speaker>
            <line>What, think you much to pay two thousand crowns,</line>
            <line>And bear the name and port of gentlemen?</line>
            <line>Cut both the villains' throats; for die you shall:</line>
            <line>The lives of those which we have lost in fight</line>
            <line>Be counterpoised with such a petty sum!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Gentleman</speaker>
            <line>I'll give it, sir; and therefore spare my life.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Gentleman</speaker>
            <line>And so will I and write home for it straight.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WHITMORE</speaker>
            <line>I lost mine eye in laying the prize aboard,</line>
            <line>And therefore to revenge it, shalt thou die;</line>
            <stagedir>To SUFFOLK</stagedir>
            <line>And so should these, if I might have my will.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Captain</speaker>
            <line>Be not so rash; take ransom, let him live.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Look on my George; I am a gentleman:</line>
            <line>Rate me at what thou wilt, thou shalt be paid.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WHITMORE</speaker>
            <line>And so am I; my name is Walter Whitmore.</line>
            <line>How now! why start'st thou? what, doth</line>
            <line>death affright?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Thy name affrights me, in whose sound is death.</line>
            <line>A cunning man did calculate my birth</line>
            <line>And told me that by water I should die:</line>
            <line>Yet let not this make thee be bloody-minded;</line>
            <line>Thy name is Gaultier, being rightly sounded.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WHITMORE</speaker>
            <line>Gaultier or Walter, which it is, I care not:</line>
            <line>Never yet did base dishonour blur our name,</line>
            <line>But with our sword we wiped away the blot;</line>
            <line>Therefore, when merchant-like I sell revenge,</line>
            <line>Broke be my sword, my arms torn and defaced,</line>
            <line>And I proclaim'd a coward through the world!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Stay, Whitmore; for thy prisoner is a prince,</line>
            <line>The Duke of Suffolk, William de la Pole.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WHITMORE</speaker>
            <line>The Duke of Suffolk muffled up in rags!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Ay, but these rags are no part of the duke:</line>
            <line>Jove sometimes went disguised, and why not I?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Captain</speaker>
            <line>But Jove was never slain, as thou shalt be.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Obscure and lowly swain, King Henry's blood,</line>
            <line>The honourable blood of Lancaster,</line>
            <line>Must not be shed by such a jaded groom.</line>
            <line>Hast thou not kiss'd thy hand and held my stirrup?</line>
            <line>Bare-headed plodded by my foot-cloth mule</line>
            <line>And thought thee happy when I shook my head?</line>
            <line>How often hast thou waited at my cup,</line>
            <line>Fed from my trencher, kneel'd down at the board.</line>
            <line>When I have feasted with Queen Margaret?</line>
            <line>Remember it and let it make thee crest-fall'n,</line>
            <line>Ay, and allay this thy abortive pride;</line>
            <line>How in our voiding lobby hast thou stood</line>
            <line>And duly waited for my coming forth?</line>
            <line>This hand of mine hath writ in thy behalf,</line>
            <line>And therefore shall it charm thy riotous tongue.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WHITMORE</speaker>
            <line>Speak, captain, shall I stab the forlorn swain?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Captain</speaker>
            <line>First let my words stab him, as he hath me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Base slave, thy words are blunt and so art thou.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Captain</speaker>
            <line>Convey him hence and on our longboat's side</line>
            <line>Strike off his head.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Thou darest not, for thy own.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Captain</speaker>
            <line>Yes, Pole.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Pole!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Captain</speaker>
            <line>Pool! Sir Pool! lord!</line>
            <line>Ay, kennel, puddle, sink; whose filth and dirt</line>
            <line>Troubles the silver spring where England drinks.</line>
            <line>Now will I dam up this thy yawning mouth</line>
            <line>For swallowing the treasure of the realm:</line>
            <line>Thy lips that kiss'd the queen shall sweep the ground;</line>
            <line>And thou that smiledst at good Duke Humphrey's death,</line>
            <line>Against the senseless winds shalt grin in vain,</line>
            <line>Who in contempt shall hiss at thee again:</line>
            <line>And wedded be thou to the hags of hell,</line>
            <line>For daring to affy a mighty lord</line>
            <line>Unto the daughter of a worthless king,</line>
            <line>Having neither subject, wealth, nor diadem.</line>
            <line>By devilish policy art thou grown great,</line>
            <line>And, like ambitious Sylla, overgorged</line>
            <line>With gobbets of thy mother's bleeding heart.</line>
            <line>By thee Anjou and Maine were sold to France,</line>
            <line>The false revolting Normans thorough thee</line>
            <line>Disdain to call us lord, and Picardy</line>
            <line>Hath slain their governors, surprised our forts,</line>
            <line>And sent the ragged soldiers wounded home.</line>
            <line>The princely Warwick, and the Nevils all,</line>
            <line>Whose dreadful swords were never drawn in vain,</line>
            <line>As hating thee, are rising up in arms:</line>
            <line>And now the house of York, thrust from the crown</line>
            <line>By shameful murder of a guiltless king</line>
            <line>And lofty proud encroaching tyranny,</line>
            <line>Burns with revenging fire; whose hopeful colours</line>
            <line>Advance our half-faced sun, striving to shine,</line>
            <line>Under the which is writ 'Invitis nubibus.'</line>
            <line>The commons here in Kent are up in arms:</line>
            <line>And, to conclude, reproach and beggary</line>
            <line>Is crept into the palace of our king.</line>
            <line>And all by thee. Away! convey him hence.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>O that I were a god, to shoot forth thunder</line>
            <line>Upon these paltry, servile, abject drudges!</line>
            <line>Small things make base men proud: this villain here,</line>
            <line>Being captain of a pinnace, threatens more</line>
            <line>Than Bargulus the strong Illyrian pirate.</line>
            <line>Drones suck not eagles' blood but rob beehives:</line>
            <line>It is impossible that I should die</line>
            <line>By such a lowly vassal as thyself.</line>
            <line>Thy words move rage and not remorse in me:</line>
            <line>I go of message from the queen to France;</line>
            <line>I charge thee waft me safely cross the Channel.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Captain</speaker>
            <line>Walter,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WHITMORE</speaker>
            <line>Come, Suffolk, I must waft thee to thy death.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Gelidus timor occupat artus it is thee I fear.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WHITMORE</speaker>
            <line>Thou shalt have cause to fear before I leave thee.</line>
            <line>What, are ye daunted now? now will ye stoop?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Gentleman</speaker>
            <line>My gracious lord, entreat him, speak him fair.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Suffolk's imperial tongue is stern and rough,</line>
            <line>Used to command, untaught to plead for favour.</line>
            <line>Far be it we should honour such as these</line>
            <line>With humble suit: no, rather let my head</line>
            <line>Stoop to the block than these knees bow to any</line>
            <line>Save to the God of heaven and to my king;</line>
            <line>And sooner dance upon a bloody pole</line>
            <line>Than stand uncover'd to the vulgar groom.</line>
            <line>True nobility is exempt from fear:</line>
            <line>More can I bear than you dare execute.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Captain</speaker>
            <line>Hale him away, and let him talk no more.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Come, soldiers, show what cruelty ye can,</line>
            <line>That this my death may never be forgot!</line>
            <line>Great men oft die by vile bezonians:</line>
            <line>A Roman sworder and banditto slave</line>
            <line>Murder'd sweet Tully; Brutus' bastard hand</line>
            <line>Stabb'd Julius Caesar; savage islanders</line>
            <line>Pompey the Great; and Suffolk dies by pirates.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt Whitmore and others with Suffolk</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Captain</speaker>
            <line>And as for these whose ransom we have set,</line>
            <line>It is our pleasure one of them depart;</line>
            <line>Therefore come you with us and let him go.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt all but the First Gentleman</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Re-enter WHITMORE with SUFFOLK's body</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WHITMORE</speaker>
            <line>There let his head and lifeless body lie,</line>
            <line>Until the queen his mistress bury it.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Gentleman</speaker>
            <line>O barbarous and bloody spectacle!</line>
            <line>His body will I bear unto the king:</line>
            <line>If he revenge it not, yet will his friends;</line>
            <line>So will the queen, that living held him dear.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit with the body</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  Blackheath.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter GEORGE BEVIS and JOHN HOLLAND</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEVIS</speaker>
            <line>Come, and get thee a sword, though made of a lath;</line>
            <line>they have been up these two days.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOLLAND</speaker>
            <line>They have the more need to sleep now, then.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEVIS</speaker>
            <line>I tell thee, Jack Cade the clothier means to dress</line>
            <line>the commonwealth, and turn it, and set a new nap upon it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOLLAND</speaker>
            <line>So he had need, for 'tis threadbare. Well, I say it</line>
            <line>was never merry world in England since gentlemen came up.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEVIS</speaker>
            <line>O miserable age! virtue is not regarded in handicrafts-men.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOLLAND</speaker>
            <line>The nobility think scorn to go in leather aprons.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEVIS</speaker>
            <line>Nay, more, the king's council are no good workmen.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOLLAND</speaker>
            <line>True; and yet it is said, labour in thy vocation;</line>
            <line>which is as much to say as, let the magistrates be</line>
            <line>labouring men; and therefore should we be</line>
            <line>magistrates.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEVIS</speaker>
            <line>Thou hast hit it; for there's no better sign of a</line>
            <line>brave mind than a hard hand.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOLLAND</speaker>
            <line>I see them! I see them! there's Best's son, the</line>
            <line>tanner of Wingham,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEVIS</speaker>
            <line>He shall have the skin of our enemies, to make</line>
            <line>dog's-leather of.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOLLAND</speaker>
            <line>And Dick the Butcher,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEVIS</speaker>
            <line>Then is sin struck down like an ox, and iniquity's</line>
            <line>throat cut like a calf.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOLLAND</speaker>
            <line>And Smith the weaver,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEVIS</speaker>
            <line>Argo, their thread of life is spun.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOLLAND</speaker>
            <line>Come, come, let's fall in with them.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Drum. Enter CADE, DICK the Butcher, SMITH the
Weaver, and a Sawyer, with infinite numbers</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>We John Cade, so termed of our supposed father,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DICK</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  Or rather, of stealing a cade of herrings.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>For our enemies shall fall before us, inspired with</line>
            <line>the spirit of putting down kings and princes,</line>
            <line>--Command silence.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DICK</speaker>
            <line>Silence!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>My father was a Mortimer,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DICK</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  He was an honest man, and a good</line>
            <line>bricklayer.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>My mother a Plantagenet,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DICK</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  I knew her well; she was a midwife.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>My wife descended of the Lacies,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DICK</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  She was, indeed, a pedler's daughter, and</line>
            <line>sold many laces.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SMITH</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  But now of late, notable to travel with her</line>
            <line>furred pack, she washes bucks here at home.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>Therefore am I of an honourable house.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DICK</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  Ay, by my faith, the field is honourable;</line>
            <line>and there was he borne, under a hedge, for his</line>
            <line>father had never a house but the cage.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>Valiant I am.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SMITH</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  A' must needs; for beggary is valiant.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>I am able to endure much.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DICK</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  No question of that; for I have seen him</line>
            <line>whipped three market-days together.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>I fear neither sword nor fire.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SMITH</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  He need not fear the sword; for his coat is of proof.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DICK</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  But methinks he should stand in fear of</line>
            <line>fire, being burnt i' the hand for stealing of sheep.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>Be brave, then; for your captain is brave, and vows</line>
            <line>reformation. There shall be in England seven</line>
            <line>halfpenny loaves sold for a penny: the three-hooped</line>
            <line>pot; shall have ten hoops and I will make it felony</line>
            <line>to drink small beer: all the realm shall be in</line>
            <line>common; and in Cheapside shall my palfrey go to</line>
            <line>grass: and when I am king, as king I will be,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALL</speaker>
            <line>God save your majesty!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>I thank you, good people: there shall be no money;</line>
            <line>all shall eat and drink on my score; and I will</line>
            <line>apparel them all in one livery, that they may agree</line>
            <line>like brothers and worship me their lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DICK</speaker>
            <line>The first thing we do, let's kill all the lawyers.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>Nay, that I mean to do. Is not this a lamentable</line>
            <line>thing, that of the skin of an innocent lamb should</line>
            <line>be made parchment? that parchment, being scribbled</line>
            <line>o'er, should undo a man? Some say the bee stings:</line>
            <line>but I say, 'tis the bee's wax; for I did but seal</line>
            <line>once to a thing, and I was never mine own man</line>
            <line>since. How now! who's there?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter some, bringing forward the Clerk of Chatham</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SMITH</speaker>
            <line>The clerk of Chatham: he can write and read and</line>
            <line>cast accompt.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>O monstrous!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SMITH</speaker>
            <line>We took him setting of boys' copies.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>Here's a villain!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SMITH</speaker>
            <line>Has a book in his pocket with red letters in't.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>Nay, then, he is a conjurer.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DICK</speaker>
            <line>Nay, he can make obligations, and write court-hand.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>I am sorry for't: the man is a proper man, of mine</line>
            <line>honour; unless I find him guilty, he shall not die.</line>
            <line>Come hither, sirrah, I must examine thee: what is thy name?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clerk</speaker>
            <line>Emmanuel.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DICK</speaker>
            <line>They use to write it on the top of letters: 'twill</line>
            <line>go hard with you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>Let me alone. Dost thou use to write thy name? or</line>
            <line>hast thou a mark to thyself, like an honest</line>
            <line>plain-dealing man?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLERK</speaker>
            <line>Sir, I thank God, I have been so well brought up</line>
            <line>that I can write my name.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALL</speaker>
            <line>He hath confessed: away with him! he's a villain</line>
            <line>and a traitor.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>Away with him, I say! hang him with his pen and</line>
            <line>ink-horn about his neck.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit one with the Clerk</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Enter MICHAEL</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MICHAEL</speaker>
            <line>Where's our general?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>Here I am, thou particular fellow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MICHAEL</speaker>
            <line>Fly, fly, fly! Sir Humphrey Stafford and his</line>
            <line>brother are hard by, with the king's forces.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>Stand, villain, stand, or I'll fell thee down. He</line>
            <line>shall be encountered with a man as good as himself:</line>
            <line>he is but a knight, is a'?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MICHAEL</speaker>
            <line>No.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>To equal him, I will make myself a knight presently.</line>
            <stagedir>Kneels</stagedir>
            <line>Rise up Sir John Mortimer.</line>
            <stagedir>Rises</stagedir>
            <line>Now have at him!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter SIR HUMPHREY and WILLIAM STAFFORD, with
drum and soldiers</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR HUMPHREY</speaker>
            <line>Rebellious hinds, the filth and scum of Kent,</line>
            <line>Mark'd for the gallows, lay your weapons down;</line>
            <line>Home to your cottages, forsake this groom:</line>
            <line>The king is merciful, if you revolt.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WILLIAM STAFFORD</speaker>
            <line>But angry, wrathful, and inclined to blood,</line>
            <line>If you go forward; therefore yield, or die.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>As for these silken-coated slaves, I pass not:</line>
            <line>It is to you, good people, that I speak,</line>
            <line>Over whom, in time to come, I hope to reign;</line>
            <line>For I am rightful heir unto the crown.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR HUMPHREY</speaker>
            <line>Villain, thy father was a plasterer;</line>
            <line>And thou thyself a shearman, art thou not?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>And Adam was a gardener.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WILLIAM STAFFORD</speaker>
            <line>And what of that?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>Marry, this: Edmund Mortimer, Earl of March.</line>
            <line>Married the Duke of Clarence' daughter, did he not?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR HUMPHREY</speaker>
            <line>Ay, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>By her he had two children at one birth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WILLIAM STAFFORD</speaker>
            <line>That's false.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>Ay, there's the question; but I say, 'tis true:</line>
            <line>The elder of them, being put to nurse,</line>
            <line>Was by a beggar-woman stolen away;</line>
            <line>And, ignorant of his birth and parentage,</line>
            <line>Became a bricklayer when he came to age:</line>
            <line>His son am I; deny it, if you can.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DICK</speaker>
            <line>Nay, 'tis too true; therefore he shall be king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SMITH</speaker>
            <line>Sir, he made a chimney in my father's house, and</line>
            <line>the bricks are alive at this day to testify it;</line>
            <line>therefore deny it not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR HUMPHREY</speaker>
            <line>And will you credit this base drudge's words,</line>
            <line>That speaks he knows not what?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALL</speaker>
            <line>Ay, marry, will we; therefore get ye gone.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WILLIAM STAFFORD</speaker>
            <line>Jack Cade, the Duke of York hath taught you this.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  He lies, for I invented it myself.</line>
            <line>Go to, sirrah, tell the king from me, that, for his</line>
            <line>father's sake, Henry the Fifth, in whose time boys</line>
            <line>went to span-counter for French crowns, I am content</line>
            <line>he shall reign; but I'll be protector over him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DICK</speaker>
            <line>And furthermore, well have the Lord Say's head for</line>
            <line>selling the dukedom of Maine.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>And good reason; for thereby is England mained, and</line>
            <line>fain to go with a staff, but that my puissance holds</line>
            <line>it up. Fellow kings, I tell you that that Lord Say</line>
            <line>hath gelded the commonwealth, and made it an eunuch:</line>
            <line>and more than that, he can speak French; and</line>
            <line>therefore he is a traitor.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR HUMPHREY</speaker>
            <line>O gross and miserable ignorance!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>Nay, answer, if you can: the Frenchmen are our</line>
            <line>enemies; go to, then, I ask but this: can he that</line>
            <line>speaks with the tongue of an enemy be a good</line>
            <line>counsellor, or no?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALL</speaker>
            <line>No, no; and therefore we'll have his head.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WILLIAM STAFFORD</speaker>
            <line>Well, seeing gentle words will not prevail,</line>
            <line>Assail them with the army of the king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR HUMPHREY</speaker>
            <line>Herald, away; and throughout every town</line>
            <line>Proclaim them traitors that are up with Cade;</line>
            <line>That those which fly before the battle ends</line>
            <line>May, even in their wives' and children's sight,</line>
            <line>Be hang'd up for example at their doors:</line>
            <line>And you that be the king's friends, follow me.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt WILLIAM STAFFORD and SIR HUMPHREY, and soldiers</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>And you that love the commons, follow me.</line>
            <line>Now show yourselves men; 'tis for liberty.</line>
            <line>We will not leave one lord, one gentleman:</line>
            <line>Spare none but such as go in clouted shoon;</line>
            <line>For they are thrifty honest men, and such</line>
            <line>As would, but that they dare not, take our parts.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DICK</speaker>
            <line>They are all in order and march toward us.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>But then are we in order when we are most</line>
            <line>out of order. Come, march forward.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  Another part of Blackheath.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Alarums to the fight, wherein SIR HUMPHREY and
WILLIAM STAFFORD are slain. Enter CADE and the rest</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>Where's Dick, the butcher of Ashford?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DICK</speaker>
            <line>Here, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>They fell before thee like sheep and oxen, and thou</line>
            <line>behavedst thyself as if thou hadst been in thine own</line>
            <line>slaughter-house: therefore thus will I reward thee,</line>
            <line>the Lent shall be as long again as it is; and thou</line>
            <line>shalt have a licence to kill for a hundred lacking</line>
            <line>one.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DICK</speaker>
            <line>I desire no more.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>And, to speak truth, thou deservest no less. This</line>
            <line>monument of the victory will I bear;</line>
            <stagedir>Putting on SIR HUMPHREY'S brigandine</stagedir>
            <line>and the bodies shall be dragged at my horse' heels</line>
            <line>till I do come to London, where we will have the</line>
            <line>mayor's sword borne before us.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DICK</speaker>
            <line>If we mean to thrive and do good, break open the</line>
            <line>gaols and let out the prisoners.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>Fear not that, I warrant thee. Come, let's march</line>
            <line>towards London.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-4">
      <title>SCENE IV.  London. The palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter KING HENRY VI with a supplication, and the
QUEEN with SUFFOLK'S head, BUCKINGHAM and Lord SAY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Oft have I heard that grief softens the mind,</line>
            <line>And makes it fearful and degenerate;</line>
            <line>Think therefore on revenge and cease to weep.</line>
            <line>But who can cease to weep and look on this?</line>
            <line>Here may his head lie on my throbbing breast:</line>
            <line>But where's the body that I should embrace?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>What answer makes your grace to the rebels'</line>
            <line>supplication?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>I'll send some holy bishop to entreat;</line>
            <line>For God forbid so many simple souls</line>
            <line>Should perish by the sword! And I myself,</line>
            <line>Rather than bloody war shall cut them short,</line>
            <line>Will parley with Jack Cade their general:</line>
            <line>But stay, I'll read it over once again.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Ah, barbarous villains! hath this lovely face</line>
            <line>Ruled, like a wandering planet, over me,</line>
            <line>And could it not enforce them to relent,</line>
            <line>That were unworthy to behold the same?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Lord Say, Jack Cade hath sworn to have thy head.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SAY</speaker>
            <line>Ay, but I hope your highness shall have his.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>How now, madam!</line>
            <line>Still lamenting and mourning for Suffolk's death?</line>
            <line>I fear me, love, if that I had been dead,</line>
            <line>Thou wouldst not have mourn'd so much for me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>No, my love, I should not mourn, but die for thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter a Messenger</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>How now! what news? why comest thou in such haste?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>The rebels are in Southwark; fly, my lord!</line>
            <line>Jack Cade proclaims himself Lord Mortimer,</line>
            <line>Descended from the Duke of Clarence' house,</line>
            <line>And calls your grace usurper openly</line>
            <line>And vows to crown himself in Westminster.</line>
            <line>His army is a ragged multitude</line>
            <line>Of hinds and peasants, rude and merciless:</line>
            <line>Sir Humphrey Stafford and his brother's death</line>
            <line>Hath given them heart and courage to proceed:</line>
            <line>All scholars, lawyers, courtiers, gentlemen,</line>
            <line>They call false caterpillars, and intend their death.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>O graceless men! they know not what they do.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>My gracious lord, return to Killingworth,</line>
            <line>Until a power be raised to put them down.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Ah, were the Duke of Suffolk now alive,</line>
            <line>These Kentish rebels would be soon appeased!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Lord Say, the traitors hate thee;</line>
            <line>Therefore away with us to Killingworth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SAY</speaker>
            <line>So might your grace's person be in danger.</line>
            <line>The sight of me is odious in their eyes;</line>
            <line>And therefore in this city will I stay</line>
            <line>And live alone as secret as I may.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter another Messenger</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>Jack Cade hath gotten London bridge:</line>
            <line>The citizens fly and forsake their houses:</line>
            <line>The rascal people, thirsting after prey,</line>
            <line>Join with the traitor, and they jointly swear</line>
            <line>To spoil the city and your royal court.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Then linger not, my lord, away, take horse.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Come, Margaret; God, our hope, will succor us.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>My hope is gone, now Suffolk is deceased.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Farewell, my lord: trust not the Kentish rebels.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Trust nobody, for fear you be betray'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SAY</speaker>
            <line>The trust I have is in mine innocence,</line>
            <line>And therefore am I bold and resolute.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-5">
      <title>SCENE V.  London. The Tower.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter SCALES upon the Tower, walking.
Then enter two or three Citizens below</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SCALES</speaker>
            <line>How now! is Jack Cade slain?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Citizen</speaker>
            <line>No, my lord, nor likely to be slain; for they have</line>
            <line>won the bridge, killing all those that withstand</line>
            <line>them: the lord mayor craves aid of your honour from</line>
            <line>the Tower, to defend the city from the rebels.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SCALES</speaker>
            <line>Such aid as I can spare you shall command;</line>
            <line>But I am troubled here with them myself;</line>
            <line>The rebels have assay'd to win the Tower.</line>
            <line>But get you to Smithfield, and gather head,</line>
            <line>And thither I will send you Matthew Goffe;</line>
            <line>Fight for your king, your country and your lives;</line>
            <line>And so, farewell, for I must hence again.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-6">
      <title>SCENE VI.  London. Cannon Street.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter CADE and the rest, and strikes his staff on
London-stone</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>Now is Mortimer lord of this city. And here, sitting</line>
            <line>upon London-stone, I charge and command that, of the</line>
            <line>city's cost, the pissing-conduit run nothing but</line>
            <line>claret wine this first year of our reign. And now</line>
            <line>henceforward it shall be treason for any that calls</line>
            <line>me other than Lord Mortimer.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter a Soldier, running</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Soldier</speaker>
            <line>Jack Cade! Jack Cade!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>Knock him down there.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>They kill him</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SMITH</speaker>
            <line>If this fellow be wise, he'll never call ye Jack</line>
            <line>Cade more: I think he hath a very fair warning.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DICK</speaker>
            <line>My lord, there's an army gathered together in</line>
            <line>Smithfield.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>Come, then, let's go fight with them; but first, go</line>
            <line>and set London bridge on fire; and, if you can, burn</line>
            <line>down the Tower too. Come, let's away.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-7">
      <title>SCENE VII.  London. Smithfield.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Alarums. MATTHEW GOFFE is slain, and all the rest.
Then enter CADE, with his company.</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>So, sirs: now go some and pull down the Savoy;</line>
            <line>others to the inns of court; down with them all.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DICK</speaker>
            <line>I have a suit unto your lordship.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>Be it a lordship, thou shalt have it for that word.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DICK</speaker>
            <line>Only that the laws of England may come out of your mouth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOLLAND</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  Mass, 'twill be sore law, then; for he was</line>
            <line>thrust in the mouth with a spear, and 'tis not whole</line>
            <line>yet.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SMITH</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  Nay, John, it will be stinking law for his</line>
            <line>breath stinks with eating toasted cheese.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>I have thought upon it, it shall be so. Away, burn</line>
            <line>all the records of the realm: my mouth shall be</line>
            <line>the parliament of England.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOLLAND</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  Then we are like to have biting statutes,</line>
            <line>unless his teeth be pulled out.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>And henceforward all things shall be in common.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter a Messenger</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>My lord, a prize, a prize! here's the Lord Say,</line>
            <line>which sold the towns in France; he that made us pay</line>
            <line>one and twenty fifteens, and one shilling to the</line>
            <line>pound, the last subsidy.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter BEVIS, with Lord SAY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>Well, he shall be beheaded for it ten times. Ah,</line>
            <line>thou say, thou serge, nay, thou buckram lord! now</line>
            <line>art thou within point-blank of our jurisdiction</line>
            <line>regal. What canst thou answer to my majesty for</line>
            <line>giving up of Normandy unto Mounsieur Basimecu, the</line>
            <line>dauphin of France? Be it known unto thee by these</line>
            <line>presence, even the presence of Lord Mortimer, that I</line>
            <line>am the besom that must sweep the court clean of such</line>
            <line>filth as thou art. Thou hast most traitorously</line>
            <line>corrupted the youth of the realm in erecting a</line>
            <line>grammar school; and whereas, before, our forefathers</line>
            <line>had no other books but the score and the tally, thou</line>
            <line>hast caused printing to be used, and, contrary to</line>
            <line>the king, his crown and dignity, thou hast built a</line>
            <line>paper-mill. It will be proved to thy face that thou</line>
            <line>hast men about thee that usually talk of a noun and</line>
            <line>a verb, and such abominable words as no Christian</line>
            <line>ear can endure to hear. Thou hast appointed</line>
            <line>justices of peace, to call poor men before them</line>
            <line>about matters they were not able to answer.</line>
            <line>Moreover, thou hast put them in prison; and because</line>
            <line>they could not read, thou hast hanged them; when,</line>
            <line>indeed, only for that cause they have been most</line>
            <line>worthy to live. Thou dost ride in a foot-cloth, dost thou not?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SAY</speaker>
            <line>What of that?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>Marry, thou oughtest not to let thy horse wear a</line>
            <line>cloak, when honester men than thou go in their hose</line>
            <line>and doublets.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DICK</speaker>
            <line>And work in their shirt too; as myself, for example,</line>
            <line>that am a butcher.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SAY</speaker>
            <line>You men of Kent,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DICK</speaker>
            <line>What say you of Kent?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SAY</speaker>
            <line>Nothing but this; 'tis 'bona terra, mala gens.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>Away with him, away with him! he speaks Latin.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SAY</speaker>
            <line>Hear me but speak, and bear me where you will.</line>
            <line>Kent, in the Commentaries Caesar writ,</line>
            <line>Is term'd the civil'st place of this isle:</line>
            <line>Sweet is the country, because full of riches;</line>
            <line>The people liberal, valiant, active, wealthy;</line>
            <line>Which makes me hope you are not void of pity.</line>
            <line>I sold not Maine, I lost not Normandy,</line>
            <line>Yet, to recover them, would lose my life.</line>
            <line>Justice with favour have I always done;</line>
            <line>Prayers and tears have moved me, gifts could never.</line>
            <line>When have I aught exacted at your hands,</line>
            <line>But to maintain the king, the realm and you?</line>
            <line>Large gifts have I bestow'd on learned clerks,</line>
            <line>Because my book preferr'd me to the king,</line>
            <line>And seeing ignorance is the curse of God,</line>
            <line>Knowledge the wing wherewith we fly to heaven,</line>
            <line>Unless you be possess'd with devilish spirits,</line>
            <line>You cannot but forbear to murder me:</line>
            <line>This tongue hath parley'd unto foreign kings</line>
            <line>For your behoof,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>Tut, when struck'st thou one blow in the field?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SAY</speaker>
            <line>Great men have reaching hands: oft have I struck</line>
            <line>Those that I never saw and struck them dead.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEVIS</speaker>
            <line>O monstrous coward! what, to come behind folks?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SAY</speaker>
            <line>These cheeks are pale for watching for your good.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>Give him a box o' the ear and that will make 'em red again.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SAY</speaker>
            <line>Long sitting to determine poor men's causes</line>
            <line>Hath made me full of sickness and diseases.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>Ye shall have a hempen caudle, then, and the help of hatchet.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DICK</speaker>
            <line>Why dost thou quiver, man?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SAY</speaker>
            <line>The palsy, and not fear, provokes me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>Nay, he nods at us, as who should say, I'll be even</line>
            <line>with you: I'll see if his head will stand steadier</line>
            <line>on a pole, or no. Take him away, and behead him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SAY</speaker>
            <line>Tell me wherein have I offended most?</line>
            <line>Have I affected wealth or honour? speak.</line>
            <line>Are my chests fill'd up with extorted gold?</line>
            <line>Is my apparel sumptuous to behold?</line>
            <line>Whom have I injured, that ye seek my death?</line>
            <line>These hands are free from guiltless bloodshedding,</line>
            <line>This breast from harbouring foul deceitful thoughts.</line>
            <line>O, let me live!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  I feel remorse in myself with his words;</line>
            <line>but I'll bridle it: he shall die, an it be but for</line>
            <line>pleading so well for his life. Away with him! he</line>
            <line>has a familiar under his tongue; he speaks not o'</line>
            <line>God's name. Go, take him away, I say, and strike</line>
            <line>off his head presently; and then break into his</line>
            <line>son-in-law's house, Sir James Cromer, and strike off</line>
            <line>his head, and bring them both upon two poles hither.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALL</speaker>
            <line>It shall be done.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SAY</speaker>
            <line>Ah, countrymen! if when you make your prayers,</line>
            <line>God should be so obdurate as yourselves,</line>
            <line>How would it fare with your departed souls?</line>
            <line>And therefore yet relent, and save my life.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>Away with him! and do as I command ye.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt some with Lord SAY</stagedir>
            <line>The proudest peer in the realm shall not wear a head</line>
            <line>on his shoulders, unless he pay me tribute; there</line>
            <line>shall not a maid be married, but she shall pay to me</line>
            <line>her maidenhead ere they have it: men shall hold of</line>
            <line>me in capite; and we charge and command that their</line>
            <line>wives be as free as heart can wish or tongue can tell.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DICK</speaker>
            <line>My lord, when shall we go to Cheapside and take up</line>
            <line>commodities upon our bills?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>Marry, presently.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALL</speaker>
            <line>O, brave!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter one with the heads</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>But is not this braver? Let them kiss one another,</line>
            <line>for they loved well when they were alive. Now part</line>
            <line>them again, lest they consult about the giving up of</line>
            <line>some more towns in France. Soldiers, defer the</line>
            <line>spoil of the city until night: for with these borne</line>
            <line>before us, instead of maces, will we ride through</line>
            <line>the streets, and at every corner have them kiss. Away!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-8">
      <title>SCENE VIII.  Southwark.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Alarum and retreat. Enter CADE and all his
rabblement</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>Up Fish Street! down Saint Magnus' Corner! Kill</line>
            <line>and knock down! throw them into Thames!</line>
            <stagedir>Sound a parley</stagedir>
            <line>What noise is this I hear? Dare any be so bold to</line>
            <line>sound retreat or parley, when I command them kill?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter BUCKINGHAM and CLIFFORD, attended</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Ay, here they be that dare and will disturb thee:</line>
            <line>Know, Cade, we come ambassadors from the king</line>
            <line>Unto the commons whom thou hast misled;</line>
            <line>And here pronounce free pardon to them all</line>
            <line>That will forsake thee and go home in peace.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLIFFORD</speaker>
            <line>What say ye, countrymen? will ye relent,</line>
            <line>And yield to mercy whilst 'tis offer'd you;</line>
            <line>Or let a rebel lead you to your deaths?</line>
            <line>Who loves the king and will embrace his pardon,</line>
            <line>Fling up his cap, and say 'God save his majesty!'</line>
            <line>Who hateth him and honours not his father,</line>
            <line>Henry the Fifth, that made all France to quake,</line>
            <line>Shake he his weapon at us and pass by.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALL</speaker>
            <line>God save the king! God save the king!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>What, Buckingham and Clifford, are ye so brave? And</line>
            <line>you, base peasants, do ye believe him? will you</line>
            <line>needs be hanged with your pardons about your necks?</line>
            <line>Hath my sword therefore broke through London gates,</line>
            <line>that you should leave me at the White Hart in</line>
            <line>Southwark? I thought ye would never have given out</line>
            <line>these arms till you had recovered your ancient</line>
            <line>freedom: but you are all recreants and dastards,</line>
            <line>and delight to live in slavery to the nobility. Let</line>
            <line>them break your backs with burthens, take your</line>
            <line>houses over your heads, ravish your wives and</line>
            <line>daughters before your faces: for me, I will make</line>
            <line>shift for one; and so, God's curse light upon you</line>
            <line>all!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALL</speaker>
            <line>We'll follow Cade, we'll follow Cade!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLIFFORD</speaker>
            <line>Is Cade the son of Henry the Fifth,</line>
            <line>That thus you do exclaim you'll go with him?</line>
            <line>Will he conduct you through the heart of France,</line>
            <line>And make the meanest of you earls and dukes?</line>
            <line>Alas, he hath no home, no place to fly to;</line>
            <line>Nor knows he how to live but by the spoil,</line>
            <line>Unless by robbing of your friends and us.</line>
            <line>Were't not a shame, that whilst you live at jar,</line>
            <line>The fearful French, whom you late vanquished,</line>
            <line>Should make a start o'er seas and vanquish you?</line>
            <line>Methinks already in this civil broil</line>
            <line>I see them lording it in London streets,</line>
            <line>Crying 'Villiago!' unto all they meet.</line>
            <line>Better ten thousand base-born Cades miscarry</line>
            <line>Than you should stoop unto a Frenchman's mercy.</line>
            <line>To France, to France, and get what you have lost;</line>
            <line>Spare England, for it is your native coast;</line>
            <line>Henry hath money, you are strong and manly;</line>
            <line>God on our side, doubt not of victory.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALL</speaker>
            <line>A Clifford! a Clifford! we'll follow the king and Clifford.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>Was ever feather so lightly blown to and fro as this</line>
            <line>multitude? The name of Henry the Fifth hales them</line>
            <line>to an hundred mischiefs, and makes them leave me</line>
            <line>desolate. I see them lay their heads together to</line>
            <line>surprise me. My sword make way for me, for here is</line>
            <line>no staying. In despite of the devils and hell, have</line>
            <line>through the very middest of you? and heavens and</line>
            <line>honour be witness, that no want of resolution in me.</line>
            <line>but only my followers' base and ignominious</line>
            <line>treasons, makes me betake me to my heels.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>What, is he fled? Go some, and follow him;</line>
            <line>And he that brings his head unto the king</line>
            <line>Shall have a thousand crowns for his reward.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt some of them</stagedir>
            <line>Follow me, soldiers: we'll devise a mean</line>
            <line>To reconcile you all unto the king.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-9">
      <title>SCENE IX.  Kenilworth Castle.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Sound Trumpets. Enter KING HENRY VI, QUEEN
MARGARET, and SOMERSET, on the terrace</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Was ever king that joy'd an earthly throne,</line>
            <line>And could command no more content than I?</line>
            <line>No sooner was I crept out of my cradle</line>
            <line>But I was made a king, at nine months old.</line>
            <line>Was never subject long'd to be a king</line>
            <line>As I do long and wish to be a subject.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter BUCKINGHAM and CLIFFORD</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Health and glad tidings to your majesty!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Why, Buckingham, is the traitor Cade surprised?</line>
            <line>Or is he but retired to make him strong?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter below, multitudes, with halters about
their necks</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLIFFORD</speaker>
            <line>He is fled, my lord, and all his powers do yield;</line>
            <line>And humbly thus, with halters on their necks,</line>
            <line>Expect your highness' doom of life or death.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Then, heaven, set ope thy everlasting gates,</line>
            <line>To entertain my vows of thanks and praise!</line>
            <line>Soldiers, this day have you redeemed your lives,</line>
            <line>And show'd how well you love your prince and country:</line>
            <line>Continue still in this so good a mind,</line>
            <line>And Henry, though he be infortunate,</line>
            <line>Assure yourselves, will never be unkind:</line>
            <line>And so, with thanks and pardon to you all,</line>
            <line>I do dismiss you to your several countries.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALL</speaker>
            <line>God save the king! God save the king!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter a Messenger</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>Please it your grace to be advertised</line>
            <line>The Duke of York is newly come from Ireland,</line>
            <line>And with a puissant and a mighty power</line>
            <line>Of gallowglasses and stout kerns</line>
            <line>Is marching hitherward in proud array,</line>
            <line>And still proclaimeth, as he comes along,</line>
            <line>His arms are only to remove from thee</line>
            <line>The Duke of Somerset, whom he terms traitor.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Thus stands my state, 'twixt Cade and York distress'd.</line>
            <line>Like to a ship that, having 'scaped a tempest,</line>
            <line>Is straightway calm'd and boarded with a pirate:</line>
            <line>But now is Cade driven back, his men dispersed;</line>
            <line>And now is York in arms to second him.</line>
            <line>I pray thee, Buckingham, go and meet him,</line>
            <line>And ask him what's the reason of these arms.</line>
            <line>Tell him I'll send Duke Edmund to the Tower;</line>
            <line>And, Somerset, we'll commit thee thither,</line>
            <line>Until his army be dismiss'd from him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SOMERSET</speaker>
            <line>My lord,</line>
            <line>I'll yield myself to prison willingly,</line>
            <line>Or unto death, to do my country good.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>In any case, be not too rough in terms;</line>
            <line>For he is fierce and cannot brook hard language.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>I will, my lord; and doubt not so to deal</line>
            <line>As all things shall redound unto your good.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Come, wife, let's in, and learn to govern better;</line>
            <line>For yet may England curse my wretched reign.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Flourish. Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-10">
      <title>SCENE X.  Kent. IDEN's garden.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter CADE</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>Fie on ambition! fie on myself, that have a sword,</line>
            <line>and yet am ready to famish! These five days have I</line>
            <line>hid me in these woods and durst not peep out, for</line>
            <line>all the country is laid for me; but now am I so</line>
            <line>hungry that if I might have a lease of my life for a</line>
            <line>thousand years I could stay no longer. Wherefore,</line>
            <line>on a brick wall have I climbed into this garden, to</line>
            <line>see if I can eat grass, or pick a sallet another</line>
            <line>while, which is not amiss to cool a man's stomach</line>
            <line>this hot weather. And I think this word 'sallet'</line>
            <line>was born to do me good: for many a time, but for a</line>
            <line>sallet, my brainpan had been cleft with a brown</line>
            <line>bill; and many a time, when I have been dry and</line>
            <line>bravely marching, it hath served me instead of a</line>
            <line>quart pot to drink in; and now the word 'sallet'</line>
            <line>must serve me to feed on.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter IDEN</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IDEN</speaker>
            <line>Lord, who would live turmoiled in the court,</line>
            <line>And may enjoy such quiet walks as these?</line>
            <line>This small inheritance my father left me</line>
            <line>Contenteth me, and worth a monarchy.</line>
            <line>I seek not to wax great by others' waning,</line>
            <line>Or gather wealth, I care not, with what envy:</line>
            <line>Sufficeth that I have maintains my state</line>
            <line>And sends the poor well pleased from my gate.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>Here's the lord of the soil come to seize me for a</line>
            <line>stray, for entering his fee-simple without leave.</line>
            <line>Ah, villain, thou wilt betray me, and get a thousand</line>
            <line>crowns of the king carrying my head to him: but</line>
            <line>I'll make thee eat iron like an ostrich, and swallow</line>
            <line>my sword like a great pin, ere thou and I part.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IDEN</speaker>
            <line>Why, rude companion, whatsoe'er thou be,</line>
            <line>I know thee not; why, then, should I betray thee?</line>
            <line>Is't not enough to break into my garden,</line>
            <line>And, like a thief, to come to rob my grounds,</line>
            <line>Climbing my walls in spite of me the owner,</line>
            <line>But thou wilt brave me with these saucy terms?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>Brave thee! ay, by the best blood that ever was</line>
            <line>broached, and beard thee too. Look on me well: I</line>
            <line>have eat no meat these five days; yet, come thou and</line>
            <line>thy five men, and if I do not leave you all as dead</line>
            <line>as a doornail, I pray God I may never eat grass more.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IDEN</speaker>
            <line>Nay, it shall ne'er be said, while England stands,</line>
            <line>That Alexander Iden, an esquire of Kent,</line>
            <line>Took odds to combat a poor famish'd man.</line>
            <line>Oppose thy steadfast-gazing eyes to mine,</line>
            <line>See if thou canst outface me with thy looks:</line>
            <line>Set limb to limb, and thou art far the lesser;</line>
            <line>Thy hand is but a finger to my fist,</line>
            <line>Thy leg a stick compared with this truncheon;</line>
            <line>My foot shall fight with all the strength thou hast;</line>
            <line>And if mine arm be heaved in the air,</line>
            <line>Thy grave is digg'd already in the earth.</line>
            <line>As for words, whose greatness answers words,</line>
            <line>Let this my sword report what speech forbears.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>By my valour, the most complete champion that ever I</line>
            <line>heard! Steel, if thou turn the edge, or cut not out</line>
            <line>the burly-boned clown in chines of beef ere thou</line>
            <line>sleep in thy sheath, I beseech God on my knees thou</line>
            <line>mayst be turned to hobnails.</line>
            <stagedir>Here they fight. CADE falls</stagedir>
            <line>O, I am slain! famine and no other hath slain me:</line>
            <line>let ten thousand devils come against me, and give me</line>
            <line>but the ten meals I have lost, and I'll defy them</line>
            <line>all. Wither, garden; and be henceforth a</line>
            <line>burying-place to all that do dwell in this house,</line>
            <line>because the unconquered soul of Cade is fled.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IDEN</speaker>
            <line>Is't Cade that I have slain, that monstrous traitor?</line>
            <line>Sword, I will hollow thee for this thy deed,</line>
            <line>And hang thee o'er my tomb when I am dead:</line>
            <line>Ne'er shall this blood be wiped from thy point;</line>
            <line>But thou shalt wear it as a herald's coat,</line>
            <line>To emblaze the honour that thy master got.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CADE</speaker>
            <line>Iden, farewell, and be proud of thy victory. Tell</line>
            <line>Kent from me, she hath lost her best man, and exhort</line>
            <line>all the world to be cowards; for I, that never</line>
            <line>feared any, am vanquished by famine, not by valour.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Dies</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>IDEN</speaker>
            <line>How much thou wrong'st me, heaven be my judge.</line>
            <line>Die, damned wretch, the curse of her that bare thee;</line>
            <line>And as I thrust thy body in with my sword,</line>
            <line>So wish I, I might thrust thy soul to hell.</line>
            <line>Hence will I drag thee headlong by the heels</line>
            <line>Unto a dunghill which shall be thy grave,</line>
            <line>And there cut off thy most ungracious head;</line>
            <line>Which I will bear in triumph to the king,</line>
            <line>Leaving thy trunk for crows to feed upon.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>