<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net/doctypes/dita/shakespear/dtd/act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-1">
   <title>ACT I</title>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  London. The palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Flourish of trumpets: then hautboys. Enter KING
HENRY VI, GLOUCESTER, SALISBURY, WARWICK, and
CARDINAL, on the one side; QUEEN MARGARET, SUFFOLK,
YORK, SOMERSET, and BUCKINGHAM, on the other</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>As by your high imperial majesty</line>
            <line>I had in charge at my depart for France,</line>
            <line>As procurator to your excellence,</line>
            <line>To marry Princess Margaret for your grace,</line>
            <line>So, in the famous ancient city, Tours,</line>
            <line>In presence of the Kings of France and Sicil,</line>
            <line>The Dukes of Orleans, Calaber, Bretagne and Alencon,</line>
            <line>Seven earls, twelve barons and twenty reverend bishops,</line>
            <line>I have perform'd my task and was espoused:</line>
            <line>And humbly now upon my bended knee,</line>
            <line>In sight of England and her lordly peers,</line>
            <line>Deliver up my title in the queen</line>
            <line>To your most gracious hands, that are the substance</line>
            <line>Of that great shadow I did represent;</line>
            <line>The happiest gift that ever marquess gave,</line>
            <line>The fairest queen that ever king received.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Suffolk, arise. Welcome, Queen Margaret:</line>
            <line>I can express no kinder sign of love</line>
            <line>Than this kind kiss. O Lord, that lends me life,</line>
            <line>Lend me a heart replete with thankfulness!</line>
            <line>For thou hast given me in this beauteous face</line>
            <line>A world of earthly blessings to my soul,</line>
            <line>If sympathy of love unite our thoughts.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Great King of England and my gracious lord,</line>
            <line>The mutual conference that my mind hath had,</line>
            <line>By day, by night, waking and in my dreams,</line>
            <line>In courtly company or at my beads,</line>
            <line>With you, mine alder-liefest sovereign,</line>
            <line>Makes me the bolder to salute my king</line>
            <line>With ruder terms, such as my wit affords</line>
            <line>And over-joy of heart doth minister.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Her sight did ravish; but her grace in speech,</line>
            <line>Her words y-clad with wisdom's majesty,</line>
            <line>Makes me from wondering fall to weeping joys;</line>
            <line>Such is the fulness of my heart's content.</line>
            <line>Lords, with one cheerful voice welcome my love.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALL</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Kneeling</stagedir>  Long live Queen Margaret, England's</line>
            <line>happiness!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>We thank you all.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Flourish</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>My lord protector, so it please your grace,</line>
            <line>Here are the articles of contracted peace</line>
            <line>Between our sovereign and the French king Charles,</line>
            <line>For eighteen months concluded by consent.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>  'Imprimis, it is agreed between the French</line>
            <line>king Charles, and William de la Pole, Marquess of</line>
            <line>Suffolk, ambassador for Henry King of England, that</line>
            <line>the said Henry shall espouse the Lady Margaret,</line>
            <line>daughter unto Reignier King of Naples, Sicilia and</line>
            <line>Jerusalem, and crown her Queen of England ere the</line>
            <line>thirtieth of May next ensuing. Item, that the duchy</line>
            <line>of Anjou and the county of Maine shall be released</line>
            <line>and delivered to the king her father'--</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Lets the paper fall</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Uncle, how now!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Pardon me, gracious lord;</line>
            <line>Some sudden qualm hath struck me at the heart</line>
            <line>And dimm'd mine eyes, that I can read no further.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Uncle of Winchester, I pray, read on.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>  'Item, It is further agreed between them,</line>
            <line>that the duchies of Anjou and Maine shall be</line>
            <line>released and delivered over to the king her father,</line>
            <line>and she sent over of the King of England's own</line>
            <line>proper cost and charges, without having any dowry.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>They please us well. Lord marquess, kneel down:</line>
            <line>We here create thee the first duke of Suffolk,</line>
            <line>And gird thee with the sword. Cousin of York,</line>
            <line>We here discharge your grace from being regent</line>
            <line>I' the parts of France, till term of eighteen months</line>
            <line>Be full expired. Thanks, uncle Winchester,</line>
            <line>Gloucester, York, Buckingham, Somerset,</line>
            <line>Salisbury, and Warwick;</line>
            <line>We thank you all for the great favour done,</line>
            <line>In entertainment to my princely queen.</line>
            <line>Come, let us in, and with all speed provide</line>
            <line>To see her coronation be perform'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt KING HENRY VI, QUEEN MARGARET, and SUFFOLK</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Brave peers of England, pillars of the state,</line>
            <line>To you Duke Humphrey must unload his grief,</line>
            <line>Your grief, the common grief of all the land.</line>
            <line>What! did my brother Henry spend his youth,</line>
            <line>His valour, coin and people, in the wars?</line>
            <line>Did he so often lodge in open field,</line>
            <line>In winter's cold and summer's parching heat,</line>
            <line>To conquer France, his true inheritance?</line>
            <line>And did my brother Bedford toil his wits,</line>
            <line>To keep by policy what Henry got?</line>
            <line>Have you yourselves, Somerset, Buckingham,</line>
            <line>Brave York, Salisbury, and victorious Warwick,</line>
            <line>Received deep scars in France and Normandy?</line>
            <line>Or hath mine uncle Beaufort and myself,</line>
            <line>With all the learned council of the realm,</line>
            <line>Studied so long, sat in the council-house</line>
            <line>Early and late, debating to and fro</line>
            <line>How France and Frenchmen might be kept in awe,</line>
            <line>And had his highness in his infancy</line>
            <line>Crowned in Paris in despite of foes?</line>
            <line>And shall these labours and these honours die?</line>
            <line>Shall Henry's conquest, Bedford's vigilance,</line>
            <line>Your deeds of war and all our counsel die?</line>
            <line>O peers of England, shameful is this league!</line>
            <line>Fatal this marriage, cancelling your fame,</line>
            <line>Blotting your names from books of memory,</line>
            <line>Razing the characters of your renown,</line>
            <line>Defacing monuments of conquer'd France,</line>
            <line>Undoing all, as all had never been!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL</speaker>
            <line>Nephew, what means this passionate discourse,</line>
            <line>This peroration with such circumstance?</line>
            <line>For France, 'tis ours; and we will keep it still.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Ay, uncle, we will keep it, if we can;</line>
            <line>But now it is impossible we should:</line>
            <line>Suffolk, the new-made duke that rules the roast,</line>
            <line>Hath given the duchy of Anjou and Maine</line>
            <line>Unto the poor King Reignier, whose large style</line>
            <line>Agrees not with the leanness of his purse.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALISBURY</speaker>
            <line>Now, by the death of Him that died for all,</line>
            <line>These counties were the keys of Normandy.</line>
            <line>But wherefore weeps Warwick, my valiant son?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>For grief that they are past recovery:</line>
            <line>For, were there hope to conquer them again,</line>
            <line>My sword should shed hot blood, mine eyes no tears.</line>
            <line>Anjou and Maine! myself did win them both;</line>
            <line>Those provinces these arms of mine did conquer:</line>
            <line>And are the cities, that I got with wounds,</line>
            <line>Delivered up again with peaceful words?</line>
            <line>Mort Dieu!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>For Suffolk's duke, may he be suffocate,</line>
            <line>That dims the honour of this warlike isle!</line>
            <line>France should have torn and rent my very heart,</line>
            <line>Before I would have yielded to this league.</line>
            <line>I never read but England's kings have had</line>
            <line>Large sums of gold and dowries with their wives:</line>
            <line>And our King Henry gives away his own,</line>
            <line>To match with her that brings no vantages.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>A proper jest, and never heard before,</line>
            <line>That Suffolk should demand a whole fifteenth</line>
            <line>For costs and charges in transporting her!</line>
            <line>She should have stayed in France and starved</line>
            <line>in France, Before--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL</speaker>
            <line>My Lord of Gloucester, now ye grow too hot:</line>
            <line>It was the pleasure of my lord the King.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>My Lord of Winchester, I know your mind;</line>
            <line>'Tis not my speeches that you do mislike,</line>
            <line>But 'tis my presence that doth trouble ye.</line>
            <line>Rancour will out: proud prelate, in thy face</line>
            <line>I see thy fury: if I longer stay,</line>
            <line>We shall begin our ancient bickerings.</line>
            <line>Lordings, farewell; and say, when I am gone,</line>
            <line>I prophesied France will be lost ere long.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL</speaker>
            <line>So, there goes our protector in a rage.</line>
            <line>'Tis known to you he is mine enemy,</line>
            <line>Nay, more, an enemy unto you all,</line>
            <line>And no great friend, I fear me, to the king.</line>
            <line>Consider, lords, he is the next of blood,</line>
            <line>And heir apparent to the English crown:</line>
            <line>Had Henry got an empire by his marriage,</line>
            <line>And all the wealthy kingdoms of the west,</line>
            <line>There's reason he should be displeased at it.</line>
            <line>Look to it, lords! let not his smoothing words</line>
            <line>Bewitch your hearts; be wise and circumspect.</line>
            <line>What though the common people favour him,</line>
            <line>Calling him 'Humphrey, the good Duke of</line>
            <line>Gloucester,'</line>
            <line>Clapping their hands, and crying with loud voice,</line>
            <line>'Jesu maintain your royal excellence!'</line>
            <line>With 'God preserve the good Duke Humphrey!'</line>
            <line>I fear me, lords, for all this flattering gloss,</line>
            <line>He will be found a dangerous protector.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Why should he, then, protect our sovereign,</line>
            <line>He being of age to govern of himself?</line>
            <line>Cousin of Somerset, join you with me,</line>
            <line>And all together, with the Duke of Suffolk,</line>
            <line>We'll quickly hoise Duke Humphrey from his seat.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL</speaker>
            <line>This weighty business will not brook delay:</line>
            <line>I'll to the Duke of Suffolk presently.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SOMERSET</speaker>
            <line>Cousin of Buckingham, though Humphrey's pride</line>
            <line>And greatness of his place be grief to us,</line>
            <line>Yet let us watch the haughty cardinal:</line>
            <line>His insolence is more intolerable</line>
            <line>Than all the princes in the land beside:</line>
            <line>If Gloucester be displaced, he'll be protector.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Or thou or I, Somerset, will be protector,</line>
            <line>Despite Duke Humphrey or the cardinal.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt BUCKINGHAM and SOMERSET</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALISBURY</speaker>
            <line>Pride went before, ambition follows him.</line>
            <line>While these do labour for their own preferment,</line>
            <line>Behoves it us to labour for the realm.</line>
            <line>I never saw but Humphrey Duke of Gloucester</line>
            <line>Did bear him like a noble gentleman.</line>
            <line>Oft have I seen the haughty cardinal,</line>
            <line>More like a soldier than a man o' the church,</line>
            <line>As stout and proud as he were lord of all,</line>
            <line>Swear like a ruffian and demean himself</line>
            <line>Unlike the ruler of a commonweal.</line>
            <line>Warwick, my son, the comfort of my age,</line>
            <line>Thy deeds, thy plainness and thy housekeeping,</line>
            <line>Hath won the greatest favour of the commons,</line>
            <line>Excepting none but good Duke Humphrey:</line>
            <line>And, brother York, thy acts in Ireland,</line>
            <line>In bringing them to civil discipline,</line>
            <line>Thy late exploits done in the heart of France,</line>
            <line>When thou wert regent for our sovereign,</line>
            <line>Have made thee fear'd and honour'd of the people:</line>
            <line>Join we together, for the public good,</line>
            <line>In what we can, to bridle and suppress</line>
            <line>The pride of Suffolk and the cardinal,</line>
            <line>With Somerset's and Buckingham's ambition;</line>
            <line>And, as we may, cherish Duke Humphrey's deeds,</line>
            <line>While they do tend the profit of the land.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>So God help Warwick, as he loves the land,</line>
            <line>And common profit of his country!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  And so says York, for he hath greatest cause.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALISBURY</speaker>
            <line>Then let's make haste away, and look unto the main.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Unto the main! O father, Maine is lost;</line>
            <line>That Maine which by main force Warwick did win,</line>
            <line>And would have kept so long as breath did last!</line>
            <line>Main chance, father, you meant; but I meant Maine,</line>
            <line>Which I will win from France, or else be slain,</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt WARWICK and SALISBURY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>Anjou and Maine are given to the French;</line>
            <line>Paris is lost; the state of Normandy</line>
            <line>Stands on a tickle point, now they are gone:</line>
            <line>Suffolk concluded on the articles,</line>
            <line>The peers agreed, and Henry was well pleased</line>
            <line>To change two dukedoms for a duke's fair daughter.</line>
            <line>I cannot blame them all: what is't to them?</line>
            <line>'Tis thine they give away, and not their own.</line>
            <line>Pirates may make cheap pennyworths of their pillage</line>
            <line>And purchase friends and give to courtezans,</line>
            <line>Still revelling like lords till all be gone;</line>
            <line>While as the silly owner of the goods</line>
            <line>Weeps over them and wrings his hapless hands</line>
            <line>And shakes his head and trembling stands aloof,</line>
            <line>While all is shared and all is borne away,</line>
            <line>Ready to starve and dare not touch his own:</line>
            <line>So York must sit and fret and bite his tongue,</line>
            <line>While his own lands are bargain'd for and sold.</line>
            <line>Methinks the realms of England, France and Ireland</line>
            <line>Bear that proportion to my flesh and blood</line>
            <line>As did the fatal brand Althaea burn'd</line>
            <line>Unto the prince's heart of Calydon.</line>
            <line>Anjou and Maine both given unto the French!</line>
            <line>Cold news for me, for I had hope of France,</line>
            <line>Even as I have of fertile England's soil.</line>
            <line>A day will come when York shall claim his own;</line>
            <line>And therefore I will take the Nevils' parts</line>
            <line>And make a show of love to proud Duke Humphrey,</line>
            <line>And, when I spy advantage, claim the crown,</line>
            <line>For that's the golden mark I seek to hit:</line>
            <line>Nor shall proud Lancaster usurp my right,</line>
            <line>Nor hold the sceptre in his childish fist,</line>
            <line>Nor wear the diadem upon his head,</line>
            <line>Whose church-like humours fits not for a crown.</line>
            <line>Then, York, be still awhile, till time do serve:</line>
            <line>Watch thou and wake when others be asleep,</line>
            <line>To pry into the secrets of the state;</line>
            <line>Till Henry, surfeiting in joys of love,</line>
            <line>With his new bride and England's dear-bought queen,</line>
            <line>And Humphrey with the peers be fall'n at jars:</line>
            <line>Then will I raise aloft the milk-white rose,</line>
            <line>With whose sweet smell the air shall be perfumed;</line>
            <line>And in my standard bear the arms of York</line>
            <line>To grapple with the house of Lancaster;</line>
            <line>And, force perforce, I'll make him yield the crown,</line>
            <line>Whose bookish rule hath pull'd fair England down.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  GLOUCESTER'S house.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter GLOUCESTER and his DUCHESS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS</speaker>
            <line>Why droops my lord, like over-ripen'd corn,</line>
            <line>Hanging the head at Ceres' plenteous load?</line>
            <line>Why doth the great Duke Humphrey knit his brows,</line>
            <line>As frowning at the favours of the world?</line>
            <line>Why are thine eyes fixed to the sullen earth,</line>
            <line>Gazing on that which seems to dim thy sight?</line>
            <line>What seest thou there? King Henry's diadem,</line>
            <line>Enchased with all the honours of the world?</line>
            <line>If so, gaze on, and grovel on thy face,</line>
            <line>Until thy head be circled with the same.</line>
            <line>Put forth thy hand, reach at the glorious gold.</line>
            <line>What, is't too short? I'll lengthen it with mine:</line>
            <line>And, having both together heaved it up,</line>
            <line>We'll both together lift our heads to heaven,</line>
            <line>And never more abase our sight so low</line>
            <line>As to vouchsafe one glance unto the ground.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>O Nell, sweet Nell, if thou dost love thy lord,</line>
            <line>Banish the canker of ambitious thoughts.</line>
            <line>And may that thought, when I imagine ill</line>
            <line>Against my king and nephew, virtuous Henry,</line>
            <line>Be my last breathing in this mortal world!</line>
            <line>My troublous dream this night doth make me sad.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS</speaker>
            <line>What dream'd my lord? tell me, and I'll requite it</line>
            <line>With sweet rehearsal of my morning's dream.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Methought this staff, mine office-badge in court,</line>
            <line>Was broke in twain; by whom I have forgot,</line>
            <line>But, as I think, it was by the cardinal;</line>
            <line>And on the pieces of the broken wand</line>
            <line>Were placed the heads of Edmund Duke of Somerset,</line>
            <line>And William de la Pole, first duke of Suffolk.</line>
            <line>This was my dream: what it doth bode, God knows.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS</speaker>
            <line>Tut, this was nothing but an argument</line>
            <line>That he that breaks a stick of Gloucester's grove</line>
            <line>Shall lose his head for his presumption.</line>
            <line>But list to me, my Humphrey, my sweet duke:</line>
            <line>Methought I sat in seat of majesty</line>
            <line>In the cathedral church of Westminster,</line>
            <line>And in that chair where kings and queens are crown'd;</line>
            <line>Where Henry and dame Margaret kneel'd to me</line>
            <line>And on my head did set the diadem.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Nay, Eleanor, then must I chide outright:</line>
            <line>Presumptuous dame, ill-nurtured Eleanor,</line>
            <line>Art thou not second woman in the realm,</line>
            <line>And the protector's wife, beloved of him?</line>
            <line>Hast thou not worldly pleasure at command,</line>
            <line>Above the reach or compass of thy thought?</line>
            <line>And wilt thou still be hammering treachery,</line>
            <line>To tumble down thy husband and thyself</line>
            <line>From top of honour to disgrace's feet?</line>
            <line>Away from me, and let me hear no more!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS</speaker>
            <line>What, what, my lord! are you so choleric</line>
            <line>With Eleanor, for telling but her dream?</line>
            <line>Next time I'll keep my dreams unto myself,</line>
            <line>And not be cheque'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Nay, be not angry; I am pleased again.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter Messenger</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>My lord protector, 'tis his highness' pleasure</line>
            <line>You do prepare to ride unto Saint Alban's,</line>
            <line>Where as the king and queen do mean to hawk.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>I go. Come, Nell, thou wilt ride with us?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS</speaker>
            <line>Yes, my good lord, I'll follow presently.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt GLOUCESTER and Messenger</stagedir>
            <line>Follow I must; I cannot go before,</line>
            <line>While Gloucester bears this base and humble mind.</line>
            <line>Were I a man, a duke, and next of blood,</line>
            <line>I would remove these tedious stumbling-blocks</line>
            <line>And smooth my way upon their headless necks;</line>
            <line>And, being a woman, I will not be slack</line>
            <line>To play my part in Fortune's pageant.</line>
            <line>Where are you there? Sir John! nay, fear not, man,</line>
            <line>We are alone; here's none but thee and I.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter HUME</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HUME</speaker>
            <line>Jesus preserve your royal majesty!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS</speaker>
            <line>What say'st thou? majesty! I am but grace.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HUME</speaker>
            <line>But, by the grace of God, and Hume's advice,</line>
            <line>Your grace's title shall be multiplied.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS</speaker>
            <line>What say'st thou, man? hast thou as yet conferr'd</line>
            <line>With Margery Jourdain, the cunning witch,</line>
            <line>With Roger Bolingbroke, the conjurer?</line>
            <line>And will they undertake to do me good?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HUME</speaker>
            <line>This they have promised, to show your highness</line>
            <line>A spirit raised from depth of under-ground,</line>
            <line>That shall make answer to such questions</line>
            <line>As by your grace shall be propounded him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS</speaker>
            <line>It is enough; I'll think upon the questions:</line>
            <line>When from St. Alban's we do make return,</line>
            <line>We'll see these things effected to the full.</line>
            <line>Here, Hume, take this reward; make merry, man,</line>
            <line>With thy confederates in this weighty cause.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HUME</speaker>
            <line>Hume must make merry with the duchess' gold;</line>
            <line>Marry, and shall. But how now, Sir John Hume!</line>
            <line>Seal up your lips, and give no words but mum:</line>
            <line>The business asketh silent secrecy.</line>
            <line>Dame Eleanor gives gold to bring the witch:</line>
            <line>Gold cannot come amiss, were she a devil.</line>
            <line>Yet have I gold flies from another coast;</line>
            <line>I dare not say, from the rich cardinal</line>
            <line>And from the great and new-made Duke of Suffolk,</line>
            <line>Yet I do find it so; for to be plain,</line>
            <line>They, knowing Dame Eleanor's aspiring humour,</line>
            <line>Have hired me to undermine the duchess</line>
            <line>And buz these conjurations in her brain.</line>
            <line>They say 'A crafty knave does need no broker;'</line>
            <line>Yet am I Suffolk and the cardinal's broker.</line>
            <line>Hume, if you take not heed, you shall go near</line>
            <line>To call them both a pair of crafty knaves.</line>
            <line>Well, so it stands; and thus, I fear, at last</line>
            <line>Hume's knavery will be the duchess' wreck,</line>
            <line>And her attainture will be Humphrey's fall:</line>
            <line>Sort how it will, I shall have gold for all.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  The palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter three or four Petitioners, PETER, the
Armourer's man, being one</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Petitioner</speaker>
            <line>My masters, let's stand close: my lord protector</line>
            <line>will come this way by and by, and then we may deliver</line>
            <line>our supplications in the quill.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Petitioner</speaker>
            <line>Marry, the Lord protect him, for he's a good man!</line>
            <line>Jesu bless him!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter SUFFOLK and QUEEN MARGARET</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETER</speaker>
            <line>Here a' comes, methinks, and the queen with him.</line>
            <line>I'll be the first, sure.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Petitioner</speaker>
            <line>Come back, fool; this is the Duke of Suffolk, and</line>
            <line>not my lord protector.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>How now, fellow! would'st anything with me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Petitioner</speaker>
            <line>I pray, my lord, pardon me; I took ye for my lord</line>
            <line>protector.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Reading</stagedir>  'To my Lord Protector!' Are your</line>
            <line>supplications to his lordship? Let me see them:</line>
            <line>what is thine?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Petitioner</speaker>
            <line>Mine is, an't please your grace, against John</line>
            <line>Goodman, my lord cardinal's man, for keeping my</line>
            <line>house, and lands, and wife and all, from me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Thy wife, too! that's some wrong, indeed. What's</line>
            <line>yours? What's here!</line>
            <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>
            <line>'Against the Duke of Suffolk, for enclosing the</line>
            <line>commons of Melford.' How now, sir knave!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Petitioner</speaker>
            <line>Alas, sir, I am but a poor petitioner of our whole township.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETER</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Giving his petition</stagedir>  Against my master, Thomas</line>
            <line>Horner, for saying that the Duke of York was rightful</line>
            <line>heir to the crown.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>What sayst thou? did the Duke of York say he was</line>
            <line>rightful heir to the crown?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETER</speaker>
            <line>That my master was? no, forsooth: my master said</line>
            <line>that he was, and that the king was an usurper.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Who is there?</line>
            <stagedir>Enter Servant</stagedir>
            <line>Take this fellow in, and send for</line>
            <line>his master with a pursuivant presently: we'll hear</line>
            <line>more of your matter before the King.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit Servant with PETER</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>And as for you, that love to be protected</line>
            <line>Under the wings of our protector's grace,</line>
            <line>Begin your suits anew, and sue to him.</line>
            <stagedir>Tears the supplication</stagedir>
            <line>Away, base cullions! Suffolk, let them go.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALL</speaker>
            <line>Come, let's be gone.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>My Lord of Suffolk, say, is this the guise,</line>
            <line>Is this the fashion in the court of England?</line>
            <line>Is this the government of Britain's isle,</line>
            <line>And this the royalty of Albion's king?</line>
            <line>What shall King Henry be a pupil still</line>
            <line>Under the surly Gloucester's governance?</line>
            <line>Am I a queen in title and in style,</line>
            <line>And must be made a subject to a duke?</line>
            <line>I tell thee, Pole, when in the city Tours</line>
            <line>Thou ran'st a tilt in honour of my love</line>
            <line>And stolest away the ladies' hearts of France,</line>
            <line>I thought King Henry had resembled thee</line>
            <line>In courage, courtship and proportion:</line>
            <line>But all his mind is bent to holiness,</line>
            <line>To number Ave-Maries on his beads;</line>
            <line>His champions are the prophets and apostles,</line>
            <line>His weapons holy saws of sacred writ,</line>
            <line>His study is his tilt-yard, and his loves</line>
            <line>Are brazen images of canonized saints.</line>
            <line>I would the college of the cardinals</line>
            <line>Would choose him pope, and carry him to Rome,</line>
            <line>And set the triple crown upon his head:</line>
            <line>That were a state fit for his holiness.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Madam, be patient: as I was cause</line>
            <line>Your highness came to England, so will I</line>
            <line>In England work your grace's full content.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Beside the haughty protector, have we Beaufort,</line>
            <line>The imperious churchman, Somerset, Buckingham,</line>
            <line>And grumbling York: and not the least of these</line>
            <line>But can do more in England than the king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>And he of these that can do most of all</line>
            <line>Cannot do more in England than the Nevils:</line>
            <line>Salisbury and Warwick are no simple peers.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Not all these lords do vex me half so much</line>
            <line>As that proud dame, the lord protector's wife.</line>
            <line>She sweeps it through the court with troops of ladies,</line>
            <line>More like an empress than Duke Humphrey's wife:</line>
            <line>Strangers in court do take her for the queen:</line>
            <line>She bears a duke's revenues on her back,</line>
            <line>And in her heart she scorns our poverty:</line>
            <line>Shall I not live to be avenged on her?</line>
            <line>Contemptuous base-born callet as she is,</line>
            <line>She vaunted 'mongst her minions t'other day,</line>
            <line>The very train of her worst wearing gown</line>
            <line>Was better worth than all my father's lands,</line>
            <line>Till Suffolk gave two dukedoms for his daughter.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Madam, myself have limed a bush for her,</line>
            <line>And placed a quire of such enticing birds,</line>
            <line>That she will light to listen to the lays,</line>
            <line>And never mount to trouble you again.</line>
            <line>So, let her rest: and, madam, list to me;</line>
            <line>For I am bold to counsel you in this.</line>
            <line>Although we fancy not the cardinal,</line>
            <line>Yet must we join with him and with the lords,</line>
            <line>Till we have brought Duke Humphrey in disgrace.</line>
            <line>As for the Duke of York, this late complaint</line>
            <line>Will make but little for his benefit.</line>
            <line>So, one by one, we'll weed them all at last,</line>
            <line>And you yourself shall steer the happy helm.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Sound a sennet. Enter KING HENRY VI, GLOUCESTER,
CARDINAL, BUCKINGHAM, YORK, SOMERSET, SALISBURY,
WARWICK, and the DUCHESS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>For my part, noble lords, I care not which;</line>
            <line>Or Somerset or York, all's one to me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>If York have ill demean'd himself in France,</line>
            <line>Then let him be denay'd the regentship.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SOMERSET</speaker>
            <line>If Somerset be unworthy of the place,</line>
            <line>Let York be regent; I will yield to him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Whether your grace be worthy, yea or no,</line>
            <line>Dispute not that: York is the worthier.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL</speaker>
            <line>Ambitious Warwick, let thy betters speak.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>The cardinal's not my better in the field.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>All in this presence are thy betters, Warwick.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Warwick may live to be the best of all.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALISBURY</speaker>
            <line>Peace, son! and show some reason, Buckingham,</line>
            <line>Why Somerset should be preferred in this.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Because the king, forsooth, will have it so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Madam, the king is old enough himself</line>
            <line>To give his censure: these are no women's matters.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>If he be old enough, what needs your grace</line>
            <line>To be protector of his excellence?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Madam, I am protector of the realm;</line>
            <line>And, at his pleasure, will resign my place.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Resign it then and leave thine insolence.</line>
            <line>Since thou wert king--as who is king but thou?--</line>
            <line>The commonwealth hath daily run to wreck;</line>
            <line>The Dauphin hath prevail'd beyond the seas;</line>
            <line>And all the peers and nobles of the realm</line>
            <line>Have been as bondmen to thy sovereignty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL</speaker>
            <line>The commons hast thou rack'd; the clergy's bags</line>
            <line>Are lank and lean with thy extortions.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SOMERSET</speaker>
            <line>Thy sumptuous buildings and thy wife's attire</line>
            <line>Have cost a mass of public treasury.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Thy cruelty in execution</line>
            <line>Upon offenders, hath exceeded law,</line>
            <line>And left thee to the mercy of the law.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>They sale of offices and towns in France,</line>
            <line>If they were known, as the suspect is great,</line>
            <line>Would make thee quickly hop without thy head.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit GLOUCESTER. QUEEN MARGARET drops her fan</stagedir>
            <line>Give me my fan: what, minion! can ye not?</line>
            <stagedir>She gives the DUCHESS a box on the ear</stagedir>
            <line>I cry you mercy, madam; was it you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS</speaker>
            <line>Was't I! yea, I it was, proud Frenchwoman:</line>
            <line>Could I come near your beauty with my nails,</line>
            <line>I'd set my ten commandments in your face.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Sweet aunt, be quiet; 'twas against her will.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS</speaker>
            <line>Against her will! good king, look to't in time;</line>
            <line>She'll hamper thee, and dandle thee like a baby:</line>
            <line>Though in this place most master wear no breeches,</line>
            <line>She shall not strike Dame Eleanor unrevenged.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Lord cardinal, I will follow Eleanor,</line>
            <line>And listen after Humphrey, how he proceeds:</line>
            <line>She's tickled now; her fume needs no spurs,</line>
            <line>She'll gallop far enough to her destruction.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Re-enter GLOUCESTER</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Now, lords, my choler being over-blown</line>
            <line>With walking once about the quadrangle,</line>
            <line>I come to talk of commonwealth affairs.</line>
            <line>As for your spiteful false objections,</line>
            <line>Prove them, and I lie open to the law:</line>
            <line>But God in mercy so deal with my soul,</line>
            <line>As I in duty love my king and country!</line>
            <line>But, to the matter that we have in hand:</line>
            <line>I say, my sovereign, York is meetest man</line>
            <line>To be your regent in the realm of France.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Before we make election, give me leave</line>
            <line>To show some reason, of no little force,</line>
            <line>That York is most unmeet of any man.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>I'll tell thee, Suffolk, why I am unmeet:</line>
            <line>First, for I cannot flatter thee in pride;</line>
            <line>Next, if I be appointed for the place,</line>
            <line>My Lord of Somerset will keep me here,</line>
            <line>Without discharge, money, or furniture,</line>
            <line>Till France be won into the Dauphin's hands:</line>
            <line>Last time, I danced attendance on his will</line>
            <line>Till Paris was besieged, famish'd, and lost.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>That can I witness; and a fouler fact</line>
            <line>Did never traitor in the land commit.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Peace, headstrong Warwick!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Image of pride, why should I hold my peace?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter HORNER, the Armourer, and his man
PETER, guarded</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Because here is a man accused of treason:</line>
            <line>Pray God the Duke of York excuse himself!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>Doth any one accuse York for a traitor?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>What mean'st thou, Suffolk; tell me, what are these?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Please it your majesty, this is the man</line>
            <line>That doth accuse his master of high treason:</line>
            <line>His words were these: that Richard, Duke of York,</line>
            <line>Was rightful heir unto the English crown</line>
            <line>And that your majesty was a usurper.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Say, man, were these thy words?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HORNER</speaker>
            <line>An't shall please your majesty, I never said nor</line>
            <line>thought any such matter: God is my witness, I am</line>
            <line>falsely accused by the villain.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETER</speaker>
            <line>By these ten bones, my lords, he did speak them to</line>
            <line>me in the garret one night, as we were scouring my</line>
            <line>Lord of York's armour.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>Base dunghill villain and mechanical,</line>
            <line>I'll have thy head for this thy traitor's speech.</line>
            <line>I do beseech your royal majesty,</line>
            <line>Let him have all the rigor of the law.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HORNER</speaker>
            <line>Alas, my lord, hang me, if ever I spake the words.</line>
            <line>My accuser is my 'prentice; and when I did correct</line>
            <line>him for his fault the other day, he did vow upon his</line>
            <line>knees he would be even with me: I have good</line>
            <line>witness of this: therefore I beseech your majesty,</line>
            <line>do not cast away an honest man for a villain's</line>
            <line>accusation.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Uncle, what shall we say to this in law?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>This doom, my lord, if I may judge:</line>
            <line>Let Somerset be regent over the French,</line>
            <line>Because in York this breeds suspicion:</line>
            <line>And let these have a day appointed them</line>
            <line>For single combat in convenient place,</line>
            <line>For he hath witness of his servant's malice:</line>
            <line>This is the law, and this Duke Humphrey's doom.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SOMERSET</speaker>
            <line>I humbly thank your royal majesty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HORNER</speaker>
            <line>And I accept the combat willingly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PETER</speaker>
            <line>Alas, my lord, I cannot fight; for God's sake, pity</line>
            <line>my case. The spite of man prevaileth against me. O</line>
            <line>Lord, have mercy upon me! I shall never be able to</line>
            <line>fight a blow. O Lord, my heart!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Sirrah, or you must fight, or else be hang'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Away with them to prison; and the day of combat</line>
            <line>shall be the last of the next month. Come,</line>
            <line>Somerset, we'll see thee sent away.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Flourish. Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-4">
      <title>SCENE IV.  GLOUCESTER's garden.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter MARGARET JOURDAIN, HUME, SOUTHWELL, and
BOLINGBROKE</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HUME</speaker>
            <line>Come, my masters; the duchess, I tell you, expects</line>
            <line>performance of your promises.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Master Hume, we are therefore provided: will her</line>
            <line>ladyship behold and hear our exorcisms?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HUME</speaker>
            <line>Ay, what else? fear you not her courage.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>I have heard her reported to be a woman of an</line>
            <line>invincible spirit: but it shall be convenient,</line>
            <line>Master Hume, that you be by her aloft, while we be</line>
            <line>busy below; and so, I pray you, go, in God's name,</line>
            <line>and leave us.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit HUME</stagedir>
            <line>Mother Jourdain, be you</line>
            <line>prostrate and grovel on the earth; John Southwell,</line>
            <line>read you; and let us to our work.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter the DUCHESS aloft, HUME following</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS</speaker>
            <line>Well said, my masters; and welcome all. To this</line>
            <line>gear the sooner the better.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Patience, good lady; wizards know their times:</line>
            <line>Deep night, dark night, the silent of the night,</line>
            <line>The time of night when Troy was set on fire;</line>
            <line>The time when screech-owls cry and ban-dogs howl,</line>
            <line>And spirits walk and ghosts break up their graves,</line>
            <line>That time best fits the work we have in hand.</line>
            <line>Madam, sit you and fear not: whom we raise,</line>
            <line>We will make fast within a hallow'd verge.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Here they do the ceremonies belonging, and make the
circle; BOLINGBROKE or SOUTHWELL reads, Conjuro te,
&amp;c. It thunders and lightens terribly; then the
Spirit riseth</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Spirit</speaker>
            <line>Adsum.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARGARET JOURDAIN</speaker>
            <line>Asmath,</line>
            <line>By the eternal God, whose name and power</line>
            <line>Thou tremblest at, answer that I shall ask;</line>
            <line>For, till thou speak, thou shalt not pass from hence.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Spirit</speaker>
            <line>Ask what thou wilt. That I had said and done!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>'First of the king: what shall of him become?'</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Reading out of a paper</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Spirit</speaker>
            <line>The duke yet lives that Henry shall depose;</line>
            <line>But him outlive, and die a violent death.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>As the Spirit speaks, SOUTHWELL writes the answer</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>'What fates await the Duke of Suffolk?'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Spirit</speaker>
            <line>By water shall he die, and take his end.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>'What shall befall the Duke of Somerset?'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Spirit</speaker>
            <line>Let him shun castles;</line>
            <line>Safer shall he be upon the sandy plains</line>
            <line>Than where castles mounted stand.</line>
            <line>Have done, for more I hardly can endure.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOLINGBROKE</speaker>
            <line>Descend to darkness and the burning lake!</line>
            <line>False fiend, avoid!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Thunder and lightning. Exit Spirit</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Enter YORK and BUCKINGHAM with their Guard
and break in</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>Lay hands upon these traitors and their trash.</line>
            <line>Beldam, I think we watch'd you at an inch.</line>
            <line>What, madam, are you there? the king and commonweal</line>
            <line>Are deeply indebted for this piece of pains:</line>
            <line>My lord protector will, I doubt it not,</line>
            <line>See you well guerdon'd for these good deserts.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUCHESS</speaker>
            <line>Not half so bad as thine to England's king,</line>
            <line>Injurious duke, that threatest where's no cause.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>True, madam, none at all: what call you this?</line>
            <line>Away with them! let them be clapp'd up close.</line>
            <line>And kept asunder. You, madam, shall with us.</line>
            <line>Stafford, take her to thee.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt above DUCHESS and HUME, guarded</stagedir>
            <line>We'll see your trinkets here all forthcoming.</line>
            <line>All, away!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt guard with MARGARET JOURDAIN, SOUTHWELL, &amp;c</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>Lord Buckingham, methinks, you watch'd her well:</line>
            <line>A pretty plot, well chosen to build upon!</line>
            <line>Now, pray, my lord, let's see the devil's writ.</line>
            <line>What have we here?</line>
            <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>
            <line>'The duke yet lives, that Henry shall depose;</line>
            <line>But him outlive, and die a violent death.'</line>
            <line>Why, this is just</line>
            <line>'Aio te, AEacida, Romanos vincere posse.'</line>
            <line>Well, to the rest:</line>
            <line>'Tell me what fate awaits the Duke of Suffolk?</line>
            <line>By water shall he die, and take his end.</line>
            <line>What shall betide the Duke of Somerset?</line>
            <line>Let him shun castles;</line>
            <line>Safer shall he be upon the sandy plains</line>
            <line>Than where castles mounted stand.'</line>
            <line>Come, come, my lords;</line>
            <line>These oracles are hardly attain'd,</line>
            <line>And hardly understood.</line>
            <line>The king is now in progress towards Saint Alban's,</line>
            <line>With him the husband of this lovely lady:</line>
            <line>Thither go these news, as fast as horse can</line>
            <line>carry them:</line>
            <line>A sorry breakfast for my lord protector.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Your grace shall give me leave, my Lord of York,</line>
            <line>To be the post, in hope of his reward.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>At your pleasure, my good lord. Who's within</line>
            <line>there, ho!</line>
            <stagedir>Enter a Servingman</stagedir>
            <line>Invite my Lords of Salisbury and Warwick</line>
            <line>To sup with me to-morrow night. Away!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>