<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:shakespear:dtd:act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-3">
   <title>ACT III</title>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  The Abbey at Bury St. Edmund's.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Sound a sennet. Enter KING HENRY VI, QUEEN
MARGARET, CARDINAL, SUFFOLK, YORK, BUCKINGHAM,
SALISBURY and WARWICK to the Parliament</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>I muse my Lord of Gloucester is not come:</line>
            <line>'Tis not his wont to be the hindmost man,</line>
            <line>Whate'er occasion keeps him from us now.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Can you not see? or will ye not observe</line>
            <line>The strangeness of his alter'd countenance?</line>
            <line>With what a majesty he bears himself,</line>
            <line>How insolent of late he is become,</line>
            <line>How proud, how peremptory, and unlike himself?</line>
            <line>We know the time since he was mild and affable,</line>
            <line>And if we did but glance a far-off look,</line>
            <line>Immediately he was upon his knee,</line>
            <line>That all the court admired him for submission:</line>
            <line>But meet him now, and, be it in the morn,</line>
            <line>When every one will give the time of day,</line>
            <line>He knits his brow and shows an angry eye,</line>
            <line>And passeth by with stiff unbowed knee,</line>
            <line>Disdaining duty that to us belongs.</line>
            <line>Small curs are not regarded when they grin;</line>
            <line>But great men tremble when the lion roars;</line>
            <line>And Humphrey is no little man in England.</line>
            <line>First note that he is near you in descent,</line>
            <line>And should you fall, he as the next will mount.</line>
            <line>Me seemeth then it is no policy,</line>
            <line>Respecting what a rancorous mind he bears</line>
            <line>And his advantage following your decease,</line>
            <line>That he should come about your royal person</line>
            <line>Or be admitted to your highness' council.</line>
            <line>By flattery hath he won the commons' hearts,</line>
            <line>And when he please to make commotion,</line>
            <line>'Tis to be fear'd they all will follow him.</line>
            <line>Now 'tis the spring, and weeds are shallow-rooted;</line>
            <line>Suffer them now, and they'll o'ergrow the garden</line>
            <line>And choke the herbs for want of husbandry.</line>
            <line>The reverent care I bear unto my lord</line>
            <line>Made me collect these dangers in the duke.</line>
            <line>If it be fond, call it a woman's fear;</line>
            <line>Which fear if better reasons can supplant,</line>
            <line>I will subscribe and say I wrong'd the duke.</line>
            <line>My Lord of Suffolk, Buckingham, and York,</line>
            <line>Reprove my allegation, if you can;</line>
            <line>Or else conclude my words effectual.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Well hath your highness seen into this duke;</line>
            <line>And, had I first been put to speak my mind,</line>
            <line>I think I should have told your grace's tale.</line>
            <line>The duchess, by his subornation,</line>
            <line>Upon my life, began her devilish practises:</line>
            <line>Or, if he were not privy to those faults,</line>
            <line>Yet, by reputing of his high descent,</line>
            <line>As next the king he was successive heir,</line>
            <line>And such high vaunts of his nobility,</line>
            <line>Did instigate the bedlam brain-sick duchess</line>
            <line>By wicked means to frame our sovereign's fall.</line>
            <line>Smooth runs the water where the brook is deep;</line>
            <line>And in his simple show he harbours treason.</line>
            <line>The fox barks not when he would steal the lamb.</line>
            <line>No, no, my sovereign; Gloucester is a man</line>
            <line>Unsounded yet and full of deep deceit.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL</speaker>
            <line>Did he not, contrary to form of law,</line>
            <line>Devise strange deaths for small offences done?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>And did he not, in his protectorship,</line>
            <line>Levy great sums of money through the realm</line>
            <line>For soldiers' pay in France, and never sent it?</line>
            <line>By means whereof the towns each day revolted.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>Tut, these are petty faults to faults unknown.</line>
            <line>Which time will bring to light in smooth</line>
            <line>Duke Humphrey.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>My lords, at once: the care you have of us,</line>
            <line>To mow down thorns that would annoy our foot,</line>
            <line>Is worthy praise: but, shall I speak my conscience,</line>
            <line>Our kinsman Gloucester is as innocent</line>
            <line>From meaning treason to our royal person</line>
            <line>As is the sucking lamb or harmless dove:</line>
            <line>The duke is virtuous, mild and too well given</line>
            <line>To dream on evil or to work my downfall.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Ah, what's more dangerous than this fond affiance!</line>
            <line>Seems he a dove? his feathers are but borrowed,</line>
            <line>For he's disposed as the hateful raven:</line>
            <line>Is he a lamb? his skin is surely lent him,</line>
            <line>For he's inclined as is the ravenous wolf.</line>
            <line>Who cannot steal a shape that means deceit?</line>
            <line>Take heed, my lord; the welfare of us all</line>
            <line>Hangs on the cutting short that fraudful man.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter SOMERSET</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SOMERSET</speaker>
            <line>All health unto my gracious sovereign!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Welcome, Lord Somerset. What news from France?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SOMERSET</speaker>
            <line>That all your interest in those territories</line>
            <line>Is utterly bereft you; all is lost.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Cold news, Lord Somerset: but God's will be done!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  Cold news for me; for I had hope of France</line>
            <line>As firmly as I hope for fertile England.</line>
            <line>Thus are my blossoms blasted in the bud</line>
            <line>And caterpillars eat my leaves away;</line>
            <line>But I will remedy this gear ere long,</line>
            <line>Or sell my title for a glorious grave.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter GLOUCESTER</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>All happiness unto my lord the king!</line>
            <line>Pardon, my liege, that I have stay'd so long.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Nay, Gloucester, know that thou art come too soon,</line>
            <line>Unless thou wert more loyal than thou art:</line>
            <line>I do arrest thee of high treason here.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Well, Suffolk, thou shalt not see me blush</line>
            <line>Nor change my countenance for this arrest:</line>
            <line>A heart unspotted is not easily daunted.</line>
            <line>The purest spring is not so free from mud</line>
            <line>As I am clear from treason to my sovereign:</line>
            <line>Who can accuse me? wherein am I guilty?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>'Tis thought, my lord, that you took bribes of France,</line>
            <line>And, being protector, stayed the soldiers' pay;</line>
            <line>By means whereof his highness hath lost France.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Is it but thought so? what are they that think it?</line>
            <line>I never robb'd the soldiers of their pay,</line>
            <line>Nor ever had one penny bribe from France.</line>
            <line>So help me God, as I have watch'd the night,</line>
            <line>Ay, night by night, in studying good for England,</line>
            <line>That doit that e'er I wrested from the king,</line>
            <line>Or any groat I hoarded to my use,</line>
            <line>Be brought against me at my trial-day!</line>
            <line>No; many a pound of mine own proper store,</line>
            <line>Because I would not tax the needy commons,</line>
            <line>Have I disbursed to the garrisons,</line>
            <line>And never ask'd for restitution.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL</speaker>
            <line>It serves you well, my lord, to say so much.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>I say no more than truth, so help me God!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>In your protectorship you did devise</line>
            <line>Strange tortures for offenders never heard of,</line>
            <line>That England was defamed by tyranny.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Why, 'tis well known that, whiles I was</line>
            <line>protector,</line>
            <line>Pity was all the fault that was in me;</line>
            <line>For I should melt at an offender's tears,</line>
            <line>And lowly words were ransom for their fault.</line>
            <line>Unless it were a bloody murderer,</line>
            <line>Or foul felonious thief that fleeced poor passengers,</line>
            <line>I never gave them condign punishment:</line>
            <line>Murder indeed, that bloody sin, I tortured</line>
            <line>Above the felon or what trespass else.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>My lord, these faults are easy, quickly answered:</line>
            <line>But mightier crimes are laid unto your charge,</line>
            <line>Whereof you cannot easily purge yourself.</line>
            <line>I do arrest you in his highness' name;</line>
            <line>And here commit you to my lord cardinal</line>
            <line>To keep, until your further time of trial.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>My lord of Gloucester, 'tis my special hope</line>
            <line>That you will clear yourself from all suspect:</line>
            <line>My conscience tells me you are innocent.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Ah, gracious lord, these days are dangerous:</line>
            <line>Virtue is choked with foul ambition</line>
            <line>And charity chased hence by rancour's hand;</line>
            <line>Foul subornation is predominant</line>
            <line>And equity exiled your highness' land.</line>
            <line>I know their complot is to have my life,</line>
            <line>And if my death might make this island happy,</line>
            <line>And prove the period of their tyranny,</line>
            <line>I would expend it with all willingness:</line>
            <line>But mine is made the prologue to their play;</line>
            <line>For thousands more, that yet suspect no peril,</line>
            <line>Will not conclude their plotted tragedy.</line>
            <line>Beaufort's red sparkling eyes blab his heart's malice,</line>
            <line>And Suffolk's cloudy brow his stormy hate;</line>
            <line>Sharp Buckingham unburthens with his tongue</line>
            <line>The envious load that lies upon his heart;</line>
            <line>And dogged York, that reaches at the moon,</line>
            <line>Whose overweening arm I have pluck'd back,</line>
            <line>By false accuse doth level at my life:</line>
            <line>And you, my sovereign lady, with the rest,</line>
            <line>Causeless have laid disgraces on my head,</line>
            <line>And with your best endeavour have stirr'd up</line>
            <line>My liefest liege to be mine enemy:</line>
            <line>Ay, all you have laid your heads together--</line>
            <line>Myself had notice of your conventicles--</line>
            <line>And all to make away my guiltless life.</line>
            <line>I shall not want false witness to condemn me,</line>
            <line>Nor store of treasons to augment my guilt;</line>
            <line>The ancient proverb will be well effected:</line>
            <line>'A staff is quickly found to beat a dog.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL</speaker>
            <line>My liege, his railing is intolerable:</line>
            <line>If those that care to keep your royal person</line>
            <line>From treason's secret knife and traitors' rage</line>
            <line>Be thus upbraided, chid and rated at,</line>
            <line>And the offender granted scope of speech,</line>
            <line>'Twill make them cool in zeal unto your grace.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Hath he not twit our sovereign lady here</line>
            <line>With ignominious words, though clerkly couch'd,</line>
            <line>As if she had suborned some to swear</line>
            <line>False allegations to o'erthrow his state?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>But I can give the loser leave to chide.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Far truer spoke than meant: I lose, indeed;</line>
            <line>Beshrew the winners, for they play'd me false!</line>
            <line>And well such losers may have leave to speak.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BUCKINGHAM</speaker>
            <line>He'll wrest the sense and hold us here all day:</line>
            <line>Lord cardinal, he is your prisoner.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL</speaker>
            <line>Sirs, take away the duke, and guard him sure.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Ah! thus King Henry throws away his crutch</line>
            <line>Before his legs be firm to bear his body.</line>
            <line>Thus is the shepherd beaten from thy side,</line>
            <line>And wolves are gnarling who shall gnaw thee first.</line>
            <line>Ah, that my fear were false! ah, that it were!</line>
            <line>For, good King Henry, thy decay I fear.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit, guarded</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>My lords, what to your wisdoms seemeth best,</line>
            <line>Do or undo, as if ourself were here.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>What, will your highness leave the parliament?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Ay, Margaret; my heart is drown'd with grief,</line>
            <line>Whose flood begins to flow within mine eyes,</line>
            <line>My body round engirt with misery,</line>
            <line>For what's more miserable than discontent?</line>
            <line>Ah, uncle Humphrey! in thy face I see</line>
            <line>The map of honour, truth and loyalty:</line>
            <line>And yet, good Humphrey, is the hour to come</line>
            <line>That e'er I proved thee false or fear'd thy faith.</line>
            <line>What louring star now envies thy estate,</line>
            <line>That these great lords and Margaret our queen</line>
            <line>Do seek subversion of thy harmless life?</line>
            <line>Thou never didst them wrong, nor no man wrong;</line>
            <line>And as the butcher takes away the calf</line>
            <line>And binds the wretch, and beats it when it strays,</line>
            <line>Bearing it to the bloody slaughter-house,</line>
            <line>Even so remorseless have they borne him hence;</line>
            <line>And as the dam runs lowing up and down,</line>
            <line>Looking the way her harmless young one went,</line>
            <line>And can do nought but wail her darling's loss,</line>
            <line>Even so myself bewails good Gloucester's case</line>
            <line>With sad unhelpful tears, and with dimm'd eyes</line>
            <line>Look after him and cannot do him good,</line>
            <line>So mighty are his vowed enemies.</line>
            <line>His fortunes I will weep; and, 'twixt each groan</line>
            <line>Say 'Who's a traitor? Gloucester he is none.'</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt all but QUEEN MARGARET, CARDINAL,
SUFFOLK, and YORK; SOMERSET remains apart</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Free lords, cold snow melts with the sun's hot beams.</line>
            <line>Henry my lord is cold in great affairs,</line>
            <line>Too full of foolish pity, and Gloucester's show</line>
            <line>Beguiles him as the mournful crocodile</line>
            <line>With sorrow snares relenting passengers,</line>
            <line>Or as the snake roll'd in a flowering bank,</line>
            <line>With shining chequer'd slough, doth sting a child</line>
            <line>That for the beauty thinks it excellent.</line>
            <line>Believe me, lords, were none more wise than I--</line>
            <line>And yet herein I judge mine own wit good--</line>
            <line>This Gloucester should be quickly rid the world,</line>
            <line>To rid us of the fear we have of him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL</speaker>
            <line>That he should die is worthy policy;</line>
            <line>But yet we want a colour for his death:</line>
            <line>'Tis meet he be condemn'd by course of law.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>But, in my mind, that were no policy:</line>
            <line>The king will labour still to save his life,</line>
            <line>The commons haply rise, to save his life;</line>
            <line>And yet we have but trivial argument,</line>
            <line>More than mistrust, that shows him worthy death.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>So that, by this, you would not have him die.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Ah, York, no man alive so fain as I!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>'Tis York that hath more reason for his death.</line>
            <line>But, my lord cardinal, and you, my Lord of Suffolk,</line>
            <line>Say as you think, and speak it from your souls,</line>
            <line>Were't not all one, an empty eagle were set</line>
            <line>To guard the chicken from a hungry kite,</line>
            <line>As place Duke Humphrey for the king's protector?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>So the poor chicken should be sure of death.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Madam, 'tis true; and were't not madness, then,</line>
            <line>To make the fox surveyor of the fold?</line>
            <line>Who being accused a crafty murderer,</line>
            <line>His guilt should be but idly posted over,</line>
            <line>Because his purpose is not executed.</line>
            <line>No; let him die, in that he is a fox,</line>
            <line>By nature proved an enemy to the flock,</line>
            <line>Before his chaps be stain'd with crimson blood,</line>
            <line>As Humphrey, proved by reasons, to my liege.</line>
            <line>And do not stand on quillets how to slay him:</line>
            <line>Be it by gins, by snares, by subtlety,</line>
            <line>Sleeping or waking, 'tis no matter how,</line>
            <line>So he be dead; for that is good deceit</line>
            <line>Which mates him first that first intends deceit.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Thrice-noble Suffolk, 'tis resolutely spoke.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Not resolute, except so much were done;</line>
            <line>For things are often spoke and seldom meant:</line>
            <line>But that my heart accordeth with my tongue,</line>
            <line>Seeing the deed is meritorious,</line>
            <line>And to preserve my sovereign from his foe,</line>
            <line>Say but the word, and I will be his priest.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL</speaker>
            <line>But I would have him dead, my Lord of Suffolk,</line>
            <line>Ere you can take due orders for a priest:</line>
            <line>Say you consent and censure well the deed,</line>
            <line>And I'll provide his executioner,</line>
            <line>I tender so the safety of my liege.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Here is my hand, the deed is worthy doing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>And so say I.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>And I    and now we three have spoke it,</line>
            <line>It skills not greatly who impugns our doom.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter a Post</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Post</speaker>
            <line>Great lords, from Ireland am I come amain,</line>
            <line>To signify that rebels there are up</line>
            <line>And put the Englishmen unto the sword:</line>
            <line>Send succors, lords, and stop the rage betime,</line>
            <line>Before the wound do grow uncurable;</line>
            <line>For, being green, there is great hope of help.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL</speaker>
            <line>A breach that craves a quick expedient stop!</line>
            <line>What counsel give you in this weighty cause?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>That Somerset be sent as regent thither:</line>
            <line>'Tis meet that lucky ruler be employ'd;</line>
            <line>Witness the fortune he hath had in France.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SOMERSET</speaker>
            <line>If York, with all his far-fet policy,</line>
            <line>Had been the regent there instead of me,</line>
            <line>He never would have stay'd in France so long.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>No, not to lose it all, as thou hast done:</line>
            <line>I rather would have lost my life betimes</line>
            <line>Than bring a burthen of dishonour home</line>
            <line>By staying there so long till all were lost.</line>
            <line>Show me one scar character'd on thy skin:</line>
            <line>Men's flesh preserved so whole do seldom win.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Nay, then, this spark will prove a raging fire,</line>
            <line>If wind and fuel be brought to feed it with:</line>
            <line>No more, good York; sweet Somerset, be still:</line>
            <line>Thy fortune, York, hadst thou been regent there,</line>
            <line>Might happily have proved far worse than his.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>What, worse than nought? nay, then, a shame take all!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SOMERSET</speaker>
            <line>And, in the number, thee that wishest shame!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL</speaker>
            <line>My Lord of York, try what your fortune is.</line>
            <line>The uncivil kerns of Ireland are in arms</line>
            <line>And temper clay with blood of Englishmen:</line>
            <line>To Ireland will you lead a band of men,</line>
            <line>Collected choicely, from each county some,</line>
            <line>And try your hap against the Irishmen?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>I will, my lord, so please his majesty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Why, our authority is his consent,</line>
            <line>And what we do establish he confirms:</line>
            <line>Then, noble York, take thou this task in hand.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>I am content: provide me soldiers, lords,</line>
            <line>Whiles I take order for mine own affairs.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>A charge, Lord York, that I will see perform'd.</line>
            <line>But now return we to the false Duke Humphrey.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL</speaker>
            <line>No more of him; for I will deal with him</line>
            <line>That henceforth he shall trouble us no more.</line>
            <line>And so break off; the day is almost spent:</line>
            <line>Lord Suffolk, you and I must talk of that event.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>My Lord of Suffolk, within fourteen days</line>
            <line>At Bristol I expect my soldiers;</line>
            <line>For there I'll ship them all for Ireland.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>I'll see it truly done, my Lord of York.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt all but YORK</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>Now, York, or never, steel thy fearful thoughts,</line>
            <line>And change misdoubt to resolution:</line>
            <line>Be that thou hopest to be, or what thou art</line>
            <line>Resign to death; it is not worth the enjoying:</line>
            <line>Let pale-faced fear keep with the mean-born man,</line>
            <line>And find no harbour in a royal heart.</line>
            <line>Faster than spring-time showers comes thought</line>
            <line>on thought,</line>
            <line>And not a thought but thinks on dignity.</line>
            <line>My brain more busy than the labouring spider</line>
            <line>Weaves tedious snares to trap mine enemies.</line>
            <line>Well, nobles, well, 'tis politicly done,</line>
            <line>To send me packing with an host of men:</line>
            <line>I fear me you but warm the starved snake,</line>
            <line>Who, cherish'd in your breasts, will sting</line>
            <line>your hearts.</line>
            <line>'Twas men I lack'd and you will give them me:</line>
            <line>I take it kindly; and yet be well assured</line>
            <line>You put sharp weapons in a madman's hands.</line>
            <line>Whiles I in Ireland nourish a mighty band,</line>
            <line>I will stir up in England some black storm</line>
            <line>Shall blow ten thousand souls to heaven or hell;</line>
            <line>And this fell tempest shall not cease to rage</line>
            <line>Until the golden circuit on my head,</line>
            <line>Like to the glorious sun's transparent beams,</line>
            <line>Do calm the fury of this mad-bred flaw.</line>
            <line>And, for a minister of my intent,</line>
            <line>I have seduced a headstrong Kentishman,</line>
            <line>John Cade of Ashford,</line>
            <line>To make commotion, as full well he can,</line>
            <line>Under the title of John Mortimer.</line>
            <line>In Ireland have I seen this stubborn Cade</line>
            <line>Oppose himself against a troop of kerns,</line>
            <line>And fought so long, till that his thighs with darts</line>
            <line>Were almost like a sharp-quill'd porpentine;</line>
            <line>And, in the end being rescued, I have seen</line>
            <line>Him caper upright like a wild Morisco,</line>
            <line>Shaking the bloody darts as he his bells.</line>
            <line>Full often, like a shag-hair'd crafty kern,</line>
            <line>Hath he conversed with the enemy,</line>
            <line>And undiscover'd come to me again</line>
            <line>And given me notice of their villanies.</line>
            <line>This devil here shall be my substitute;</line>
            <line>For that John Mortimer, which now is dead,</line>
            <line>In face, in gait, in speech, he doth resemble:</line>
            <line>By this I shall perceive the commons' mind,</line>
            <line>How they affect the house and claim of York.</line>
            <line>Say he be taken, rack'd and tortured,</line>
            <line>I know no pain they can inflict upon him</line>
            <line>Will make him say I moved him to those arms.</line>
            <line>Say that he thrive, as 'tis great like he will,</line>
            <line>Why, then from Ireland come I with my strength</line>
            <line>And reap the harvest which that rascal sow'd;</line>
            <line>For Humphrey being dead, as he shall be,</line>
            <line>And Henry put apart, the next for me.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  Bury St. Edmund's. A room of state.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter certain Murderers, hastily</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Murderer</speaker>
            <line>Run to my Lord of Suffolk; let him know</line>
            <line>We have dispatch'd the duke, as he commanded.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Murderer</speaker>
            <line>O that it were to do! What have we done?</line>
            <line>Didst ever hear a man so penitent?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter SUFFOLK</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Murder</speaker>
            <line>Here comes my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Now, sirs, have you dispatch'd this thing?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Murderer</speaker>
            <line>Ay, my good lord, he's dead.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Why, that's well said. Go, get you to my house;</line>
            <line>I will reward you for this venturous deed.</line>
            <line>The king and all the peers are here at hand.</line>
            <line>Have you laid fair the bed? Is all things well,</line>
            <line>According as I gave directions?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Murderer</speaker>
            <line>'Tis, my good lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Away! be gone.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt Murderers</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Sound trumpets. Enter KING HENRY VI, QUEEN
MARGARET, CARDINAL, SOMERSET, with Attendants</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Go, call our uncle to our presence straight;</line>
            <line>Say we intend to try his grace to-day.</line>
            <line>If he be guilty, as 'tis published.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>I'll call him presently, my noble lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Lords, take your places; and, I pray you all,</line>
            <line>Proceed no straiter 'gainst our uncle Gloucester</line>
            <line>Than from true evidence of good esteem</line>
            <line>He be approved in practise culpable.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>God forbid any malice should prevail,</line>
            <line>That faultless may condemn a nobleman!</line>
            <line>Pray God he may acquit him of suspicion!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>I thank thee, Meg; these words content me much.</line>
            <stagedir>Re-enter SUFFOLK</stagedir>
            <line>How now! why look'st thou pale? why tremblest thou?</line>
            <line>Where is our uncle? what's the matter, Suffolk?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Dead in his bed, my lord; Gloucester is dead.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Marry, God forfend!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL</speaker>
            <line>God's secret judgment: I did dream to-night</line>
            <line>The duke was dumb and could not speak a word.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>KING HENRY VI swoons</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>How fares my lord? Help, lords! the king is dead.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SOMERSET</speaker>
            <line>Rear up his body; wring him by the nose.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Run, go, help, help! O Henry, ope thine eyes!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>He doth revive again: madam, be patient.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>O heavenly God!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>How fares my gracious lord?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Comfort, my sovereign! gracious Henry, comfort!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>What, doth my Lord of Suffolk comfort me?</line>
            <line>Came he right now to sing a raven's note,</line>
            <line>Whose dismal tune bereft my vital powers;</line>
            <line>And thinks he that the chirping of a wren,</line>
            <line>By crying comfort from a hollow breast,</line>
            <line>Can chase away the first-conceived sound?</line>
            <line>Hide not thy poison with such sugar'd words;</line>
            <line>Lay not thy hands on me; forbear, I say;</line>
            <line>Their touch affrights me as a serpent's sting.</line>
            <line>Thou baleful messenger, out of my sight!</line>
            <line>Upon thy eye-balls murderous tyranny</line>
            <line>Sits in grim majesty, to fright the world.</line>
            <line>Look not upon me, for thine eyes are wounding:</line>
            <line>Yet do not go away: come, basilisk,</line>
            <line>And kill the innocent gazer with thy sight;</line>
            <line>For in the shade of death I shall find joy;</line>
            <line>In life but double death, now Gloucester's dead.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Why do you rate my Lord of Suffolk thus?</line>
            <line>Although the duke was enemy to him,</line>
            <line>Yet he most Christian-like laments his death:</line>
            <line>And for myself, foe as he was to me,</line>
            <line>Might liquid tears or heart-offending groans</line>
            <line>Or blood-consuming sighs recall his life,</line>
            <line>I would be blind with weeping, sick with groans,</line>
            <line>Look pale as primrose with blood-drinking sighs,</line>
            <line>And all to have the noble duke alive.</line>
            <line>What know I how the world may deem of me?</line>
            <line>For it is known we were but hollow friends:</line>
            <line>It may be judged I made the duke away;</line>
            <line>So shall my name with slander's tongue be wounded,</line>
            <line>And princes' courts be fill'd with my reproach.</line>
            <line>This get I by his death: ay me, unhappy!</line>
            <line>To be a queen, and crown'd with infamy!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Ah, woe is me for Gloucester, wretched man!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Be woe for me, more wretched than he is.</line>
            <line>What, dost thou turn away and hide thy face?</line>
            <line>I am no loathsome leper; look on me.</line>
            <line>What! art thou, like the adder, waxen deaf?</line>
            <line>Be poisonous too and kill thy forlorn queen.</line>
            <line>Is all thy comfort shut in Gloucester's tomb?</line>
            <line>Why, then, dame Margaret was ne'er thy joy.</line>
            <line>Erect his statue and worship it,</line>
            <line>And make my image but an alehouse sign.</line>
            <line>Was I for this nigh wreck'd upon the sea</line>
            <line>And twice by awkward wind from England's bank</line>
            <line>Drove back again unto my native clime?</line>
            <line>What boded this, but well forewarning wind</line>
            <line>Did seem to say 'Seek not a scorpion's nest,</line>
            <line>Nor set no footing on this unkind shore'?</line>
            <line>What did I then, but cursed the gentle gusts</line>
            <line>And he that loosed them forth their brazen caves:</line>
            <line>And bid them blow towards England's blessed shore,</line>
            <line>Or turn our stern upon a dreadful rock</line>
            <line>Yet AEolus would not be a murderer,</line>
            <line>But left that hateful office unto thee:</line>
            <line>The pretty-vaulting sea refused to drown me,</line>
            <line>Knowing that thou wouldst have me drown'd on shore,</line>
            <line>With tears as salt as sea, through thy unkindness:</line>
            <line>The splitting rocks cower'd in the sinking sands</line>
            <line>And would not dash me with their ragged sides,</line>
            <line>Because thy flinty heart, more hard than they,</line>
            <line>Might in thy palace perish Margaret.</line>
            <line>As far as I could ken thy chalky cliffs,</line>
            <line>When from thy shore the tempest beat us back,</line>
            <line>I stood upon the hatches in the storm,</line>
            <line>And when the dusky sky began to rob</line>
            <line>My earnest-gaping sight of thy land's view,</line>
            <line>I took a costly jewel from my neck,</line>
            <line>A heart it was, bound in with diamonds,</line>
            <line>And threw it towards thy land: the sea received it,</line>
            <line>And so I wish'd thy body might my heart:</line>
            <line>And even with this I lost fair England's view</line>
            <line>And bid mine eyes be packing with my heart</line>
            <line>And call'd them blind and dusky spectacles,</line>
            <line>For losing ken of Albion's wished coast.</line>
            <line>How often have I tempted Suffolk's tongue,</line>
            <line>The agent of thy foul inconstancy,</line>
            <line>To sit and witch me, as Ascanius did</line>
            <line>When he to madding Dido would unfold</line>
            <line>His father's acts commenced in burning Troy!</line>
            <line>Am I not witch'd like her? or thou not false like him?</line>
            <line>Ay me, I can no more! die, Margaret!</line>
            <line>For Henry weeps that thou dost live so long.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Noise within. Enter WARWICK, SALISBURY, and many Commons</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>It is reported, mighty sovereign,</line>
            <line>That good Duke Humphrey traitorously is murder'd</line>
            <line>By Suffolk and the Cardinal Beaufort's means.</line>
            <line>The commons, like an angry hive of bees</line>
            <line>That want their leader, scatter up and down</line>
            <line>And care not who they sting in his revenge.</line>
            <line>Myself have calm'd their spleenful mutiny,</line>
            <line>Until they hear the order of his death.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>That he is dead, good Warwick, 'tis too true;</line>
            <line>But how he died God knows, not Henry:</line>
            <line>Enter his chamber, view his breathless corpse,</line>
            <line>And comment then upon his sudden death.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>That shall I do, my liege. Stay, Salisbury,</line>
            <line>With the rude multitude till I return.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>O Thou that judgest all things, stay my thoughts,</line>
            <line>My thoughts, that labour to persuade my soul</line>
            <line>Some violent hands were laid on Humphrey's life!</line>
            <line>If my suspect be false, forgive me, God,</line>
            <line>For judgment only doth belong to thee.</line>
            <line>Fain would I go to chafe his paly lips</line>
            <line>With twenty thousand kisses, and to drain</line>
            <line>Upon his face an ocean of salt tears,</line>
            <line>To tell my love unto his dumb deaf trunk,</line>
            <line>And with my fingers feel his hand unfeeling:</line>
            <line>But all in vain are these mean obsequies;</line>
            <line>And to survey his dead and earthly image,</line>
            <line>What were it but to make my sorrow greater?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter WARWICK and others, bearing
GLOUCESTER'S body on a bed</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Come hither, gracious sovereign, view this body.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>That is to see how deep my grave is made;</line>
            <line>For with his soul fled all my worldly solace,</line>
            <line>For seeing him I see my life in death.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>As surely as my soul intends to live</line>
            <line>With that dread King that took our state upon him</line>
            <line>To free us from his father's wrathful curse,</line>
            <line>I do believe that violent hands were laid</line>
            <line>Upon the life of this thrice-famed duke.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>A dreadful oath, sworn with a solemn tongue!</line>
            <line>What instance gives Lord Warwick for his vow?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>See how the blood is settled in his face.</line>
            <line>Oft have I seen a timely-parted ghost,</line>
            <line>Of ashy semblance, meagre, pale and bloodless,</line>
            <line>Being all descended to the labouring heart;</line>
            <line>Who, in the conflict that it holds with death,</line>
            <line>Attracts the same for aidance 'gainst the enemy;</line>
            <line>Which with the heart there cools and ne'er returneth</line>
            <line>To blush and beautify the cheek again.</line>
            <line>But see, his face is black and full of blood,</line>
            <line>His eye-balls further out than when he lived,</line>
            <line>Staring full ghastly like a strangled man;</line>
            <line>His hair uprear'd, his nostrils stretched with struggling;</line>
            <line>His hands abroad display'd, as one that grasp'd</line>
            <line>And tugg'd for life and was by strength subdued:</line>
            <line>Look, on the sheets his hair you see, is sticking;</line>
            <line>His well-proportion'd beard made rough and rugged,</line>
            <line>Like to the summer's corn by tempest lodged.</line>
            <line>It cannot be but he was murder'd here;</line>
            <line>The least of all these signs were probable.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Why, Warwick, who should do the duke to death?</line>
            <line>Myself and Beaufort had him in protection;</line>
            <line>And we, I hope, sir, are no murderers.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>But both of you were vow'd Duke Humphrey's foes,</line>
            <line>And you, forsooth, had the good duke to keep:</line>
            <line>'Tis like you would not feast him like a friend;</line>
            <line>And 'tis well seen he found an enemy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Then you, belike, suspect these noblemen</line>
            <line>As guilty of Duke Humphrey's timeless death.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Who finds the heifer dead and bleeding fresh</line>
            <line>And sees fast by a butcher with an axe,</line>
            <line>But will suspect 'twas he that made the slaughter?</line>
            <line>Who finds the partridge in the puttock's nest,</line>
            <line>But may imagine how the bird was dead,</line>
            <line>Although the kite soar with unbloodied beak?</line>
            <line>Even so suspicious is this tragedy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Are you the butcher, Suffolk? Where's your knife?</line>
            <line>Is Beaufort term'd a kite? Where are his talons?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>I wear no knife to slaughter sleeping men;</line>
            <line>But here's a vengeful sword, rusted with ease,</line>
            <line>That shall be scoured in his rancorous heart</line>
            <line>That slanders me with murder's crimson badge.</line>
            <line>Say, if thou darest, proud Lord of Warwick-shire,</line>
            <line>That I am faulty in Duke Humphrey's death.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt CARDINAL, SOMERSET, and others</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>What dares not Warwick, if false Suffolk dare him?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>He dares not calm his contumelious spirit</line>
            <line>Nor cease to be an arrogant controller,</line>
            <line>Though Suffolk dare him twenty thousand times.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Madam, be still; with reverence may I say;</line>
            <line>For every word you speak in his behalf</line>
            <line>Is slander to your royal dignity.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Blunt-witted lord, ignoble in demeanor!</line>
            <line>If ever lady wrong'd her lord so much,</line>
            <line>Thy mother took into her blameful bed</line>
            <line>Some stern untutor'd churl, and noble stock</line>
            <line>Was graft with crab-tree slip; whose fruit thou art,</line>
            <line>And never of the Nevils' noble race.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>But that the guilt of murder bucklers thee</line>
            <line>And I should rob the deathsman of his fee,</line>
            <line>Quitting thee thereby of ten thousand shames,</line>
            <line>And that my sovereign's presence makes me mild,</line>
            <line>I would, false murderous coward, on thy knee</line>
            <line>Make thee beg pardon for thy passed speech,</line>
            <line>And say it was thy mother that thou meant'st</line>
            <line>That thou thyself was born in bastardy;</line>
            <line>And after all this fearful homage done,</line>
            <line>Give thee thy hire and send thy soul to hell,</line>
            <line>Pernicious blood-sucker of sleeping men!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Thou shall be waking well I shed thy blood,</line>
            <line>If from this presence thou darest go with me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Away even now, or I will drag thee hence:</line>
            <line>Unworthy though thou art, I'll cope with thee</line>
            <line>And do some service to Duke Humphrey's ghost.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt SUFFOLK and WARWICK</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>What stronger breastplate than a heart untainted!</line>
            <line>Thrice is he armed that hath his quarrel just,</line>
            <line>And he but naked, though lock'd up in steel</line>
            <line>Whose conscience with injustice is corrupted.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>A noise within</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>What noise is this?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter SUFFOLK and WARWICK, with their
weapons drawn</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Why, how now, lords! your wrathful weapons drawn</line>
            <line>Here in our presence! dare you be so bold?</line>
            <line>Why, what tumultuous clamour have we here?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>The traitorous Warwick with the men of Bury</line>
            <line>Set all upon me, mighty sovereign.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALISBURY</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>To the Commons, entering</stagedir>  Sirs, stand apart;</line>
            <line>the king shall know your mind.</line>
            <line>Dread lord, the commons send you word by me,</line>
            <line>Unless Lord Suffolk straight be done to death,</line>
            <line>Or banished fair England's territories,</line>
            <line>They will by violence tear him from your palace</line>
            <line>And torture him with grievous lingering death.</line>
            <line>They say, by him the good Duke Humphrey died;</line>
            <line>They say, in him they fear your highness' death;</line>
            <line>And mere instinct of love and loyalty,</line>
            <line>Free from a stubborn opposite intent,</line>
            <line>As being thought to contradict your liking,</line>
            <line>Makes them thus forward in his banishment.</line>
            <line>They say, in care of your most royal person,</line>
            <line>That if your highness should intend to sleep</line>
            <line>And charge that no man should disturb your rest</line>
            <line>In pain of your dislike or pain of death,</line>
            <line>Yet, notwithstanding such a strait edict,</line>
            <line>Were there a serpent seen, with forked tongue,</line>
            <line>That slily glided towards your majesty,</line>
            <line>It were but necessary you were waked,</line>
            <line>Lest, being suffer'd in that harmful slumber,</line>
            <line>The mortal worm might make the sleep eternal;</line>
            <line>And therefore do they cry, though you forbid,</line>
            <line>That they will guard you, whether you will or no,</line>
            <line>From such fell serpents as false Suffolk is,</line>
            <line>With whose envenomed and fatal sting,</line>
            <line>Your loving uncle, twenty times his worth,</line>
            <line>They say, is shamefully bereft of life.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Commons</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Within</stagedir>  An answer from the king, my</line>
            <line>Lord of Salisbury!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>'Tis like the commons, rude unpolish'd hinds,</line>
            <line>Could send such message to their sovereign:</line>
            <line>But you, my lord, were glad to be employ'd,</line>
            <line>To show how quaint an orator you are:</line>
            <line>But all the honour Salisbury hath won</line>
            <line>Is, that he was the lord ambassador</line>
            <line>Sent from a sort of tinkers to the king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Commons</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Within</stagedir>  An answer from the king, or we will all break in!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Go, Salisbury, and tell them all from me.</line>
            <line>I thank them for their tender loving care;</line>
            <line>And had I not been cited so by them,</line>
            <line>Yet did I purpose as they do entreat;</line>
            <line>For, sure, my thoughts do hourly prophesy</line>
            <line>Mischance unto my state by Suffolk's means:</line>
            <line>And therefore, by His majesty I swear,</line>
            <line>Whose far unworthy deputy I am,</line>
            <line>He shall not breathe infection in this air</line>
            <line>But three days longer, on the pain of death.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit SALISBURY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>O Henry, let me plead for gentle Suffolk!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Ungentle queen, to call him gentle Suffolk!</line>
            <line>No more, I say: if thou dost plead for him,</line>
            <line>Thou wilt but add increase unto my wrath.</line>
            <line>Had I but said, I would have kept my word,</line>
            <line>But when I swear, it is irrevocable.</line>
            <line>If, after three days' space, thou here be'st found</line>
            <line>On any ground that I am ruler of,</line>
            <line>The world shall not be ransom for thy life.</line>
            <line>Come, Warwick, come, good Warwick, go with me;</line>
            <line>I have great matters to impart to thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt all but QUEEN MARGARET and SUFFOLK</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Mischance and sorrow go along with you!</line>
            <line>Heart's discontent and sour affliction</line>
            <line>Be playfellows to keep you company!</line>
            <line>There's two of you; the devil make a third!</line>
            <line>And threefold vengeance tend upon your steps!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Cease, gentle queen, these execrations,</line>
            <line>And let thy Suffolk take his heavy leave.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Fie, coward woman and soft-hearted wretch!</line>
            <line>Hast thou not spirit to curse thine enemy?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>A plague upon them! wherefore should I curse them?</line>
            <line>Would curses kill, as doth the mandrake's groan,</line>
            <line>I would invent as bitter-searching terms,</line>
            <line>As curst, as harsh and horrible to hear,</line>
            <line>Deliver'd strongly through my fixed teeth,</line>
            <line>With full as many signs of deadly hate,</line>
            <line>As lean-faced Envy in her loathsome cave:</line>
            <line>My tongue should stumble in mine earnest words;</line>
            <line>Mine eyes should sparkle like the beaten flint;</line>
            <line>Mine hair be fixed on end, as one distract;</line>
            <line>Ay, every joint should seem to curse and ban:</line>
            <line>And even now my burthen'd heart would break,</line>
            <line>Should I not curse them. Poison be their drink!</line>
            <line>Gall, worse than gall, the daintiest that they taste!</line>
            <line>Their sweetest shade a grove of cypress trees!</line>
            <line>Their chiefest prospect murdering basilisks!</line>
            <line>Their softest touch as smart as lizards' sting!</line>
            <line>Their music frightful as the serpent's hiss,</line>
            <line>And boding screech-owls make the concert full!</line>
            <line>All the foul terrors in dark-seated hell--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Enough, sweet Suffolk; thou torment'st thyself;</line>
            <line>And these dread curses, like the sun 'gainst glass,</line>
            <line>Or like an overcharged gun, recoil,</line>
            <line>And turn the force of them upon thyself.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>You bade me ban, and will you bid me leave?</line>
            <line>Now, by the ground that I am banish'd from,</line>
            <line>Well could I curse away a winter's night,</line>
            <line>Though standing naked on a mountain top,</line>
            <line>Where biting cold would never let grass grow,</line>
            <line>And think it but a minute spent in sport.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>O, let me entreat thee cease. Give me thy hand,</line>
            <line>That I may dew it with my mournful tears;</line>
            <line>Nor let the rain of heaven wet this place,</line>
            <line>To wash away my woful monuments.</line>
            <line>O, could this kiss be printed in thy hand,</line>
            <line>That thou mightst think upon these by the seal,</line>
            <line>Through whom a thousand sighs are breathed for thee!</line>
            <line>So, get thee gone, that I may know my grief;</line>
            <line>'Tis but surmised whiles thou art standing by,</line>
            <line>As one that surfeits thinking on a want.</line>
            <line>I will repeal thee, or, be well assured,</line>
            <line>Adventure to be banished myself:</line>
            <line>And banished I am, if but from thee.</line>
            <line>Go; speak not to me; even now be gone.</line>
            <line>O, go not yet! Even thus two friends condemn'd</line>
            <line>Embrace and kiss and take ten thousand leaves,</line>
            <line>Loather a hundred times to part than die.</line>
            <line>Yet now farewell; and farewell life with thee!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Thus is poor Suffolk ten times banished;</line>
            <line>Once by the king, and three times thrice by thee.</line>
            <line>'Tis not the land I care for, wert thou thence;</line>
            <line>A wilderness is populous enough,</line>
            <line>So Suffolk had thy heavenly company:</line>
            <line>For where thou art, there is the world itself,</line>
            <line>With every several pleasure in the world,</line>
            <line>And where thou art not, desolation.</line>
            <line>I can no more: live thou to joy thy life;</line>
            <line>Myself no joy in nought but that thou livest.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter VAUX</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Wither goes Vaux so fast? what news, I prithee?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VAUX</speaker>
            <line>To signify unto his majesty</line>
            <line>That Cardinal Beaufort is at point of death;</line>
            <line>For suddenly a grievous sickness took him,</line>
            <line>That makes him gasp and stare and catch the air,</line>
            <line>Blaspheming God and cursing men on earth.</line>
            <line>Sometimes he talks as if Duke Humphrey's ghost</line>
            <line>Were by his side; sometime he calls the king,</line>
            <line>And whispers to his pillow, as to him,</line>
            <line>The secrets of his overcharged soul;</line>
            <line>And I am sent to tell his majesty</line>
            <line>That even now he cries aloud for him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Go tell this heavy message to the king.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit VAUX</stagedir>
            <line>Ay me! what is this world! what news are these!</line>
            <line>But wherefore grieve I at an hour's poor loss,</line>
            <line>Omitting Suffolk's exile, my soul's treasure?</line>
            <line>Why only, Suffolk, mourn I not for thee,</line>
            <line>And with the southern clouds contend in tears,</line>
            <line>Theirs for the earth's increase, mine for my sorrows?</line>
            <line>Now get thee hence: the king, thou know'st, is coming;</line>
            <line>If thou be found by me, thou art but dead.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>If I depart from thee, I cannot live;</line>
            <line>And in thy sight to die, what were it else</line>
            <line>But like a pleasant slumber in thy lap?</line>
            <line>Here could I breathe my soul into the air,</line>
            <line>As mild and gentle as the cradle-babe</line>
            <line>Dying with mother's dug between its lips:</line>
            <line>Where, from thy sight, I should be raging mad,</line>
            <line>And cry out for thee to close up mine eyes,</line>
            <line>To have thee with thy lips to stop my mouth;</line>
            <line>So shouldst thou either turn my flying soul,</line>
            <line>Or I should breathe it so into thy body,</line>
            <line>And then it lived in sweet Elysium.</line>
            <line>To die by thee were but to die in jest;</line>
            <line>From thee to die were torture more than death:</line>
            <line>O, let me stay, befall what may befall!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Away! though parting be a fretful corrosive,</line>
            <line>It is applied to a deathful wound.</line>
            <line>To France, sweet Suffolk: let me hear from thee;</line>
            <line>For wheresoe'er thou art in this world's globe,</line>
            <line>I'll have an Iris that shall find thee out.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>I go.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>And take my heart with thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>A jewel, lock'd into the wofull'st cask</line>
            <line>That ever did contain a thing of worth.</line>
            <line>Even as a splitted bark, so sunder we</line>
            <line>This way fall I to death.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>This way for me.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt severally</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  A bedchamber.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter the KING, SALISBURY, WARWICK, to the
CARDINAL in bed</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>How fares my lord? speak, Beaufort, to</line>
            <line>thy sovereign.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL</speaker>
            <line>If thou be'st death, I'll give thee England's treasure,</line>
            <line>Enough to purchase such another island,</line>
            <line>So thou wilt let me live, and feel no pain.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Ah, what a sign it is of evil life,</line>
            <line>Where death's approach is seen so terrible!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Beaufort, it is thy sovereign speaks to thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL</speaker>
            <line>Bring me unto my trial when you will.</line>
            <line>Died he not in his bed? where should he die?</line>
            <line>Can I make men live, whether they will or no?</line>
            <line>O, torture me no more! I will confess.</line>
            <line>Alive again? then show me where he is:</line>
            <line>I'll give a thousand pound to look upon him.</line>
            <line>He hath no eyes, the dust hath blinded them.</line>
            <line>Comb down his hair; look, look! it stands upright,</line>
            <line>Like lime-twigs set to catch my winged soul.</line>
            <line>Give me some drink; and bid the apothecary</line>
            <line>Bring the strong poison that I bought of him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>O thou eternal Mover of the heavens.</line>
            <line>Look with a gentle eye upon this wretch!</line>
            <line>O, beat away the busy meddling fiend</line>
            <line>That lays strong siege unto this wretch's soul.</line>
            <line>And from his bosom purge this black despair!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>See, how the pangs of death do make him grin!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALISBURY</speaker>
            <line>Disturb him not; let him pass peaceably.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Peace to his soul, if God's good pleasure be!</line>
            <line>Lord cardinal, if thou think'st on heaven's bliss,</line>
            <line>Hold up thy hand, make signal of thy hope.</line>
            <line>He dies, and makes no sign. O God, forgive him!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>So bad a death argues a monstrous life.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Forbear to judge, for we are sinners all.</line>
            <line>Close up his eyes and draw the curtain close;</line>
            <line>And let us all to meditation.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>