<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?> 
<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.1 plus MathML 2.0//EN" 
"http://www.w3.org/Math/DTD/mathml2/xhtml-math11-f.dtd" > 
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="fcla-xml-2.30.css"?> 
<html  
xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"  
><head><title>Preface</title> 
<meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=iso-8859-1" /> 
<meta name="generator" content="TeX4ht (http://www.tug.org/tex4ht/)" /> 
<meta name="originator" content="TeX4ht (http://www.tug.org/tex4ht/)" /> 
<!-- html,xhtml,mozilla,3 --> 
<meta name="src" content="fcla-xml-2.30.tex" /> 
<meta name="date" content="2011-12-23 18:20:00" /> 
<link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href="fcla-xml-2.30.css" /> 
</head><body 
>
   <!--l. 324--><div class="crosslinks"><p class="noindent">[<a 
href="fcla-xml-2.30li13.xml" >next</a>] [<a 
href="fcla-xml-2.30li11.xml" >prev</a>] [<a 
href="fcla-xml-2.30li11.xml#tailfcla-xml-2.30li11.xml" >prev-tail</a>] [<a 
href="#tailfcla-xml-2.30li12.xml">tail</a>] [<a 
href="fcla-xml-2.30.xml#fcla-xml-2.30li12.xml" >up</a>] </p></div>
   <h2 class="likechapterHead"><a 
 id="x13-12000"></a>Preface</h2>
<!--l. 11--><p class="noindent" >This textbook is designed to teach the university mathematics student the basics
of linear algebra and the techniques of formal mathematics. There are no
prerequisites other than ordinary algebra, but it is probably best used by a
student who has the &#x201C;mathematical maturity&#x201D; of a sophomore or junior. The text
has two goals: to teach the fundamental concepts and techniques of matrix
algebra and abstract vector spaces, and to teach the techniques associated with
understanding the definitions and theorems forming a coherent area of
mathematics. So there is an emphasis on worked examples of nontrivial size and
on proving theorems carefully.
</p><!--l. 13--><p class="indent" >   This book is copyrighted. This means that governments have granted the
author a monopoly &#x2014; the exclusive right to control the making of copies
and derivative works for many years (too many years in some cases). It
also gives others limited rights, generally referred to as &#x201C;fair use,&#x201D; such
as the right to quote sections in a review without seeking permission.
However, the author licenses this book to anyone under the terms of the
GNU Free Documentation License (GFDL), which gives you more rights
than most copyrights (see <a 
href="fcla-xml-2.30li97.xml#appendix.GFDL">Appendix&#x00A0;GFDL</a>). Loosely speaking, you may
make as many copies as you like at no cost, and you may distribute these
unmodified copies if you please. You may modify the book for your own
use. The catch is that if you make modifications and you distribute the
modified version, or make use of portions in excess of fair use in another
work, then you must also license the new work with the GFDL. So the
book has lots of inherent freedom, and no one is allowed to distribute a
derivative work that restricts these freedoms. (See the license itself in
the appendix for the exact details of the additional rights you have been
given.)
</p><!--l. 15--><p class="indent" >   Notice that initially most people are struck by the notion that this book is
                                                                          

                                                                          
<span 
class="cmbx-12">free </span>(the French would say <span 
class="cmti-12">gratuit</span>, at no cost). And it is. However, it is more
important that the book has <span 
class="cmbx-12">freedom </span>(the French would say <span 
class="cmti-12">libert</span><span 
class="cmti-12">&#x00E9;</span>, liberty). It
will never go &#x201C;out of print&#x201D; nor will there ever be trivial updates designed only to
frustrate the used book market. Those considering teaching a course with this
book can examine it thoroughly in advance. Adding new exercises or new sections
has been purposely made very easy, and the hope is that others will contribute
these modifications back for incorporation into the book, for the benefit of
all.
</p><!--l. 18--><p class="indent" >   Depending on how you received your copy, you may want to check for the
latest version (and other news) at <a 
href="http://linear.ups.edu/" class="url" ><span 
class="cmtt-12">http://linear.ups.edu/</span></a>.
</p>
   <div class="paragraphTOCS">
   </div>
<!--l. 20--><p class="noindent" ><span class="paragraphHead"><a 
 id="x13-13000"></a><span 
class="cmbx-12">Topics</span></span>
   The first half of this text (through <a 
href="fcla-xml-2.30li29.xml#chapter.M">Chapter&#x00A0;M</a>) is basically a course in matrix
algebra, though the foundation of some more advanced ideas is also being formed
in these early sections. Vectors are presented exclusively as column vectors
(since we also have the typographic freedom to avoid writing a column
vector inline as the transpose of a row vector), and linear combinations are
presented very early. Spans, null spaces, column spaces and row spaces are
also presented early, simply as sets, saving most of their vector space
properties for later, so they are familiar objects before being scrutinized
carefully.
</p><!--l. 24--><p class="indent" >   You cannot do <span 
class="cmti-12">everything </span>early, so in particular matrix multiplication comes
later than usual. However, with a definition built on linear combinations of
column vectors, it should seem more natural than the more frequent definition
using dot products of rows with columns. And this delay emphasizes that linear
algebra is built upon vector addition and scalar multiplication. Of course, matrix
inverses must wait for matrix multiplication, but this does not prevent
nonsingular matrices from occurring sooner. Vector space properties are hinted at
when vector and matrix operations are first defined, but the notion of a vector
space is saved for a more axiomatic treatment later (<a 
href="fcla-xml-2.30li36.xml#chapter.VS">Chapter&#x00A0;VS</a>). Once bases
and dimension have been explored in the context of vector spaces, linear
transformations and their matrix representation follow. The goal of the book is to
go as far as Jordan canonical form in the Core (<a 
href="fcla-xml-2.30li14.xml#part.C">Part&#x00A0;C</a>), with less central topics
collected in the Topics (<a 
href="fcla-xml-2.30li98.xml#part.T">Part&#x00A0;T</a>). A third part contains contributed applications
(<a 
href="fcla-xml-2.30li110.xml#part.A">Part&#x00A0;A</a>), with notation and theorems integrated with the earlier two
parts.
                                                                          

                                                                          
</p><!--l. 26--><p class="indent" >   Linear algebra is an ideal subject for the novice mathematics student to learn
how to develop a topic precisely, with all the rigor mathematics requires.
Unfortunately, much of this rigor seems to have escaped the standard calculus
curriculum, so for many university students this is their first exposure
to careful definitions and theorems, and the expectation that they fully
understand them, to say nothing of the expectation that they become
proficient in formulating their own proofs. We have tried to make this
text as helpful as possible with this transition. Every definition is stated
carefully, set apart from the text. Likewise, every theorem is carefully stated,
and almost every one has a complete proof. Theorems usually have just
one conclusion, so they can be referenced precisely later. Definitions and
theorems are cataloged in order of their appearance in the front of the book
(<a 
href="#definition">Definitions</a>, <a 
href="#theorem">Theorems</a>), and alphabetical order in the index at the back. Along
the way, there are discussions of some more important ideas relating to
formulating proofs (<a 
href="fcla-xml-2.30li71.xml#technique">Proof Techniques</a>), which is part advice and part
logic.
</p>
<!--l. 28--><p class="noindent" ><span class="paragraphHead"><a 
 id="x13-14000"></a><span 
class="cmbx-12">Origin and History</span></span>
   This book is the result of the confluence of several related events and trends.
</p>
     <ul class="itemize1">
     <li class="itemize">At the University of Puget Sound we teach a one-semester, post-calculus
     linear algebra course to students majoring in mathematics, computer
     science, physics, chemistry and economics. Between January 1986 and
     June 2002, I taught this course seventeen times. For the Spring 2003
     semester, I elected to convert my course notes to an electronic form so
     that it would be easier to incorporate the inevitable and nearly-constant
     revisions. Central to my new notes was a collection of stock examples
     that would be used repeatedly to illustrate new concepts. (These would
     become the Archetypes, <a 
href="fcla-xml-2.30li72.xml#appendix.A">Appendix&#x00A0;A</a>.) It was only a short leap to then
     decide to distribute copies of these notes and examples to the students
     in the two sections of this course. As the semester wore on, the notes
     began to look less like notes and more like a textbook.
     </li>
                                                                          

                                                                          
     <li class="itemize">I used the notes again in the Fall 2003 semester for a single section of
     the course. Simultaneously, the textbook I was using came out in a fifth
     edition. A new chapter was added toward the start of the book, and a
     few additional exercises were added in other chapters. This demanded
     the annoyance of reworking my notes and list of suggested exercises to
     conform with the changed numbering of the chapters and exercises. I
     had an almost identical experience with the third course I was teaching
     that semester. I also learned that in the next academic year I would be
     teaching a course where my textbook of choice had gone out of print. I
     felt there had to be a better alternative to having the organization of my
     courses buffeted by the economics of traditional textbook publishing.
     </li>
     <li class="itemize">I had used <span class="TEX">T<span 
class="E">E</span>X</span>&#x00A0;and the Internet for many years, so there was little
     to  stand  in  the  way  of  typesetting,  distributing  and  &#x201C;marketing&#x201D;  a
     free  book.  With  recreational  and  professional  interests  in  software
     development, I had long been fascinated by the open-source software
     movement, as exemplified by the success of GNU and Linux, though
     public-domain <span class="TEX">T<span 
class="E">E</span>X</span>&#x00A0;might also deserve mention. Obviously, this book
     is an attempt to carry over that model of creative endeavor to textbook
     publishing.
     </li>
     <li class="itemize">As a sabbatical project during the Spring 2004 semester, I embarked
     on the current project of creating a freely-distributable linear algebra
     textbook.  (Notice  the  implied  financial  support  of  the  University  of
     Puget Sound to this project.) Most of the material was written from
     scratch since changes in notation and approach made much of my notes
     of little use. By August 2004 I had written half the material necessary
     for our Math 232 course. The remaining half was written during the Fall
     2004 semester as I taught another two sections of Math 232.
     </li>
     <li class="itemize">While in early 2005 the book was complete enough to build a course
     around and Version 1.0 was released. Work has continued since, filling
     out the narrative, exercises and supplements.</li></ul>
<!--l. 46--><p class="noindent" >However, much of my motivation for writing this book is captured by the
sentiments expressed by H.M.&#x00A0;Cundy and A.P.&#x00A0;Rollet in their Preface to
                                                                          

                                                                          
the First Edition of <span 
class="cmsl-12">Mathematical Models </span>(1952), especially the final
sentence,
     </p><div class="quote">
     <!--l. 50--><p class="noindent" >This  book  was  born  in  the  classroom,  and  arose  from  the
     spontaneous interest of a Mathematical Sixth in the construction
     of  simple  models.  A  desire  to  show  that  even  in  mathematics
     one  could  have  fun  led  to  an  exhibition  of  the  results  and
     attracted considerable attention throughout the school. Since then
     the Sherborne collection has grown, ideas have come from many
     sources, and widespread interest has been shown. It seems therefore
     desirable to give permanent form to the lessons of experience so
     that others can benefit by them and be encouraged to undertake
     similar work.</p></div>
<!--l. 53--><p class="noindent" ><span class="paragraphHead"><a 
 id="x13-15000"></a><span 
class="cmbx-12">How To Use This Book</span></span>
   Chapters, Theorems, etc.&#x00A0;are not numbered in this book, but are instead
referenced by acronyms. This means that Theorem&#x00A0;XYZ will always be
Theorem&#x00A0;XYZ, no matter if new sections are added, or if an individual decides to
remove certain other sections. Within sections, the subsections are acronyms that
begin with the acronym of the section. So Subsection&#x00A0;XYZ.AB is the subsection
AB in Section&#x00A0;XYZ. Acronyms are unique within their type, so for example there
is just one <a 
href="fcla-xml-2.30li40.xml#definition.B">Definition&#x00A0;B</a>, but there is also a <a 
href="fcla-xml-2.30li40.xml#section.B">Section&#x00A0;B</a>. At first, all the
letters flying around may be confusing, but with time, you will begin to
recognize the more important ones on sight. Furthermore, there are lists of
theorems, examples, etc.&#x00A0;in the front of the book, and an index that
contains every acronym. If you are reading this in an electronic version
(PDF or XML), you will see that all of the cross-references are hyperlinks,
allowing you to click to a definition or example, and then use the back
button to return. In printed versions, you must rely on the page numbers.
However, note that page numbers are not permanent! Different editions,
different margins, or different sized paper will affect what content is on
each page. And in time, the addition of new material will affect the page
numbering.
</p><!--l. 57--><p class="indent" >   Chapter divisions are not critical to the organization of the book, as Sections
are the main organizational unit. Sections are designed to be the subject of
                                                                          

                                                                          
a single lecture or classroom session, though there is frequently more
material than can be discussed and illustrated in a fifty-minute session.
Consequently, the instructor will need to be selective about which topics to
illustrate with other examples and which topics to leave to the student&#x2019;s
reading. Many of the examples are meant to be large, such as using five or
six variables in a system of equations, so the instructor may just want
to &#x201C;walk&#x201D; a class through these examples. The book has been written
with the idea that some may work through it independently, so the hope
is that students can learn some of the more mechanical ideas on their
own.
</p><!--l. 59--><p class="indent" >   The highest level division of the book is the three Parts: Core, Topics,
Applications (<a 
href="fcla-xml-2.30li14.xml#part.C">Part&#x00A0;C</a>, <a 
href="fcla-xml-2.30li98.xml#part.T">Part&#x00A0;T</a>, <a 
href="fcla-xml-2.30li110.xml#part.A">Part&#x00A0;A</a>). The Core is meant to carefully describe
the basic ideas required of a first exposure to linear algebra. In the final sections
of the Core, one should ask the question: which previous Sections could be
removed without destroying the logical development of the subject? Hopefully, the
answer is &#x201C;none.&#x201D; The goal of the book is to finish the Core with a very general
representation of a linear transformation (Jordan canonical form, <a 
href="fcla-xml-2.30li62.xml#section.JCF">Section&#x00A0;JCF</a>).
Of course, there will not be universal agreement on what should, or should
not, constitute the Core, but the main idea is to limit it to about forty
sections. Topics (<a 
href="fcla-xml-2.30li98.xml#part.T">Part&#x00A0;T</a>) is meant to contain those subjects that are
important in linear algebra, and which would make profitable detours from the
Core for those interested in pursuing them. Applications (<a 
href="fcla-xml-2.30li110.xml#part.A">Part&#x00A0;A</a>) should
illustrate the power and widespread applicability of linear algebra to as
many fields as possible. The Archetypes (<a 
href="fcla-xml-2.30li72.xml#appendix.A">Appendix&#x00A0;A</a>) cover many of the
computational aspects of systems of linear equations, matrices and linear
transformations. The student should consult them often, and this is encouraged
by exercises that simply suggest the right properties to examine at the
right time. But what is more important, this a repository that contains
enough variety to provide abundant examples of key theorems, while
also providing counterexamples to hypotheses or converses of theorems.
The summary table at the start of this appendix should be especially
useful.
</p><!--l. 63--><p class="indent" >   I require my students to read each Section <span 
class="cmti-12">prior </span>to the day&#x2019;s discussion on
that section. For some students this is a novel idea, but at the end of the semester
a few always report on the benefits, both for this course and other courses where
they have adopted the habit. To make good on this requirement, each section
contains three Reading Questions. These sometimes only require parroting back a
key definition or theorem, or they require performing a small example of a key
                                                                          

                                                                          
computation, or they ask for musings on key ideas or new relationships
between old ideas. Answers are emailed to me the evening before the lecture.
Given the flavor and purpose of these questions, including solutions seems
foolish.
</p><!--l. 65--><p class="indent" >   Every chapter of <a 
href="fcla-xml-2.30li14.xml#part.C">Part&#x00A0;C</a> ends with &#x201C;Annotated Acronyms&#x201D;, a short list of
critical theorems or definitions from that chapter. There are a variety of
reasons for any one of these to have been chosen, and reading the short
paragraphs after some of these might provide insight into the possibilities. An
end-of-chapter review might usefully incorporate a close reading of these
lists.
</p><!--l. 67--><p class="indent" >   Formulating interesting and effective exercises is as difficult, or more so, than
building a narrative. But it is the place where a student really learns the material.
As such, for the student&#x2019;s benefit, complete solutions should be given. As the list
of exercises expands, the amount with solutions should similarly expand. Exercises
and their solutions are referenced with a section name, followed by a dot, then a
letter (C,M, or T) and a number. The letter &#x2018;C&#x2019; indicates a problem that is mostly
computational in nature, while the letter &#x2018;T&#x2019; indicates a problem that is more
theoretical in nature. A problem with a letter &#x2018;M&#x2019; is somewhere in between
(middle, mid-level, median, middling), probably a mix of computation and
applications of theorems. So <a 
href="fcla-xml-2.30li30.xml#solution.MO.T13">Solution&#x00A0;MO.T13</a> is a solution to an exercise in
<a 
href="fcla-xml-2.30li30.xml#section.MO">Section&#x00A0;MO</a> that is theoretical in nature. The number &#x2018;13&#x2019; has no intrinsic
meaning.
</p>
<!--l. 69--><p class="noindent" ><span class="paragraphHead"><a 
 id="x13-16000"></a><span 
class="cmbx-12">More on Freedom</span></span>
   This book is freely-distributable under the terms of the GFDL, along with the
underlying <span class="TEX">T<span 
class="E">E</span>X</span>&#x00A0;code from which the book is built. This arrangement provides
many benefits unavailable with traditional texts. </p>
     <ul class="itemize1">
     <li class="itemize">No cost, or low cost, to students. With no physical vessel (i.e.&#x00A0;paper,
     binding), no transportation costs (Internet bandwidth being a negligible
     cost) and no marketing costs (evaluation and desk copies are free to all),
     anyone with an Internet connection can obtain it, and a teacher could
     make available paper copies in sufficient quantities for a class. The cost
     to print a copy is not insignificant, but is just a fraction of the cost of
     a traditional textbook when printing is handled by a print-on-demand
                                                                          

                                                                          
     service over the Internet. Students will not feel the need to sell back
     their book (nor should there be much of a market for used copies), and
     in future years can even pick up a newer edition freely.
     </li>
     <li class="itemize">Electronic versions of the book contain extensive hyperlinks. Specifically,
     most logical steps in proofs and examples include links back to the
     previous definitions or theorems that support that step. With whatever
     viewer you might be using (web browser, PDF reader) the &#x201C;back&#x201D; button
     can then return you to the middle of the proof you were studying. So
     even if you are reading a physical copy of this book, you can benefit
     from also working with an electronic version.
     <!--l. 79--><p class="noindent" >A traditional book, which the publisher is unwilling to distribute in an
     easily-copied electronic form, cannot offer this very intuitive and flexible
     approach to learning mathematics.
     </p></li>
     <li class="itemize">The  book  will  not  go  out  of  print.  No  matter  what,  a  teacher  can
     maintain their own copy and use the book for as many years as they
     desire. Further, the naming schemes for chapters, sections, theorems,
     etc.&#x00A0;is designed so that the addition of new material will not break any
     course syllabi or assignment list.
     </li>
     <li class="itemize">With many eyes reading the book and with frequent postings of updates,
     the reliability should become very high. Please report any errors you
     find that persist into the latest version.
     </li>
     <li class="itemize">For those with a working installation of the popular typesetting program
     <span class="TEX">T<span 
class="E">E</span>X</span>, the book has been designed so that it can be customized. Page
     layouts, presence of exercises, solutions, sections or chapters can all be
     easily controlled. Furthermore, many variants of mathematical notation
     are achieved via <span class="TEX">T<span 
class="E">E</span>X</span>&#x00A0;macros. So by changing a single macro, one&#x2019;s
     favorite notation can be reflected throughout the text. For example,
     every transpose of a matrix is coded in the source as <span class="obeylines-h"><span class="verb"><span 
class="cmtt-12">&#x005C;transpose{A}</span></span></span>,
     which when printed will yield <!--l. 85--><math 
 xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="inline" ><msup><mrow 
><mi 
>A</mi></mrow><mrow 
><mi 
>t</mi></mrow></msup 
></math>.
     However by changing the definition of <span class="obeylines-h"><span class="verb"><span 
class="cmtt-12">&#x005C;transpose{</span><span 
class="cmtt-12">&#x00A0;}</span></span></span>, any desired alternative
     notation (superscript t, superscript T, superscript prime) will then appear
                                                                          

                                                                          
     throughout the text instead.
     </li>
     <li class="itemize">The book has also been designed to make it easy for others to contribute
     material. Would you like to see a section on symmetric bilinear forms?
     Consider writing one and contributing it to one of the Topics chapters.
     Should there be more exercises about the null space of a matrix? Send
     me some. Historical Notes? Contact me, and we will see about adding
     those in also.
     </li>
     <li class="itemize">You have no legal obligation to pay for this book. It has been licensed with
     no expectation that you pay for it. You do not even have a moral obligation
     to pay for the book. Thomas Jefferson (1743 &#x2013; 1826), the author of the
     United States Declaration of Independence, wrote,
         <div class="quote">
         <!--l. 92--><p class="noindent" >If nature has made any one thing less susceptible than all others of
         exclusive property, it is the action of the thinking power called an
         idea, which an individual may exclusively possess as long as he keeps
         it to himself; but the moment it is divulged, it forces itself into the
         possession of every one, and the receiver cannot dispossess himself
         of it. Its peculiar character, too, is that no one possesses
         the less, because every other possesses the whole of it. He
         who receives an idea from me, receives instruction himself
         without lessening mine; as he who lights his taper at mine,
         receives light without darkening me. That ideas should freely
         spread from one to another over the globe, for the moral and
         mutual instruction of man, and improvement of his condition,
         seems to have been peculiarly and benevolently designed by
         nature, when she made them, like fire, expansible over all
         space, without lessening their density in any point, and like
         the air in which we breathe, move, and have our physical
         being, incapable of confinement or exclusive appropriation.
         </p>
                                                                      <div class="flushright" 
>
<!--l. 93--><p class="noindent" >
                                                                          

                                                                          
 Letter to Isaac McPherson<br />
August 13, 1813</p></div>
         </div>
     <!--l. 100--><p class="noindent" >However, if you feel a royalty is due the author, or if you would like to
     encourage the author, or if you wish to show others that this approach to
     textbook publishing can also bring financial compensation, then donations
     are gratefully received. Moreover, non-financial forms of help can often be
     even more valuable. A simple note of encouragement, submitting a report of
     an error, or contributing some exercises or perhaps an entire section for the
     Topics or Applications are all important ways you can acknowledge the
     freedoms accorded to this work by the copyright holder and other
     contributors.</p></li></ul>
<!--l. 104--><p class="noindent" ><span class="paragraphHead"><a 
 id="x13-17000"></a><span 
class="cmbx-12">Conclusion</span></span>
   Foremost, I hope that students find their time spent with this book profitable.
I hope that instructors find it flexible enough to fit the needs of their course. And
I hope that everyone will send me their comments and suggestions, and also
consider the myriad ways they can help (as listed on the book&#x2019;s website at
<a 
href="http://linear.ups.edu" class="url" ><span 
class="cmtt-12">http://linear.ups.edu</span></a>). </p>
                                                                          <div class="flushright" 
>
<!--l. 108--><p class="noindent" >
 Robert A.&#x00A0;Beezer<br />
Tacoma, Washington<br />
July 2008</p></div>
<!--l. 324--><div class="crosslinks"><p class="noindent">[<a 
href="fcla-xml-2.30li13.xml" >next</a>] [<a 
href="fcla-xml-2.30li11.xml" >prev</a>] [<a 
href="fcla-xml-2.30li11.xml#tailfcla-xml-2.30li11.xml" >prev-tail</a>] [<a 
href="fcla-xml-2.30li12.xml" >front</a>] [<a 
href="fcla-xml-2.30.xml#fcla-xml-2.30li12.xml" >up</a>] </p></div>
<!--l. 324--><p class="indent" >   <a 
 id="tailfcla-xml-2.30li12.xml"></a>  </p> 
</body> 
</html> 
