<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE learningContent
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Learning Content//EN" "learningContent.dtd">
<learningContent id="SEC007_003">
   <title>7.3 The formation of light nuclei</title>
   <learningContentbody>
      <section>
          
          <p>It is the very high temperatures that make the early stages of the big bang
            relatively simple to calculate. When it comes to the formation of the first nuclei, we
            are looking at a temperature that has dropped to about 10<sup>9</sup> K, this being
            achieved approximately 3 minutes after the instant of the big bang. For nuclei to form,
            the temperature must still be high enough that charged nuclei can approach each other
            closely – despite the electrostatic repulsion between their positive charges
            – thus allowing further fusion to take place. On the other hand, if the
            temperature is too high, any nuclei that are formed will immediately be disrupted again
            by a subsequent violent collision with another particle.</p>
          <p>The only particles taking part (to any significant extent) in the reactions at
            this time were neutrons, protons, electrons, and photons. In addition there were
            neutrinos – a very weakly interacting particle. The simplest reaction, and
            perhaps the most important as far as cosmology is concerned, is the fusion of a neutron
            (n) and a proton (p) to give a deuteron, d (i.e. a deuterium nucleus) plus a photon of
            sufficiently high energy to be called a gamma ray (<ph outputclass="InlineEquation">
               <image href="../../media/gamma.gif"/>
               <ph outputclass="inlineequation-description"/>
            </ph>):</p>
          <fig outputclass="Equation">
            <image href="../../media/S357_1_e021i.gif"/>
            <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
         </fig>
          <p>Note that the energy is mostly carried away by the gamma ray. This is essential
            if the neutron and proton are to bind, for otherwise the neutron and proton would simply
            bounce apart again. The probability of this fusion reaction occurring is high, as is
            that of the reverse reaction, in which a gamma ray destroys a deuteron.</p>
          
          <p>As we have noted, significant numbers of deuterons could form and remain
            undisturbed only after the temperature had dropped to about 10<sup>9</sup> K. On the
            other hand, by the time the temperature had dropped to about
              5 × 10<sup>8</sup> K, at 20 minutes after the big bang, the density had
            become so reduced that there were now no longer sufficient collisions taking place to
            produce many deuterons. Deuteron formation was therefore confined to the period during
            which the temperature fell between these two values.</p>
          <p>More complicated nuclei can be produced by similar reactions. For example,
            helium (<sup>4</sup>He) can be formed through the fusion of two deuterons:</p>
          <fig outputclass="Equation">
            <image href="../../media/S357_1_e016i.gif"/>
            <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
         </fig>
          <p>But there are also several other ways in which it can be formed, each involving
            two steps. For example:</p>
          <fig outputclass="Equation">
            <image href="../../media/S357_1_e017i.gif"/>
            <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
         </fig>
          <fig outputclass="Equation">
            <image href="../../media/S357_1_e018i.gif"/>
            <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
         </fig>
          <p>and</p>
          <fig outputclass="Equation">
            <image href="../../media/S357_1_e019i.gif"/>
            <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
         </fig>
          <fig outputclass="Equation">
            <image href="../../media/S357_1_e020i.gif"/>
            <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
         </fig>
          <p>where <sup>3</sup>H is a tritium nucleus (a triton), i.e. the nuclear isotope
            of hydrogen consisting of a proton and two neutrons.</p>
          <p>Each of the above reactions can occur in either direction. Thus, for example,
            corresponding to Reaction 20 there will be its reverse:</p>
          <fig outputclass="Equation">
            <image href="../../media/S357_1_e020ai.gif"/>
            <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
         </fig>
          <p>Given sufficient time, an equilibrium state would arise whereby the particles
            present will yield the same rate for Reaction 20a as for Reaction 20. And the same will
            apply for each of the other reactions. Thus, corresponding to any particular temperature
            (the temperature governing the reaction rates) it is possible to estimate the
            proportions of the various particles that would be present once equilibrium had been
            established. This estimate is independent of whether equilibrium was reached quickly
            (under conditions of high density where the interactions happen frequently) or slowly
            (under low-density conditions).</p>
          <p>So much for the density-independent equilibrium state achieved over a lengthy
            period of time. But the case of the big bang is different. The matter was rapidly
            dispersed only a short time after the mixture of neutrons and protons had started the
            chain of fusion processes. Under these circumstances, the final abundances of nuclides
            depended on how many collisions were able to take place before the dispersion
            effectively brought the processes to a halt. This in turn means that the final mix of
            particles <i>is</i> expected to depend on the density. More specifically, it is
            encounters with protons and neutrons that are significant, so it is the cosmic density
            of protons, neutrons and matter based on protons and neutrons that is important. This
            particular contribution to the overall density of the Universe is known as the
              <i>baryonic density</i>, since the proton and neutron are the lightest members of a
            family of particles known as <i>baryons</i>.
            We shall
            represent the average mass density of baryonic matter in the Universe as
              <i>ρ</i>
            <sub>b</sub>/<i>c</i>
            <sup>2</sup>, preserving the symbol
              <i>ρ</i>
            <sub>b</sub> for the associated energy density
            of
            baryonic matter. Thus, the baryonic density prevailing at the time of nuclear synthesis
            had an important part to play in governing the relative abundances of the light elements
            formed.</p>
          <p>Roughly speaking, you can think of the baryonic density as the density of
            ‘ordinary’ matter. You are essentially made of baryonic matter as are the
            Earth, the Sun and all familiar objects.</p>
          <p>There is a second reason why the baryonic density was important. It arises from
            the fact that while these fusion reactions were taking place, free neutrons (those that
            had not yet been incorporated into nuclei) were decaying:</p>
          <fig outputclass="Equation">
            <image href="../../media/S357_1_ue008i.gif"/>
            <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
         </fig>
          <p>where <ph outputclass="InlineEquation">
               <image href="../../media/S357_1_ie001i.gif"/>
               <ph outputclass="inlineequation-description"/>
            </ph> is an
            antineutrino.</p>
          <p>Unlike the fusion reactions, the rate for this decay is independent of baryonic
            density. Thus when the baryonic density changes, the balance between the two types of
            reaction changes. At low densities, a neutron travels further before colliding with
            another baryon, so it has a <i>greater</i> chance of decaying before being captured into
            a nucleus. Contrast this with collision reactions which have <i>less</i> probability of
            occurring at low densities. It is these different dependences on density that provide
            the second reason why the final mix of nuclei will depend on the baryonic density during
            the period of nuclear synthesis.</p>
          <p>Now let us take a look at the result of detailed calculations. The rate of each
            reaction depends on the concentrations of the parent nuclei, on experimentally
            determined relationships between the reaction probability and the energies of the
            particles, and on the relationship between the equilibrium distribution of energies and
            the temperature. To find out the net effect of all the reactions is, mathematically,
            simply a matter of solving simultaneous differential equations; but they must be solved
            numerically, and judgement must be exercised in interpolating the experimental data. It
            is a lengthy computer calculation, even though it is basically straightforward. Several
            groups have made these calculations. We show the results of one particular investigation
            in <xref href="#FIG001_028">Figure 31</xref>.</p>
          <p>
            <xref href="#FIG001_028">Figure 31</xref> is based on a model with an assumed value of
            the baryonic density as it is today, <i>ρ</i>
            <sub>b,now</sub>, from which one can
            extrapolate back in time to what it would have been at the time of the primordial
            nuclear synthesis (making due allowance for the expansion of the Universe between those
            two times). The <i>mass fractions</i> of the various nuclei were calculated as a
            function of time. Since the temperature at a given time can be calculated, the
            horizontal scales are marked with temperature (at the top) as well as time elapsed since
            the big bang (at the bottom).</p>
          <fig>
            <title>
              <b>Figure 31</b>: Evolution of nuclear abundances during the expansion of a typical
              model of the big bang. The vertical scale shows what fraction of the total mass the
              various types of nucleus form at different times. Note: H, He, Li and Be stand for the
              nuclei of hydrogen, helium, lithium and beryllium respectively, and the superscript
              indicates the mass of the isotope (e.g. <sup>3</sup>He is the isotope of helium
              containing two protons and one neutron). The deuteron is signified by d, and the
              nucleus of tritium (two neutrons + one proton) by t.</title>
            <image href="../../media/S357_1_028i.jpg"/>
            <p outputclass="SourceReference">Source: from M.S. Smith, L.H. Kawano and R.A. Malaney (1993) <i>The Astrophys.
                J. Supp.</i>, 85, 219–47 <data name="ItemRights">
                  <data name="OwnerRef"/>
                  <data name="ItemRef"/>
                  <data name="ItemAcknowledgement">from M.S. Smith, L.H. Kawano and R.A. Malaney (1993) <i>The
                    Astrophys. J. Supp.</i>, 85, 219–47</data>
              </data>
            </p>
            <p/>
         </fig>
          <p>Look first at the basic particles: neutrons and protons. Initially, at time 1
            second, we have essentially 13% neutrons and 87% protons. This ratio can be calculated
            with confidence as it depends only on the mass difference between neutrons and protons.
            </p>
          <p>As far as we are concerned, the interesting action starts just above
              10<sup>9</sup> K, the temperature at which the proton and neutron numbers begin to
            drop because they are being used up in thermonuclear reactions (similar numbers of
            neutrons and protons are used up – it is only the logarithmic scale that makes
            the drop in the proton curve almost invisible). Some elements, such as helium (both the
            normal <sup>4</sup>He and its isotope <sup>3</sup>He), show no decrease, with the main
            production close to 10<sup>9</sup> K. The deuterium concentration, on the other hand,
            increases rapidly at temperatures around 10<sup>9</sup> K, but later (below
              6 × 10<sup>8</sup> K) the concentration falls a little, because more
            deuterium is being used in making helium than is being synthesised from raw neutrons and
            protons. The point is that at this stage we are dealing with periods of time comparable
            to the mean lifetime of the neutron (930 s, i.e. about 15 minutes). Neutrons are being
            removed by decay – note the steady decline in its curve – and are thus no
            longer available for synthesising deuterons. However, there are still collisions going
            on that are destroying the deuterons. From a cosmologist's point of view, this is the
            crucial stage. The <i>greater</i> the baryonic density of the Universe at that time, the
            longer the process of deuteron destruction can continue after the synthesis of deuterons
            has effectively ceased, and therefore, the <i>lower</i> the final concentration of
            deuterium. It is true that this effect is partly offset by the fact that in a denser
            Universe, more deuterium would have been formed in the first place. But the destruction
            of deuterium is more sensitive to density than is its initial formation.</p>
          
          <p>Below about 4 × 10<sup>8</sup> K, all the nuclide mass fractions
            – apart from the decaying neutrons and tritons, the latter decaying to
              <sup>3</sup>He – are more or less constant because the thermonuclear reactions
            are then so slow. The most important feature of <xref href="#FIG001_028">Figure 31</xref> is the set of ‘freeze-out’
            values of the elemental mass fractions to be found at the extreme right-hand side. This
            set of values corresponds to the particular assumption made about baryonic density. A
            different assumption for the baryonic density now (and hence at earlier times) would
            have led to a different set of curves, and these in turn would be expected to yield a
            different set of freeze-out values.</p>
          
          <sectiondiv outputclass="SAQ">
            <p outputclass="Heading">
               <b>Question 15</b>
            </p>
            <sectiondiv outputclass="saq.question">
              <p>Imagine a universe that differs from ours in that neutrons live twice as
                long, on average, as they do in our Universe, but the Hubble constant and the
                baryonic density have the same values as ours. On the basis of Reactions 15 to 20,
                would inhabitants of that universe expect to find more or less deuterium left over
                from the first 20 minutes of their universe than is left over from the first 20
                minutes of ours?</p>
            </sectiondiv>
            <sectiondiv outputclass="saq.answer">
              <p>Other things being equal, the increase in neutron lifetime will mean that
                more deuterium is formed in the reaction</p>
              <fig outputclass="Equation">
                  <image href="../../media/S357_1_e021i.gif"/>
                  <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
               </fig>
              <p>and more is destroyed in the reaction</p>
              <fig outputclass="Equation">
                  <image href="../../media/S357_1_e022i.gif"/>
                  <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
               </fig>
              <p>eventually producing <sup>4</sup>He in the reaction</p>
              <fig outputclass="Equation">
                  <image href="../../media/S357_1_e023i.gif"/>
                  <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
               </fig>
              <p>In their universe, the increase of neutron lifetime will mean that at any
                point in time there will be more neutrons in their universe than in ours. Moreover,
                the <i>ratio</i> of neutrons in their universe to neutrons in ours will steadily
                increase with time. Thus although at the time when Reaction 15 is important their
                rate of formation of deuterium will be somewhat faster than ours, by the time the
                later Reaction 19 comes into its own their rate of destroying deuterium will be
                greater still in comparison with ours. Thus, deuterium will be formed more readily,
                but <i>destroyed even more readily</i>. The net result will be that they find
                  <i>less</i> deuterium than we do.</p>
            </sectiondiv>
          </sectiondiv>
          <p>
            <xref href="#FIG001_029">Figure 32</xref> shows how the computed freeze-out mass
            fractions of light nuclei depend on the assumed present-day value of the baryonic
            density. As you can see, the freeze-out abundance of <sup>4</sup>He is almost
            independent of the present baryonic density, whereas the freeze-out abundance of
            deuterium <sup>2</sup>H depends very sensitively on <i>ρ</i>
            <sub>b,now</sub>. The
            most abundant nuclide of hydrogen (<sup>1</sup>H) is not shown, but if it had been
            shown, it too would have been relatively insensitive to the present baryonic density,
            its mass fraction being about 0.75.</p>
          <fig>
            <title>
              <b>Figure 32</b>: Predicted freeze-out mass fractions (at around 10<sup>4</sup> s
              after the big bang) for various light nuclei plotted against the assumed present-day
              mass density of baryonic matter,
              <i>ρ</i>
               <sub>b,now</sub>/<i>c</i>
               <sup>2</sup>
            </title>
            <image href="../../media/S357_1_029i.jpg"/>
            <p outputclass="SourceReference">Source: adapted from R.V. Wagoner (1973) <i>The Astrophys. J.</i>, 179(2), 349
                <data name="ItemRights">
                  <data name="OwnerRef"/>
                  <data name="ItemRef"/>
                  <data name="ItemAcknowledgement">adapted from R.V. Wagoner (1973) <i>The Astrophys. J.</i>,
                  179(2), 349</data>
              </data>
            </p>
            <p/>
         </fig>
        </section>
   </learningContentbody>
</learningContent>