<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE learningContent
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Learning Content//EN" "learningContent.dtd">
<learningContent id="SEC009">
   <title>Summary</title>
   <learningContentbody>
      <section>
        
        <p>1 The visible matter in the Universe, stars and interstellar gas, is concentrated
          into galaxies, which are collections of ∼10<sup>11</sup> stars. The galaxies
          themselves are usually to be found in clusters with typically tens or hundreds of members.
          The clusters, in their turn, are loosely associated in superclusters.</p>
        <p>2 Distances are estimated via a series of intercalibrated techniques, each
          overlapping with and extending further than the previous one. The principal stages
          are:</p>
        <ul>
            <li>
               <p>Earth–Moon and Earth–Sun distances involving radar
              ranging;</p>
            </li>
            <li>
               <p>Triangulation to nearer stars, using the diameter of the Earth's orbit as
              baseline;</p>
            </li>
            <li>
               <p>Calibration of luminosity against temperature for typical stars, using the
              stars of the Hyades cluster;</p>
            </li>
            <li>
               <p>Period-luminosity relationship for Cepheids, first for stars in our Galaxy,
              then in other galaxies;</p>
            </li>
            <li>
               <p>Type Ia supernovae, first in nearer, then in further-off galaxies;
              Classification of galaxies into recognisable types, of different
              luminosities.</p>
            </li>
        </ul>
        <p>Independent checks are provided by radio galaxies and observations of Type II
          supernovae.</p>
        <p>3 The spectra of light emitted by the stars of distant galaxies is redshifted,
          such that the redshift, <i>z</i>, is proportional to the distance of the
          galaxy.</p>
        <p>4 This cosmological redshift finds a natural explanation in terms of the galaxies
          receding from us (and from each other), in accordance with Hubble's law. This is the first
          indication that the Universe began with a big bang.</p>
        <p>5 Radio astronomers have detected microwave radiation (i.e. radiation with
          wavelengths in the region of 1 cm) coming almost isotropically from all directions, with a
          thermal spectrum which tallies, as far as can be measured, with that expected from
          calculations based on the big bang model. No convincing alternative explanations have so
          far been advanced. This 3 K radiation therefore provides good evidence both for there
          having been a big bang, and for the isotropy of the Universe at the time when the
          radiation decoupled from matter, 4 × 10<sup>5</sup> years
          later.</p>
        <p>6 If the Earth at present is moving with respect to the 3 K radiation, which we
          assume is the same as the ‘rest frame’ of the Universe at the time of
          decoupling, the angular distribution of the intensity of the radiation would be slightly
          distorted in a characteristic way. Measurements indicate that the Earth <i>does</i> have
          such a velocity, with a magnitude of about 400 km s<sup>−1</sup>.</p>
        <p>7 If galaxies, or clusters of galaxies, had already begun to form at a time
          considerably less than 10<sup>7</sup> years after the big bang, one would have expected
          pre-existent inhomogeneities in the matter distribution to have left a trace of their
          presence by imparting some intensity variation to the angular distribution of the 3 K
          radiation. Such inhomogeneities have now been detected at the level of 1 part in 100
          000.</p>
        <p>8 If there has been a hot big bang, we would expect the material produced to
          consist of 23% by mass of helium, the rest being mostly hydrogen, with traces of other
          light elements.</p>
        <p>9 Detailed comparisons of predicted primordial nuclear mass fractions with those
          deduced from observations also constrain the value of the present-day baryonic mass
          density. A value of 4 or 5 ×10<sup>−28</sup> kg m<sup>−3</sup> fits
          well with both the nuclear abundance data and the data on anisotropies in the cosmic
          microwave background radiation.</p>
        <fig outputclass="Box">
            <p outputclass="Heading">
               <b>Do this</b>
            </p>
            <p>Now you have completed this unit, you might like to:</p>
            <ul>
               <li>
                  <p>Post a message to the unit forum.</p>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <p>Review or add to your Learning Journal.</p>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <p>Rate this unit.</p>
               </li>
            </ul>
        </fig>
        <fig outputclass="Box">
            <p outputclass="Heading">
               <b>Try this</b>
            </p>
            <p>You might also like to:</p>
            <ul>
               <li>
                  <p>Find out more about the related <xref href="http://www3.open.ac.uk/courses/bin/p12.dll?C01S357" scope="external"
                           format="html">Open University course</xref>
                  </p>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <p>Book a FlashMeeting to talk live with other learners</p>
               </li>
               <li>
                  <p>Create a Knowledge Map to summarise this topic.</p>
               </li>
            </ul>
        </fig>
      </section>
   </learningContentbody>
</learningContent>