<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.org:doctypes:dita:concept" "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.org:doctypes:dita:concept">
<concept id="conceptId">
 <title>Generating InCopy Articles from DITA Topics</title>
 <shortdesc>You can directly generate InCopy articles from DITA topics using the
    XSLT transforms in the org.dita4publishers.dita2indesign plugin. You do not
    have to use the Open Toolkit to run the transform.</shortdesc>
  <prolog>
    <metadata>
      <keywords>
        <indexterm>InCopy</indexterm>
      </keywords>
    </metadata>
  </prolog>
 <conbody>
   <p>The <filepath>org.dita4publishers.dita2indesign/xsl</filepath> directory
      holds the XSLT transforms used to generate InCopy articles from topics and
      maps. You can run the transforms directly or run them using the Open
      Toolkit in order to do all necessary DITA preprocessing (conref
      resolution, filtering, etc.). For testing purposes it is usually most
      efficient to run the transforms directly, e.g., in a tool like the oXygen
      XML editor.</p>
    <p>The transforms can generate either the old INCX format or the newer ICML
      format. For use with InDesign CS5 and newer you must generate the ICML
      format. For InDesign CS3 and CS4 you must use the INCX format. The INCX
      format is essentially obsolete and that form of the transforms is not
      being actively maintained. This discussion only describes generating ICML
      InCopy articles.</p>
    <p>The root transform is <filepath>topic2articleIcml.xsl</filepath>. Here
      the term "article" means "InCopy article" as opposed to "magazine
      article". This transform manages the generation of one or more InCopy
      articles from the input topic. The direct output of the transform is an
      XML manifest file that lists all the InCopy articles generated. The
      manifest is designed primarily to support the use of the transform from
      Java code where the Java code needs to know about all the generated InCopy
      articles. </p>
    <p>The core ICML generation is done by the
      <filepath>topic2icmlImpl.xsl</filepath> transform. It's processing a
      little convoluted because of the need to generate all result documents
      before generating the manifest. It uses the file
      <filepath>elem2styleMapperIcml.xsl</filepath> as the default
      element-to-style mapping module. Use this module as the model for your own
      custom mapping.</p>
    <p>By default each input topic results in one InCopy article, reflecting the
      element-to-style mapping defined in the elem2styleMapperIcml.xsl module.
      However, you can extend the base transform to generate multiple InCopy
      articles from a single input topic. You would need to do this for any
      content that needs to be placed in its own disconnected frame, such as
      figures, sidebars, pull quotes, and so on.</p>
    <p>TBD: Provide sample transform that does this.</p>
    <p>TBD: Document general pattern for creating a custom InCopy generation
      transform</p>
    <p>TBD: How to set up the Toolkit-based transform</p>
    <p>TBD: Processing a map and its topics</p>
 </conbody>
</concept>
