<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE learningContent
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Learning Content//EN" "learningContent.dtd">
<learningContent id="SEC001_006">
   <title>1.6 Significant figures for numbers less than one</title>
   <learningContentbody>
      <section>
          
          <p>You can use the same procedure for numbers less than one.</p>
          <sectiondiv outputclass="Example">
            <p outputclass="Heading">
               <b>Example 4</b>
            </p>
            <p>In scientific work people deal with very small units of measurement. Suppose
              you read that the spacing between adjacent atoms in a solid was 0.000 002 456 84
              metres. You could make the number more memorable by using two significant figure
              accuracy.</p>
            <sectiondiv outputclass="Answer">
               <p outputclass="SubHeading">
                  <b>Solution</b>
               </p>
              <p>To find 0.000 002 456 84 metres correct to two significant figures, count
                from the first non-zero digit on the left. The first significant digit in this
                number is the 2. The zeros to the left of this digit are not significant but they
                maintain the place value of the other digits. The second significant digit is the 4
                and to the right of this digit is a 5 which means round up to give 0.000 0025 metres
                (2 s.f.).</p>
            </sectiondiv>
          </sectiondiv>
          <p>You may have noticed that the word ‘significant’ has a more precise meaning in
            mathematics than when used in everyday language and that sometimes zeros are not counted
            as significant figures, even though they are obviously important in specifying the place
            value of a digit.</p>
          <p>At the beginning of <xref href="#SEC001_005">Section 1.5</xref> there was a £600 estimate for the cost of
            fencing. The zeros are necessary to indicate that the 6 represents six hundreds, rather
            than six tens or six units, but the fact that they are zeros (rather than another digit)
            is not significant (in the exact cost, it is unlikely that both would be zero). However
            if an exact calculation gives a cost of £609, then the zero is significant. (To tell you
            it is six hundred, zero tens and nine units.) This is a price quoted to three
            significant figures.</p>
          <p>For decimal numbers like 0.060 09 metres, the zeros to the left of the 6 are
            not considered significant (although they are important to indicate the place value),
            but those to the right are significant.</p>
          
        </section>
   </learningContentbody>
</learningContent>