<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net/doctypes/dita/shakespear/dtd/act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-1">
   <title>ACT I</title>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  Westminster Abbey.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Dead March. Enter the Funeral of KING HENRY the
Fifth, attended on by Dukes of BEDFORD, Regent of
France; GLOUCESTER, Protector; and EXETER, Earl of
WARWICK, the BISHOP OF WINCHESTER, Heralds, &amp;c</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEDFORD</speaker>
            <line>Hung be the heavens with black, yield day to night!</line>
            <line>Comets, importing change of times and states,</line>
            <line>Brandish your crystal tresses in the sky,</line>
            <line>And with them scourge the bad revolting stars</line>
            <line>That have consented unto Henry's death!</line>
            <line>King Henry the Fifth, too famous to live long!</line>
            <line>England ne'er lost a king of so much worth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>England ne'er had a king until his time.</line>
            <line>Virtue he had, deserving to command:</line>
            <line>His brandish'd sword did blind men with his beams:</line>
            <line>His arms spread wider than a dragon's wings;</line>
            <line>His sparking eyes, replete with wrathful fire,</line>
            <line>More dazzled and drove back his enemies</line>
            <line>Than mid-day sun fierce bent against their faces.</line>
            <line>What should I say? his deeds exceed all speech:</line>
            <line>He ne'er lift up his hand but conquered.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EXETER</speaker>
            <line>We mourn in black: why mourn we not in blood?</line>
            <line>Henry is dead and never shall revive:</line>
            <line>Upon a wooden coffin we attend,</line>
            <line>And death's dishonourable victory</line>
            <line>We with our stately presence glorify,</line>
            <line>Like captives bound to a triumphant car.</line>
            <line>What! shall we curse the planets of mishap</line>
            <line>That plotted thus our glory's overthrow?</line>
            <line>Or shall we think the subtle-witted French</line>
            <line>Conjurers and sorcerers, that afraid of him</line>
            <line>By magic verses have contrived his end?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BISHOP OF WINCHESTER</speaker>
            <line>He was a king bless'd of the King of kings.</line>
            <line>Unto the French the dreadful judgement-day</line>
            <line>So dreadful will not be as was his sight.</line>
            <line>The battles of the Lord of hosts he fought:</line>
            <line>The church's prayers made him so prosperous.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>The church! where is it? Had not churchmen pray'd,</line>
            <line>His thread of life had not so soon decay'd:</line>
            <line>None do you like but an effeminate prince,</line>
            <line>Whom, like a school-boy, you may over-awe.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BISHOP OF WINCHESTER</speaker>
            <line>Gloucester, whate'er we like, thou art protector</line>
            <line>And lookest to command the prince and realm.</line>
            <line>Thy wife is proud; she holdeth thee in awe,</line>
            <line>More than God or religious churchmen may.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Name not religion, for thou lovest the flesh,</line>
            <line>And ne'er throughout the year to church thou go'st</line>
            <line>Except it be to pray against thy foes.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEDFORD</speaker>
            <line>Cease, cease these jars and rest your minds in peace:</line>
            <line>Let's to the altar: heralds, wait on us:</line>
            <line>Instead of gold, we'll offer up our arms:</line>
            <line>Since arms avail not now that Henry's dead.</line>
            <line>Posterity, await for wretched years,</line>
            <line>When at their mothers' moist eyes babes shall suck,</line>
            <line>Our isle be made a nourish of salt tears,</line>
            <line>And none but women left to wail the dead.</line>
            <line>Henry the Fifth, thy ghost I invocate:</line>
            <line>Prosper this realm, keep it from civil broils,</line>
            <line>Combat with adverse planets in the heavens!</line>
            <line>A far more glorious star thy soul will make</line>
            <line>Than Julius Caesar or bright--</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter a Messenger</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>My honourable lords, health to you all!</line>
            <line>Sad tidings bring I to you out of France,</line>
            <line>Of loss, of slaughter and discomfiture:</line>
            <line>Guienne, Champagne, Rheims, Orleans,</line>
            <line>Paris, Guysors, Poictiers, are all quite lost.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEDFORD</speaker>
            <line>What say'st thou, man, before dead Henry's corse?</line>
            <line>Speak softly, or the loss of those great towns</line>
            <line>Will make him burst his lead and rise from death.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Is Paris lost? is Rouen yielded up?</line>
            <line>If Henry were recall'd to life again,</line>
            <line>These news would cause him once more yield the ghost.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EXETER</speaker>
            <line>How were they lost? what treachery was used?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>No treachery; but want of men and money.</line>
            <line>Amongst the soldiers this is muttered,</line>
            <line>That here you maintain several factions,</line>
            <line>And whilst a field should be dispatch'd and fought,</line>
            <line>You are disputing of your generals:</line>
            <line>One would have lingering wars with little cost;</line>
            <line>Another would fly swift, but wanteth wings;</line>
            <line>A third thinks, without expense at all,</line>
            <line>By guileful fair words peace may be obtain'd.</line>
            <line>Awake, awake, English nobility!</line>
            <line>Let not sloth dim your horrors new-begot:</line>
            <line>Cropp'd are the flower-de-luces in your arms;</line>
            <line>Of England's coat one half is cut away.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EXETER</speaker>
            <line>Were our tears wanting to this funeral,</line>
            <line>These tidings would call forth their flowing tides.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEDFORD</speaker>
            <line>Me they concern; Regent I am of France.</line>
            <line>Give me my steeled coat. I'll fight for France.</line>
            <line>Away with these disgraceful wailing robes!</line>
            <line>Wounds will I lend the French instead of eyes,</line>
            <line>To weep their intermissive miseries.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter to them another Messenger</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>Lords, view these letters full of bad mischance.</line>
            <line>France is revolted from the English quite,</line>
            <line>Except some petty towns of no import:</line>
            <line>The Dauphin Charles is crowned king of Rheims;</line>
            <line>The Bastard of Orleans with him is join'd;</line>
            <line>Reignier, Duke of Anjou, doth take his part;</line>
            <line>The Duke of Alencon flieth to his side.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EXETER</speaker>
            <line>The Dauphin crowned king! all fly to him!</line>
            <line>O, whither shall we fly from this reproach?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>We will not fly, but to our enemies' throats.</line>
            <line>Bedford, if thou be slack, I'll fight it out.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEDFORD</speaker>
            <line>Gloucester, why doubt'st thou of my forwardness?</line>
            <line>An army have I muster'd in my thoughts,</line>
            <line>Wherewith already France is overrun.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter another Messenger</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>My gracious lords, to add to your laments,</line>
            <line>Wherewith you now bedew King Henry's hearse,</line>
            <line>I must inform you of a dismal fight</line>
            <line>Betwixt the stout Lord Talbot and the French.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BISHOP OF WINCHESTER</speaker>
            <line>What! wherein Talbot overcame? is't so?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>O, no; wherein Lord Talbot was o'erthrown:</line>
            <line>The circumstance I'll tell you more at large.</line>
            <line>The tenth of August last this dreadful lord,</line>
            <line>Retiring from the siege of Orleans,</line>
            <line>Having full scarce six thousand in his troop.</line>
            <line>By three and twenty thousand of the French</line>
            <line>Was round encompassed and set upon.</line>
            <line>No leisure had he to enrank his men;</line>
            <line>He wanted pikes to set before his archers;</line>
            <line>Instead whereof sharp stakes pluck'd out of hedges</line>
            <line>They pitched in the ground confusedly,</line>
            <line>To keep the horsemen off from breaking in.</line>
            <line>More than three hours the fight continued;</line>
            <line>Where valiant Talbot above human thought</line>
            <line>Enacted wonders with his sword and lance:</line>
            <line>Hundreds he sent to hell, and none durst stand him;</line>
            <line>Here, there, and every where, enraged he flew:</line>
            <line>The French exclaim'd, the devil was in arms;</line>
            <line>All the whole army stood agazed on him:</line>
            <line>His soldiers spying his undaunted spirit</line>
            <line>A Talbot! a Talbot! cried out amain</line>
            <line>And rush'd into the bowels of the battle.</line>
            <line>Here had the conquest fully been seal'd up,</line>
            <line>If Sir John Fastolfe had not play'd the coward:</line>
            <line>He, being in the vaward, placed behind</line>
            <line>With purpose to relieve and follow them,</line>
            <line>Cowardly fled, not having struck one stroke.</line>
            <line>Hence grew the general wreck and massacre;</line>
            <line>Enclosed were they with their enemies:</line>
            <line>A base Walloon, to win the Dauphin's grace,</line>
            <line>Thrust Talbot with a spear into the back,</line>
            <line>Whom all France with their chief assembled strength</line>
            <line>Durst not presume to look once in the face.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEDFORD</speaker>
            <line>Is Talbot slain? then I will slay myself,</line>
            <line>For living idly here in pomp and ease,</line>
            <line>Whilst such a worthy leader, wanting aid,</line>
            <line>Unto his dastard foemen is betray'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>O no, he lives; but is took prisoner,</line>
            <line>And Lord Scales with him and Lord Hungerford:</line>
            <line>Most of the rest slaughter'd or took likewise.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEDFORD</speaker>
            <line>His ransom there is none but I shall pay:</line>
            <line>I'll hale the Dauphin headlong from his throne:</line>
            <line>His crown shall be the ransom of my friend;</line>
            <line>Four of their lords I'll change for one of ours.</line>
            <line>Farewell, my masters; to my task will I;</line>
            <line>Bonfires in France forthwith I am to make,</line>
            <line>To keep our great Saint George's feast withal:</line>
            <line>Ten thousand soldiers with me I will take,</line>
            <line>Whose bloody deeds shall make all Europe quake.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>So you had need; for Orleans is besieged;</line>
            <line>The English army is grown weak and faint:</line>
            <line>The Earl of Salisbury craveth supply,</line>
            <line>And hardly keeps his men from mutiny,</line>
            <line>Since they, so few, watch such a multitude.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EXETER</speaker>
            <line>Remember, lords, your oaths to Henry sworn,</line>
            <line>Either to quell the Dauphin utterly,</line>
            <line>Or bring him in obedience to your yoke.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEDFORD</speaker>
            <line>I do remember it; and here take my leave,</line>
            <line>To go about my preparation.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>I'll to the Tower with all the haste I can,</line>
            <line>To view the artillery and munition;</line>
            <line>And then I will proclaim young Henry king.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EXETER</speaker>
            <line>To Eltham will I, where the young king is,</line>
            <line>Being ordain'd his special governor,</line>
            <line>And for his safety there I'll best devise.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BISHOP OF WINCHESTER</speaker>
            <line>Each hath his place and function to attend:</line>
            <line>I am left out; for me nothing remains.</line>
            <line>But long I will not be Jack out of office:</line>
            <line>The king from Eltham I intend to steal</line>
            <line>And sit at chiefest stern of public weal.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  France. Before Orleans.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Sound a flourish. Enter CHARLES, ALENCON, and
REIGNIER, marching with drum and Soldiers</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHARLES</speaker>
            <line>Mars his true moving, even as in the heavens</line>
            <line>So in the earth, to this day is not known:</line>
            <line>Late did he shine upon the English side;</line>
            <line>Now we are victors; upon us he smiles.</line>
            <line>What towns of any moment but we have?</line>
            <line>At pleasure here we lie near Orleans;</line>
            <line>Otherwhiles the famish'd English, like pale ghosts,</line>
            <line>Faintly besiege us one hour in a month.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALENCON</speaker>
            <line>They want their porridge and their fat bull-beeves:</line>
            <line>Either they must be dieted like mules</line>
            <line>And have their provender tied to their mouths</line>
            <line>Or piteous they will look, like drowned mice.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>REIGNIER</speaker>
            <line>Let's raise the siege: why live we idly here?</line>
            <line>Talbot is taken, whom we wont to fear:</line>
            <line>Remaineth none but mad-brain'd Salisbury;</line>
            <line>And he may well in fretting spend his gall,</line>
            <line>Nor men nor money hath he to make war.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHARLES</speaker>
            <line>Sound, sound alarum! we will rush on them.</line>
            <line>Now for the honour of the forlorn French!</line>
            <line>Him I forgive my death that killeth me</line>
            <line>When he sees me go back one foot or fly.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Here alarum; they are beaten back by the English
with great loss. Re-enter CHARLES, ALENCON, and REIGNIER</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHARLES</speaker>
            <line>Who ever saw the like? what men have I!</line>
            <line>Dogs! cowards! dastards! I would ne'er have fled,</line>
            <line>But that they left me 'midst my enemies.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>REIGNIER</speaker>
            <line>Salisbury is a desperate homicide;</line>
            <line>He fighteth as one weary of his life.</line>
            <line>The other lords, like lions wanting food,</line>
            <line>Do rush upon us as their hungry prey.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALENCON</speaker>
            <line>Froissart, a countryman of ours, records,</line>
            <line>England all Olivers and Rowlands bred,</line>
            <line>During the time Edward the Third did reign.</line>
            <line>More truly now may this be verified;</line>
            <line>For none but Samsons and Goliases</line>
            <line>It sendeth forth to skirmish. One to ten!</line>
            <line>Lean, raw-boned rascals! who would e'er suppose</line>
            <line>They had such courage and audacity?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHARLES</speaker>
            <line>Let's leave this town; for they are hare-brain'd slaves,</line>
            <line>And hunger will enforce them to be more eager:</line>
            <line>Of old I know them; rather with their teeth</line>
            <line>The walls they'll tear down than forsake the siege.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>REIGNIER</speaker>
            <line>I think, by some odd gimmors or device</line>
            <line>Their arms are set like clocks, stiff to strike on;</line>
            <line>Else ne'er could they hold out so as they do.</line>
            <line>By my consent, we'll even let them alone.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALENCON</speaker>
            <line>Be it so.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter the BASTARD OF ORLEANS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD OF ORLEANS</speaker>
            <line>Where's the Prince Dauphin? I have news for him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHARLES</speaker>
            <line>Bastard of Orleans, thrice welcome to us.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD OF ORLEANS</speaker>
            <line>Methinks your looks are sad, your cheer appall'd:</line>
            <line>Hath the late overthrow wrought this offence?</line>
            <line>Be not dismay'd, for succor is at hand:</line>
            <line>A holy maid hither with me I bring,</line>
            <line>Which by a vision sent to her from heaven</line>
            <line>Ordained is to raise this tedious siege</line>
            <line>And drive the English forth the bounds of France.</line>
            <line>The spirit of deep prophecy she hath,</line>
            <line>Exceeding the nine sibyls of old Rome:</line>
            <line>What's past and what's to come she can descry.</line>
            <line>Speak, shall I call her in? Believe my words,</line>
            <line>For they are certain and unfallible.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHARLES</speaker>
            <line>Go, call her in.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit BASTARD OF ORLEANS</stagedir>
            <line>But first, to try her skill,</line>
            <line>Reignier, stand thou as Dauphin in my place:</line>
            <line>Question her proudly; let thy looks be stern:</line>
            <line>By this means shall we sound what skill she hath.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter the BASTARD OF ORLEANS, with JOAN LA PUCELLE</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>REIGNIER</speaker>
            <line>Fair maid, is't thou wilt do these wondrous feats?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOAN LA PUCELLE</speaker>
            <line>Reignier, is't thou that thinkest to beguile me?</line>
            <line>Where is the Dauphin? Come, come from behind;</line>
            <line>I know thee well, though never seen before.</line>
            <line>Be not amazed, there's nothing hid from me:</line>
            <line>In private will I talk with thee apart.</line>
            <line>Stand back, you lords, and give us leave awhile.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>REIGNIER</speaker>
            <line>She takes upon her bravely at first dash.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOAN LA PUCELLE</speaker>
            <line>Dauphin, I am by birth a shepherd's daughter,</line>
            <line>My wit untrain'd in any kind of art.</line>
            <line>Heaven and our Lady gracious hath it pleased</line>
            <line>To shine on my contemptible estate:</line>
            <line>Lo, whilst I waited on my tender lambs,</line>
            <line>And to sun's parching heat display'd my cheeks,</line>
            <line>God's mother deigned to appear to me</line>
            <line>And in a vision full of majesty</line>
            <line>Will'd me to leave my base vocation</line>
            <line>And free my country from calamity:</line>
            <line>Her aid she promised and assured success:</line>
            <line>In complete glory she reveal'd herself;</line>
            <line>And, whereas I was black and swart before,</line>
            <line>With those clear rays which she infused on me</line>
            <line>That beauty am I bless'd with which you see.</line>
            <line>Ask me what question thou canst possible,</line>
            <line>And I will answer unpremeditated:</line>
            <line>My courage try by combat, if thou darest,</line>
            <line>And thou shalt find that I exceed my sex.</line>
            <line>Resolve on this, thou shalt be fortunate,</line>
            <line>If thou receive me for thy warlike mate.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHARLES</speaker>
            <line>Thou hast astonish'd me with thy high terms:</line>
            <line>Only this proof I'll of thy valour make,</line>
            <line>In single combat thou shalt buckle with me,</line>
            <line>And if thou vanquishest, thy words are true;</line>
            <line>Otherwise I renounce all confidence.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOAN LA PUCELLE</speaker>
            <line>I am prepared: here is my keen-edged sword,</line>
            <line>Deck'd with five flower-de-luces on each side;</line>
            <line>The which at Touraine, in Saint Katharine's</line>
            <line>churchyard,</line>
            <line>Out of a great deal of old iron I chose forth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHARLES</speaker>
            <line>Then come, o' God's name; I fear no woman.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOAN LA PUCELLE</speaker>
            <line>And while I live, I'll ne'er fly from a man.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Here they fight, and JOAN LA PUCELLE overcomes</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHARLES</speaker>
            <line>Stay, stay thy hands! thou art an Amazon</line>
            <line>And fightest with the sword of Deborah.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOAN LA PUCELLE</speaker>
            <line>Christ's mother helps me, else I were too weak.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHARLES</speaker>
            <line>Whoe'er helps thee, 'tis thou that must help me:</line>
            <line>Impatiently I burn with thy desire;</line>
            <line>My heart and hands thou hast at once subdued.</line>
            <line>Excellent Pucelle, if thy name be so,</line>
            <line>Let me thy servant and not sovereign be:</line>
            <line>'Tis the French Dauphin sueth to thee thus.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOAN LA PUCELLE</speaker>
            <line>I must not yield to any rites of love,</line>
            <line>For my profession's sacred from above:</line>
            <line>When I have chased all thy foes from hence,</line>
            <line>Then will I think upon a recompense.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHARLES</speaker>
            <line>Meantime look gracious on thy prostrate thrall.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>REIGNIER</speaker>
            <line>My lord, methinks, is very long in talk.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALENCON</speaker>
            <line>Doubtless he shrives this woman to her smock;</line>
            <line>Else ne'er could he so long protract his speech.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>REIGNIER</speaker>
            <line>Shall we disturb him, since he keeps no mean?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALENCON</speaker>
            <line>He may mean more than we poor men do know:</line>
            <line>These women are shrewd tempters with their tongues.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>REIGNIER</speaker>
            <line>My lord, where are you? what devise you on?</line>
            <line>Shall we give over Orleans, or no?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOAN LA PUCELLE</speaker>
            <line>Why, no, I say, distrustful recreants!</line>
            <line>Fight till the last gasp; I will be your guard.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHARLES</speaker>
            <line>What she says I'll confirm: we'll fight it out.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOAN LA PUCELLE</speaker>
            <line>Assign'd am I to be the English scourge.</line>
            <line>This night the siege assuredly I'll raise:</line>
            <line>Expect Saint Martin's summer, halcyon days,</line>
            <line>Since I have entered into these wars.</line>
            <line>Glory is like a circle in the water,</line>
            <line>Which never ceaseth to enlarge itself</line>
            <line>Till by broad spreading it disperse to nought.</line>
            <line>With Henry's death the English circle ends;</line>
            <line>Dispersed are the glories it included.</line>
            <line>Now am I like that proud insulting ship</line>
            <line>Which Caesar and his fortune bare at once.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHARLES</speaker>
            <line>Was Mahomet inspired with a dove?</line>
            <line>Thou with an eagle art inspired then.</line>
            <line>Helen, the mother of great Constantine,</line>
            <line>Nor yet Saint Philip's daughters, were like thee.</line>
            <line>Bright star of Venus, fall'n down on the earth,</line>
            <line>How may I reverently worship thee enough?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALENCON</speaker>
            <line>Leave off delays, and let us raise the siege.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>REIGNIER</speaker>
            <line>Woman, do what thou canst to save our honours;</line>
            <line>Drive them from Orleans and be immortalized.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHARLES</speaker>
            <line>Presently we'll try: come, let's away about it:</line>
            <line>No prophet will I trust, if she prove false.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  London. Before the Tower.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter GLOUCESTER, with his Serving-men in blue coats</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>I am come to survey the Tower this day:</line>
            <line>Since Henry's death, I fear, there is conveyance.</line>
            <line>Where be these warders, that they wait not here?</line>
            <line>Open the gates; 'tis Gloucester that calls.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Warder</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Within</stagedir>  Who's there that knocks so imperiously?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Serving-Man</speaker>
            <line>It is the noble Duke of Gloucester.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Warder</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Within</stagedir>  Whoe'er he be, you may not be let in.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Serving-Man</speaker>
            <line>Villains, answer you so the lord protector?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Warder</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Within</stagedir>  The Lord protect him! so we answer him:</line>
            <line>We do no otherwise than we are will'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Who willed you? or whose will stands but mine?</line>
            <line>There's none protector of the realm but I.</line>
            <line>Break up the gates, I'll be your warrantize.</line>
            <line>Shall I be flouted thus by dunghill grooms?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Gloucester's men rush at the Tower Gates, and
WOODVILE the Lieutenant speaks within</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WOODVILE</speaker>
            <line>What noise is this? what traitors have we here?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Lieutenant, is it you whose voice I hear?</line>
            <line>Open the gates; here's Gloucester that would enter.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WOODVILE</speaker>
            <line>Have patience, noble duke; I may not open;</line>
            <line>The Cardinal of Winchester forbids:</line>
            <line>From him I have express commandment</line>
            <line>That thou nor none of thine shall be let in.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Faint-hearted Woodvile, prizest him 'fore me?</line>
            <line>Arrogant Winchester, that haughty prelate,</line>
            <line>Whom Henry, our late sovereign, ne'er could brook?</line>
            <line>Thou art no friend to God or to the king:</line>
            <line>Open the gates, or I'll shut thee out shortly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Serving-Men</speaker>
            <line>Open the gates unto the lord protector,</line>
            <line>Or we'll burst them open, if that you come not quickly.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter to the Protector at the Tower Gates BISHOP
OF WINCHESTER and his men in tawny coats</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BISHOP OF WINCHESTER</speaker>
            <line>How now, ambitious Humphry! what means this?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Peel'd priest, dost thou command me to be shut out?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BISHOP OF WINCHESTER</speaker>
            <line>I do, thou most usurping proditor,</line>
            <line>And not protector, of the king or realm.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Stand back, thou manifest conspirator,</line>
            <line>Thou that contrivedst to murder our dead lord;</line>
            <line>Thou that givest whores indulgences to sin:</line>
            <line>I'll canvass thee in thy broad cardinal's hat,</line>
            <line>If thou proceed in this thy insolence.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BISHOP OF WINCHESTER</speaker>
            <line>Nay, stand thou back, I will not budge a foot:</line>
            <line>This be Damascus, be thou cursed Cain,</line>
            <line>To slay thy brother Abel, if thou wilt.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>I will not slay thee, but I'll drive thee back:</line>
            <line>Thy scarlet robes as a child's bearing-cloth</line>
            <line>I'll use to carry thee out of this place.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BISHOP OF WINCHESTER</speaker>
            <line>Do what thou darest; I beard thee to thy face.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>What! am I dared and bearded to my face?</line>
            <line>Draw, men, for all this privileged place;</line>
            <line>Blue coats to tawny coats. Priest, beware your beard,</line>
            <line>I mean to tug it and to cuff you soundly:</line>
            <line>Under my feet I stamp thy cardinal's hat:</line>
            <line>In spite of pope or dignities of church,</line>
            <line>Here by the cheeks I'll drag thee up and down.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BISHOP OF WINCHESTER</speaker>
            <line>Gloucester, thou wilt answer this before the pope.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Winchester goose, I cry, a rope! a rope!</line>
            <line>Now beat them hence; why do you let them stay?</line>
            <line>Thee I'll chase hence, thou wolf in sheep's array.</line>
            <line>Out, tawny coats! out, scarlet hypocrite!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Here GLOUCESTER's men beat out BISHOP OF
WINCHESTER's men, and enter in the hurly-
burly the Mayor of London and his Officers</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Mayor</speaker>
            <line>Fie, lords! that you, being supreme magistrates,</line>
            <line>Thus contumeliously should break the peace!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Peace, mayor! thou know'st little of my wrongs:</line>
            <line>Here's Beaufort, that regards nor God nor king,</line>
            <line>Hath here distrain'd the Tower to his use.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BISHOP OF WINCHESTER</speaker>
            <line>Here's Gloucester, a foe to citizens,</line>
            <line>One that still motions war and never peace,</line>
            <line>O'ercharging your free purses with large fines,</line>
            <line>That seeks to overthrow religion,</line>
            <line>Because he is protector of the realm,</line>
            <line>And would have armour here out of the Tower,</line>
            <line>To crown himself king and suppress the prince.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>I will not answer thee with words, but blows.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Here they skirmish again</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Mayor</speaker>
            <line>Naught rests for me in this tumultuous strife</line>
            <line>But to make open proclamation:</line>
            <line>Come, officer; as loud as e'er thou canst,</line>
            <line>Cry.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Officer</speaker>
            <line>All manner of men assembled here in arms this day</line>
            <line>against God's peace and the king's, we charge and</line>
            <line>command you, in his highness' name, to repair to</line>
            <line>your several dwelling-places; and not to wear,</line>
            <line>handle, or use any sword, weapon, or dagger,</line>
            <line>henceforward, upon pain of death.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Cardinal, I'll be no breaker of the law:</line>
            <line>But we shall meet, and break our minds at large.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BISHOP OF WINCHESTER</speaker>
            <line>Gloucester, we will meet; to thy cost, be sure:</line>
            <line>Thy heart-blood I will have for this day's work.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Mayor</speaker>
            <line>I'll call for clubs, if you will not away.</line>
            <line>This cardinal's more haughty than the devil.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Mayor, farewell: thou dost but what thou mayst.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BISHOP OF WINCHESTER</speaker>
            <line>Abominable Gloucester, guard thy head;</line>
            <line>For I intend to have it ere long.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt, severally, GLOUCESTER and BISHOP OF
WINCHESTER with their Serving-men</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Mayor</speaker>
            <line>See the coast clear'd, and then we will depart.</line>
            <line>Good God, these nobles should such stomachs bear!</line>
            <line>I myself fight not once in forty year.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-4">
      <title>SCENE IV.  Orleans.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter, on the walls, a Master Gunner and his Boy</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Master-Gunner</speaker>
            <line>Sirrah, thou know'st how Orleans is besieged,</line>
            <line>And how the English have the suburbs won.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Boy</speaker>
            <line>Father, I know; and oft have shot at them,</line>
            <line>Howe'er unfortunate I miss'd my aim.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Master-Gunner</speaker>
            <line>But now thou shalt not. Be thou ruled by me:</line>
            <line>Chief master-gunner am I of this town;</line>
            <line>Something I must do to procure me grace.</line>
            <line>The prince's espials have informed me</line>
            <line>How the English, in the suburbs close intrench'd,</line>
            <line>Wont, through a secret grate of iron bars</line>
            <line>In yonder tower, to overpeer the city,</line>
            <line>And thence discover how with most advantage</line>
            <line>They may vex us with shot, or with assault.</line>
            <line>To intercept this inconvenience,</line>
            <line>A piece of ordnance 'gainst it I have placed;</line>
            <line>And even these three days have I watch'd,</line>
            <line>If I could see them.</line>
            <line>Now do thou watch, for I can stay no longer.</line>
            <line>If thou spy'st any, run and bring me word;</line>
            <line>And thou shalt find me at the governor's.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Boy</speaker>
            <line>Father, I warrant you; take you no care;</line>
            <line>I'll never trouble you, if I may spy them.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Enter, on the turrets, SALISBURY and TALBOT,
GLANSDALE, GARGRAVE, and others</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALISBURY</speaker>
            <line>Talbot, my life, my joy, again return'd!</line>
            <line>How wert thou handled being prisoner?</line>
            <line>Or by what means got'st thou to be released?</line>
            <line>Discourse, I prithee, on this turret's top.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TALBOT</speaker>
            <line>The Duke of Bedford had a prisoner</line>
            <line>Call'd the brave Lord Ponton de Santrailles;</line>
            <line>For him was I exchanged and ransomed.</line>
            <line>But with a baser man of arms by far</line>
            <line>Once in contempt they would have barter'd me:</line>
            <line>Which I, disdaining, scorn'd; and craved death,</line>
            <line>Rather than I would be so vile esteem'd.</line>
            <line>In fine, redeem'd I was as I desired.</line>
            <line>But, O! the treacherous Fastolfe wounds my heart,</line>
            <line>Whom with my bare fists I would execute,</line>
            <line>If I now had him brought into my power.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALISBURY</speaker>
            <line>Yet tell'st thou not how thou wert entertain'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TALBOT</speaker>
            <line>With scoffs and scorns and contumelious taunts.</line>
            <line>In open market-place produced they me,</line>
            <line>To be a public spectacle to all:</line>
            <line>Here, said they, is the terror of the French,</line>
            <line>The scarecrow that affrights our children so.</line>
            <line>Then broke I from the officers that led me,</line>
            <line>And with my nails digg'd stones out of the ground,</line>
            <line>To hurl at the beholders of my shame:</line>
            <line>My grisly countenance made others fly;</line>
            <line>None durst come near for fear of sudden death.</line>
            <line>In iron walls they deem'd me not secure;</line>
            <line>So great fear of my name 'mongst them was spread,</line>
            <line>That they supposed I could rend bars of steel,</line>
            <line>And spurn in pieces posts of adamant:</line>
            <line>Wherefore a guard of chosen shot I had,</line>
            <line>That walked about me every minute-while;</line>
            <line>And if I did but stir out of my bed,</line>
            <line>Ready they were to shoot me to the heart.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter the Boy with a linstock</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALISBURY</speaker>
            <line>I grieve to hear what torments you endured,</line>
            <line>But we will be revenged sufficiently</line>
            <line>Now it is supper-time in Orleans:</line>
            <line>Here, through this grate, I count each one</line>
            <line>and view the Frenchmen how they fortify:</line>
            <line>Let us look in; the sight will much delight thee.</line>
            <line>Sir Thomas Gargrave, and Sir William Glansdale,</line>
            <line>Let me have your express opinions</line>
            <line>Where is best place to make our battery next.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GARGRAVE</speaker>
            <line>I think, at the north gate; for there stand lords.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLANSDALE</speaker>
            <line>And I, here, at the bulwark of the bridge.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TALBOT</speaker>
            <line>For aught I see, this city must be famish'd,</line>
            <line>Or with light skirmishes enfeebled.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Here they shoot. SALISBURY and GARGRAVE fall</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SALISBURY</speaker>
            <line>O Lord, have mercy on us, wretched sinners!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GARGRAVE</speaker>
            <line>O Lord, have mercy on me, woful man!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TALBOT</speaker>
            <line>What chance is this that suddenly hath cross'd us?</line>
            <line>Speak, Salisbury; at least, if thou canst speak:</line>
            <line>How farest thou, mirror of all martial men?</line>
            <line>One of thy eyes and thy cheek's side struck off!</line>
            <line>Accursed tower! accursed fatal hand</line>
            <line>That hath contrived this woful tragedy!</line>
            <line>In thirteen battles Salisbury o'ercame;</line>
            <line>Henry the Fifth he first train'd to the wars;</line>
            <line>Whilst any trump did sound, or drum struck up,</line>
            <line>His sword did ne'er leave striking in the field.</line>
            <line>Yet livest thou, Salisbury? though thy speech doth fail,</line>
            <line>One eye thou hast, to look to heaven for grace:</line>
            <line>The sun with one eye vieweth all the world.</line>
            <line>Heaven, be thou gracious to none alive,</line>
            <line>If Salisbury wants mercy at thy hands!</line>
            <line>Bear hence his body; I will help to bury it.</line>
            <line>Sir Thomas Gargrave, hast thou any life?</line>
            <line>Speak unto Talbot; nay, look up to him.</line>
            <line>Salisbury, cheer thy spirit with this comfort;</line>
            <line>Thou shalt not die whiles--</line>
            <line>He beckons with his hand and smiles on me.</line>
            <line>As who should say 'When I am dead and gone,</line>
            <line>Remember to avenge me on the French.'</line>
            <line>Plantagenet, I will; and like thee, Nero,</line>
            <line>Play on the lute, beholding the towns burn:</line>
            <line>Wretched shall France be only in my name.</line>
            <stagedir>Here an alarum, and it thunders and lightens</stagedir>
            <line>What stir is this? what tumult's in the heavens?</line>
            <line>Whence cometh this alarum and the noise?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter a Messenger</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>My lord, my lord, the French have gathered head:</line>
            <line>The Dauphin, with one Joan la Pucelle join'd,</line>
            <line>A holy prophetess new risen up,</line>
            <line>Is come with a great power to raise the siege.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Here SALISBURY lifteth himself up and groans</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TALBOT</speaker>
            <line>Hear, hear how dying Salisbury doth groan!</line>
            <line>It irks his heart he cannot be revenged.</line>
            <line>Frenchmen, I'll be a Salisbury to you:</line>
            <line>Pucelle or puzzel, dolphin or dogfish,</line>
            <line>Your hearts I'll stamp out with my horse's heels,</line>
            <line>And make a quagmire of your mingled brains.</line>
            <line>Convey me Salisbury into his tent,</line>
            <line>And then we'll try what these dastard Frenchmen dare.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Alarum. Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-5">
      <title>SCENE V.  The same.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Here an alarum again: and TALBOT pursueth the
DAUPHIN, and driveth him: then enter JOAN LA
PUCELLE, driving Englishmen before her, and exit
after them then re-enter TALBOT</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TALBOT</speaker>
            <line>Where is my strength, my valour, and my force?</line>
            <line>Our English troops retire, I cannot stay them:</line>
            <line>A woman clad in armour chaseth them.</line>
            <stagedir>Re-enter JOAN LA PUCELLE</stagedir>
            <line>Here, here she comes. I'll have a bout with thee;</line>
            <line>Devil or devil's dam, I'll conjure thee:</line>
            <line>Blood will I draw on thee, thou art a witch,</line>
            <line>And straightway give thy soul to him thou servest.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOAN LA PUCELLE</speaker>
            <line>Come, come, 'tis only I that must disgrace thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Here they fight</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TALBOT</speaker>
            <line>Heavens, can you suffer hell so to prevail?</line>
            <line>My breast I'll burst with straining of my courage</line>
            <line>And from my shoulders crack my arms asunder.</line>
            <line>But I will chastise this high-minded strumpet.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>They fight again</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOAN LA PUCELLE</speaker>
            <line>Talbot, farewell; thy hour is not yet come:</line>
            <line>I must go victual Orleans forthwith.</line>
            <stagedir>A short alarum; then enter the town with soldiers</stagedir>
            <line>O'ertake me, if thou canst; I scorn thy strength.</line>
            <line>Go, go, cheer up thy hungry-starved men;</line>
            <line>Help Salisbury to make his testament:</line>
            <line>This day is ours, as many more shall be.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TALBOT</speaker>
            <line>My thoughts are whirled like a potter's wheel;</line>
            <line>I know not where I am, nor what I do;</line>
            <line>A witch, by fear, not force, like Hannibal,</line>
            <line>Drives back our troops and conquers as she lists:</line>
            <line>So bees with smoke and doves with noisome stench</line>
            <line>Are from their hives and houses driven away.</line>
            <line>They call'd us for our fierceness English dogs;</line>
            <line>Now, like to whelps, we crying run away.</line>
            <stagedir>A short alarum</stagedir>
            <line>Hark, countrymen! either renew the fight,</line>
            <line>Or tear the lions out of England's coat;</line>
            <line>Renounce your soil, give sheep in lions' stead:</line>
            <line>Sheep run not half so treacherous from the wolf,</line>
            <line>Or horse or oxen from the leopard,</line>
            <line>As you fly from your oft-subdued slaves.</line>
            <stagedir>Alarum. Here another skirmish</stagedir>
            <line>It will not be: retire into your trenches:</line>
            <line>You all consented unto Salisbury's death,</line>
            <line>For none would strike a stroke in his revenge.</line>
            <line>Pucelle is enter'd into Orleans,</line>
            <line>In spite of us or aught that we could do.</line>
            <line>O, would I were to die with Salisbury!</line>
            <line>The shame hereof will make me hide my head.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit TALBOT. Alarum; retreat; flourish</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-6">
      <title>SCENE VI.  The same.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter, on the walls, JOAN LA PUCELLE, CHARLES,
REIGNIER, ALENCON, and Soldiers</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOAN LA PUCELLE</speaker>
            <line>Advance our waving colours on the walls;</line>
            <line>Rescued is Orleans from the English</line>
            <line>Thus Joan la Pucelle hath perform'd her word.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHARLES</speaker>
            <line>Divinest creature, Astraea's daughter,</line>
            <line>How shall I honour thee for this success?</line>
            <line>Thy promises are like Adonis' gardens</line>
            <line>That one day bloom'd and fruitful were the next.</line>
            <line>France, triumph in thy glorious prophetess!</line>
            <line>Recover'd is the town of Orleans:</line>
            <line>More blessed hap did ne'er befall our state.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>REIGNIER</speaker>
            <line>Why ring not out the bells aloud throughout the town?</line>
            <line>Dauphin, command the citizens make bonfires</line>
            <line>And feast and banquet in the open streets,</line>
            <line>To celebrate the joy that God hath given us.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALENCON</speaker>
            <line>All France will be replete with mirth and joy,</line>
            <line>When they shall hear how we have play'd the men.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHARLES</speaker>
            <line>'Tis Joan, not we, by whom the day is won;</line>
            <line>For which I will divide my crown with her,</line>
            <line>And all the priests and friars in my realm</line>
            <line>Shall in procession sing her endless praise.</line>
            <line>A statelier pyramis to her I'll rear</line>
            <line>Than Rhodope's or Memphis' ever was:</line>
            <line>In memory of her when she is dead,</line>
            <line>Her ashes, in an urn more precious</line>
            <line>Than the rich-jewel'd of Darius,</line>
            <line>Transported shall be at high festivals</line>
            <line>Before the kings and queens of France.</line>
            <line>No longer on Saint Denis will we cry,</line>
            <line>But Joan la Pucelle shall be France's saint.</line>
            <line>Come in, and let us banquet royally,</line>
            <line>After this golden day of victory.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Flourish. Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>