<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net/doctypes/dita/shakespear/dtd/act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-3">
   <title>ACT III</title>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  London. The Parliament-house.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Flourish. Enter KING HENRY VI, EXETER, GLOUCESTER,
WARWICK, SOMERSET, and SUFFOLK; the BISHOP OF
WINCHESTER, RICHARD PLANTAGENET, and others.
GLOUCESTER offers to put up a bill; BISHOP OF
WINCHESTER snatches it, and tears it</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BISHOP OF WINCHESTER</speaker>
            <line>Comest thou with deep premeditated lines,</line>
            <line>With written pamphlets studiously devised,</line>
            <line>Humphrey of Gloucester? If thou canst accuse,</line>
            <line>Or aught intend'st to lay unto my charge,</line>
            <line>Do it without invention, suddenly;</line>
            <line>As I with sudden and extemporal speech</line>
            <line>Purpose to answer what thou canst object.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Presumptuous priest! this place commands my patience,</line>
            <line>Or thou shouldst find thou hast dishonour'd me.</line>
            <line>Think not, although in writing I preferr'd</line>
            <line>The manner of thy vile outrageous crimes,</line>
            <line>That therefore I have forged, or am not able</line>
            <line>Verbatim to rehearse the method of my pen:</line>
            <line>No, prelate; such is thy audacious wickedness,</line>
            <line>Thy lewd, pestiferous and dissentious pranks,</line>
            <line>As very infants prattle of thy pride.</line>
            <line>Thou art a most pernicious usurer,</line>
            <line>Forward by nature, enemy to peace;</line>
            <line>Lascivious, wanton, more than well beseems</line>
            <line>A man of thy profession and degree;</line>
            <line>And for thy treachery, what's more manifest?</line>
            <line>In that thou laid'st a trap to take my life,</line>
            <line>As well at London bridge as at the Tower.</line>
            <line>Beside, I fear me, if thy thoughts were sifted,</line>
            <line>The king, thy sovereign, is not quite exempt</line>
            <line>From envious malice of thy swelling heart.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BISHOP OF WINCHESTER</speaker>
            <line>Gloucester, I do defy thee. Lords, vouchsafe</line>
            <line>To give me hearing what I shall reply.</line>
            <line>If I were covetous, ambitious or perverse,</line>
            <line>As he will have me, how am I so poor?</line>
            <line>Or how haps it I seek not to advance</line>
            <line>Or raise myself, but keep my wonted calling?</line>
            <line>And for dissension, who preferreth peace</line>
            <line>More than I do?--except I be provoked.</line>
            <line>No, my good lords, it is not that offends;</line>
            <line>It is not that that hath incensed the duke:</line>
            <line>It is, because no one should sway but he;</line>
            <line>No one but he should be about the king;</line>
            <line>And that engenders thunder in his breast</line>
            <line>And makes him roar these accusations forth.</line>
            <line>But he shall know I am as good--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>As good!</line>
            <line>Thou bastard of my grandfather!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BISHOP OF WINCHESTER</speaker>
            <line>Ay, lordly sir; for what are you, I pray,</line>
            <line>But one imperious in another's throne?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Am I not protector, saucy priest?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BISHOP OF WINCHESTER</speaker>
            <line>And am not I a prelate of the church?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Yes, as an outlaw in a castle keeps</line>
            <line>And useth it to patronage his theft.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BISHOP OF WINCHESTER</speaker>
            <line>Unreverent Gloster!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Thou art reverent</line>
            <line>Touching thy spiritual function, not thy life.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BISHOP OF WINCHESTER</speaker>
            <line>Rome shall remedy this.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Roam thither, then.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SOMERSET</speaker>
            <line>My lord, it were your duty to forbear.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Ay, see the bishop be not overborne.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SOMERSET</speaker>
            <line>Methinks my lord should be religious</line>
            <line>And know the office that belongs to such.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Methinks his lordship should be humbler;</line>
            <line>it fitteth not a prelate so to plead.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SOMERSET</speaker>
            <line>Yes, when his holy state is touch'd so near.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>State holy or unhallow'd, what of that?</line>
            <line>Is not his grace protector to the king?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD PLANTAGENET</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  Plantagenet, I see, must hold his tongue,</line>
            <line>Lest it be said 'Speak, sirrah, when you should;</line>
            <line>Must your bold verdict enter talk with lords?'</line>
            <line>Else would I have a fling at Winchester.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Uncles of Gloucester and of Winchester,</line>
            <line>The special watchmen of our English weal,</line>
            <line>I would prevail, if prayers might prevail,</line>
            <line>To join your hearts in love and amity.</line>
            <line>O, what a scandal is it to our crown,</line>
            <line>That two such noble peers as ye should jar!</line>
            <line>Believe me, lords, my tender years can tell</line>
            <line>Civil dissension is a viperous worm</line>
            <line>That gnaws the bowels of the commonwealth.</line>
            <stagedir>A noise within, 'Down with the tawny-coats!'</stagedir>
            <line>What tumult's this?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>An uproar, I dare warrant,</line>
            <line>Begun through malice of the bishop's men.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>A noise again, 'Stones! stones!' Enter Mayor</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Mayor</speaker>
            <line>O, my good lords, and virtuous Henry,</line>
            <line>Pity the city of London, pity us!</line>
            <line>The bishop and the Duke of Gloucester's men,</line>
            <line>Forbidden late to carry any weapon,</line>
            <line>Have fill'd their pockets full of pebble stones</line>
            <line>And banding themselves in contrary parts</line>
            <line>Do pelt so fast at one another's pate</line>
            <line>That many have their giddy brains knock'd out:</line>
            <line>Our windows are broke down in every street</line>
            <line>And we for fear compell'd to shut our shops.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter Serving-men, in skirmish, with bloody pates</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>We charge you, on allegiance to ourself,</line>
            <line>To hold your slaughtering hands and keep the peace.</line>
            <line>Pray, uncle Gloucester, mitigate this strife.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Serving-man</speaker>
            <line>Nay, if we be forbidden stones,</line>
            <line>We'll fall to it with our teeth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Serving-man</speaker>
            <line>Do what ye dare, we are as resolute.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Skirmish again</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>You of my household, leave this peevish broil</line>
            <line>And set this unaccustom'd fight aside.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Serving-man</speaker>
            <line>My lord, we know your grace to be a man</line>
            <line>Just and upright; and, for your royal birth,</line>
            <line>Inferior to none but to his majesty:</line>
            <line>And ere that we will suffer such a prince,</line>
            <line>So kind a father of the commonweal,</line>
            <line>To be disgraced by an inkhorn mate,</line>
            <line>We and our wives and children all will fight</line>
            <line>And have our bodies slaughtered by thy foes.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Serving-man</speaker>
            <line>Ay, and the very parings of our nails</line>
            <line>Shall pitch a field when we are dead.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Begin again</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Stay, stay, I say!</line>
            <line>And if you love me, as you say you do,</line>
            <line>Let me persuade you to forbear awhile.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>O, how this discord doth afflict my soul!</line>
            <line>Can you, my Lord of Winchester, behold</line>
            <line>My sighs and tears and will not once relent?</line>
            <line>Who should be pitiful, if you be not?</line>
            <line>Or who should study to prefer a peace.</line>
            <line>If holy churchmen take delight in broils?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Yield, my lord protector; yield, Winchester;</line>
            <line>Except you mean with obstinate repulse</line>
            <line>To slay your sovereign and destroy the realm.</line>
            <line>You see what mischief and what murder too</line>
            <line>Hath been enacted through your enmity;</line>
            <line>Then be at peace except ye thirst for blood.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BISHOP OF WINCHESTER</speaker>
            <line>He shall submit, or I will never yield.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Compassion on the king commands me stoop;</line>
            <line>Or I would see his heart out, ere the priest</line>
            <line>Should ever get that privilege of me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Behold, my Lord of Winchester, the duke</line>
            <line>Hath banish'd moody discontented fury,</line>
            <line>As by his smoothed brows it doth appear:</line>
            <line>Why look you still so stern and tragical?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Here, Winchester, I offer thee my hand.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Fie, uncle Beaufort! I have heard you preach</line>
            <line>That malice was a great and grievous sin;</line>
            <line>And will not you maintain the thing you teach,</line>
            <line>But prove a chief offender in the same?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Sweet king! the bishop hath a kindly gird.</line>
            <line>For shame, my lord of Winchester, relent!</line>
            <line>What, shall a child instruct you what to do?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BISHOP OF WINCHESTER</speaker>
            <line>Well, Duke of Gloucester, I will yield to thee;</line>
            <line>Love for thy love and hand for hand I give.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  Ay, but, I fear me, with a hollow heart.--</line>
            <line>See here, my friends and loving countrymen,</line>
            <line>This token serveth for a flag of truce</line>
            <line>Betwixt ourselves and all our followers:</line>
            <line>So help me God, as I dissemble not!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BISHOP OF WINCHESTER</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  So help me God, as I intend it not!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>O, loving uncle, kind Duke of Gloucester,</line>
            <line>How joyful am I made by this contract!</line>
            <line>Away, my masters! trouble us no more;</line>
            <line>But join in friendship, as your lords have done.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Serving-man</speaker>
            <line>Content: I'll to the surgeon's.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Serving-man</speaker>
            <line>And so will I.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Serving-man</speaker>
            <line>And I will see what physic the tavern affords.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt Serving-men, Mayor, &amp;c</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Accept this scroll, most gracious sovereign,</line>
            <line>Which in the right of Richard Plantagenet</line>
            <line>We do exhibit to your majesty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Well urged, my Lord of Warwick: or sweet prince,</line>
            <line>And if your grace mark every circumstance,</line>
            <line>You have great reason to do Richard right;</line>
            <line>Especially for those occasions</line>
            <line>At Eltham Place I told your majesty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>And those occasions, uncle, were of force:</line>
            <line>Therefore, my loving lords, our pleasure is</line>
            <line>That Richard be restored to his blood.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Let Richard be restored to his blood;</line>
            <line>So shall his father's wrongs be recompensed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BISHOP OF WINCHESTER</speaker>
            <line>As will the rest, so willeth Winchester.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>If Richard will be true, not that alone</line>
            <line>But all the whole inheritance I give</line>
            <line>That doth belong unto the house of York,</line>
            <line>From whence you spring by lineal descent.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD PLANTAGENET</speaker>
            <line>Thy humble servant vows obedience</line>
            <line>And humble service till the point of death.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Stoop then and set your knee against my foot;</line>
            <line>And, in reguerdon of that duty done,</line>
            <line>I gird thee with the valiant sword of York:</line>
            <line>Rise Richard, like a true Plantagenet,</line>
            <line>And rise created princely Duke of York.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD PLANTAGENET</speaker>
            <line>And so thrive Richard as thy foes may fall!</line>
            <line>And as my duty springs, so perish they</line>
            <line>That grudge one thought against your majesty!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALL</speaker>
            <line>Welcome, high prince, the mighty Duke of York!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SOMERSET</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  Perish, base prince, ignoble Duke of York!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Now will it best avail your majesty</line>
            <line>To cross the seas and to be crown'd in France:</line>
            <line>The presence of a king engenders love</line>
            <line>Amongst his subjects and his loyal friends,</line>
            <line>As it disanimates his enemies.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>When Gloucester says the word, King Henry goes;</line>
            <line>For friendly counsel cuts off many foes.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Your ships already are in readiness.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Sennet. Flourish. Exeunt all but EXETER</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EXETER</speaker>
            <line>Ay, we may march in England or in France,</line>
            <line>Not seeing what is likely to ensue.</line>
            <line>This late dissension grown betwixt the peers</line>
            <line>Burns under feigned ashes of forged love</line>
            <line>And will at last break out into a flame:</line>
            <line>As fester'd members rot but by degree,</line>
            <line>Till bones and flesh and sinews fall away,</line>
            <line>So will this base and envious discord breed.</line>
            <line>And now I fear that fatal prophecy</line>
            <line>Which in the time of Henry named the Fifth</line>
            <line>Was in the mouth of every sucking babe;</line>
            <line>That Henry born at Monmouth should win all</line>
            <line>And Henry born at Windsor lose all:</line>
            <line>Which is so plain that Exeter doth wish</line>
            <line>His days may finish ere that hapless time.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  France. Before Rouen.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter JOAN LA PUCELLE disguised, with four Soldiers
with sacks upon their backs</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOAN LA PUCELLE</speaker>
            <line>These are the city gates, the gates of Rouen,</line>
            <line>Through which our policy must make a breach:</line>
            <line>Take heed, be wary how you place your words;</line>
            <line>Talk like the vulgar sort of market men</line>
            <line>That come to gather money for their corn.</line>
            <line>If we have entrance, as I hope we shall,</line>
            <line>And that we find the slothful watch but weak,</line>
            <line>I'll by a sign give notice to our friends,</line>
            <line>That Charles the Dauphin may encounter them.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Soldier</speaker>
            <line>Our sacks shall be a mean to sack the city,</line>
            <line>And we be lords and rulers over Rouen;</line>
            <line>Therefore we'll knock.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Knocks</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Watch</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Within</stagedir>  Qui est la?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOAN LA PUCELLE</speaker>
            <line>Paysans, pauvres gens de France;</line>
            <line>Poor market folks that come to sell their corn.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Watch</speaker>
            <line>Enter, go in; the market bell is rung.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOAN LA PUCELLE</speaker>
            <line>Now, Rouen, I'll shake thy bulwarks to the ground.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Enter CHARLES, the BASTARD OF ORLEANS, ALENCON,
REIGNIER, and forces</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHARLES</speaker>
            <line>Saint Denis bless this happy stratagem!</line>
            <line>And once again we'll sleep secure in Rouen.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD OF ORLEANS</speaker>
            <line>Here enter'd Pucelle and her practisants;</line>
            <line>Now she is there, how will she specify</line>
            <line>Where is the best and safest passage in?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>REIGNIER</speaker>
            <line>By thrusting out a torch from yonder tower;</line>
            <line>Which, once discern'd, shows that her meaning is,</line>
            <line>No way to that, for weakness, which she enter'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter JOAN LA PUCELLE on the top, thrusting out a
torch burning</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOAN LA PUCELLE</speaker>
            <line>Behold, this is the happy wedding torch</line>
            <line>That joineth Rouen unto her countrymen,</line>
            <line>But burning fatal to the Talbotites!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD OF ORLEANS</speaker>
            <line>See, noble Charles, the beacon of our friend;</line>
            <line>The burning torch in yonder turret stands.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHARLES</speaker>
            <line>Now shine it like a comet of revenge,</line>
            <line>A prophet to the fall of all our foes!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>REIGNIER</speaker>
            <line>Defer no time, delays have dangerous ends;</line>
            <line>Enter, and cry 'The Dauphin!' presently,</line>
            <line>And then do execution on the watch.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Alarum. Exeunt</stagedir>
         <stagedir>An alarum. Enter TALBOT in an excursion</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TALBOT</speaker>
            <line>France, thou shalt rue this treason with thy tears,</line>
            <line>If Talbot but survive thy treachery.</line>
            <line>Pucelle, that witch, that damned sorceress,</line>
            <line>Hath wrought this hellish mischief unawares,</line>
            <line>That hardly we escaped the pride of France.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <stagedir>An alarum: excursions. BEDFORD, brought in sick
in a chair. Enter TALBOT and BURGUNDY without:
within JOAN LA PUCELLE, CHARLES, BASTARD OF ORLEANS,
ALENCON, and REIGNIER, on the walls</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOAN LA PUCELLE</speaker>
            <line>Good morrow, gallants! want ye corn for bread?</line>
            <line>I think the Duke of Burgundy will fast</line>
            <line>Before he'll buy again at such a rate:</line>
            <line>'Twas full of darnel; do you like the taste?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BURGUNDY</speaker>
            <line>Scoff on, vile fiend and shameless courtezan!</line>
            <line>I trust ere long to choke thee with thine own</line>
            <line>And make thee curse the harvest of that corn.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHARLES</speaker>
            <line>Your grace may starve perhaps before that time.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEDFORD</speaker>
            <line>O, let no words, but deeds, revenge this treason!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOAN LA PUCELLE</speaker>
            <line>What will you do, good grey-beard? break a lance,</line>
            <line>And run a tilt at death within a chair?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TALBOT</speaker>
            <line>Foul fiend of France, and hag of all despite,</line>
            <line>Encompass'd with thy lustful paramours!</line>
            <line>Becomes it thee to taunt his valiant age</line>
            <line>And twit with cowardice a man half dead?</line>
            <line>Damsel, I'll have a bout with you again,</line>
            <line>Or else let Talbot perish with this shame.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOAN LA PUCELLE</speaker>
            <line>Are ye so hot, sir? yet, Pucelle, hold thy peace;</line>
            <line>If Talbot do but thunder, rain will follow.</line>
            <stagedir>The English whisper together in council</stagedir>
            <line>God speed the parliament! who shall be the speaker?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TALBOT</speaker>
            <line>Dare ye come forth and meet us in the field?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOAN LA PUCELLE</speaker>
            <line>Belike your lordship takes us then for fools,</line>
            <line>To try if that our own be ours or no.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TALBOT</speaker>
            <line>I speak not to that railing Hecate,</line>
            <line>But unto thee, Alencon, and the rest;</line>
            <line>Will ye, like soldiers, come and fight it out?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALENCON</speaker>
            <line>Signior, no.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TALBOT</speaker>
            <line>Signior, hang! base muleters of France!</line>
            <line>Like peasant foot-boys do they keep the walls</line>
            <line>And dare not take up arms like gentlemen.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOAN LA PUCELLE</speaker>
            <line>Away, captains! let's get us from the walls;</line>
            <line>For Talbot means no goodness by his looks.</line>
            <line>God be wi' you, my lord! we came but to tell you</line>
            <line>That we are here.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt from the walls</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TALBOT</speaker>
            <line>And there will we be too, ere it be long,</line>
            <line>Or else reproach be Talbot's greatest fame!</line>
            <line>Vow, Burgundy, by honour of thy house,</line>
            <line>Prick'd on by public wrongs sustain'd in France,</line>
            <line>Either to get the town again or die:</line>
            <line>And I, as sure as English Henry lives</line>
            <line>And as his father here was conqueror,</line>
            <line>As sure as in this late-betrayed town</line>
            <line>Great Coeur-de-lion's heart was buried,</line>
            <line>So sure I swear to get the town or die.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BURGUNDY</speaker>
            <line>My vows are equal partners with thy vows.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TALBOT</speaker>
            <line>But, ere we go, regard this dying prince,</line>
            <line>The valiant Duke of Bedford. Come, my lord,</line>
            <line>We will bestow you in some better place,</line>
            <line>Fitter for sickness and for crazy age.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEDFORD</speaker>
            <line>Lord Talbot, do not so dishonour me:</line>
            <line>Here will I sit before the walls of Rouen</line>
            <line>And will be partner of your weal or woe.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BURGUNDY</speaker>
            <line>Courageous Bedford, let us now persuade you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEDFORD</speaker>
            <line>Not to be gone from hence; for once I read</line>
            <line>That stout Pendragon in his litter sick</line>
            <line>Came to the field and vanquished his foes:</line>
            <line>Methinks I should revive the soldiers' hearts,</line>
            <line>Because I ever found them as myself.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TALBOT</speaker>
            <line>Undaunted spirit in a dying breast!</line>
            <line>Then be it so: heavens keep old Bedford safe!</line>
            <line>And now no more ado, brave Burgundy,</line>
            <line>But gather we our forces out of hand</line>
            <line>And set upon our boasting enemy.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt all but BEDFORD and Attendants</stagedir>
         <stagedir>An alarum: excursions. Enter FASTOLFE and
a Captain</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Captain</speaker>
            <line>Whither away, Sir John Fastolfe, in such haste?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FASTOLFE</speaker>
            <line>Whither away! to save myself by flight:</line>
            <line>We are like to have the overthrow again.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Captain</speaker>
            <line>What! will you fly, and leave Lord Talbot?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FASTOLFE</speaker>
            <line>Ay,</line>
            <line>All the Talbots in the world, to save my life!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Captain</speaker>
            <line>Cowardly knight! ill fortune follow thee!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Retreat: excursions. JOAN LA PUCELLE, ALENCON,
and CHARLES fly</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEDFORD</speaker>
            <line>Now, quiet soul, depart when heaven please,</line>
            <line>For I have seen our enemies' overthrow.</line>
            <line>What is the trust or strength of foolish man?</line>
            <line>They that of late were daring with their scoffs</line>
            <line>Are glad and fain by flight to save themselves.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>BEDFORD dies, and is carried in by two in his chair</stagedir>
         <stagedir>An alarum. Re-enter TALBOT, BURGUNDY, and the rest</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TALBOT</speaker>
            <line>Lost, and recover'd in a day again!</line>
            <line>This is a double honour, Burgundy:</line>
            <line>Yet heavens have glory for this victory!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BURGUNDY</speaker>
            <line>Warlike and martial Talbot, Burgundy</line>
            <line>Enshrines thee in his heart and there erects</line>
            <line>Thy noble deeds as valour's monuments.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TALBOT</speaker>
            <line>Thanks, gentle duke. But where is Pucelle now?</line>
            <line>I think her old familiar is asleep:</line>
            <line>Now where's the Bastard's braves, and Charles his gleeks?</line>
            <line>What, all amort? Rouen hangs her head for grief</line>
            <line>That such a valiant company are fled.</line>
            <line>Now will we take some order in the town,</line>
            <line>Placing therein some expert officers,</line>
            <line>And then depart to Paris to the king,</line>
            <line>For there young Henry with his nobles lie.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BURGUNDY</speaker>
            <line>What wills Lord Talbot pleaseth Burgundy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TALBOT</speaker>
            <line>But yet, before we go, let's not forget</line>
            <line>The noble Duke of Bedford late deceased,</line>
            <line>But see his exequies fulfill'd in Rouen:</line>
            <line>A braver soldier never couched lance,</line>
            <line>A gentler heart did never sway in court;</line>
            <line>But kings and mightiest potentates must die,</line>
            <line>For that's the end of human misery.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  The plains near Rouen.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter CHARLES, the BASTARD OF ORLEANS, ALENCON, JOAN
LA PUCELLE, and forces</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOAN LA PUCELLE</speaker>
            <line>Dismay not, princes, at this accident,</line>
            <line>Nor grieve that Rouen is so recovered:</line>
            <line>Care is no cure, but rather corrosive,</line>
            <line>For things that are not to be remedied.</line>
            <line>Let frantic Talbot triumph for a while</line>
            <line>And like a peacock sweep along his tail;</line>
            <line>We'll pull his plumes and take away his train,</line>
            <line>If Dauphin and the rest will be but ruled.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHARLES</speaker>
            <line>We have been guided by thee hitherto,</line>
            <line>And of thy cunning had no diffidence:</line>
            <line>One sudden foil shall never breed distrust.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD OF ORLEANS</speaker>
            <line>Search out thy wit for secret policies,</line>
            <line>And we will make thee famous through the world.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALENCON</speaker>
            <line>We'll set thy statue in some holy place,</line>
            <line>And have thee reverenced like a blessed saint:</line>
            <line>Employ thee then, sweet virgin, for our good.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOAN LA PUCELLE</speaker>
            <line>Then thus it must be; this doth Joan devise:</line>
            <line>By fair persuasions mix'd with sugar'd words</line>
            <line>We will entice the Duke of Burgundy</line>
            <line>To leave the Talbot and to follow us.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHARLES</speaker>
            <line>Ay, marry, sweeting, if we could do that,</line>
            <line>France were no place for Henry's warriors;</line>
            <line>Nor should that nation boast it so with us,</line>
            <line>But be extirped from our provinces.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALENCON</speaker>
            <line>For ever should they be expulsed from France</line>
            <line>And not have title of an earldom here.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOAN LA PUCELLE</speaker>
            <line>Your honours shall perceive how I will work</line>
            <line>To bring this matter to the wished end.</line>
            <stagedir>Drum sounds afar off</stagedir>
            <line>Hark! by the sound of drum you may perceive</line>
            <line>Their powers are marching unto Paris-ward.</line>
            <stagedir>Here sound an English march. Enter, and pass over
at a distance, TALBOT and his forces</stagedir>
            <line>There goes the Talbot, with his colours spread,</line>
            <line>And all the troops of English after him.</line>
            <stagedir>French march. Enter BURGUNDY and forces</stagedir>
            <line>Now in the rearward comes the duke and his:</line>
            <line>Fortune in favour makes him lag behind.</line>
            <line>Summon a parley; we will talk with him.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Trumpets sound a parley</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHARLES</speaker>
            <line>A parley with the Duke of Burgundy!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BURGUNDY</speaker>
            <line>Who craves a parley with the Burgundy?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOAN LA PUCELLE</speaker>
            <line>The princely Charles of France, thy countryman.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BURGUNDY</speaker>
            <line>What say'st thou, Charles? for I am marching hence.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHARLES</speaker>
            <line>Speak, Pucelle, and enchant him with thy words.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOAN LA PUCELLE</speaker>
            <line>Brave Burgundy, undoubted hope of France!</line>
            <line>Stay, let thy humble handmaid speak to thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BURGUNDY</speaker>
            <line>Speak on; but be not over-tedious.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOAN LA PUCELLE</speaker>
            <line>Look on thy country, look on fertile France,</line>
            <line>And see the cities and the towns defaced</line>
            <line>By wasting ruin of the cruel foe.</line>
            <line>As looks the mother on her lowly babe</line>
            <line>When death doth close his tender dying eyes,</line>
            <line>See, see the pining malady of France;</line>
            <line>Behold the wounds, the most unnatural wounds,</line>
            <line>Which thou thyself hast given her woful breast.</line>
            <line>O, turn thy edged sword another way;</line>
            <line>Strike those that hurt, and hurt not those that help.</line>
            <line>One drop of blood drawn from thy country's bosom</line>
            <line>Should grieve thee more than streams of foreign gore:</line>
            <line>Return thee therefore with a flood of tears,</line>
            <line>And wash away thy country's stained spots.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BURGUNDY</speaker>
            <line>Either she hath bewitch'd me with her words,</line>
            <line>Or nature makes me suddenly relent.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOAN LA PUCELLE</speaker>
            <line>Besides, all French and France exclaims on thee,</line>
            <line>Doubting thy birth and lawful progeny.</line>
            <line>Who joint'st thou with but with a lordly nation</line>
            <line>That will not trust thee but for profit's sake?</line>
            <line>When Talbot hath set footing once in France</line>
            <line>And fashion'd thee that instrument of ill,</line>
            <line>Who then but English Henry will be lord</line>
            <line>And thou be thrust out like a fugitive?</line>
            <line>Call we to mind, and mark but this for proof,</line>
            <line>Was not the Duke of Orleans thy foe?</line>
            <line>And was he not in England prisoner?</line>
            <line>But when they heard he was thine enemy,</line>
            <line>They set him free without his ransom paid,</line>
            <line>In spite of Burgundy and all his friends.</line>
            <line>See, then, thou fight'st against thy countrymen</line>
            <line>And joint'st with them will be thy slaughtermen.</line>
            <line>Come, come, return; return, thou wandering lord:</line>
            <line>Charles and the rest will take thee in their arms.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BURGUNDY</speaker>
            <line>I am vanquished; these haughty words of hers</line>
            <line>Have batter'd me like roaring cannon-shot,</line>
            <line>And made me almost yield upon my knees.</line>
            <line>Forgive me, country, and sweet countrymen,</line>
            <line>And, lords, accept this hearty kind embrace:</line>
            <line>My forces and my power of men are yours:</line>
            <line>So farewell, Talbot; I'll no longer trust thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOAN LA PUCELLE</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  Done like a Frenchman: turn, and turn again!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHARLES</speaker>
            <line>Welcome, brave duke! thy friendship makes us fresh.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD OF ORLEANS</speaker>
            <line>And doth beget new courage in our breasts.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALENCON</speaker>
            <line>Pucelle hath bravely play'd her part in this,</line>
            <line>And doth deserve a coronet of gold.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHARLES</speaker>
            <line>Now let us on, my lords, and join our powers,</line>
            <line>And seek how we may prejudice the foe.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-4">
      <title>SCENE IV.  Paris. The palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter KING HENRY VI, GLOUCESTER, BISHOP OF
WINCHESTER, YORK, SUFFOLK, SOMERSET, WARWICK,
EXETER, VERNON BASSET, and others. To them
with his Soldiers, TALBOT</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TALBOT</speaker>
            <line>My gracious prince, and honourable peers,</line>
            <line>Hearing of your arrival in this realm,</line>
            <line>I have awhile given truce unto my wars,</line>
            <line>To do my duty to my sovereign:</line>
            <line>In sign, whereof, this arm, that hath reclaim'd</line>
            <line>To your obedience fifty fortresses,</line>
            <line>Twelve cities and seven walled towns of strength,</line>
            <line>Beside five hundred prisoners of esteem,</line>
            <line>Lets fall his sword before your highness' feet,</line>
            <line>And with submissive loyalty of heart</line>
            <line>Ascribes the glory of his conquest got</line>
            <line>First to my God and next unto your grace.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Kneels</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Is this the Lord Talbot, uncle Gloucester,</line>
            <line>That hath so long been resident in France?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Yes, if it please your majesty, my liege.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Welcome, brave captain and victorious lord!</line>
            <line>When I was young, as yet I am not old,</line>
            <line>I do remember how my father said</line>
            <line>A stouter champion never handled sword.</line>
            <line>Long since we were resolved of your truth,</line>
            <line>Your faithful service and your toil in war;</line>
            <line>Yet never have you tasted our reward,</line>
            <line>Or been reguerdon'd with so much as thanks,</line>
            <line>Because till now we never saw your face:</line>
            <line>Therefore, stand up; and, for these good deserts,</line>
            <line>We here create you Earl of Shrewsbury;</line>
            <line>And in our coronation take your place.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Sennet. Flourish. Exeunt all but VERNON and BASSET</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VERNON</speaker>
            <line>Now, sir, to you, that were so hot at sea,</line>
            <line>Disgracing of these colours that I wear</line>
            <line>In honour of my noble Lord of York:</line>
            <line>Darest thou maintain the former words thou spakest?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSET</speaker>
            <line>Yes, sir; as well as you dare patronage</line>
            <line>The envious barking of your saucy tongue</line>
            <line>Against my lord the Duke of Somerset.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VERNON</speaker>
            <line>Sirrah, thy lord I honour as he is.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSET</speaker>
            <line>Why, what is he? as good a man as York.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VERNON</speaker>
            <line>Hark ye; not so: in witness, take ye that.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Strikes him</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASSET</speaker>
            <line>Villain, thou know'st the law of arms is such</line>
            <line>That whoso draws a sword, 'tis present death,</line>
            <line>Or else this blow should broach thy dearest blood.</line>
            <line>But I'll unto his majesty, and crave</line>
            <line>I may have liberty to venge this wrong;</line>
            <line>When thou shalt see I'll meet thee to thy cost.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VERNON</speaker>
            <line>Well, miscreant, I'll be there as soon as you;</line>
            <line>And, after, meet you sooner than you would.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>