<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net/doctypes/dita/shakespear/dtd/act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-5">
   <title>ACT V</title>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  London. The palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Sennet. Enter KING HENRY VI, GLOUCESTER, and EXETER</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Have you perused the letters from the pope,</line>
            <line>The emperor and the Earl of Armagnac?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>I have, my lord: and their intent is this:</line>
            <line>They humbly sue unto your excellence</line>
            <line>To have a godly peace concluded of</line>
            <line>Between the realms of England and of France.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>How doth your grace affect their motion?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Well, my good lord; and as the only means</line>
            <line>To stop effusion of our Christian blood</line>
            <line>And 'stablish quietness on every side.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Ay, marry, uncle; for I always thought</line>
            <line>It was both impious and unnatural</line>
            <line>That such immanity and bloody strife</line>
            <line>Should reign among professors of one faith.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Beside, my lord, the sooner to effect</line>
            <line>And surer bind this knot of amity,</line>
            <line>The Earl of Armagnac, near knit to Charles,</line>
            <line>A man of great authority in France,</line>
            <line>Proffers his only daughter to your grace</line>
            <line>In marriage, with a large and sumptuous dowry.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Marriage, uncle! alas, my years are young!</line>
            <line>And fitter is my study and my books</line>
            <line>Than wanton dalliance with a paramour.</line>
            <line>Yet call the ambassador; and, as you please,</line>
            <line>So let them have their answers every one:</line>
            <line>I shall be well content with any choice</line>
            <line>Tends to God's glory and my country's weal.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter CARDINAL OF WINCHESTER in Cardinal's habit,
a Legate and two Ambassadors</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EXETER</speaker>
            <line>What! is my Lord of Winchester install'd,</line>
            <line>And call'd unto a cardinal's degree?</line>
            <line>Then I perceive that will be verified</line>
            <line>Henry the Fifth did sometime prophesy,</line>
            <line>'If once he come to be a cardinal,</line>
            <line>He'll make his cap co-equal with the crown.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>My lords ambassadors, your several suits</line>
            <line>Have been consider'd and debated on.</line>
            <line>And therefore are we certainly resolved</line>
            <line>To draw conditions of a friendly peace;</line>
            <line>Which by my Lord of Winchester we mean</line>
            <line>Shall be transported presently to France.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>And for the proffer of my lord your master,</line>
            <line>I have inform'd his highness so at large</line>
            <line>As liking of the lady's virtuous gifts,</line>
            <line>Her beauty and the value of her dower,</line>
            <line>He doth intend she shall be England's queen.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>In argument and proof of which contract,</line>
            <line>Bear her this jewel, pledge of my affection.</line>
            <line>And so, my lord protector, see them guarded</line>
            <line>And safely brought to Dover; where inshipp'd</line>
            <line>Commit them to the fortune of the sea.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt all but CARDINAL OF WINCHESTER and Legate</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL OF WINCHESTER</speaker>
            <line>Stay, my lord legate: you shall first receive</line>
            <line>The sum of money which I promised</line>
            <line>Should be deliver'd to his holiness</line>
            <line>For clothing me in these grave ornaments.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Legate</speaker>
            <line>I will attend upon your lordship's leisure.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL OF WINCHESTER</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  Now Winchester will not submit, I trow,</line>
            <line>Or be inferior to the proudest peer.</line>
            <line>Humphrey of Gloucester, thou shalt well perceive</line>
            <line>That, neither in birth or for authority,</line>
            <line>The bishop will be overborne by thee:</line>
            <line>I'll either make thee stoop and bend thy knee,</line>
            <line>Or sack this country with a mutiny.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  France. Plains in Anjou.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter CHARLES, BURGUNDY, ALENCON, BASTARD OF
ORLEANS, REIGNIER, JOAN LA PUCELLE, and forces</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHARLES</speaker>
            <line>These news, my lord, may cheer our drooping spirits:</line>
            <line>'Tis said the stout Parisians do revolt</line>
            <line>And turn again unto the warlike French.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALENCON</speaker>
            <line>Then march to Paris, royal Charles of France,</line>
            <line>And keep not back your powers in dalliance.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOAN LA PUCELLE</speaker>
            <line>Peace be amongst them, if they turn to us;</line>
            <line>Else, ruin combat with their palaces!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter Scout</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Scout</speaker>
            <line>Success unto our valiant general,</line>
            <line>And happiness to his accomplices!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHARLES</speaker>
            <line>What tidings send our scouts? I prithee, speak.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Scout</speaker>
            <line>The English army, that divided was</line>
            <line>Into two parties, is now conjoined in one,</line>
            <line>And means to give you battle presently.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHARLES</speaker>
            <line>Somewhat too sudden, sirs, the warning is;</line>
            <line>But we will presently provide for them.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BURGUNDY</speaker>
            <line>I trust the ghost of Talbot is not there:</line>
            <line>Now he is gone, my lord, you need not fear.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOAN LA PUCELLE</speaker>
            <line>Of all base passions, fear is most accursed.</line>
            <line>Command the conquest, Charles, it shall be thine,</line>
            <line>Let Henry fret and all the world repine.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHARLES</speaker>
            <line>Then on, my lords; and France be fortunate!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  Before Angiers.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Alarum. Excursions. Enter JOAN LA PUCELLE</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOAN LA PUCELLE</speaker>
            <line>The regent conquers, and the Frenchmen fly.</line>
            <line>Now help, ye charming spells and periapts;</line>
            <line>And ye choice spirits that admonish me</line>
            <line>And give me signs of future accidents.</line>
            <stagedir>Thunder</stagedir>
            <line>You speedy helpers, that are substitutes</line>
            <line>Under the lordly monarch of the north,</line>
            <line>Appear and aid me in this enterprise.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter Fiends</stagedir>
            <line>This speedy and quick appearance argues proof</line>
            <line>Of your accustom'd diligence to me.</line>
            <line>Now, ye familiar spirits, that are cull'd</line>
            <line>Out of the powerful regions under earth,</line>
            <line>Help me this once, that France may get the field.</line>
            <stagedir>They walk, and speak not</stagedir>
            <line>O, hold me not with silence over-long!</line>
            <line>Where I was wont to feed you with my blood,</line>
            <line>I'll lop a member off and give it you</line>
            <line>In earnest of further benefit,</line>
            <line>So you do condescend to help me now.</line>
            <stagedir>They hang their heads</stagedir>
            <line>No hope to have redress? My body shall</line>
            <line>Pay recompense, if you will grant my suit.</line>
            <stagedir>They shake their heads</stagedir>
            <line>Cannot my body nor blood-sacrifice</line>
            <line>Entreat you to your wonted furtherance?</line>
            <line>Then take my soul, my body, soul and all,</line>
            <line>Before that England give the French the foil.</line>
            <stagedir>They depart</stagedir>
            <line>See, they forsake me! Now the time is come</line>
            <line>That France must vail her lofty-plumed crest</line>
            <line>And let her head fall into England's lap.</line>
            <line>My ancient incantations are too weak,</line>
            <line>And hell too strong for me to buckle with:</line>
            <line>Now, France, thy glory droopeth to the dust.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Excursions. Re-enter JOAN LA PUCELLE fighting hand
to hand with YORK JOAN LA PUCELLE is taken. The
French fly</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>Damsel of France, I think I have you fast:</line>
            <line>Unchain your spirits now with spelling charms</line>
            <line>And try if they can gain your liberty.</line>
            <line>A goodly prize, fit for the devil's grace!</line>
            <line>See, how the ugly wench doth bend her brows,</line>
            <line>As if with Circe she would change my shape!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOAN LA PUCELLE</speaker>
            <line>Changed to a worser shape thou canst not be.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>O, Charles the Dauphin is a proper man;</line>
            <line>No shape but his can please your dainty eye.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOAN LA PUCELLE</speaker>
            <line>A plaguing mischief light on Charles and thee!</line>
            <line>And may ye both be suddenly surprised</line>
            <line>By bloody hands, in sleeping on your beds!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>Fell banning hag, enchantress, hold thy tongue!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOAN LA PUCELLE</speaker>
            <line>I prithee, give me leave to curse awhile.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>Curse, miscreant, when thou comest to the stake.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Alarum. Enter SUFFOLK with MARGARET in his hand</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Be what thou wilt, thou art my prisoner.</line>
            <stagedir>Gazes on her</stagedir>
            <line>O fairest beauty, do not fear nor fly!</line>
            <line>For I will touch thee but with reverent hands;</line>
            <line>I kiss these fingers for eternal peace,</line>
            <line>And lay them gently on thy tender side.</line>
            <line>Who art thou? say, that I may honour thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Margaret my name, and daughter to a king,</line>
            <line>The King of Naples, whosoe'er thou art.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>An earl I am, and Suffolk am I call'd.</line>
            <line>Be not offended, nature's miracle,</line>
            <line>Thou art allotted to be ta'en by me:</line>
            <line>So doth the swan her downy cygnets save,</line>
            <line>Keeping them prisoner underneath her wings.</line>
            <line>Yet, if this servile usage once offend.</line>
            <line>Go, and be free again, as Suffolk's friend.</line>
            <stagedir>She is going</stagedir>
            <line>O, stay! I have no power to let her pass;</line>
            <line>My hand would free her, but my heart says no</line>
            <line>As plays the sun upon the glassy streams,</line>
            <line>Twinkling another counterfeited beam,</line>
            <line>So seems this gorgeous beauty to mine eyes.</line>
            <line>Fain would I woo her, yet I dare not speak:</line>
            <line>I'll call for pen and ink, and write my mind.</line>
            <line>Fie, de la Pole! disable not thyself;</line>
            <line>Hast not a tongue? is she not here?</line>
            <line>Wilt thou be daunted at a woman's sight?</line>
            <line>Ay, beauty's princely majesty is such,</line>
            <line>Confounds the tongue and makes the senses rough.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Say, Earl of Suffolk--if thy name be so--</line>
            <line>What ransom must I pay before I pass?</line>
            <line>For I perceive I am thy prisoner.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>How canst thou tell she will deny thy suit,</line>
            <line>Before thou make a trial of her love?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Why speak'st thou not? what ransom must I pay?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>She's beautiful, and therefore to be woo'd;</line>
            <line>She is a woman, therefore to be won.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Wilt thou accept of ransom? yea, or no.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Fond man, remember that thou hast a wife;</line>
            <line>Then how can Margaret be thy paramour?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>I were best to leave him, for he will not hear.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>There all is marr'd; there lies a cooling card.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>He talks at random; sure, the man is mad.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>And yet a dispensation may be had.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>And yet I would that you would answer me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>I'll win this Lady Margaret. For whom?</line>
            <line>Why, for my king: tush, that's a wooden thing!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>He talks of wood: it is some carpenter.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Yet so my fancy may be satisfied,</line>
            <line>And peace established between these realms</line>
            <line>But there remains a scruple in that too;</line>
            <line>For though her father be the King of Naples,</line>
            <line>Duke of Anjou and Maine, yet is he poor,</line>
            <line>And our nobility will scorn the match.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Hear ye, captain, are you not at leisure?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>It shall be so, disdain they ne'er so much.</line>
            <line>Henry is youthful and will quickly yield.</line>
            <line>Madam, I have a secret to reveal.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>What though I be enthrall'd? he seems a knight,</line>
            <line>And will not any way dishonour me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Lady, vouchsafe to listen what I say.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Perhaps I shall be rescued by the French;</line>
            <line>And then I need not crave his courtesy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Sweet madam, give me a hearing in a cause--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Tush, women have been captivate ere now.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Lady, wherefore talk you so?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>I cry you mercy, 'tis but Quid for Quo.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Say, gentle princess, would you not suppose</line>
            <line>Your bondage happy, to be made a queen?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>To be a queen in bondage is more vile</line>
            <line>Than is a slave in base servility;</line>
            <line>For princes should be free.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>And so shall you,</line>
            <line>If happy England's royal king be free.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Why, what concerns his freedom unto me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>I'll undertake to make thee Henry's queen,</line>
            <line>To put a golden sceptre in thy hand</line>
            <line>And set a precious crown upon thy head,</line>
            <line>If thou wilt condescend to be my--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>What?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>His love.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>I am unworthy to be Henry's wife.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>No, gentle madam; I unworthy am</line>
            <line>To woo so fair a dame to be his wife,</line>
            <line>And have no portion in the choice myself.</line>
            <line>How say you, madam, are ye so content?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>An if my father please, I am content.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Then call our captains and our colours forth.</line>
            <line>And, madam, at your father's castle walls</line>
            <line>We'll crave a parley, to confer with him.</line>
            <stagedir>A parley sounded. Enter REIGNIER on the walls</stagedir>
            <line>See, Reignier, see, thy daughter prisoner!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>REIGNIER</speaker>
            <line>To whom?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>To me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>REIGNIER</speaker>
            <line>Suffolk, what remedy?</line>
            <line>I am a soldier, and unapt to weep,</line>
            <line>Or to exclaim on fortune's fickleness.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Yes, there is remedy enough, my lord:</line>
            <line>Consent, and for thy honour give consent,</line>
            <line>Thy daughter shall be wedded to my king;</line>
            <line>Whom I with pain have woo'd and won thereto;</line>
            <line>And this her easy-held imprisonment</line>
            <line>Hath gained thy daughter princely liberty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>REIGNIER</speaker>
            <line>Speaks Suffolk as he thinks?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Fair Margaret knows</line>
            <line>That Suffolk doth not flatter, face, or feign.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>REIGNIER</speaker>
            <line>Upon thy princely warrant, I descend</line>
            <line>To give thee answer of thy just demand.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit from the walls</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>And here I will expect thy coming.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Trumpets sound. Enter REIGNIER, below</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>REIGNIER</speaker>
            <line>Welcome, brave earl, into our territories:</line>
            <line>Command in Anjou what your honour pleases.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Thanks, Reignier, happy for so sweet a child,</line>
            <line>Fit to be made companion with a king:</line>
            <line>What answer makes your grace unto my suit?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>REIGNIER</speaker>
            <line>Since thou dost deign to woo her little worth</line>
            <line>To be the princely bride of such a lord;</line>
            <line>Upon condition I may quietly</line>
            <line>Enjoy mine own, the country Maine and Anjou,</line>
            <line>Free from oppression or the stroke of war,</line>
            <line>My daughter shall be Henry's, if he please.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>That is her ransom; I deliver her;</line>
            <line>And those two counties I will undertake</line>
            <line>Your grace shall well and quietly enjoy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>REIGNIER</speaker>
            <line>And I again, in Henry's royal name,</line>
            <line>As deputy unto that gracious king,</line>
            <line>Give thee her hand, for sign of plighted faith.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Reignier of France, I give thee kingly thanks,</line>
            <line>Because this is in traffic of a king.</line>
            <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>
            <line>And yet, methinks, I could be well content</line>
            <line>To be mine own attorney in this case.</line>
            <line>I'll over then to England with this news,</line>
            <line>And make this marriage to be solemnized.</line>
            <line>So farewell, Reignier: set this diamond safe</line>
            <line>In golden palaces, as it becomes.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>REIGNIER</speaker>
            <line>I do embrace thee, as I would embrace</line>
            <line>The Christian prince, King Henry, were he here.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Farewell, my lord: good wishes, praise and prayers</line>
            <line>Shall Suffolk ever have of Margaret.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Going</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Farewell, sweet madam: but hark you, Margaret;</line>
            <line>No princely commendations to my king?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Such commendations as becomes a maid,</line>
            <line>A virgin and his servant, say to him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Words sweetly placed and modestly directed.</line>
            <line>But madam, I must trouble you again;</line>
            <line>No loving token to his majesty?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>Yes, my good lord, a pure unspotted heart,</line>
            <line>Never yet taint with love, I send the king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>And this withal.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Kisses her</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARGARET</speaker>
            <line>That for thyself: I will not so presume</line>
            <line>To send such peevish tokens to a king.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt REIGNIER and MARGARET</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>O, wert thou for myself! But, Suffolk, stay;</line>
            <line>Thou mayst not wander in that labyrinth;</line>
            <line>There Minotaurs and ugly treasons lurk.</line>
            <line>Solicit Henry with her wondrous praise:</line>
            <line>Bethink thee on her virtues that surmount,</line>
            <line>And natural graces that extinguish art;</line>
            <line>Repeat their semblance often on the seas,</line>
            <line>That, when thou comest to kneel at Henry's feet,</line>
            <line>Thou mayst bereave him of his wits with wonder.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-4">
      <title>SCENE IV.  Camp of the YORK in Anjou.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter YORK, WARWICK, and others</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>Bring forth that sorceress condemn'd to burn.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter JOAN LA PUCELLE, guarded, and a Shepherd</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Shepherd</speaker>
            <line>Ah, Joan, this kills thy father's heart outright!</line>
            <line>Have I sought every country far and near,</line>
            <line>And, now it is my chance to find thee out,</line>
            <line>Must I behold thy timeless cruel death?</line>
            <line>Ah, Joan, sweet daughter Joan, I'll die with thee!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOAN LA PUCELLE</speaker>
            <line>Decrepit miser! base ignoble wretch!</line>
            <line>I am descended of a gentler blood:</line>
            <line>Thou art no father nor no friend of mine.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Shepherd</speaker>
            <line>Out, out! My lords, an please you, 'tis not so;</line>
            <line>I did beget her, all the parish knows:</line>
            <line>Her mother liveth yet, can testify</line>
            <line>She was the first fruit of my bachelorship.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Graceless! wilt thou deny thy parentage?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>This argues what her kind of life hath been,</line>
            <line>Wicked and vile; and so her death concludes.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Shepherd</speaker>
            <line>Fie, Joan, that thou wilt be so obstacle!</line>
            <line>God knows thou art a collop of my flesh;</line>
            <line>And for thy sake have I shed many a tear:</line>
            <line>Deny me not, I prithee, gentle Joan.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOAN LA PUCELLE</speaker>
            <line>Peasant, avaunt! You have suborn'd this man,</line>
            <line>Of purpose to obscure my noble birth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Shepherd</speaker>
            <line>'Tis true, I gave a noble to the priest</line>
            <line>The morn that I was wedded to her mother.</line>
            <line>Kneel down and take my blessing, good my girl.</line>
            <line>Wilt thou not stoop? Now cursed be the time</line>
            <line>Of thy nativity! I would the milk</line>
            <line>Thy mother gave thee when thou suck'dst her breast,</line>
            <line>Had been a little ratsbane for thy sake!</line>
            <line>Or else, when thou didst keep my lambs a-field,</line>
            <line>I wish some ravenous wolf had eaten thee!</line>
            <line>Dost thou deny thy father, cursed drab?</line>
            <line>O, burn her, burn her! hanging is too good.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>Take her away; for she hath lived too long,</line>
            <line>To fill the world with vicious qualities.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOAN LA PUCELLE</speaker>
            <line>First, let me tell you whom you have condemn'd:</line>
            <line>Not me begotten of a shepherd swain,</line>
            <line>But issued from the progeny of kings;</line>
            <line>Virtuous and holy; chosen from above,</line>
            <line>By inspiration of celestial grace,</line>
            <line>To work exceeding miracles on earth.</line>
            <line>I never had to do with wicked spirits:</line>
            <line>But you, that are polluted with your lusts,</line>
            <line>Stain'd with the guiltless blood of innocents,</line>
            <line>Corrupt and tainted with a thousand vices,</line>
            <line>Because you want the grace that others have,</line>
            <line>You judge it straight a thing impossible</line>
            <line>To compass wonders but by help of devils.</line>
            <line>No, misconceived! Joan of Arc hath been</line>
            <line>A virgin from her tender infancy,</line>
            <line>Chaste and immaculate in very thought;</line>
            <line>Whose maiden blood, thus rigorously effused,</line>
            <line>Will cry for vengeance at the gates of heaven.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>Ay, ay: away with her to execution!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>And hark ye, sirs; because she is a maid,</line>
            <line>Spare for no faggots, let there be enow:</line>
            <line>Place barrels of pitch upon the fatal stake,</line>
            <line>That so her torture may be shortened.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOAN LA PUCELLE</speaker>
            <line>Will nothing turn your unrelenting hearts?</line>
            <line>Then, Joan, discover thine infirmity,</line>
            <line>That warranteth by law to be thy privilege.</line>
            <line>I am with child, ye bloody homicides:</line>
            <line>Murder not then the fruit within my womb,</line>
            <line>Although ye hale me to a violent death.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>Now heaven forfend! the holy maid with child!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>The greatest miracle that e'er ye wrought:</line>
            <line>Is all your strict preciseness come to this?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>She and the Dauphin have been juggling:</line>
            <line>I did imagine what would be her refuge.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Well, go to; we'll have no bastards live;</line>
            <line>Especially since Charles must father it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOAN LA PUCELLE</speaker>
            <line>You are deceived; my child is none of his:</line>
            <line>It was Alencon that enjoy'd my love.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>Alencon! that notorious Machiavel!</line>
            <line>It dies, an if it had a thousand lives.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOAN LA PUCELLE</speaker>
            <line>O, give me leave, I have deluded you:</line>
            <line>'Twas neither Charles nor yet the duke I named,</line>
            <line>But Reignier, king of Naples, that prevail'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>A married man! that's most intolerable.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>Why, here's a girl! I think she knows not well,</line>
            <line>There were so many, whom she may accuse.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>It's sign she hath been liberal and free.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>And yet, forsooth, she is a virgin pure.</line>
            <line>Strumpet, thy words condemn thy brat and thee:</line>
            <line>Use no entreaty, for it is in vain.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOAN LA PUCELLE</speaker>
            <line>Then lead me hence; with whom I leave my curse:</line>
            <line>May never glorious sun reflex his beams</line>
            <line>Upon the country where you make abode;</line>
            <line>But darkness and the gloomy shade of death</line>
            <line>Environ you, till mischief and despair</line>
            <line>Drive you to break your necks or hang yourselves!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit, guarded</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>Break thou in pieces and consume to ashes,</line>
            <line>Thou foul accursed minister of hell!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter CARDINAL OF WINCHESTER, attended</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL OF WINCHESTER</speaker>
            <line>Lord regent, I do greet your excellence</line>
            <line>With letters of commission from the king.</line>
            <line>For know, my lords, the states of Christendom,</line>
            <line>Moved with remorse of these outrageous broils,</line>
            <line>Have earnestly implored a general peace</line>
            <line>Betwixt our nation and the aspiring French;</line>
            <line>And here at hand the Dauphin and his train</line>
            <line>Approacheth, to confer about some matter.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>Is all our travail turn'd to this effect?</line>
            <line>After the slaughter of so many peers,</line>
            <line>So many captains, gentlemen and soldiers,</line>
            <line>That in this quarrel have been overthrown</line>
            <line>And sold their bodies for their country's benefit,</line>
            <line>Shall we at last conclude effeminate peace?</line>
            <line>Have we not lost most part of all the towns,</line>
            <line>By treason, falsehood and by treachery,</line>
            <line>Our great progenitors had conquered?</line>
            <line>O Warwick, Warwick! I foresee with grief</line>
            <line>The utter loss of all the realm of France.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Be patient, York: if we conclude a peace,</line>
            <line>It shall be with such strict and severe covenants</line>
            <line>As little shall the Frenchmen gain thereby.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter CHARLES, ALENCON, BASTARD OF ORLEANS,
REIGNIER, and others</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHARLES</speaker>
            <line>Since, lords of England, it is thus agreed</line>
            <line>That peaceful truce shall be proclaim'd in France,</line>
            <line>We come to be informed by yourselves</line>
            <line>What the conditions of that league must be.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>Speak, Winchester; for boiling choler chokes</line>
            <line>The hollow passage of my poison'd voice,</line>
            <line>By sight of these our baleful enemies.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL OF WINCHESTER</speaker>
            <line>Charles, and the rest, it is enacted thus:</line>
            <line>That, in regard King Henry gives consent,</line>
            <line>Of mere compassion and of lenity,</line>
            <line>To ease your country of distressful war,</line>
            <line>And suffer you to breathe in fruitful peace,</line>
            <line>You shall become true liegemen to his crown:</line>
            <line>And Charles, upon condition thou wilt swear</line>
            <line>To pay him tribute, submit thyself,</line>
            <line>Thou shalt be placed as viceroy under him,</line>
            <line>And still enjoy thy regal dignity.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALENCON</speaker>
            <line>Must he be then as shadow of himself?</line>
            <line>Adorn his temples with a coronet,</line>
            <line>And yet, in substance and authority,</line>
            <line>Retain but privilege of a private man?</line>
            <line>This proffer is absurd and reasonless.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHARLES</speaker>
            <line>'Tis known already that I am possess'd</line>
            <line>With more than half the Gallian territories,</line>
            <line>And therein reverenced for their lawful king:</line>
            <line>Shall I, for lucre of the rest unvanquish'd,</line>
            <line>Detract so much from that prerogative,</line>
            <line>As to be call'd but viceroy of the whole?</line>
            <line>No, lord ambassador, I'll rather keep</line>
            <line>That which I have than, coveting for more,</line>
            <line>Be cast from possibility of all.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>Insulting Charles! hast thou by secret means</line>
            <line>Used intercession to obtain a league,</line>
            <line>And, now the matter grows to compromise,</line>
            <line>Stand'st thou aloof upon comparison?</line>
            <line>Either accept the title thou usurp'st,</line>
            <line>Of benefit proceeding from our king</line>
            <line>And not of any challenge of desert,</line>
            <line>Or we will plague thee with incessant wars.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>REIGNIER</speaker>
            <line>My lord, you do not well in obstinacy</line>
            <line>To cavil in the course of this contract:</line>
            <line>If once it be neglected, ten to one</line>
            <line>We shall not find like opportunity.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALENCON</speaker>
            <line>To say the truth, it is your policy</line>
            <line>To save your subjects from such massacre</line>
            <line>And ruthless slaughters as are daily seen</line>
            <line>By our proceeding in hostility;</line>
            <line>And therefore take this compact of a truce,</line>
            <line>Although you break it when your pleasure serves.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>How say'st thou, Charles? shall our condition stand?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHARLES</speaker>
            <line>It shall;</line>
            <line>Only reserved, you claim no interest</line>
            <line>In any of our towns of garrison.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>YORK</speaker>
            <line>Then swear allegiance to his majesty,</line>
            <line>As thou art knight, never to disobey</line>
            <line>Nor be rebellious to the crown of England,</line>
            <line>Thou, nor thy nobles, to the crown of England.</line>
            <line>So, now dismiss your army when ye please:</line>
            <line>Hang up your ensign, let your drums be still,</line>
            <line>For here we entertain a solemn peace.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-5">
      <title>SCENE V.  London. The palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter SUFFOLK in conference with KING HENRY VI,
GLOUCESTER and EXETER</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Your wondrous rare description, noble earl,</line>
            <line>Of beauteous Margaret hath astonish'd me:</line>
            <line>Her virtues graced with external gifts</line>
            <line>Do breed love's settled passions in my heart:</line>
            <line>And like as rigor of tempestuous gusts</line>
            <line>Provokes the mightiest hulk against the tide,</line>
            <line>So am I driven by breath of her renown</line>
            <line>Either to suffer shipwreck or arrive</line>
            <line>Where I may have fruition of her love.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Tush, my good lord, this superficial tale</line>
            <line>Is but a preface of her worthy praise;</line>
            <line>The chief perfections of that lovely dame</line>
            <line>Had I sufficient skill to utter them,</line>
            <line>Would make a volume of enticing lines,</line>
            <line>Able to ravish any dull conceit:</line>
            <line>And, which is more, she is not so divine,</line>
            <line>So full-replete with choice of all delights,</line>
            <line>But with as humble lowliness of mind</line>
            <line>She is content to be at your command;</line>
            <line>Command, I mean, of virtuous chaste intents,</line>
            <line>To love and honour Henry as her lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>And otherwise will Henry ne'er presume.</line>
            <line>Therefore, my lord protector, give consent</line>
            <line>That Margaret may be England's royal queen.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>So should I give consent to flatter sin.</line>
            <line>You know, my lord, your highness is betroth'd</line>
            <line>Unto another lady of esteem:</line>
            <line>How shall we then dispense with that contract,</line>
            <line>And not deface your honour with reproach?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>As doth a ruler with unlawful oaths;</line>
            <line>Or one that, at a triumph having vow'd</line>
            <line>To try his strength, forsaketh yet the lists</line>
            <line>By reason of his adversary's odds:</line>
            <line>A poor earl's daughter is unequal odds,</line>
            <line>And therefore may be broke without offence.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Why, what, I pray, is Margaret more than that?</line>
            <line>Her father is no better than an earl,</line>
            <line>Although in glorious titles he excel.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Yes, lord, her father is a king,</line>
            <line>The King of Naples and Jerusalem;</line>
            <line>And of such great authority in France</line>
            <line>As his alliance will confirm our peace</line>
            <line>And keep the Frenchmen in allegiance.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>And so the Earl of Armagnac may do,</line>
            <line>Because he is near kinsman unto Charles.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EXETER</speaker>
            <line>Beside, his wealth doth warrant a liberal dower,</line>
            <line>Where Reignier sooner will receive than give.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>A dower, my lords! disgrace not so your king,</line>
            <line>That he should be so abject, base and poor,</line>
            <line>To choose for wealth and not for perfect love.</line>
            <line>Henry is able to enrich his queen</line>
            <line>And not seek a queen to make him rich:</line>
            <line>So worthless peasants bargain for their wives,</line>
            <line>As market-men for oxen, sheep, or horse.</line>
            <line>Marriage is a matter of more worth</line>
            <line>Than to be dealt in by attorneyship;</line>
            <line>Not whom we will, but whom his grace affects,</line>
            <line>Must be companion of his nuptial bed:</line>
            <line>And therefore, lords, since he affects her most,</line>
            <line>It most of all these reasons bindeth us,</line>
            <line>In our opinions she should be preferr'd.</line>
            <line>For what is wedlock forced but a hell,</line>
            <line>An age of discord and continual strife?</line>
            <line>Whereas the contrary bringeth bliss,</line>
            <line>And is a pattern of celestial peace.</line>
            <line>Whom should we match with Henry, being a king,</line>
            <line>But Margaret, that is daughter to a king?</line>
            <line>Her peerless feature, joined with her birth,</line>
            <line>Approves her fit for none but for a king:</line>
            <line>Her valiant courage and undaunted spirit,</line>
            <line>More than in women commonly is seen,</line>
            <line>Will answer our hope in issue of a king;</line>
            <line>For Henry, son unto a conqueror,</line>
            <line>Is likely to beget more conquerors,</line>
            <line>If with a lady of so high resolve</line>
            <line>As is fair Margaret he be link'd in love.</line>
            <line>Then yield, my lords; and here conclude with me</line>
            <line>That Margaret shall be queen, and none but she.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VI</speaker>
            <line>Whether it be through force of your report,</line>
            <line>My noble Lord of Suffolk, or for that</line>
            <line>My tender youth was never yet attaint</line>
            <line>With any passion of inflaming love,</line>
            <line>I cannot tell; but this I am assured,</line>
            <line>I feel such sharp dissension in my breast,</line>
            <line>Such fierce alarums both of hope and fear,</line>
            <line>As I am sick with working of my thoughts.</line>
            <line>Take, therefore, shipping; post, my lord, to France;</line>
            <line>Agree to any covenants, and procure</line>
            <line>That Lady Margaret do vouchsafe to come</line>
            <line>To cross the seas to England and be crown'd</line>
            <line>King Henry's faithful and anointed queen:</line>
            <line>For your expenses and sufficient charge,</line>
            <line>Among the people gather up a tenth.</line>
            <line>Be gone, I say; for, till you do return,</line>
            <line>I rest perplexed with a thousand cares.</line>
            <line>And you, good uncle, banish all offence:</line>
            <line>If you do censure me by what you were,</line>
            <line>Not what you are, I know it will excuse</line>
            <line>This sudden execution of my will.</line>
            <line>And so, conduct me where, from company,</line>
            <line>I may revolve and ruminate my grief.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GLOUCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Ay, grief, I fear me, both at first and last.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt GLOUCESTER and EXETER</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Thus Suffolk hath prevail'd; and thus he goes,</line>
            <line>As did the youthful Paris once to Greece,</line>
            <line>With hope to find the like event in love,</line>
            <line>But prosper better than the Trojan did.</line>
            <line>Margaret shall now be queen, and rule the king;</line>
            <line>But I will rule both her, the king and realm.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>