<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net/doctypes/dita/shakespear/dtd/act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-2">
   <title>ACT II</title>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  Before Orleans.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter a Sergeant of a band with two Sentinels</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Sergeant</speaker>
            <line>Sirs, take your places and be vigilant:</line>
            <line>If any noise or soldier you perceive</line>
            <line>Near to the walls, by some apparent sign</line>
            <line>Let us have knowledge at the court of guard.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Sentinel</speaker>
            <line>Sergeant, you shall.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit Sergeant</stagedir>
            <line>Thus are poor servitors,</line>
            <line>When others sleep upon their quiet beds,</line>
            <line>Constrain'd to watch in darkness, rain and cold.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter TALBOT, BEDFORD, BURGUNDY, and Forces, with
scaling-ladders, their drums beating a dead march</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TALBOT</speaker>
            <line>Lord Regent, and redoubted Burgundy,</line>
            <line>By whose approach the regions of Artois,</line>
            <line>Wallon and Picardy are friends to us,</line>
            <line>This happy night the Frenchmen are secure,</line>
            <line>Having all day caroused and banqueted:</line>
            <line>Embrace we then this opportunity</line>
            <line>As fitting best to quittance their deceit</line>
            <line>Contrived by art and baleful sorcery.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEDFORD</speaker>
            <line>Coward of France! how much he wrongs his fame,</line>
            <line>Despairing of his own arm's fortitude,</line>
            <line>To join with witches and the help of hell!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BURGUNDY</speaker>
            <line>Traitors have never other company.</line>
            <line>But what's that Pucelle whom they term so pure?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TALBOT</speaker>
            <line>A maid, they say.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEDFORD</speaker>
            <line>A maid! and be so martial!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BURGUNDY</speaker>
            <line>Pray God she prove not masculine ere long,</line>
            <line>If underneath the standard of the French</line>
            <line>She carry armour as she hath begun.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TALBOT</speaker>
            <line>Well, let them practise and converse with spirits:</line>
            <line>God is our fortress, in whose conquering name</line>
            <line>Let us resolve to scale their flinty bulwarks.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEDFORD</speaker>
            <line>Ascend, brave Talbot; we will follow thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TALBOT</speaker>
            <line>Not all together: better far, I guess,</line>
            <line>That we do make our entrance several ways;</line>
            <line>That, if it chance the one of us do fail,</line>
            <line>The other yet may rise against their force.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEDFORD</speaker>
            <line>Agreed: I'll to yond corner.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BURGUNDY</speaker>
            <line>And I to this.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TALBOT</speaker>
            <line>And here will Talbot mount, or make his grave.</line>
            <line>Now, Salisbury, for thee, and for the right</line>
            <line>Of English Henry, shall this night appear</line>
            <line>How much in duty I am bound to both.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Sentinels</speaker>
            <line>Arm! arm! the enemy doth make assault!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Cry: 'St. George,' 'A Talbot.'</stagedir>
         <stagedir>The French leap over the walls in their shirts.
Enter, several ways, the BASTARD OF ORLEANS,
ALENCON, and REIGNIER, half ready, and half unready</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALENCON</speaker>
            <line>How now, my lords! what, all unready so?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD OF ORLEANS</speaker>
            <line>Unready! ay, and glad we 'scaped so well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>REIGNIER</speaker>
            <line>'Twas time, I trow, to wake and leave our beds,</line>
            <line>Hearing alarums at our chamber-doors.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALENCON</speaker>
            <line>Of all exploits since first I follow'd arms,</line>
            <line>Ne'er heard I of a warlike enterprise</line>
            <line>More venturous or desperate than this.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD OF ORLEANS</speaker>
            <line>I think this Talbot be a fiend of hell.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>REIGNIER</speaker>
            <line>If not of hell, the heavens, sure, favour him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALENCON</speaker>
            <line>Here cometh Charles: I marvel how he sped.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD OF ORLEANS</speaker>
            <line>Tut, holy Joan was his defensive guard.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter CHARLES and JOAN LA PUCELLE</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHARLES</speaker>
            <line>Is this thy cunning, thou deceitful dame?</line>
            <line>Didst thou at first, to flatter us withal,</line>
            <line>Make us partakers of a little gain,</line>
            <line>That now our loss might be ten times so much?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOAN LA PUCELLE</speaker>
            <line>Wherefore is Charles impatient with his friend!</line>
            <line>At all times will you have my power alike?</line>
            <line>Sleeping or waking must I still prevail,</line>
            <line>Or will you blame and lay the fault on me?</line>
            <line>Improvident soldiers! had your watch been good,</line>
            <line>This sudden mischief never could have fall'n.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHARLES</speaker>
            <line>Duke of Alencon, this was your default,</line>
            <line>That, being captain of the watch to-night,</line>
            <line>Did look no better to that weighty charge.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALENCON</speaker>
            <line>Had all your quarters been as safely kept</line>
            <line>As that whereof I had the government,</line>
            <line>We had not been thus shamefully surprised.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BASTARD OF ORLEANS</speaker>
            <line>Mine was secure.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>REIGNIER</speaker>
            <line>And so was mine, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CHARLES</speaker>
            <line>And, for myself, most part of all this night,</line>
            <line>Within her quarter and mine own precinct</line>
            <line>I was employ'd in passing to and fro,</line>
            <line>About relieving of the sentinels:</line>
            <line>Then how or which way should they first break in?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JOAN LA PUCELLE</speaker>
            <line>Question, my lords, no further of the case,</line>
            <line>How or which way: 'tis sure they found some place</line>
            <line>But weakly guarded, where the breach was made.</line>
            <line>And now there rests no other shift but this;</line>
            <line>To gather our soldiers, scatter'd and dispersed,</line>
            <line>And lay new platforms to endamage them.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Alarum. Enter an English Soldier, crying 'A
Talbot! a Talbot!' They fly, leaving their
clothes behind</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Soldier</speaker>
            <line>I'll be so bold to take what they have left.</line>
            <line>The cry of Talbot serves me for a sword;</line>
            <line>For I have loaden me with many spoils,</line>
            <line>Using no other weapon but his name.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  Orleans. Within the town.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter TALBOT, BEDFORD, BURGUNDY, a Captain, and others</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEDFORD</speaker>
            <line>The day begins to break, and night is fled,</line>
            <line>Whose pitchy mantle over-veil'd the earth.</line>
            <line>Here sound retreat, and cease our hot pursuit.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Retreat sounded</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TALBOT</speaker>
            <line>Bring forth the body of old Salisbury,</line>
            <line>And here advance it in the market-place,</line>
            <line>The middle centre of this cursed town.</line>
            <line>Now have I paid my vow unto his soul;</line>
            <line>For every drop of blood was drawn from him,</line>
            <line>There hath at least five Frenchmen died tonight.</line>
            <line>And that hereafter ages may behold</line>
            <line>What ruin happen'd in revenge of him,</line>
            <line>Within their chiefest temple I'll erect</line>
            <line>A tomb, wherein his corpse shall be interr'd:</line>
            <line>Upon the which, that every one may read,</line>
            <line>Shall be engraved the sack of Orleans,</line>
            <line>The treacherous manner of his mournful death</line>
            <line>And what a terror he had been to France.</line>
            <line>But, lords, in all our bloody massacre,</line>
            <line>I muse we met not with the Dauphin's grace,</line>
            <line>His new-come champion, virtuous Joan of Arc,</line>
            <line>Nor any of his false confederates.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEDFORD</speaker>
            <line>'Tis thought, Lord Talbot, when the fight began,</line>
            <line>Roused on the sudden from their drowsy beds,</line>
            <line>They did amongst the troops of armed men</line>
            <line>Leap o'er the walls for refuge in the field.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BURGUNDY</speaker>
            <line>Myself, as far as I could well discern</line>
            <line>For smoke and dusky vapours of the night,</line>
            <line>Am sure I scared the Dauphin and his trull,</line>
            <line>When arm in arm they both came swiftly running,</line>
            <line>Like to a pair of loving turtle-doves</line>
            <line>That could not live asunder day or night.</line>
            <line>After that things are set in order here,</line>
            <line>We'll follow them with all the power we have.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter a Messenger</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>All hail, my lords! which of this princely train</line>
            <line>Call ye the warlike Talbot, for his acts</line>
            <line>So much applauded through the realm of France?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TALBOT</speaker>
            <line>Here is the Talbot: who would speak with him?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>The virtuous lady, Countess of Auvergne,</line>
            <line>With modesty admiring thy renown,</line>
            <line>By me entreats, great lord, thou wouldst vouchsafe</line>
            <line>To visit her poor castle where she lies,</line>
            <line>That she may boast she hath beheld the man</line>
            <line>Whose glory fills the world with loud report.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BURGUNDY</speaker>
            <line>Is it even so? Nay, then, I see our wars</line>
            <line>Will turn unto a peaceful comic sport,</line>
            <line>When ladies crave to be encounter'd with.</line>
            <line>You may not, my lord, despise her gentle suit.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TALBOT</speaker>
            <line>Ne'er trust me then; for when a world of men</line>
            <line>Could not prevail with all their oratory,</line>
            <line>Yet hath a woman's kindness over-ruled:</line>
            <line>And therefore tell her I return great thanks,</line>
            <line>And in submission will attend on her.</line>
            <line>Will not your honours bear me company?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BEDFORD</speaker>
            <line>No, truly; it is more than manners will:</line>
            <line>And I have heard it said, unbidden guests</line>
            <line>Are often welcomest when they are gone.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TALBOT</speaker>
            <line>Well then, alone, since there's no remedy,</line>
            <line>I mean to prove this lady's courtesy.</line>
            <line>Come hither, captain.</line>
            <stagedir>Whispers</stagedir>
            <line>You perceive my mind?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Captain</speaker>
            <line>I do, my lord, and mean accordingly.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  Auvergne. The COUNTESS's castle.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter the COUNTESS and her Porter</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS OF AUVERGNE</speaker>
            <line>Porter, remember what I gave in charge;</line>
            <line>And when you have done so, bring the keys to me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Porter</speaker>
            <line>Madam, I will.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS OF AUVERGNE</speaker>
            <line>The plot is laid: if all things fall out right,</line>
            <line>I shall as famous be by this exploit</line>
            <line>As Scythian Tomyris by Cyrus' death.</line>
            <line>Great is the rumor of this dreadful knight,</line>
            <line>And his achievements of no less account:</line>
            <line>Fain would mine eyes be witness with mine ears,</line>
            <line>To give their censure of these rare reports.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter Messenger and TALBOT</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>Madam,</line>
            <line>According as your ladyship desired,</line>
            <line>By message craved, so is Lord Talbot come.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS OF AUVERGNE</speaker>
            <line>And he is welcome. What! is this the man?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>Madam, it is.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS OF AUVERGNE</speaker>
            <line>Is this the scourge of France?</line>
            <line>Is this the Talbot, so much fear'd abroad</line>
            <line>That with his name the mothers still their babes?</line>
            <line>I see report is fabulous and false:</line>
            <line>I thought I should have seen some Hercules,</line>
            <line>A second Hector, for his grim aspect,</line>
            <line>And large proportion of his strong-knit limbs.</line>
            <line>Alas, this is a child, a silly dwarf!</line>
            <line>It cannot be this weak and writhled shrimp</line>
            <line>Should strike such terror to his enemies.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TALBOT</speaker>
            <line>Madam, I have been bold to trouble you;</line>
            <line>But since your ladyship is not at leisure,</line>
            <line>I'll sort some other time to visit you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS OF AUVERGNE</speaker>
            <line>What means he now? Go ask him whither he goes.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>Stay, my Lord Talbot; for my lady craves</line>
            <line>To know the cause of your abrupt departure.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TALBOT</speaker>
            <line>Marry, for that she's in a wrong belief,</line>
            <line>I go to certify her Talbot's here.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter Porter with keys</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS OF AUVERGNE</speaker>
            <line>If thou be he, then art thou prisoner.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TALBOT</speaker>
            <line>Prisoner! to whom?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS OF AUVERGNE</speaker>
            <line>To me, blood-thirsty lord;</line>
            <line>And for that cause I trained thee to my house.</line>
            <line>Long time thy shadow hath been thrall to me,</line>
            <line>For in my gallery thy picture hangs:</line>
            <line>But now the substance shall endure the like,</line>
            <line>And I will chain these legs and arms of thine,</line>
            <line>That hast by tyranny these many years</line>
            <line>Wasted our country, slain our citizens</line>
            <line>And sent our sons and husbands captivate.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TALBOT</speaker>
            <line>Ha, ha, ha!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS OF AUVERGNE</speaker>
            <line>Laughest thou, wretch? thy mirth shall turn to moan.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TALBOT</speaker>
            <line>I laugh to see your ladyship so fond</line>
            <line>To think that you have aught but Talbot's shadow</line>
            <line>Whereon to practise your severity.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS OF AUVERGNE</speaker>
            <line>Why, art not thou the man?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TALBOT</speaker>
            <line>I am indeed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS OF AUVERGNE</speaker>
            <line>Then have I substance too.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TALBOT</speaker>
            <line>No, no, I am but shadow of myself:</line>
            <line>You are deceived, my substance is not here;</line>
            <line>For what you see is but the smallest part</line>
            <line>And least proportion of humanity:</line>
            <line>I tell you, madam, were the whole frame here,</line>
            <line>It is of such a spacious lofty pitch,</line>
            <line>Your roof were not sufficient to contain't.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS OF AUVERGNE</speaker>
            <line>This is a riddling merchant for the nonce;</line>
            <line>He will be here, and yet he is not here:</line>
            <line>How can these contrarieties agree?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TALBOT</speaker>
            <line>That will I show you presently.</line>
            <stagedir>Winds his horn. Drums strike up: a peal of
ordnance. Enter soldiers</stagedir>
            <line>How say you, madam? are you now persuaded</line>
            <line>That Talbot is but shadow of himself?</line>
            <line>These are his substance, sinews, arms and strength,</line>
            <line>With which he yoketh your rebellious necks,</line>
            <line>Razeth your cities and subverts your towns</line>
            <line>And in a moment makes them desolate.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS OF AUVERGNE</speaker>
            <line>Victorious Talbot! pardon my abuse:</line>
            <line>I find thou art no less than fame hath bruited</line>
            <line>And more than may be gather'd by thy shape.</line>
            <line>Let my presumption not provoke thy wrath;</line>
            <line>For I am sorry that with reverence</line>
            <line>I did not entertain thee as thou art.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TALBOT</speaker>
            <line>Be not dismay'd, fair lady; nor misconstrue</line>
            <line>The mind of Talbot, as you did mistake</line>
            <line>The outward composition of his body.</line>
            <line>What you have done hath not offended me;</line>
            <line>Nor other satisfaction do I crave,</line>
            <line>But only, with your patience, that we may</line>
            <line>Taste of your wine and see what cates you have;</line>
            <line>For soldiers' stomachs always serve them well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS OF AUVERGNE</speaker>
            <line>With all my heart, and think me honoured</line>
            <line>To feast so great a warrior in my house.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-4">
      <title>SCENE IV.  London. The Temple-garden.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter the Earls of SOMERSET, SUFFOLK, and WARWICK;
RICHARD PLANTAGENET, VERNON, and another Lawyer</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD PLANTAGENET</speaker>
            <line>Great lords and gentlemen, what means this silence?</line>
            <line>Dare no man answer in a case of truth?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Within the Temple-hall we were too loud;</line>
            <line>The garden here is more convenient.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD PLANTAGENET</speaker>
            <line>Then say at once if I maintain'd the truth;</line>
            <line>Or else was wrangling Somerset in the error?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Faith, I have been a truant in the law,</line>
            <line>And never yet could frame my will to it;</line>
            <line>And therefore frame the law unto my will.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SOMERSET</speaker>
            <line>Judge you, my Lord of Warwick, then, between us.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Between two hawks, which flies the higher pitch;</line>
            <line>Between two dogs, which hath the deeper mouth;</line>
            <line>Between two blades, which bears the better temper:</line>
            <line>Between two horses, which doth bear him best;</line>
            <line>Between two girls, which hath the merriest eye;</line>
            <line>I have perhaps some shallow spirit of judgement;</line>
            <line>But in these nice sharp quillets of the law,</line>
            <line>Good faith, I am no wiser than a daw.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD PLANTAGENET</speaker>
            <line>Tut, tut, here is a mannerly forbearance:</line>
            <line>The truth appears so naked on my side</line>
            <line>That any purblind eye may find it out.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SOMERSET</speaker>
            <line>And on my side it is so well apparell'd,</line>
            <line>So clear, so shining and so evident</line>
            <line>That it will glimmer through a blind man's eye.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD PLANTAGENET</speaker>
            <line>Since you are tongue-tied and so loath to speak,</line>
            <line>In dumb significants proclaim your thoughts:</line>
            <line>Let him that is a true-born gentleman</line>
            <line>And stands upon the honour of his birth,</line>
            <line>If he suppose that I have pleaded truth,</line>
            <line>From off this brier pluck a white rose with me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SOMERSET</speaker>
            <line>Let him that is no coward nor no flatterer,</line>
            <line>But dare maintain the party of the truth,</line>
            <line>Pluck a red rose from off this thorn with me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>I love no colours, and without all colour</line>
            <line>Of base insinuating flattery</line>
            <line>I pluck this white rose with Plantagenet.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>I pluck this red rose with young Somerset</line>
            <line>And say withal I think he held the right.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VERNON</speaker>
            <line>Stay, lords and gentlemen, and pluck no more,</line>
            <line>Till you conclude that he upon whose side</line>
            <line>The fewest roses are cropp'd from the tree</line>
            <line>Shall yield the other in the right opinion.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SOMERSET</speaker>
            <line>Good Master Vernon, it is well objected:</line>
            <line>If I have fewest, I subscribe in silence.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD PLANTAGENET</speaker>
            <line>And I.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VERNON</speaker>
            <line>Then for the truth and plainness of the case.</line>
            <line>I pluck this pale and maiden blossom here,</line>
            <line>Giving my verdict on the white rose side.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SOMERSET</speaker>
            <line>Prick not your finger as you pluck it off,</line>
            <line>Lest bleeding you do paint the white rose red</line>
            <line>And fall on my side so, against your will.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VERNON</speaker>
            <line>If I my lord, for my opinion bleed,</line>
            <line>Opinion shall be surgeon to my hurt</line>
            <line>And keep me on the side where still I am.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SOMERSET</speaker>
            <line>Well, well, come on: who else?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lawyer</speaker>
            <line>Unless my study and my books be false,</line>
            <line>The argument you held was wrong in you:</line>
            <stagedir>To SOMERSET</stagedir>
            <line>In sign whereof I pluck a white rose too.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD PLANTAGENET</speaker>
            <line>Now, Somerset, where is your argument?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SOMERSET</speaker>
            <line>Here in my scabbard, meditating that</line>
            <line>Shall dye your white rose in a bloody red.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD PLANTAGENET</speaker>
            <line>Meantime your cheeks do counterfeit our roses;</line>
            <line>For pale they look with fear, as witnessing</line>
            <line>The truth on our side.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SOMERSET</speaker>
            <line>No, Plantagenet,</line>
            <line>'Tis not for fear but anger that thy cheeks</line>
            <line>Blush for pure shame to counterfeit our roses,</line>
            <line>And yet thy tongue will not confess thy error.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD PLANTAGENET</speaker>
            <line>Hath not thy rose a canker, Somerset?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SOMERSET</speaker>
            <line>Hath not thy rose a thorn, Plantagenet?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD PLANTAGENET</speaker>
            <line>Ay, sharp and piercing, to maintain his truth;</line>
            <line>Whiles thy consuming canker eats his falsehood.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SOMERSET</speaker>
            <line>Well, I'll find friends to wear my bleeding roses,</line>
            <line>That shall maintain what I have said is true,</line>
            <line>Where false Plantagenet dare not be seen.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD PLANTAGENET</speaker>
            <line>Now, by this maiden blossom in my hand,</line>
            <line>I scorn thee and thy fashion, peevish boy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Turn not thy scorns this way, Plantagenet.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD PLANTAGENET</speaker>
            <line>Proud Pole, I will, and scorn both him and thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>I'll turn my part thereof into thy throat.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SOMERSET</speaker>
            <line>Away, away, good William de la Pole!</line>
            <line>We grace the yeoman by conversing with him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>Now, by God's will, thou wrong'st him, Somerset;</line>
            <line>His grandfather was Lionel Duke of Clarence,</line>
            <line>Third son to the third Edward King of England:</line>
            <line>Spring crestless yeomen from so deep a root?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD PLANTAGENET</speaker>
            <line>He bears him on the place's privilege,</line>
            <line>Or durst not, for his craven heart, say thus.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SOMERSET</speaker>
            <line>By him that made me, I'll maintain my words</line>
            <line>On any plot of ground in Christendom.</line>
            <line>Was not thy father, Richard Earl of Cambridge,</line>
            <line>For treason executed in our late king's days?</line>
            <line>And, by his treason, stand'st not thou attainted,</line>
            <line>Corrupted, and exempt from ancient gentry?</line>
            <line>His trespass yet lives guilty in thy blood;</line>
            <line>And, till thou be restored, thou art a yeoman.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD PLANTAGENET</speaker>
            <line>My father was attached, not attainted,</line>
            <line>Condemn'd to die for treason, but no traitor;</line>
            <line>And that I'll prove on better men than Somerset,</line>
            <line>Were growing time once ripen'd to my will.</line>
            <line>For your partaker Pole and you yourself,</line>
            <line>I'll note you in my book of memory,</line>
            <line>To scourge you for this apprehension:</line>
            <line>Look to it well and say you are well warn'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SOMERSET</speaker>
            <line>Ah, thou shalt find us ready for thee still;</line>
            <line>And know us by these colours for thy foes,</line>
            <line>For these my friends in spite of thee shall wear.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD PLANTAGENET</speaker>
            <line>And, by my soul, this pale and angry rose,</line>
            <line>As cognizance of my blood-drinking hate,</line>
            <line>Will I for ever and my faction wear,</line>
            <line>Until it wither with me to my grave</line>
            <line>Or flourish to the height of my degree.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Go forward and be choked with thy ambition!</line>
            <line>And so farewell until I meet thee next.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SOMERSET</speaker>
            <line>Have with thee, Pole. Farewell, ambitious Richard.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD PLANTAGENET</speaker>
            <line>How I am braved and must perforce endure it!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WARWICK</speaker>
            <line>This blot that they object against your house</line>
            <line>Shall be wiped out in the next parliament</line>
            <line>Call'd for the truce of Winchester and Gloucester;</line>
            <line>And if thou be not then created York,</line>
            <line>I will not live to be accounted Warwick.</line>
            <line>Meantime, in signal of my love to thee,</line>
            <line>Against proud Somerset and William Pole,</line>
            <line>Will I upon thy party wear this rose:</line>
            <line>And here I prophesy: this brawl to-day,</line>
            <line>Grown to this faction in the Temple-garden,</line>
            <line>Shall send between the red rose and the white</line>
            <line>A thousand souls to death and deadly night.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD PLANTAGENET</speaker>
            <line>Good Master Vernon, I am bound to you,</line>
            <line>That you on my behalf would pluck a flower.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VERNON</speaker>
            <line>In your behalf still will I wear the same.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lawyer</speaker>
            <line>And so will I.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD PLANTAGENET</speaker>
            <line>Thanks, gentle sir.</line>
            <line>Come, let us four to dinner: I dare say</line>
            <line>This quarrel will drink blood another day.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-5">
      <title>SCENE V.  The Tower of London.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter MORTIMER, brought in a chair, and Gaolers</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MORTIMER</speaker>
            <line>Kind keepers of my weak decaying age,</line>
            <line>Let dying Mortimer here rest himself.</line>
            <line>Even like a man new haled from the rack,</line>
            <line>So fare my limbs with long imprisonment.</line>
            <line>And these grey locks, the pursuivants of death,</line>
            <line>Nestor-like aged in an age of care,</line>
            <line>Argue the end of Edmund Mortimer.</line>
            <line>These eyes, like lamps whose wasting oil is spent,</line>
            <line>Wax dim, as drawing to their exigent;</line>
            <line>Weak shoulders, overborne with burthening grief,</line>
            <line>And pithless arms, like to a wither'd vine</line>
            <line>That droops his sapless branches to the ground;</line>
            <line>Yet are these feet, whose strengthless stay is numb,</line>
            <line>Unable to support this lump of clay,</line>
            <line>Swift-winged with desire to get a grave,</line>
            <line>As witting I no other comfort have.</line>
            <line>But tell me, keeper, will my nephew come?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Gaoler</speaker>
            <line>Richard Plantagenet, my lord, will come:</line>
            <line>We sent unto the Temple, unto his chamber;</line>
            <line>And answer was return'd that he will come.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MORTIMER</speaker>
            <line>Enough: my soul shall then be satisfied.</line>
            <line>Poor gentleman! his wrong doth equal mine.</line>
            <line>Since Henry Monmouth first began to reign,</line>
            <line>Before whose glory I was great in arms,</line>
            <line>This loathsome sequestration have I had:</line>
            <line>And even since then hath Richard been obscured,</line>
            <line>Deprived of honour and inheritance.</line>
            <line>But now the arbitrator of despairs,</line>
            <line>Just death, kind umpire of men's miseries,</line>
            <line>With sweet enlargement doth dismiss me hence:</line>
            <line>I would his troubles likewise were expired,</line>
            <line>That so he might recover what was lost.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter RICHARD PLANTAGENET</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Gaoler</speaker>
            <line>My lord, your loving nephew now is come.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MORTIMER</speaker>
            <line>Richard Plantagenet, my friend, is he come?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD PLANTAGENET</speaker>
            <line>Ay, noble uncle, thus ignobly used,</line>
            <line>Your nephew, late despised Richard, comes.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MORTIMER</speaker>
            <line>Direct mine arms I may embrace his neck,</line>
            <line>And in his bosom spend my latter gasp:</line>
            <line>O, tell me when my lips do touch his cheeks,</line>
            <line>That I may kindly give one fainting kiss.</line>
            <line>And now declare, sweet stem from York's great stock,</line>
            <line>Why didst thou say, of late thou wert despised?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD PLANTAGENET</speaker>
            <line>First, lean thine aged back against mine arm;</line>
            <line>And, in that ease, I'll tell thee my disease.</line>
            <line>This day, in argument upon a case,</line>
            <line>Some words there grew 'twixt Somerset and me;</line>
            <line>Among which terms he used his lavish tongue</line>
            <line>And did upbraid me with my father's death:</line>
            <line>Which obloquy set bars before my tongue,</line>
            <line>Else with the like I had requited him.</line>
            <line>Therefore, good uncle, for my father's sake,</line>
            <line>In honour of a true Plantagenet</line>
            <line>And for alliance sake, declare the cause</line>
            <line>My father, Earl of Cambridge, lost his head.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MORTIMER</speaker>
            <line>That cause, fair nephew, that imprison'd me</line>
            <line>And hath detain'd me all my flowering youth</line>
            <line>Within a loathsome dungeon, there to pine,</line>
            <line>Was cursed instrument of his decease.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD PLANTAGENET</speaker>
            <line>Discover more at large what cause that was,</line>
            <line>For I am ignorant and cannot guess.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MORTIMER</speaker>
            <line>I will, if that my fading breath permit</line>
            <line>And death approach not ere my tale be done.</line>
            <line>Henry the Fourth, grandfather to this king,</line>
            <line>Deposed his nephew Richard, Edward's son,</line>
            <line>The first-begotten and the lawful heir,</line>
            <line>Of Edward king, the third of that descent:</line>
            <line>During whose reign the Percies of the north,</line>
            <line>Finding his usurpation most unjust,</line>
            <line>Endeavor'd my advancement to the throne:</line>
            <line>The reason moved these warlike lords to this</line>
            <line>Was, for that--young King Richard thus removed,</line>
            <line>Leaving no heir begotten of his body--</line>
            <line>I was the next by birth and parentage;</line>
            <line>For by my mother I derived am</line>
            <line>From Lionel Duke of Clarence, the third son</line>
            <line>To King Edward the Third; whereas he</line>
            <line>From John of Gaunt doth bring his pedigree,</line>
            <line>Being but fourth of that heroic line.</line>
            <line>But mark: as in this haughty attempt</line>
            <line>They laboured to plant the rightful heir,</line>
            <line>I lost my liberty and they their lives.</line>
            <line>Long after this, when Henry the Fifth,</line>
            <line>Succeeding his father Bolingbroke, did reign,</line>
            <line>Thy father, Earl of Cambridge, then derived</line>
            <line>From famous Edmund Langley, Duke of York,</line>
            <line>Marrying my sister that thy mother was,</line>
            <line>Again in pity of my hard distress</line>
            <line>Levied an army, weening to redeem</line>
            <line>And have install'd me in the diadem:</line>
            <line>But, as the rest, so fell that noble earl</line>
            <line>And was beheaded. Thus the Mortimers,</line>
            <line>In whom the tide rested, were suppress'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD PLANTAGENET</speaker>
            <line>Of which, my lord, your honour is the last.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MORTIMER</speaker>
            <line>True; and thou seest that I no issue have</line>
            <line>And that my fainting words do warrant death;</line>
            <line>Thou art my heir; the rest I wish thee gather:</line>
            <line>But yet be wary in thy studious care.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD PLANTAGENET</speaker>
            <line>Thy grave admonishments prevail with me:</line>
            <line>But yet, methinks, my father's execution</line>
            <line>Was nothing less than bloody tyranny.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MORTIMER</speaker>
            <line>With silence, nephew, be thou politic:</line>
            <line>Strong-fixed is the house of Lancaster,</line>
            <line>And like a mountain, not to be removed.</line>
            <line>But now thy uncle is removing hence:</line>
            <line>As princes do their courts, when they are cloy'd</line>
            <line>With long continuance in a settled place.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD PLANTAGENET</speaker>
            <line>O, uncle, would some part of my young years</line>
            <line>Might but redeem the passage of your age!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MORTIMER</speaker>
            <line>Thou dost then wrong me, as that slaughterer doth</line>
            <line>Which giveth many wounds when one will kill.</line>
            <line>Mourn not, except thou sorrow for my good;</line>
            <line>Only give order for my funeral:</line>
            <line>And so farewell, and fair be all thy hopes</line>
            <line>And prosperous be thy life in peace and war!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Dies</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>RICHARD PLANTAGENET</speaker>
            <line>And peace, no war, befall thy parting soul!</line>
            <line>In prison hast thou spent a pilgrimage</line>
            <line>And like a hermit overpass'd thy days.</line>
            <line>Well, I will lock his counsel in my breast;</line>
            <line>And what I do imagine let that rest.</line>
            <line>Keepers, convey him hence, and I myself</line>
            <line>Will see his burial better than his life.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt Gaolers, bearing out the body of MORTIMER</stagedir>
            <line>Here dies the dusky torch of Mortimer,</line>
            <line>Choked with ambition of the meaner sort:</line>
            <line>And for those wrongs, those bitter injuries,</line>
            <line>Which Somerset hath offer'd to my house:</line>
            <line>I doubt not but with honour to redress;</line>
            <line>And therefore haste I to the parliament,</line>
            <line>Either to be restored to my blood,</line>
            <line>Or make my ill the advantage of my good.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>