<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net/doctypes/dita/shakespear/dtd/act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-3">
   <title>ACT III</title>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  London. QUEEN KATHARINE's apartments.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter QUEEN KATHARINE and her Women, as at work</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN KATHARINE</speaker>
            <line>Take thy lute, wench: my soul grows sad with troubles;</line>
            <line>Sing, and disperse 'em, if thou canst: leave working.</line>
            <stagedir>SONG</stagedir>
            <line>Orpheus with his lute made trees,</line>
            <line>And the mountain tops that freeze,</line>
            <line>Bow themselves when he did sing:</line>
            <line>To his music plants and flowers</line>
            <line>Ever sprung; as sun and showers</line>
            <line>There had made a lasting spring.</line>
            <line>Every thing that heard him play,</line>
            <line>Even the billows of the sea,</line>
            <line>Hung their heads, and then lay by.</line>
            <line>In sweet music is such art,</line>
            <line>Killing care and grief of heart</line>
            <line>Fall asleep, or hearing, die.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter a Gentleman</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN KATHARINE</speaker>
            <line>How now!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Gentleman</speaker>
            <line>An't please your grace, the two great cardinals</line>
            <line>Wait in the presence.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN KATHARINE</speaker>
            <line>Would they speak with me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Gentleman</speaker>
            <line>They will'd me say so, madam.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN KATHARINE</speaker>
            <line>Pray their graces</line>
            <line>To come near.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit Gentleman</stagedir>
            <line>What can be their business</line>
            <line>With me, a poor weak woman, fall'n from favour?</line>
            <line>I do not like their coming. Now I think on't,</line>
            <line>They should be good men; their affairs as righteous:</line>
            <line>But all hoods make not monks.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter CARDINAL WOLSEY and CARDINAL CAMPEIUS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL WOLSEY</speaker>
            <line>Peace to your highness!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN KATHARINE</speaker>
            <line>Your graces find me here part of a housewife,</line>
            <line>I would be all, against the worst may happen.</line>
            <line>What are your pleasures with me, reverend lords?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL WOLSEY</speaker>
            <line>May it please you noble madam, to withdraw</line>
            <line>Into your private chamber, we shall give you</line>
            <line>The full cause of our coming.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN KATHARINE</speaker>
            <line>Speak it here:</line>
            <line>There's nothing I have done yet, o' my conscience,</line>
            <line>Deserves a corner: would all other women</line>
            <line>Could speak this with as free a soul as I do!</line>
            <line>My lords, I care not, so much I am happy</line>
            <line>Above a number, if my actions</line>
            <line>Were tried by every tongue, every eye saw 'em,</line>
            <line>Envy and base opinion set against 'em,</line>
            <line>I know my life so even. If your business</line>
            <line>Seek me out, and that way I am wife in,</line>
            <line>Out with it boldly: truth loves open dealing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL WOLSEY</speaker>
            <line>Tanta est erga te mentis integritas, regina</line>
            <line>serenissima,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN KATHARINE</speaker>
            <line>O, good my lord, no Latin;</line>
            <line>I am not such a truant since my coming,</line>
            <line>As not to know the language I have lived in:</line>
            <line>A strange tongue makes my cause more strange,</line>
            <line>suspicious;</line>
            <line>Pray, speak in English: here are some will thank you,</line>
            <line>If you speak truth, for their poor mistress' sake;</line>
            <line>Believe me, she has had much wrong: lord cardinal,</line>
            <line>The willing'st sin I ever yet committed</line>
            <line>May be absolved in English.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL WOLSEY</speaker>
            <line>Noble lady,</line>
            <line>I am sorry my integrity should breed,</line>
            <line>And service to his majesty and you,</line>
            <line>So deep suspicion, where all faith was meant.</line>
            <line>We come not by the way of accusation,</line>
            <line>To taint that honour every good tongue blesses,</line>
            <line>Nor to betray you any way to sorrow,</line>
            <line>You have too much, good lady; but to know</line>
            <line>How you stand minded in the weighty difference</line>
            <line>Between the king and you; and to deliver,</line>
            <line>Like free and honest men, our just opinions</line>
            <line>And comforts to your cause.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL CAMPEIUS</speaker>
            <line>Most honour'd madam,</line>
            <line>My Lord of York, out of his noble nature,</line>
            <line>Zeal and obedience he still bore your grace,</line>
            <line>Forgetting, like a good man your late censure</line>
            <line>Both of his truth and him, which was too far,</line>
            <line>Offers, as I do, in a sign of peace,</line>
            <line>His service and his counsel.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN KATHARINE</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir> To betray me.--</line>
            <line>My lords, I thank you both for your good wills;</line>
            <line>Ye speak like honest men; pray God, ye prove so!</line>
            <line>But how to make ye suddenly an answer,</line>
            <line>In such a point of weight, so near mine honour,--</line>
            <line>More near my life, I fear,--with my weak wit,</line>
            <line>And to such men of gravity and learning,</line>
            <line>In truth, I know not. I was set at work</line>
            <line>Among my maids: full little, God knows, looking</line>
            <line>Either for such men or such business.</line>
            <line>For her sake that I have been,--for I feel</line>
            <line>The last fit of my greatness,--good your graces,</line>
            <line>Let me have time and counsel for my cause:</line>
            <line>Alas, I am a woman, friendless, hopeless!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL WOLSEY</speaker>
            <line>Madam, you wrong the king's love with these fears:</line>
            <line>Your hopes and friends are infinite.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN KATHARINE</speaker>
            <line>In England</line>
            <line>But little for my profit: can you think, lords,</line>
            <line>That any Englishman dare give me counsel?</line>
            <line>Or be a known friend, 'gainst his highness' pleasure,</line>
            <line>Though he be grown so desperate to be honest,</line>
            <line>And live a subject? Nay, forsooth, my friends,</line>
            <line>They that must weigh out my afflictions,</line>
            <line>They that my trust must grow to, live not here:</line>
            <line>They are, as all my other comforts, far hence</line>
            <line>In mine own country, lords.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL CAMPEIUS</speaker>
            <line>I would your grace</line>
            <line>Would leave your griefs, and take my counsel.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN KATHARINE</speaker>
            <line>How, sir?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL CAMPEIUS</speaker>
            <line>Put your main cause into the king's protection;</line>
            <line>He's loving and most gracious: 'twill be much</line>
            <line>Both for your honour better and your cause;</line>
            <line>For if the trial of the law o'ertake ye,</line>
            <line>You'll part away disgraced.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL WOLSEY</speaker>
            <line>He tells you rightly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN KATHARINE</speaker>
            <line>Ye tell me what ye wish for both,--my ruin:</line>
            <line>Is this your Christian counsel? out upon ye!</line>
            <line>Heaven is above all yet; there sits a judge</line>
            <line>That no king can corrupt.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL CAMPEIUS</speaker>
            <line>Your rage mistakes us.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN KATHARINE</speaker>
            <line>The more shame for ye: holy men I thought ye,</line>
            <line>Upon my soul, two reverend cardinal virtues;</line>
            <line>But cardinal sins and hollow hearts I fear ye:</line>
            <line>Mend 'em, for shame, my lords. Is this your comfort?</line>
            <line>The cordial that ye bring a wretched lady,</line>
            <line>A woman lost among ye, laugh'd at, scorn'd?</line>
            <line>I will not wish ye half my miseries;</line>
            <line>I have more charity: but say, I warn'd ye;</line>
            <line>Take heed, for heaven's sake, take heed, lest at once</line>
            <line>The burthen of my sorrows fall upon ye.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL WOLSEY</speaker>
            <line>Madam, this is a mere distraction;</line>
            <line>You turn the good we offer into envy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN KATHARINE</speaker>
            <line>Ye turn me into nothing: woe upon ye</line>
            <line>And all such false professors! would you have me--</line>
            <line>If you have any justice, any pity;</line>
            <line>If ye be any thing but churchmen's habits--</line>
            <line>Put my sick cause into his hands that hates me?</line>
            <line>Alas, has banish'd me his bed already,</line>
            <line>His love, too long ago! I am old, my lords,</line>
            <line>And all the fellowship I hold now with him</line>
            <line>Is only my obedience. What can happen</line>
            <line>To me above this wretchedness? all your studies</line>
            <line>Make me a curse like this.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL CAMPEIUS</speaker>
            <line>Your fears are worse.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN KATHARINE</speaker>
            <line>Have I lived thus long--let me speak myself,</line>
            <line>Since virtue finds no friends--a wife, a true one?</line>
            <line>A woman, I dare say without vain-glory,</line>
            <line>Never yet branded with suspicion?</line>
            <line>Have I with all my full affections</line>
            <line>Still met the king? loved him next heaven?</line>
            <line>obey'd him?</line>
            <line>Been, out of fondness, superstitious to him?</line>
            <line>Almost forgot my prayers to content him?</line>
            <line>And am I thus rewarded? 'tis not well, lords.</line>
            <line>Bring me a constant woman to her husband,</line>
            <line>One that ne'er dream'd a joy beyond his pleasure;</line>
            <line>And to that woman, when she has done most,</line>
            <line>Yet will I add an honour, a great patience.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL WOLSEY</speaker>
            <line>Madam, you wander from the good we aim at.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN KATHARINE</speaker>
            <line>My lord, I dare not make myself so guilty,</line>
            <line>To give up willingly that noble title</line>
            <line>Your master wed me to: nothing but death</line>
            <line>Shall e'er divorce my dignities.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL WOLSEY</speaker>
            <line>Pray, hear me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN KATHARINE</speaker>
            <line>Would I had never trod this English earth,</line>
            <line>Or felt the flatteries that grow upon it!</line>
            <line>Ye have angels' faces, but heaven knows your hearts.</line>
            <line>What will become of me now, wretched lady!</line>
            <line>I am the most unhappy woman living.</line>
            <line>Alas, poor wenches, where are now your fortunes!</line>
            <line>Shipwreck'd upon a kingdom, where no pity,</line>
            <line>No friend, no hope; no kindred weep for me;</line>
            <line>Almost no grave allow'd me: like the lily,</line>
            <line>That once was mistress of the field and flourish'd,</line>
            <line>I'll hang my head and perish.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL WOLSEY</speaker>
            <line>If your grace</line>
            <line>Could but be brought to know our ends are honest,</line>
            <line>You'ld feel more comfort: why should we, good lady,</line>
            <line>Upon what cause, wrong you? alas, our places,</line>
            <line>The way of our profession is against it:</line>
            <line>We are to cure such sorrows, not to sow 'em.</line>
            <line>For goodness' sake, consider what you do;</line>
            <line>How you may hurt yourself, ay, utterly</line>
            <line>Grow from the king's acquaintance, by this carriage.</line>
            <line>The hearts of princes kiss obedience,</line>
            <line>So much they love it; but to stubborn spirits</line>
            <line>They swell, and grow as terrible as storms.</line>
            <line>I know you have a gentle, noble temper,</line>
            <line>A soul as even as a calm: pray, think us</line>
            <line>Those we profess, peace-makers, friends, and servants.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL CAMPEIUS</speaker>
            <line>Madam, you'll find it so. You wrong your virtues</line>
            <line>With these weak women's fears: a noble spirit,</line>
            <line>As yours was put into you, ever casts</line>
            <line>Such doubts, as false coin, from it. The king loves you;</line>
            <line>Beware you lose it not: for us, if you please</line>
            <line>To trust us in your business, we are ready</line>
            <line>To use our utmost studies in your service.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>QUEEN KATHARINE</speaker>
            <line>Do what ye will, my lords: and, pray, forgive me,</line>
            <line>If I have used myself unmannerly;</line>
            <line>You know I am a woman, lacking wit</line>
            <line>To make a seemly answer to such persons.</line>
            <line>Pray, do my service to his majesty:</line>
            <line>He has my heart yet; and shall have my prayers</line>
            <line>While I shall have my life. Come, reverend fathers,</line>
            <line>Bestow your counsels on me: she now begs,</line>
            <line>That little thought, when she set footing here,</line>
            <line>She should have bought her dignities so dear.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  Ante-chamber to KING HENRY VIII's apartment.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter NORFOLK, SUFFOLK, SURREY, and Chamberlain</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORFOLK</speaker>
            <line>If you will now unite in your complaints,</line>
            <line>And force them with a constancy, the cardinal</line>
            <line>Cannot stand under them: if you omit</line>
            <line>The offer of this time, I cannot promise</line>
            <line>But that you shall sustain moe new disgraces,</line>
            <line>With these you bear already.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SURREY</speaker>
            <line>I am joyful</line>
            <line>To meet the least occasion that may give me</line>
            <line>Remembrance of my father-in-law, the duke,</line>
            <line>To be revenged on him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Which of the peers</line>
            <line>Have uncontemn'd gone by him, or at least</line>
            <line>Strangely neglected? when did he regard</line>
            <line>The stamp of nobleness in any person</line>
            <line>Out of himself?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Chamberlain</speaker>
            <line>My lords, you speak your pleasures:</line>
            <line>What he deserves of you and me I know;</line>
            <line>What we can do to him, though now the time</line>
            <line>Gives way to us, I much fear. If you cannot</line>
            <line>Bar his access to the king, never attempt</line>
            <line>Any thing on him; for he hath a witchcraft</line>
            <line>Over the king in's tongue.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORFOLK</speaker>
            <line>O, fear him not;</line>
            <line>His spell in that is out: the king hath found</line>
            <line>Matter against him that for ever mars</line>
            <line>The honey of his language. No, he's settled,</line>
            <line>Not to come off, in his displeasure.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SURREY</speaker>
            <line>Sir,</line>
            <line>I should be glad to hear such news as this</line>
            <line>Once every hour.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Believe it, this is true:</line>
            <line>In the divorce his contrary proceedings</line>
            <line>Are all unfolded wherein he appears</line>
            <line>As I would wish mine enemy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SURREY</speaker>
            <line>How came</line>
            <line>His practises to light?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Most strangely.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SURREY</speaker>
            <line>O, how, how?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>The cardinal's letters to the pope miscarried,</line>
            <line>And came to the eye o' the king: wherein was read,</line>
            <line>How that the cardinal did entreat his holiness</line>
            <line>To stay the judgment o' the divorce; for if</line>
            <line>It did take place, 'I do,' quoth he, 'perceive</line>
            <line>My king is tangled in affection to</line>
            <line>A creature of the queen's, Lady Anne Bullen.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SURREY</speaker>
            <line>Has the king this?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Believe it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SURREY</speaker>
            <line>Will this work?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Chamberlain</speaker>
            <line>The king in this perceives him, how he coasts</line>
            <line>And hedges his own way. But in this point</line>
            <line>All his tricks founder, and he brings his physic</line>
            <line>After his patient's death: the king already</line>
            <line>Hath married the fair lady.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SURREY</speaker>
            <line>Would he had!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>May you be happy in your wish, my lord</line>
            <line>For, I profess, you have it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SURREY</speaker>
            <line>Now, all my joy</line>
            <line>Trace the conjunction!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>My amen to't!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORFOLK</speaker>
            <line>All men's!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>There's order given for her coronation:</line>
            <line>Marry, this is yet but young, and may be left</line>
            <line>To some ears unrecounted. But, my lords,</line>
            <line>She is a gallant creature, and complete</line>
            <line>In mind and feature: I persuade me, from her</line>
            <line>Will fall some blessing to this land, which shall</line>
            <line>In it be memorised.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SURREY</speaker>
            <line>But, will the king</line>
            <line>Digest this letter of the cardinal's?</line>
            <line>The Lord forbid!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Marry, amen!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>No, no;</line>
            <line>There be moe wasps that buzz about his nose</line>
            <line>Will make this sting the sooner. Cardinal Campeius</line>
            <line>Is stol'n away to Rome; hath ta'en no leave;</line>
            <line>Has left the cause o' the king unhandled; and</line>
            <line>Is posted, as the agent of our cardinal,</line>
            <line>To second all his plot. I do assure you</line>
            <line>The king cried Ha! at this.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Chamberlain</speaker>
            <line>Now, God incense him,</line>
            <line>And let him cry Ha! louder!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORFOLK</speaker>
            <line>But, my lord,</line>
            <line>When returns Cranmer?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>He is return'd in his opinions; which</line>
            <line>Have satisfied the king for his divorce,</line>
            <line>Together with all famous colleges</line>
            <line>Almost in Christendom: shortly, I believe,</line>
            <line>His second marriage shall be publish'd, and</line>
            <line>Her coronation. Katharine no more</line>
            <line>Shall be call'd queen, but princess dowager</line>
            <line>And widow to Prince Arthur.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORFOLK</speaker>
            <line>This same Cranmer's</line>
            <line>A worthy fellow, and hath ta'en much pain</line>
            <line>In the king's business.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>He has; and we shall see him</line>
            <line>For it an archbishop.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORFOLK</speaker>
            <line>So I hear.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>'Tis so.</line>
            <line>The cardinal!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter CARDINAL WOLSEY and CROMWELL</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Observe, observe, he's moody.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL WOLSEY</speaker>
            <line>The packet, Cromwell.</line>
            <line>Gave't you the king?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CROMWELL</speaker>
            <line>To his own hand, in's bedchamber.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL WOLSEY</speaker>
            <line>Look'd he o' the inside of the paper?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CROMWELL</speaker>
            <line>Presently</line>
            <line>He did unseal them: and the first he view'd,</line>
            <line>He did it with a serious mind; a heed</line>
            <line>Was in his countenance. You he bade</line>
            <line>Attend him here this morning.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL WOLSEY</speaker>
            <line>Is he ready</line>
            <line>To come abroad?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CROMWELL</speaker>
            <line>I think, by this he is.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL WOLSEY</speaker>
            <line>Leave me awhile.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit CROMWELL</stagedir>
            <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>
            <line>It shall be to the Duchess of Alencon,</line>
            <line>The French king's sister: he shall marry her.</line>
            <line>Anne Bullen! No; I'll no Anne Bullens for him:</line>
            <line>There's more in't than fair visage. Bullen!</line>
            <line>No, we'll no Bullens. Speedily I wish</line>
            <line>To hear from Rome. The Marchioness of Pembroke!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORFOLK</speaker>
            <line>He's discontented.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>May be, he hears the king</line>
            <line>Does whet his anger to him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SURREY</speaker>
            <line>Sharp enough,</line>
            <line>Lord, for thy justice!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL WOLSEY</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  The late queen's gentlewoman,</line>
            <line>a knight's daughter,</line>
            <line>To be her mistress' mistress! the queen's queen!</line>
            <line>This candle burns not clear: 'tis I must snuff it;</line>
            <line>Then out it goes. What though I know her virtuous</line>
            <line>And well deserving? yet I know her for</line>
            <line>A spleeny Lutheran; and not wholesome to</line>
            <line>Our cause, that she should lie i' the bosom of</line>
            <line>Our hard-ruled king. Again, there is sprung up</line>
            <line>An heretic, an arch one, Cranmer; one</line>
            <line>Hath crawl'd into the favour of the king,</line>
            <line>And is his oracle.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORFOLK</speaker>
            <line>He is vex'd at something.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SURREY</speaker>
            <line>I would 'twere something that would fret the string,</line>
            <line>The master-cord on's heart!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter KING HENRY VIII, reading of a schedule, and LOVELL</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>The king, the king!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VIII</speaker>
            <line>What piles of wealth hath he accumulated</line>
            <line>To his own portion! and what expense by the hour</line>
            <line>Seems to flow from him! How, i' the name of thrift,</line>
            <line>Does he rake this together! Now, my lords,</line>
            <line>Saw you the cardinal?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORFOLK</speaker>
            <line>My lord, we have</line>
            <line>Stood here observing him: some strange commotion</line>
            <line>Is in his brain: he bites his lip, and starts;</line>
            <line>Stops on a sudden, looks upon the ground,</line>
            <line>Then lays his finger on his temple, straight</line>
            <line>Springs out into fast gait; then stops again,</line>
            <line>Strikes his breast hard, and anon he casts</line>
            <line>His eye against the moon: in most strange postures</line>
            <line>We have seen him set himself.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VIII</speaker>
            <line>It may well be;</line>
            <line>There is a mutiny in's mind. This morning</line>
            <line>Papers of state he sent me to peruse,</line>
            <line>As I required: and wot you what I found</line>
            <line>There,--on my conscience, put unwittingly?</line>
            <line>Forsooth, an inventory, thus importing;</line>
            <line>The several parcels of his plate, his treasure,</line>
            <line>Rich stuffs, and ornaments of household; which</line>
            <line>I find at such proud rate, that it out-speaks</line>
            <line>Possession of a subject.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORFOLK</speaker>
            <line>It's heaven's will:</line>
            <line>Some spirit put this paper in the packet,</line>
            <line>To bless your eye withal.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VIII</speaker>
            <line>If we did think</line>
            <line>His contemplation were above the earth,</line>
            <line>And fix'd on spiritual object, he should still</line>
            <line>Dwell in his musings: but I am afraid</line>
            <line>His thinkings are below the moon, not worth</line>
            <line>His serious considering.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>King HENRY VIII takes his seat; whispers LOVELL,
who goes to CARDINAL WOLSEY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL WOLSEY</speaker>
            <line>Heaven forgive me!</line>
            <line>Ever God bless your highness!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VIII</speaker>
            <line>Good my lord,</line>
            <line>You are full of heavenly stuff, and bear the inventory</line>
            <line>Of your best graces in your mind; the which</line>
            <line>You were now running o'er: you have scarce time</line>
            <line>To steal from spiritual leisure a brief span</line>
            <line>To keep your earthly audit: sure, in that</line>
            <line>I deem you an ill husband, and am glad</line>
            <line>To have you therein my companion.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL WOLSEY</speaker>
            <line>Sir,</line>
            <line>For holy offices I have a time; a time</line>
            <line>To think upon the part of business which</line>
            <line>I bear i' the state; and nature does require</line>
            <line>Her times of preservation, which perforce</line>
            <line>I, her frail son, amongst my brethren mortal,</line>
            <line>Must give my tendence to.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VIII</speaker>
            <line>You have said well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL WOLSEY</speaker>
            <line>And ever may your highness yoke together,</line>
            <line>As I will lend you cause, my doing well</line>
            <line>With my well saying!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VIII</speaker>
            <line>'Tis well said again;</line>
            <line>And 'tis a kind of good deed to say well:</line>
            <line>And yet words are no deeds. My father loved you:</line>
            <line>His said he did; and with his deed did crown</line>
            <line>His word upon you. Since I had my office,</line>
            <line>I have kept you next my heart; have not alone</line>
            <line>Employ'd you where high profits might come home,</line>
            <line>But pared my present havings, to bestow</line>
            <line>My bounties upon you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL WOLSEY</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>             What should this mean?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SURREY</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  The Lord increase this business!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VIII</speaker>
            <line>Have I not made you,</line>
            <line>The prime man of the state? I pray you, tell me,</line>
            <line>If what I now pronounce you have found true:</line>
            <line>And, if you may confess it, say withal,</line>
            <line>If you are bound to us or no. What say you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL WOLSEY</speaker>
            <line>My sovereign, I confess your royal graces,</line>
            <line>Shower'd on me daily, have been more than could</line>
            <line>My studied purposes requite; which went</line>
            <line>Beyond all man's endeavours: my endeavours</line>
            <line>Have ever come too short of my desires,</line>
            <line>Yet filed with my abilities: mine own ends</line>
            <line>Have been mine so that evermore they pointed</line>
            <line>To the good of your most sacred person and</line>
            <line>The profit of the state. For your great graces</line>
            <line>Heap'd upon me, poor undeserver, I</line>
            <line>Can nothing render but allegiant thanks,</line>
            <line>My prayers to heaven for you, my loyalty,</line>
            <line>Which ever has and ever shall be growing,</line>
            <line>Till death, that winter, kill it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VIII</speaker>
            <line>Fairly answer'd;</line>
            <line>A loyal and obedient subject is</line>
            <line>Therein illustrated: the honour of it</line>
            <line>Does pay the act of it; as, i' the contrary,</line>
            <line>The foulness is the punishment. I presume</line>
            <line>That, as my hand has open'd bounty to you,</line>
            <line>My heart dropp'd love, my power rain'd honour, more</line>
            <line>On you than any; so your hand and heart,</line>
            <line>Your brain, and every function of your power,</line>
            <line>Should, notwithstanding that your bond of duty,</line>
            <line>As 'twere in love's particular, be more</line>
            <line>To me, your friend, than any.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL WOLSEY</speaker>
            <line>I do profess</line>
            <line>That for your highness' good I ever labour'd</line>
            <line>More than mine own; that am, have, and will be--</line>
            <line>Though all the world should crack their duty to you,</line>
            <line>And throw it from their soul; though perils did</line>
            <line>Abound, as thick as thought could make 'em, and</line>
            <line>Appear in forms more horrid,--yet my duty,</line>
            <line>As doth a rock against the chiding flood,</line>
            <line>Should the approach of this wild river break,</line>
            <line>And stand unshaken yours.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY VIII</speaker>
            <line>'Tis nobly spoken:</line>
            <line>Take notice, lords, he has a loyal breast,</line>
            <line>For you have seen him open't. Read o'er this;</line>
            <stagedir>Giving him papers</stagedir>
            <line>And after, this: and then to breakfast with</line>
            <line>What appetite you have.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit KING HENRY VIII, frowning upon CARDINAL WOLSEY:
the Nobles throng after him, smiling and whispering</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL WOLSEY</speaker>
            <line>What should this mean?</line>
            <line>What sudden anger's this? how have I reap'd it?</line>
            <line>He parted frowning from me, as if ruin</line>
            <line>Leap'd from his eyes: so looks the chafed lion</line>
            <line>Upon the daring huntsman that has gall'd him;</line>
            <line>Then makes him nothing. I must read this paper;</line>
            <line>I fear, the story of his anger. 'Tis so;</line>
            <line>This paper has undone me: 'tis the account</line>
            <line>Of all that world of wealth I have drawn together</line>
            <line>For mine own ends; indeed, to gain the popedom,</line>
            <line>And fee my friends in Rome. O negligence!</line>
            <line>Fit for a fool to fall by: what cross devil</line>
            <line>Made me put this main secret in the packet</line>
            <line>I sent the king? Is there no way to cure this?</line>
            <line>No new device to beat this from his brains?</line>
            <line>I know 'twill stir him strongly; yet I know</line>
            <line>A way, if it take right, in spite of fortune</line>
            <line>Will bring me off again. What's this? 'To the Pope!'</line>
            <line>The letter, as I live, with all the business</line>
            <line>I writ to's holiness. Nay then, farewell!</line>
            <line>I have touch'd the highest point of all my greatness;</line>
            <line>And, from that full meridian of my glory,</line>
            <line>I haste now to my setting: I shall fall</line>
            <line>Like a bright exhalation m the evening,</line>
            <line>And no man see me more.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter to CARDINAL WOLSEY, NORFOLK and SUFFOLK, SURREY,
and the Chamberlain</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Hear the king's pleasure, cardinal: who commands you</line>
            <line>To render up the great seal presently</line>
            <line>Into our hands; and to confine yourself</line>
            <line>To Asher House, my Lord of Winchester's,</line>
            <line>Till you hear further from his highness.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL WOLSEY</speaker>
            <line>Stay:</line>
            <line>Where's your commission, lords? words cannot carry</line>
            <line>Authority so weighty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Who dare cross 'em,</line>
            <line>Bearing the king's will from his mouth expressly?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL WOLSEY</speaker>
            <line>Till I find more than will or words to do it,</line>
            <line>I mean your malice, know, officious lords,</line>
            <line>I dare and must deny it. Now I feel</line>
            <line>Of what coarse metal ye are moulded, envy:</line>
            <line>How eagerly ye follow my disgraces,</line>
            <line>As if it fed ye! and how sleek and wanton</line>
            <line>Ye appear in every thing may bring my ruin!</line>
            <line>Follow your envious courses, men of malice;</line>
            <line>You have Christian warrant for 'em, and, no doubt,</line>
            <line>In time will find their fit rewards. That seal,</line>
            <line>You ask with such a violence, the king,</line>
            <line>Mine and your master, with his own hand gave me;</line>
            <line>Bade me enjoy it, with the place and honours,</line>
            <line>During my life; and, to confirm his goodness,</line>
            <line>Tied it by letters-patents: now, who'll take it?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SURREY</speaker>
            <line>The king, that gave it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL WOLSEY</speaker>
            <line>It must be himself, then.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SURREY</speaker>
            <line>Thou art a proud traitor, priest.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL WOLSEY</speaker>
            <line>Proud lord, thou liest:</line>
            <line>Within these forty hours Surrey durst better</line>
            <line>Have burnt that tongue than said so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SURREY</speaker>
            <line>Thy ambition,</line>
            <line>Thou scarlet sin, robb'd this bewailing land</line>
            <line>Of noble Buckingham, my father-in-law:</line>
            <line>The heads of all thy brother cardinals,</line>
            <line>With thee and all thy best parts bound together,</line>
            <line>Weigh'd not a hair of his. Plague of your policy!</line>
            <line>You sent me deputy for Ireland;</line>
            <line>Far from his succor, from the king, from all</line>
            <line>That might have mercy on the fault thou gavest him;</line>
            <line>Whilst your great goodness, out of holy pity,</line>
            <line>Absolved him with an axe.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL WOLSEY</speaker>
            <line>This, and all else</line>
            <line>This talking lord can lay upon my credit,</line>
            <line>I answer is most false. The duke by law</line>
            <line>Found his deserts: how innocent I was</line>
            <line>From any private malice in his end,</line>
            <line>His noble jury and foul cause can witness.</line>
            <line>If I loved many words, lord, I should tell you</line>
            <line>You have as little honesty as honour,</line>
            <line>That in the way of loyalty and truth</line>
            <line>Toward the king, my ever royal master,</line>
            <line>Dare mate a sounder man than Surrey can be,</line>
            <line>And all that love his follies.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SURREY</speaker>
            <line>By my soul,</line>
            <line>Your long coat, priest, protects you; thou</line>
            <line>shouldst feel</line>
            <line>My sword i' the life-blood of thee else. My lords,</line>
            <line>Can ye endure to hear this arrogance?</line>
            <line>And from this fellow? if we live thus tamely,</line>
            <line>To be thus jaded by a piece of scarlet,</line>
            <line>Farewell nobility; let his grace go forward,</line>
            <line>And dare us with his cap like larks.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL WOLSEY</speaker>
            <line>All goodness</line>
            <line>Is poison to thy stomach.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SURREY</speaker>
            <line>Yes, that goodness</line>
            <line>Of gleaning all the land's wealth into one,</line>
            <line>Into your own hands, cardinal, by extortion;</line>
            <line>The goodness of your intercepted packets</line>
            <line>You writ to the pope against the king: your goodness,</line>
            <line>Since you provoke me, shall be most notorious.</line>
            <line>My Lord of Norfolk, as you are truly noble,</line>
            <line>As you respect the common good, the state</line>
            <line>Of our despised nobility, our issues,</line>
            <line>Who, if he live, will scarce be gentlemen,</line>
            <line>Produce the grand sum of his sins, the articles</line>
            <line>Collected from his life. I'll startle you</line>
            <line>Worse than the scaring bell, when the brown wench</line>
            <line>Lay kissing in your arms, lord cardinal.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL WOLSEY</speaker>
            <line>How much, methinks, I could despise this man,</line>
            <line>But that I am bound in charity against it!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Those articles, my lord, are in the king's hand:</line>
            <line>But, thus much, they are foul ones.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL WOLSEY</speaker>
            <line>So much fairer</line>
            <line>And spotless shall mine innocence arise,</line>
            <line>When the king knows my truth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SURREY</speaker>
            <line>This cannot save you:</line>
            <line>I thank my memory, I yet remember</line>
            <line>Some of these articles; and out they shall.</line>
            <line>Now, if you can blush and cry 'guilty,' cardinal,</line>
            <line>You'll show a little honesty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL WOLSEY</speaker>
            <line>Speak on, sir;</line>
            <line>I dare your worst objections: if I blush,</line>
            <line>It is to see a nobleman want manners.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SURREY</speaker>
            <line>I had rather want those than my head. Have at you!</line>
            <line>First, that, without the king's assent or knowledge,</line>
            <line>You wrought to be a legate; by which power</line>
            <line>You maim'd the jurisdiction of all bishops.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Then, that in all you writ to Rome, or else</line>
            <line>To foreign princes, 'Ego et Rex meus'</line>
            <line>Was still inscribed; in which you brought the king</line>
            <line>To be your servant.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Then that, without the knowledge</line>
            <line>Either of king or council, when you went</line>
            <line>Ambassador to the emperor, you made bold</line>
            <line>To carry into Flanders the great seal.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SURREY</speaker>
            <line>Item, you sent a large commission</line>
            <line>To Gregory de Cassado, to conclude,</line>
            <line>Without the king's will or the state's allowance,</line>
            <line>A league between his highness and Ferrara.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>That, out of mere ambition, you have caused</line>
            <line>Your holy hat to be stamp'd on the king's coin.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SURREY</speaker>
            <line>Then that you have sent innumerable substance--</line>
            <line>By what means got, I leave to your own conscience--</line>
            <line>To furnish Rome, and to prepare the ways</line>
            <line>You have for dignities; to the mere undoing</line>
            <line>Of all the kingdom. Many more there are;</line>
            <line>Which, since they are of you, and odious,</line>
            <line>I will not taint my mouth with.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Chamberlain</speaker>
            <line>O my lord,</line>
            <line>Press not a falling man too far! 'tis virtue:</line>
            <line>His faults lie open to the laws; let them,</line>
            <line>Not you, correct him. My heart weeps to see him</line>
            <line>So little of his great self.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SURREY</speaker>
            <line>I forgive him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SUFFOLK</speaker>
            <line>Lord cardinal, the king's further pleasure is,</line>
            <line>Because all those things you have done of late,</line>
            <line>By your power legatine, within this kingdom,</line>
            <line>Fall into the compass of a praemunire,</line>
            <line>That therefore such a writ be sued against you;</line>
            <line>To forfeit all your goods, lands, tenements,</line>
            <line>Chattels, and whatsoever, and to be</line>
            <line>Out of the king's protection. This is my charge.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORFOLK</speaker>
            <line>And so we'll leave you to your meditations</line>
            <line>How to live better. For your stubborn answer</line>
            <line>About the giving back the great seal to us,</line>
            <line>The king shall know it, and, no doubt, shall thank you.</line>
            <line>So fare you well, my little good lord cardinal.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt all but CARDINAL WOLSEY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL WOLSEY</speaker>
            <line>So farewell to the little good you bear me.</line>
            <line>Farewell! a long farewell, to all my greatness!</line>
            <line>This is the state of man: to-day he puts forth</line>
            <line>The tender leaves of hopes; to-morrow blossoms,</line>
            <line>And bears his blushing honours thick upon him;</line>
            <line>The third day comes a frost, a killing frost,</line>
            <line>And, when he thinks, good easy man, full surely</line>
            <line>His greatness is a-ripening, nips his root,</line>
            <line>And then he falls, as I do. I have ventured,</line>
            <line>Like little wanton boys that swim on bladders,</line>
            <line>This many summers in a sea of glory,</line>
            <line>But far beyond my depth: my high-blown pride</line>
            <line>At length broke under me and now has left me,</line>
            <line>Weary and old with service, to the mercy</line>
            <line>Of a rude stream, that must for ever hide me.</line>
            <line>Vain pomp and glory of this world, I hate ye:</line>
            <line>I feel my heart new open'd. O, how wretched</line>
            <line>Is that poor man that hangs on princes' favours!</line>
            <line>There is, betwixt that smile we would aspire to,</line>
            <line>That sweet aspect of princes, and their ruin,</line>
            <line>More pangs and fears than wars or women have:</line>
            <line>And when he falls, he falls like Lucifer,</line>
            <line>Never to hope again.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter CROMWELL, and stands amazed</stagedir>
            <line>Why, how now, Cromwell!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CROMWELL</speaker>
            <line>I have no power to speak, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL WOLSEY</speaker>
            <line>What, amazed</line>
            <line>At my misfortunes? can thy spirit wonder</line>
            <line>A great man should decline? Nay, an you weep,</line>
            <line>I am fall'n indeed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CROMWELL</speaker>
            <line>How does your grace?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL WOLSEY</speaker>
            <line>Why, well;</line>
            <line>Never so truly happy, my good Cromwell.</line>
            <line>I know myself now; and I feel within me</line>
            <line>A peace above all earthly dignities,</line>
            <line>A still and quiet conscience. The king has cured me,</line>
            <line>I humbly thank his grace; and from these shoulders,</line>
            <line>These ruin'd pillars, out of pity, taken</line>
            <line>A load would sink a navy, too much honour:</line>
            <line>O, 'tis a burthen, Cromwell, 'tis a burthen</line>
            <line>Too heavy for a man that hopes for heaven!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CROMWELL</speaker>
            <line>I am glad your grace has made that right use of it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL WOLSEY</speaker>
            <line>I hope I have: I am able now, methinks,</line>
            <line>Out of a fortitude of soul I feel,</line>
            <line>To endure more miseries and greater far</line>
            <line>Than my weak-hearted enemies dare offer.</line>
            <line>What news abroad?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CROMWELL</speaker>
            <line>The heaviest and the worst</line>
            <line>Is your displeasure with the king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL WOLSEY</speaker>
            <line>God bless him!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CROMWELL</speaker>
            <line>The next is, that Sir Thomas More is chosen</line>
            <line>Lord chancellor in your place.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL WOLSEY</speaker>
            <line>That's somewhat sudden:</line>
            <line>But he's a learned man. May he continue</line>
            <line>Long in his highness' favour, and do justice</line>
            <line>For truth's sake and his conscience; that his bones,</line>
            <line>When he has run his course and sleeps in blessings,</line>
            <line>May have a tomb of orphans' tears wept on em! What more?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CROMWELL</speaker>
            <line>That Cranmer is return'd with welcome,</line>
            <line>Install'd lord archbishop of Canterbury.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL WOLSEY</speaker>
            <line>That's news indeed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CROMWELL</speaker>
            <line>Last, that the Lady Anne,</line>
            <line>Whom the king hath in secrecy long married,</line>
            <line>This day was view'd in open as his queen,</line>
            <line>Going to chapel; and the voice is now</line>
            <line>Only about her coronation.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL WOLSEY</speaker>
            <line>There was the weight that pull'd me down. O Cromwell,</line>
            <line>The king has gone beyond me: all my glories</line>
            <line>In that one woman I have lost for ever:</line>
            <line>No sun shall ever usher forth mine honours,</line>
            <line>Or gild again the noble troops that waited</line>
            <line>Upon my smiles. Go, get thee from me, Cromwell;</line>
            <line>I am a poor fall'n man, unworthy now</line>
            <line>To be thy lord and master: seek the king;</line>
            <line>That sun, I pray, may never set! I have told him</line>
            <line>What and how true thou art: he will advance thee;</line>
            <line>Some little memory of me will stir him--</line>
            <line>I know his noble nature--not to let</line>
            <line>Thy hopeful service perish too: good Cromwell,</line>
            <line>Neglect him not; make use now, and provide</line>
            <line>For thine own future safety.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CROMWELL</speaker>
            <line>O my lord,</line>
            <line>Must I, then, leave you? must I needs forego</line>
            <line>So good, so noble and so true a master?</line>
            <line>Bear witness, all that have not hearts of iron,</line>
            <line>With what a sorrow Cromwell leaves his lord.</line>
            <line>The king shall have my service: but my prayers</line>
            <line>For ever and for ever shall be yours.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL WOLSEY</speaker>
            <line>Cromwell, I did not think to shed a tear</line>
            <line>In all my miseries; but thou hast forced me,</line>
            <line>Out of thy honest truth, to play the woman.</line>
            <line>Let's dry our eyes: and thus far hear me, Cromwell;</line>
            <line>And, when I am forgotten, as I shall be,</line>
            <line>And sleep in dull cold marble, where no mention</line>
            <line>Of me more must be heard of, say, I taught thee,</line>
            <line>Say, Wolsey, that once trod the ways of glory,</line>
            <line>And sounded all the depths and shoals of honour,</line>
            <line>Found thee a way, out of his wreck, to rise in;</line>
            <line>A sure and safe one, though thy master miss'd it.</line>
            <line>Mark but my fall, and that that ruin'd me.</line>
            <line>Cromwell, I charge thee, fling away ambition:</line>
            <line>By that sin fell the angels; how can man, then,</line>
            <line>The image of his Maker, hope to win by it?</line>
            <line>Love thyself last: cherish those hearts that hate thee;</line>
            <line>Corruption wins not more than honesty.</line>
            <line>Still in thy right hand carry gentle peace,</line>
            <line>To silence envious tongues. Be just, and fear not:</line>
            <line>Let all the ends thou aim'st at be thy country's,</line>
            <line>Thy God's, and truth's; then if thou fall'st,</line>
            <line>O Cromwell,</line>
            <line>Thou fall'st a blessed martyr! Serve the king;</line>
            <line>And,--prithee, lead me in:</line>
            <line>There take an inventory of all I have,</line>
            <line>To the last penny; 'tis the king's: my robe,</line>
            <line>And my integrity to heaven, is all</line>
            <line>I dare now call mine own. O Cromwell, Cromwell!</line>
            <line>Had I but served my God with half the zeal</line>
            <line>I served my king, he would not in mine age</line>
            <line>Have left me naked to mine enemies.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CROMWELL</speaker>
            <line>Good sir, have patience.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CARDINAL WOLSEY</speaker>
            <line>So I have. Farewell</line>
            <line>The hopes of court! my hopes in heaven do dwell.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>