<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:shakespear:dtd:act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-1">
   <title>ACT I</title>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  London. The palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter KING HENRY, LORD JOHN OF LANCASTER, the EARL
of WESTMORELAND, SIR WALTER BLUNT, and others</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>So shaken as we are, so wan with care,</line>
            <line>Find we a time for frighted peace to pant,</line>
            <line>And breathe short-winded accents of new broils</line>
            <line>To be commenced in strands afar remote.</line>
            <line>No more the thirsty entrance of this soil</line>
            <line>Shall daub her lips with her own children's blood;</line>
            <line>Nor more shall trenching war channel her fields,</line>
            <line>Nor bruise her flowerets with the armed hoofs</line>
            <line>Of hostile paces: those opposed eyes,</line>
            <line>Which, like the meteors of a troubled heaven,</line>
            <line>All of one nature, of one substance bred,</line>
            <line>Did lately meet in the intestine shock</line>
            <line>And furious close of civil butchery</line>
            <line>Shall now, in mutual well-beseeming ranks,</line>
            <line>March all one way and be no more opposed</line>
            <line>Against acquaintance, kindred and allies:</line>
            <line>The edge of war, like an ill-sheathed knife,</line>
            <line>No more shall cut his master. Therefore, friends,</line>
            <line>As far as to the sepulchre of Christ,</line>
            <line>Whose soldier now, under whose blessed cross</line>
            <line>We are impressed and engaged to fight,</line>
            <line>Forthwith a power of English shall we levy;</line>
            <line>Whose arms were moulded in their mothers' womb</line>
            <line>To chase these pagans in those holy fields</line>
            <line>Over whose acres walk'd those blessed feet</line>
            <line>Which fourteen hundred years ago were nail'd</line>
            <line>For our advantage on the bitter cross.</line>
            <line>But this our purpose now is twelve month old,</line>
            <line>And bootless 'tis to tell you we will go:</line>
            <line>Therefore we meet not now. Then let me hear</line>
            <line>Of you, my gentle cousin Westmoreland,</line>
            <line>What yesternight our council did decree</line>
            <line>In forwarding this dear expedience.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WESTMORELAND</speaker>
            <line>My liege, this haste was hot in question,</line>
            <line>And many limits of the charge set down</line>
            <line>But yesternight: when all athwart there came</line>
            <line>A post from Wales loaden with heavy news;</line>
            <line>Whose worst was, that the noble Mortimer,</line>
            <line>Leading the men of Herefordshire to fight</line>
            <line>Against the irregular and wild Glendower,</line>
            <line>Was by the rude hands of that Welshman taken,</line>
            <line>A thousand of his people butchered;</line>
            <line>Upon whose dead corpse there was such misuse,</line>
            <line>Such beastly shameless transformation,</line>
            <line>By those Welshwomen done as may not be</line>
            <line>Without much shame retold or spoken of.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>It seems then that the tidings of this broil</line>
            <line>Brake off our business for the Holy Land.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WESTMORELAND</speaker>
            <line>This match'd with other did, my gracious lord;</line>
            <line>For more uneven and unwelcome news</line>
            <line>Came from the north and thus it did import:</line>
            <line>On Holy-rood day, the gallant Hotspur there,</line>
            <line>Young Harry Percy and brave Archibald,</line>
            <line>That ever-valiant and approved Scot,</line>
            <line>At Holmedon met,</line>
            <line>Where they did spend a sad and bloody hour,</line>
            <line>As by discharge of their artillery,</line>
            <line>And shape of likelihood, the news was told;</line>
            <line>For he that brought them, in the very heat</line>
            <line>And pride of their contention did take horse,</line>
            <line>Uncertain of the issue any way.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>Here is a dear, a true industrious friend,</line>
            <line>Sir Walter Blunt, new lighted from his horse.</line>
            <line>Stain'd with the variation of each soil</line>
            <line>Betwixt that Holmedon and this seat of ours;</line>
            <line>And he hath brought us smooth and welcome news.</line>
            <line>The Earl of Douglas is discomfited:</line>
            <line>Ten thousand bold Scots, two and twenty knights,</line>
            <line>Balk'd in their own blood did Sir Walter see</line>
            <line>On Holmedon's plains. Of prisoners, Hotspur took</line>
            <line>Mordake the Earl of Fife, and eldest son</line>
            <line>To beaten Douglas; and the Earl of Athol,</line>
            <line>Of Murray, Angus, and Menteith:</line>
            <line>And is not this an honourable spoil?</line>
            <line>A gallant prize? ha, cousin, is it not?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WESTMORELAND</speaker>
            <line>In faith,</line>
            <line>It is a conquest for a prince to boast of.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>Yea, there thou makest me sad and makest me sin</line>
            <line>In envy that my Lord Northumberland</line>
            <line>Should be the father to so blest a son,</line>
            <line>A son who is the theme of honour's tongue;</line>
            <line>Amongst a grove, the very straightest plant;</line>
            <line>Who is sweet Fortune's minion and her pride:</line>
            <line>Whilst I, by looking on the praise of him,</line>
            <line>See riot and dishonour stain the brow</line>
            <line>Of my young Harry. O that it could be proved</line>
            <line>That some night-tripping fairy had exchanged</line>
            <line>In cradle-clothes our children where they lay,</line>
            <line>And call'd mine Percy, his Plantagenet!</line>
            <line>Then would I have his Harry, and he mine.</line>
            <line>But let him from my thoughts. What think you, coz,</line>
            <line>Of this young Percy's pride? the prisoners,</line>
            <line>Which he in this adventure hath surprised,</line>
            <line>To his own use he keeps; and sends me word,</line>
            <line>I shall have none but Mordake Earl of Fife.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WESTMORELAND</speaker>
            <line>This is his uncle's teaching; this is Worcester,</line>
            <line>Malevolent to you in all aspects;</line>
            <line>Which makes him prune himself, and bristle up</line>
            <line>The crest of youth against your dignity.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>But I have sent for him to answer this;</line>
            <line>And for this cause awhile we must neglect</line>
            <line>Our holy purpose to Jerusalem.</line>
            <line>Cousin, on Wednesday next our council we</line>
            <line>Will hold at Windsor; so inform the lords:</line>
            <line>But come yourself with speed to us again;</line>
            <line>For more is to be said and to be done</line>
            <line>Than out of anger can be uttered.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WESTMORELAND</speaker>
            <line>I will, my liege.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  London. An apartment of the Prince's.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter the PRINCE OF WALES and FALSTAFF</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Now, Hal, what time of day is it, lad?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>Thou art so fat-witted, with drinking of old sack</line>
            <line>and unbuttoning thee after supper and sleeping upon</line>
            <line>benches after noon, that thou hast forgotten to</line>
            <line>demand that truly which thou wouldst truly know.</line>
            <line>What a devil hast thou to do with the time of the</line>
            <line>day? Unless hours were cups of sack and minutes</line>
            <line>capons and clocks the tongues of bawds and dials the</line>
            <line>signs of leaping-houses and the blessed sun himself</line>
            <line>a fair hot wench in flame-coloured taffeta, I see no</line>
            <line>reason why thou shouldst be so superfluous to demand</line>
            <line>the time of the day.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Indeed, you come near me now, Hal; for we that take</line>
            <line>purses go by the moon and the seven stars, and not</line>
            <line>by Phoebus, he,'that wandering knight so fair.' And,</line>
            <line>I prithee, sweet wag, when thou art king, as, God</line>
            <line>save thy grace,--majesty I should say, for grace</line>
            <line>thou wilt have none,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>What, none?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>No, by my troth, not so much as will serve to</line>
            <line>prologue to an egg and butter.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>Well, how then? come, roundly, roundly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Marry, then, sweet wag, when thou art king, let not</line>
            <line>us that are squires of the night's body be called</line>
            <line>thieves of the day's beauty: let us be Diana's</line>
            <line>foresters, gentlemen of the shade, minions of the</line>
            <line>moon; and let men say we be men of good government,</line>
            <line>being governed, as the sea is, by our noble and</line>
            <line>chaste mistress the moon, under whose countenance we steal.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>Thou sayest well, and it holds well too; for the</line>
            <line>fortune of us that are the moon's men doth ebb and</line>
            <line>flow like the sea, being governed, as the sea is,</line>
            <line>by the moon. As, for proof, now: a purse of gold</line>
            <line>most resolutely snatched on Monday night and most</line>
            <line>dissolutely spent on Tuesday morning; got with</line>
            <line>swearing 'Lay by' and spent with crying 'Bring in;'</line>
            <line>now in as low an ebb as the foot of the ladder</line>
            <line>and by and by in as high a flow as the ridge of the gallows.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>By the Lord, thou sayest true, lad. And is not my</line>
            <line>hostess of the tavern a most sweet wench?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>As the honey of Hybla, my old lad of the castle. And</line>
            <line>is not a buff jerkin a most sweet robe of durance?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>How now, how now, mad wag! what, in thy quips and</line>
            <line>thy quiddities? what a plague have I to do with a</line>
            <line>buff jerkin?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>Why, what a pox have I to do with my hostess of the tavern?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Well, thou hast called her to a reckoning many a</line>
            <line>time and oft.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>Did I ever call for thee to pay thy part?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>No; I'll give thee thy due, thou hast paid all there.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>Yea, and elsewhere, so far as my coin would stretch;</line>
            <line>and where it would not, I have used my credit.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Yea, and so used it that were it not here apparent</line>
            <line>that thou art heir apparent--But, I prithee, sweet</line>
            <line>wag, shall there be gallows standing in England when</line>
            <line>thou art king? and resolution thus fobbed as it is</line>
            <line>with the rusty curb of old father antic the law? Do</line>
            <line>not thou, when thou art king, hang a thief.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>No; thou shalt.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Shall I? O rare! By the Lord, I'll be a brave judge.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>Thou judgest false already: I mean, thou shalt have</line>
            <line>the hanging of the thieves and so become a rare hangman.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Well, Hal, well; and in some sort it jumps with my</line>
            <line>humour as well as waiting in the court, I can tell</line>
            <line>you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>For obtaining of suits?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Yea, for obtaining of suits, whereof the hangman</line>
            <line>hath no lean wardrobe. 'Sblood, I am as melancholy</line>
            <line>as a gib cat or a lugged bear.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>Or an old lion, or a lover's lute.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Yea, or the drone of a Lincolnshire bagpipe.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>What sayest thou to a hare, or the melancholy of</line>
            <line>Moor-ditch?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Thou hast the most unsavoury similes and art indeed</line>
            <line>the most comparative, rascalliest, sweet young</line>
            <line>prince. But, Hal, I prithee, trouble me no more</line>
            <line>with vanity. I would to God thou and I knew where a</line>
            <line>commodity of good names were to be bought. An old</line>
            <line>lord of the council rated me the other day in the</line>
            <line>street about you, sir, but I marked him not; and yet</line>
            <line>he talked very wisely, but I regarded him not; and</line>
            <line>yet he talked wisely, and in the street too.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>Thou didst well; for wisdom cries out in the</line>
            <line>streets, and no man regards it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>O, thou hast damnable iteration and art indeed able</line>
            <line>to corrupt a saint. Thou hast done much harm upon</line>
            <line>me, Hal; God forgive thee for it! Before I knew</line>
            <line>thee, Hal, I knew nothing; and now am I, if a man</line>
            <line>should speak truly, little better than one of the</line>
            <line>wicked. I must give over this life, and I will give</line>
            <line>it over: by the Lord, and I do not, I am a villain:</line>
            <line>I'll be damned for never a king's son in</line>
            <line>Christendom.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>Where shall we take a purse tomorrow, Jack?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>'Zounds, where thou wilt, lad; I'll make one; an I</line>
            <line>do not, call me villain and baffle me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>I see a good amendment of life in thee; from praying</line>
            <line>to purse-taking.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Why, Hal, 'tis my vocation, Hal; 'tis no sin for a</line>
            <line>man to labour in his vocation.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter POINS</stagedir>
            <line>Poins! Now shall we know if Gadshill have set a</line>
            <line>match. O, if men were to be saved by merit, what</line>
            <line>hole in hell were hot enough for him? This is the</line>
            <line>most omnipotent villain that ever cried 'Stand' to</line>
            <line>a true man.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>Good morrow, Ned.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POINS</speaker>
            <line>Good morrow, sweet Hal. What says Monsieur Remorse?</line>
            <line>what says Sir John Sack and Sugar? Jack! how</line>
            <line>agrees the devil and thee about thy soul, that thou</line>
            <line>soldest him on Good-Friday last for a cup of Madeira</line>
            <line>and a cold capon's leg?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>Sir John stands to his word, the devil shall have</line>
            <line>his bargain; for he was never yet a breaker of</line>
            <line>proverbs: he will give the devil his due.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POINS</speaker>
            <line>Then art thou damned for keeping thy word with the devil.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>Else he had been damned for cozening the devil.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POINS</speaker>
            <line>But, my lads, my lads, to-morrow morning, by four</line>
            <line>o'clock, early at Gadshill! there are pilgrims going</line>
            <line>to Canterbury with rich offerings, and traders</line>
            <line>riding to London with fat purses: I have vizards</line>
            <line>for you all; you have horses for yourselves:</line>
            <line>Gadshill lies to-night in Rochester: I have bespoke</line>
            <line>supper to-morrow night in Eastcheap: we may do it</line>
            <line>as secure as sleep. If you will go, I will stuff</line>
            <line>your purses full of crowns; if you will not, tarry</line>
            <line>at home and be hanged.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Hear ye, Yedward; if I tarry at home and go not,</line>
            <line>I'll hang you for going.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POINS</speaker>
            <line>You will, chops?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Hal, wilt thou make one?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>Who, I rob? I a thief? not I, by my faith.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>There's neither honesty, manhood, nor good</line>
            <line>fellowship in thee, nor thou camest not of the blood</line>
            <line>royal, if thou darest not stand for ten shillings.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>Well then, once in my days I'll be a madcap.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Why, that's well said.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>Well, come what will, I'll tarry at home.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>By the Lord, I'll be a traitor then, when thou art king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>I care not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POINS</speaker>
            <line>Sir John, I prithee, leave the prince and me alone:</line>
            <line>I will lay him down such reasons for this adventure</line>
            <line>that he shall go.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Well, God give thee the spirit of persuasion and him</line>
            <line>the ears of profiting, that what thou speakest may</line>
            <line>move and what he hears may be believed, that the</line>
            <line>true prince may, for recreation sake, prove a false</line>
            <line>thief; for the poor abuses of the time want</line>
            <line>countenance. Farewell: you shall find me in Eastcheap.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>Farewell, thou latter spring! farewell, All-hallown summer!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit Falstaff</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POINS</speaker>
            <line>Now, my good sweet honey lord, ride with us</line>
            <line>to-morrow: I have a jest to execute that I cannot</line>
            <line>manage alone. Falstaff, Bardolph, Peto and Gadshill</line>
            <line>shall rob those men that we have already waylaid:</line>
            <line>yourself and I will not be there; and when they</line>
            <line>have the booty, if you and I do not rob them, cut</line>
            <line>this head off from my shoulders.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>How shall we part with them in setting forth?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POINS</speaker>
            <line>Why, we will set forth before or after them, and</line>
            <line>appoint them a place of meeting, wherein it is at</line>
            <line>our pleasure to fail, and then will they adventure</line>
            <line>upon the exploit themselves; which they shall have</line>
            <line>no sooner achieved, but we'll set upon them.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>Yea, but 'tis like that they will know us by our</line>
            <line>horses, by our habits and by every other</line>
            <line>appointment, to be ourselves.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POINS</speaker>
            <line>Tut! our horses they shall not see: I'll tie them</line>
            <line>in the wood; our vizards we will change after we</line>
            <line>leave them: and, sirrah, I have cases of buckram</line>
            <line>for the nonce, to immask our noted outward garments.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>Yea, but I doubt they will be too hard for us.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POINS</speaker>
            <line>Well, for two of them, I know them to be as</line>
            <line>true-bred cowards as ever turned back; and for the</line>
            <line>third, if he fight longer than he sees reason, I'll</line>
            <line>forswear arms. The virtue of this jest will be, the</line>
            <line>incomprehensible lies that this same fat rogue will</line>
            <line>tell us when we meet at supper: how thirty, at</line>
            <line>least, he fought with; what wards, what blows, what</line>
            <line>extremities he endured; and in the reproof of this</line>
            <line>lies the jest.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>Well, I'll go with thee: provide us all things</line>
            <line>necessary and meet me to-morrow night in Eastcheap;</line>
            <line>there I'll sup. Farewell.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POINS</speaker>
            <line>Farewell, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit Poins</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>I know you all, and will awhile uphold</line>
            <line>The unyoked humour of your idleness:</line>
            <line>Yet herein will I imitate the sun,</line>
            <line>Who doth permit the base contagious clouds</line>
            <line>To smother up his beauty from the world,</line>
            <line>That, when he please again to be himself,</line>
            <line>Being wanted, he may be more wonder'd at,</line>
            <line>By breaking through the foul and ugly mists</line>
            <line>Of vapours that did seem to strangle him.</line>
            <line>If all the year were playing holidays,</line>
            <line>To sport would be as tedious as to work;</line>
            <line>But when they seldom come, they wish'd for come,</line>
            <line>And nothing pleaseth but rare accidents.</line>
            <line>So, when this loose behavior I throw off</line>
            <line>And pay the debt I never promised,</line>
            <line>By how much better than my word I am,</line>
            <line>By so much shall I falsify men's hopes;</line>
            <line>And like bright metal on a sullen ground,</line>
            <line>My reformation, glittering o'er my fault,</line>
            <line>Shall show more goodly and attract more eyes</line>
            <line>Than that which hath no foil to set it off.</line>
            <line>I'll so offend, to make offence a skill;</line>
            <line>Redeeming time when men think least I will.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  London. The palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter the KING, NORTHUMBERLAND, WORCESTER, HOTSPUR,
SIR WALTER BLUNT, with others</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>My blood hath been too cold and temperate,</line>
            <line>Unapt to stir at these indignities,</line>
            <line>And you have found me; for accordingly</line>
            <line>You tread upon my patience: but be sure</line>
            <line>I will from henceforth rather be myself,</line>
            <line>Mighty and to be fear'd, than my condition;</line>
            <line>Which hath been smooth as oil, soft as young down,</line>
            <line>And therefore lost that title of respect</line>
            <line>Which the proud soul ne'er pays but to the proud.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Our house, my sovereign liege, little deserves</line>
            <line>The scourge of greatness to be used on it;</line>
            <line>And that same greatness too which our own hands</line>
            <line>Have holp to make so portly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>My lord.--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>Worcester, get thee gone; for I do see</line>
            <line>Danger and disobedience in thine eye:</line>
            <line>O, sir, your presence is too bold and peremptory,</line>
            <line>And majesty might never yet endure</line>
            <line>The moody frontier of a servant brow.</line>
            <line>You have good leave to leave us: when we need</line>
            <line>Your use and counsel, we shall send for you.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit Worcester</stagedir>
            <line>You were about to speak.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>To North</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>Yea, my good lord.</line>
            <line>Those prisoners in your highness' name demanded,</line>
            <line>Which Harry Percy here at Holmedon took,</line>
            <line>Were, as he says, not with such strength denied</line>
            <line>As is deliver'd to your majesty:</line>
            <line>Either envy, therefore, or misprison</line>
            <line>Is guilty of this fault and not my son.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>My liege, I did deny no prisoners.</line>
            <line>But I remember, when the fight was done,</line>
            <line>When I was dry with rage and extreme toil,</line>
            <line>Breathless and faint, leaning upon my sword,</line>
            <line>Came there a certain lord, neat, and trimly dress'd,</line>
            <line>Fresh as a bridegroom; and his chin new reap'd</line>
            <line>Show'd like a stubble-land at harvest-home;</line>
            <line>He was perfumed like a milliner;</line>
            <line>And 'twixt his finger and his thumb he held</line>
            <line>A pouncet-box, which ever and anon</line>
            <line>He gave his nose and took't away again;</line>
            <line>Who therewith angry, when it next came there,</line>
            <line>Took it in snuff; and still he smiled and talk'd,</line>
            <line>And as the soldiers bore dead bodies by,</line>
            <line>He call'd them untaught knaves, unmannerly,</line>
            <line>To bring a slovenly unhandsome corse</line>
            <line>Betwixt the wind and his nobility.</line>
            <line>With many holiday and lady terms</line>
            <line>He question'd me; amongst the rest, demanded</line>
            <line>My prisoners in your majesty's behalf.</line>
            <line>I then, all smarting with my wounds being cold,</line>
            <line>To be so pester'd with a popinjay,</line>
            <line>Out of my grief and my impatience,</line>
            <line>Answer'd neglectingly I know not what,</line>
            <line>He should or he should not; for he made me mad</line>
            <line>To see him shine so brisk and smell so sweet</line>
            <line>And talk so like a waiting-gentlewoman</line>
            <line>Of guns and drums and wounds,--God save the mark!--</line>
            <line>And telling me the sovereign'st thing on earth</line>
            <line>Was parmaceti for an inward bruise;</line>
            <line>And that it was great pity, so it was,</line>
            <line>This villanous salt-petre should be digg'd</line>
            <line>Out of the bowels of the harmless earth,</line>
            <line>Which many a good tall fellow had destroy'd</line>
            <line>So cowardly; and but for these vile guns,</line>
            <line>He would himself have been a soldier.</line>
            <line>This bald unjointed chat of his, my lord,</line>
            <line>I answer'd indirectly, as I said;</line>
            <line>And I beseech you, let not his report</line>
            <line>Come current for an accusation</line>
            <line>Betwixt my love and your high majesty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR WALTER BLUNT</speaker>
            <line>The circumstance consider'd, good my lord,</line>
            <line>Whate'er Lord Harry Percy then had said</line>
            <line>To such a person and in such a place,</line>
            <line>At such a time, with all the rest retold,</line>
            <line>May reasonably die and never rise</line>
            <line>To do him wrong or any way impeach</line>
            <line>What then he said, so he unsay it now.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>Why, yet he doth deny his prisoners,</line>
            <line>But with proviso and exception,</line>
            <line>That we at our own charge shall ransom straight</line>
            <line>His brother-in-law, the foolish Mortimer;</line>
            <line>Who, on my soul, hath wilfully betray'd</line>
            <line>The lives of those that he did lead to fight</line>
            <line>Against that great magician, damn'd Glendower,</line>
            <line>Whose daughter, as we hear, the Earl of March</line>
            <line>Hath lately married. Shall our coffers, then,</line>
            <line>Be emptied to redeem a traitor home?</line>
            <line>Shall we but treason? and indent with fears,</line>
            <line>When they have lost and forfeited themselves?</line>
            <line>No, on the barren mountains let him starve;</line>
            <line>For I shall never hold that man my friend</line>
            <line>Whose tongue shall ask me for one penny cost</line>
            <line>To ransom home revolted Mortimer.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>Revolted Mortimer!</line>
            <line>He never did fall off, my sovereign liege,</line>
            <line>But by the chance of war; to prove that true</line>
            <line>Needs no more but one tongue for all those wounds,</line>
            <line>Those mouthed wounds, which valiantly he took</line>
            <line>When on the gentle Severn's sedgy bank,</line>
            <line>In single opposition, hand to hand,</line>
            <line>He did confound the best part of an hour</line>
            <line>In changing hardiment with great Glendower:</line>
            <line>Three times they breathed and three times did</line>
            <line>they drink,</line>
            <line>Upon agreement, of swift Severn's flood;</line>
            <line>Who then, affrighted with their bloody looks,</line>
            <line>Ran fearfully among the trembling reeds,</line>
            <line>And hid his crisp head in the hollow bank,</line>
            <line>Bloodstained with these valiant combatants.</line>
            <line>Never did base and rotten policy</line>
            <line>Colour her working with such deadly wounds;</line>
            <line>Nor could the noble Mortimer</line>
            <line>Receive so many, and all willingly:</line>
            <line>Then let not him be slander'd with revolt.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>Thou dost belie him, Percy, thou dost belie him;</line>
            <line>He never did encounter with Glendower:</line>
            <line>I tell thee,</line>
            <line>He durst as well have met the devil alone</line>
            <line>As Owen Glendower for an enemy.</line>
            <line>Art thou not ashamed? But, sirrah, henceforth</line>
            <line>Let me not hear you speak of Mortimer:</line>
            <line>Send me your prisoners with the speediest means,</line>
            <line>Or you shall hear in such a kind from me</line>
            <line>As will displease you. My Lord Northumberland,</line>
            <line>We licence your departure with your son.</line>
            <line>Send us your prisoners, or you will hear of it.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt King Henry, Blunt, and train</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>An if the devil come and roar for them,</line>
            <line>I will not send them: I will after straight</line>
            <line>And tell him so; for I will ease my heart,</line>
            <line>Albeit I make a hazard of my head.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>What, drunk with choler? stay and pause awhile:</line>
            <line>Here comes your uncle.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter WORCESTER</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>Speak of Mortimer!</line>
            <line>'Zounds, I will speak of him; and let my soul</line>
            <line>Want mercy, if I do not join with him:</line>
            <line>Yea, on his part I'll empty all these veins,</line>
            <line>And shed my dear blood drop by drop in the dust,</line>
            <line>But I will lift the down-trod Mortimer</line>
            <line>As high in the air as this unthankful king,</line>
            <line>As this ingrate and canker'd Bolingbroke.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>Brother, the king hath made your nephew mad.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Who struck this heat up after I was gone?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>He will, forsooth, have all my prisoners;</line>
            <line>And when I urged the ransom once again</line>
            <line>Of my wife's brother, then his cheek look'd pale,</line>
            <line>And on my face he turn'd an eye of death,</line>
            <line>Trembling even at the name of Mortimer.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
            <line>I cannot blame him: was not he proclaim'd</line>
            <line>By Richard that dead is the next of blood?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>He was; I heard the proclamation:</line>
            <line>And then it was when the unhappy king,</line>
            <line>--Whose wrongs in us God pardon!--did set forth</line>
            <line>Upon his Irish expedition;</line>
            <line>From whence he intercepted did return</line>
            <line>To be deposed and shortly murdered.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
            <line>And for whose death we in the world's wide mouth</line>
            <line>Live scandalized and foully spoken of.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>But soft, I pray you; did King Richard then</line>
            <line>Proclaim my brother Edmund Mortimer</line>
            <line>Heir to the crown?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>He did; myself did hear it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>Nay, then I cannot blame his cousin king,</line>
            <line>That wished him on the barren mountains starve.</line>
            <line>But shall it be that you, that set the crown</line>
            <line>Upon the head of this forgetful man</line>
            <line>And for his sake wear the detested blot</line>
            <line>Of murderous subornation, shall it be,</line>
            <line>That you a world of curses undergo,</line>
            <line>Being the agents, or base second means,</line>
            <line>The cords, the ladder, or the hangman rather?</line>
            <line>O, pardon me that I descend so low,</line>
            <line>To show the line and the predicament</line>
            <line>Wherein you range under this subtle king;</line>
            <line>Shall it for shame be spoken in these days,</line>
            <line>Or fill up chronicles in time to come,</line>
            <line>That men of your nobility and power</line>
            <line>Did gage them both in an unjust behalf,</line>
            <line>As both of you--God pardon it!--have done,</line>
            <line>To put down Richard, that sweet lovely rose,</line>
            <line>An plant this thorn, this canker, Bolingbroke?</line>
            <line>And shall it in more shame be further spoken,</line>
            <line>That you are fool'd, discarded and shook off</line>
            <line>By him for whom these shames ye underwent?</line>
            <line>No; yet time serves wherein you may redeem</line>
            <line>Your banish'd honours and restore yourselves</line>
            <line>Into the good thoughts of the world again,</line>
            <line>Revenge the jeering and disdain'd contempt</line>
            <line>Of this proud king, who studies day and night</line>
            <line>To answer all the debt he owes to you</line>
            <line>Even with the bloody payment of your deaths:</line>
            <line>Therefore, I say--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Peace, cousin, say no more:</line>
            <line>And now I will unclasp a secret book,</line>
            <line>And to your quick-conceiving discontents</line>
            <line>I'll read you matter deep and dangerous,</line>
            <line>As full of peril and adventurous spirit</line>
            <line>As to o'er-walk a current roaring loud</line>
            <line>On the unsteadfast footing of a spear.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>If he fall in, good night! or sink or swim:</line>
            <line>Send danger from the east unto the west,</line>
            <line>So honour cross it from the north to south,</line>
            <line>And let them grapple: O, the blood more stirs</line>
            <line>To rouse a lion than to start a hare!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>Imagination of some great exploit</line>
            <line>Drives him beyond the bounds of patience.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>By heaven, methinks it were an easy leap,</line>
            <line>To pluck bright honour from the pale-faced moon,</line>
            <line>Or dive into the bottom of the deep,</line>
            <line>Where fathom-line could never touch the ground,</line>
            <line>And pluck up drowned honour by the locks;</line>
            <line>So he that doth redeem her thence might wear</line>
            <line>Without corrival, all her dignities:</line>
            <line>But out upon this half-faced fellowship!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
            <line>He apprehends a world of figures here,</line>
            <line>But not the form of what he should attend.</line>
            <line>Good cousin, give me audience for a while.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>I cry you mercy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Those same noble Scots</line>
            <line>That are your prisoners,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>I'll keep them all;</line>
            <line>By God, he shall not have a Scot of them;</line>
            <line>No, if a Scot would save his soul, he shall not:</line>
            <line>I'll keep them, by this hand.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
            <line>You start away</line>
            <line>And lend no ear unto my purposes.</line>
            <line>Those prisoners you shall keep.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>Nay, I will; that's flat:</line>
            <line>He said he would not ransom Mortimer;</line>
            <line>Forbad my tongue to speak of Mortimer;</line>
            <line>But I will find him when he lies asleep,</line>
            <line>And in his ear I'll holla 'Mortimer!'</line>
            <line>Nay,</line>
            <line>I'll have a starling shall be taught to speak</line>
            <line>Nothing but 'Mortimer,' and give it him</line>
            <line>To keep his anger still in motion.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Hear you, cousin; a word.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>All studies here I solemnly defy,</line>
            <line>Save how to gall and pinch this Bolingbroke:</line>
            <line>And that same sword-and-buckler Prince of Wales,</line>
            <line>But that I think his father loves him not</line>
            <line>And would be glad he met with some mischance,</line>
            <line>I would have him poison'd with a pot of ale.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Farewell, kinsman: I'll talk to you</line>
            <line>When you are better temper'd to attend.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>Why, what a wasp-stung and impatient fool</line>
            <line>Art thou to break into this woman's mood,</line>
            <line>Tying thine ear to no tongue but thine own!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>Why, look you, I am whipp'd and scourged with rods,</line>
            <line>Nettled and stung with pismires, when I hear</line>
            <line>Of this vile politician, Bolingbroke.</line>
            <line>In Richard's time,--what do you call the place?--</line>
            <line>A plague upon it, it is in Gloucestershire;</line>
            <line>'Twas where the madcap duke his uncle kept,</line>
            <line>His uncle York; where I first bow'd my knee</line>
            <line>Unto this king of smiles, this Bolingbroke,--</line>
            <line>'Sblood!--</line>
            <line>When you and he came back from Ravenspurgh.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>At Berkley castle.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>You say true:</line>
            <line>Why, what a candy deal of courtesy</line>
            <line>This fawning greyhound then did proffer me!</line>
            <line>Look,'when his infant fortune came to age,'</line>
            <line>And 'gentle Harry Percy,' and 'kind cousin;'</line>
            <line>O, the devil take such cozeners! God forgive me!</line>
            <line>Good uncle, tell your tale; I have done.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Nay, if you have not, to it again;</line>
            <line>We will stay your leisure.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>I have done, i' faith.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Then once more to your Scottish prisoners.</line>
            <line>Deliver them up without their ransom straight,</line>
            <line>And make the Douglas' son your only mean</line>
            <line>For powers in Scotland; which, for divers reasons</line>
            <line>Which I shall send you written, be assured,</line>
            <line>Will easily be granted. You, my lord,</line>
            <stagedir>To Northumberland</stagedir>
            <line>Your son in Scotland being thus employ'd,</line>
            <line>Shall secretly into the bosom creep</line>
            <line>Of that same noble prelate, well beloved,</line>
            <line>The archbishop.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>Of York, is it not?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
            <line>True; who bears hard</line>
            <line>His brother's death at Bristol, the Lord Scroop.</line>
            <line>I speak not this in estimation,</line>
            <line>As what I think might be, but what I know</line>
            <line>Is ruminated, plotted and set down,</line>
            <line>And only stays but to behold the face</line>
            <line>Of that occasion that shall bring it on.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>I smell it: upon my life, it will do well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>Before the game is afoot, thou still let'st slip.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>Why, it cannot choose but be a noble plot;</line>
            <line>And then the power of Scotland and of York,</line>
            <line>To join with Mortimer, ha?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
            <line>And so they shall.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>In faith, it is exceedingly well aim'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
            <line>And 'tis no little reason bids us speed,</line>
            <line>To save our heads by raising of a head;</line>
            <line>For, bear ourselves as even as we can,</line>
            <line>The king will always think him in our debt,</line>
            <line>And think we think ourselves unsatisfied,</line>
            <line>Till he hath found a time to pay us home:</line>
            <line>And see already how he doth begin</line>
            <line>To make us strangers to his looks of love.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>He does, he does: we'll be revenged on him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Cousin, farewell: no further go in this</line>
            <line>Than I by letters shall direct your course.</line>
            <line>When time is ripe, which will be suddenly,</line>
            <line>I'll steal to Glendower and Lord Mortimer;</line>
            <line>Where you and Douglas and our powers at once,</line>
            <line>As I will fashion it, shall happily meet,</line>
            <line>To bear our fortunes in our own strong arms,</line>
            <line>Which now we hold at much uncertainty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NORTHUMBERLAND</speaker>
            <line>Farewell, good brother: we shall thrive, I trust.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>Uncle, Adieu: O, let the hours be short</line>
            <line>Till fields and blows and groans applaud our sport!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>