<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net/doctypes/dita/shakespear/dtd/act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-5">
   <title>ACT V</title>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  KING HENRY IV's camp near Shrewsbury.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter KING HENRY, PRINCE HENRY, Lord John of
LANCASTER, EARL OF WESTMORELAND, SIR WALTER BLUNT,
and FALSTAFF</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>How bloodily the sun begins to peer</line>
            <line>Above yon busky hill! the day looks pale</line>
            <line>At his distemperature.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>The southern wind</line>
            <line>Doth play the trumpet to his purposes,</line>
            <line>And by his hollow whistling in the leaves</line>
            <line>Foretells a tempest and a blustering day.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>Then with the losers let it sympathize,</line>
            <line>For nothing can seem foul to those that win.</line>
            <stagedir>The trumpet sounds</stagedir>
            <stagedir>Enter WORCESTER and VERNON</stagedir>
            <line>How now, my Lord of Worcester! 'tis not well</line>
            <line>That you and I should meet upon such terms</line>
            <line>As now we meet. You have deceived our trust,</line>
            <line>And made us doff our easy robes of peace,</line>
            <line>To crush our old limbs in ungentle steel:</line>
            <line>This is not well, my lord, this is not well.</line>
            <line>What say you to it? will you again unknit</line>
            <line>This curlish knot of all-abhorred war?</line>
            <line>And move in that obedient orb again</line>
            <line>Where you did give a fair and natural light,</line>
            <line>And be no more an exhaled meteor,</line>
            <line>A prodigy of fear and a portent</line>
            <line>Of broached mischief to the unborn times?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Hear me, my liege:</line>
            <line>For mine own part, I could be well content</line>
            <line>To entertain the lag-end of my life</line>
            <line>With quiet hours; for I do protest,</line>
            <line>I have not sought the day of this dislike.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>You have not sought it! how comes it, then?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Rebellion lay in his way, and he found it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>Peace, chewet, peace!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
            <line>It pleased your majesty to turn your looks</line>
            <line>Of favour from myself and all our house;</line>
            <line>And yet I must remember you, my lord,</line>
            <line>We were the first and dearest of your friends.</line>
            <line>For you my staff of office did I break</line>
            <line>In Richard's time; and posted day and night</line>
            <line>to meet you on the way, and kiss your hand,</line>
            <line>When yet you were in place and in account</line>
            <line>Nothing so strong and fortunate as I.</line>
            <line>It was myself, my brother and his son,</line>
            <line>That brought you home and boldly did outdare</line>
            <line>The dangers of the time. You swore to us,</line>
            <line>And you did swear that oath at Doncaster,</line>
            <line>That you did nothing purpose 'gainst the state;</line>
            <line>Nor claim no further than your new-fall'n right,</line>
            <line>The seat of Gaunt, dukedom of Lancaster:</line>
            <line>To this we swore our aid. But in short space</line>
            <line>It rain'd down fortune showering on your head;</line>
            <line>And such a flood of greatness fell on you,</line>
            <line>What with our help, what with the absent king,</line>
            <line>What with the injuries of a wanton time,</line>
            <line>The seeming sufferances that you had borne,</line>
            <line>And the contrarious winds that held the king</line>
            <line>So long in his unlucky Irish wars</line>
            <line>That all in England did repute him dead:</line>
            <line>And from this swarm of fair advantages</line>
            <line>You took occasion to be quickly woo'd</line>
            <line>To gripe the general sway into your hand;</line>
            <line>Forget your oath to us at Doncaster;</line>
            <line>And being fed by us you used us so</line>
            <line>As that ungentle hull, the cuckoo's bird,</line>
            <line>Useth the sparrow; did oppress our nest;</line>
            <line>Grew by our feeding to so great a bulk</line>
            <line>That even our love durst not come near your sight</line>
            <line>For fear of swallowing; but with nimble wing</line>
            <line>We were enforced, for safety sake, to fly</line>
            <line>Out of sight and raise this present head;</line>
            <line>Whereby we stand opposed by such means</line>
            <line>As you yourself have forged against yourself</line>
            <line>By unkind usage, dangerous countenance,</line>
            <line>And violation of all faith and troth</line>
            <line>Sworn to us in your younger enterprise.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>These things indeed you have articulate,</line>
            <line>Proclaim'd at market-crosses, read in churches,</line>
            <line>To face the garment of rebellion</line>
            <line>With some fine colour that may please the eye</line>
            <line>Of fickle changelings and poor discontents,</line>
            <line>Which gape and rub the elbow at the news</line>
            <line>Of hurlyburly innovation:</line>
            <line>And never yet did insurrection want</line>
            <line>Such water-colours to impaint his cause;</line>
            <line>Nor moody beggars, starving for a time</line>
            <line>Of pellmell havoc and confusion.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>In both your armies there is many a soul</line>
            <line>Shall pay full dearly for this encounter,</line>
            <line>If once they join in trial. Tell your nephew,</line>
            <line>The Prince of Wales doth join with all the world</line>
            <line>In praise of Henry Percy: by my hopes,</line>
            <line>This present enterprise set off his head,</line>
            <line>I do not think a braver gentleman,</line>
            <line>More active-valiant or more valiant-young,</line>
            <line>More daring or more bold, is now alive</line>
            <line>To grace this latter age with noble deeds.</line>
            <line>For my part, I may speak it to my shame,</line>
            <line>I have a truant been to chivalry;</line>
            <line>And so I hear he doth account me too;</line>
            <line>Yet this before my father's majesty--</line>
            <line>I am content that he shall take the odds</line>
            <line>Of his great name and estimation,</line>
            <line>And will, to save the blood on either side,</line>
            <line>Try fortune with him in a single fight.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>And, Prince of Wales, so dare we venture thee,</line>
            <line>Albeit considerations infinite</line>
            <line>Do make against it. No, good Worcester, no,</line>
            <line>We love our people well; even those we love</line>
            <line>That are misled upon your cousin's part;</line>
            <line>And, will they take the offer of our grace,</line>
            <line>Both he and they and you, every man</line>
            <line>Shall be my friend again and I'll be his:</line>
            <line>So tell your cousin, and bring me word</line>
            <line>What he will do: but if he will not yield,</line>
            <line>Rebuke and dread correction wait on us</line>
            <line>And they shall do their office. So, be gone;</line>
            <line>We will not now be troubled with reply:</line>
            <line>We offer fair; take it advisedly.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt WORCESTER and VERNON</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>It will not be accepted, on my life:</line>
            <line>The Douglas and the Hotspur both together</line>
            <line>Are confident against the world in arms.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>Hence, therefore, every leader to his charge;</line>
            <line>For, on their answer, will we set on them:</line>
            <line>And God befriend us, as our cause is just!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt all but PRINCE HENRY and FALSTAFF</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Hal, if thou see me down in the battle and bestride</line>
            <line>me, so; 'tis a point of friendship.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>Nothing but a colossus can do thee that friendship.</line>
            <line>Say thy prayers, and farewell.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>I  would 'twere bed-time, Hal, and all well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>Why, thou owest God a death.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit PRINCE HENRY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>'Tis not due yet; I would be loath to pay him before</line>
            <line>his day. What need I be so forward with him that</line>
            <line>calls not on me? Well, 'tis no matter; honour pricks</line>
            <line>me on. Yea, but how if honour prick me off when I</line>
            <line>come on? how then? Can honour set to a leg? no: or</line>
            <line>an arm? no: or take away the grief of a wound? no.</line>
            <line>Honour hath no skill in surgery, then? no. What is</line>
            <line>honour? a word. What is in that word honour? what</line>
            <line>is that honour? air. A trim reckoning! Who hath it?</line>
            <line>he that died o' Wednesday. Doth he feel it? no.</line>
            <line>Doth he hear it? no. 'Tis insensible, then. Yea,</line>
            <line>to the dead. But will it not live with the living?</line>
            <line>no. Why? detraction will not suffer it. Therefore</line>
            <line>I'll none of it. Honour is a mere scutcheon: and so</line>
            <line>ends my catechism.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  The rebel camp.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter WORCESTER and VERNON</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
            <line>O, no, my nephew must not know, Sir Richard,</line>
            <line>The liberal and kind offer of the king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VERNON</speaker>
            <line>'Twere best he did.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Then are we all undone.</line>
            <line>It is not possible, it cannot be,</line>
            <line>The king should keep his word in loving us;</line>
            <line>He will suspect us still and find a time</line>
            <line>To punish this offence in other faults:</line>
            <line>Suspicion all our lives shall be stuck full of eyes;</line>
            <line>For treason is but trusted like the fox,</line>
            <line>Who, ne'er so tame, so cherish'd and lock'd up,</line>
            <line>Will have a wild trick of his ancestors.</line>
            <line>Look how we can, or sad or merrily,</line>
            <line>Interpretation will misquote our looks,</line>
            <line>And we shall feed like oxen at a stall,</line>
            <line>The better cherish'd, still the nearer death.</line>
            <line>My nephew's trespass may be well forgot;</line>
            <line>it hath the excuse of youth and heat of blood,</line>
            <line>And an adopted name of privilege,</line>
            <line>A hair-brain'd Hotspur, govern'd by a spleen:</line>
            <line>All his offences live upon my head</line>
            <line>And on his father's; we did train him on,</line>
            <line>And, his corruption being ta'en from us,</line>
            <line>We, as the spring of all, shall pay for all.</line>
            <line>Therefore, good cousin, let not Harry know,</line>
            <line>In any case, the offer of the king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VERNON</speaker>
            <line>Deliver what you will; I'll say 'tis so.</line>
            <line>Here comes your cousin.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter HOTSPUR and DOUGLAS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>My uncle is return'd:</line>
            <line>Deliver up my Lord of Westmoreland.</line>
            <line>Uncle, what news?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
            <line>The king will bid you battle presently.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EARL OF DOUGLAS</speaker>
            <line>Defy him by the Lord of Westmoreland.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>Lord Douglas, go you and tell him so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EARL OF DOUGLAS</speaker>
            <line>Marry, and shall, and very willingly.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
            <line>There is no seeming mercy in the king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>Did you beg any? God forbid!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
            <line>I told him gently of our grievances,</line>
            <line>Of his oath-breaking; which he mended thus,</line>
            <line>By now forswearing that he is forsworn:</line>
            <line>He calls us rebels, traitors; and will scourge</line>
            <line>With haughty arms this hateful name in us.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter the EARL OF DOUGLAS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EARL OF DOUGLAS</speaker>
            <line>Arm, gentlemen; to arms! for I have thrown</line>
            <line>A brave defiance in King Henry's teeth,</line>
            <line>And Westmoreland, that was engaged, did bear it;</line>
            <line>Which cannot choose but bring him quickly on.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
            <line>The Prince of Wales stepp'd forth before the king,</line>
            <line>And, nephew, challenged you to single fight.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>O, would the quarrel lay upon our heads,</line>
            <line>And that no man might draw short breath today</line>
            <line>But I and Harry Monmouth! Tell me, tell me,</line>
            <line>How show'd his tasking? seem'd it in contempt?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VERNON</speaker>
            <line>No, by my soul; I never in my life</line>
            <line>Did hear a challenge urged more modestly,</line>
            <line>Unless a brother should a brother dare</line>
            <line>To gentle exercise and proof of arms.</line>
            <line>He gave you all the duties of a man;</line>
            <line>Trimm'd up your praises with a princely tongue,</line>
            <line>Spoke to your deservings like a chronicle,</line>
            <line>Making you ever better than his praise</line>
            <line>By still dispraising praise valued in you;</line>
            <line>And, which became him like a prince indeed,</line>
            <line>He made a blushing cital of himself;</line>
            <line>And chid his truant youth with such a grace</line>
            <line>As if he master'd there a double spirit.</line>
            <line>Of teaching and of learning instantly.</line>
            <line>There did he pause: but let me tell the world,</line>
            <line>If he outlive the envy of this day,</line>
            <line>England did never owe so sweet a hope,</line>
            <line>So much misconstrued in his wantonness.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>Cousin, I think thou art enamoured</line>
            <line>On his follies: never did I hear</line>
            <line>Of any prince so wild a libertine.</line>
            <line>But be he as he will, yet once ere night</line>
            <line>I will embrace him with a soldier's arm,</line>
            <line>That he shall shrink under my courtesy.</line>
            <line>Arm, arm with speed: and, fellows, soldiers, friends,</line>
            <line>Better consider what you have to do</line>
            <line>Than I, that have not well the gift of tongue,</line>
            <line>Can lift your blood up with persuasion.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter a Messenger</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>My lord, here are letters for you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>I cannot read them now.</line>
            <line>O gentlemen, the time of life is short!</line>
            <line>To spend that shortness basely were too long,</line>
            <line>If life did ride upon a dial's point,</line>
            <line>Still ending at the arrival of an hour.</line>
            <line>An if we live, we live to tread on kings;</line>
            <line>If die, brave death, when princes die with us!</line>
            <line>Now, for our consciences, the arms are fair,</line>
            <line>When the intent of bearing them is just.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter another Messenger</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>My lord, prepare; the king comes on apace.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>I thank him, that he cuts me from my tale,</line>
            <line>For I profess not talking; only this--</line>
            <line>Let each man do his best: and here draw I</line>
            <line>A sword, whose temper I intend to stain</line>
            <line>With the best blood that I can meet withal</line>
            <line>In the adventure of this perilous day.</line>
            <line>Now, Esperance! Percy! and set on.</line>
            <line>Sound all the lofty instruments of war,</line>
            <line>And by that music let us all embrace;</line>
            <line>For, heaven to earth, some of us never shall</line>
            <line>A second time do such a courtesy.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>The trumpets sound. They embrace, and exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  Plain between the camps.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>KING HENRY enters with his power. Alarum to the
battle. Then enter DOUGLAS and SIR WALTER BLUNT</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR WALTER BLUNT</speaker>
            <line>What is thy name, that in the battle thus</line>
            <line>Thou crossest me? what honour dost thou seek</line>
            <line>Upon my head?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EARL OF DOUGLAS</speaker>
            <line>Know then, my name is Douglas;</line>
            <line>And I do haunt thee in the battle thus</line>
            <line>Because some tell me that thou art a king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR WALTER BLUNT</speaker>
            <line>They tell thee true.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EARL OF DOUGLAS</speaker>
            <line>The Lord of Stafford dear to-day hath bought</line>
            <line>Thy likeness, for instead of thee, King Harry,</line>
            <line>This sword hath ended him: so shall it thee,</line>
            <line>Unless thou yield thee as my prisoner.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR WALTER BLUNT</speaker>
            <line>I was not born a yielder, thou proud Scot;</line>
            <line>And thou shalt find a king that will revenge</line>
            <line>Lord Stafford's death.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>They fight. DOUGLAS kills SIR WALTER BLUNT.
Enter HOTSPUR</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>O Douglas, hadst thou fought at Holmedon thus,</line>
            <line>never had triumph'd upon a Scot.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EARL OF DOUGLAS</speaker>
            <line>All's done, all's won; here breathless lies the king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>Where?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EARL OF DOUGLAS</speaker>
            <line>Here.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>This, Douglas? no: I know this face full well:</line>
            <line>A gallant knight he was, his name was Blunt;</line>
            <line>Semblably furnish'd like the king himself.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EARL OF DOUGLAS</speaker>
            <line>A fool go with thy soul, whither it goes!</line>
            <line>A borrow'd title hast thou bought too dear:</line>
            <line>Why didst thou tell me that thou wert a king?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>The king hath many marching in his coats.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EARL OF DOUGLAS</speaker>
            <line>Now, by my sword, I will kill all his coats;</line>
            <line>I'll murder all his wardrobe, piece by piece,</line>
            <line>Until I meet the king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>Up, and away!</line>
            <line>Our soldiers stand full fairly for the day.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Alarum. Enter FALSTAFF, solus</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Though I could 'scape shot-free at London, I fear</line>
            <line>the shot here; here's no scoring but upon the pate.</line>
            <line>Soft! who are you? Sir Walter Blunt: there's honour</line>
            <line>for you! here's no vanity! I am as hot as moulten</line>
            <line>lead, and as heavy too: God keep lead out of me! I</line>
            <line>need no more weight than mine own bowels. I have</line>
            <line>led my ragamuffins where they are peppered: there's</line>
            <line>not three of my hundred and fifty left alive; and</line>
            <line>they are for the town's end, to beg during life.</line>
            <line>But who comes here?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter PRINCE HENRY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>What, stand'st thou idle here? lend me thy sword:</line>
            <line>Many a nobleman lies stark and stiff</line>
            <line>Under the hoofs of vaunting enemies,</line>
            <line>Whose deaths are yet unrevenged: I prithee,</line>
            <line>lend me thy sword.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>O Hal, I prithee, give me leave to breathe awhile.</line>
            <line>Turk Gregory never did such deeds in arms as I have</line>
            <line>done this day. I have paid Percy, I have made him sure.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>He is, indeed; and living to kill thee. I prithee,</line>
            <line>lend me thy sword.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Nay, before God, Hal, if Percy be alive, thou get'st</line>
            <line>not my sword; but take my pistol, if thou wilt.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>Give it to me: what, is it in the case?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Ay, Hal; 'tis hot, 'tis hot; there's that will sack a city.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>PRINCE HENRY draws it out, and finds it to be a
bottle of sack</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>What, is it a time to jest and dally now?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>He throws the bottle at him. Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Well, if Percy be alive, I'll pierce him. If he do</line>
            <line>come in my way, so: if he do not, if I come in his</line>
            <line>willingly, let him make a carbonado of me. I like</line>
            <line>not such grinning honour as Sir Walter hath: give me</line>
            <line>life: which if I can save, so; if not, honour comes</line>
            <line>unlooked for, and there's an end.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit FALSTAFF</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-4">
      <title>SCENE IV.  Another part of the field.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Alarum. Excursions. Enter PRINCE HENRY, LORD JOHN
OF LANCASTER, and EARL OF WESTMORELAND</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>I prithee,</line>
            <line>Harry, withdraw thyself; thou bleed'st too much.</line>
            <line>Lord John of Lancaster, go you with him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LANCASTER</speaker>
            <line>Not I, my lord, unless I did bleed too.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>I beseech your majesty, make up,</line>
            <line>Lest your retirement do amaze your friends.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>I will do so.</line>
            <line>My Lord of Westmoreland, lead him to his tent.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WESTMORELAND</speaker>
            <line>Come, my lord, I'll lead you to your tent.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>Lead me, my lord? I do not need your help:</line>
            <line>And God forbid a shallow scratch should drive</line>
            <line>The Prince of Wales from such a field as this,</line>
            <line>Where stain'd nobility lies trodden on,</line>
            <line>and rebels' arms triumph in massacres!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LANCASTER</speaker>
            <line>We breathe too long: come, cousin Westmoreland,</line>
            <line>Our duty this way lies; for God's sake come.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt LANCASTER and WESTMORELAND</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>By God, thou hast deceived me, Lancaster;</line>
            <line>I did not think thee lord of such a spirit:</line>
            <line>Before, I loved thee as a brother, John;</line>
            <line>But now, I do respect thee as my soul.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>I saw him hold Lord Percy at the point</line>
            <line>With lustier maintenance than I did look for</line>
            <line>Of such an ungrown warrior.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>O, this boy</line>
            <line>Lends mettle to us all!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Enter DOUGLAS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EARL OF DOUGLAS</speaker>
            <line>Another king! they grow like Hydra's heads:</line>
            <line>I am the Douglas, fatal to all those</line>
            <line>That wear those colours on them: what art thou,</line>
            <line>That counterfeit'st the person of a king?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>The king himself; who, Douglas, grieves at heart</line>
            <line>So many of his shadows thou hast met</line>
            <line>And not the very king. I have two boys</line>
            <line>Seek Percy and thyself about the field:</line>
            <line>But, seeing thou fall'st on me so luckily,</line>
            <line>I will assay thee: so, defend thyself.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EARL OF DOUGLAS</speaker>
            <line>I fear thou art another counterfeit;</line>
            <line>And yet, in faith, thou bear'st thee like a king:</line>
            <line>But mine I am sure thou art, whoe'er thou be,</line>
            <line>And thus I win thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>They fight. KING HENRY being in danger, PRINCE
HENRY enters</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>Hold up thy head, vile Scot, or thou art like</line>
            <line>Never to hold it up again! the spirits</line>
            <line>Of valiant Shirley, Stafford, Blunt, are in my arms:</line>
            <line>It is the Prince of Wales that threatens thee;</line>
            <line>Who never promiseth but he means to pay.</line>
            <stagedir>They fight: DOUGLAS flies</stagedir>
            <line>Cheerly, my lord how fares your grace?</line>
            <line>Sir Nicholas Gawsey hath for succor sent,</line>
            <line>And so hath Clifton: I'll to Clifton straight.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>Stay, and breathe awhile:</line>
            <line>Thou hast redeem'd thy lost opinion,</line>
            <line>And show'd thou makest some tender of my life,</line>
            <line>In this fair rescue thou hast brought to me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>O God! they did me too much injury</line>
            <line>That ever said I hearken'd for your death.</line>
            <line>If it were so, I might have let alone</line>
            <line>The insulting hand of Douglas over you,</line>
            <line>Which would have been as speedy in your end</line>
            <line>As all the poisonous potions in the world</line>
            <line>And saved the treacherous labour of your son.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>Make up to Clifton: I'll to Sir Nicholas Gawsey.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Enter HOTSPUR</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>If I mistake not, thou art Harry Monmouth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>Thou speak'st as if I would deny my name.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>My name is Harry Percy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>Why, then I see</line>
            <line>A very valiant rebel of the name.</line>
            <line>I am the Prince of Wales; and think not, Percy,</line>
            <line>To share with me in glory any more:</line>
            <line>Two stars keep not their motion in one sphere;</line>
            <line>Nor can one England brook a double reign,</line>
            <line>Of Harry Percy and the Prince of Wales.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>Nor shall it, Harry; for the hour is come</line>
            <line>To end the one of us; and would to God</line>
            <line>Thy name in arms were now as great as mine!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>I'll make it greater ere I part from thee;</line>
            <line>And all the budding honours on thy crest</line>
            <line>I'll crop, to make a garland for my head.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>I can no longer brook thy vanities.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>They fight</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Enter FALSTAFF</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Well said, Hal! to it Hal! Nay, you shall find no</line>
            <line>boy's play here, I can tell you.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter DOUGLAS; he fights with FALSTAFF,
who falls down as if he were dead, and exit
DOUGLAS. HOTSPUR is wounded, and falls</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>O, Harry, thou hast robb'd me of my youth!</line>
            <line>I better brook the loss of brittle life</line>
            <line>Than those proud titles thou hast won of me;</line>
            <line>They wound my thoughts worse than sword my flesh:</line>
            <line>But thought's the slave of life, and life time's fool;</line>
            <line>And time, that takes survey of all the world,</line>
            <line>Must have a stop. O, I could prophesy,</line>
            <line>But that the earthy and cold hand of death</line>
            <line>Lies on my tongue: no, Percy, thou art dust</line>
            <line>And food for--</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Dies</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>For worms, brave Percy: fare thee well, great heart!</line>
            <line>Ill-weaved ambition, how much art thou shrunk!</line>
            <line>When that this body did contain a spirit,</line>
            <line>A kingdom for it was too small a bound;</line>
            <line>But now two paces of the vilest earth</line>
            <line>Is room enough: this earth that bears thee dead</line>
            <line>Bears not alive so stout a gentleman.</line>
            <line>If thou wert sensible of courtesy,</line>
            <line>I should not make so dear a show of zeal:</line>
            <line>But let my favours hide thy mangled face;</line>
            <line>And, even in thy behalf, I'll thank myself</line>
            <line>For doing these fair rites of tenderness.</line>
            <line>Adieu, and take thy praise with thee to heaven!</line>
            <line>Thy ignominy sleep with thee in the grave,</line>
            <line>But not remember'd in thy epitaph!</line>
            <stagedir>He spieth FALSTAFF on the ground</stagedir>
            <line>What, old acquaintance! could not all this flesh</line>
            <line>Keep in a little life? Poor Jack, farewell!</line>
            <line>I could have better spared a better man:</line>
            <line>O, I should have a heavy miss of thee,</line>
            <line>If I were much in love with vanity!</line>
            <line>Death hath not struck so fat a deer to-day,</line>
            <line>Though many dearer, in this bloody fray.</line>
            <line>Embowell'd will I see thee by and by:</line>
            <line>Till then in blood by noble Percy lie.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit PRINCE HENRY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Rising up</stagedir>  Embowelled! if thou embowel me to-day,</line>
            <line>I'll give you leave to powder me and eat me too</line>
            <line>to-morrow. 'Sblood,'twas time to counterfeit, or</line>
            <line>that hot termagant Scot had paid me scot and lot too.</line>
            <line>Counterfeit? I lie, I am no counterfeit: to die,</line>
            <line>is to be a counterfeit; for he is but the</line>
            <line>counterfeit of a man who hath not the life of a man:</line>
            <line>but to counterfeit dying, when a man thereby</line>
            <line>liveth, is to be no counterfeit, but the true and</line>
            <line>perfect image of life indeed. The better part of</line>
            <line>valour is discretion; in the which better part I</line>
            <line>have saved my life.'Zounds, I am afraid of this</line>
            <line>gunpowder Percy, though he be dead: how, if he</line>
            <line>should counterfeit too and rise? by my faith, I am</line>
            <line>afraid he would prove the better counterfeit.</line>
            <line>Therefore I'll make him sure; yea, and I'll swear I</line>
            <line>killed him. Why may not he rise as well as I?</line>
            <line>Nothing confutes me but eyes, and nobody sees me.</line>
            <line>Therefore, sirrah,</line>
            <stagedir>Stabbing him</stagedir>
            <line>with a new wound in your thigh, come you along with me.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Takes up HOTSPUR on his back</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Re-enter PRINCE HENRY and LORD JOHN OF LANCASTER</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>Come, brother John; full bravely hast thou flesh'd</line>
            <line>Thy maiden sword.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LANCASTER</speaker>
            <line>But, soft! whom have we here?</line>
            <line>Did you not tell me this fat man was dead?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>I did; I saw him dead,</line>
            <line>Breathless and bleeding on the ground. Art</line>
            <line>thou alive?</line>
            <line>Or is it fantasy that plays upon our eyesight?</line>
            <line>I prithee, speak; we will not trust our eyes</line>
            <line>Without our ears: thou art not what thou seem'st.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>No, that's certain; I am not a double man: but if I</line>
            <line>be not Jack Falstaff, then am I a Jack. There is Percy:</line>
            <stagedir>Throwing the body down</stagedir>
            <line>if your father will do me any honour, so; if not, let</line>
            <line>him kill the next Percy himself. I look to be either</line>
            <line>earl or duke, I can assure you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>Why, Percy I killed myself and saw thee dead.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Didst thou? Lord, Lord, how this world is given to</line>
            <line>lying! I grant you I was down and out of breath;</line>
            <line>and so was he: but we rose both at an instant and</line>
            <line>fought a long hour by Shrewsbury clock. If I may be</line>
            <line>believed, so; if not, let them that should reward</line>
            <line>valour bear the sin upon their own heads. I'll take</line>
            <line>it upon my death, I gave him this wound in the</line>
            <line>thigh: if the man were alive and would deny it,</line>
            <line>'zounds, I would make him eat a piece of my sword.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LANCASTER</speaker>
            <line>This is the strangest tale that ever I heard.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>This is the strangest fellow, brother John.</line>
            <line>Come, bring your luggage nobly on your back:</line>
            <line>For my part, if a lie may do thee grace,</line>
            <line>I'll gild it with the happiest terms I have.</line>
            <stagedir>A retreat is sounded</stagedir>
            <line>The trumpet sounds retreat; the day is ours.</line>
            <line>Come, brother, let us to the highest of the field,</line>
            <line>To see what friends are living, who are dead.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt PRINCE HENRY and LANCASTER</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>I'll follow, as they say, for reward. He that</line>
            <line>rewards me, God reward him! If I do grow great,</line>
            <line>I'll grow less; for I'll purge, and leave sack, and</line>
            <line>live cleanly as a nobleman should do.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-5">
      <title>SCENE V.  Another part of the field.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>The trumpets sound. Enter KING HENRY IV, PRINCE
HENRY, LORD JOHN LANCASTER, EARL OF WESTMORELAND,
with WORCESTER and VERNON prisoners</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>Thus ever did rebellion find rebuke.</line>
            <line>Ill-spirited Worcester! did not we send grace,</line>
            <line>Pardon and terms of love to all of you?</line>
            <line>And wouldst thou turn our offers contrary?</line>
            <line>Misuse the tenor of thy kinsman's trust?</line>
            <line>Three knights upon our party slain to-day,</line>
            <line>A noble earl and many a creature else</line>
            <line>Had been alive this hour,</line>
            <line>If like a Christian thou hadst truly borne</line>
            <line>Betwixt our armies true intelligence.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
            <line>What I have done my safety urged me to;</line>
            <line>And I embrace this fortune patiently,</line>
            <line>Since not to be avoided it falls on me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>Bear Worcester to the death and Vernon too:</line>
            <line>Other offenders we will pause upon.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt WORCESTER and VERNON, guarded</stagedir>
            <line>How goes the field?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>The noble Scot, Lord Douglas, when he saw</line>
            <line>The fortune of the day quite turn'd from him,</line>
            <line>The noble Percy slain, and all his men</line>
            <line>Upon the foot of fear, fled with the rest;</line>
            <line>And falling from a hill, he was so bruised</line>
            <line>That the pursuers took him. At my tent</line>
            <line>The Douglas is; and I beseech your grace</line>
            <line>I may dispose of him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>With all my heart.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>Then, brother John of Lancaster, to you</line>
            <line>This honourable bounty shall belong:</line>
            <line>Go to the Douglas, and deliver him</line>
            <line>Up to his pleasure, ransomless and free:</line>
            <line>His valour shown upon our crests to-day</line>
            <line>Hath taught us how to cherish such high deeds</line>
            <line>Even in the bosom of our adversaries.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LANCASTER</speaker>
            <line>I thank your grace for this high courtesy,</line>
            <line>Which I shall give away immediately.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING HENRY IV</speaker>
            <line>Then this remains, that we divide our power.</line>
            <line>You, son John, and my cousin Westmoreland</line>
            <line>Towards York shall bend you with your dearest speed,</line>
            <line>To meet Northumberland and the prelate Scroop,</line>
            <line>Who, as we hear, are busily in arms:</line>
            <line>Myself and you, son Harry, will towards Wales,</line>
            <line>To fight with Glendower and the Earl of March.</line>
            <line>Rebellion in this land shall lose his sway,</line>
            <line>Meeting the cheque of such another day:</line>
            <line>And since this business so fair is done,</line>
            <line>Let us not leave till all our own be won.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>