<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net/doctypes/dita/shakespear/dtd/act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-4">
   <title>ACT IV</title>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  The rebel camp near Shrewsbury.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter HOTSPUR, WORCESTER, and DOUGLAS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>Well said, my noble Scot: if speaking truth</line>
            <line>In this fine age were not thought flattery,</line>
            <line>Such attribution should the Douglas have,</line>
            <line>As not a soldier of this season's stamp</line>
            <line>Should go so general current through the world.</line>
            <line>By God, I cannot flatter; I do defy</line>
            <line>The tongues of soothers; but a braver place</line>
            <line>In my heart's love hath no man than yourself:</line>
            <line>Nay, task me to my word; approve me, lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EARL OF DOUGLAS</speaker>
            <line>Thou art the king of honour:</line>
            <line>No man so potent breathes upon the ground</line>
            <line>But I will beard him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>Do so, and 'tis well.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter a Messenger with letters</stagedir>
            <line>What letters hast thou there?--I can but thank you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>These letters come from your father.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>Letters from him! why comes he not himself?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>He cannot come, my lord; he is grievous sick.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>'Zounds! how has he the leisure to be sick</line>
            <line>In such a rustling time? Who leads his power?</line>
            <line>Under whose government come they along?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>His letters bear his mind, not I, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
            <line>I prithee, tell me, doth he keep his bed?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
            <line>He did, my lord, four days ere I set forth;</line>
            <line>And at the time of my departure thence</line>
            <line>He was much fear'd by his physicians.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
            <line>I would the state of time had first been whole</line>
            <line>Ere he by sickness had been visited:</line>
            <line>His health was never better worth than now.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>Sick now! droop now! this sickness doth infect</line>
            <line>The very life-blood of our enterprise;</line>
            <line>'Tis catching hither, even to our camp.</line>
            <line>He writes me here, that inward sickness--</line>
            <line>And that his friends by deputation could not</line>
            <line>So soon be drawn, nor did he think it meet</line>
            <line>To lay so dangerous and dear a trust</line>
            <line>On any soul removed but on his own.</line>
            <line>Yet doth he give us bold advertisement,</line>
            <line>That with our small conjunction we should on,</line>
            <line>To see how fortune is disposed to us;</line>
            <line>For, as he writes, there is no quailing now.</line>
            <line>Because the king is certainly possess'd</line>
            <line>Of all our purposes. What say you to it?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Your father's sickness is a maim to us.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>A perilous gash, a very limb lopp'd off:</line>
            <line>And yet, in faith, it is not; his present want</line>
            <line>Seems more than we shall find it: were it good</line>
            <line>To set the exact wealth of all our states</line>
            <line>All at one cast? to set so rich a main</line>
            <line>On the nice hazard of one doubtful hour?</line>
            <line>It were not good; for therein should we read</line>
            <line>The very bottom and the soul of hope,</line>
            <line>The very list, the very utmost bound</line>
            <line>Of all our fortunes.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EARL OF DOUGLAS</speaker>
            <line>'Faith, and so we should;</line>
            <line>Where now remains a sweet reversion:</line>
            <line>We may boldly spend upon the hope of what</line>
            <line>Is to come in:</line>
            <line>A comfort of retirement lives in this.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>A rendezvous, a home to fly unto.</line>
            <line>If that the devil and mischance look big</line>
            <line>Upon the maidenhead of our affairs.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
            <line>But yet I would your father had been here.</line>
            <line>The quality and hair of our attempt</line>
            <line>Brooks no division: it will be thought</line>
            <line>By some, that know not why he is away,</line>
            <line>That wisdom, loyalty and mere dislike</line>
            <line>Of our proceedings kept the earl from hence:</line>
            <line>And think how such an apprehension</line>
            <line>May turn the tide of fearful faction</line>
            <line>And breed a kind of question in our cause;</line>
            <line>For well you know we of the offering side</line>
            <line>Must keep aloof from strict arbitrement,</line>
            <line>And stop all sight-holes, every loop from whence</line>
            <line>The eye of reason may pry in upon us:</line>
            <line>This absence of your father's draws a curtain,</line>
            <line>That shows the ignorant a kind of fear</line>
            <line>Before not dreamt of.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>You strain too far.</line>
            <line>I rather of his absence make this use:</line>
            <line>It lends a lustre and more great opinion,</line>
            <line>A larger dare to our great enterprise,</line>
            <line>Than if the earl were here; for men must think,</line>
            <line>If we without his help can make a head</line>
            <line>To push against a kingdom, with his help</line>
            <line>We shall o'erturn it topsy-turvy down.</line>
            <line>Yet all goes well, yet all our joints are whole.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EARL OF DOUGLAS</speaker>
            <line>As heart can think: there is not such a word</line>
            <line>Spoke of in Scotland as this term of fear.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter SIR RICHARD VERNON</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>My cousin Vernon, welcome, by my soul.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VERNON</speaker>
            <line>Pray God my news be worth a welcome, lord.</line>
            <line>The Earl of Westmoreland, seven thousand strong,</line>
            <line>Is marching hitherwards; with him Prince John.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>No harm: what more?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VERNON</speaker>
            <line>And further, I have learn'd,</line>
            <line>The king himself in person is set forth,</line>
            <line>Or hitherwards intended speedily,</line>
            <line>With strong and mighty preparation.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>He shall be welcome too. Where is his son,</line>
            <line>The nimble-footed madcap Prince of Wales,</line>
            <line>And his comrades, that daff'd the world aside,</line>
            <line>And bid it pass?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VERNON</speaker>
            <line>All furnish'd, all in arms;</line>
            <line>All plumed like estridges that with the wind</line>
            <line>Baited like eagles having lately bathed;</line>
            <line>Glittering in golden coats, like images;</line>
            <line>As full of spirit as the month of May,</line>
            <line>And gorgeous as the sun at midsummer;</line>
            <line>Wanton as youthful goats, wild as young bulls.</line>
            <line>I saw young Harry, with his beaver on,</line>
            <line>His cuisses on his thighs, gallantly arm'd</line>
            <line>Rise from the ground like feather'd Mercury,</line>
            <line>And vaulted with such ease into his seat,</line>
            <line>As if an angel dropp'd down from the clouds,</line>
            <line>To turn and wind a fiery Pegasus</line>
            <line>And witch the world with noble horsemanship.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>No more, no more: worse than the sun in March,</line>
            <line>This praise doth nourish agues. Let them come:</line>
            <line>They come like sacrifices in their trim,</line>
            <line>And to the fire-eyed maid of smoky war</line>
            <line>All hot and bleeding will we offer them:</line>
            <line>The mailed Mars shall on his altar sit</line>
            <line>Up to the ears in blood. I am on fire</line>
            <line>To hear this rich reprisal is so nigh</line>
            <line>And yet not ours. Come, let me taste my horse,</line>
            <line>Who is to bear me like a thunderbolt</line>
            <line>Against the bosom of the Prince of Wales:</line>
            <line>Harry to Harry shall, hot horse to horse,</line>
            <line>Meet and ne'er part till one drop down a corse.</line>
            <line>O that Glendower were come!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VERNON</speaker>
            <line>There is more news:</line>
            <line>I learn'd in Worcester, as I rode along,</line>
            <line>He cannot draw his power this fourteen days.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EARL OF DOUGLAS</speaker>
            <line>That's the worst tidings that I hear of yet.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WORCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Ay, by my faith, that bears a frosty sound.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>What may the king's whole battle reach unto?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VERNON</speaker>
            <line>To thirty thousand.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>Forty let it be:</line>
            <line>My father and Glendower being both away,</line>
            <line>The powers of us may serve so great a day</line>
            <line>Come, let us take a muster speedily:</line>
            <line>Doomsday is near; die all, die merrily.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EARL OF DOUGLAS</speaker>
            <line>Talk not of dying: I am out of fear</line>
            <line>Of death or death's hand for this one-half year.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  A public road near Coventry.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter FALSTAFF and BARDOLPH</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Bardolph, get thee before to Coventry; fill me a</line>
            <line>bottle of sack: our soldiers shall march through;</line>
            <line>we'll to Sutton Co'fil' tonight.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BARDOLPH</speaker>
            <line>Will you give me money, captain?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Lay out, lay out.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BARDOLPH</speaker>
            <line>This bottle makes an angel.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>An if it do, take it for thy labour; and if it make</line>
            <line>twenty, take them all; I'll answer the coinage. Bid</line>
            <line>my lieutenant Peto meet me at town's end.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BARDOLPH</speaker>
            <line>I will, captain: farewell.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>If I be not ashamed of my soldiers, I am a soused</line>
            <line>gurnet. I have misused the king's press damnably.</line>
            <line>I have got, in exchange of a hundred and fifty</line>
            <line>soldiers, three hundred and odd pounds. I press me</line>
            <line>none but good house-holders, yeoman's sons; inquire</line>
            <line>me out contracted bachelors, such as had been asked</line>
            <line>twice on the banns; such a commodity of warm slaves,</line>
            <line>as had as lieve hear the devil as a drum; such as</line>
            <line>fear the report of a caliver worse than a struck</line>
            <line>fowl or a hurt wild-duck. I pressed me none but such</line>
            <line>toasts-and-butter, with hearts in their bellies no</line>
            <line>bigger than pins' heads, and they have bought out</line>
            <line>their services; and now my whole charge consists of</line>
            <line>ancients, corporals, lieutenants, gentlemen of</line>
            <line>companies, slaves as ragged as Lazarus in the</line>
            <line>painted cloth, where the glutton's dogs licked his</line>
            <line>sores; and such as indeed were never soldiers, but</line>
            <line>discarded unjust serving-men, younger sons to</line>
            <line>younger brothers, revolted tapsters and ostlers</line>
            <line>trade-fallen, the cankers of a calm world and a</line>
            <line>long peace, ten times more dishonourable ragged than</line>
            <line>an old faced ancient: and such have I, to fill up</line>
            <line>the rooms of them that have bought out their</line>
            <line>services, that you would think that I had a hundred</line>
            <line>and fifty tattered prodigals lately come from</line>
            <line>swine-keeping, from eating draff and husks. A mad</line>
            <line>fellow met me on the way and told me I had unloaded</line>
            <line>all the gibbets and pressed the dead bodies. No eye</line>
            <line>hath seen such scarecrows. I'll not march through</line>
            <line>Coventry with them, that's flat: nay, and the</line>
            <line>villains march wide betwixt the legs, as if they had</line>
            <line>gyves on; for indeed I had the most of them out of</line>
            <line>prison. There's but a shirt and a half in all my</line>
            <line>company; and the half shirt is two napkins tacked</line>
            <line>together and thrown over the shoulders like an</line>
            <line>herald's coat without sleeves; and the shirt, to say</line>
            <line>the truth, stolen from my host at Saint Alban's, or</line>
            <line>the red-nose innkeeper of Daventry. But that's all</line>
            <line>one; they'll find linen enough on every hedge.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter the PRINCE and WESTMORELAND</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>How now, blown Jack! how now, quilt!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>What, Hal! how now, mad wag! what a devil dost thou</line>
            <line>in Warwickshire? My good Lord of Westmoreland, I</line>
            <line>cry you mercy: I thought your honour had already been</line>
            <line>at Shrewsbury.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WESTMORELAND</speaker>
            <line>Faith, Sir John,'tis more than time that I were</line>
            <line>there, and you too; but my powers are there already.</line>
            <line>The king, I can tell you, looks for us all: we must</line>
            <line>away all night.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Tut, never fear me: I am as vigilant as a cat to</line>
            <line>steal cream.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>I think, to steal cream indeed, for thy theft hath</line>
            <line>already made thee butter. But tell me, Jack, whose</line>
            <line>fellows are these that come after?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Mine, Hal, mine.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>I did never see such pitiful rascals.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Tut, tut; good enough to toss; food for powder, food</line>
            <line>for powder; they'll fill a pit as well as better:</line>
            <line>tush, man, mortal men, mortal men.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WESTMORELAND</speaker>
            <line>Ay, but, Sir John, methinks they are exceeding poor</line>
            <line>and bare, too beggarly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>'Faith, for their poverty, I know not where they had</line>
            <line>that; and for their bareness, I am sure they never</line>
            <line>learned that of me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PRINCE HENRY</speaker>
            <line>No I'll be sworn; unless you call three fingers on</line>
            <line>the ribs bare. But, sirrah, make haste: Percy is</line>
            <line>already in the field.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>What, is the king encamped?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>WESTMORELAND</speaker>
            <line>He is, Sir John: I fear we shall stay too long.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FALSTAFF</speaker>
            <line>Well,</line>
            <line>To the latter end of a fray and the beginning of a feast</line>
            <line>Fits a dull fighter and a keen guest.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  The rebel camp near Shrewsbury.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter HOTSPUR, WORCESTER, DOUGLAS, and VERNON</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>We'll fight with him to-night.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
            <line>It may not be.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EARL OF DOUGLAS</speaker>
            <line>You give him then the advantage.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VERNON</speaker>
            <line>Not a whit.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>Why say you so? looks he not for supply?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VERNON</speaker>
            <line>So do we.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>His is certain, ours is doubtful.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
            <line>Good cousin, be advised; stir not tonight.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VERNON</speaker>
            <line>Do not, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EARL OF DOUGLAS</speaker>
            <line>You do not counsel well:</line>
            <line>You speak it out of fear and cold heart.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VERNON</speaker>
            <line>Do me no slander, Douglas: by my life,</line>
            <line>And I dare well maintain it with my life,</line>
            <line>If well-respected honour bid me on,</line>
            <line>I hold as little counsel with weak fear</line>
            <line>As you, my lord, or any Scot that this day lives:</line>
            <line>Let it be seen to-morrow in the battle</line>
            <line>Which of us fears.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EARL OF DOUGLAS</speaker>
            <line>Yea, or to-night.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VERNON</speaker>
            <line>Content.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>To-night, say I.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VERNON</speaker>
            <line>Come, come it nay not be. I wonder much,</line>
            <line>Being men of such great leading as you are,</line>
            <line>That you foresee not what impediments</line>
            <line>Drag back our expedition: certain horse</line>
            <line>Of my cousin Vernon's are not yet come up:</line>
            <line>Your uncle Worcester's horse came but today;</line>
            <line>And now their pride and mettle is asleep,</line>
            <line>Their courage with hard labour tame and dull,</line>
            <line>That not a horse is half the half of himself.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>So are the horses of the enemy</line>
            <line>In general, journey-bated and brought low:</line>
            <line>The better part of ours are full of rest.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EARL OF WORCESTER</speaker>
            <line>The number of the king exceedeth ours:</line>
            <line>For God's sake. cousin, stay till all come in.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>The trumpet sounds a parley</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Enter SIR WALTER BLUNT</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR WALTER BLUNT</speaker>
            <line>I come with gracious offers from the king,</line>
            <line>if you vouchsafe me hearing and respect.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>Welcome, Sir Walter Blunt; and would to God</line>
            <line>You were of our determination!</line>
            <line>Some of us love you well; and even those some</line>
            <line>Envy your great deservings and good name,</line>
            <line>Because you are not of our quality,</line>
            <line>But stand against us like an enemy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR WALTER BLUNT</speaker>
            <line>And God defend but still I should stand so,</line>
            <line>So long as out of limit and true rule</line>
            <line>You stand against anointed majesty.</line>
            <line>But to my charge. The king hath sent to know</line>
            <line>The nature of your griefs, and whereupon</line>
            <line>You conjure from the breast of civil peace</line>
            <line>Such bold hostility, teaching his duteous land</line>
            <line>Audacious cruelty. If that the king</line>
            <line>Have any way your good deserts forgot,</line>
            <line>Which he confesseth to be manifold,</line>
            <line>He bids you name your griefs; and with all speed</line>
            <line>You shall have your desires with interest</line>
            <line>And pardon absolute for yourself and these</line>
            <line>Herein misled by your suggestion.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>The king is kind; and well we know the king</line>
            <line>Knows at what time to promise, when to pay.</line>
            <line>My father and my uncle and myself</line>
            <line>Did give him that same royalty he wears;</line>
            <line>And when he was not six and twenty strong,</line>
            <line>Sick in the world's regard, wretched and low,</line>
            <line>A poor unminded outlaw sneaking home,</line>
            <line>My father gave him welcome to the shore;</line>
            <line>And when he heard him swear and vow to God</line>
            <line>He came but to be Duke of Lancaster,</line>
            <line>To sue his livery and beg his peace,</line>
            <line>With tears of innocency and terms of zeal,</line>
            <line>My father, in kind heart and pity moved,</line>
            <line>Swore him assistance and perform'd it too.</line>
            <line>Now when the lords and barons of the realm</line>
            <line>Perceived Northumberland did lean to him,</line>
            <line>The more and less came in with cap and knee;</line>
            <line>Met him in boroughs, cities, villages,</line>
            <line>Attended him on bridges, stood in lanes,</line>
            <line>Laid gifts before him, proffer'd him their oaths,</line>
            <line>Gave him their heirs, as pages follow'd him</line>
            <line>Even at the heels in golden multitudes.</line>
            <line>He presently, as greatness knows itself,</line>
            <line>Steps me a little higher than his vow</line>
            <line>Made to my father, while his blood was poor,</line>
            <line>Upon the naked shore at Ravenspurgh;</line>
            <line>And now, forsooth, takes on him to reform</line>
            <line>Some certain edicts and some strait decrees</line>
            <line>That lie too heavy on the commonwealth,</line>
            <line>Cries out upon abuses, seems to weep</line>
            <line>Over his country's wrongs; and by this face,</line>
            <line>This seeming brow of justice, did he win</line>
            <line>The hearts of all that he did angle for;</line>
            <line>Proceeded further; cut me off the heads</line>
            <line>Of all the favourites that the absent king</line>
            <line>In deputation left behind him here,</line>
            <line>When he was personal in the Irish war.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR WALTER BLUNT</speaker>
            <line>Tut, I came not to hear this.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>Then to the point.</line>
            <line>In short time after, he deposed the king;</line>
            <line>Soon after that, deprived him of his life;</line>
            <line>And in the neck of that, task'd the whole state:</line>
            <line>To make that worse, suffer'd his kinsman March,</line>
            <line>Who is, if every owner were well placed,</line>
            <line>Indeed his king, to be engaged in Wales,</line>
            <line>There without ransom to lie forfeited;</line>
            <line>Disgraced me in my happy victories,</line>
            <line>Sought to entrap me by intelligence;</line>
            <line>Rated mine uncle from the council-board;</line>
            <line>In rage dismiss'd my father from the court;</line>
            <line>Broke oath on oath, committed wrong on wrong,</line>
            <line>And in conclusion drove us to seek out</line>
            <line>This head of safety; and withal to pry</line>
            <line>Into his title, the which we find</line>
            <line>Too indirect for long continuance.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR WALTER BLUNT</speaker>
            <line>Shall I return this answer to the king?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>Not so, Sir Walter: we'll withdraw awhile.</line>
            <line>Go to the king; and let there be impawn'd</line>
            <line>Some surety for a safe return again,</line>
            <line>And in the morning early shall my uncle</line>
            <line>Bring him our purposes: and so farewell.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR WALTER BLUNT</speaker>
            <line>I would you would accept of grace and love.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HOTSPUR</speaker>
            <line>And may be so we shall.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR WALTER BLUNT</speaker>
            <line>Pray God you do.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-4">
      <title>SCENE IV.  York. The ARCHBISHOP'S palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter the ARCHBISHOP OF YORK and SIR MICHAEL</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARCHBISHOP OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Hie, good Sir Michael; bear this sealed brief</line>
            <line>With winged haste to the lord marshal;</line>
            <line>This to my cousin Scroop, and all the rest</line>
            <line>To whom they are directed. If you knew</line>
            <line>How much they do to import, you would make haste.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR MICHAEL</speaker>
            <line>My good lord,</line>
            <line>I guess their tenor.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARCHBISHOP OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>Like enough you do.</line>
            <line>To-morrow, good Sir Michael, is a day</line>
            <line>Wherein the fortune of ten thousand men</line>
            <line>Must bide the touch; for, sir, at Shrewsbury,</line>
            <line>As I am truly given to understand,</line>
            <line>The king with mighty and quick-raised power</line>
            <line>Meets with Lord Harry: and, I fear, Sir Michael,</line>
            <line>What with the sickness of Northumberland,</line>
            <line>Whose power was in the first proportion,</line>
            <line>And what with Owen Glendower's absence thence,</line>
            <line>Who with them was a rated sinew too</line>
            <line>And comes not in, o'er-ruled by prophecies,</line>
            <line>I fear the power of Percy is too weak</line>
            <line>To wage an instant trial with the king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR MICHAEL</speaker>
            <line>Why, my good lord, you need not fear;</line>
            <line>There is Douglas and Lord Mortimer.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARCHBISHOP OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>No, Mortimer is not there.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR MICHAEL</speaker>
            <line>But there is Mordake, Vernon, Lord Harry Percy,</line>
            <line>And there is my Lord of Worcester and a head</line>
            <line>Of gallant warriors, noble gentlemen.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARCHBISHOP OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>And so there is: but yet the king hath drawn</line>
            <line>The special head of all the land together:</line>
            <line>The Prince of Wales, Lord John of Lancaster,</line>
            <line>The noble Westmoreland and warlike Blunt;</line>
            <line>And moe corrivals and dear men</line>
            <line>Of estimation and command in arms.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR MICHAEL</speaker>
            <line>Doubt not, my lord, they shall be well opposed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARCHBISHOP OF YORK</speaker>
            <line>I hope no less, yet needful 'tis to fear;</line>
            <line>And, to prevent the worst, Sir Michael, speed:</line>
            <line>For if Lord Percy thrive not, ere the king</line>
            <line>Dismiss his power, he means to visit us,</line>
            <line>For he hath heard of our confederacy,</line>
            <line>And 'tis but wisdom to make strong against him:</line>
            <line>Therefore make haste. I must go write again</line>
            <line>To other friends; and so farewell, Sir Michael.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>