<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE learningContent
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Learning Content//EN" "learningContent.dtd">
<learningContent id="SEC003_002">
   <title>3.2 Some general properties of galaxies</title>
   <learningContentbody>
      <section>
          
          <p>Firstly, we note that galaxies tend to occur in clusters rather than singly.
            The mutual gravitational attraction of galaxies naturally tends to hold them on paths
            that remain close to each other. Typically a cluster contains tens or hundreds of
            galaxies. There are, however, large clusters with thousands of galaxies, and there are
            some solitary galaxies. Our own Galaxy is a member of a smallish cluster of about 36
            galaxies called the Local Group (see <xref href="#FIG001_005">Figure 7</xref>). A typical cluster of moderate size is shown
            in <xref href="#FIG001_006">Figure 8</xref>.</p>
          <fig>
            <title>
              <b>Figure 7</b>: Our cluster of galaxies, called the Local Group. M31, the Andromeda
              galaxy, can be seen with binoculars. The Large Magellanic Cloud is one of our nearest
              neighbours, and is visible to the naked eye from the Southern Hemisphere</title>
            <image href="../../media/S357_1_005i.jpg"/>
            <p outputclass="SourceReference">Source: from <i>Le Grand Atlas de l’Astronomie</i>, Encyclopaedia
              Universalis editeur <data name="ItemRights">
                  <data name="OwnerRef"/>
                  <data name="ItemRef"/>
                  <data name="ItemAcknowledgement">from <i>Le Grand Atlas de l’Astronomie</i>,
                  Encyclopaedia Universalis editeur</data>
              </data>
            </p>
            <p/>
         </fig>
          <fig>
            <title>
              <b>Figure 8</b>: A cluster of galaxies whose position in the sky is behind the
              constellation of stars in our Galaxy which we call Hercules. This cluster is not
              visible to the naked eye – not because it is too small but because it is too
              faint</title>
            <image href="../../media/S357_1_006i.jpg"/>
            <p outputclass="SourceReference">Source: Hale Observatories <data name="ItemRights">
                  <data name="OwnerRef"/>
                  <data name="ItemRef"/>
                  <data name="ItemAcknowledgement">Hale Observatories</data>
              </data>
            </p>
            <p/>
         </fig>
          <p>How are the galaxy clusters distributed? Are they close enough to affect each
            other? If they are, then the motion of a given cluster would depend mostly on the
            distortion of spacetime caused by its nearest neighbours. Because the distances between
            clusters vary, this would correspond to a large spread in relative speeds. At the other
            extreme, if the clusters of galaxies were very far apart, then the attraction of
            neighbouring clusters would be negligible, and the motion would be dominated by the
            overall spacetime curvature due to the matter of the <i>whole</i> Universe – a
            much simpler situation.</p>
          <p>In fact, galaxy clusters are loosely
            associated in superclusters. However, they are far enough apart for one to regard
            clusters as essentially independent (see <xref href="#FIG001_007">Figure 9</xref>). The fact that clusters are, in effect,
            independent of one another is of central importance to cosmology. It means that a
            cluster of galaxies can be taken as the basic ‘particle’ of cosmological
            dynamics, and the motion of individual galaxies within a cluster can be ignored on the
            grand scale of cosmology. Thus, we conclude:</p>
          <fig outputclass="Box">
            <p>Galaxy clusters are the basic test particles of cosmology, their motion
              following geodesic paths through spacetime.</p>
          </fig>
          <fig>
            <title>
              <b>Figure 9</b>: A very schematic view of three clusters, showing typical diameters of
              galaxies (single dots) and clusters (groups of dots), and typical distances between
              clusters</title>
            <image href="../../media/S357_1_007i.jpg"/>
            <p outputclass="SourceReference">Source: 
              <data name="ItemRights">
                  <data name="OwnerRef"/>
                  <data name="ItemRef"/>
                  <data name="ItemAcknowledgement"/>
              </data>
            </p>
            <p/>
         </fig>
          <p>In other words, a galaxy cluster plays a similar role on the grand scale to
            that of a planet (e.g. Mercury) mapping out the local region of spacetime in the Solar
            System, or Newton's falling apple doing the same thing closer to the Earth's
            surface.</p>
          <p>The next important property of galaxies is that there is a statistical
            predictability about their masses and luminosities. <xref href="#FIG001_008">Figure 10</xref> shows the proportion of galaxies having a
            given luminosity. It varies over quite a wide range, the distribution falling off
            steeply on the high-luminosity side. (Note that the luminosity is expressed in terms of
            (absolute) ‘magnitudes’, this being a parameter such that the <i>smaller
              or more negative</i> the value of the magnitude, the more luminous the object. This
            rather odd choice arises for historical reasons.) There are large numbers of the least
            luminous galaxies (shown by the rising curve on the left-hand side), but in practice
            these tend to be invisible in the more distant clusters which are of greater interest to
            cosmologists. No doubt it would have been easier for cosmology if galaxies had been more
            similar. However, because galaxies occur in clusters, one can at least use statistical
            methods. For instance, the distribution of luminosities is more or less the same for all
            clusters, resulting in the average luminosity of galaxies in a cluster being fairly
            standard even though the individual galaxies vary greatly. This statement assumes, of
            course, that we are dealing with galaxy clusters of the same age. As we have already
            pointed out, this might not be the case when observing galaxies at a great distance, and
            hence as they were some time in the distant past.</p>
          <fig>
            <title>
              <b>Figure 10</b>: Number of galaxies per magnitude class per cubic megaparsec, as a
              function of absolute magnitude. Different symbols represent the results of different
              observers</title>
            <image href="../../media/S357_1_008i.jpg"/>
            <p outputclass="SourceReference">Source: based on Erik Holmberg in E.M. and G.R. Burbidge (1975) <i>Galaxies and
                the Universe</i>, University of Chicago Press <data name="ItemRights">
                  <data name="OwnerRef"/>
                  <data name="ItemRef"/>
                  <data name="ItemAcknowledgement">based on Erik Holmberg in E.M. and G.R. Burbidge (1975)
                    <i>Galaxies and the Universe</i>, University of Chicago
                  Press</data>
              </data>
            </p>
            <p/>
         </fig>
        </section>
   </learningContentbody>
</learningContent>