<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE learningContent
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Learning Content//EN" "learningContent.dtd">
<learningContent id="SEC003_001">
   <title>3.1 First steps towards a distance scale</title>
   <learningContentbody>
      <section>
          
          <p>As you will see from <xref href="#TBL001">Table 2</xref>, when it comes to astronomy and cosmology, one is
            called on to deal with a wide range of distances. (Note that a light-year (ly) is the
            distance light travels in one year, i.e. 9.46 × 10<sup>15</sup> m. The
            distances are also quoted in a very commonly used astronomical unit of distance: the
            megaparsec, Mpc, where a parsec (pc) is 3.26 ly or
            3.09 × 10<sup>16</sup>m.)</p>
          <table>
            <title>Table 2</title>
            <tgroup cols="2">
               <tbody>
                  <row>
                     <entry outputclass="th">
                        <b/>
                     </entry>
                     <entry outputclass="th">
                        <b>Distance</b>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry>Earth–Moon</entry>
                     <entry>1.28 light-seconds</entry>
                     <entry>1.25 × 10<sup>−14</sup> Mpc</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry>Earth–Sun</entry>
                     <entry>8.3 light-minutes</entry>
                     <entry>4.8 × 10<sup>−12</sup> Mpc</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry>Nearest star</entry>
                     <entry>≈ 4 ly</entry>
                     <entry>1.23 × 10<sup>−6</sup> Mpc</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry>Diameter of our Galaxy</entry>
                     <entry>≈ 10<sup>5</sup> ly</entry>
                     <entry>3 × 10<sup>−2</sup> Mpc</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry>Distance to nearest galaxy</entry>
                     <entry>≈ 2 × 10<sup>6</sup> ly</entry>
                     <entry>≈ 1 Mpc</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry>Farthest galaxy seen</entry>
                     <entry>≈ 4 × 10<sup>9</sup> ly</entry>
                     <entry>≈ 1.2 × 10<sup>3</sup> Mpc</entry>
                  </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
         </table>
         <p outputclass="SourceReference">Source: </p>
          
          
          <p>To measure the distance of a far-off galaxy clearly requires a series of steps.
            The first of these, the Earth–Sun distance, is based on our knowledge of the
            orbital period of the Earth about the Sun, and that of some other planet. One can then
            readily obtain an estimate of their <i>relative</i> distances from the Sun by using
            Kepler's third law. To convert this to an <i>absolute</i> measurement, one needs a
            determination of the actual distance between the Earth and the planet at some time. In
            practice, this fix is gained by measuring the distances to Mercury, Venus and Mars,
            using radar. These then allow one to compute the Earth–Sun distance. It is
            currently estimated, with obvious high precision, to be 149 597 870.66 km.</p>
          <p>Knowing this, the diameter of the Earth's orbit can now be used as a baseline
            for measuring the distance to nearby stars, using the surveyor's triangulation method.
            One makes angular measurements on a star from opposite ends of an Earth-orbital
            diameter, i.e. at intervals of 6 months. At the time of writing (2004), data from the
            Hipparcos satellite surpass in precision and scope all previous measurements of nearby
            stellar distances.</p>
          <p>But no matter how good this satellite-gathered data, there soon comes a stage
            where the angles become too small to measure accurately using the triangulation method.
            Some other method must be employed to extend the distance scale to the more distant
            stars.</p>
          <p>If a source has a known total light output, i.e. known <i>luminosity</i>, then
            it can be used as a standard source. The distance of the source can be found from the
              <i>received</i> light power. The further away the star is, the fainter it appears. The
            relationship follows an inverse square law (allowing for various corrections, such as
            that due to the absorption of light by interstellar dust). The light power received per
            unit area of detector is called the <i>flux density</i>. It follows, summing over the
            area of a sphere centred on the star and of radius, <i>r</i>, equal to the distance to
            the star, that in the absence of absorption:</p>
          <fig outputclass="Equation">
            <image href="../../media/S357_1_e002i.gif"/>
            <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
         </fig>
          <p>Unfortunately stars differ widely in their luminosities, so if we simply look
            up at the sky and pick out a faint star, it may be either an intrinsically dim star, or
            a particularly distant star – or partly dim and distant.</p>
          <p>This ambiguity can be partly overcome by recognising that, while it is
            impossible to directly measure the luminosity of a particular source, one <i>can</i>
            estimate the temperature of the star. This is done from measurements on the overall
            shape of its emitted spectrum – stars emitting predominantly in the red part of
            the spectrum being cooler than those that emit more in the blue region. Thus the
            spectrum, and hence temperature, can be determined with a fair degree of confidence.
            Now, it turns out that when observations are made on a compact cluster of stars (the
            cluster being small enough for all its stars to be considered equidistant from us), a
            plot of flux density versus temperature generally gives the <i>same</i> distribution no
            matter which cluster is chosen – apart from an overall constant factor depending
            on the distance to the cluster. Thus, the most likely luminosity of a star is related to
            its temperature. But in order to use the temperatures of stars to obtain luminosities,
            and hence distances, from Equation 2, we need to progress beyond a plot of <i>flux
              density</i> versus temperature to one of luminosity versus temperature.</p>
          <p>In order to achieve this, studies have been made of a group of about 100 stars
            called the ‘Hyades star cluster’. This group is close enough to us for its
            distance to be determined by the Hipparcos satellite. Knowing this distance and the flux
            density of the stars, the luminosities could be established, and the plot of luminosity
            versus temperature calibrated. By studying the flux densities and colours of stars more
            distant than the Hyades star cluster, we can use this calibrated plot to infer their
            distances from us.</p>
          <p>This method applies to stars confined to our own Galaxy. As for stars in other
            galaxies, most of these cannot be distinguished separately. So, the next step is to try
            to find a particularly bright type of star – one that <i>can</i> be recognised
            not only in our Galaxy but also in neighbouring galaxies. If this were possible, it
            would give us a method of extending the distance scale out to other galaxies.
            Fortunately there <i>does</i> exist a type of star that can be recognised at least in
            neighbouring galaxies – a star known as a
            
            <i>Cepheid variable</i>. The important characteristic of a Cepheid is that its light
            output varies in a regular fashion, with a period which is directly related to its mean
            luminosity (see <xref href="#FIG001_004">Figure 6</xref>a). The variation is due to cyclical changes in
            diameter. The relationship between mean luminosity and period can be calibrated by
            studying Cepheids that are sufficiently close for their distances to have been measured
            by methods mentioned earlier. So whenever such stars can be distinguished from the other
            types of variable star in the more distant galaxies, their luminosities can be deduced
            (see <xref href="#FIG001_004">Figure 6</xref>b). Comparing luminosity with the measured flux
            density then enables the distance of the star to be calculated. Cepheids have been used
            extensively to measure the distances to nearby galaxies -those belonging to a cluster of
            galaxies known as the Local Group (to be described later). Following the advent of the
            Hubble Space Telescope with its superior resolution of individual stars, it became
            possible in 1996 to extend Cepheid-based measurements as far as a galaxy known as M100,
            in the Virgo cluster, yielding a distance of 5.6 × 10<sup>7</sup>
            ly.</p>
          <fig>
            <title>
              <b>Figure 6</b>: (a) An 18-day section of the light curve of the typical Cepheid
              variable, Delta Cephei, which has a 5.37-day oscillation.
              (b)
              The observed relationship between the period and luminosity (in watts) of Cepheid
              variables (1 W = 1 J s<sup>−1</sup>). Notice that both
              scales are logarithmic, so the straight line implies that period
              ∝
                (luminosity)<sup>
                  <i>m</i>
               </sup>, where 1/<i>m</i> is the slope of the
              line.</title>
            <image href="../../media/S357_1_004i.jpg"/>
            <p outputclass="SourceReference">Source: based on H. Arp (1960) in <i>Astronomical J.</i>, 65, 426 <data name="ItemRights">
                  <data name="OwnerRef"/>
                  <data name="ItemRef"/>
                  <data name="ItemAcknowledgement">based on H. Arp (1960) in <i>Astronomical J.</i>, 65,
                  426</data>
              </data>
            </p>
            <p/>
         </fig>
          
          <p>Another type of star that can be recognised in other galaxies is a <i>Type Ia
              supernova</i>. What happens is this: when a medium-sized star, such as the Sun,
            approaches the end of its active life, it shrinks down to a small star called a
            ‘white dwarf’. If the white dwarf happens to belong to a binary system of
            two stars, it can, from time to time, capture material from the atmosphere of its
            companion, so increasing its own mass. But this is a process that cannot continue
            indefinitely. The maximum mass for a white dwarf is 1.4 solar masses; anything above
            that limit and its inner forces cannot resist the inward pull of gravity, and the star
            has to collapse down to the next stable form (called a ‘neutron star’).
            Thus, the white dwarf in the binary system can capture material only up to this limiting
            mass. Once it exceeds this limit, the collapse occurs with the excess energy emitted as
            an explosion – the Type Ia supernova. Because white dwarfs are always of the same
            limiting mass when this happens, the explosions are similar, yielding essentially the
            same spectrum and variation of light intensity over time. (It is these characteristics
            that allow the Type Ia supernovae to be distinguished from other types.) Why they are
            important in the present context is that, to within ±30%, they have the same
            luminosity. Taking into account that the variation in luminosity with time does show a
            difference in characteristic decay times, and these are correlated to somewhat different
            values of peak luminosity, allowance can be made for this, and the uncertainty spread in
            peak luminosity reduced to ±20%. This in turn leads to relative distances
            measurable to ±10%.</p>
          <p>Type Ia supernovae provide us with standard lamps (or standard
              <i>explosions!</i>), that, at their peak, are 100 000 times brighter than a Cepheid,
            and are visible hundreds of times further away. Having established their luminosity by
            measuring the few that occur in galaxies for which the distance is already known from
            measurements on Cepheids, they can be used to extend the distance scale to very great
            distances.</p>
          <p>This however still does not go far enough. Since normal stars cannot be
            resolved in the farther galaxies, the additional methods of estimating distance will
            have to be based on the properties of galaxies <i>as a whole</i>. We therefore interrupt
            the distance story to describe some properties of whole galaxies, showing first why they
            are important to cosmology, and then how they have led to new ways of measuring
            distance.</p>
          
          <sectiondiv outputclass="SAQ">
            <p outputclass="Heading">
               <b>Question 4</b>
            </p>
            <sectiondiv outputclass="saq.question">
              <p>Suppose an astronomer using a telescope of 2 m diameter has a detector
                whose limit of sensitivity is 3.2 ×10<sup>−17</sup> W. Use <xref href="#FIG001_004">Figure 6</xref> to deduce, for this instrument, the period
                of the faintest Cepheid variable that can be observed at a distance of
                  2 × 10<sup>6</sup> ly [light years].</p>
              <p>(<i>Remember:</i> The value of a light-year in SI units is given on the <xref href="http://openlearn.open.ac.uk/file.php/3639/S357Datasheets.pdf"
                        scope="external"
                        format="html">data sheet</xref>)</p>
            </sectiondiv>
            <sectiondiv outputclass="saq.answer">
              <p>At 2 × 10<sup>6</sup> ly, the fraction of light intercepted
                is:</p>
              <p>
                  <ph outputclass="InlineEquation">
                     <image href="../../media/S357_1_ie002i.gif"/>
                     <ph outputclass="inlineequation-description"/>
                  </ph>
               </p>
              <p>The energy received from the faintest star is
                  3.2 × 10<sup>−17</sup> W.</p>
              <p>Therefore the output of the star must be</p>
              <fig outputclass="Equation">
                  <image href="../../media/S357_1_ue030i.gif"/>
                  <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
               </fig>
              <p>From <xref href="#FIG001_004">Figure 6</xref>(b), the corresponding period of the Cepheid
                variable is about 3 days.</p>
            </sectiondiv>
          </sectiondiv>
          
        </section>
   </learningContentbody>
</learningContent>