<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE learningContent
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Learning Content//EN" "learningContent.dtd">
<learningContent id="SEC003_003">
   <title>3.3 Extending the distance scale</title>
   <learningContentbody>
      <section>
          
          <p>Having reviewed some of the properties of galaxies, we are now in a position to
            return to the question of how we are to develop further our methods of measuring
            distance.</p>
          <p>The various steps taken in determining larger distances from known smaller ones
            are often called ‘rungs in the distance ladder’. The process of
            constructing a rung has been:</p>
          <ol>
            <li>
              <p>Find a measurable quantity associated with a class of objects.</p>
            </li>
            <li>
              <p>Observe how the measurable quantity depends on distance for objects close
                enough to have had their distances measured by the method of a previous
                rung.</p>
            </li>
            <li>
              <p>Assume the same relationship holds for more distant objects of the same
                class, and hence calculate their distances.</p>
            </li>
            <li>
              <p>Return to step 1, with a new measurable quantity.</p>
            </li>
          </ol>
          <p>The classes of objects (and distance indicators) for the first four rungs of
            the distance ladder were:</p>
          <table>
            <title/>
            <tgroup cols="2">
               <tbody>
                  <row>
                     <entry>Sun</entry>
                     <entry>(by radar ranging)</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry>Nearby stars in our Galaxy</entry>
                     <entry>(by triangulation)</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry>Our Galaxy and nearby galaxies</entry>
                     <entry>(using Cepheid variables)</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry>Nearby and somewhat further off galaxies</entry>
                     <entry> (using Type Ia supernovae)</entry>
                  </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
         </table>
         <p outputclass="SourceReference">Source: </p>
          <p>These distance indicators all depended on recognising a particular type of
              <i>star</i>. But, as was mentioned in <xref href="#SEC003_001">Section 3.1</xref>, individual stars can be resolved only in
            galaxies that are not too distant. For most galaxies, a method is needed which depends
            on recognising, or deducing, the luminosity of the galaxy as a whole. Although, as
            already noted, individual galaxies vary considerably in their luminosity, they occur in
            clusters. A simple rule which seems to work in practice is to assume that the
            third-brightest galaxy in all clusters has the same luminosity (a standard
              10<sup>37</sup> W lamp).</p>
          
          <p>An alternative method is to separate galaxies into different types, with the
            assumption, or at least the hope, that the types have characteristic luminosities. There
            are certainly generic differences between spiral galaxies (<xref href="#FIG001_009">Figure 11</xref>) and elliptical galaxies (<xref href="#FIG001_010">Figure 12</xref>). But it is also well established that there
            is a useful correlation between the luminosities of spiral galaxies and their rotation
            speeds, which can be determined from (radio) observations of Doppler
            broadening.</p>
          
          <fig>
            <title>
              <b>Figure 11</b>: Spiral galaxy M81 (NGC 3031), taken with the 200-inch telescope at
              the Palomar Observatory in California. This galaxy, like our own, has tightly wound
              arms and a prominent bulge (known as a nuclear bulge)</title>
            <image href="../../media/S357_1_009i.jpg"/>
            <p outputclass="SourceReference">Source: Hale Observatories <data name="ItemRights">
                  <data name="OwnerRef"/>
                  <data name="ItemRef"/>
                  <data name="ItemAcknowledgement">Hale Observatories</data>
              </data>
            </p>
            <p/>
         </fig>
          <fig>
            <title>
              <b>Figure 12</b>: M59 (NGC 4261), an elliptical galaxy about 19 Mly (i.e.
                1.9 × 10<sup>7</sup> ly) away. Like all elliptical galaxies, M59 has
              no spiral arms</title>
            <image href="../../media/S357_1_010i.jpg"/>
            <p outputclass="SourceReference">Source: NASA/IPAC Extragalactic Database (NED), Jet Propulsion Laboratory,
              California Institute of Technology <data name="ItemRights">
                  <data name="OwnerRef"/>
                  <data name="ItemRef"/>
                  <data name="ItemAcknowledgement">NASA/IPAC Extragalactic Database (NED), Jet Propulsion
                  Laboratory, California Institute of Technology</data>
              </data>
            </p>
            <p/>
         </fig>
          <p>Another method exploits the fact that some types of <i>radio galaxy</i>
            (so-called because they are strong emitters at radio frequencies) are fairly uniform in
              <i>size</i>, and radio interferometers can resolve very small angular separations
            – a thousand times smaller than those resolved by optical telescopes. The
            apparent size leads to an estimate of the distance of the galaxy. Because some radio
            galaxies are also visible at optical wavelengths, the optical and radio distance scales
            can be intercalibrated.</p>
          
          <p>Yet another method should also be mentioned. It involves the behaviour of a
            single star in a galaxy, though one too distant to be resolved. We have already
            mentioned Type Ia supernovae. These are events that occur when a white dwarf (which
            itself originally resulted from the last stages in the active life of a medium-sized
            star) captures material from a companion star, and undergoes collapse to a neutron star.
            If instead of a medium-sized star one begins with a very massive star, then at the end
            of its active life it catastrophically collapses <i>directly</i> to a neutron star or
            black hole. This leads to a gigantic explosion even more energetic than a Type Ia
            supernova; it is called a <i>Type II supernova</i>. These explosions are bright enough
            to be visible at large distances – in some cases briefly shining more brightly
            than all the other stars of the galaxy put together. Unfortunately they are rather rare,
            occurring only once every hundred years or so in a typical galaxy. A Type II supernova
            explosion causes a spherical shell of hot gas to expand out of the star at high speed
            – thousands of kilometres per second. The spectral lines in the observed light
            from this shell (mostly from hydrogen and therefore easily identified) are
              <i>blueshifted</i> by its velocity towards us. Knowing this velocity from the amount
            of blueshift, the increase in size of the shell, month by month, can be calculated. Thus
            the shell is a source of known size, even though this cannot be resolved from an
            observed angular width. The temperature can be found from the overall shape of the
            continuous spectrum between the spectral lines. Knowing both the size and temperature of
            the shell, its total light output (that is, its luminosity) can be found. From this and
            the observed flux this and the observed flux density, the distance can be calculated
            using the inverse square law.</p>
          <p>Remember, luminosity = 4<ph outputclass="InlineEquation">
               <image href="../../media/pi.gif"/>
               <ph outputclass="inlineequation-description"/>
            </ph>
            <i>r</i>
            <sup>2</sup> × flux
            density, where <i>r</i> is the distance.</p>
          <fig>
            <title>
              <b>Figure 13</b>: NGC 5457, a spiral galaxy in our Local Group, having looser arms and
              a far less noticeable nuclear bulge than the galaxy shown in Figure 11</title>
            <image href="../../media/S357_1_011i.jpg"/>
            <p outputclass="SourceReference">Source: Hale Observatories <data name="ItemRights">
                  <data name="OwnerRef"/>
                  <data name="ItemRef"/>
                  <data name="ItemAcknowledgement">Hale Observatories</data>
              </data>
            </p>
            <p/>
         </fig>
          <sectiondiv outputclass="SAQ">
            <p outputclass="Heading">
               <b>Question 5</b>
            </p>
            <sectiondiv outputclass="saq.question">
              
              <p>Comment on the truth or otherwise of the following statements:</p>
              <p>(i) Averaging statistically over the luminosities of its constituent
                galaxies, each cluster of galaxies can be assumed to have the same overall
                luminosity.</p>
              <p>(ii) The distance-measuring method involving Type II supernovae relies on
                the fact that the shell of material thrown out by the explosion greatly exceeds the
                parent star in size, to the extent that it can be optically resolved.</p>
            </sectiondiv>
            <sectiondiv outputclass="saq.answer">
              <p>Both statements are incorrect.</p>
              <p>
                  <b>(i)</b> The overall luminosity of a cluster cannot be used as a standard
                lamp because, as stated in <xref href="#SEC003_002">Section 3.2</xref>, clusters can vary enormously in size
                from thousands of galaxies to a single galaxy. All one can say is that the
                luminosity of a <i>typical</i> galaxy in that cluster (averaged over a number of the
                galaxies it contains) is the same for each cluster.</p>
              <p>
                  <b>(ii)</b> The shell thrown out from the supernova cannot be resolved
                optically. Instead, the radius of the fireball at a given moment is
                  <i>calculated</i> from the estimated speed of the ejected material and the time
                that has elapsed since the explosion. The colour (temperature) determines the light
                output per unit area. Hence, knowing the surface area from the radius, one arrives
                at an estimate of the luminosity of the supernova at the given time after the
                explosion. This luminosity is then compared to the measured flux density to obtain
                the distance to the star.</p>
            </sectiondiv>
          </sectiondiv>
        </section>
   </learningContentbody>
</learningContent>