<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:shakespear:dtd:act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-5">
   <title>ACT V</title>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  Marseilles. A street.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter HELENA, Widow, and DIANA, with two
Attendants</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>But this exceeding posting day and night</line>
            <line>Must wear your spirits low; we cannot help it:</line>
            <line>But since you have made the days and nights as one,</line>
            <line>To wear your gentle limbs in my affairs,</line>
            <line>Be bold you do so grow in my requital</line>
            <line>As nothing can unroot you. In happy time;</line>
            <stagedir>Enter a Gentleman</stagedir>
            <line>This man may help me to his majesty's ear,</line>
            <line>If he would spend his power. God save you, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Gentleman</speaker>
            <line>And you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>Sir, I have seen you in the court of France.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Gentleman</speaker>
            <line>I have been sometimes there.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>I do presume, sir, that you are not fallen</line>
            <line>From the report that goes upon your goodness;</line>
            <line>An therefore, goaded with most sharp occasions,</line>
            <line>Which lay nice manners by, I put you to</line>
            <line>The use of your own virtues, for the which</line>
            <line>I shall continue thankful.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Gentleman</speaker>
            <line>What's your will?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>That it will please you</line>
            <line>To give this poor petition to the king,</line>
            <line>And aid me with that store of power you have</line>
            <line>To come into his presence.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Gentleman</speaker>
            <line>The king's not here.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>Not here, sir!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Gentleman</speaker>
            <line>Not, indeed:</line>
            <line>He hence removed last night and with more haste</line>
            <line>Than is his use.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Widow</speaker>
            <line>Lord, how we lose our pains!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>All's well that ends well yet,</line>
            <line>Though time seem so adverse and means unfit.</line>
            <line>I do beseech you, whither is he gone?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Gentleman</speaker>
            <line>Marry, as I take it, to Rousillon;</line>
            <line>Whither I am going.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>I do beseech you, sir,</line>
            <line>Since you are like to see the king before me,</line>
            <line>Commend the paper to his gracious hand,</line>
            <line>Which I presume shall render you no blame</line>
            <line>But rather make you thank your pains for it.</line>
            <line>I will come after you with what good speed</line>
            <line>Our means will make us means.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Gentleman</speaker>
            <line>This I'll do for you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>And you shall find yourself to be well thank'd,</line>
            <line>Whate'er falls more. We must to horse again.</line>
            <line>Go, go, provide.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  Rousillon. Before the COUNT's palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter Clown, and PAROLLES, following</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Good Monsieur Lavache, give my Lord Lafeu this</line>
            <line>letter: I have ere now, sir, been better known to</line>
            <line>you, when I have held familiarity with fresher</line>
            <line>clothes; but I am now, sir, muddied in fortune's</line>
            <line>mood, and smell somewhat strong of her strong</line>
            <line>displeasure.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Truly, fortune's displeasure is but sluttish, if it</line>
            <line>smell so strongly as thou speakest of: I will</line>
            <line>henceforth eat no fish of fortune's buttering.</line>
            <line>Prithee, allow the wind.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Nay, you need not to stop your nose, sir; I spake</line>
            <line>but by a metaphor.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Indeed, sir, if your metaphor stink, I will stop my</line>
            <line>nose; or against any man's metaphor. Prithee, get</line>
            <line>thee further.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Pray you, sir, deliver me this paper.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Foh! prithee, stand away: a paper from fortune's</line>
            <line>close-stool to give to a nobleman! Look, here he</line>
            <line>comes himself.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter LAFEU</stagedir>
            <line>Here is a purr of fortune's, sir, or of fortune's</line>
            <line>cat,--but not a musk-cat,--that has fallen into the</line>
            <line>unclean fishpond of her displeasure, and, as he</line>
            <line>says, is muddied withal: pray you, sir, use the</line>
            <line>carp as you may; for he looks like a poor, decayed,</line>
            <line>ingenious, foolish, rascally knave. I do pity his</line>
            <line>distress in my similes of comfort and leave him to</line>
            <line>your lordship.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>My lord, I am a man whom fortune hath cruelly</line>
            <line>scratched.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>And what would you have me to do? 'Tis too late to</line>
            <line>pare her nails now. Wherein have you played the</line>
            <line>knave with fortune, that she should scratch you, who</line>
            <line>of herself is a good lady and would not have knaves</line>
            <line>thrive long under her? There's a quart d'ecu for</line>
            <line>you: let the justices make you and fortune friends:</line>
            <line>I am for other business.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>I beseech your honour to hear me one single word.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>You beg a single penny more: come, you shall ha't;</line>
            <line>save your word.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>My name, my good lord, is Parolles.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>You beg more than 'word,' then. Cox my passion!</line>
            <line>give me your hand. How does your drum?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>O my good lord, you were the first that found me!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>Was I, in sooth? and I was the first that lost thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>It lies in you, my lord, to bring me in some grace,</line>
            <line>for you did bring me out.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>Out upon thee, knave! dost thou put upon me at once</line>
            <line>both the office of God and the devil? One brings</line>
            <line>thee in grace and the other brings thee out.</line>
            <stagedir>Trumpets sound</stagedir>
            <line>The king's coming; I know by his trumpets. Sirrah,</line>
            <line>inquire further after me; I had talk of you last</line>
            <line>night: though you are a fool and a knave, you shall</line>
            <line>eat; go to, follow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>I praise God for you.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-5-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  Rousillon. The COUNT's palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Flourish. Enter KING, COUNTESS, LAFEU, the two
French Lords, with Attendants</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>We lost a jewel of her; and our esteem</line>
            <line>Was made much poorer by it: but your son,</line>
            <line>As mad in folly, lack'd the sense to know</line>
            <line>Her estimation home.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>'Tis past, my liege;</line>
            <line>And I beseech your majesty to make it</line>
            <line>Natural rebellion, done i' the blaze of youth;</line>
            <line>When oil and fire, too strong for reason's force,</line>
            <line>O'erbears it and burns on.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>My honour'd lady,</line>
            <line>I have forgiven and forgotten all;</line>
            <line>Though my revenges were high bent upon him,</line>
            <line>And watch'd the time to shoot.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>This I must say,</line>
            <line>But first I beg my pardon, the young lord</line>
            <line>Did to his majesty, his mother and his lady</line>
            <line>Offence of mighty note; but to himself</line>
            <line>The greatest wrong of all. He lost a wife</line>
            <line>Whose beauty did astonish the survey</line>
            <line>Of richest eyes, whose words all ears took captive,</line>
            <line>Whose dear perfection hearts that scorn'd to serve</line>
            <line>Humbly call'd mistress.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>Praising what is lost</line>
            <line>Makes the remembrance dear. Well, call him hither;</line>
            <line>We are reconciled, and the first view shall kill</line>
            <line>All repetition: let him not ask our pardon;</line>
            <line>The nature of his great offence is dead,</line>
            <line>And deeper than oblivion we do bury</line>
            <line>The incensing relics of it: let him approach,</line>
            <line>A stranger, no offender; and inform him</line>
            <line>So 'tis our will he should.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Gentleman</speaker>
            <line>I shall, my liege.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>What says he to your daughter? have you spoke?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>All that he is hath reference to your highness.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>Then shall we have a match. I have letters sent me</line>
            <line>That set him high in fame.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter BERTRAM</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>He looks well on't.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>I am not a day of season,</line>
            <line>For thou mayst see a sunshine and a hail</line>
            <line>In me at once: but to the brightest beams</line>
            <line>Distracted clouds give way; so stand thou forth;</line>
            <line>The time is fair again.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>My high-repented blames,</line>
            <line>Dear sovereign, pardon to me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>All is whole;</line>
            <line>Not one word more of the consumed time.</line>
            <line>Let's take the instant by the forward top;</line>
            <line>For we are old, and on our quick'st decrees</line>
            <line>The inaudible and noiseless foot of Time</line>
            <line>Steals ere we can effect them. You remember</line>
            <line>The daughter of this lord?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>Admiringly, my liege, at first</line>
            <line>I stuck my choice upon her, ere my heart</line>
            <line>Durst make too bold a herald of my tongue</line>
            <line>Where the impression of mine eye infixing,</line>
            <line>Contempt his scornful perspective did lend me,</line>
            <line>Which warp'd the line of every other favour;</line>
            <line>Scorn'd a fair colour, or express'd it stolen;</line>
            <line>Extended or contracted all proportions</line>
            <line>To a most hideous object: thence it came</line>
            <line>That she whom all men praised and whom myself,</line>
            <line>Since I have lost, have loved, was in mine eye</line>
            <line>The dust that did offend it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>Well excused:</line>
            <line>That thou didst love her, strikes some scores away</line>
            <line>From the great compt: but love that comes too late,</line>
            <line>Like a remorseful pardon slowly carried,</line>
            <line>To the great sender turns a sour offence,</line>
            <line>Crying, 'That's good that's gone.' Our rash faults</line>
            <line>Make trivial price of serious things we have,</line>
            <line>Not knowing them until we know their grave:</line>
            <line>Oft our displeasures, to ourselves unjust,</line>
            <line>Destroy our friends and after weep their dust</line>
            <line>Our own love waking cries to see what's done,</line>
            <line>While shame full late sleeps out the afternoon.</line>
            <line>Be this sweet Helen's knell, and now forget her.</line>
            <line>Send forth your amorous token for fair Maudlin:</line>
            <line>The main consents are had; and here we'll stay</line>
            <line>To see our widower's second marriage-day.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>Which better than the first, O dear heaven, bless!</line>
            <line>Or, ere they meet, in me, O nature, cesse!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>Come on, my son, in whom my house's name</line>
            <line>Must be digested, give a favour from you</line>
            <line>To sparkle in the spirits of my daughter,</line>
            <line>That she may quickly come.</line>
            <stagedir>BERTRAM gives a ring</stagedir>
            <line>By my old beard,</line>
            <line>And every hair that's on't, Helen, that's dead,</line>
            <line>Was a sweet creature: such a ring as this,</line>
            <line>The last that e'er I took her at court,</line>
            <line>I saw upon her finger.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>Hers it was not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>Now, pray you, let me see it; for mine eye,</line>
            <line>While I was speaking, oft was fasten'd to't.</line>
            <line>This ring was mine; and, when I gave it Helen,</line>
            <line>I bade her, if her fortunes ever stood</line>
            <line>Necessitied to help, that by this token</line>
            <line>I would relieve her. Had you that craft, to reave</line>
            <line>her</line>
            <line>Of what should stead her most?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>My gracious sovereign,</line>
            <line>Howe'er it pleases you to take it so,</line>
            <line>The ring was never hers.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>Son, on my life,</line>
            <line>I have seen her wear it; and she reckon'd it</line>
            <line>At her life's rate.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>I am sure I saw her wear it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>You are deceived, my lord; she never saw it:</line>
            <line>In Florence was it from a casement thrown me,</line>
            <line>Wrapp'd in a paper, which contain'd the name</line>
            <line>Of her that threw it: noble she was, and thought</line>
            <line>I stood engaged: but when I had subscribed</line>
            <line>To mine own fortune and inform'd her fully</line>
            <line>I could not answer in that course of honour</line>
            <line>As she had made the overture, she ceased</line>
            <line>In heavy satisfaction and would never</line>
            <line>Receive the ring again.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>Plutus himself,</line>
            <line>That knows the tinct and multiplying medicine,</line>
            <line>Hath not in nature's mystery more science</line>
            <line>Than I have in this ring: 'twas mine, 'twas Helen's,</line>
            <line>Whoever gave it you. Then, if you know</line>
            <line>That you are well acquainted with yourself,</line>
            <line>Confess 'twas hers, and by what rough enforcement</line>
            <line>You got it from her: she call'd the saints to surety</line>
            <line>That she would never put it from her finger,</line>
            <line>Unless she gave it to yourself in bed,</line>
            <line>Where you have never come, or sent it us</line>
            <line>Upon her great disaster.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>She never saw it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>Thou speak'st it falsely, as I love mine honour;</line>
            <line>And makest conjectural fears to come into me</line>
            <line>Which I would fain shut out. If it should prove</line>
            <line>That thou art so inhuman,--'twill not prove so;--</line>
            <line>And yet I know not: thou didst hate her deadly,</line>
            <line>And she is dead; which nothing, but to close</line>
            <line>Her eyes myself, could win me to believe,</line>
            <line>More than to see this ring. Take him away.</line>
            <stagedir>Guards seize BERTRAM</stagedir>
            <line>My fore-past proofs, howe'er the matter fall,</line>
            <line>Shall tax my fears of little vanity,</line>
            <line>Having vainly fear'd too little. Away with him!</line>
            <line>We'll sift this matter further.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>If you shall prove</line>
            <line>This ring was ever hers, you shall as easy</line>
            <line>Prove that I husbanded her bed in Florence,</line>
            <line>Where yet she never was.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit, guarded</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>I am wrapp'd in dismal thinkings.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter a Gentleman</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Gentleman</speaker>
            <line>Gracious sovereign,</line>
            <line>Whether I have been to blame or no, I know not:</line>
            <line>Here's a petition from a Florentine,</line>
            <line>Who hath for four or five removes come short</line>
            <line>To tender it herself. I undertook it,</line>
            <line>Vanquish'd thereto by the fair grace and speech</line>
            <line>Of the poor suppliant, who by this I know</line>
            <line>Is here attending: her business looks in her</line>
            <line>With an importing visage; and she told me,</line>
            <line>In a sweet verbal brief, it did concern</line>
            <line>Your highness with herself.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>  Upon his many protestations to marry me</line>
            <line>when his wife was dead, I blush to say it, he won</line>
            <line>me. Now is the Count Rousillon a widower: his vows</line>
            <line>are forfeited to me, and my honour's paid to him. He</line>
            <line>stole from Florence, taking no leave, and I follow</line>
            <line>him to his country for justice: grant it me, O</line>
            <line>king! in you it best lies; otherwise a seducer</line>
            <line>flourishes, and a poor maid is undone.</line>
            <line>DIANA CAPILET.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>I will buy me a son-in-law in a fair, and toll for</line>
            <line>this: I'll none of him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>The heavens have thought well on thee Lafeu,</line>
            <line>To bring forth this discovery. Seek these suitors:</line>
            <line>Go speedily and bring again the count.</line>
            <line>I am afeard the life of Helen, lady,</line>
            <line>Was foully snatch'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>Now, justice on the doers!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter BERTRAM, guarded</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>I wonder, sir, sith wives are monsters to you,</line>
            <line>And that you fly them as you swear them lordship,</line>
            <line>Yet you desire to marry.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter Widow and DIANA</stagedir>
            <line>What woman's that?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DIANA</speaker>
            <line>I am, my lord, a wretched Florentine,</line>
            <line>Derived from the ancient Capilet:</line>
            <line>My suit, as I do understand, you know,</line>
            <line>And therefore know how far I may be pitied.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Widow</speaker>
            <line>I am her mother, sir, whose age and honour</line>
            <line>Both suffer under this complaint we bring,</line>
            <line>And both shall cease, without your remedy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>Come hither, count; do you know these women?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>My lord, I neither can nor will deny</line>
            <line>But that I know them: do they charge me further?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DIANA</speaker>
            <line>Why do you look so strange upon your wife?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>She's none of mine, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DIANA</speaker>
            <line>If you shall marry,</line>
            <line>You give away this hand, and that is mine;</line>
            <line>You give away heaven's vows, and those are mine;</line>
            <line>You give away myself, which is known mine;</line>
            <line>For I by vow am so embodied yours,</line>
            <line>That she which marries you must marry me,</line>
            <line>Either both or none.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>Your reputation comes too short for my daughter; you</line>
            <line>are no husband for her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>My lord, this is a fond and desperate creature,</line>
            <line>Whom sometime I have laugh'd with: let your highness</line>
            <line>Lay a more noble thought upon mine honour</line>
            <line>Than for to think that I would sink it here.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>Sir, for my thoughts, you have them ill to friend</line>
            <line>Till your deeds gain them: fairer prove your honour</line>
            <line>Than in my thought it lies.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DIANA</speaker>
            <line>Good my lord,</line>
            <line>Ask him upon his oath, if he does think</line>
            <line>He had not my virginity.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>What say'st thou to her?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>She's impudent, my lord,</line>
            <line>And was a common gamester to the camp.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DIANA</speaker>
            <line>He does me wrong, my lord; if I were so,</line>
            <line>He might have bought me at a common price:</line>
            <line>Do not believe him. O, behold this ring,</line>
            <line>Whose high respect and rich validity</line>
            <line>Did lack a parallel; yet for all that</line>
            <line>He gave it to a commoner o' the camp,</line>
            <line>If I be one.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>He blushes, and 'tis it:</line>
            <line>Of six preceding ancestors, that gem,</line>
            <line>Conferr'd by testament to the sequent issue,</line>
            <line>Hath it been owed and worn. This is his wife;</line>
            <line>That ring's a thousand proofs.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>Methought you said</line>
            <line>You saw one here in court could witness it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DIANA</speaker>
            <line>I did, my lord, but loath am to produce</line>
            <line>So bad an instrument: his name's Parolles.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>I saw the man to-day, if man he be.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>Find him, and bring him hither.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit an Attendant</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>What of him?</line>
            <line>He's quoted for a most perfidious slave,</line>
            <line>With all the spots o' the world tax'd and debosh'd;</line>
            <line>Whose nature sickens but to speak a truth.</line>
            <line>Am I or that or this for what he'll utter,</line>
            <line>That will speak any thing?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>She hath that ring of yours.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>I think she has: certain it is I liked her,</line>
            <line>And boarded her i' the wanton way of youth:</line>
            <line>She knew her distance and did angle for me,</line>
            <line>Madding my eagerness with her restraint,</line>
            <line>As all impediments in fancy's course</line>
            <line>Are motives of more fancy; and, in fine,</line>
            <line>Her infinite cunning, with her modern grace,</line>
            <line>Subdued me to her rate: she got the ring;</line>
            <line>And I had that which any inferior might</line>
            <line>At market-price have bought.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DIANA</speaker>
            <line>I must be patient:</line>
            <line>You, that have turn'd off a first so noble wife,</line>
            <line>May justly diet me. I pray you yet;</line>
            <line>Since you lack virtue, I will lose a husband;</line>
            <line>Send for your ring, I will return it home,</line>
            <line>And give me mine again.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>I have it not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>What ring was yours, I pray you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DIANA</speaker>
            <line>Sir, much like</line>
            <line>The same upon your finger.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>Know you this ring? this ring was his of late.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DIANA</speaker>
            <line>And this was it I gave him, being abed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>The story then goes false, you threw it him</line>
            <line>Out of a casement.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DIANA</speaker>
            <line>I have spoke the truth.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter PAROLLES</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>My lord, I do confess the ring was hers.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>You boggle shrewdly, every feather stars you.</line>
            <line>Is this the man you speak of?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DIANA</speaker>
            <line>Ay, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>Tell me, sirrah, but tell me true, I charge you,</line>
            <line>Not fearing the displeasure of your master,</line>
            <line>Which on your just proceeding I'll keep off,</line>
            <line>By him and by this woman here what know you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>So please your majesty, my master hath been an</line>
            <line>honourable gentleman: tricks he hath had in him,</line>
            <line>which gentlemen have.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>Come, come, to the purpose: did he love this woman?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Faith, sir, he did love her; but how?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>How, I pray you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>He did love her, sir, as a gentleman loves a woman.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>How is that?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>He loved her, sir, and loved her not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>As thou art a knave, and no knave. What an</line>
            <line>equivocal companion is this!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>I am a poor man, and at your majesty's command.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>He's a good drum, my lord, but a naughty orator.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DIANA</speaker>
            <line>Do you know he promised me marriage?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Faith, I know more than I'll speak.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>But wilt thou not speak all thou knowest?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Yes, so please your majesty. I did go between them,</line>
            <line>as I said; but more than that, he loved her: for</line>
            <line>indeed he was mad for her, and talked of Satan and</line>
            <line>of Limbo and of Furies and I know not what: yet I</line>
            <line>was in that credit with them at that time that I</line>
            <line>knew of their going to bed, and of other motions,</line>
            <line>as promising her marriage, and things which would</line>
            <line>derive me ill will to speak of; therefore I will not</line>
            <line>speak what I know.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>Thou hast spoken all already, unless thou canst say</line>
            <line>they are married: but thou art too fine in thy</line>
            <line>evidence; therefore stand aside.</line>
            <line>This ring, you say, was yours?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DIANA</speaker>
            <line>Ay, my good lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>Where did you buy it? or who gave it you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DIANA</speaker>
            <line>It was not given me, nor I did not buy it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>Who lent it you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DIANA</speaker>
            <line>It was not lent me neither.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>Where did you find it, then?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DIANA</speaker>
            <line>I found it not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>If it were yours by none of all these ways,</line>
            <line>How could you give it him?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DIANA</speaker>
            <line>I never gave it him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>This woman's an easy glove, my lord; she goes off</line>
            <line>and on at pleasure.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>This ring was mine; I gave it his first wife.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DIANA</speaker>
            <line>It might be yours or hers, for aught I know.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>Take her away; I do not like her now;</line>
            <line>To prison with her: and away with him.</line>
            <line>Unless thou tell'st me where thou hadst this ring,</line>
            <line>Thou diest within this hour.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DIANA</speaker>
            <line>I'll never tell you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>Take her away.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DIANA</speaker>
            <line>I'll put in bail, my liege.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>I think thee now some common customer.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DIANA</speaker>
            <line>By Jove, if ever I knew man, 'twas you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>Wherefore hast thou accused him all this while?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DIANA</speaker>
            <line>Because he's guilty, and he is not guilty:</line>
            <line>He knows I am no maid, and he'll swear to't;</line>
            <line>I'll swear I am a maid, and he knows not.</line>
            <line>Great king, I am no strumpet, by my life;</line>
            <line>I am either maid, or else this old man's wife.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>She does abuse our ears: to prison with her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DIANA</speaker>
            <line>Good mother, fetch my bail. Stay, royal sir:</line>
            <stagedir>Exit Widow</stagedir>
            <line>The jeweller that owes the ring is sent for,</line>
            <line>And he shall surety me. But for this lord,</line>
            <line>Who hath abused me, as he knows himself,</line>
            <line>Though yet he never harm'd me, here I quit him:</line>
            <line>He knows himself my bed he hath defiled;</line>
            <line>And at that time he got his wife with child:</line>
            <line>Dead though she be, she feels her young one kick:</line>
            <line>So there's my riddle: one that's dead is quick:</line>
            <line>And now behold the meaning.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter Widow, with HELENA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>Is there no exorcist</line>
            <line>Beguiles the truer office of mine eyes?</line>
            <line>Is't real that I see?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>No, my good lord;</line>
            <line>'Tis but the shadow of a wife you see,</line>
            <line>The name and not the thing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>Both, both. O, pardon!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>O my good lord, when I was like this maid,</line>
            <line>I found you wondrous kind. There is your ring;</line>
            <line>And, look you, here's your letter; this it says:</line>
            <line>'When from my finger you can get this ring</line>
            <line>And are by me with child,' &amp;c. This is done:</line>
            <line>Will you be mine, now you are doubly won?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>If she, my liege, can make me know this clearly,</line>
            <line>I'll love her dearly, ever, ever dearly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>If it appear not plain and prove untrue,</line>
            <line>Deadly divorce step between me and you!</line>
            <line>O my dear mother, do I see you living?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>Mine eyes smell onions; I shall weep anon:</line>
            <stagedir>To PAROLLES</stagedir>
            <line>Good Tom Drum, lend me a handkercher: so,</line>
            <line>I thank thee: wait on me home, I'll make sport with thee:</line>
            <line>Let thy courtesies alone, they are scurvy ones.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>Let us from point to point this story know,</line>
            <line>To make the even truth in pleasure flow.</line>
            <stagedir>To DIANA</stagedir>
            <line>If thou be'st yet a fresh uncropped flower,</line>
            <line>Choose thou thy husband, and I'll pay thy dower;</line>
            <line>For I can guess that by thy honest aid</line>
            <line>Thou keep'st a wife herself, thyself a maid.</line>
            <line>Of that and all the progress, more or less,</line>
            <line>Resolvedly more leisure shall express:</line>
            <line>All yet seems well; and if it end so meet,</line>
            <line>The bitter past, more welcome is the sweet.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Flourish</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <epilogue id="act-5-epilog">
      <title>EPILOGUE</title>
      <epilogue-body>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>The king's a beggar, now the play is done:</line>
            <line>All is well ended, if this suit be won,</line>
            <line>That you express content; which we will pay,</line>
            <line>With strife to please you, day exceeding day:</line>
            <line>Ours be your patience then, and yours our parts;</line>
            <line>Your gentle hands lend us, and take our hearts.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </epilogue-body>
   </epilogue>
</act>