<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net/doctypes/dita/shakespear/dtd/act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-4">
   <title>ACT IV</title>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  Without the Florentine camp.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter Second French Lord, with five or six other
Soldiers in ambush</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>He can come no other way but by this hedge-corner.</line>
            <line>When you sally upon him, speak what terrible</line>
            <line>language you will: though you understand it not</line>
            <line>yourselves, no matter; for we must not seem to</line>
            <line>understand him, unless some one among us whom we</line>
            <line>must produce for an interpreter.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Soldier</speaker>
            <line>Good captain, let me be the interpreter.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>Art not acquainted with him? knows he not thy voice?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Soldier</speaker>
            <line>No, sir, I warrant you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>But what linsey-woolsey hast thou to speak to us again?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Soldier</speaker>
            <line>E'en such as you speak to me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>He must think us some band of strangers i' the</line>
            <line>adversary's entertainment. Now he hath a smack of</line>
            <line>all neighbouring languages; therefore we must every</line>
            <line>one be a man of his own fancy, not to know what we</line>
            <line>speak one to another; so we seem to know, is to</line>
            <line>know straight our purpose: choughs' language,</line>
            <line>gabble enough, and good enough. As for you,</line>
            <line>interpreter, you must seem very politic. But couch,</line>
            <line>ho! here he comes, to beguile two hours in a sleep,</line>
            <line>and then to return and swear the lies he forges.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter PAROLLES</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Ten o'clock: within these three hours 'twill be</line>
            <line>time enough to go home. What shall I say I have</line>
            <line>done? It must be a very plausive invention that</line>
            <line>carries it: they begin to smoke me; and disgraces</line>
            <line>have of late knocked too often at my door. I find</line>
            <line>my tongue is too foolhardy; but my heart hath the</line>
            <line>fear of Mars before it and of his creatures, not</line>
            <line>daring the reports of my tongue.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>This is the first truth that e'er thine own tongue</line>
            <line>was guilty of.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>What the devil should move me to undertake the</line>
            <line>recovery of this drum, being not ignorant of the</line>
            <line>impossibility, and knowing I had no such purpose? I</line>
            <line>must give myself some hurts, and say I got them in</line>
            <line>exploit: yet slight ones will not carry it; they</line>
            <line>will say, 'Came you off with so little?' and great</line>
            <line>ones I dare not give. Wherefore, what's the</line>
            <line>instance? Tongue, I must put you into a</line>
            <line>butter-woman's mouth and buy myself another of</line>
            <line>Bajazet's mule, if you prattle me into these perils.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>Is it possible he should know what he is, and be</line>
            <line>that he is?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>I would the cutting of my garments would serve the</line>
            <line>turn, or the breaking of my Spanish sword.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>We cannot afford you so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Or the baring of my beard; and to say it was in</line>
            <line>stratagem.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>'Twould not do.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Or to drown my clothes, and say I was stripped.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>Hardly serve.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Though I swore I leaped from the window of the citadel.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>How deep?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Thirty fathom.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>Three great oaths would scarce make that be believed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>I would I had any drum of the enemy's: I would swear</line>
            <line>I recovered it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>You shall hear one anon.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>A drum now of the enemy's,--</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Alarum within</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>Throca movousus, cargo, cargo, cargo.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>All</speaker>
            <line>Cargo, cargo, cargo, villiando par corbo, cargo.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>O, ransom, ransom! do not hide mine eyes.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>They seize and blindfold him</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Soldier</speaker>
            <line>Boskos thromuldo boskos.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>I know you are the Muskos' regiment:</line>
            <line>And I shall lose my life for want of language;</line>
            <line>If there be here German, or Dane, low Dutch,</line>
            <line>Italian, or French, let him speak to me; I'll</line>
            <line>Discover that which shall undo the Florentine.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Soldier</speaker>
            <line>Boskos vauvado: I understand thee, and can speak</line>
            <line>thy tongue. Kerely bonto, sir, betake thee to thy</line>
            <line>faith, for seventeen poniards are at thy bosom.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>O!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Soldier</speaker>
            <line>O, pray, pray, pray! Manka revania dulche.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>Oscorbidulchos volivorco.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Soldier</speaker>
            <line>The general is content to spare thee yet;</line>
            <line>And, hoodwink'd as thou art, will lead thee on</line>
            <line>To gather from thee: haply thou mayst inform</line>
            <line>Something to save thy life.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>O, let me live!</line>
            <line>And all the secrets of our camp I'll show,</line>
            <line>Their force, their purposes; nay, I'll speak that</line>
            <line>Which you will wonder at.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Soldier</speaker>
            <line>But wilt thou faithfully?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>If I do not, damn me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Soldier</speaker>
            <line>Acordo linta.</line>
            <line>Come on; thou art granted space.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit, with PAROLLES guarded. A short alarum within</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>Go, tell the Count Rousillon, and my brother,</line>
            <line>We have caught the woodcock, and will keep him muffled</line>
            <line>Till we do hear from them.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Soldier</speaker>
            <line>Captain, I will.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>A' will betray us all unto ourselves:</line>
            <line>Inform on that.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Soldier</speaker>
            <line>So I will, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>Till then I'll keep him dark and safely lock'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  Florence. The Widow's house.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter BERTRAM and DIANA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>They told me that your name was Fontibell.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DIANA</speaker>
            <line>No, my good lord, Diana.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>Titled goddess;</line>
            <line>And worth it, with addition! But, fair soul,</line>
            <line>In your fine frame hath love no quality?</line>
            <line>If quick fire of youth light not your mind,</line>
            <line>You are no maiden, but a monument:</line>
            <line>When you are dead, you should be such a one</line>
            <line>As you are now, for you are cold and stem;</line>
            <line>And now you should be as your mother was</line>
            <line>When your sweet self was got.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DIANA</speaker>
            <line>She then was honest.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>So should you be.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DIANA</speaker>
            <line>No:</line>
            <line>My mother did but duty; such, my lord,</line>
            <line>As you owe to your wife.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>No more o' that;</line>
            <line>I prithee, do not strive against my vows:</line>
            <line>I was compell'd to her; but I love thee</line>
            <line>By love's own sweet constraint, and will for ever</line>
            <line>Do thee all rights of service.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DIANA</speaker>
            <line>Ay, so you serve us</line>
            <line>Till we serve you; but when you have our roses,</line>
            <line>You barely leave our thorns to prick ourselves</line>
            <line>And mock us with our bareness.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>How have I sworn!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DIANA</speaker>
            <line>'Tis not the many oaths that makes the truth,</line>
            <line>But the plain single vow that is vow'd true.</line>
            <line>What is not holy, that we swear not by,</line>
            <line>But take the High'st to witness: then, pray you, tell me,</line>
            <line>If I should swear by God's great attributes,</line>
            <line>I loved you dearly, would you believe my oaths,</line>
            <line>When I did love you ill? This has no holding,</line>
            <line>To swear by him whom I protest to love,</line>
            <line>That I will work against him: therefore your oaths</line>
            <line>Are words and poor conditions, but unseal'd,</line>
            <line>At least in my opinion.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>Change it, change it;</line>
            <line>Be not so holy-cruel: love is holy;</line>
            <line>And my integrity ne'er knew the crafts</line>
            <line>That you do charge men with. Stand no more off,</line>
            <line>But give thyself unto my sick desires,</line>
            <line>Who then recover: say thou art mine, and ever</line>
            <line>My love as it begins shall so persever.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DIANA</speaker>
            <line>I see that men make ropes in such a scarre</line>
            <line>That we'll forsake ourselves. Give me that ring.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>I'll lend it thee, my dear; but have no power</line>
            <line>To give it from me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DIANA</speaker>
            <line>Will you not, my lord?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>It is an honour 'longing to our house,</line>
            <line>Bequeathed down from many ancestors;</line>
            <line>Which were the greatest obloquy i' the world</line>
            <line>In me to lose.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DIANA</speaker>
            <line>Mine honour's such a ring:</line>
            <line>My chastity's the jewel of our house,</line>
            <line>Bequeathed down from many ancestors;</line>
            <line>Which were the greatest obloquy i' the world</line>
            <line>In me to lose: thus your own proper wisdom</line>
            <line>Brings in the champion Honour on my part,</line>
            <line>Against your vain assault.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>Here, take my ring:</line>
            <line>My house, mine honour, yea, my life, be thine,</line>
            <line>And I'll be bid by thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DIANA</speaker>
            <line>When midnight comes, knock at my chamber-window:</line>
            <line>I'll order take my mother shall not hear.</line>
            <line>Now will I charge you in the band of truth,</line>
            <line>When you have conquer'd my yet maiden bed,</line>
            <line>Remain there but an hour, nor speak to me:</line>
            <line>My reasons are most strong; and you shall know them</line>
            <line>When back again this ring shall be deliver'd:</line>
            <line>And on your finger in the night I'll put</line>
            <line>Another ring, that what in time proceeds</line>
            <line>May token to the future our past deeds.</line>
            <line>Adieu, till then; then, fail not. You have won</line>
            <line>A wife of me, though there my hope be done.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>A heaven on earth I have won by wooing thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DIANA</speaker>
            <line>For which live long to thank both heaven and me!</line>
            <line>You may so in the end.</line>
            <line>My mother told me just how he would woo,</line>
            <line>As if she sat in 's heart; she says all men</line>
            <line>Have the like oaths: he had sworn to marry me</line>
            <line>When his wife's dead; therefore I'll lie with him</line>
            <line>When I am buried. Since Frenchmen are so braid,</line>
            <line>Marry that will, I live and die a maid:</line>
            <line>Only in this disguise I think't no sin</line>
            <line>To cozen him that would unjustly win.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  The Florentine camp.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter the two French Lords and some two or three Soldiers</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>You have not given him his mother's letter?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>I have delivered it an hour since: there is</line>
            <line>something in't that stings his nature; for on the</line>
            <line>reading it he changed almost into another man.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>He has much worthy blame laid upon him for shaking</line>
            <line>off so good a wife and so sweet a lady.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>Especially he hath incurred the everlasting</line>
            <line>displeasure of the king, who had even tuned his</line>
            <line>bounty to sing happiness to him. I will tell you a</line>
            <line>thing, but you shall let it dwell darkly with you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>When you have spoken it, 'tis dead, and I am the</line>
            <line>grave of it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>He hath perverted a young gentlewoman here in</line>
            <line>Florence, of a most chaste renown; and this night he</line>
            <line>fleshes his will in the spoil of her honour: he hath</line>
            <line>given her his monumental ring, and thinks himself</line>
            <line>made in the unchaste composition.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>Now, God delay our rebellion! as we are ourselves,</line>
            <line>what things are we!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>Merely our own traitors. And as in the common course</line>
            <line>of all treasons, we still see them reveal</line>
            <line>themselves, till they attain to their abhorred ends,</line>
            <line>so he that in this action contrives against his own</line>
            <line>nobility, in his proper stream o'erflows himself.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>Is it not meant damnable in us, to be trumpeters of</line>
            <line>our unlawful intents? We shall not then have his</line>
            <line>company to-night?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>Not till after midnight; for he is dieted to his hour.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>That approaches apace; I would gladly have him see</line>
            <line>his company anatomized, that he might take a measure</line>
            <line>of his own judgments, wherein so curiously he had</line>
            <line>set this counterfeit.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>We will not meddle with him till he come; for his</line>
            <line>presence must be the whip of the other.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>In the mean time, what hear you of these wars?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>I hear there is an overture of peace.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>Nay, I assure you, a peace concluded.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>What will Count Rousillon do then? will he travel</line>
            <line>higher, or return again into France?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>I perceive, by this demand, you are not altogether</line>
            <line>of his council.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>Let it be forbid, sir; so should I be a great deal</line>
            <line>of his act.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>Sir, his wife some two months since fled from his</line>
            <line>house: her pretence is a pilgrimage to Saint Jaques</line>
            <line>le Grand; which holy undertaking with most austere</line>
            <line>sanctimony she accomplished; and, there residing the</line>
            <line>tenderness of her nature became as a prey to her</line>
            <line>grief; in fine, made a groan of her last breath, and</line>
            <line>now she sings in heaven.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>How is this justified?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>The stronger part of it by her own letters, which</line>
            <line>makes her story true, even to the point of her</line>
            <line>death: her death itself, which could not be her</line>
            <line>office to say is come, was faithfully confirmed by</line>
            <line>the rector of the place.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>Hath the count all this intelligence?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>Ay, and the particular confirmations, point from</line>
            <line>point, so to the full arming of the verity.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>I am heartily sorry that he'll be glad of this.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>How mightily sometimes we make us comforts of our losses!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>And how mightily some other times we drown our gain</line>
            <line>in tears! The great dignity that his valour hath</line>
            <line>here acquired for him shall at home be encountered</line>
            <line>with a shame as ample.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>The web of our life is of a mingled yarn, good and</line>
            <line>ill together: our virtues would be proud, if our</line>
            <line>faults whipped them not; and our crimes would</line>
            <line>despair, if they were not cherished by our virtues.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter a Messenger</stagedir>
            <line>How now! where's your master?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>He met the duke in the street, sir, of whom he hath</line>
            <line>taken a solemn leave: his lordship will next</line>
            <line>morning for France. The duke hath offered him</line>
            <line>letters of commendations to the king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>They shall be no more than needful there, if they</line>
            <line>were more than they can commend.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>They cannot be too sweet for the king's tartness.</line>
            <line>Here's his lordship now.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter BERTRAM</stagedir>
            <line>How now, my lord! is't not after midnight?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>I have to-night dispatched sixteen businesses, a</line>
            <line>month's length a-piece, by an abstract of success:</line>
            <line>I have congied with the duke, done my adieu with his</line>
            <line>nearest; buried a wife, mourned for her; writ to my</line>
            <line>lady mother I am returning; entertained my convoy;</line>
            <line>and between these main parcels of dispatch effected</line>
            <line>many nicer needs; the last was the greatest, but</line>
            <line>that I have not ended yet.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>If the business be of any difficulty, and this</line>
            <line>morning your departure hence, it requires haste of</line>
            <line>your lordship.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>I mean, the business is not ended, as fearing to</line>
            <line>hear of it hereafter. But shall we have this</line>
            <line>dialogue between the fool and the soldier? Come,</line>
            <line>bring forth this counterfeit module, he has deceived</line>
            <line>me, like a double-meaning prophesier.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>Bring him forth: has sat i' the stocks all night,</line>
            <line>poor gallant knave.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>No matter: his heels have deserved it, in usurping</line>
            <line>his spurs so long. How does he carry himself?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>I have told your lordship already, the stocks carry</line>
            <line>him. But to answer you as you would be understood;</line>
            <line>he weeps like a wench that had shed her milk: he</line>
            <line>hath confessed himself to Morgan, whom he supposes</line>
            <line>to be a friar, from the time of his remembrance to</line>
            <line>this very instant disaster of his setting i' the</line>
            <line>stocks: and what think you he hath confessed?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>Nothing of me, has a'?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>His confession is taken, and it shall be read to his</line>
            <line>face: if your lordship be in't, as I believe you</line>
            <line>are, you must have the patience to hear it.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter PAROLLES guarded, and First Soldier</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>A plague upon him! muffled! he can say nothing of</line>
            <line>me: hush, hush!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>Hoodman comes! Portotartarosa</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Soldier</speaker>
            <line>He calls for the tortures: what will you say</line>
            <line>without 'em?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>I will confess what I know without constraint: if</line>
            <line>ye pinch me like a pasty, I can say no more.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Soldier</speaker>
            <line>Bosko chimurcho.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>Boblibindo chicurmurco.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Soldier</speaker>
            <line>You are a merciful general. Our general bids you</line>
            <line>answer to what I shall ask you out of a note.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>And truly, as I hope to live.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Soldier</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>  'First demand of him how many horse the</line>
            <line>duke is strong.' What say you to that?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Five or six thousand; but very weak and</line>
            <line>unserviceable: the troops are all scattered, and</line>
            <line>the commanders very poor rogues, upon my reputation</line>
            <line>and credit and as I hope to live.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Soldier</speaker>
            <line>Shall I set down your answer so?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Do: I'll take the sacrament on't, how and which way you will.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>All's one to him. What a past-saving slave is this!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>You're deceived, my lord: this is Monsieur</line>
            <line>Parolles, the gallant militarist,--that was his own</line>
            <line>phrase,--that had the whole theoric of war in the</line>
            <line>knot of his scarf, and the practise in the chape of</line>
            <line>his dagger.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>I will never trust a man again for keeping his sword</line>
            <line>clean. nor believe he can have every thing in him</line>
            <line>by wearing his apparel neatly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Soldier</speaker>
            <line>Well, that's set down.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Five or six thousand horse, I said,-- I will say</line>
            <line>true,--or thereabouts, set down, for I'll speak truth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>He's very near the truth in this.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>But I con him no thanks for't, in the nature he</line>
            <line>delivers it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Poor rogues, I pray you, say.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Soldier</speaker>
            <line>Well, that's set down.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>I humbly thank you, sir: a truth's a truth, the</line>
            <line>rogues are marvellous poor.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Soldier</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>  'Demand of him, of what strength they are</line>
            <line>a-foot.' What say you to that?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>By my troth, sir, if I were to live this present</line>
            <line>hour, I will tell true. Let me see: Spurio, a</line>
            <line>hundred and fifty; Sebastian, so many; Corambus, so</line>
            <line>many; Jaques, so many; Guiltian, Cosmo, Lodowick,</line>
            <line>and Gratii, two hundred and fifty each; mine own</line>
            <line>company, Chitopher, Vaumond, Bentii, two hundred and</line>
            <line>fifty each: so that the muster-file, rotten and</line>
            <line>sound, upon my life, amounts not to fifteen thousand</line>
            <line>poll; half of the which dare not shake snow from off</line>
            <line>their cassocks, lest they shake themselves to pieces.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>What shall be done to him?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>Nothing, but let him have thanks. Demand of him my</line>
            <line>condition, and what credit I have with the duke.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Soldier</speaker>
            <line>Well, that's set down.</line>
            <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>
            <line>'You shall demand of him, whether one Captain Dumain</line>
            <line>be i' the camp, a Frenchman; what his reputation is</line>
            <line>with the duke; what his valour, honesty, and</line>
            <line>expertness in wars; or whether he thinks it were not</line>
            <line>possible, with well-weighing sums of gold, to</line>
            <line>corrupt him to revolt.' What say you to this? what</line>
            <line>do you know of it?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>I beseech you, let me answer to the particular of</line>
            <line>the inter'gatories: demand them singly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Soldier</speaker>
            <line>Do you know this Captain Dumain?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>I know him: a' was a botcher's 'prentice in Paris,</line>
            <line>from whence he was whipped for getting the shrieve's</line>
            <line>fool with child,--a dumb innocent, that could not</line>
            <line>say him nay.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>Nay, by your leave, hold your hands; though I know</line>
            <line>his brains are forfeit to the next tile that falls.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Soldier</speaker>
            <line>Well, is this captain in the duke of Florence's camp?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Upon my knowledge, he is, and lousy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>Nay look not so upon me; we shall hear of your</line>
            <line>lordship anon.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Soldier</speaker>
            <line>What is his reputation with the duke?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>The duke knows him for no other but a poor officer</line>
            <line>of mine; and writ to me this other day to turn him</line>
            <line>out o' the band: I think I have his letter in my pocket.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Soldier</speaker>
            <line>Marry, we'll search.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>In good sadness, I do not know; either it is there,</line>
            <line>or it is upon a file with the duke's other letters</line>
            <line>in my tent.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Soldier</speaker>
            <line>Here 'tis; here's a paper: shall I read it to you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>I do not know if it be it or no.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>Our interpreter does it well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>Excellently.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Soldier</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>  'Dian, the count's a fool, and full of gold,'--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>That is not the duke's letter, sir; that is an</line>
            <line>advertisement to a proper maid in Florence, one</line>
            <line>Diana, to take heed of the allurement of one Count</line>
            <line>Rousillon, a foolish idle boy, but for all that very</line>
            <line>ruttish: I pray you, sir, put it up again.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Soldier</speaker>
            <line>Nay, I'll read it first, by your favour.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>My meaning in't, I protest, was very honest in the</line>
            <line>behalf of the maid; for I knew the young count to be</line>
            <line>a dangerous and lascivious boy, who is a whale to</line>
            <line>virginity and devours up all the fry it finds.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>Damnable both-sides rogue!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Soldier</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>  'When he swears oaths, bid him drop gold, and take it;</line>
            <line>After he scores, he never pays the score:</line>
            <line>Half won is match well made; match, and well make it;</line>
            <line>He ne'er pays after-debts, take it before;</line>
            <line>And say a soldier, Dian, told thee this,</line>
            <line>Men are to mell with, boys are not to kiss:</line>
            <line>For count of this, the count's a fool, I know it,</line>
            <line>Who pays before, but not when he does owe it.</line>
            <line>Thine, as he vowed to thee in thine ear,</line>
            <line>PAROLLES.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>He shall be whipped through the army with this rhyme</line>
            <line>in's forehead.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>This is your devoted friend, sir, the manifold</line>
            <line>linguist and the armipotent soldier.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>I could endure any thing before but a cat, and now</line>
            <line>he's a cat to me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Soldier</speaker>
            <line>I perceive, sir, by the general's looks, we shall be</line>
            <line>fain to hang you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>My life, sir, in any case: not that I am afraid to</line>
            <line>die; but that, my offences being many, I would</line>
            <line>repent out the remainder of nature: let me live,</line>
            <line>sir, in a dungeon, i' the stocks, or any where, so I may live.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Soldier</speaker>
            <line>We'll see what may be done, so you confess freely;</line>
            <line>therefore, once more to this Captain Dumain: you</line>
            <line>have answered to his reputation with the duke and to</line>
            <line>his valour: what is his honesty?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>He will steal, sir, an egg out of a cloister: for</line>
            <line>rapes and ravishments he parallels Nessus: he</line>
            <line>professes not keeping of oaths; in breaking 'em he</line>
            <line>is stronger than Hercules: he will lie, sir, with</line>
            <line>such volubility, that you would think truth were a</line>
            <line>fool: drunkenness is his best virtue, for he will</line>
            <line>be swine-drunk; and in his sleep he does little</line>
            <line>harm, save to his bed-clothes about him; but they</line>
            <line>know his conditions and lay him in straw. I have but</line>
            <line>little more to say, sir, of his honesty: he has</line>
            <line>every thing that an honest man should not have; what</line>
            <line>an honest man should have, he has nothing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>I begin to love him for this.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>For this description of thine honesty? A pox upon</line>
            <line>him for me, he's more and more a cat.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Soldier</speaker>
            <line>What say you to his expertness in war?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Faith, sir, he has led the drum before the English</line>
            <line>tragedians; to belie him, I will not, and more of</line>
            <line>his soldiership I know not; except, in that country</line>
            <line>he had the honour to be the officer at a place there</line>
            <line>called Mile-end, to instruct for the doubling of</line>
            <line>files: I would do the man what honour I can, but of</line>
            <line>this I am not certain.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>He hath out-villained villany so far, that the</line>
            <line>rarity redeems him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>A pox on him, he's a cat still.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Soldier</speaker>
            <line>His qualities being at this poor price, I need not</line>
            <line>to ask you if gold will corrupt him to revolt.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Sir, for a quart d'ecu he will sell the fee-simple</line>
            <line>of his salvation, the inheritance of it; and cut the</line>
            <line>entail from all remainders, and a perpetual</line>
            <line>succession for it perpetually.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Soldier</speaker>
            <line>What's his brother, the other Captain Dumain?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>Why does be ask him of me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Soldier</speaker>
            <line>What's he?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>E'en a crow o' the same nest; not altogether so</line>
            <line>great as the first in goodness, but greater a great</line>
            <line>deal in evil: he excels his brother for a coward,</line>
            <line>yet his brother is reputed one of the best that is:</line>
            <line>in a retreat he outruns any lackey; marry, in coming</line>
            <line>on he has the cramp.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Soldier</speaker>
            <line>If your life be saved, will you undertake to betray</line>
            <line>the Florentine?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Ay, and the captain of his horse, Count Rousillon.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Soldier</speaker>
            <line>I'll whisper with the general, and know his pleasure.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  I'll no more drumming; a plague of all</line>
            <line>drums! Only to seem to deserve well, and to</line>
            <line>beguile the supposition of that lascivious young boy</line>
            <line>the count, have I run into this danger. Yet who</line>
            <line>would have suspected an ambush where I was taken?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Soldier</speaker>
            <line>There is no remedy, sir, but you must die: the</line>
            <line>general says, you that have so traitorously</line>
            <line>discovered the secrets of your army and made such</line>
            <line>pestiferous reports of men very nobly held, can</line>
            <line>serve the world for no honest use; therefore you</line>
            <line>must die. Come, headsman, off with his head.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>O Lord, sir, let me live, or let me see my death!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>That shall you, and take your leave of all your friends.</line>
            <stagedir>Unblinding him</stagedir>
            <line>So, look about you: know you any here?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>Good morrow, noble captain.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>God bless you, Captain Parolles.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>God save you, noble captain.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>Captain, what greeting will you to my Lord Lafeu?</line>
            <line>I am for France.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>Good captain, will you give me a copy of the sonnet</line>
            <line>you writ to Diana in behalf of the Count Rousillon?</line>
            <line>an I were not a very coward, I'ld compel it of you:</line>
            <line>but fare you well.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt BERTRAM and Lords</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Soldier</speaker>
            <line>You are undone, captain, all but your scarf; that</line>
            <line>has a knot on't yet</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Who cannot be crushed with a plot?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Soldier</speaker>
            <line>If you could find out a country where but women were</line>
            <line>that had received so much shame, you might begin an</line>
            <line>impudent nation. Fare ye well, sir; I am for France</line>
            <line>too: we shall speak of you there.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit with Soldiers</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Yet am I thankful: if my heart were great,</line>
            <line>'Twould burst at this. Captain I'll be no more;</line>
            <line>But I will eat and drink, and sleep as soft</line>
            <line>As captain shall: simply the thing I am</line>
            <line>Shall make me live. Who knows himself a braggart,</line>
            <line>Let him fear this, for it will come to pass</line>
            <line>that every braggart shall be found an ass.</line>
            <line>Rust, sword? cool, blushes! and, Parolles, live</line>
            <line>Safest in shame! being fool'd, by foolery thrive!</line>
            <line>There's place and means for every man alive.</line>
            <line>I'll after them.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-4">
      <title>SCENE IV.  Florence. The Widow's house.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter HELENA, Widow, and DIANA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>That you may well perceive I have not wrong'd you,</line>
            <line>One of the greatest in the Christian world</line>
            <line>Shall be my surety; 'fore whose throne 'tis needful,</line>
            <line>Ere I can perfect mine intents, to kneel:</line>
            <line>Time was, I did him a desired office,</line>
            <line>Dear almost as his life; which gratitude</line>
            <line>Through flinty Tartar's bosom would peep forth,</line>
            <line>And answer, thanks: I duly am inform'd</line>
            <line>His grace is at Marseilles; to which place</line>
            <line>We have convenient convoy. You must know</line>
            <line>I am supposed dead: the army breaking,</line>
            <line>My husband hies him home; where, heaven aiding,</line>
            <line>And by the leave of my good lord the king,</line>
            <line>We'll be before our welcome.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Widow</speaker>
            <line>Gentle madam,</line>
            <line>You never had a servant to whose trust</line>
            <line>Your business was more welcome.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>Nor you, mistress,</line>
            <line>Ever a friend whose thoughts more truly labour</line>
            <line>To recompense your love: doubt not but heaven</line>
            <line>Hath brought me up to be your daughter's dower,</line>
            <line>As it hath fated her to be my motive</line>
            <line>And helper to a husband. But, O strange men!</line>
            <line>That can such sweet use make of what they hate,</line>
            <line>When saucy trusting of the cozen'd thoughts</line>
            <line>Defiles the pitchy night: so lust doth play</line>
            <line>With what it loathes for that which is away.</line>
            <line>But more of this hereafter. You, Diana,</line>
            <line>Under my poor instructions yet must suffer</line>
            <line>Something in my behalf.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DIANA</speaker>
            <line>Let death and honesty</line>
            <line>Go with your impositions, I am yours</line>
            <line>Upon your will to suffer.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>Yet, I pray you:</line>
            <line>But with the word the time will bring on summer,</line>
            <line>When briers shall have leaves as well as thorns,</line>
            <line>And be as sweet as sharp. We must away;</line>
            <line>Our wagon is prepared, and time revives us:</line>
            <line>All's well that ends well; still the fine's the crown;</line>
            <line>Whate'er the course, the end is the renown.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-5">
      <title>SCENE V.  Rousillon. The COUNT's palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter COUNTESS, LAFEU, and Clown</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>No, no, no, your son was misled with a snipt-taffeta</line>
            <line>fellow there, whose villanous saffron would have</line>
            <line>made all the unbaked and doughy youth of a nation in</line>
            <line>his colour: your daughter-in-law had been alive at</line>
            <line>this hour, and your son here at home, more advanced</line>
            <line>by the king than by that red-tailed humble-bee I speak of.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>I would I had not known him; it was the death of the</line>
            <line>most virtuous gentlewoman that ever nature had</line>
            <line>praise for creating. If she had partaken of my</line>
            <line>flesh, and cost me the dearest groans of a mother, I</line>
            <line>could not have owed her a more rooted love.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>'Twas a good lady, 'twas a good lady: we may pick a</line>
            <line>thousand salads ere we light on such another herb.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Indeed, sir, she was the sweet marjoram of the</line>
            <line>salad, or rather, the herb of grace.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>They are not herbs, you knave; they are nose-herbs.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>I am no great Nebuchadnezzar, sir; I have not much</line>
            <line>skill in grass.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>Whether dost thou profess thyself, a knave or a fool?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>A fool, sir, at a woman's service, and a knave at a man's.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>Your distinction?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>I would cozen the man of his wife and do his service.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>So you were a knave at his service, indeed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>And I would give his wife my bauble, sir, to do her service.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>I will subscribe for thee, thou art both knave and fool.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>At your service.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>No, no, no.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Why, sir, if I cannot serve you, I can serve as</line>
            <line>great a prince as you are.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>Who's that? a Frenchman?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Faith, sir, a' has an English name; but his fisnomy</line>
            <line>is more hotter in France than there.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>What prince is that?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>The black prince, sir; alias, the prince of</line>
            <line>darkness; alias, the devil.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>Hold thee, there's my purse: I give thee not this</line>
            <line>to suggest thee from thy master thou talkest of;</line>
            <line>serve him still.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>I am a woodland fellow, sir, that always loved a</line>
            <line>great fire; and the master I speak of ever keeps a</line>
            <line>good fire. But, sure, he is the prince of the</line>
            <line>world; let his nobility remain in's court. I am for</line>
            <line>the house with the narrow gate, which I take to be</line>
            <line>too little for pomp to enter: some that humble</line>
            <line>themselves may; but the many will be too chill and</line>
            <line>tender, and they'll be for the flowery way that</line>
            <line>leads to the broad gate and the great fire.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>Go thy ways, I begin to be aweary of thee; and I</line>
            <line>tell thee so before, because I would not fall out</line>
            <line>with thee. Go thy ways: let my horses be well</line>
            <line>looked to, without any tricks.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>If I put any tricks upon 'em, sir, they shall be</line>
            <line>jades' tricks; which are their own right by the law of nature.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>A shrewd knave and an unhappy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>So he is. My lord that's gone made himself much</line>
            <line>sport out of him: by his authority he remains here,</line>
            <line>which he thinks is a patent for his sauciness; and,</line>
            <line>indeed, he has no pace, but runs where he will.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>I like him well; 'tis not amiss. And I was about to</line>
            <line>tell you, since I heard of the good lady's death and</line>
            <line>that my lord your son was upon his return home, I</line>
            <line>moved the king my master to speak in the behalf of</line>
            <line>my daughter; which, in the minority of them both,</line>
            <line>his majesty, out of a self-gracious remembrance, did</line>
            <line>first propose: his highness hath promised me to do</line>
            <line>it: and, to stop up the displeasure he hath</line>
            <line>conceived against your son, there is no fitter</line>
            <line>matter. How does your ladyship like it?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>With very much content, my lord; and I wish it</line>
            <line>happily effected.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>His highness comes post from Marseilles, of as able</line>
            <line>body as when he numbered thirty: he will be here</line>
            <line>to-morrow, or I am deceived by him that in such</line>
            <line>intelligence hath seldom failed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>It rejoices me, that I hope I shall see him ere I</line>
            <line>die. I have letters that my son will be here</line>
            <line>to-night: I shall beseech your lordship to remain</line>
            <line>with me till they meet together.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>Madam, I was thinking with what manners I might</line>
            <line>safely be admitted.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>You need but plead your honourable privilege.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>Lady, of that I have made a bold charter; but I</line>
            <line>thank my God it holds yet.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter Clown</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>O madam, yonder's my lord your son with a patch of</line>
            <line>velvet on's face: whether there be a scar under't</line>
            <line>or no, the velvet knows; but 'tis a goodly patch of</line>
            <line>velvet: his left cheek is a cheek of two pile and a</line>
            <line>half, but his right cheek is worn bare.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>A scar nobly got, or a noble scar, is a good livery</line>
            <line>of honour; so belike is that.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>But it is your carbonadoed face.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>Let us go see your son, I pray you: I long to talk</line>
            <line>with the young noble soldier.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Faith there's a dozen of 'em, with delicate fine</line>
            <line>hats and most courteous feathers, which bow the head</line>
            <line>and nod at every man.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>