<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net/doctypes/dita/shakespear/dtd/act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-2">
   <title>ACT II</title>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  Paris. The KING's palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Flourish of cornets. Enter the KING, attended
with divers young Lords taking leave for the
Florentine war; BERTRAM, and PAROLLES</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>Farewell, young lords; these warlike principles</line>
            <line>Do not throw from you: and you, my lords, farewell:</line>
            <line>Share the advice betwixt you; if both gain, all</line>
            <line>The gift doth stretch itself as 'tis received,</line>
            <line>And is enough for both.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>'Tis our hope, sir,</line>
            <line>After well enter'd soldiers, to return</line>
            <line>And find your grace in health.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>No, no, it cannot be; and yet my heart</line>
            <line>Will not confess he owes the malady</line>
            <line>That doth my life besiege. Farewell, young lords;</line>
            <line>Whether I live or die, be you the sons</line>
            <line>Of worthy Frenchmen: let higher Italy,--</line>
            <line>Those bated that inherit but the fall</line>
            <line>Of the last monarchy,--see that you come</line>
            <line>Not to woo honour, but to wed it; when</line>
            <line>The bravest questant shrinks, find what you seek,</line>
            <line>That fame may cry you loud: I say, farewell.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>Health, at your bidding, serve your majesty!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>Those girls of Italy, take heed of them:</line>
            <line>They say, our French lack language to deny,</line>
            <line>If they demand: beware of being captives,</line>
            <line>Before you serve.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Both</speaker>
            <line>Our hearts receive your warnings.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>Farewell. Come hither to me.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit, attended</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>O, my sweet lord, that you will stay behind us!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>'Tis not his fault, the spark.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>O, 'tis brave wars!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Most admirable: I have seen those wars.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>I am commanded here, and kept a coil with</line>
            <line>'Too young' and 'the next year' and ''tis too early.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>An thy mind stand to't, boy, steal away bravely.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>I shall stay here the forehorse to a smock,</line>
            <line>Creaking my shoes on the plain masonry,</line>
            <line>Till honour be bought up and no sword worn</line>
            <line>But one to dance with! By heaven, I'll steal away.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>There's honour in the theft.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Commit it, count.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>I am your accessary; and so, farewell.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>I grow to you, and our parting is a tortured body.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>Farewell, captain.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>Sweet Monsieur Parolles!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Noble heroes, my sword and yours are kin. Good</line>
            <line>sparks and lustrous, a word, good metals: you shall</line>
            <line>find in the regiment of the Spinii one Captain</line>
            <line>Spurio, with his cicatrice, an emblem of war, here</line>
            <line>on his sinister cheek; it was this very sword</line>
            <line>entrenched it: say to him, I live; and observe his</line>
            <line>reports for me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>We shall, noble captain.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt Lords</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Mars dote on you for his novices! what will ye do?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>Stay: the king.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter KING. BERTRAM and PAROLLES retire</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>To BERTRAM</stagedir>  Use a more spacious ceremony to the</line>
            <line>noble lords; you have restrained yourself within the</line>
            <line>list of too cold an adieu: be more expressive to</line>
            <line>them: for they wear themselves in the cap of the</line>
            <line>time, there do muster true gait, eat, speak, and</line>
            <line>move under the influence of the most received star;</line>
            <line>and though the devil lead the measure, such are to</line>
            <line>be followed: after them, and take a more dilated farewell.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>And I will do so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Worthy fellows; and like to prove most sinewy sword-men.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt BERTRAM and PAROLLES</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Enter LAFEU</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Kneeling</stagedir>  Pardon, my lord, for me and for my tidings.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>I'll fee thee to stand up.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>Then here's a man stands, that has brought his pardon.</line>
            <line>I would you had kneel'd, my lord, to ask me mercy,</line>
            <line>And that at my bidding you could so stand up.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>I would I had; so I had broke thy pate,</line>
            <line>And ask'd thee mercy for't.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>Good faith, across: but, my good lord 'tis thus;</line>
            <line>Will you be cured of your infirmity?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>No.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>O, will you eat no grapes, my royal fox?</line>
            <line>Yes, but you will my noble grapes, an if</line>
            <line>My royal fox could reach them: I have seen a medicine</line>
            <line>That's able to breathe life into a stone,</line>
            <line>Quicken a rock, and make you dance canary</line>
            <line>With spritely fire and motion; whose simple touch,</line>
            <line>Is powerful to araise King Pepin, nay,</line>
            <line>To give great Charlemain a pen in's hand,</line>
            <line>And write to her a love-line.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>What 'her' is this?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>Why, Doctor She: my lord, there's one arrived,</line>
            <line>If you will see her: now, by my faith and honour,</line>
            <line>If seriously I may convey my thoughts</line>
            <line>In this my light deliverance, I have spoke</line>
            <line>With one that, in her sex, her years, profession,</line>
            <line>Wisdom and constancy, hath amazed me more</line>
            <line>Than I dare blame my weakness: will you see her</line>
            <line>For that is her demand, and know her business?</line>
            <line>That done, laugh well at me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>Now, good Lafeu,</line>
            <line>Bring in the admiration; that we with thee</line>
            <line>May spend our wonder too, or take off thine</line>
            <line>By wondering how thou took'st it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>Nay, I'll fit you,</line>
            <line>And not be all day neither.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>Thus he his special nothing ever prologues.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter LAFEU, with HELENA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>Nay, come your ways.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>This haste hath wings indeed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>Nay, come your ways:</line>
            <line>This is his majesty; say your mind to him:</line>
            <line>A traitor you do look like; but such traitors</line>
            <line>His majesty seldom fears: I am Cressid's uncle,</line>
            <line>That dare leave two together; fare you well.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>Now, fair one, does your business follow us?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>Ay, my good lord.</line>
            <line>Gerard de Narbon was my father;</line>
            <line>In what he did profess, well found.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>I knew him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>The rather will I spare my praises towards him:</line>
            <line>Knowing him is enough. On's bed of death</line>
            <line>Many receipts he gave me: chiefly one.</line>
            <line>Which, as the dearest issue of his practise,</line>
            <line>And of his old experience the oily darling,</line>
            <line>He bade me store up, as a triple eye,</line>
            <line>Safer than mine own two, more dear; I have so;</line>
            <line>And hearing your high majesty is touch'd</line>
            <line>With that malignant cause wherein the honour</line>
            <line>Of my dear father's gift stands chief in power,</line>
            <line>I come to tender it and my appliance</line>
            <line>With all bound humbleness.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>We thank you, maiden;</line>
            <line>But may not be so credulous of cure,</line>
            <line>When our most learned doctors leave us and</line>
            <line>The congregated college have concluded</line>
            <line>That labouring art can never ransom nature</line>
            <line>From her inaidible estate; I say we must not</line>
            <line>So stain our judgment, or corrupt our hope,</line>
            <line>To prostitute our past-cure malady</line>
            <line>To empirics, or to dissever so</line>
            <line>Our great self and our credit, to esteem</line>
            <line>A senseless help when help past sense we deem.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>My duty then shall pay me for my pains:</line>
            <line>I will no more enforce mine office on you.</line>
            <line>Humbly entreating from your royal thoughts</line>
            <line>A modest one, to bear me back a again.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>I cannot give thee less, to be call'd grateful:</line>
            <line>Thou thought'st to help me; and such thanks I give</line>
            <line>As one near death to those that wish him live:</line>
            <line>But what at full I know, thou know'st no part,</line>
            <line>I knowing all my peril, thou no art.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>What I can do can do no hurt to try,</line>
            <line>Since you set up your rest 'gainst remedy.</line>
            <line>He that of greatest works is finisher</line>
            <line>Oft does them by the weakest minister:</line>
            <line>So holy writ in babes hath judgment shown,</line>
            <line>When judges have been babes; great floods have flown</line>
            <line>From simple sources, and great seas have dried</line>
            <line>When miracles have by the greatest been denied.</line>
            <line>Oft expectation fails and most oft there</line>
            <line>Where most it promises, and oft it hits</line>
            <line>Where hope is coldest and despair most fits.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>I must not hear thee; fare thee well, kind maid;</line>
            <line>Thy pains not used must by thyself be paid:</line>
            <line>Proffers not took reap thanks for their reward.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>Inspired merit so by breath is barr'd:</line>
            <line>It is not so with Him that all things knows</line>
            <line>As 'tis with us that square our guess by shows;</line>
            <line>But most it is presumption in us when</line>
            <line>The help of heaven we count the act of men.</line>
            <line>Dear sir, to my endeavours give consent;</line>
            <line>Of heaven, not me, make an experiment.</line>
            <line>I am not an impostor that proclaim</line>
            <line>Myself against the level of mine aim;</line>
            <line>But know I think and think I know most sure</line>
            <line>My art is not past power nor you past cure.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>Are thou so confident? within what space</line>
            <line>Hopest thou my cure?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>The great'st grace lending grace</line>
            <line>Ere twice the horses of the sun shall bring</line>
            <line>Their fiery torcher his diurnal ring,</line>
            <line>Ere twice in murk and occidental damp</line>
            <line>Moist Hesperus hath quench'd his sleepy lamp,</line>
            <line>Or four and twenty times the pilot's glass</line>
            <line>Hath told the thievish minutes how they pass,</line>
            <line>What is infirm from your sound parts shall fly,</line>
            <line>Health shall live free and sickness freely die.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>Upon thy certainty and confidence</line>
            <line>What darest thou venture?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>Tax of impudence,</line>
            <line>A strumpet's boldness, a divulged shame</line>
            <line>Traduced by odious ballads: my maiden's name</line>
            <line>Sear'd otherwise; nay, worse--if worse--extended</line>
            <line>With vilest torture let my life be ended.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>Methinks in thee some blessed spirit doth speak</line>
            <line>His powerful sound within an organ weak:</line>
            <line>And what impossibility would slay</line>
            <line>In common sense, sense saves another way.</line>
            <line>Thy life is dear; for all that life can rate</line>
            <line>Worth name of life in thee hath estimate,</line>
            <line>Youth, beauty, wisdom, courage, all</line>
            <line>That happiness and prime can happy call:</line>
            <line>Thou this to hazard needs must intimate</line>
            <line>Skill infinite or monstrous desperate.</line>
            <line>Sweet practiser, thy physic I will try,</line>
            <line>That ministers thine own death if I die.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>If I break time, or flinch in property</line>
            <line>Of what I spoke, unpitied let me die,</line>
            <line>And well deserved: not helping, death's my fee;</line>
            <line>But, if I help, what do you promise me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>Make thy demand.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>But will you make it even?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>Ay, by my sceptre and my hopes of heaven.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>Then shalt thou give me with thy kingly hand</line>
            <line>What husband in thy power I will command:</line>
            <line>Exempted be from me the arrogance</line>
            <line>To choose from forth the royal blood of France,</line>
            <line>My low and humble name to propagate</line>
            <line>With any branch or image of thy state;</line>
            <line>But such a one, thy vassal, whom I know</line>
            <line>Is free for me to ask, thee to bestow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>Here is my hand; the premises observed,</line>
            <line>Thy will by my performance shall be served:</line>
            <line>So make the choice of thy own time, for I,</line>
            <line>Thy resolved patient, on thee still rely.</line>
            <line>More should I question thee, and more I must,</line>
            <line>Though more to know could not be more to trust,</line>
            <line>From whence thou camest, how tended on: but rest</line>
            <line>Unquestion'd welcome and undoubted blest.</line>
            <line>Give me some help here, ho! If thou proceed</line>
            <line>As high as word, my deed shall match thy meed.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Flourish. Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  Rousillon. The COUNT's palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter COUNTESS and Clown</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>Come on, sir; I shall now put you to the height of</line>
            <line>your breeding.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>I will show myself highly fed and lowly taught: I</line>
            <line>know my business is but to the court.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>To the court! why, what place make you special,</line>
            <line>when you put off that with such contempt? But to the court!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Truly, madam, if God have lent a man any manners, he</line>
            <line>may easily put it off at court: he that cannot make</line>
            <line>a leg, put off's cap, kiss his hand and say nothing,</line>
            <line>has neither leg, hands, lip, nor cap; and indeed</line>
            <line>such a fellow, to say precisely, were not for the</line>
            <line>court; but for me, I have an answer will serve all</line>
            <line>men.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>Marry, that's a bountiful answer that fits all</line>
            <line>questions.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>It is like a barber's chair that fits all buttocks,</line>
            <line>the pin-buttock, the quatch-buttock, the brawn</line>
            <line>buttock, or any buttock.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>Will your answer serve fit to all questions?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>As fit as ten groats is for the hand of an attorney,</line>
            <line>as your French crown for your taffeta punk, as Tib's</line>
            <line>rush for Tom's forefinger, as a pancake for Shrove</line>
            <line>Tuesday, a morris for May-day, as the nail to his</line>
            <line>hole, the cuckold to his horn, as a scolding queen</line>
            <line>to a wrangling knave, as the nun's lip to the</line>
            <line>friar's mouth, nay, as the pudding to his skin.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>Have you, I say, an answer of such fitness for all</line>
            <line>questions?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>From below your duke to beneath your constable, it</line>
            <line>will fit any question.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>It must be an answer of most monstrous size that</line>
            <line>must fit all demands.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>But a trifle neither, in good faith, if the learned</line>
            <line>should speak truth of it: here it is, and all that</line>
            <line>belongs to't. Ask me if I am a courtier: it shall</line>
            <line>do you no harm to learn.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>To be young again, if we could: I will be a fool in</line>
            <line>question, hoping to be the wiser by your answer. I</line>
            <line>pray you, sir, are you a courtier?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>O Lord, sir! There's a simple putting off. More,</line>
            <line>more, a hundred of them.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>Sir, I am a poor friend of yours, that loves you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>O Lord, sir! Thick, thick, spare not me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>I think, sir, you can eat none of this homely meat.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>O Lord, sir! Nay, put me to't, I warrant you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>You were lately whipped, sir, as I think.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>O Lord, sir! spare not me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>Do you cry, 'O Lord, sir!' at your whipping, and</line>
            <line>'spare not me?' Indeed your 'O Lord, sir!' is very</line>
            <line>sequent to your whipping: you would answer very well</line>
            <line>to a whipping, if you were but bound to't.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>I ne'er had worse luck in my life in my 'O Lord,</line>
            <line>sir!' I see things may serve long, but not serve ever.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>I play the noble housewife with the time</line>
            <line>To entertain't so merrily with a fool.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>O Lord, sir! why, there't serves well again.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>An end, sir; to your business. Give Helen this,</line>
            <line>And urge her to a present answer back:</line>
            <line>Commend me to my kinsmen and my son:</line>
            <line>This is not much.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Not much commendation to them.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>Not much employment for you: you understand me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Most fruitfully: I am there before my legs.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>Haste you again.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt severally</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  Paris. The KING's palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter BERTRAM, LAFEU, and PAROLLES</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>They say miracles are past; and we have our</line>
            <line>philosophical persons, to make modern and familiar,</line>
            <line>things supernatural and causeless. Hence is it that</line>
            <line>we make trifles of terrors, ensconcing ourselves</line>
            <line>into seeming knowledge, when we should submit</line>
            <line>ourselves to an unknown fear.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Why, 'tis the rarest argument of wonder that hath</line>
            <line>shot out in our latter times.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>And so 'tis.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>To be relinquish'd of the artists,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>So I say.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>Both of Galen and Paracelsus.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>So I say.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>Of all the learned and authentic fellows,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Right; so I say.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>That gave him out incurable,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Why, there 'tis; so say I too.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>Not to be helped,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Right; as 'twere, a man assured of a--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>Uncertain life, and sure death.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Just, you say well; so would I have said.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>I may truly say, it is a novelty to the world.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>It is, indeed: if you will have it in showing, you</line>
            <line>shall read it in--what do you call there?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>A showing of a heavenly effect in an earthly actor.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>That's it; I would have said the very same.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>Why, your dolphin is not lustier: 'fore me,</line>
            <line>I speak in respect--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Nay, 'tis strange, 'tis very strange, that is the</line>
            <line>brief and the tedious of it; and he's of a most</line>
            <line>facinerious spirit that will not acknowledge it to be the--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>Very hand of heaven.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Ay, so I say.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>In a most weak--</line>
            <stagedir>pausing</stagedir>
            <line>and debile minister, great power, great</line>
            <line>transcendence: which should, indeed, give us a</line>
            <line>further use to be made than alone the recovery of</line>
            <line>the king, as to be--</line>
            <stagedir>pausing</stagedir>
            <line>generally thankful.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>I would have said it; you say well. Here comes the king.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter KING, HELENA, and Attendants. LAFEU and
PAROLLES retire</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>Lustig, as the Dutchman says: I'll like a maid the</line>
            <line>better, whilst I have a tooth in my head: why, he's</line>
            <line>able to lead her a coranto.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Mort du vinaigre! is not this Helen?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>'Fore God, I think so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>Go, call before me all the lords in court.</line>
            <line>Sit, my preserver, by thy patient's side;</line>
            <line>And with this healthful hand, whose banish'd sense</line>
            <line>Thou hast repeal'd, a second time receive</line>
            <line>The confirmation of my promised gift,</line>
            <line>Which but attends thy naming.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter three or four Lords</stagedir>
            <line>Fair maid, send forth thine eye: this youthful parcel</line>
            <line>Of noble bachelors stand at my bestowing,</line>
            <line>O'er whom both sovereign power and father's voice</line>
            <line>I have to use: thy frank election make;</line>
            <line>Thou hast power to choose, and they none to forsake.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>To each of you one fair and virtuous mistress</line>
            <line>Fall, when Love please! marry, to each, but one!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>I'ld give bay Curtal and his furniture,</line>
            <line>My mouth no more were broken than these boys',</line>
            <line>And writ as little beard.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>Peruse them well:</line>
            <line>Not one of those but had a noble father.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>Gentlemen,</line>
            <line>Heaven hath through me restored the king to health.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>All</speaker>
            <line>We understand it, and thank heaven for you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>I am a simple maid, and therein wealthiest,</line>
            <line>That I protest I simply am a maid.</line>
            <line>Please it your majesty, I have done already:</line>
            <line>The blushes in my cheeks thus whisper me,</line>
            <line>'We blush that thou shouldst choose; but, be refused,</line>
            <line>Let the white death sit on thy cheek for ever;</line>
            <line>We'll ne'er come there again.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>Make choice; and, see,</line>
            <line>Who shuns thy love shuns all his love in me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>Now, Dian, from thy altar do I fly,</line>
            <line>And to imperial Love, that god most high,</line>
            <line>Do my sighs stream. Sir, will you hear my suit?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>And grant it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>Thanks, sir; all the rest is mute.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>I had rather be in this choice than throw ames-ace</line>
            <line>for my life.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>The honour, sir, that flames in your fair eyes,</line>
            <line>Before I speak, too threateningly replies:</line>
            <line>Love make your fortunes twenty times above</line>
            <line>Her that so wishes and her humble love!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>No better, if you please.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>My wish receive,</line>
            <line>Which great Love grant! and so, I take my leave.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>Do all they deny her? An they were sons of mine,</line>
            <line>I'd have them whipped; or I would send them to the</line>
            <line>Turk, to make eunuchs of.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>Be not afraid that I your hand should take;</line>
            <line>I'll never do you wrong for your own sake:</line>
            <line>Blessing upon your vows! and in your bed</line>
            <line>Find fairer fortune, if you ever wed!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>These boys are boys of ice, they'll none have her:</line>
            <line>sure, they are bastards to the English; the French</line>
            <line>ne'er got 'em.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>You are too young, too happy, and too good,</line>
            <line>To make yourself a son out of my blood.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Fourth Lord</speaker>
            <line>Fair one, I think not so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>There's one grape yet; I am sure thy father drunk</line>
            <line>wine: but if thou be'st not an ass, I am a youth</line>
            <line>of fourteen; I have known thee already.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>To BERTRAM</stagedir>  I dare not say I take you; but I give</line>
            <line>Me and my service, ever whilst I live,</line>
            <line>Into your guiding power. This is the man.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>Why, then, young Bertram, take her; she's thy wife.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>My wife, my liege! I shall beseech your highness,</line>
            <line>In such a business give me leave to use</line>
            <line>The help of mine own eyes.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>Know'st thou not, Bertram,</line>
            <line>What she has done for me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>Yes, my good lord;</line>
            <line>But never hope to know why I should marry her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>Thou know'st she has raised me from my sickly bed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>But follows it, my lord, to bring me down</line>
            <line>Must answer for your raising? I know her well:</line>
            <line>She had her breeding at my father's charge.</line>
            <line>A poor physician's daughter my wife! Disdain</line>
            <line>Rather corrupt me ever!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>'Tis only title thou disdain'st in her, the which</line>
            <line>I can build up. Strange is it that our bloods,</line>
            <line>Of colour, weight, and heat, pour'd all together,</line>
            <line>Would quite confound distinction, yet stand off</line>
            <line>In differences so mighty. If she be</line>
            <line>All that is virtuous, save what thou dislikest,</line>
            <line>A poor physician's daughter, thou dislikest</line>
            <line>Of virtue for the name: but do not so:</line>
            <line>From lowest place when virtuous things proceed,</line>
            <line>The place is dignified by the doer's deed:</line>
            <line>Where great additions swell's, and virtue none,</line>
            <line>It is a dropsied honour. Good alone</line>
            <line>Is good without a name. Vileness is so:</line>
            <line>The property by what it is should go,</line>
            <line>Not by the title. She is young, wise, fair;</line>
            <line>In these to nature she's immediate heir,</line>
            <line>And these breed honour: that is honour's scorn,</line>
            <line>Which challenges itself as honour's born</line>
            <line>And is not like the sire: honours thrive,</line>
            <line>When rather from our acts we them derive</line>
            <line>Than our foregoers: the mere word's a slave</line>
            <line>Debosh'd on every tomb, on every grave</line>
            <line>A lying trophy, and as oft is dumb</line>
            <line>Where dust and damn'd oblivion is the tomb</line>
            <line>Of honour'd bones indeed. What should be said?</line>
            <line>If thou canst like this creature as a maid,</line>
            <line>I can create the rest: virtue and she</line>
            <line>Is her own dower; honour and wealth from me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>I cannot love her, nor will strive to do't.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>Thou wrong'st thyself, if thou shouldst strive to choose.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>That you are well restored, my lord, I'm glad:</line>
            <line>Let the rest go.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>My honour's at the stake; which to defeat,</line>
            <line>I must produce my power. Here, take her hand,</line>
            <line>Proud scornful boy, unworthy this good gift;</line>
            <line>That dost in vile misprision shackle up</line>
            <line>My love and her desert; that canst not dream,</line>
            <line>We, poising us in her defective scale,</line>
            <line>Shall weigh thee to the beam; that wilt not know,</line>
            <line>It is in us to plant thine honour where</line>
            <line>We please to have it grow. Cheque thy contempt:</line>
            <line>Obey our will, which travails in thy good:</line>
            <line>Believe not thy disdain, but presently</line>
            <line>Do thine own fortunes that obedient right</line>
            <line>Which both thy duty owes and our power claims;</line>
            <line>Or I will throw thee from my care for ever</line>
            <line>Into the staggers and the careless lapse</line>
            <line>Of youth and ignorance; both my revenge and hate</line>
            <line>Loosing upon thee, in the name of justice,</line>
            <line>Without all terms of pity. Speak; thine answer.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>Pardon, my gracious lord; for I submit</line>
            <line>My fancy to your eyes: when I consider</line>
            <line>What great creation and what dole of honour</line>
            <line>Flies where you bid it, I find that she, which late</line>
            <line>Was in my nobler thoughts most base, is now</line>
            <line>The praised of the king; who, so ennobled,</line>
            <line>Is as 'twere born so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>Take her by the hand,</line>
            <line>And tell her she is thine: to whom I promise</line>
            <line>A counterpoise, if not to thy estate</line>
            <line>A balance more replete.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>I take her hand.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>Good fortune and the favour of the king</line>
            <line>Smile upon this contract; whose ceremony</line>
            <line>Shall seem expedient on the now-born brief,</line>
            <line>And be perform'd to-night: the solemn feast</line>
            <line>Shall more attend upon the coming space,</line>
            <line>Expecting absent friends. As thou lovest her,</line>
            <line>Thy love's to me religious; else, does err.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt all but LAFEU and PAROLLES</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Advancing</stagedir>  Do you hear, monsieur? a word with you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Your pleasure, sir?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>Your lord and master did well to make his</line>
            <line>recantation.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Recantation! My lord! my master!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>Ay; is it not a language I speak?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>A most harsh one, and not to be understood without</line>
            <line>bloody succeeding. My master!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>Are you companion to the Count Rousillon?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>To any count, to all counts, to what is man.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>To what is count's man: count's master is of</line>
            <line>another style.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>You are too old, sir; let it satisfy you, you are too old.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>I must tell thee, sirrah, I write man; to which</line>
            <line>title age cannot bring thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>What I dare too well do, I dare not do.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>I did think thee, for two ordinaries, to be a pretty</line>
            <line>wise fellow; thou didst make tolerable vent of thy</line>
            <line>travel; it might pass: yet the scarfs and the</line>
            <line>bannerets about thee did manifoldly dissuade me from</line>
            <line>believing thee a vessel of too great a burthen. I</line>
            <line>have now found thee; when I lose thee again, I care</line>
            <line>not: yet art thou good for nothing but taking up; and</line>
            <line>that thou't scarce worth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Hadst thou not the privilege of antiquity upon thee,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>Do not plunge thyself too far in anger, lest thou</line>
            <line>hasten thy trial; which if--Lord have mercy on thee</line>
            <line>for a hen! So, my good window of lattice, fare thee</line>
            <line>well: thy casement I need not open, for I look</line>
            <line>through thee. Give me thy hand.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>My lord, you give me most egregious indignity.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>Ay, with all my heart; and thou art worthy of it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>I have not, my lord, deserved it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>Yes, good faith, every dram of it; and I will not</line>
            <line>bate thee a scruple.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Well, I shall be wiser.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>Even as soon as thou canst, for thou hast to pull at</line>
            <line>a smack o' the contrary. If ever thou be'st bound</line>
            <line>in thy scarf and beaten, thou shalt find what it is</line>
            <line>to be proud of thy bondage. I have a desire to hold</line>
            <line>my acquaintance with thee, or rather my knowledge,</line>
            <line>that I may say in the default, he is a man I know.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>My lord, you do me most insupportable vexation.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>I would it were hell-pains for thy sake, and my poor</line>
            <line>doing eternal: for doing I am past: as I will by</line>
            <line>thee, in what motion age will give me leave.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Well, thou hast a son shall take this disgrace off</line>
            <line>me; scurvy, old, filthy, scurvy lord! Well, I must</line>
            <line>be patient; there is no fettering of authority.</line>
            <line>I'll beat him, by my life, if I can meet him with</line>
            <line>any convenience, an he were double and double a</line>
            <line>lord. I'll have no more pity of his age than I</line>
            <line>would of--I'll beat him, an if I could but meet him again.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter LAFEU</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>Sirrah, your lord and master's married; there's news</line>
            <line>for you: you have a new mistress.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>I most unfeignedly beseech your lordship to make</line>
            <line>some reservation of your wrongs: he is my good</line>
            <line>lord: whom I serve above is my master.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>Who? God?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Ay, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>The devil it is that's thy master. Why dost thou</line>
            <line>garter up thy arms o' this fashion? dost make hose of</line>
            <line>sleeves? do other servants so? Thou wert best set</line>
            <line>thy lower part where thy nose stands. By mine</line>
            <line>honour, if I were but two hours younger, I'ld beat</line>
            <line>thee: methinks, thou art a general offence, and</line>
            <line>every man should beat thee: I think thou wast</line>
            <line>created for men to breathe themselves upon thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>This is hard and undeserved measure, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>Go to, sir; you were beaten in Italy for picking a</line>
            <line>kernel out of a pomegranate; you are a vagabond and</line>
            <line>no true traveller: you are more saucy with lords</line>
            <line>and honourable personages than the commission of your</line>
            <line>birth and virtue gives you heraldry. You are not</line>
            <line>worth another word, else I'ld call you knave. I leave you.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Good, very good; it is so then: good, very good;</line>
            <line>let it be concealed awhile.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter BERTRAM</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>Undone, and forfeited to cares for ever!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>What's the matter, sweet-heart?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>Although before the solemn priest I have sworn,</line>
            <line>I will not bed her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>What, what, sweet-heart?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>O my Parolles, they have married me!</line>
            <line>I'll to the Tuscan wars, and never bed her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>France is a dog-hole, and it no more merits</line>
            <line>The tread of a man's foot: to the wars!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>There's letters from my mother: what the import is,</line>
            <line>I know not yet.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Ay, that would be known. To the wars, my boy, to the wars!</line>
            <line>He wears his honour in a box unseen,</line>
            <line>That hugs his kicky-wicky here at home,</line>
            <line>Spending his manly marrow in her arms,</line>
            <line>Which should sustain the bound and high curvet</line>
            <line>Of Mars's fiery steed. To other regions</line>
            <line>France is a stable; we that dwell in't jades;</line>
            <line>Therefore, to the war!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>It shall be so: I'll send her to my house,</line>
            <line>Acquaint my mother with my hate to her,</line>
            <line>And wherefore I am fled; write to the king</line>
            <line>That which I durst not speak; his present gift</line>
            <line>Shall furnish me to those Italian fields,</line>
            <line>Where noble fellows strike: war is no strife</line>
            <line>To the dark house and the detested wife.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Will this capriccio hold in thee? art sure?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>Go with me to my chamber, and advise me.</line>
            <line>I'll send her straight away: to-morrow</line>
            <line>I'll to the wars, she to her single sorrow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Why, these balls bound; there's noise in it. 'Tis hard:</line>
            <line>A young man married is a man that's marr'd:</line>
            <line>Therefore away, and leave her bravely; go:</line>
            <line>The king has done you wrong: but, hush, 'tis so.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-4">
      <title>SCENE IV.  Paris. The KING's palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter HELENA and Clown</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>My mother greets me kindly; is she well?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>She is not well; but yet she has her health: she's</line>
            <line>very merry; but yet she is not well: but thanks be</line>
            <line>given, she's very well and wants nothing i', the</line>
            <line>world; but yet she is not well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>If she be very well, what does she ail, that she's</line>
            <line>not very well?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Truly, she's very well indeed, but for two things.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>What two things?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>One, that she's not in heaven, whither God send her</line>
            <line>quickly! the other that she's in earth, from whence</line>
            <line>God send her quickly!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter PAROLLES</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Bless you, my fortunate lady!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>I hope, sir, I have your good will to have mine own</line>
            <line>good fortunes.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>You had my prayers to lead them on; and to keep them</line>
            <line>on, have them still. O, my knave, how does my old lady?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>So that you had her wrinkles and I her money,</line>
            <line>I would she did as you say.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Why, I say nothing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Marry, you are the wiser man; for many a man's</line>
            <line>tongue shakes out his master's undoing: to say</line>
            <line>nothing, to do nothing, to know nothing, and to have</line>
            <line>nothing, is to be a great part of your title; which</line>
            <line>is within a very little of nothing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Away! thou'rt a knave.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>You should have said, sir, before a knave thou'rt a</line>
            <line>knave; that's, before me thou'rt a knave: this had</line>
            <line>been truth, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Go to, thou art a witty fool; I have found thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Did you find me in yourself, sir? or were you</line>
            <line>taught to find me? The search, sir, was profitable;</line>
            <line>and much fool may you find in you, even to the</line>
            <line>world's pleasure and the increase of laughter.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>A good knave, i' faith, and well fed.</line>
            <line>Madam, my lord will go away to-night;</line>
            <line>A very serious business calls on him.</line>
            <line>The great prerogative and rite of love,</line>
            <line>Which, as your due, time claims, he does acknowledge;</line>
            <line>But puts it off to a compell'd restraint;</line>
            <line>Whose want, and whose delay, is strew'd with sweets,</line>
            <line>Which they distil now in the curbed time,</line>
            <line>To make the coming hour o'erflow with joy</line>
            <line>And pleasure drown the brim.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>What's his will else?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>That you will take your instant leave o' the king</line>
            <line>And make this haste as your own good proceeding,</line>
            <line>Strengthen'd with what apology you think</line>
            <line>May make it probable need.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>What more commands he?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>That, having this obtain'd, you presently</line>
            <line>Attend his further pleasure.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>In every thing I wait upon his will.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>I shall report it so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>I pray you.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit PAROLLES</stagedir>
            <line>Come, sirrah.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-5">
      <title>SCENE V.  Paris. The KING's palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter LAFEU and BERTRAM</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>But I hope your lordship thinks not him a soldier.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>Yes, my lord, and of very valiant approof.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>You have it from his own deliverance.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>And by other warranted testimony.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>Then my dial goes not true: I took this lark for a bunting.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>I do assure you, my lord, he is very great in</line>
            <line>knowledge and accordingly valiant.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>I have then sinned against his experience and</line>
            <line>transgressed against his valour; and my state that</line>
            <line>way is dangerous, since I cannot yet find in my</line>
            <line>heart to repent. Here he comes: I pray you, make</line>
            <line>us friends; I will pursue the amity.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter PAROLLES</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>To BERTRAM</stagedir>  These things shall be done, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>Pray you, sir, who's his tailor?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Sir?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>O, I know him well, I, sir; he, sir, 's a good</line>
            <line>workman, a very good tailor.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside to PAROLLES</stagedir>  Is she gone to the king?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>She is.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>Will she away to-night?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>As you'll have her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>I have writ my letters, casketed my treasure,</line>
            <line>Given order for our horses; and to-night,</line>
            <line>When I should take possession of the bride,</line>
            <line>End ere I do begin.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>A good traveller is something at the latter end of a</line>
            <line>dinner; but one that lies three thirds and uses a</line>
            <line>known truth to pass a thousand nothings with, should</line>
            <line>be once heard and thrice beaten. God save you, captain.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>Is there any unkindness between my lord and you, monsieur?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>I know not how I have deserved to run into my lord's</line>
            <line>displeasure.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>You have made shift to run into 't, boots and spurs</line>
            <line>and all, like him that leaped into the custard; and</line>
            <line>out of it you'll run again, rather than suffer</line>
            <line>question for your residence.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>It may be you have mistaken him, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>And shall do so ever, though I took him at 's</line>
            <line>prayers. Fare you well, my lord; and believe this</line>
            <line>of me, there can be no kernel in this light nut; the</line>
            <line>soul of this man is his clothes. Trust him not in</line>
            <line>matter of heavy consequence; I have kept of them</line>
            <line>tame, and know their natures. Farewell, monsieur:</line>
            <line>I have spoken better of you than you have or will to</line>
            <line>deserve at my hand; but we must do good against evil.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>An idle lord. I swear.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>I think so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Why, do you not know him?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>Yes, I do know him well, and common speech</line>
            <line>Gives him a worthy pass. Here comes my clog.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter HELENA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>I have, sir, as I was commanded from you,</line>
            <line>Spoke with the king and have procured his leave</line>
            <line>For present parting; only he desires</line>
            <line>Some private speech with you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>I shall obey his will.</line>
            <line>You must not marvel, Helen, at my course,</line>
            <line>Which holds not colour with the time, nor does</line>
            <line>The ministration and required office</line>
            <line>On my particular. Prepared I was not</line>
            <line>For such a business; therefore am I found</line>
            <line>So much unsettled: this drives me to entreat you</line>
            <line>That presently you take our way for home;</line>
            <line>And rather muse than ask why I entreat you,</line>
            <line>For my respects are better than they seem</line>
            <line>And my appointments have in them a need</line>
            <line>Greater than shows itself at the first view</line>
            <line>To you that know them not. This to my mother:</line>
            <stagedir>Giving a letter</stagedir>
            <line>'Twill be two days ere I shall see you, so</line>
            <line>I leave you to your wisdom.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>Sir, I can nothing say,</line>
            <line>But that I am your most obedient servant.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>Come, come, no more of that.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>And ever shall</line>
            <line>With true observance seek to eke out that</line>
            <line>Wherein toward me my homely stars have fail'd</line>
            <line>To equal my great fortune.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>Let that go:</line>
            <line>My haste is very great: farewell; hie home.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>Pray, sir, your pardon.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>Well, what would you say?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>I am not worthy of the wealth I owe,</line>
            <line>Nor dare I say 'tis mine, and yet it is;</line>
            <line>But, like a timorous thief, most fain would steal</line>
            <line>What law does vouch mine own.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>What would you have?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>Something; and scarce so much: nothing, indeed.</line>
            <line>I would not tell you what I would, my lord:</line>
            <line>Faith yes;</line>
            <line>Strangers and foes do sunder, and not kiss.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>I pray you, stay not, but in haste to horse.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>I shall not break your bidding, good my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>Where are my other men, monsieur? Farewell.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit HELENA</stagedir>
            <line>Go thou toward home; where I will never come</line>
            <line>Whilst I can shake my sword or hear the drum.</line>
            <line>Away, and for our flight.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Bravely, coragio!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>