<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:shakespear:dtd:act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-3">
   <title>ACT III</title>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  Florence. The DUKE's palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Flourish. Enter the DUKE of Florence attended;
the two Frenchmen, with a troop of soldiers.</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE</speaker>
            <line>So that from point to point now have you heard</line>
            <line>The fundamental reasons of this war,</line>
            <line>Whose great decision hath much blood let forth</line>
            <line>And more thirsts after.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>Holy seems the quarrel</line>
            <line>Upon your grace's part; black and fearful</line>
            <line>On the opposer.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE</speaker>
            <line>Therefore we marvel much our cousin France</line>
            <line>Would in so just a business shut his bosom</line>
            <line>Against our borrowing prayers.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>Good my lord,</line>
            <line>The reasons of our state I cannot yield,</line>
            <line>But like a common and an outward man,</line>
            <line>That the great figure of a council frames</line>
            <line>By self-unable motion: therefore dare not</line>
            <line>Say what I think of it, since I have found</line>
            <line>Myself in my incertain grounds to fail</line>
            <line>As often as I guess'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE</speaker>
            <line>Be it his pleasure.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>But I am sure the younger of our nature,</line>
            <line>That surfeit on their ease, will day by day</line>
            <line>Come here for physic.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE</speaker>
            <line>Welcome shall they be;</line>
            <line>And all the honours that can fly from us</line>
            <line>Shall on them settle. You know your places well;</line>
            <line>When better fall, for your avails they fell:</line>
            <line>To-morrow to the field.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Flourish. Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  Rousillon. The COUNT's palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter COUNTESS and Clown</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>It hath happened all as I would have had it, save</line>
            <line>that he comes not along with her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>By my troth, I take my young lord to be a very</line>
            <line>melancholy man.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>By what observance, I pray you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Why, he will look upon his boot and sing; mend the</line>
            <line>ruff and sing; ask questions and sing; pick his</line>
            <line>teeth and sing. I know a man that had this trick of</line>
            <line>melancholy sold a goodly manor for a song.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>Let me see what he writes, and when he means to come.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Opening a letter</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>I have no mind to Isbel since I was at court: our</line>
            <line>old ling and our Isbels o' the country are nothing</line>
            <line>like your old ling and your Isbels o' the court:</line>
            <line>the brains of my Cupid's knocked out, and I begin to</line>
            <line>love, as an old man loves money, with no stomach.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>What have we here?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>E'en that you have there.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>  I have sent you a daughter-in-law: she hath</line>
            <line>recovered the king, and undone me. I have wedded</line>
            <line>her, not bedded her; and sworn to make the 'not'</line>
            <line>eternal. You shall hear I am run away: know it</line>
            <line>before the report come. If there be breadth enough</line>
            <line>in the world, I will hold a long distance. My duty</line>
            <line>to you. Your unfortunate son,</line>
            <line>BERTRAM.</line>
            <line>This is not well, rash and unbridled boy.</line>
            <line>To fly the favours of so good a king;</line>
            <line>To pluck his indignation on thy head</line>
            <line>By the misprising of a maid too virtuous</line>
            <line>For the contempt of empire.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter Clown</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>O madam, yonder is heavy news within between two</line>
            <line>soldiers and my young lady!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>What is the matter?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Nay, there is some comfort in the news, some</line>
            <line>comfort; your son will not be killed so soon as I</line>
            <line>thought he would.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>Why should he be killed?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>So say I, madam, if he run away, as I hear he does:</line>
            <line>the danger is in standing to't; that's the loss of</line>
            <line>men, though it be the getting of children. Here</line>
            <line>they come will tell you more: for my part, I only</line>
            <line>hear your son was run away.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Enter HELENA, and two Gentlemen</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Gentleman</speaker>
            <line>Save you, good madam.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>Madam, my lord is gone, for ever gone.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Gentleman</speaker>
            <line>Do not say so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>Think upon patience. Pray you, gentlemen,</line>
            <line>I have felt so many quirks of joy and grief,</line>
            <line>That the first face of neither, on the start,</line>
            <line>Can woman me unto't: where is my son, I pray you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Gentleman</speaker>
            <line>Madam, he's gone to serve the duke of Florence:</line>
            <line>We met him thitherward; for thence we came,</line>
            <line>And, after some dispatch in hand at court,</line>
            <line>Thither we bend again.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>Look on his letter, madam; here's my passport.</line>
            <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>
            <line>When thou canst get the ring upon my finger which</line>
            <line>never shall come off, and show me a child begotten</line>
            <line>of thy body that I am father to, then call me</line>
            <line>husband: but in such a 'then' I write a 'never.'</line>
            <line>This is a dreadful sentence.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>Brought you this letter, gentlemen?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Gentleman</speaker>
            <line>Ay, madam;</line>
            <line>And for the contents' sake are sorry for our pain.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>I prithee, lady, have a better cheer;</line>
            <line>If thou engrossest all the griefs are thine,</line>
            <line>Thou robb'st me of a moiety: he was my son;</line>
            <line>But I do wash his name out of my blood,</line>
            <line>And thou art all my child. Towards Florence is he?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Gentleman</speaker>
            <line>Ay, madam.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>And to be a soldier?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Gentleman</speaker>
            <line>Such is his noble purpose; and believe 't,</line>
            <line>The duke will lay upon him all the honour</line>
            <line>That good convenience claims.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>Return you thither?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Gentleman</speaker>
            <line>Ay, madam, with the swiftest wing of speed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>  Till I have no wife I have nothing in France.</line>
            <line>'Tis bitter.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>Find you that there?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>Ay, madam.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Gentleman</speaker>
            <line>'Tis but the boldness of his hand, haply, which his</line>
            <line>heart was not consenting to.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>Nothing in France, until he have no wife!</line>
            <line>There's nothing here that is too good for him</line>
            <line>But only she; and she deserves a lord</line>
            <line>That twenty such rude boys might tend upon</line>
            <line>And call her hourly mistress. Who was with him?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Gentleman</speaker>
            <line>A servant only, and a gentleman</line>
            <line>Which I have sometime known.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>Parolles, was it not?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Gentleman</speaker>
            <line>Ay, my good lady, he.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>A very tainted fellow, and full of wickedness.</line>
            <line>My son corrupts a well-derived nature</line>
            <line>With his inducement.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Gentleman</speaker>
            <line>Indeed, good lady,</line>
            <line>The fellow has a deal of that too much,</line>
            <line>Which holds him much to have.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>You're welcome, gentlemen.</line>
            <line>I will entreat you, when you see my son,</line>
            <line>To tell him that his sword can never win</line>
            <line>The honour that he loses: more I'll entreat you</line>
            <line>Written to bear along.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Gentleman</speaker>
            <line>We serve you, madam,</line>
            <line>In that and all your worthiest affairs.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>Not so, but as we change our courtesies.</line>
            <line>Will you draw near!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt COUNTESS and Gentlemen</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>'Till I have no wife, I have nothing in France.'</line>
            <line>Nothing in France, until he has no wife!</line>
            <line>Thou shalt have none, Rousillon, none in France;</line>
            <line>Then hast thou all again. Poor lord! is't I</line>
            <line>That chase thee from thy country and expose</line>
            <line>Those tender limbs of thine to the event</line>
            <line>Of the none-sparing war? and is it I</line>
            <line>That drive thee from the sportive court, where thou</line>
            <line>Wast shot at with fair eyes, to be the mark</line>
            <line>Of smoky muskets? O you leaden messengers,</line>
            <line>That ride upon the violent speed of fire,</line>
            <line>Fly with false aim; move the still-peering air,</line>
            <line>That sings with piercing; do not touch my lord.</line>
            <line>Whoever shoots at him, I set him there;</line>
            <line>Whoever charges on his forward breast,</line>
            <line>I am the caitiff that do hold him to't;</line>
            <line>And, though I kill him not, I am the cause</line>
            <line>His death was so effected: better 'twere</line>
            <line>I met the ravin lion when he roar'd</line>
            <line>With sharp constraint of hunger; better 'twere</line>
            <line>That all the miseries which nature owes</line>
            <line>Were mine at once. No, come thou home, Rousillon,</line>
            <line>Whence honour but of danger wins a scar,</line>
            <line>As oft it loses all: I will be gone;</line>
            <line>My being here it is that holds thee hence:</line>
            <line>Shall I stay here to do't?  no, no, although</line>
            <line>The air of paradise did fan the house</line>
            <line>And angels officed all: I will be gone,</line>
            <line>That pitiful rumour may report my flight,</line>
            <line>To consolate thine ear. Come, night; end, day!</line>
            <line>For with the dark, poor thief, I'll steal away.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  Florence. Before the DUKE's palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Flourish. Enter the DUKE of Florence, BERTRAM,
PAROLLES, Soldiers, Drum, and Trumpets</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE</speaker>
            <line>The general of our horse thou art; and we,</line>
            <line>Great in our hope, lay our best love and credence</line>
            <line>Upon thy promising fortune.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>Sir, it is</line>
            <line>A charge too heavy for my strength, but yet</line>
            <line>We'll strive to bear it for your worthy sake</line>
            <line>To the extreme edge of hazard.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE</speaker>
            <line>Then go thou forth;</line>
            <line>And fortune play upon thy prosperous helm,</line>
            <line>As thy auspicious mistress!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>This very day,</line>
            <line>Great Mars, I put myself into thy file:</line>
            <line>Make me but like my thoughts, and I shall prove</line>
            <line>A lover of thy drum, hater of love.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-4">
      <title>SCENE IV.  Rousillon. The COUNT's palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter COUNTESS and Steward</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>Alas! and would you take the letter of her?</line>
            <line>Might you not know she would do as she has done,</line>
            <line>By sending me a letter? Read it again.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Steward</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>
            </line>
            <line>I am Saint Jaques' pilgrim, thither gone:</line>
            <line>Ambitious love hath so in me offended,</line>
            <line>That barefoot plod I the cold ground upon,</line>
            <line>With sainted vow my faults to have amended.</line>
            <line>Write, write, that from the bloody course of war</line>
            <line>My dearest master, your dear son, may hie:</line>
            <line>Bless him at home in peace, whilst I from far</line>
            <line>His name with zealous fervor sanctify:</line>
            <line>His taken labours bid him me forgive;</line>
            <line>I, his despiteful Juno, sent him forth</line>
            <line>From courtly friends, with camping foes to live,</line>
            <line>Where death and danger dogs the heels of worth:</line>
            <line>He is too good and fair for death and me:</line>
            <line>Whom I myself embrace, to set him free.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>Ah, what sharp stings are in her mildest words!</line>
            <line>Rinaldo, you did never lack advice so much,</line>
            <line>As letting her pass so: had I spoke with her,</line>
            <line>I could have well diverted her intents,</line>
            <line>Which thus she hath prevented.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Steward</speaker>
            <line>Pardon me, madam:</line>
            <line>If I had given you this at over-night,</line>
            <line>She might have been o'erta'en; and yet she writes,</line>
            <line>Pursuit would be but vain.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>What angel shall</line>
            <line>Bless this unworthy husband? he cannot thrive,</line>
            <line>Unless her prayers, whom heaven delights to hear</line>
            <line>And loves to grant, reprieve him from the wrath</line>
            <line>Of greatest justice. Write, write, Rinaldo,</line>
            <line>To this unworthy husband of his wife;</line>
            <line>Let every word weigh heavy of her worth</line>
            <line>That he does weigh too light: my greatest grief.</line>
            <line>Though little he do feel it, set down sharply.</line>
            <line>Dispatch the most convenient messenger:</line>
            <line>When haply he shall hear that she is gone,</line>
            <line>He will return; and hope I may that she,</line>
            <line>Hearing so much, will speed her foot again,</line>
            <line>Led hither by pure love: which of them both</line>
            <line>Is dearest to me. I have no skill in sense</line>
            <line>To make distinction: provide this messenger:</line>
            <line>My heart is heavy and mine age is weak;</line>
            <line>Grief would have tears, and sorrow bids me speak.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-5">
      <title>SCENE V.  Florence. Without the walls. A tucket afar off.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter an old Widow of Florence, DIANA, VIOLENTA,
and MARIANA, with other Citizens</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Widow</speaker>
            <line>Nay, come; for if they do approach the city, we</line>
            <line>shall lose all the sight.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DIANA</speaker>
            <line>They say the French count has done most honourable service.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Widow</speaker>
            <line>It is reported that he has taken their greatest</line>
            <line>commander; and that with his own hand he slew the</line>
            <line>duke's brother.</line>
            <stagedir>Tucket</stagedir>
            <line>We have lost our labour; they are gone a contrary</line>
            <line>way: hark! you may know by their trumpets.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIANA</speaker>
            <line>Come, let's return again, and suffice ourselves with</line>
            <line>the report of it. Well, Diana, take heed of this</line>
            <line>French earl: the honour of a maid is her name; and</line>
            <line>no legacy is so rich as honesty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Widow</speaker>
            <line>I have told my neighbour how you have been solicited</line>
            <line>by a gentleman his companion.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIANA</speaker>
            <line>I know that knave; hang him! one Parolles: a</line>
            <line>filthy officer he is in those suggestions for the</line>
            <line>young earl. Beware of them, Diana; their promises,</line>
            <line>enticements, oaths, tokens, and all these engines of</line>
            <line>lust, are not the things they go under: many a maid</line>
            <line>hath been seduced by them; and the misery is,</line>
            <line>example, that so terrible shows in the wreck of</line>
            <line>maidenhood, cannot for all that dissuade succession,</line>
            <line>but that they are limed with the twigs that threaten</line>
            <line>them. I hope I need not to advise you further; but</line>
            <line>I hope your own grace will keep you where you are,</line>
            <line>though there were no further danger known but the</line>
            <line>modesty which is so lost.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DIANA</speaker>
            <line>You shall not need to fear me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Widow</speaker>
            <line>I hope so.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter HELENA, disguised like a Pilgrim</stagedir>
            <line>Look, here comes a pilgrim: I know she will lie at</line>
            <line>my house; thither they send one another: I'll</line>
            <line>question her. God save you, pilgrim! whither are you bound?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>To Saint Jaques le Grand.</line>
            <line>Where do the palmers lodge, I do beseech you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Widow</speaker>
            <line>At the Saint Francis here beside the port.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>Is this the way?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Widow</speaker>
            <line>Ay, marry, is't.</line>
            <stagedir>A march afar</stagedir>
            <line>Hark you! they come this way.</line>
            <line>If you will tarry, holy pilgrim,</line>
            <line>But till the troops come by,</line>
            <line>I will conduct you where you shall be lodged;</line>
            <line>The rather, for I think I know your hostess</line>
            <line>As ample as myself.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>Is it yourself?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Widow</speaker>
            <line>If you shall please so, pilgrim.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>I thank you, and will stay upon your leisure.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Widow</speaker>
            <line>You came, I think, from France?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>I did so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Widow</speaker>
            <line>Here you shall see a countryman of yours</line>
            <line>That has done worthy service.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>His name, I pray you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DIANA</speaker>
            <line>The Count Rousillon: know you such a one?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>But by the ear, that hears most nobly of him:</line>
            <line>His face I know not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DIANA</speaker>
            <line>Whatsome'er he is,</line>
            <line>He's bravely taken here. He stole from France,</line>
            <line>As 'tis reported, for the king had married him</line>
            <line>Against his liking: think you it is so?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>Ay, surely, mere the truth: I know his lady.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DIANA</speaker>
            <line>There is a gentleman that serves the count</line>
            <line>Reports but coarsely of her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>What's his name?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DIANA</speaker>
            <line>Monsieur Parolles.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>O, I believe with him,</line>
            <line>In argument of praise, or to the worth</line>
            <line>Of the great count himself, she is too mean</line>
            <line>To have her name repeated: all her deserving</line>
            <line>Is a reserved honesty, and that</line>
            <line>I have not heard examined.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DIANA</speaker>
            <line>Alas, poor lady!</line>
            <line>'Tis a hard bondage to become the wife</line>
            <line>Of a detesting lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Widow</speaker>
            <line>I warrant, good creature, wheresoe'er she is,</line>
            <line>Her heart weighs sadly: this young maid might do her</line>
            <line>A shrewd turn, if she pleased.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>How do you mean?</line>
            <line>May be the amorous count solicits her</line>
            <line>In the unlawful purpose.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Widow</speaker>
            <line>He does indeed;</line>
            <line>And brokes with all that can in such a suit</line>
            <line>Corrupt the tender honour of a maid:</line>
            <line>But she is arm'd for him and keeps her guard</line>
            <line>In honestest defence.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIANA</speaker>
            <line>The gods forbid else!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Widow</speaker>
            <line>So, now they come:</line>
            <stagedir>Drum and Colours</stagedir>
            <stagedir>Enter BERTRAM, PAROLLES, and the whole army</stagedir>
            <line>That is Antonio, the duke's eldest son;</line>
            <line>That, Escalus.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>Which is the Frenchman?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DIANA</speaker>
            <line>He;</line>
            <line>That with the plume: 'tis a most gallant fellow.</line>
            <line>I would he loved his wife: if he were honester</line>
            <line>He were much goodlier: is't not a handsome gentleman?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>I like him well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DIANA</speaker>
            <line>'Tis pity he is not honest: yond's that same knave</line>
            <line>That leads him to these places: were I his lady,</line>
            <line>I would Poison that vile rascal.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>Which is he?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DIANA</speaker>
            <line>That jack-an-apes with scarfs: why is he melancholy?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>Perchance he's hurt i' the battle.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Lose our drum! well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIANA</speaker>
            <line>He's shrewdly vexed at something: look, he has spied us.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Widow</speaker>
            <line>Marry, hang you!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIANA</speaker>
            <line>And your courtesy, for a ring-carrier!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt BERTRAM, PAROLLES, and army</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Widow</speaker>
            <line>The troop is past. Come, pilgrim, I will bring you</line>
            <line>Where you shall host: of enjoin'd penitents</line>
            <line>There's four or five, to great Saint Jaques bound,</line>
            <line>Already at my house.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>I humbly thank you:</line>
            <line>Please it this matron and this gentle maid</line>
            <line>To eat with us to-night, the charge and thanking</line>
            <line>Shall be for me; and, to requite you further,</line>
            <line>I will bestow some precepts of this virgin</line>
            <line>Worthy the note.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOTH</speaker>
            <line>We'll take your offer kindly.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-6">
      <title>SCENE VI.  Camp before Florence.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter BERTRAM and the two French Lords</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>Nay, good my lord, put him to't; let him have his</line>
            <line>way.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>If your lordship find him not a hilding, hold me no</line>
            <line>more in your respect.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>On my life, my lord, a bubble.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>Do you think I am so far deceived in him?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>Believe it, my lord, in mine own direct knowledge,</line>
            <line>without any malice, but to speak of him as my</line>
            <line>kinsman, he's a most notable coward, an infinite and</line>
            <line>endless liar, an hourly promise-breaker, the owner</line>
            <line>of no one good quality worthy your lordship's</line>
            <line>entertainment.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>It were fit you knew him; lest, reposing too far in</line>
            <line>his virtue, which he hath not, he might at some</line>
            <line>great and trusty business in a main danger fail you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>I would I knew in what particular action to try him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>None better than to let him fetch off his drum,</line>
            <line>which you hear him so confidently undertake to do.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>I, with a troop of Florentines, will suddenly</line>
            <line>surprise him; such I will have, whom I am sure he</line>
            <line>knows not from the enemy: we will bind and hoodwink</line>
            <line>him so, that he shall suppose no other but that he</line>
            <line>is carried into the leaguer of the adversaries, when</line>
            <line>we bring him to our own tents. Be but your lordship</line>
            <line>present at his examination: if he do not, for the</line>
            <line>promise of his life and in the highest compulsion of</line>
            <line>base fear, offer to betray you and deliver all the</line>
            <line>intelligence in his power against you, and that with</line>
            <line>the divine forfeit of his soul upon oath, never</line>
            <line>trust my judgment in any thing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>O, for the love of laughter, let him fetch his drum;</line>
            <line>he says he has a stratagem for't: when your</line>
            <line>lordship sees the bottom of his success in't, and to</line>
            <line>what metal this counterfeit lump of ore will be</line>
            <line>melted, if you give him not John Drum's</line>
            <line>entertainment, your inclining cannot be removed.</line>
            <line>Here he comes.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter PAROLLES</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside to BERTRAM</stagedir>  O, for the love of laughter,</line>
            <line>hinder not the honour of his design: let him fetch</line>
            <line>off his drum in any hand.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>How now, monsieur! this drum sticks sorely in your</line>
            <line>disposition.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>A pox on't, let it go; 'tis but a drum.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>'But a drum'! is't 'but a drum'? A drum so lost!</line>
            <line>There was excellent command,--to charge in with our</line>
            <line>horse upon our own wings, and to rend our own soldiers!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>That was not to be blamed in the command of the</line>
            <line>service: it was a disaster of war that Caesar</line>
            <line>himself could not have prevented, if he had been</line>
            <line>there to command.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>Well, we cannot greatly condemn our success: some</line>
            <line>dishonour we had in the loss of that drum; but it is</line>
            <line>not to be recovered.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>It might have been recovered.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>It might; but it is not now.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>It is to be recovered: but that the merit of</line>
            <line>service is seldom attributed to the true and exact</line>
            <line>performer, I would have that drum or another, or</line>
            <line>'hic jacet.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>Why, if you have a stomach, to't, monsieur: if you</line>
            <line>think your mystery in stratagem can bring this</line>
            <line>instrument of honour again into his native quarter,</line>
            <line>be magnanimous in the enterprise and go on; I will</line>
            <line>grace the attempt for a worthy exploit: if you</line>
            <line>speed well in it, the duke shall both speak of it.</line>
            <line>and extend to you what further becomes his</line>
            <line>greatness, even to the utmost syllable of your</line>
            <line>worthiness.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>By the hand of a soldier, I will undertake it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>But you must not now slumber in it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>I'll about it this evening: and I will presently</line>
            <line>pen down my dilemmas, encourage myself in my</line>
            <line>certainty, put myself into my mortal preparation;</line>
            <line>and by midnight look to hear further from me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>May I be bold to acquaint his grace you are gone about it?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>I know not what the success will be, my lord; but</line>
            <line>the attempt I vow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>I know thou'rt valiant; and, to the possibility of</line>
            <line>thy soldiership, will subscribe for thee. Farewell.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>I love not many words.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>No more than a fish loves water. Is not this a</line>
            <line>strange fellow, my lord, that so confidently seems</line>
            <line>to undertake this business, which he knows is not to</line>
            <line>be done; damns himself to do and dares better be</line>
            <line>damned than to do't?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>You do not know him, my lord, as we do: certain it</line>
            <line>is that he will steal himself into a man's favour and</line>
            <line>for a week escape a great deal of discoveries; but</line>
            <line>when you find him out, you have him ever after.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>Why, do you think he will make no deed at all of</line>
            <line>this that so seriously he does address himself unto?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>None in the world; but return with an invention and</line>
            <line>clap upon you two or three probable lies: but we</line>
            <line>have almost embossed him; you shall see his fall</line>
            <line>to-night; for indeed he is not for your lordship's respect.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>We'll make you some sport with the fox ere we case</line>
            <line>him. He was first smoked by the old lord Lafeu:</line>
            <line>when his disguise and he is parted, tell me what a</line>
            <line>sprat you shall find him; which you shall see this</line>
            <line>very night.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>I must go look my twigs: he shall be caught.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>Your brother he shall go along with me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>As't please your lordship: I'll leave you.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>Now will I lead you to the house, and show you</line>
            <line>The lass I spoke of.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>But you say she's honest.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>That's all the fault: I spoke with her but once</line>
            <line>And found her wondrous cold; but I sent to her,</line>
            <line>By this same coxcomb that we have i' the wind,</line>
            <line>Tokens and letters which she did re-send;</line>
            <line>And this is all I have done. She's a fair creature:</line>
            <line>Will you go see her?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>With all my heart, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-7">
      <title>SCENE VII.  Florence. The Widow's house.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter HELENA and Widow</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>If you misdoubt me that I am not she,</line>
            <line>I know not how I shall assure you further,</line>
            <line>But I shall lose the grounds I work upon.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Widow</speaker>
            <line>Though my estate be fallen, I was well born,</line>
            <line>Nothing acquainted with these businesses;</line>
            <line>And would not put my reputation now</line>
            <line>In any staining act.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>Nor would I wish you.</line>
            <line>First, give me trust, the count he is my husband,</line>
            <line>And what to your sworn counsel I have spoken</line>
            <line>Is so from word to word; and then you cannot,</line>
            <line>By the good aid that I of you shall borrow,</line>
            <line>Err in bestowing it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Widow</speaker>
            <line>I should believe you:</line>
            <line>For you have show'd me that which well approves</line>
            <line>You're great in fortune.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>Take this purse of gold,</line>
            <line>And let me buy your friendly help thus far,</line>
            <line>Which I will over-pay and pay again</line>
            <line>When I have found it. The count he wooes your daughter,</line>
            <line>Lays down his wanton siege before her beauty,</line>
            <line>Resolved to carry her: let her in fine consent,</line>
            <line>As we'll direct her how 'tis best to bear it.</line>
            <line>Now his important blood will nought deny</line>
            <line>That she'll demand: a ring the county wears,</line>
            <line>That downward hath succeeded in his house</line>
            <line>From son to son, some four or five descents</line>
            <line>Since the first father wore it: this ring he holds</line>
            <line>In most rich choice; yet in his idle fire,</line>
            <line>To buy his will, it would not seem too dear,</line>
            <line>Howe'er repented after.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Widow</speaker>
            <line>Now I see</line>
            <line>The bottom of your purpose.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>You see it lawful, then: it is no more,</line>
            <line>But that your daughter, ere she seems as won,</line>
            <line>Desires this ring; appoints him an encounter;</line>
            <line>In fine, delivers me to fill the time,</line>
            <line>Herself most chastely absent: after this,</line>
            <line>To marry her, I'll add three thousand crowns</line>
            <line>To what is passed already.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Widow</speaker>
            <line>I have yielded:</line>
            <line>Instruct my daughter how she shall persever,</line>
            <line>That time and place with this deceit so lawful</line>
            <line>May prove coherent. Every night he comes</line>
            <line>With musics of all sorts and songs composed</line>
            <line>To her unworthiness: it nothing steads us</line>
            <line>To chide him from our eaves; for he persists</line>
            <line>As if his life lay on't.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>Why then to-night</line>
            <line>Let us assay our plot; which, if it speed,</line>
            <line>Is wicked meaning in a lawful deed</line>
            <line>And lawful meaning in a lawful act,</line>
            <line>Where both not sin, and yet a sinful fact:</line>
            <line>But let's about it.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>