<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net/doctypes/dita/shakespear/dtd/act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-1">
   <title>ACT I</title>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  Rousillon. The COUNT's palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter BERTRAM, the COUNTESS of Rousillon, HELENA,
and LAFEU, all in black</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>In delivering my son from me, I bury a second husband.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>And I in going, madam, weep o'er my father's death</line>
            <line>anew: but I must attend his majesty's command, to</line>
            <line>whom I am now in ward, evermore in subjection.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>You shall find of the king a husband, madam; you,</line>
            <line>sir, a father: he that so generally is at all times</line>
            <line>good must of necessity hold his virtue to you; whose</line>
            <line>worthiness would stir it up where it wanted rather</line>
            <line>than lack it where there is such abundance.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>What hope is there of his majesty's amendment?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>He hath abandoned his physicians, madam; under whose</line>
            <line>practises he hath persecuted time with hope, and</line>
            <line>finds no other advantage in the process but only the</line>
            <line>losing of hope by time.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>This young gentlewoman had a father,--O, that</line>
            <line>'had'! how sad a passage 'tis!--whose skill was</line>
            <line>almost as great as his honesty; had it stretched so</line>
            <line>far, would have made nature immortal, and death</line>
            <line>should have play for lack of work. Would, for the</line>
            <line>king's sake, he were living! I think it would be</line>
            <line>the death of the king's disease.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>How called you the man you speak of, madam?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>He was famous, sir, in his profession, and it was</line>
            <line>his great right to be so: Gerard de Narbon.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>He was excellent indeed, madam: the king very</line>
            <line>lately spoke of him admiringly and mourningly: he</line>
            <line>was skilful enough to have lived still, if knowledge</line>
            <line>could be set up against mortality.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>What is it, my good lord, the king languishes of?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>A fistula, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>I heard not of it before.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>I would it were not notorious. Was this gentlewoman</line>
            <line>the daughter of Gerard de Narbon?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>His sole child, my lord, and bequeathed to my</line>
            <line>overlooking. I have those hopes of her good that</line>
            <line>her education promises; her dispositions she</line>
            <line>inherits, which makes fair gifts fairer; for where</line>
            <line>an unclean mind carries virtuous qualities, there</line>
            <line>commendations go with pity; they are virtues and</line>
            <line>traitors too; in her they are the better for their</line>
            <line>simpleness; she derives her honesty and achieves her goodness.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>Your commendations, madam, get from her tears.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>'Tis the best brine a maiden can season her praise</line>
            <line>in. The remembrance of her father never approaches</line>
            <line>her heart but the tyranny of her sorrows takes all</line>
            <line>livelihood from her cheek. No more of this, Helena;</line>
            <line>go to, no more; lest it be rather thought you affect</line>
            <line>a sorrow than have it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>I do affect a sorrow indeed, but I have it too.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>Moderate lamentation is the right of the dead,</line>
            <line>excessive grief the enemy to the living.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>If the living be enemy to the grief, the excess</line>
            <line>makes it soon mortal.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>Madam, I desire your holy wishes.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>How understand we that?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>Be thou blest, Bertram, and succeed thy father</line>
            <line>In manners, as in shape! thy blood and virtue</line>
            <line>Contend for empire in thee, and thy goodness</line>
            <line>Share with thy birthright! Love all, trust a few,</line>
            <line>Do wrong to none: be able for thine enemy</line>
            <line>Rather in power than use, and keep thy friend</line>
            <line>Under thy own life's key: be cheque'd for silence,</line>
            <line>But never tax'd for speech. What heaven more will,</line>
            <line>That thee may furnish and my prayers pluck down,</line>
            <line>Fall on thy head! Farewell, my lord;</line>
            <line>'Tis an unseason'd courtier; good my lord,</line>
            <line>Advise him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>He cannot want the best</line>
            <line>That shall attend his love.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>Heaven bless him! Farewell, Bertram.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>To HELENA</stagedir>  The best wishes that can be forged in</line>
            <line>your thoughts be servants to you! Be comfortable</line>
            <line>to my mother, your mistress, and make much of her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LAFEU</speaker>
            <line>Farewell, pretty lady: you must hold the credit of</line>
            <line>your father.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt BERTRAM and LAFEU</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>O, were that all! I think not on my father;</line>
            <line>And these great tears grace his remembrance more</line>
            <line>Than those I shed for him. What was he like?</line>
            <line>I have forgot him: my imagination</line>
            <line>Carries no favour in't but Bertram's.</line>
            <line>I am undone: there is no living, none,</line>
            <line>If Bertram be away. 'Twere all one</line>
            <line>That I should love a bright particular star</line>
            <line>And think to wed it, he is so above me:</line>
            <line>In his bright radiance and collateral light</line>
            <line>Must I be comforted, not in his sphere.</line>
            <line>The ambition in my love thus plagues itself:</line>
            <line>The hind that would be mated by the lion</line>
            <line>Must die for love. 'Twas pretty, though plague,</line>
            <line>To see him every hour; to sit and draw</line>
            <line>His arched brows, his hawking eye, his curls,</line>
            <line>In our heart's table; heart too capable</line>
            <line>Of every line and trick of his sweet favour:</line>
            <line>But now he's gone, and my idolatrous fancy</line>
            <line>Must sanctify his reliques. Who comes here?</line>
            <stagedir>Enter PAROLLES</stagedir>
            <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>
            <line>One that goes with him: I love him for his sake;</line>
            <line>And yet I know him a notorious liar,</line>
            <line>Think him a great way fool, solely a coward;</line>
            <line>Yet these fixed evils sit so fit in him,</line>
            <line>That they take place, when virtue's steely bones</line>
            <line>Look bleak i' the cold wind: withal, full oft we see</line>
            <line>Cold wisdom waiting on superfluous folly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Save you, fair queen!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>And you, monarch!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>No.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>And no.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Are you meditating on virginity?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>Ay. You have some stain of soldier in you: let me</line>
            <line>ask you a question. Man is enemy to virginity; how</line>
            <line>may we barricado it against him?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Keep him out.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>But he assails; and our virginity, though valiant,</line>
            <line>in the defence yet is weak: unfold to us some</line>
            <line>warlike resistance.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>There is none: man, sitting down before you, will</line>
            <line>undermine you and blow you up.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>Bless our poor virginity from underminers and</line>
            <line>blowers up! Is there no military policy, how</line>
            <line>virgins might blow up men?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Virginity being blown down, man will quicklier be</line>
            <line>blown up: marry, in blowing him down again, with</line>
            <line>the breach yourselves made, you lose your city. It</line>
            <line>is not politic in the commonwealth of nature to</line>
            <line>preserve virginity. Loss of virginity is rational</line>
            <line>increase and there was never virgin got till</line>
            <line>virginity was first lost. That you were made of is</line>
            <line>metal to make virgins. Virginity by being once lost</line>
            <line>may be ten times found; by being ever kept, it is</line>
            <line>ever lost: 'tis too cold a companion; away with 't!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>I will stand for 't a little, though therefore I die a virgin.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>There's little can be said in 't; 'tis against the</line>
            <line>rule of nature. To speak on the part of virginity,</line>
            <line>is to accuse your mothers; which is most infallible</line>
            <line>disobedience. He that hangs himself is a virgin:</line>
            <line>virginity murders itself and should be buried in</line>
            <line>highways out of all sanctified limit, as a desperate</line>
            <line>offendress against nature. Virginity breeds mites,</line>
            <line>much like a cheese; consumes itself to the very</line>
            <line>paring, and so dies with feeding his own stomach.</line>
            <line>Besides, virginity is peevish, proud, idle, made of</line>
            <line>self-love, which is the most inhibited sin in the</line>
            <line>canon. Keep it not; you cannot choose but loose</line>
            <line>by't: out with 't! within ten year it will make</line>
            <line>itself ten, which is a goodly increase; and the</line>
            <line>principal itself not much the worse: away with 't!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>How might one do, sir, to lose it to her own liking?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Let me see: marry, ill, to like him that ne'er it</line>
            <line>likes. 'Tis a commodity will lose the gloss with</line>
            <line>lying; the longer kept, the less worth: off with 't</line>
            <line>while 'tis vendible; answer the time of request.</line>
            <line>Virginity, like an old courtier, wears her cap out</line>
            <line>of fashion: richly suited, but unsuitable: just</line>
            <line>like the brooch and the tooth-pick, which wear not</line>
            <line>now. Your date is better in your pie and your</line>
            <line>porridge than in your cheek; and your virginity,</line>
            <line>your old virginity, is like one of our French</line>
            <line>withered pears, it looks ill, it eats drily; marry,</line>
            <line>'tis a withered pear; it was formerly better;</line>
            <line>marry, yet 'tis a withered pear: will you anything with it?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>Not my virginity yet</line>
            <line>There shall your master have a thousand loves,</line>
            <line>A mother and a mistress and a friend,</line>
            <line>A phoenix, captain and an enemy,</line>
            <line>A guide, a goddess, and a sovereign,</line>
            <line>A counsellor, a traitress, and a dear;</line>
            <line>His humble ambition, proud humility,</line>
            <line>His jarring concord, and his discord dulcet,</line>
            <line>His faith, his sweet disaster; with a world</line>
            <line>Of pretty, fond, adoptious christendoms,</line>
            <line>That blinking Cupid gossips. Now shall he--</line>
            <line>I know not what he shall. God send him well!</line>
            <line>The court's a learning place, and he is one--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>What one, i' faith?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>That I wish well. 'Tis pity--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>What's pity?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>That wishing well had not a body in't,</line>
            <line>Which might be felt; that we, the poorer born,</line>
            <line>Whose baser stars do shut us up in wishes,</line>
            <line>Might with effects of them follow our friends,</line>
            <line>And show what we alone must think, which never</line>
            <line>Return us thanks.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter Page</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Page</speaker>
            <line>Monsieur Parolles, my lord calls for you.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Little Helen, farewell; if I can remember thee, I</line>
            <line>will think of thee at court.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>Monsieur Parolles, you were born under a charitable star.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Under Mars, I.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>I especially think, under Mars.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Why under Mars?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>The wars have so kept you under that you must needs</line>
            <line>be born under Mars.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>When he was predominant.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>When he was retrograde, I think, rather.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>Why think you so?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>You go so much backward when you fight.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>That's for advantage.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>So is running away, when fear proposes the safety;</line>
            <line>but the composition that your valour and fear makes</line>
            <line>in you is a virtue of a good wing, and I like the wear well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAROLLES</speaker>
            <line>I am so full of businesses, I cannot answer thee</line>
            <line>acutely. I will return perfect courtier; in the</line>
            <line>which, my instruction shall serve to naturalize</line>
            <line>thee, so thou wilt be capable of a courtier's</line>
            <line>counsel and understand what advice shall thrust upon</line>
            <line>thee; else thou diest in thine unthankfulness, and</line>
            <line>thine ignorance makes thee away: farewell. When</line>
            <line>thou hast leisure, say thy prayers; when thou hast</line>
            <line>none, remember thy friends; get thee a good husband,</line>
            <line>and use him as he uses thee; so, farewell.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>Our remedies oft in ourselves do lie,</line>
            <line>Which we ascribe to heaven: the fated sky</line>
            <line>Gives us free scope, only doth backward pull</line>
            <line>Our slow designs when we ourselves are dull.</line>
            <line>What power is it which mounts my love so high,</line>
            <line>That makes me see, and cannot feed mine eye?</line>
            <line>The mightiest space in fortune nature brings</line>
            <line>To join like likes and kiss like native things.</line>
            <line>Impossible be strange attempts to those</line>
            <line>That weigh their pains in sense and do suppose</line>
            <line>What hath been cannot be: who ever strove</line>
            <line>So show her merit, that did miss her love?</line>
            <line>The king's disease--my project may deceive me,</line>
            <line>But my intents are fix'd and will not leave me.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  Paris. The KING's palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Flourish of cornets. Enter the KING of France,
with letters, and divers Attendants</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>The Florentines and Senoys are by the ears;</line>
            <line>Have fought with equal fortune and continue</line>
            <line>A braving war.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>So 'tis reported, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>Nay, 'tis most credible; we here received it</line>
            <line>A certainty, vouch'd from our cousin Austria,</line>
            <line>With caution that the Florentine will move us</line>
            <line>For speedy aid; wherein our dearest friend</line>
            <line>Prejudicates the business and would seem</line>
            <line>To have us make denial.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>His love and wisdom,</line>
            <line>Approved so to your majesty, may plead</line>
            <line>For amplest credence.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>He hath arm'd our answer,</line>
            <line>And Florence is denied before he comes:</line>
            <line>Yet, for our gentlemen that mean to see</line>
            <line>The Tuscan service, freely have they leave</line>
            <line>To stand on either part.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>It well may serve</line>
            <line>A nursery to our gentry, who are sick</line>
            <line>For breathing and exploit.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>What's he comes here?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter BERTRAM, LAFEU, and PAROLLES</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>It is the Count Rousillon, my good lord,</line>
            <line>Young Bertram.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>Youth, thou bear'st thy father's face;</line>
            <line>Frank nature, rather curious than in haste,</line>
            <line>Hath well composed thee. Thy father's moral parts</line>
            <line>Mayst thou inherit too! Welcome to Paris.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>My thanks and duty are your majesty's.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>I would I had that corporal soundness now,</line>
            <line>As when thy father and myself in friendship</line>
            <line>First tried our soldiership! He did look far</line>
            <line>Into the service of the time and was</line>
            <line>Discipled of the bravest: he lasted long;</line>
            <line>But on us both did haggish age steal on</line>
            <line>And wore us out of act. It much repairs me</line>
            <line>To talk of your good father. In his youth</line>
            <line>He had the wit which I can well observe</line>
            <line>To-day in our young lords; but they may jest</line>
            <line>Till their own scorn return to them unnoted</line>
            <line>Ere they can hide their levity in honour;</line>
            <line>So like a courtier, contempt nor bitterness</line>
            <line>Were in his pride or sharpness; if they were,</line>
            <line>His equal had awaked them, and his honour,</line>
            <line>Clock to itself, knew the true minute when</line>
            <line>Exception bid him speak, and at this time</line>
            <line>His tongue obey'd his hand: who were below him</line>
            <line>He used as creatures of another place</line>
            <line>And bow'd his eminent top to their low ranks,</line>
            <line>Making them proud of his humility,</line>
            <line>In their poor praise he humbled. Such a man</line>
            <line>Might be a copy to these younger times;</line>
            <line>Which, follow'd well, would demonstrate them now</line>
            <line>But goers backward.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>His good remembrance, sir,</line>
            <line>Lies richer in your thoughts than on his tomb;</line>
            <line>So in approof lives not his epitaph</line>
            <line>As in your royal speech.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>Would I were with him! He would always say--</line>
            <line>Methinks I hear him now; his plausive words</line>
            <line>He scatter'd not in ears, but grafted them,</line>
            <line>To grow there and to bear,--'Let me not live,'--</line>
            <line>This his good melancholy oft began,</line>
            <line>On the catastrophe and heel of pastime,</line>
            <line>When it was out,--'Let me not live,' quoth he,</line>
            <line>'After my flame lacks oil, to be the snuff</line>
            <line>Of younger spirits, whose apprehensive senses</line>
            <line>All but new things disdain; whose judgments are</line>
            <line>Mere fathers of their garments; whose constancies</line>
            <line>Expire before their fashions.' This he wish'd;</line>
            <line>I after him do after him wish too,</line>
            <line>Since I nor wax nor honey can bring home,</line>
            <line>I quickly were dissolved from my hive,</line>
            <line>To give some labourers room.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>You are loved, sir:</line>
            <line>They that least lend it you shall lack you first.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>I fill a place, I know't. How long is't, count,</line>
            <line>Since the physician at your father's died?</line>
            <line>He was much famed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>Some six months since, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KING</speaker>
            <line>If he were living, I would try him yet.</line>
            <line>Lend me an arm; the rest have worn me out</line>
            <line>With several applications; nature and sickness</line>
            <line>Debate it at their leisure. Welcome, count;</line>
            <line>My son's no dearer.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BERTRAM</speaker>
            <line>Thank your majesty.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt. Flourish</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  Rousillon. The COUNT's palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter COUNTESS, Steward, and Clown</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>I will now hear; what say you of this gentlewoman?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Steward</speaker>
            <line>Madam, the care I have had to even your content, I</line>
            <line>wish might be found in the calendar of my past</line>
            <line>endeavours; for then we wound our modesty and make</line>
            <line>foul the clearness of our deservings, when of</line>
            <line>ourselves we publish them.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>What does this knave here? Get you gone, sirrah:</line>
            <line>the complaints I have heard of you I do not all</line>
            <line>believe: 'tis my slowness that I do not; for I know</line>
            <line>you lack not folly to commit them, and have ability</line>
            <line>enough to make such knaveries yours.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>'Tis not unknown to you, madam, I am a poor fellow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>Well, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>No, madam, 'tis not so well that I am poor, though</line>
            <line>many of the rich are damned: but, if I may have</line>
            <line>your ladyship's good will to go to the world, Isbel</line>
            <line>the woman and I will do as we may.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>Wilt thou needs be a beggar?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>I do beg your good will in this case.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>In what case?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>In Isbel's case and mine own. Service is no</line>
            <line>heritage: and I think I shall never have the</line>
            <line>blessing of God till I have issue o' my body; for</line>
            <line>they say barnes are blessings.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>Tell me thy reason why thou wilt marry.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>My poor body, madam, requires it: I am driven on</line>
            <line>by the flesh; and he must needs go that the devil drives.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>Is this all your worship's reason?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Faith, madam, I have other holy reasons such as they</line>
            <line>are.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>May the world know them?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>I have been, madam, a wicked creature, as you and</line>
            <line>all flesh and blood are; and, indeed, I do marry</line>
            <line>that I may repent.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>Thy marriage, sooner than thy wickedness.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>I am out o' friends, madam; and I hope to have</line>
            <line>friends for my wife's sake.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>Such friends are thine enemies, knave.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>You're shallow, madam, in great friends; for the</line>
            <line>knaves come to do that for me which I am aweary of.</line>
            <line>He that ears my land spares my team and gives me</line>
            <line>leave to in the crop; if I be his cuckold, he's my</line>
            <line>drudge: he that comforts my wife is the cherisher</line>
            <line>of my flesh and blood; he that cherishes my flesh</line>
            <line>and blood loves my flesh and blood; he that loves my</line>
            <line>flesh and blood is my friend: ergo, he that kisses</line>
            <line>my wife is my friend. If men could be contented to</line>
            <line>be what they are, there were no fear in marriage;</line>
            <line>for young Charbon the Puritan and old Poysam the</line>
            <line>Papist, howsome'er their hearts are severed in</line>
            <line>religion, their heads are both one; they may jowl</line>
            <line>horns together, like any deer i' the herd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>Wilt thou ever be a foul-mouthed and calumnious knave?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>A prophet I, madam; and I speak the truth the next</line>
            <line>way:</line>
            <line>For I the ballad will repeat,</line>
            <line>Which men full true shall find;</line>
            <line>Your marriage comes by destiny,</line>
            <line>Your cuckoo sings by kind.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>Get you gone, sir; I'll talk with you more anon.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Steward</speaker>
            <line>May it please you, madam, that he bid Helen come to</line>
            <line>you: of her I am to speak.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>Sirrah, tell my gentlewoman I would speak with her;</line>
            <line>Helen, I mean.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Was this fair face the cause, quoth she,</line>
            <line>Why the Grecians sacked Troy?</line>
            <line>Fond done, done fond,</line>
            <line>Was this King Priam's joy?</line>
            <line>With that she sighed as she stood,</line>
            <line>With that she sighed as she stood,</line>
            <line>And gave this sentence then;</line>
            <line>Among nine bad if one be good,</line>
            <line>Among nine bad if one be good,</line>
            <line>There's yet one good in ten.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>What, one good in ten? you corrupt the song, sirrah.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>One good woman in ten, madam; which is a purifying</line>
            <line>o' the song: would God would serve the world so all</line>
            <line>the year! we'ld find no fault with the tithe-woman,</line>
            <line>if I were the parson. One in ten, quoth a'! An we</line>
            <line>might have a good woman born but one every blazing</line>
            <line>star, or at an earthquake, 'twould mend the lottery</line>
            <line>well: a man may draw his heart out, ere a' pluck</line>
            <line>one.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>You'll be gone, sir knave, and do as I command you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>That man should be at woman's command, and yet no</line>
            <line>hurt done! Though honesty be no puritan, yet it</line>
            <line>will do no hurt; it will wear the surplice of</line>
            <line>humility over the black gown of a big heart. I am</line>
            <line>going, forsooth: the business is for Helen to come hither.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>Well, now.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Steward</speaker>
            <line>I know, madam, you love your gentlewoman entirely.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>Faith, I do: her father bequeathed her to me; and</line>
            <line>she herself, without other advantage, may lawfully</line>
            <line>make title to as much love as she finds: there is</line>
            <line>more owing her than is paid; and more shall be paid</line>
            <line>her than she'll demand.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Steward</speaker>
            <line>Madam, I was very late more near her than I think</line>
            <line>she wished me: alone she was, and did communicate</line>
            <line>to herself her own words to her own ears; she</line>
            <line>thought, I dare vow for her, they touched not any</line>
            <line>stranger sense. Her matter was, she loved your son:</line>
            <line>Fortune, she said, was no goddess, that had put</line>
            <line>such difference betwixt their two estates; Love no</line>
            <line>god, that would not extend his might, only where</line>
            <line>qualities were level; Dian no queen of virgins, that</line>
            <line>would suffer her poor knight surprised, without</line>
            <line>rescue in the first assault or ransom afterward.</line>
            <line>This she delivered in the most bitter touch of</line>
            <line>sorrow that e'er I heard virgin exclaim in: which I</line>
            <line>held my duty speedily to acquaint you withal;</line>
            <line>sithence, in the loss that may happen, it concerns</line>
            <line>you something to know it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>You have discharged this honestly; keep it to</line>
            <line>yourself: many likelihoods informed me of this</line>
            <line>before, which hung so tottering in the balance that</line>
            <line>I could neither believe nor misdoubt. Pray you,</line>
            <line>leave me: stall this in your bosom; and I thank you</line>
            <line>for your honest care: I will speak with you further anon.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit Steward</stagedir>
            <stagedir>Enter HELENA</stagedir>
            <line>Even so it was with me when I was young:</line>
            <line>If ever we are nature's, these are ours; this thorn</line>
            <line>Doth to our rose of youth rightly belong;</line>
            <line>Our blood to us, this to our blood is born;</line>
            <line>It is the show and seal of nature's truth,</line>
            <line>Where love's strong passion is impress'd in youth:</line>
            <line>By our remembrances of days foregone,</line>
            <line>Such were our faults, or then we thought them none.</line>
            <line>Her eye is sick on't: I observe her now.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>What is your pleasure, madam?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>You know, Helen,</line>
            <line>I am a mother to you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>Mine honourable mistress.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>Nay, a mother:</line>
            <line>Why not a mother? When I said 'a mother,'</line>
            <line>Methought you saw a serpent: what's in 'mother,'</line>
            <line>That you start at it? I say, I am your mother;</line>
            <line>And put you in the catalogue of those</line>
            <line>That were enwombed mine: 'tis often seen</line>
            <line>Adoption strives with nature and choice breeds</line>
            <line>A native slip to us from foreign seeds:</line>
            <line>You ne'er oppress'd me with a mother's groan,</line>
            <line>Yet I express to you a mother's care:</line>
            <line>God's mercy, maiden! does it curd thy blood</line>
            <line>To say I am thy mother? What's the matter,</line>
            <line>That this distemper'd messenger of wet,</line>
            <line>The many-colour'd Iris, rounds thine eye?</line>
            <line>Why? that you are my daughter?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>That I am not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>I say, I am your mother.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>Pardon, madam;</line>
            <line>The Count Rousillon cannot be my brother:</line>
            <line>I am from humble, he from honour'd name;</line>
            <line>No note upon my parents, his all noble:</line>
            <line>My master, my dear lord he is; and I</line>
            <line>His servant live, and will his vassal die:</line>
            <line>He must not be my brother.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>Nor I your mother?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>You are my mother, madam; would you were,--</line>
            <line>So that my lord your son were not my brother,--</line>
            <line>Indeed my mother! or were you both our mothers,</line>
            <line>I care no more for than I do for heaven,</line>
            <line>So I were not his sister. Can't no other,</line>
            <line>But, I your daughter, he must be my brother?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>Yes, Helen, you might be my daughter-in-law:</line>
            <line>God shield you mean it not! daughter and mother</line>
            <line>So strive upon your pulse. What, pale again?</line>
            <line>My fear hath catch'd your fondness: now I see</line>
            <line>The mystery of your loneliness, and find</line>
            <line>Your salt tears' head: now to all sense 'tis gross</line>
            <line>You love my son; invention is ashamed,</line>
            <line>Against the proclamation of thy passion,</line>
            <line>To say thou dost not: therefore tell me true;</line>
            <line>But tell me then, 'tis so; for, look thy cheeks</line>
            <line>Confess it, th' one to th' other; and thine eyes</line>
            <line>See it so grossly shown in thy behaviors</line>
            <line>That in their kind they speak it: only sin</line>
            <line>And hellish obstinacy tie thy tongue,</line>
            <line>That truth should be suspected. Speak, is't so?</line>
            <line>If it be so, you have wound a goodly clew;</line>
            <line>If it be not, forswear't: howe'er, I charge thee,</line>
            <line>As heaven shall work in me for thine avail,</line>
            <line>Tell me truly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>Good madam, pardon me!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>Do you love my son?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>Your pardon, noble mistress!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>Love you my son?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>Do not you love him, madam?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>Go not about; my love hath in't a bond,</line>
            <line>Whereof the world takes note: come, come, disclose</line>
            <line>The state of your affection; for your passions</line>
            <line>Have to the full appeach'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>Then, I confess,</line>
            <line>Here on my knee, before high heaven and you,</line>
            <line>That before you, and next unto high heaven,</line>
            <line>I love your son.</line>
            <line>My friends were poor, but honest; so's my love:</line>
            <line>Be not offended; for it hurts not him</line>
            <line>That he is loved of me: I follow him not</line>
            <line>By any token of presumptuous suit;</line>
            <line>Nor would I have him till I do deserve him;</line>
            <line>Yet never know how that desert should be.</line>
            <line>I know I love in vain, strive against hope;</line>
            <line>Yet in this captious and intenible sieve</line>
            <line>I still pour in the waters of my love</line>
            <line>And lack not to lose still: thus, Indian-like,</line>
            <line>Religious in mine error, I adore</line>
            <line>The sun, that looks upon his worshipper,</line>
            <line>But knows of him no more. My dearest madam,</line>
            <line>Let not your hate encounter with my love</line>
            <line>For loving where you do: but if yourself,</line>
            <line>Whose aged honour cites a virtuous youth,</line>
            <line>Did ever in so true a flame of liking</line>
            <line>Wish chastely and love dearly, that your Dian</line>
            <line>Was both herself and love: O, then, give pity</line>
            <line>To her, whose state is such that cannot choose</line>
            <line>But lend and give where she is sure to lose;</line>
            <line>That seeks not to find that her search implies,</line>
            <line>But riddle-like lives sweetly where she dies!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>Had you not lately an intent,--speak truly,--</line>
            <line>To go to Paris?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>Madam, I had.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>Wherefore? tell true.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>I will tell truth; by grace itself I swear.</line>
            <line>You know my father left me some prescriptions</line>
            <line>Of rare and proved effects, such as his reading</line>
            <line>And manifest experience had collected</line>
            <line>For general sovereignty; and that he will'd me</line>
            <line>In heedfull'st reservation to bestow them,</line>
            <line>As notes whose faculties inclusive were</line>
            <line>More than they were in note: amongst the rest,</line>
            <line>There is a remedy, approved, set down,</line>
            <line>To cure the desperate languishings whereof</line>
            <line>The king is render'd lost.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>This was your motive</line>
            <line>For Paris, was it? speak.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>My lord your son made me to think of this;</line>
            <line>Else Paris and the medicine and the king</line>
            <line>Had from the conversation of my thoughts</line>
            <line>Haply been absent then.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>But think you, Helen,</line>
            <line>If you should tender your supposed aid,</line>
            <line>He would receive it? he and his physicians</line>
            <line>Are of a mind; he, that they cannot help him,</line>
            <line>They, that they cannot help: how shall they credit</line>
            <line>A poor unlearned virgin, when the schools,</line>
            <line>Embowell'd of their doctrine, have left off</line>
            <line>The danger to itself?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>There's something in't,</line>
            <line>More than my father's skill, which was the greatest</line>
            <line>Of his profession, that his good receipt</line>
            <line>Shall for my legacy be sanctified</line>
            <line>By the luckiest stars in heaven: and, would your honour</line>
            <line>But give me leave to try success, I'ld venture</line>
            <line>The well-lost life of mine on his grace's cure</line>
            <line>By such a day and hour.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>Dost thou believe't?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELENA</speaker>
            <line>Ay, madam, knowingly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>COUNTESS</speaker>
            <line>Why, Helen, thou shalt have my leave and love,</line>
            <line>Means and attendants and my loving greetings</line>
            <line>To those of mine in court: I'll stay at home</line>
            <line>And pray God's blessing into thy attempt:</line>
            <line>Be gone to-morrow; and be sure of this,</line>
            <line>What I can help thee to thou shalt not miss.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>