<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net/doctypes/dita/shakespear/dtd/act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-3">
   <title>ACT III</title>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  A room in the prison.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter DUKE VINCENTIO disguised as before, CLAUDIO,
and Provost</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>So then you hope of pardon from Lord Angelo?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>The miserable have no other medicine</line>
            <line>But only hope:</line>
            <line>I've hope to live, and am prepared to die.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>Be absolute for death; either death or life</line>
            <line>Shall thereby be the sweeter. Reason thus with life:</line>
            <line>If I do lose thee, I do lose a thing</line>
            <line>That none but fools would keep: a breath thou art,</line>
            <line>Servile to all the skyey influences,</line>
            <line>That dost this habitation, where thou keep'st,</line>
            <line>Hourly afflict: merely, thou art death's fool;</line>
            <line>For him thou labour'st by thy flight to shun</line>
            <line>And yet runn'st toward him still. Thou art not noble;</line>
            <line>For all the accommodations that thou bear'st</line>
            <line>Are nursed by baseness. Thou'rt by no means valiant;</line>
            <line>For thou dost fear the soft and tender fork</line>
            <line>Of a poor worm. Thy best of rest is sleep,</line>
            <line>And that thou oft provokest; yet grossly fear'st</line>
            <line>Thy death, which is no more. Thou art not thyself;</line>
            <line>For thou exist'st on many a thousand grains</line>
            <line>That issue out of dust. Happy thou art not;</line>
            <line>For what thou hast not, still thou strivest to get,</line>
            <line>And what thou hast, forget'st. Thou art not certain;</line>
            <line>For thy complexion shifts to strange effects,</line>
            <line>After the moon. If thou art rich, thou'rt poor;</line>
            <line>For, like an ass whose back with ingots bows,</line>
            <line>Thou bear's thy heavy riches but a journey,</line>
            <line>And death unloads thee. Friend hast thou none;</line>
            <line>For thine own bowels, which do call thee sire,</line>
            <line>The mere effusion of thy proper loins,</line>
            <line>Do curse the gout, serpigo, and the rheum,</line>
            <line>For ending thee no sooner. Thou hast nor youth nor age,</line>
            <line>But, as it were, an after-dinner's sleep,</line>
            <line>Dreaming on both; for all thy blessed youth</line>
            <line>Becomes as aged, and doth beg the alms</line>
            <line>Of palsied eld; and when thou art old and rich,</line>
            <line>Thou hast neither heat, affection, limb, nor beauty,</line>
            <line>To make thy riches pleasant. What's yet in this</line>
            <line>That bears the name of life? Yet in this life</line>
            <line>Lie hid moe thousand deaths: yet death we fear,</line>
            <line>That makes these odds all even.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>I humbly thank you.</line>
            <line>To sue to live, I find I seek to die;</line>
            <line>And, seeking death, find life: let it come on.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Within</stagedir>  What, ho! Peace here; grace and good company!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Provost</speaker>
            <line>Who's there? come in: the wish deserves a welcome.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>Dear sir, ere long I'll visit you again.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Most holy sir, I thank you.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter ISABELLA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>My business is a word or two with Claudio.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Provost</speaker>
            <line>And very welcome. Look, signior, here's your sister.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>Provost, a word with you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Provost</speaker>
            <line>As many as you please.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>Bring me to hear them speak, where I may be concealed.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt DUKE VINCENTIO and Provost</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Now, sister, what's the comfort?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>Why,</line>
            <line>As all comforts are; most good, most good indeed.</line>
            <line>Lord Angelo, having affairs to heaven,</line>
            <line>Intends you for his swift ambassador,</line>
            <line>Where you shall be an everlasting leiger:</line>
            <line>Therefore your best appointment make with speed;</line>
            <line>To-morrow you set on.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Is there no remedy?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>None, but such remedy as, to save a head,</line>
            <line>To cleave a heart in twain.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>But is there any?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>Yes, brother, you may live:</line>
            <line>There is a devilish mercy in the judge,</line>
            <line>If you'll implore it, that will free your life,</line>
            <line>But fetter you till death.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Perpetual durance?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>Ay, just; perpetual durance, a restraint,</line>
            <line>Though all the world's vastidity you had,</line>
            <line>To a determined scope.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>But in what nature?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>In such a one as, you consenting to't,</line>
            <line>Would bark your honour from that trunk you bear,</line>
            <line>And leave you naked.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Let me know the point.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>O, I do fear thee, Claudio; and I quake,</line>
            <line>Lest thou a feverous life shouldst entertain,</line>
            <line>And six or seven winters more respect</line>
            <line>Than a perpetual honour. Darest thou die?</line>
            <line>The sense of death is most in apprehension;</line>
            <line>And the poor beetle, that we tread upon,</line>
            <line>In corporal sufferance finds a pang as great</line>
            <line>As when a giant dies.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Why give you me this shame?</line>
            <line>Think you I can a resolution fetch</line>
            <line>From flowery tenderness? If I must die,</line>
            <line>I will encounter darkness as a bride,</line>
            <line>And hug it in mine arms.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>There spake my brother; there my father's grave</line>
            <line>Did utter forth a voice. Yes, thou must die:</line>
            <line>Thou art too noble to conserve a life</line>
            <line>In base appliances. This outward-sainted deputy,</line>
            <line>Whose settled visage and deliberate word</line>
            <line>Nips youth i' the head and follies doth emmew</line>
            <line>As falcon doth the fowl, is yet a devil</line>
            <line>His filth within being cast, he would appear</line>
            <line>A pond as deep as hell.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>The prenzie Angelo!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>O, 'tis the cunning livery of hell,</line>
            <line>The damned'st body to invest and cover</line>
            <line>In prenzie guards! Dost thou think, Claudio?</line>
            <line>If I would yield him my virginity,</line>
            <line>Thou mightst be freed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>O heavens! it cannot be.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>Yes, he would give't thee, from this rank offence,</line>
            <line>So to offend him still. This night's the time</line>
            <line>That I should do what I abhor to name,</line>
            <line>Or else thou diest to-morrow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Thou shalt not do't.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>O, were it but my life,</line>
            <line>I'ld throw it down for your deliverance</line>
            <line>As frankly as a pin.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Thanks, dear Isabel.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>Be ready, Claudio, for your death tomorrow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Yes. Has he affections in him,</line>
            <line>That thus can make him bite the law by the nose,</line>
            <line>When he would force it? Sure, it is no sin,</line>
            <line>Or of the deadly seven, it is the least.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>Which is the least?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>If it were damnable, he being so wise,</line>
            <line>Why would he for the momentary trick</line>
            <line>Be perdurably fined? O Isabel!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>What says my brother?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Death is a fearful thing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>And shamed life a hateful.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Ay, but to die, and go we know not where;</line>
            <line>To lie in cold obstruction and to rot;</line>
            <line>This sensible warm motion to become</line>
            <line>A kneaded clod; and the delighted spirit</line>
            <line>To bathe in fiery floods, or to reside</line>
            <line>In thrilling region of thick-ribbed ice;</line>
            <line>To be imprison'd in the viewless winds,</line>
            <line>And blown with restless violence round about</line>
            <line>The pendent world; or to be worse than worst</line>
            <line>Of those that lawless and incertain thought</line>
            <line>Imagine howling: 'tis too horrible!</line>
            <line>The weariest and most loathed worldly life</line>
            <line>That age, ache, penury and imprisonment</line>
            <line>Can lay on nature is a paradise</line>
            <line>To what we fear of death.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>Alas, alas!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Sweet sister, let me live:</line>
            <line>What sin you do to save a brother's life,</line>
            <line>Nature dispenses with the deed so far</line>
            <line>That it becomes a virtue.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>O you beast!</line>
            <line>O faithless coward! O dishonest wretch!</line>
            <line>Wilt thou be made a man out of my vice?</line>
            <line>Is't not a kind of incest, to take life</line>
            <line>From thine own sister's shame? What should I think?</line>
            <line>Heaven shield my mother play'd my father fair!</line>
            <line>For such a warped slip of wilderness</line>
            <line>Ne'er issued from his blood. Take my defiance!</line>
            <line>Die, perish! Might but my bending down</line>
            <line>Reprieve thee from thy fate, it should proceed:</line>
            <line>I'll pray a thousand prayers for thy death,</line>
            <line>No word to save thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Nay, hear me, Isabel.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>O, fie, fie, fie!</line>
            <line>Thy sin's not accidental, but a trade.</line>
            <line>Mercy to thee would prove itself a bawd:</line>
            <line>'Tis best thou diest quickly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>O hear me, Isabella!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter DUKE VINCENTIO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>Vouchsafe a word, young sister, but one word.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>What is your will?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>Might you dispense with your leisure, I would by and</line>
            <line>by have some speech with you: the satisfaction I</line>
            <line>would require is likewise your own benefit.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>I have no superfluous leisure; my stay must be</line>
            <line>stolen out of other affairs; but I will attend you awhile.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Walks apart</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>Son, I have overheard what hath passed between you</line>
            <line>and your sister. Angelo had never the purpose to</line>
            <line>corrupt her; only he hath made an essay of her</line>
            <line>virtue to practise his judgment with the disposition</line>
            <line>of natures: she, having the truth of honour in her,</line>
            <line>hath made him that gracious denial which he is most</line>
            <line>glad to receive. I am confessor to Angelo, and I</line>
            <line>know this to be true; therefore prepare yourself to</line>
            <line>death: do not satisfy your resolution with hopes</line>
            <line>that are fallible: tomorrow you must die; go to</line>
            <line>your knees and make ready.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLAUDIO</speaker>
            <line>Let me ask my sister pardon. I am so out of love</line>
            <line>with life that I will sue to be rid of it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>Hold you there: farewell.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit CLAUDIO</stagedir>
            <line>Provost, a word with you!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter Provost</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Provost</speaker>
            <line>What's your will, father</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>That now you are come, you will be gone. Leave me</line>
            <line>awhile with the maid: my mind promises with my</line>
            <line>habit no loss shall touch her by my company.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Provost</speaker>
            <line>In good time.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit Provost. ISABELLA comes forward</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>The hand that hath made you fair hath made you good:</line>
            <line>the goodness that is cheap in beauty makes beauty</line>
            <line>brief in goodness; but grace, being the soul of</line>
            <line>your complexion, shall keep the body of it ever</line>
            <line>fair. The assault that Angelo hath made to you,</line>
            <line>fortune hath conveyed to my understanding; and, but</line>
            <line>that frailty hath examples for his falling, I should</line>
            <line>wonder at Angelo. How will you do to content this</line>
            <line>substitute, and to save your brother?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>I am now going to resolve him: I had rather my</line>
            <line>brother die by the law than my son should be</line>
            <line>unlawfully born. But, O, how much is the good duke</line>
            <line>deceived in Angelo! If ever he return and I can</line>
            <line>speak to him, I will open my lips in vain, or</line>
            <line>discover his government.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>That shall not be much amiss: Yet, as the matter</line>
            <line>now stands, he will avoid your accusation; he made</line>
            <line>trial of you only. Therefore fasten your ear on my</line>
            <line>advisings: to the love I have in doing good a</line>
            <line>remedy presents itself. I do make myself believe</line>
            <line>that you may most uprighteously do a poor wronged</line>
            <line>lady a merited benefit; redeem your brother from</line>
            <line>the angry law; do no stain to your own gracious</line>
            <line>person; and much please the absent duke, if</line>
            <line>peradventure he shall ever return to have hearing of</line>
            <line>this business.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>Let me hear you speak farther. I have spirit to do</line>
            <line>anything that appears not foul in the truth of my spirit.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>Virtue is bold, and goodness never fearful. Have</line>
            <line>you not heard speak of Mariana, the sister of</line>
            <line>Frederick the great soldier who miscarried at sea?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>I have heard of the lady, and good words went with her name.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>She should this Angelo have married; was affianced</line>
            <line>to her by oath, and the nuptial appointed: between</line>
            <line>which time of the contract and limit of the</line>
            <line>solemnity, her brother Frederick was wrecked at sea,</line>
            <line>having in that perished vessel the dowry of his</line>
            <line>sister. But mark how heavily this befell to the</line>
            <line>poor gentlewoman: there she lost a noble and</line>
            <line>renowned brother, in his love toward her ever most</line>
            <line>kind and natural; with him, the portion and sinew of</line>
            <line>her fortune, her marriage-dowry; with both, her</line>
            <line>combinate husband, this well-seeming Angelo.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>Can this be so? did Angelo so leave her?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>Left her in her tears, and dried not one of them</line>
            <line>with his comfort; swallowed his vows whole,</line>
            <line>pretending in her discoveries of dishonour: in few,</line>
            <line>bestowed her on her own lamentation, which she yet</line>
            <line>wears for his sake; and he, a marble to her tears,</line>
            <line>is washed with them, but relents not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>What a merit were it in death to take this poor maid</line>
            <line>from the world! What corruption in this life, that</line>
            <line>it will let this man live! But how out of this can she avail?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>It is a rupture that you may easily heal: and the</line>
            <line>cure of it not only saves your brother, but keeps</line>
            <line>you from dishonour in doing it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>Show me how, good father.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>This forenamed maid hath yet in her the continuance</line>
            <line>of her first affection: his unjust unkindness, that</line>
            <line>in all reason should have quenched her love, hath,</line>
            <line>like an impediment in the current, made it more</line>
            <line>violent and unruly. Go you to Angelo; answer his</line>
            <line>requiring with a plausible obedience; agree with</line>
            <line>his demands to the point; only refer yourself to</line>
            <line>this advantage, first, that your stay with him may</line>
            <line>not be long; that the time may have all shadow and</line>
            <line>silence in it; and the place answer to convenience.</line>
            <line>This being granted in course,--and now follows</line>
            <line>all,--we shall advise this wronged maid to stead up</line>
            <line>your appointment, go in your place; if the encounter</line>
            <line>acknowledge itself hereafter, it may compel him to</line>
            <line>her recompense: and here, by this, is your brother</line>
            <line>saved, your honour untainted, the poor Mariana</line>
            <line>advantaged, and the corrupt deputy scaled. The maid</line>
            <line>will I frame and make fit for his attempt. If you</line>
            <line>think well to carry this as you may, the doubleness</line>
            <line>of the benefit defends the deceit from reproof.</line>
            <line>What think you of it?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>The image of it gives me content already; and I</line>
            <line>trust it will grow to a most prosperous perfection.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>It lies much in your holding up. Haste you speedily</line>
            <line>to Angelo: if for this night he entreat you to his</line>
            <line>bed, give him promise of satisfaction. I will</line>
            <line>presently to Saint Luke's: there, at the moated</line>
            <line>grange, resides this dejected Mariana. At that</line>
            <line>place call upon me; and dispatch with Angelo, that</line>
            <line>it may be quickly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>I thank you for this comfort. Fare you well, good father.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt severally</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  The street before the prison.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter, on one side, DUKE VINCENTIO disguised as
before; on the other, ELBOW, and Officers with POMPEY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ELBOW</speaker>
            <line>Nay, if there be no remedy for it, but that you will</line>
            <line>needs buy and sell men and women like beasts, we</line>
            <line>shall have all the world drink brown and white bastard.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>O heavens! what stuff is here</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POMPEY</speaker>
            <line>'Twas never merry world since, of two usuries, the</line>
            <line>merriest was put down, and the worser allowed by</line>
            <line>order of law a furred gown to keep him warm; and</line>
            <line>furred with fox and lamb-skins too, to signify, that</line>
            <line>craft, being richer than innocency, stands for the facing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ELBOW</speaker>
            <line>Come your way, sir. 'Bless you, good father friar.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>And you, good brother father. What offence hath</line>
            <line>this man made you, sir?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ELBOW</speaker>
            <line>Marry, sir, he hath offended the law: and, sir, we</line>
            <line>take him to be a thief too, sir; for we have found</line>
            <line>upon him, sir, a strange picklock, which we have</line>
            <line>sent to the deputy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>Fie, sirrah! a bawd, a wicked bawd!</line>
            <line>The evil that thou causest to be done,</line>
            <line>That is thy means to live. Do thou but think</line>
            <line>What 'tis to cram a maw or clothe a back</line>
            <line>From such a filthy vice: say to thyself,</line>
            <line>From their abominable and beastly touches</line>
            <line>I drink, I eat, array myself, and live.</line>
            <line>Canst thou believe thy living is a life,</line>
            <line>So stinkingly depending? Go mend, go mend.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POMPEY</speaker>
            <line>Indeed, it does stink in some sort, sir; but yet,</line>
            <line>sir, I would prove--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>Nay, if the devil have given thee proofs for sin,</line>
            <line>Thou wilt prove his. Take him to prison, officer:</line>
            <line>Correction and instruction must both work</line>
            <line>Ere this rude beast will profit.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ELBOW</speaker>
            <line>He must before the deputy, sir; he has given him</line>
            <line>warning: the deputy cannot abide a whoremaster: if</line>
            <line>he be a whoremonger, and comes before him, he were</line>
            <line>as good go a mile on his errand.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>That we were all, as some would seem to be,</line>
            <line>From our faults, as faults from seeming, free!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ELBOW</speaker>
            <line>His neck will come to your waist,--a cord, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POMPEY</speaker>
            <line>I spy comfort; I cry bail. Here's a gentleman and a</line>
            <line>friend of mine.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter LUCIO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIO</speaker>
            <line>How now, noble Pompey! What, at the wheels of</line>
            <line>Caesar? art thou led in triumph? What, is there</line>
            <line>none of Pygmalion's images, newly made woman, to be</line>
            <line>had now, for putting the hand in the pocket and</line>
            <line>extracting it clutch'd? What reply, ha? What</line>
            <line>sayest thou to this tune, matter and method? Is't</line>
            <line>not drowned i' the last rain, ha? What sayest</line>
            <line>thou, Trot? Is the world as it was, man? Which is</line>
            <line>the way? Is it sad, and few words? or how? The</line>
            <line>trick of it?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>Still thus, and thus; still worse!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIO</speaker>
            <line>How doth my dear morsel, thy mistress? Procures she</line>
            <line>still, ha?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POMPEY</speaker>
            <line>Troth, sir, she hath eaten up all her beef, and she</line>
            <line>is herself in the tub.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIO</speaker>
            <line>Why, 'tis good; it is the right of it; it must be</line>
            <line>so: ever your fresh whore and your powdered bawd:</line>
            <line>an unshunned consequence; it must be so. Art going</line>
            <line>to prison, Pompey?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POMPEY</speaker>
            <line>Yes, faith, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIO</speaker>
            <line>Why, 'tis not amiss, Pompey. Farewell: go, say I</line>
            <line>sent thee thither. For debt, Pompey? or how?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ELBOW</speaker>
            <line>For being a bawd, for being a bawd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIO</speaker>
            <line>Well, then, imprison him: if imprisonment be the</line>
            <line>due of a bawd, why, 'tis his right: bawd is he</line>
            <line>doubtless, and of antiquity too; bawd-born.</line>
            <line>Farewell, good Pompey. Commend me to the prison,</line>
            <line>Pompey: you will turn good husband now, Pompey; you</line>
            <line>will keep the house.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POMPEY</speaker>
            <line>I hope, sir, your good worship will be my bail.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIO</speaker>
            <line>No, indeed, will I not, Pompey; it is not the wear.</line>
            <line>I will pray, Pompey, to increase your bondage: If</line>
            <line>you take it not patiently, why, your mettle is the</line>
            <line>more. Adieu, trusty Pompey. 'Bless you, friar.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>And you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIO</speaker>
            <line>Does Bridget paint still, Pompey, ha?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ELBOW</speaker>
            <line>Come your ways, sir; come.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POMPEY</speaker>
            <line>You will not bail me, then, sir?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIO</speaker>
            <line>Then, Pompey, nor now. What news abroad, friar?</line>
            <line>what news?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ELBOW</speaker>
            <line>Come your ways, sir; come.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIO</speaker>
            <line>Go to kennel, Pompey; go.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt ELBOW, POMPEY and Officers</stagedir>
            <line>What news, friar, of the duke?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>I know none. Can you tell me of any?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIO</speaker>
            <line>Some say he is with the Emperor of Russia; other</line>
            <line>some, he is in Rome: but where is he, think you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>I know not where; but wheresoever, I wish him well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIO</speaker>
            <line>It was a mad fantastical trick of him to steal from</line>
            <line>the state, and usurp the beggary he was never born</line>
            <line>to. Lord Angelo dukes it well in his absence; he</line>
            <line>puts transgression to 't.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>He does well in 't.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIO</speaker>
            <line>A little more lenity to lechery would do no harm in</line>
            <line>him: something too crabbed that way, friar.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>It is too general a vice, and severity must cure it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIO</speaker>
            <line>Yes, in good sooth, the vice is of a great kindred;</line>
            <line>it is well allied: but it is impossible to extirp</line>
            <line>it quite, friar, till eating and drinking be put</line>
            <line>down. They say this Angelo was not made by man and</line>
            <line>woman after this downright way of creation: is it</line>
            <line>true, think you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>How should he be made, then?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIO</speaker>
            <line>Some report a sea-maid spawned him; some, that he</line>
            <line>was begot between two stock-fishes. But it is</line>
            <line>certain that when he makes water his urine is</line>
            <line>congealed ice; that I know to be true: and he is a</line>
            <line>motion generative; that's infallible.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>You are pleasant, sir, and speak apace.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIO</speaker>
            <line>Why, what a ruthless thing is this in him, for the</line>
            <line>rebellion of a codpiece to take away the life of a</line>
            <line>man! Would the duke that is absent have done this?</line>
            <line>Ere he would have hanged a man for the getting a</line>
            <line>hundred bastards, he would have paid for the nursing</line>
            <line>a thousand: he had some feeling of the sport: he</line>
            <line>knew the service, and that instructed him to mercy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>I never heard the absent duke much detected for</line>
            <line>women; he was not inclined that way.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIO</speaker>
            <line>O, sir, you are deceived.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>'Tis not possible.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIO</speaker>
            <line>Who, not the duke? yes, your beggar of fifty; and</line>
            <line>his use was to put a ducat in her clack-dish: the</line>
            <line>duke had crotchets in him. He would be drunk too;</line>
            <line>that let me inform you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>You do him wrong, surely.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIO</speaker>
            <line>Sir, I was an inward of his. A shy fellow was the</line>
            <line>duke: and I believe I know the cause of his</line>
            <line>withdrawing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>What, I prithee, might be the cause?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIO</speaker>
            <line>No, pardon; 'tis a secret must be locked within the</line>
            <line>teeth and the lips: but this I can let you</line>
            <line>understand, the greater file of the subject held the</line>
            <line>duke to be wise.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>Wise! why, no question but he was.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIO</speaker>
            <line>A very superficial, ignorant, unweighing fellow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>Either this is the envy in you, folly, or mistaking:</line>
            <line>the very stream of his life and the business he hath</line>
            <line>helmed must upon a warranted need give him a better</line>
            <line>proclamation. Let him be but testimonied in his own</line>
            <line>bringings-forth, and he shall appear to the</line>
            <line>envious a scholar, a statesman and a soldier.</line>
            <line>Therefore you speak unskilfully: or if your</line>
            <line>knowledge be more it is much darkened in your malice.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIO</speaker>
            <line>Sir, I know him, and I love him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>Love talks with better knowledge, and knowledge with</line>
            <line>dearer love.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIO</speaker>
            <line>Come, sir, I know what I know.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>I can hardly believe that, since you know not what</line>
            <line>you speak. But, if ever the duke return, as our</line>
            <line>prayers are he may, let me desire you to make your</line>
            <line>answer before him. If it be honest you have spoke,</line>
            <line>you have courage to maintain it: I am bound to call</line>
            <line>upon you; and, I pray you, your name?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIO</speaker>
            <line>Sir, my name is Lucio; well known to the duke.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>He shall know you better, sir, if I may live to</line>
            <line>report you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIO</speaker>
            <line>I fear you not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>O, you hope the duke will return no more; or you</line>
            <line>imagine me too unhurtful an opposite. But indeed I</line>
            <line>can do you little harm; you'll forswear this again.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIO</speaker>
            <line>I'll be hanged first: thou art deceived in me,</line>
            <line>friar. But no more of this. Canst thou tell if</line>
            <line>Claudio die to-morrow or no?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>Why should he die, sir?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIO</speaker>
            <line>Why? For filling a bottle with a tundish. I would</line>
            <line>the duke we talk of were returned again: the</line>
            <line>ungenitured agent will unpeople the province with</line>
            <line>continency; sparrows must not build in his</line>
            <line>house-eaves, because they are lecherous. The duke</line>
            <line>yet would have dark deeds darkly answered; he would</line>
            <line>never bring them to light: would he were returned!</line>
            <line>Marry, this Claudio is condemned for untrussing.</line>
            <line>Farewell, good friar: I prithee, pray for me. The</line>
            <line>duke, I say to thee again, would eat mutton on</line>
            <line>Fridays. He's not past it yet, and I say to thee,</line>
            <line>he would mouth with a beggar, though she smelt brown</line>
            <line>bread and garlic: say that I said so. Farewell.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>No might nor greatness in mortality</line>
            <line>Can censure 'scape; back-wounding calumny</line>
            <line>The whitest virtue strikes. What king so strong</line>
            <line>Can tie the gall up in the slanderous tongue?</line>
            <line>But who comes here?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter ESCALUS, Provost, and Officers with MISTRESS OVERDONE</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ESCALUS</speaker>
            <line>Go; away with her to prison!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS OVERDONE</speaker>
            <line>Good my lord, be good to me; your honour is accounted</line>
            <line>a merciful man; good my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ESCALUS</speaker>
            <line>Double and treble admonition, and still forfeit in</line>
            <line>the same kind! This would make mercy swear and play</line>
            <line>the tyrant.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Provost</speaker>
            <line>A bawd of eleven years' continuance, may it please</line>
            <line>your honour.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MISTRESS OVERDONE</speaker>
            <line>My lord, this is one Lucio's information against me.</line>
            <line>Mistress Kate Keepdown was with child by him in the</line>
            <line>duke's time; he promised her marriage: his child</line>
            <line>is a year and a quarter old, come Philip and Jacob:</line>
            <line>I have kept it myself; and see how he goes about to abuse me!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ESCALUS</speaker>
            <line>That fellow is a fellow of much licence: let him be</line>
            <line>called before us. Away with her to prison! Go to;</line>
            <line>no more words.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt Officers with MISTRESS OVERDONE</stagedir>
            <line>Provost, my brother Angelo will not be altered;</line>
            <line>Claudio must die to-morrow: let him be furnished</line>
            <line>with divines, and have all charitable preparation.</line>
            <line>if my brother wrought by my pity, it should not be</line>
            <line>so with him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Provost</speaker>
            <line>So please you, this friar hath been with him, and</line>
            <line>advised him for the entertainment of death.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ESCALUS</speaker>
            <line>Good even, good father.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>Bliss and goodness on you!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ESCALUS</speaker>
            <line>Of whence are you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>Not of this country, though my chance is now</line>
            <line>To use it for my time: I am a brother</line>
            <line>Of gracious order, late come from the See</line>
            <line>In special business from his holiness.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ESCALUS</speaker>
            <line>What news abroad i' the world?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>None, but that there is so great a fever on</line>
            <line>goodness, that the dissolution of it must cure it:</line>
            <line>novelty is only in request; and it is as dangerous</line>
            <line>to be aged in any kind of course, as it is virtuous</line>
            <line>to be constant in any undertaking. There is scarce</line>
            <line>truth enough alive to make societies secure; but</line>
            <line>security enough to make fellowships accurst: much</line>
            <line>upon this riddle runs the wisdom of the world. This</line>
            <line>news is old enough, yet it is every day's news. I</line>
            <line>pray you, sir, of what disposition was the duke?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ESCALUS</speaker>
            <line>One that, above all other strifes, contended</line>
            <line>especially to know himself.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>What pleasure was he given to?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ESCALUS</speaker>
            <line>Rather rejoicing to see another merry, than merry at</line>
            <line>any thing which professed to make him rejoice: a</line>
            <line>gentleman of all temperance. But leave we him to</line>
            <line>his events, with a prayer they may prove prosperous;</line>
            <line>and let me desire to know how you find Claudio</line>
            <line>prepared. I am made to understand that you have</line>
            <line>lent him visitation.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>He professes to have received no sinister measure</line>
            <line>from his judge, but most willingly humbles himself</line>
            <line>to the determination of justice: yet had he framed</line>
            <line>to himself, by the instruction of his frailty, many</line>
            <line>deceiving promises of life; which I by my good</line>
            <line>leisure have discredited to him, and now is he</line>
            <line>resolved to die.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ESCALUS</speaker>
            <line>You have paid the heavens your function, and the</line>
            <line>prisoner the very debt of your calling. I have</line>
            <line>laboured for the poor gentleman to the extremest</line>
            <line>shore of my modesty: but my brother justice have I</line>
            <line>found so severe, that he hath forced me to tell him</line>
            <line>he is indeed Justice.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>If his own life answer the straitness of his</line>
            <line>proceeding, it shall become him well; wherein if he</line>
            <line>chance to fail, he hath sentenced himself.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ESCALUS</speaker>
            <line>I am going to visit the prisoner. Fare you well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>Peace be with you!</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt ESCALUS and Provost</stagedir>
            <line>He who the sword of heaven will bear</line>
            <line>Should be as holy as severe;</line>
            <line>Pattern in himself to know,</line>
            <line>Grace to stand, and virtue go;</line>
            <line>More nor less to others paying</line>
            <line>Than by self-offences weighing.</line>
            <line>Shame to him whose cruel striking</line>
            <line>Kills for faults of his own liking!</line>
            <line>Twice treble shame on Angelo,</line>
            <line>To weed my vice and let his grow!</line>
            <line>O, what may man within him hide,</line>
            <line>Though angel on the outward side!</line>
            <line>How may likeness made in crimes,</line>
            <line>Making practise on the times,</line>
            <line>To draw with idle spiders' strings</line>
            <line>Most ponderous and substantial things!</line>
            <line>Craft against vice I must apply:</line>
            <line>With Angelo to-night shall lie</line>
            <line>His old betrothed but despised;</line>
            <line>So disguise shall, by the disguised,</line>
            <line>Pay with falsehood false exacting,</line>
            <line>And perform an old contracting.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>