<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:shakespear:dtd:act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-2">
   <title>ACT II</title>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  A hall In ANGELO's house.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter ANGELO, ESCALUS, and a Justice, Provost,
Officers, and other Attendants, behind</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>We must not make a scarecrow of the law,</line>
            <line>Setting it up to fear the birds of prey,</line>
            <line>And let it keep one shape, till custom make it</line>
            <line>Their perch and not their terror.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ESCALUS</speaker>
            <line>Ay, but yet</line>
            <line>Let us be keen, and rather cut a little,</line>
            <line>Than fall, and bruise to death. Alas, this gentleman</line>
            <line>Whom I would save, had a most noble father!</line>
            <line>Let but your honour know,</line>
            <line>Whom I believe to be most strait in virtue,</line>
            <line>That, in the working of your own affections,</line>
            <line>Had time cohered with place or place with wishing,</line>
            <line>Or that the resolute acting of your blood</line>
            <line>Could have attain'd the effect of your own purpose,</line>
            <line>Whether you had not sometime in your life</line>
            <line>Err'd in this point which now you censure him,</line>
            <line>And pull'd the law upon you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>'Tis one thing to be tempted, Escalus,</line>
            <line>Another thing to fall. I not deny,</line>
            <line>The jury, passing on the prisoner's life,</line>
            <line>May in the sworn twelve have a thief or two</line>
            <line>Guiltier than him they try. What's open made to justice,</line>
            <line>That justice seizes: what know the laws</line>
            <line>That thieves do pass on thieves? 'Tis very pregnant,</line>
            <line>The jewel that we find, we stoop and take't</line>
            <line>Because we see it; but what we do not see</line>
            <line>We tread upon, and never think of it.</line>
            <line>You may not so extenuate his offence</line>
            <line>For I have had such faults; but rather tell me,</line>
            <line>When I, that censure him, do so offend,</line>
            <line>Let mine own judgment pattern out my death,</line>
            <line>And nothing come in partial. Sir, he must die.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ESCALUS</speaker>
            <line>Be it as your wisdom will.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>Where is the provost?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Provost</speaker>
            <line>Here, if it like your honour.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>See that Claudio</line>
            <line>Be executed by nine to-morrow morning:</line>
            <line>Bring him his confessor, let him be prepared;</line>
            <line>For that's the utmost of his pilgrimage.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit Provost</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ESCALUS</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  Well, heaven forgive him! and forgive us all!</line>
            <line>Some rise by sin, and some by virtue fall:</line>
            <line>Some run from brakes of ice, and answer none:</line>
            <line>And some condemned for a fault alone.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter ELBOW, and Officers with FROTH and POMPEY</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ELBOW</speaker>
            <line>Come, bring them away: if these be good people in</line>
            <line>a commonweal that do nothing but use their abuses in</line>
            <line>common houses, I know no law: bring them away.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>How now, sir! What's your name? and what's the matter?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ELBOW</speaker>
            <line>If it Please your honour, I am the poor duke's</line>
            <line>constable, and my name is Elbow: I do lean upon</line>
            <line>justice, sir, and do bring in here before your good</line>
            <line>honour two notorious benefactors.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>Benefactors? Well; what benefactors are they? are</line>
            <line>they not malefactors?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ELBOW</speaker>
            <line>If it? please your honour, I know not well what they</line>
            <line>are: but precise villains they are, that I am sure</line>
            <line>of; and void of all profanation in the world that</line>
            <line>good Christians ought to have.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ESCALUS</speaker>
            <line>This comes off well; here's a wise officer.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>Go to: what quality are they of? Elbow is your</line>
            <line>name? why dost thou not speak, Elbow?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POMPEY</speaker>
            <line>He cannot, sir; he's out at elbow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>What are you, sir?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ELBOW</speaker>
            <line>He, sir! a tapster, sir; parcel-bawd; one that</line>
            <line>serves a bad woman; whose house, sir, was, as they</line>
            <line>say, plucked down in the suburbs; and now she</line>
            <line>professes a hot-house, which, I think, is a very ill house too.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ESCALUS</speaker>
            <line>How know you that?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ELBOW</speaker>
            <line>My wife, sir, whom I detest before heaven and your honour,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ESCALUS</speaker>
            <line>How? thy wife?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ELBOW</speaker>
            <line>Ay, sir; whom, I thank heaven, is an honest woman,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ESCALUS</speaker>
            <line>Dost thou detest her therefore?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ELBOW</speaker>
            <line>I say, sir, I will detest myself also, as well as</line>
            <line>she, that this house, if it be not a bawd's house,</line>
            <line>it is pity of her life, for it is a naughty house.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ESCALUS</speaker>
            <line>How dost thou know that, constable?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ELBOW</speaker>
            <line>Marry, sir, by my wife; who, if she had been a woman</line>
            <line>cardinally given, might have been accused in</line>
            <line>fornication, adultery, and all uncleanliness there.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ESCALUS</speaker>
            <line>By the woman's means?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ELBOW</speaker>
            <line>Ay, sir, by Mistress Overdone's means: but as she</line>
            <line>spit in his face, so she defied him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POMPEY</speaker>
            <line>Sir, if it please your honour, this is not so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ELBOW</speaker>
            <line>Prove it before these varlets here, thou honourable</line>
            <line>man; prove it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ESCALUS</speaker>
            <line>Do you hear how he misplaces?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POMPEY</speaker>
            <line>Sir, she came in great with child; and longing,</line>
            <line>saving your honour's reverence, for stewed prunes;</line>
            <line>sir, we had but two in the house, which at that very</line>
            <line>distant time stood, as it were, in a fruit-dish, a</line>
            <line>dish of some three-pence; your honours have seen</line>
            <line>such dishes; they are not China dishes, but very</line>
            <line>good dishes,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ESCALUS</speaker>
            <line>Go to, go to: no matter for the dish, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POMPEY</speaker>
            <line>No, indeed, sir, not of a pin; you are therein in</line>
            <line>the right: but to the point. As I say, this</line>
            <line>Mistress Elbow, being, as I say, with child, and</line>
            <line>being great-bellied, and longing, as I said, for</line>
            <line>prunes; and having but two in the dish, as I said,</line>
            <line>Master Froth here, this very man, having eaten the</line>
            <line>rest, as I said, and, as I say, paying for them very</line>
            <line>honestly; for, as you know, Master Froth, I could</line>
            <line>not give you three-pence again.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FROTH</speaker>
            <line>No, indeed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POMPEY</speaker>
            <line>Very well: you being then, if you be remembered,</line>
            <line>cracking the stones of the foresaid prunes,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FROTH</speaker>
            <line>Ay, so I did indeed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POMPEY</speaker>
            <line>Why, very well; I telling you then, if you be</line>
            <line>remembered, that such a one and such a one were past</line>
            <line>cure of the thing you wot of, unless they kept very</line>
            <line>good diet, as I told you,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FROTH</speaker>
            <line>All this is true.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POMPEY</speaker>
            <line>Why, very well, then,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ESCALUS</speaker>
            <line>Come, you are a tedious fool: to the purpose. What</line>
            <line>was done to Elbow's wife, that he hath cause to</line>
            <line>complain of? Come me to what was done to her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POMPEY</speaker>
            <line>Sir, your honour cannot come to that yet.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ESCALUS</speaker>
            <line>No, sir, nor I mean it not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POMPEY</speaker>
            <line>Sir, but you shall come to it, by your honour's</line>
            <line>leave. And, I beseech you, look into Master Froth</line>
            <line>here, sir; a man of four-score pound a year; whose</line>
            <line>father died at Hallowmas: was't not at Hallowmas,</line>
            <line>Master Froth?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FROTH</speaker>
            <line>All-hallond eve.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POMPEY</speaker>
            <line>Why, very well; I hope here be truths. He, sir,</line>
            <line>sitting, as I say, in a lower chair, sir; 'twas in</line>
            <line>the Bunch of Grapes, where indeed you have a delight</line>
            <line>to sit, have you not?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FROTH</speaker>
            <line>I have so; because it is an open room and good for winter.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POMPEY</speaker>
            <line>Why, very well, then; I hope here be truths.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>This will last out a night in Russia,</line>
            <line>When nights are longest there: I'll take my leave.</line>
            <line>And leave you to the hearing of the cause;</line>
            <line>Hoping you'll find good cause to whip them all.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ESCALUS</speaker>
            <line>I think no less. Good morrow to your lordship.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit ANGELO</stagedir>
            <line>Now, sir, come on: what was done to Elbow's wife, once more?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POMPEY</speaker>
            <line>Once, sir? there was nothing done to her once.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ELBOW</speaker>
            <line>I beseech you, sir, ask him what this man did to my wife.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POMPEY</speaker>
            <line>I beseech your honour, ask me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ESCALUS</speaker>
            <line>Well, sir; what did this gentleman to her?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POMPEY</speaker>
            <line>I beseech you, sir, look in this gentleman's face.</line>
            <line>Good Master Froth, look upon his honour; 'tis for a</line>
            <line>good purpose. Doth your honour mark his face?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ESCALUS</speaker>
            <line>Ay, sir, very well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POMPEY</speaker>
            <line>Nay; I beseech you, mark it well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ESCALUS</speaker>
            <line>Well, I do so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POMPEY</speaker>
            <line>Doth your honour see any harm in his face?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ESCALUS</speaker>
            <line>Why, no.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POMPEY</speaker>
            <line>I'll be supposed upon a book, his face is the worst</line>
            <line>thing about him. Good, then; if his face be the</line>
            <line>worst thing about him, how could Master Froth do the</line>
            <line>constable's wife any harm? I would know that of</line>
            <line>your honour.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ESCALUS</speaker>
            <line>He's in the right. Constable, what say you to it?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ELBOW</speaker>
            <line>First, an it like you, the house is a respected</line>
            <line>house; next, this is a respected fellow; and his</line>
            <line>mistress is a respected woman.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POMPEY</speaker>
            <line>By this hand, sir, his wife is a more respected</line>
            <line>person than any of us all.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ELBOW</speaker>
            <line>Varlet, thou liest; thou liest, wicked varlet! the</line>
            <line>time has yet to come that she was ever respected</line>
            <line>with man, woman, or child.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POMPEY</speaker>
            <line>Sir, she was respected with him before he married with her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ESCALUS</speaker>
            <line>Which is the wiser here? Justice or Iniquity? Is</line>
            <line>this true?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ELBOW</speaker>
            <line>O thou caitiff! O thou varlet! O thou wicked</line>
            <line>Hannibal! I respected with her before I was married</line>
            <line>to her! If ever I was respected with her, or she</line>
            <line>with me, let not your worship think me the poor</line>
            <line>duke's officer. Prove this, thou wicked Hannibal, or</line>
            <line>I'll have mine action of battery on thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ESCALUS</speaker>
            <line>If he took you a box o' the ear, you might have your</line>
            <line>action of slander too.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ELBOW</speaker>
            <line>Marry, I thank your good worship for it. What is't</line>
            <line>your worship's pleasure I shall do with this wicked caitiff?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ESCALUS</speaker>
            <line>Truly, officer, because he hath some offences in him</line>
            <line>that thou wouldst discover if thou couldst, let him</line>
            <line>continue in his courses till thou knowest what they</line>
            <line>are.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ELBOW</speaker>
            <line>Marry, I thank your worship for it. Thou seest, thou</line>
            <line>wicked varlet, now, what's come upon thee: thou art</line>
            <line>to continue now, thou varlet; thou art to continue.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ESCALUS</speaker>
            <line>Where were you born, friend?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FROTH</speaker>
            <line>Here in Vienna, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ESCALUS</speaker>
            <line>Are you of fourscore pounds a year?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FROTH</speaker>
            <line>Yes, an't please you, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ESCALUS</speaker>
            <line>So. What trade are you of, sir?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POMPHEY</speaker>
            <line>Tapster; a poor widow's tapster.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ESCALUS</speaker>
            <line>Your mistress' name?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POMPHEY</speaker>
            <line>Mistress Overdone.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ESCALUS</speaker>
            <line>Hath she had any more than one husband?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POMPEY</speaker>
            <line>Nine, sir; Overdone by the last.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ESCALUS</speaker>
            <line>Nine! Come hither to me, Master Froth. Master</line>
            <line>Froth, I would not have you acquainted with</line>
            <line>tapsters: they will draw you, Master Froth, and you</line>
            <line>will hang them. Get you gone, and let me hear no</line>
            <line>more of you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FROTH</speaker>
            <line>I thank your worship. For mine own part, I never</line>
            <line>come into any room in a tap-house, but I am drawn</line>
            <line>in.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ESCALUS</speaker>
            <line>Well, no more of it, Master Froth: farewell.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit FROTH</stagedir>
            <line>Come you hither to me, Master tapster. What's your</line>
            <line>name, Master tapster?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POMPEY</speaker>
            <line>Pompey.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ESCALUS</speaker>
            <line>What else?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POMPEY</speaker>
            <line>Bum, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ESCALUS</speaker>
            <line>Troth, and your bum is the greatest thing about you;</line>
            <line>so that in the beastliest sense you are Pompey the</line>
            <line>Great. Pompey, you are partly a bawd, Pompey,</line>
            <line>howsoever you colour it in being a tapster, are you</line>
            <line>not? come, tell me true: it shall be the better for you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POMPEY</speaker>
            <line>Truly, sir, I am a poor fellow that would live.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ESCALUS</speaker>
            <line>How would you live, Pompey? by being a bawd? What</line>
            <line>do you think of the trade, Pompey? is it a lawful trade?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POMPEY</speaker>
            <line>If the law would allow it, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ESCALUS</speaker>
            <line>But the law will not allow it, Pompey; nor it shall</line>
            <line>not be allowed in Vienna.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POMPEY</speaker>
            <line>Does your worship mean to geld and splay all the</line>
            <line>youth of the city?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ESCALUS</speaker>
            <line>No, Pompey.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POMPEY</speaker>
            <line>Truly, sir, in my poor opinion, they will to't then.</line>
            <line>If your worship will take order for the drabs and</line>
            <line>the knaves, you need not to fear the bawds.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ESCALUS</speaker>
            <line>There are pretty orders beginning, I can tell you:</line>
            <line>it is but heading and hanging.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POMPEY</speaker>
            <line>If you head and hang all that offend that way but</line>
            <line>for ten year together, you'll be glad to give out a</line>
            <line>commission for more heads: if this law hold in</line>
            <line>Vienna ten year, I'll rent the fairest house in it</line>
            <line>after three-pence a bay: if you live to see this</line>
            <line>come to pass, say Pompey told you so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ESCALUS</speaker>
            <line>Thank you, good Pompey; and, in requital of your</line>
            <line>prophecy, hark you: I advise you, let me not find</line>
            <line>you before me again upon any complaint whatsoever;</line>
            <line>no, not for dwelling where you do: if I do, Pompey,</line>
            <line>I shall beat you to your tent, and prove a shrewd</line>
            <line>Caesar to you; in plain dealing, Pompey, I shall</line>
            <line>have you whipt: so, for this time, Pompey, fare you well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POMPEY</speaker>
            <line>I thank your worship for your good counsel:</line>
            <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>
            <line>but I shall follow it as the flesh and fortune shall</line>
            <line>better determine.</line>
            <line>Whip me? No, no; let carman whip his jade:</line>
            <line>The valiant heart is not whipt out of his trade.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ESCALUS</speaker>
            <line>Come hither to me, Master Elbow; come hither, Master</line>
            <line>constable. How long have you been in this place of constable?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ELBOW</speaker>
            <line>Seven year and a half, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ESCALUS</speaker>
            <line>I thought, by your readiness in the office, you had</line>
            <line>continued in it some time. You say, seven years together?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ELBOW</speaker>
            <line>And a half, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ESCALUS</speaker>
            <line>Alas, it hath been great pains to you. They do you</line>
            <line>wrong to put you so oft upon 't: are there not men</line>
            <line>in your ward sufficient to serve it?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ELBOW</speaker>
            <line>Faith, sir, few of any wit in such matters: as they</line>
            <line>are chosen, they are glad to choose me for them; I</line>
            <line>do it for some piece of money, and go through with</line>
            <line>all.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ESCALUS</speaker>
            <line>Look you bring me in the names of some six or seven,</line>
            <line>the most sufficient of your parish.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ELBOW</speaker>
            <line>To your worship's house, sir?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ESCALUS</speaker>
            <line>To my house. Fare you well.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit ELBOW</stagedir>
            <line>What's o'clock, think you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Justice</speaker>
            <line>Eleven, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ESCALUS</speaker>
            <line>I pray you home to dinner with me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Justice</speaker>
            <line>I humbly thank you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ESCALUS</speaker>
            <line>It grieves me for the death of Claudio;</line>
            <line>But there's no remedy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Justice</speaker>
            <line>Lord Angelo is severe.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ESCALUS</speaker>
            <line>It is but needful:</line>
            <line>Mercy is not itself, that oft looks so;</line>
            <line>Pardon is still the nurse of second woe:</line>
            <line>But yet,--poor Claudio! There is no remedy.</line>
            <line>Come, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  Another room in the same.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter Provost and a Servant</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>He's hearing of a cause; he will come straight</line>
            <line>I'll tell him of you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Provost</speaker>
            <line>Pray you, do.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit Servant</stagedir>
            <line>I'll know</line>
            <line>His pleasure; may be he will relent. Alas,</line>
            <line>He hath but as offended in a dream!</line>
            <line>All sects, all ages smack of this vice; and he</line>
            <line>To die for't!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter ANGELO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>Now, what's the matter. Provost?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Provost</speaker>
            <line>Is it your will Claudio shall die tomorrow?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>Did not I tell thee yea? hadst thou not order?</line>
            <line>Why dost thou ask again?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Provost</speaker>
            <line>Lest I might be too rash:</line>
            <line>Under your good correction, I have seen,</line>
            <line>When, after execution, judgment hath</line>
            <line>Repented o'er his doom.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>Go to; let that be mine:</line>
            <line>Do you your office, or give up your place,</line>
            <line>And you shall well be spared.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Provost</speaker>
            <line>I crave your honour's pardon.</line>
            <line>What shall be done, sir, with the groaning Juliet?</line>
            <line>She's very near her hour.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>Dispose of her</line>
            <line>To some more fitter place, and that with speed.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter Servant</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>Here is the sister of the man condemn'd</line>
            <line>Desires access to you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>Hath he a sister?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Provost</speaker>
            <line>Ay, my good lord; a very virtuous maid,</line>
            <line>And to be shortly of a sisterhood,</line>
            <line>If not already.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>Well, let her be admitted.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit Servant</stagedir>
            <line>See you the fornicatress be removed:</line>
            <line>Let have needful, but not lavish, means;</line>
            <line>There shall be order for't.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter ISABELLA and LUCIO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Provost</speaker>
            <line>God save your honour!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>Stay a little while.</line>
            <stagedir>To ISABELLA</stagedir>
            <line>You're welcome: what's your will?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>I am a woeful suitor to your honour,</line>
            <line>Please but your honour hear me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>Well; what's your suit?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>There is a vice that most I do abhor,</line>
            <line>And most desire should meet the blow of justice;</line>
            <line>For which I would not plead, but that I must;</line>
            <line>For which I must not plead, but that I am</line>
            <line>At war 'twixt will and will not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>Well; the matter?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>I have a brother is condemn'd to die:</line>
            <line>I do beseech you, let it be his fault,</line>
            <line>And not my brother.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Provost</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  Heaven give thee moving graces!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>Condemn the fault and not the actor of it?</line>
            <line>Why, every fault's condemn'd ere it be done:</line>
            <line>Mine were the very cipher of a function,</line>
            <line>To fine the faults whose fine stands in record,</line>
            <line>And let go by the actor.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>O just but severe law!</line>
            <line>I had a brother, then. Heaven keep your honour!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIO</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside to ISABELLA</stagedir>  Give't not o'er so: to him</line>
            <line>again, entreat him;</line>
            <line>Kneel down before him, hang upon his gown:</line>
            <line>You are too cold; if you should need a pin,</line>
            <line>You could not with more tame a tongue desire it:</line>
            <line>To him, I say!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>Must he needs die?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>Maiden, no remedy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>Yes; I do think that you might pardon him,</line>
            <line>And neither heaven nor man grieve at the mercy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>I will not do't.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>But can you, if you would?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>Look, what I will not, that I cannot do.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>But might you do't, and do the world no wrong,</line>
            <line>If so your heart were touch'd with that remorse</line>
            <line>As mine is to him?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>He's sentenced; 'tis too late.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIO</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside to ISABELLA</stagedir>  You are too cold.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>Too late? why, no; I, that do speak a word.</line>
            <line>May call it back again. Well, believe this,</line>
            <line>No ceremony that to great ones 'longs,</line>
            <line>Not the king's crown, nor the deputed sword,</line>
            <line>The marshal's truncheon, nor the judge's robe,</line>
            <line>Become them with one half so good a grace</line>
            <line>As mercy does.</line>
            <line>If he had been as you and you as he,</line>
            <line>You would have slipt like him; but he, like you,</line>
            <line>Would not have been so stern.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>Pray you, be gone.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>I would to heaven I had your potency,</line>
            <line>And you were Isabel! should it then be thus?</line>
            <line>No; I would tell what 'twere to be a judge,</line>
            <line>And what a prisoner.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIO</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside to ISABELLA</stagedir>
            </line>
            <line>Ay, touch him; there's the vein.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>Your brother is a forfeit of the law,</line>
            <line>And you but waste your words.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>Alas, alas!</line>
            <line>Why, all the souls that were were forfeit once;</line>
            <line>And He that might the vantage best have took</line>
            <line>Found out the remedy. How would you be,</line>
            <line>If He, which is the top of judgment, should</line>
            <line>But judge you as you are? O, think on that;</line>
            <line>And mercy then will breathe within your lips,</line>
            <line>Like man new made.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>Be you content, fair maid;</line>
            <line>It is the law, not I condemn your brother:</line>
            <line>Were he my kinsman, brother, or my son,</line>
            <line>It should be thus with him: he must die tomorrow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>To-morrow! O, that's sudden! Spare him, spare him!</line>
            <line>He's not prepared for death. Even for our kitchens</line>
            <line>We kill the fowl of season: shall we serve heaven</line>
            <line>With less respect than we do minister</line>
            <line>To our gross selves? Good, good my lord, bethink you;</line>
            <line>Who is it that hath died for this offence?</line>
            <line>There's many have committed it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIO</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside to ISABELLA</stagedir>           Ay, well said.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>The law hath not been dead, though it hath slept:</line>
            <line>Those many had not dared to do that evil,</line>
            <line>If the first that did the edict infringe</line>
            <line>Had answer'd for his deed: now 'tis awake</line>
            <line>Takes note of what is done; and, like a prophet,</line>
            <line>Looks in a glass, that shows what future evils,</line>
            <line>Either new, or by remissness new-conceived,</line>
            <line>And so in progress to be hatch'd and born,</line>
            <line>Are now to have no successive degrees,</line>
            <line>But, ere they live, to end.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>Yet show some pity.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>I show it most of all when I show justice;</line>
            <line>For then I pity those I do not know,</line>
            <line>Which a dismiss'd offence would after gall;</line>
            <line>And do him right that, answering one foul wrong,</line>
            <line>Lives not to act another. Be satisfied;</line>
            <line>Your brother dies to-morrow; be content.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>So you must be the first that gives this sentence,</line>
            <line>And he, that suffer's. O, it is excellent</line>
            <line>To have a giant's strength; but it is tyrannous</line>
            <line>To use it like a giant.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIO</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside to ISABELLA</stagedir>   That's well said.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>Could great men thunder</line>
            <line>As Jove himself does, Jove would ne'er be quiet,</line>
            <line>For every pelting, petty officer</line>
            <line>Would use his heaven for thunder;</line>
            <line>Nothing but thunder! Merciful Heaven,</line>
            <line>Thou rather with thy sharp and sulphurous bolt</line>
            <line>Split'st the unwedgeable and gnarled oak</line>
            <line>Than the soft myrtle: but man, proud man,</line>
            <line>Drest in a little brief authority,</line>
            <line>Most ignorant of what he's most assured,</line>
            <line>His glassy essence, like an angry ape,</line>
            <line>Plays such fantastic tricks before high heaven</line>
            <line>As make the angels weep; who, with our spleens,</line>
            <line>Would all themselves laugh mortal.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIO</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside to ISABELLA</stagedir>  O, to him, to him, wench! he</line>
            <line>will relent;</line>
            <line>He's coming; I perceive 't.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Provost</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  Pray heaven she win him!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>We cannot weigh our brother with ourself:</line>
            <line>Great men may jest with saints; 'tis wit in them,</line>
            <line>But in the less foul profanation.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIO</speaker>
            <line>Thou'rt i' the right, girl; more o, that.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>That in the captain's but a choleric word,</line>
            <line>Which in the soldier is flat blasphemy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIO</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside to ISABELLA</stagedir>  Art avised o' that? more on 't.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>Why do you put these sayings upon me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>Because authority, though it err like others,</line>
            <line>Hath yet a kind of medicine in itself,</line>
            <line>That skins the vice o' the top. Go to your bosom;</line>
            <line>Knock there, and ask your heart what it doth know</line>
            <line>That's like my brother's fault: if it confess</line>
            <line>A natural guiltiness such as is his,</line>
            <line>Let it not sound a thought upon your tongue</line>
            <line>Against my brother's life.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>                  She speaks, and 'tis</line>
            <line>Such sense, that my sense breeds with it. Fare you well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>Gentle my lord, turn back.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>I will bethink me: come again tomorrow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>Hark how I'll bribe you: good my lord, turn back.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>How! bribe me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>Ay, with such gifts that heaven shall share with you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIO</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside to ISABELLA</stagedir>  You had marr'd all else.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>Not with fond shekels of the tested gold,</line>
            <line>Or stones whose rates are either rich or poor</line>
            <line>As fancy values them; but with true prayers</line>
            <line>That shall be up at heaven and enter there</line>
            <line>Ere sun-rise, prayers from preserved souls,</line>
            <line>From fasting maids whose minds are dedicate</line>
            <line>To nothing temporal.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>Well; come to me to-morrow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LUCIO</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside to ISABELLA</stagedir>  Go to; 'tis well; away!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>Heaven keep your honour safe!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir> Amen:</line>
            <line>For I am that way going to temptation,</line>
            <line>Where prayers cross.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>At what hour to-morrow</line>
            <line>Shall I attend your lordship?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>At any time 'fore noon.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>'Save your honour!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt ISABELLA, LUCIO, and Provost</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>From thee, even from thy virtue!</line>
            <line>What's this, what's this? Is this her fault or mine?</line>
            <line>The tempter or the tempted, who sins most?</line>
            <line>Ha!</line>
            <line>Not she: nor doth she tempt: but it is I</line>
            <line>That, lying by the violet in the sun,</line>
            <line>Do as the carrion does, not as the flower,</line>
            <line>Corrupt with virtuous season. Can it be</line>
            <line>That modesty may more betray our sense</line>
            <line>Than woman's lightness? Having waste ground enough,</line>
            <line>Shall we desire to raze the sanctuary</line>
            <line>And pitch our evils there? O, fie, fie, fie!</line>
            <line>What dost thou, or what art thou, Angelo?</line>
            <line>Dost thou desire her foully for those things</line>
            <line>That make her good? O, let her brother live!</line>
            <line>Thieves for their robbery have authority</line>
            <line>When judges steal themselves. What, do I love her,</line>
            <line>That I desire to hear her speak again,</line>
            <line>And feast upon her eyes? What is't I dream on?</line>
            <line>O cunning enemy, that, to catch a saint,</line>
            <line>With saints dost bait thy hook! Most dangerous</line>
            <line>Is that temptation that doth goad us on</line>
            <line>To sin in loving virtue: never could the strumpet,</line>
            <line>With all her double vigour, art and nature,</line>
            <line>Once stir my temper; but this virtuous maid</line>
            <line>Subdues me quite. Even till now,</line>
            <line>When men were fond, I smiled and wonder'd how.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  A room in a prison.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter, severally, DUKE VINCENTIO disguised as a
friar, and Provost</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>Hail to you, provost! so I think you are.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Provost</speaker>
            <line>I am the provost. What's your will, good friar?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>Bound by my charity and my blest order,</line>
            <line>I come to visit the afflicted spirits</line>
            <line>Here in the prison. Do me the common right</line>
            <line>To let me see them and to make me know</line>
            <line>The nature of their crimes, that I may minister</line>
            <line>To them accordingly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Provost</speaker>
            <line>I would do more than that, if more were needful.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter JULIET</stagedir>
            <line>Look, here comes one: a gentlewoman of mine,</line>
            <line>Who, falling in the flaws of her own youth,</line>
            <line>Hath blister'd her report: she is with child;</line>
            <line>And he that got it, sentenced; a young man</line>
            <line>More fit to do another such offence</line>
            <line>Than die for this.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>When must he die?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Provost</speaker>
            <line>As I do think, to-morrow.</line>
            <line>I have provided for you: stay awhile,</line>
            <stagedir>To JULIET</stagedir>
            <line>And you shall be conducted.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>Repent you, fair one, of the sin you carry?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JULIET</speaker>
            <line>I do; and bear the shame most patiently.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>I'll teach you how you shall arraign your conscience,</line>
            <line>And try your penitence, if it be sound,</line>
            <line>Or hollowly put on.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JULIET</speaker>
            <line>I'll gladly learn.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>Love you the man that wrong'd you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JULIET</speaker>
            <line>Yes, as I love the woman that wrong'd him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>So then it seems your most offenceful act</line>
            <line>Was mutually committed?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JULIET</speaker>
            <line>Mutually.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>Then was your sin of heavier kind than his.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JULIET</speaker>
            <line>I do confess it, and repent it, father.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>'Tis meet so, daughter: but lest you do repent,</line>
            <line>As that the sin hath brought you to this shame,</line>
            <line>Which sorrow is always towards ourselves, not heaven,</line>
            <line>Showing we would not spare heaven as we love it,</line>
            <line>But as we stand in fear,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JULIET</speaker>
            <line>I do repent me, as it is an evil,</line>
            <line>And take the shame with joy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE VINCENTIO</speaker>
            <line>There rest.</line>
            <line>Your partner, as I hear, must die to-morrow,</line>
            <line>And I am going with instruction to him.</line>
            <line>Grace go with you, Benedicite!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>JULIET</speaker>
            <line>Must die to-morrow! O injurious love,</line>
            <line>That respites me a life, whose very comfort</line>
            <line>Is still a dying horror!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Provost</speaker>
            <line>'Tis pity of him.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-4">
      <title>SCENE IV.  A room in ANGELO's house.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter ANGELO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>When I would pray and think, I think and pray</line>
            <line>To several subjects. Heaven hath my empty words;</line>
            <line>Whilst my invention, hearing not my tongue,</line>
            <line>Anchors on Isabel: Heaven in my mouth,</line>
            <line>As if I did but only chew his name;</line>
            <line>And in my heart the strong and swelling evil</line>
            <line>Of my conception. The state, whereon I studied</line>
            <line>Is like a good thing, being often read,</line>
            <line>Grown fear'd and tedious; yea, my gravity,</line>
            <line>Wherein--let no man hear me--I take pride,</line>
            <line>Could I with boot change for an idle plume,</line>
            <line>Which the air beats for vain. O place, O form,</line>
            <line>How often dost thou with thy case, thy habit,</line>
            <line>Wrench awe from fools and tie the wiser souls</line>
            <line>To thy false seeming! Blood, thou art blood:</line>
            <line>Let's write good angel on the devil's horn:</line>
            <line>'Tis not the devil's crest.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter a Servant</stagedir>
            <line>How now! who's there?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>One Isabel, a sister, desires access to you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>Teach her the way.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit Servant</stagedir>
            <line>O heavens!</line>
            <line>Why does my blood thus muster to my heart,</line>
            <line>Making both it unable for itself,</line>
            <line>And dispossessing all my other parts</line>
            <line>Of necessary fitness?</line>
            <line>So play the foolish throngs with one that swoons;</line>
            <line>Come all to help him, and so stop the air</line>
            <line>By which he should revive: and even so</line>
            <line>The general, subject to a well-wish'd king,</line>
            <line>Quit their own part, and in obsequious fondness</line>
            <line>Crowd to his presence, where their untaught love</line>
            <line>Must needs appear offence.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter ISABELLA</stagedir>
            <line>How now, fair maid?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>I am come to know your pleasure.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>That you might know it, would much better please me</line>
            <line>Than to demand what 'tis. Your brother cannot live.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>Even so. Heaven keep your honour!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>Yet may he live awhile; and, it may be,</line>
            <line>As long as you or I yet he must die.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>Under your sentence?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>Yea.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>When, I beseech you? that in his reprieve,</line>
            <line>Longer or shorter, he may be so fitted</line>
            <line>That his soul sicken not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>Ha! fie, these filthy vices! It were as good</line>
            <line>To pardon him that hath from nature stolen</line>
            <line>A man already made, as to remit</line>
            <line>Their saucy sweetness that do coin heaven's image</line>
            <line>In stamps that are forbid: 'tis all as easy</line>
            <line>Falsely to take away a life true made</line>
            <line>As to put metal in restrained means</line>
            <line>To make a false one.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>'Tis set down so in heaven, but not in earth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>Say you so? then I shall pose you quickly.</line>
            <line>Which had you rather, that the most just law</line>
            <line>Now took your brother's life; or, to redeem him,</line>
            <line>Give up your body to such sweet uncleanness</line>
            <line>As she that he hath stain'd?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>Sir, believe this,</line>
            <line>I had rather give my body than my soul.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>I talk not of your soul: our compell'd sins</line>
            <line>Stand more for number than for accompt.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>How say you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>Nay, I'll not warrant that; for I can speak</line>
            <line>Against the thing I say. Answer to this:</line>
            <line>I, now the voice of the recorded law,</line>
            <line>Pronounce a sentence on your brother's life:</line>
            <line>Might there not be a charity in sin</line>
            <line>To save this brother's life?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>Please you to do't,</line>
            <line>I'll take it as a peril to my soul,</line>
            <line>It is no sin at all, but charity.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>Pleased you to do't at peril of your soul,</line>
            <line>Were equal poise of sin and charity.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>That I do beg his life, if it be sin,</line>
            <line>Heaven let me bear it! you granting of my suit,</line>
            <line>If that be sin, I'll make it my morn prayer</line>
            <line>To have it added to the faults of mine,</line>
            <line>And nothing of your answer.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>Nay, but hear me.</line>
            <line>Your sense pursues not mine: either you are ignorant,</line>
            <line>Or seem so craftily; and that's not good.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>Let me be ignorant, and in nothing good,</line>
            <line>But graciously to know I am no better.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>Thus wisdom wishes to appear most bright</line>
            <line>When it doth tax itself; as these black masks</line>
            <line>Proclaim an enshield beauty ten times louder</line>
            <line>Than beauty could, display'd. But mark me;</line>
            <line>To be received plain, I'll speak more gross:</line>
            <line>Your brother is to die.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>So.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>And his offence is so, as it appears,</line>
            <line>Accountant to the law upon that pain.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>True.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>Admit no other way to save his life,--</line>
            <line>As I subscribe not that, nor any other,</line>
            <line>But in the loss of question,--that you, his sister,</line>
            <line>Finding yourself desired of such a person,</line>
            <line>Whose credit with the judge, or own great place,</line>
            <line>Could fetch your brother from the manacles</line>
            <line>Of the all-building law; and that there were</line>
            <line>No earthly mean to save him, but that either</line>
            <line>You must lay down the treasures of your body</line>
            <line>To this supposed, or else to let him suffer;</line>
            <line>What would you do?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>As much for my poor brother as myself:</line>
            <line>That is, were I under the terms of death,</line>
            <line>The impression of keen whips I'ld wear as rubies,</line>
            <line>And strip myself to death, as to a bed</line>
            <line>That longing have been sick for, ere I'ld yield</line>
            <line>My body up to shame.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>Then must your brother die.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>And 'twere the cheaper way:</line>
            <line>Better it were a brother died at once,</line>
            <line>Than that a sister, by redeeming him,</line>
            <line>Should die for ever.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>Were not you then as cruel as the sentence</line>
            <line>That you have slander'd so?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>Ignomy in ransom and free pardon</line>
            <line>Are of two houses: lawful mercy</line>
            <line>Is nothing kin to foul redemption.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>You seem'd of late to make the law a tyrant;</line>
            <line>And rather proved the sliding of your brother</line>
            <line>A merriment than a vice.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>O, pardon me, my lord; it oft falls out,</line>
            <line>To have what we would have, we speak not what we mean:</line>
            <line>I something do excuse the thing I hate,</line>
            <line>For his advantage that I dearly love.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>We are all frail.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>Else let my brother die,</line>
            <line>If not a feodary, but only he</line>
            <line>Owe and succeed thy weakness.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>Nay, women are frail too.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>Ay, as the glasses where they view themselves;</line>
            <line>Which are as easy broke as they make forms.</line>
            <line>Women! Help Heaven! men their creation mar</line>
            <line>In profiting by them. Nay, call us ten times frail;</line>
            <line>For we are soft as our complexions are,</line>
            <line>And credulous to false prints.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>I think it well:</line>
            <line>And from this testimony of your own sex,--</line>
            <line>Since I suppose we are made to be no stronger</line>
            <line>Than faults may shake our frames,--let me be bold;</line>
            <line>I do arrest your words. Be that you are,</line>
            <line>That is, a woman; if you be more, you're none;</line>
            <line>If you be one, as you are well express'd</line>
            <line>By all external warrants, show it now,</line>
            <line>By putting on the destined livery.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>I have no tongue but one: gentle my lord,</line>
            <line>Let me entreat you speak the former language.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>Plainly conceive, I love you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>My brother did love Juliet,</line>
            <line>And you tell me that he shall die for it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>He shall not, Isabel, if you give me love.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>I know your virtue hath a licence in't,</line>
            <line>Which seems a little fouler than it is,</line>
            <line>To pluck on others.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>Believe me, on mine honour,</line>
            <line>My words express my purpose.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>Ha! little honour to be much believed,</line>
            <line>And most pernicious purpose! Seeming, seeming!</line>
            <line>I will proclaim thee, Angelo; look for't:</line>
            <line>Sign me a present pardon for my brother,</line>
            <line>Or with an outstretch'd throat I'll tell the world aloud</line>
            <line>What man thou art.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANGELO</speaker>
            <line>Who will believe thee, Isabel?</line>
            <line>My unsoil'd name, the austereness of my life,</line>
            <line>My vouch against you, and my place i' the state,</line>
            <line>Will so your accusation overweigh,</line>
            <line>That you shall stifle in your own report</line>
            <line>And smell of calumny. I have begun,</line>
            <line>And now I give my sensual race the rein:</line>
            <line>Fit thy consent to my sharp appetite;</line>
            <line>Lay by all nicety and prolixious blushes,</line>
            <line>That banish what they sue for; redeem thy brother</line>
            <line>By yielding up thy body to my will;</line>
            <line>Or else he must not only die the death,</line>
            <line>But thy unkindness shall his death draw out</line>
            <line>To lingering sufferance. Answer me to-morrow,</line>
            <line>Or, by the affection that now guides me most,</line>
            <line>I'll prove a tyrant to him. As for you,</line>
            <line>Say what you can, my false o'erweighs your true.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ISABELLA</speaker>
            <line>To whom should I complain? Did I tell this,</line>
            <line>Who would believe me? O perilous mouths,</line>
            <line>That bear in them one and the self-same tongue,</line>
            <line>Either of condemnation or approof;</line>
            <line>Bidding the law make court'sy to their will:</line>
            <line>Hooking both right and wrong to the appetite,</line>
            <line>To follow as it draws! I'll to my brother:</line>
            <line>Though he hath fallen by prompture of the blood,</line>
            <line>Yet hath he in him such a mind of honour.</line>
            <line>That, had he twenty heads to tender down</line>
            <line>On twenty bloody blocks, he'ld yield them up,</line>
            <line>Before his sister should her body stoop</line>
            <line>To such abhorr'd pollution.</line>
            <line>Then, Isabel, live chaste, and, brother, die:</line>
            <line>More than our brother is our chastity.</line>
            <line>I'll tell him yet of Angelo's request,</line>
            <line>And fit his mind to death, for his soul's rest.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>