<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:chapter" "chapter.dtd">
<chapter
  id="chapterid">
  <title>The Winged Monkeys</title>
  <body>
    <p>You will remember there was no road—not even a pathway—between the castle of the Wicked Witch
      and the Emerald City. When the four travelers went in search of the Witch she had seen them
      coming, and so sent the Winged Monkeys to bring them to her. It was much harder to find their
      way back through the big fields of buttercups and yellow daisies than it was being carried.
      They knew, of course, they must go straight east, toward the rising sun; and they started off
      in the right way. But at noon, when the sun was over their heads, they did not know which was
      east and which was west, and that was the reason they were lost in the great fields. They kept
      on walking, however, and at night the moon came out and shone brightly. So they lay down among
      the sweet smelling yellow flowers and slept soundly until morning—all but the Scarecrow and
      the Tin Woodman. </p>
    <p>The next morning the sun was behind a cloud, but they started on, as if they were quite sure
      which way they were going. </p>
    <p>"If we walk far enough," said Dorothy, "I am sure we shall sometime come to some place." </p>
    <p>But day by day passed away, and they still saw nothing before them but the scarlet fields.
      The Scarecrow began to grumble a bit. </p>
    <p>"We have surely lost our way," he said, "and unless we find it again in time to reach the
      Emerald City, I shall never get my brains." </p>
    <p>"Nor I my heart," declared the Tin Woodman. "It seems to me I can scarcely wait till I get to
      Oz, and you must admit this is a very long journey." </p>
    <p>"You see," said the Cowardly Lion, with a whimper, "I haven't the courage to keep tramping
      forever, without getting anywhere at all." </p>
    <p>Then Dorothy lost heart. She sat down on the grass and looked at her companions, and they sat
      down and looked at her, and Toto found that for the first time in his life he was too tired to
      chase a butterfly that flew past his head. So he put out his tongue and panted and looked at
      Dorothy as if to ask what they should do next. </p>
    <p>"Suppose we call the field mice," she suggested. "They could probably tell us the way to the
      Emerald City." </p>
    <p>"To be sure they could," cried the Scarecrow. "Why didn't we think of that before?" </p>
    <p>Dorothy blew the little whistle she had always carried about her neck since the Queen of the
      Mice had given it to her. In a few minutes they heard the pattering of tiny feet, and many of
      the small gray mice came running up to her. Among them was the Queen herself, who asked, in
      her squeaky little voice: </p>
    <p>"What can I do for my friends?" </p>
    <p>"We have lost our way," said Dorothy. "Can you tell us where the Emerald City is?" </p>
    <p>"Certainly," answered the Queen; "but it is a great way off, for you have had it at your
      backs all this time." Then she noticed Dorothy's Golden Cap, and said, "Why don't you use the
      charm of the Cap, and call the Winged Monkeys to you? They will carry you to the City of Oz in
      less than an hour." </p>
    <p>"I didn't know there was a charm," answered Dorothy, in surprise. "What is it?" </p>
    <p>"It is written inside the Golden Cap," replied the Queen of the Mice. "But if you are going
      to call the Winged Monkeys we must run away, for they are full of mischief and think it great
      fun to plague us." </p>
    <p>"Won't they hurt me?" asked the girl anxiously. </p>
    <p>"Oh, no. They must obey the wearer of the Cap. Good-bye!" And she scampered out of sight,
      with all the mice hurrying after her. </p>
    <p>Dorothy looked inside the Golden Cap and saw some words written upon the lining. These, she
      thought, must be the charm, so she read the directions carefully and put the Cap upon her
      head. </p>
    <p>"Ep-pe, pep-pe, kak-ke!" she said, standing on her left foot. </p>
    <p>"What did you say?" asked the Scarecrow, who did not know what she was doing. </p>
    <p>"Hil-lo, hol-lo, hel-lo!" Dorothy went on, standing this time on her right foot. </p>
    <p>"Hello!" replied the Tin Woodman calmly. </p>
    <p>"Ziz-zy, zuz-zy, zik!" said Dorothy, who was now standing on both feet. This ended the saying
      of the charm, and they heard a great chattering and flapping of wings, as the band of Winged
      Monkeys flew up to them. <art><art_title>The Winged Monkeys carry away Dorothy and the Tin
          Woodman</art_title><image
          href="images/1407-06.jpg">
          <alt>Two flying monkeys carry Dorothy, one carries Toto, and one carries the Tin
            Woodman</alt>
        </image></art></p>
    <p>The King bowed low before Dorothy, and asked, "What is your command?" </p>
    <p>"We wish to go to the Emerald City," said the child, "and we have lost our way." </p>
    <p>"We will carry you," replied the King, and no sooner had he spoken than two of the Monkeys
      caught Dorothy in their arms and flew away with her. Others took the Scarecrow and the Woodman
      and the Lion, and one little Monkey seized Toto and flew after them, although the dog tried
      hard to bite him. </p>
    <p>The Scarecrow and the Tin Woodman were rather frightened at first, for they remembered how
      badly the Winged Monkeys had treated them before; but they saw that no harm was intended, so
      they rode through the air quite cheerfully, and had a fine time looking at the pretty gardens
      and woods far below them. </p>
    <p>Dorothy found herself riding easily between two of the biggest Monkeys, one of them the King
      himself. They had made a chair of their hands and were careful not to hurt her. </p>
    <p>"Why do you have to obey the charm of the Golden Cap?" she asked. </p>
    <p>"That is a long story," answered the King, with a Winged laugh; "but as we have a long
      journey before us, I will pass the time by telling you about it, if you wish." </p>
    <p>"I shall be glad to hear it," she replied. </p>
    <p>"Once," began the leader, "we were a free people, living happily in the great forest, flying
      from tree to tree, eating nuts and fruit, and doing just as we pleased without calling anybody
      master. Perhaps some of us were rather too full of mischief at times, flying down to pull the
      tails of the animals that had no wings, chasing birds, and throwing nuts at the people who
      walked in the forest. But we were careless and happy and full of fun, and enjoyed every minute
      of the day. This was many years ago, long before Oz came out of the clouds to rule over this
      land. </p>
    <p>"There lived here then, away at the North, a beautiful princess, who was also a powerful
      sorceress. All her magic was used to help the people, and she was never known to hurt anyone
      who was good. Her name was Gayelette, and she lived in a handsome palace built from great
      blocks of ruby. Everyone loved her, but her greatest sorrow was that she could find no one to
      love in return, since all the men were much too stupid and ugly to mate with one so beautiful
      and wise. At last, however, she found a boy who was handsome and manly and wise beyond his
      years. Gayelette made up her mind that when he grew to be a man she would make him her
      husband, so she took him to her ruby palace and used all her magic powers to make him as
      strong and good and lovely as any woman could wish. When he grew to manhood, Quelala, as he
      was called, was said to be the best and wisest man in all the land, while his manly beauty was
      so great that Gayelette loved him dearly, and hastened to make everything ready for the
      wedding. </p>
    <p>"My grandfather was at that time the King of the Winged Monkeys which lived in the forest
      near Gayelette's palace, and the old fellow loved a joke better than a good dinner. One day,
      just before the wedding, my grandfather was flying out with his band when he saw Quelala
      walking beside the river. He was dressed in a rich costume of pink silk and purple velvet, and
      my grandfather thought he would see what he could do. At his word the band flew down and
      seized Quelala, carried him in their arms until they were over the middle of the river, and
      then dropped him into the water. </p>
    <p>"`Swim out, my fine fellow,' cried my grandfather, `and see if the water has spotted your
      clothes.' Quelala was much too wise not to swim, and he was not in the least spoiled by all
      his good fortune. He laughed, when he came to the top of the water, and swam in to shore. But
      when Gayelette came running out to him she found his silks and velvet all ruined by the river. </p>
    <p>"The princess was angry, and she knew, of course, who did it. She had all the Winged Monkeys
      brought before her, and she said at first that their wings should be tied and they should be
      treated as they had treated Quelala, and dropped in the river. But my grandfather pleaded
      hard, for he knew the Monkeys would drown in the river with their wings tied, and Quelala said
      a kind word for them also; so that Gayelette finally spared them, on condition that the Winged
      Monkeys should ever after do three times the bidding of the owner of the Golden Cap. This Cap
      had been made for a wedding present to Quelala, and it is said to have cost the princess half
      her kingdom. Of course my grandfather and all the other Monkeys at once agreed to the
      condition, and that is how it happens that we are three times the slaves of the owner of the
      Golden Cap, whosoever he may be." </p>
    <p>"And what became of them?" asked Dorothy, who had been greatly interested in the story. </p>
    <p>"Quelala being the first owner of the Golden Cap," replied the Monkey, "he was the first to
      lay his wishes upon us. As his bride could not bear the sight of us, he called us all to him
      in the forest after he had married her and ordered us always to keep where she could never
      again set eyes on a Winged Monkey, which we were glad to do, for we were all afraid of her. </p>
    <p>"This was all we ever had to do until the Golden Cap fell into the hands of the Wicked Witch
      of the West, who made us enslave the Winkies, and afterward drive Oz himself out of the Land
      of the West. Now the Golden Cap is yours, and three times you have the right to lay your
      wishes upon us." </p>
    <p>As the Monkey King finished his story Dorothy looked down and saw the green, shining walls of
      the Emerald City before them. She wondered at the rapid flight of the Monkeys, but was glad
      the journey was over. The strange creatures set the travelers down carefully before the gate
      of the City, the King bowed low to Dorothy, and then flew swiftly away, followed by all his
      band. </p>
    <p>"That was a good ride," said the little girl. </p>
    <p>"Yes, and a quick way out of our troubles," replied the Lion. "How lucky it was you brought
      away that wonderful Cap!" </p>
  </body>
</chapter>
