<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE learningContent
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Learning Content//EN" "learningContent.dtd">
<learningContent id="SEC006_002_004">
   <title>6.2.4 The speed and direction of the Earth's motion</title>
   <learningContentbody>
      <section>
            
            <p>The first significant claim to have detected the motion of the Earth relative
              to the ‘frame of isotropic 3 K radiation’ came in 1977 from a group at
              Berkeley, California. They concluded that the Earth is moving at a speed of (390
              ± 60) km s<sup>−1</sup>, in a direction towards the constellation Leo,
              relative to a frame in which the 3 K radiation is isotropic. Their conclusion resulted
              from observations of a variation of intensity with angle of the form predicted by
              Equation 14, which we have called a 24-hour variation.</p>
            <p>Now this motion of the Earth through the 3 K radiation will be the resultant
              of several component motions:</p>
            <ol>
              <li>
                <p>The Earth's velocity about the Sun (of magnitude 30 km
                    s<sup>−1</sup>):</p>
              </li>
              <li>
                <p>The velocity of the Sun itself about the Galactic centre (currently
                  estimated to be of magnitude 230 km s<sup>−1</sup>):</p>
              </li>
              <li>
                <p>The velocity of the Galaxy relative to the Local Group;</p>
              </li>
              <li>
                <p>Whatever velocity the Local Group has relative to the ‘frame of
                  isotropic 3 K radiation’.</p>
              </li>
            </ol>
            <fig>
            <title>
                <b>Figure 28</b>: The absolute motion of the Earth. The Earth travels in its orbit
                round the Sun at 30 km s<sup>−1</sup> and is being swept around the centre of
                the Galaxy at 230 km s<sup>−1</sup>. Experiment shows that the Earth's net
                speed through the 3 K radiation is about 400 km s<sup>−1</sup>. The Earth's
                net velocity lies in the same plane as its orbit round the Sun and at an angle
                tilted sharply upwards (northwards) from the plane of the Galaxy. In this diagram,
                the Earth's net velocity is depicted as a heavy arrow centred on the Sun (pointing
                upwards and to the right), since the two bodies travel together. Both are being
                carried by the Galaxy's own motion through the 3 K radiation. In order to account
                for the Earth's motion with respect to the 3 K radiation, the Galaxy must be
                travelling at about 600 km s<sup>−1</sup> in the direction shown by the
                coloured arrow centred on the disc of the Galaxy.</title>
            <image href="../../media/S357_1_025i.jpg"/>
            <p outputclass="SourceReference">Source: based on R.A. Muller (1978) in <i>Scientific American</i>, 238,
                64–74 <data name="ItemRights">
                  <data name="OwnerRef"/>
                  <data name="ItemRef"/>
                  <data name="ItemAcknowledgement">based on R.A. Muller (1978) in <i>Scientific American</i>,
                    238, 64–74</data>
                </data>
              </p>
            <p/>
         </fig>
            <p>The Earth's speed of about 400 km s<sup>−1</sup>, relative to this
              frame in which the radiation is isotropic, is comparable to its speed of about 230 km
                s<sup>−1</sup> relative to the Galactic centre of mass. Nevertheless, the
              Galaxy as a whole must be moving through the 3 K radiation even <i>faster</i> than the
              Earth, because the direction of the Solar System's orbital velocity round the Galaxy
              is almost <i>opposite</i> to the direction of maximum observed intensity of the 3 K
              radiation and hence opposite to the direction of the Earth's velocity through the 3 K
              radiation, as depicted in <xref href="#FIG001_025">Figure 28</xref>. Adding the two velocity vectors gives the
              centre of the Galaxy a velocity whose magnitude is about 600 km s<sup>−1</sup>
              with respect to the 3 K radiation. Now <i>if our Galaxy were isolated</i>, this
              velocity could only be interpreted as a departure (and 600 km s<sup>−1</sup>
              would be an embarrassingly large departure) from the basic idea of cosmology that the
              expansion of the Universe is shared by all matter and radiation; an isolated galaxy,
              or the centre of mass of a cluster of galaxies, should <i>not</i> be moving with
              respect to the 3 K radiation. But our Galaxy is not isolated, it is a member of our
              Local Group of galaxies. It cannot be stationary with respect to the centre of mass of
              the Local Group but must, to avoid falling in, be travelling around in some quite
              complicated orbit. So the next step towards an understanding of the 600 km
                s<sup>−1</sup> is to subtract from it the velocity of our Galaxy in its
              movement about the Local Group. Unfortunately this velocity is not very well known,
              because the estimates of the masses of some of the galaxies in the Local Group are
              very rough. But current data give the speed of our Galaxy with respect to the
              Andromeda galaxy (which is the other major member of our Local Group) as 40 km
                s<sup>−1</sup>. This might be an indication of the kind of velocity we have
              relative to the centre of mass of the Local Group. If so, it still leaves an
              unexplained speed of 500–600 km s<sup>−1</sup>.</p>
            <p>Our Local Group is thought to be a member of a cluster of clusters called the
              Local Supercluster. So the next step is to subtract the velocity of our Local Group
              with respect to the centre of mass of the Local Supercluster from the 600 km
                s<sup>−1</sup>. If this is also the final step, the answer should be
              compatible with zero. Unfortunately, the uncertainties are, at this stage, too great
              to be able to decide whether the velocity of our Local Group can be entirely explained
              in terms of the effects of a Local Supercluster. If not, then the effects of other
              structures such as more distant superclusters and the voids between them, must also be
              taken into account.</p>
          </section>
   </learningContentbody>
</learningContent>