<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE learningContent
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Learning Content//EN" "learningContent.dtd">
<learningContent id="SEC006_002_002">
   <title>6.2.2 The Earth's motion relative to the 3 K radiation</title>
   <learningContentbody>
      <section>
            
            <p>Radiation has energy and momentum, so we can use
              the molecules of a fluid such as air as an analogy for the photons of radiation. A
              detector pointing forwards along the direction of our motion (if any) will encounter a
              greater number of photons than a detector pointing backwards; in other words, it will
              record a higher intensity of 3 K radiation. (If the detector is tuned to a narrow band
              of frequencies one would also have to take account of the change in observed spectrum,
              but the principle remains the same.)</p>
            <fig>
            <title>
                <b>Figure 26</b>: The radiation detected at an angle <i>θ</i> to the direction
                of motion has a thermal spectrum characterised by a temperature <i>T</i>(<i>v</i>,
                  <i>θ</i>) which depends on the speed <i>v</i> and the angle
                <i>θ</i>.</title>
            <image href="../../media/S357_1_023i.jpg"/>
            <p/>
         </fig>
            <p>Not only does the Earth's motion affect the intensity as a function of angle,
              but also the <i>energy</i> of the photons. Suppose the Earth is moving with a velocity <ph outputclass="InlineEquation">
               <image href="../../media/S357_1_ie00italvi.gif"/>
               <ph outputclass="inlineequation-description"/>
            </ph> with respect to the
              frame in which the radiation is isotropic and we observe the component of the 3 K
              radiation that arrives in a direction making an angle <i>θ</i> with our
              direction of motion (see <xref href="#FIG001_023">Figure 26</xref>). What sort of spectrum would we observe?
              One might think that the observed spectrum would be very complicated. After all, the
              photons have been shifted to different frequencies, because of the Doppler effect, and
              our clocks and measuring rods will measure different intervals of time and length,
              compared with clocks and measuring rods in the ‘frame of isotropic 3 K
              radiation’. But it turns out that the result is very simple: Cosmic microwave
              radiation observed at an angle <i>θ</i> relative to the observer's direction of
              motion will still have a <i>thermal</i> spectrum, though it will be characterised by a
              temperature <i>T</i>(<ph outputclass="InlineEquation">
               <image href="../../media/S357_1_ie00italvi.gif"/>
               <ph outputclass="inlineequation-description"/>
            </ph>, <i>θ</i>)
              which depends on the observer's speed <ph outputclass="InlineEquation">
               <image href="../../media/S357_1_ie00italvi.gif"/>
               <ph outputclass="inlineequation-description"/>
            </ph> and the angle
                <i>θ</i>. (This reminds us of how the expansion of the Universe affected the
              cosmic background radiation: in that case too the thermal character of the spectrum
              was maintained; only the temperature was changed.)</p>
            <p>It is in fact easy to calculate how <i>T</i>(<ph outputclass="InlineEquation">
               <image href="../../media/S357_1_ie00italvi.gif"/>
               <ph outputclass="inlineequation-description"/>
            </ph>, <i>θ</i>)
              depends on <ph outputclass="InlineEquation">
               <image href="../../media/S357_1_ie00italvi.gif"/>
               <ph outputclass="inlineequation-description"/>
            </ph> and <i>θ</i>.
              We shall use the fact that the frequency <i>f</i>
            <sub>max</sub>, corresponding to the
              maximum intensity, is proportional to the temperature (see <xref href="#SAQ001_010">Question 10</xref>). That means that in the ‘rest
              frame’</p>
            <fig outputclass="Equation">
            <image href="../../media/S357_1_ue003i.gif"/>
            <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
         </fig>
            <p>where <i>C</i> is a constant and <i>T</i>
            <sub>0</sub> (≈ 3 K) is the
              temperature of the radiation in the frame in which it is isotropic. But when we are
              moving with a speed <ph outputclass="InlineEquation">
               <image href="../../media/S357_1_ie00italvi.gif"/>
               <ph outputclass="inlineequation-description"/>
            </ph> and observing at an
              angle <i>θ</i>, we find a different frequency, <i>f</i>′<sub>max</sub>,
              corresponding to maximum intensity:</p>
            <fig outputclass="Equation">
            <image href="../../media/S357_1_ue004i.gif"/>
            <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
         </fig>
            <p>The relationship between <i>f</i>
            <sub>max</sub> and
                <i>f</i>′<sub>max</sub> is given by the formula for the relativistic Doppler
              shift:</p>
            <fig outputclass="Equation">
            <image href="../../media/S357_1_ue005i.gif"/>
            <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
         </fig>
            <p>Thus we find that</p>
            <fig outputclass="Equation">
            <image href="../../media/S357_1_e012i.gif"/>
            <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
         </fig>
            <p>Thus, if we were to measure the apparent temperature of the radiation at
              different angles, we could determine our speed <ph outputclass="InlineEquation">
               <image href="../../media/S357_1_ie00italvi.gif"/>
               <ph outputclass="inlineequation-description"/>
            </ph> and the direction in
              which we are moving (which is the direction in which the radiation has the highest
              temperature, corresponding to <i>θ</i> = 0).</p>
            <p>Radio astronomers measure the intensity of radiation at a particular
              frequency or over a particular range of frequencies. The variation of intensity with
              angle is particularly simple if measurements are taken at <i>low</i> frequencies, well
              below the frequency for maximum intensity, <i>f</i>
            <sub>max</sub>. In this region of
              the spectrum, the intensity at a given frequency is proportional to the temperature
              (see Equation 8),</p>
            <fig outputclass="Equation">
            <image href="../../media/S357_1_ue006i.gif"/>
            <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
         </fig>
            <p>and hence</p>
            <fig outputclass="Equation">
            <image href="../../media/S357_1_e013i.gif"/>
            <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
         </fig>
            <p>The prediction of Equation 13 is plotted in <xref href="#FIG001_024">Figure 27</xref> for values of <ph outputclass="InlineEquation">
               <image href="../../media/S357_1_ie00italvi.gif"/>
               <ph outputclass="inlineequation-description"/>
            </ph>/<i>c</i> = 0,
              0.1 and 0.2. The angular distributions (b) and (c) show a <i>dipolar
              anisotropy</i>.</p>
            
            <fig>
            <title>
                <b>Figure 27</b>: The radiation intensity at low frequencies,
                  <i>W</i>(<i>θ</i>), as a function of <i>θ</i>, for <i>v</i>/<i>c</i>
                equal to (a) 0, (b) 0.1 and (c) 0.2, where <i>W</i>(<i>θ</i>) is calculated
                from Equation 13. (Note that <i>v</i>/<i>c</i> for the Earth's motion round the Sun
                is only 10<sup>−4</sup>)</title>
            <image href="../../media/S357_1_024i.jpg"/>
            <p/>
         </fig>
            <p>At higher frequencies, the coefficient of cos <i>θ</i> is more
              complicated and must be calculated from Equation 7. The result of such a calculation,
              which applies at all frequencies, is</p>
            <fig outputclass="Equation">
            <image href="../../media/S357_1_e014i.gif"/>
            <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
         </fig>
            <p>where</p>
            <fig outputclass="Equation">
            <image href="../../media/S357_1_ue007i.gif"/>
            <p outputclass="equation-description"/>
         </fig>
            <p>But for <i>f</i> ≪
              <i>T</i>/<i>B</i> ≈ 6 × 10<sup>10</sup> Hz, we have
                <i>F</i>(<i>f</i>) ≈ 1 and obtain the simpler result of Equation
              13.</p>
          </section>
   </learningContentbody>
</learningContent>