<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE reference PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.org:doctypes:dita:reference" "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.org:doctypes:dita:reference">
<reference
  id="referenceId">
  <title>DitaDxpMapPackager</title>
  <shortdesc>Creates a DITA Interchange Package (DXP) Zip file from a DITA map containing all the
    local dependencies required by the map.</shortdesc>
  <refbody>
    <refsyn>
      <syntaxdiagram>
        <groupseq>
          <kwd>DitaDxpMapPackager</kwd>
        </groupseq>
        <groupseq><groupcomp><delim>-</delim><kwd>i</kwd></groupcomp>
          <var>input map file</var></groupseq>
        <groupseq
          importance="optional"><groupcomp><delim>-</delim><kwd>o</kwd></groupcomp>
          <var>DXP zip file</var></groupseq>
        <groupseq
          importance="optional"><groupcomp><delim>-</delim><kwd>c</kwd></groupcomp>
          <var>XML catalog file</var></groupseq>
        <groupseq
          importance="optional"><groupcomp><delim>-</delim><kwd>d</kwd></groupcomp>
          <var>Ditaval file</var></groupseq>
      </syntaxdiagram>
    </refsyn>
    <properties
      spectitle="Parameters">
      <prophead>
        <proptypehd>Option</proptypehd>
        <propdeschd>Description</propdeschd>
      </prophead>
      <property>
        <proptype>-i</proptype>
        <propvalue>Path and filename of the root map to process</propvalue>
      </property>
      <property>
        <proptype>-o</proptype>
        <propvalue>(optional) Path and filename of the DXP package. If not specified, a package
          named <filepath><varname>mapFilename</varname>.dxp</filepath> in the same directory as the
          input map will be created.</propvalue>
      </property>
      <property>
        <proptype>-c</proptype>
        <propvalue>(optional) Path and filename of the XML catalog to use for resolving DTD and
          schema references. If not specified, and the DITA_HOME environment variable is set, the
            <filepath>catalog-dita.xml</filepath> file will be used, if found. If DITA_HOME is not
          set, then no catalogs are used.</propvalue>
      </property>
      <property>
        <proptype>-d</proptype>
        <propvalue>(optional) Path and filename of the Ditaval file to use when determining the key
          space and constructing the BOS. If not specified, all elements are applicable.</propvalue>
      </property>
    </properties>
    <section
      spectitle="Usage">
      <p>To run from the command line, use a Java command like so (all on one
        line):<codeblock>java -Xmx512M -jar dita4publishers-dxppackager.jar 
  -i ~/workspace/dita_12_spec/dita1.2-complete.ditamap  
  -o ditaspec-complete.dxp</codeblock></p>
      <p>As the BOS construction process builds DOMs of each document in the BOS, larger maps will
        require more Java memory, as specified by the <parmname>-Xmx</parmname> Java parameter. This
        example processes the DITA 1.2 full specification (architectural spec and language
        reference), consistent of 779 separate documents.</p>
      <p>The resulting Zip file contains all the local dependencies required by the root map as
        determined by the BOS construction process.</p>
      <p>The DITA Interchange Package specification requires that the resulting package have either
        exactly one root map in the top-level directory or have a DXP manifest map. By default the
        DXP map packager reorganizes the BOS members so that the root map is by itself in the root
        directory and all dependencies are in directories below it. If files have to be moved to
        accomplish this all affected pointers will be rewritten to reflect the moves.</p>
    </section>
  </refbody>
</reference>
