<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.org:doctypes:dita:topic" "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.org:doctypes:dita:topic">
<topic
  id="topic-id">
  <title>DITA For Publishers Java API and Tools</title>
  <shortdesc>The DITA for Publishers (D4P) Java API and tools provide a general-purpose API for DITA
    link management, as well as various utilities for working with collections of DITA documents.
    These APIs are intended to be a public and open API suitable for use by a variety of tools and
    applications, including DITA-aware editors, content management systems, and processors. The
    tools are intended to serve as both tests and demonstrations of the APIs as well as useful
    utilities.</shortdesc>
  <prolog>
    <copyright><copyryear
        year="2010"/><copyrholder>DITA for Publishers</copyrholder></copyright>
  </prolog>
  <body>
    <p>The D4P API (dita4publishers-dita-api.jar) provides the following general services and
        classes:<ul
        id="ul_cbd397b2-99c7-4ca3-a212-6b6924e8b449">
        <li>DITA Link Management service, which provides general facilities for working with
          DITA-defined links and addresses, especially the management of DITA key spaces and
          resolution of key references.</li>
        <li>DITA key space classes and APIs</li>
        <li>Conditional processing (filtering) services</li>
        <li>DITA "bounded object set" (BOS) management. A DITA bounded object set is the set of
          resources (DITA documents and non-DITA resources) used in the context maps and topics
          ultimately used from a given root map.</li>
      </ul></p>
    <p>The D4P Tools (dita4publishers-dita-impl.jar) provides the following tools and services:<ul
        id="ul_a57be980-b4bc-4516-988b-52d410609f04">
        <li>MapBosReporter—command-line application for constructing a DITA bounded object set and
          then reporting the BOS members, their dependencies, and any keys defined by the BOS's map
          tree.</li>
        <li>DITA BOS classes and utilities for constructing DITA bounded object sets.</li>
        <li>An in-memory DITA Link Management Service, which implements the link management API
          using a single in-memory implementation.</li>
        <li>An in-memory DITA key space implementation (used by the link management service)</li>
        <li>A general DITA utility class for working with DITA documents.</li>
      </ul></p>
    <p>See the Javadocs for the API and implementation classes for details. These topics provide a
      general conceptual and design overview for the API and tools.</p>
  </body>
</topic>
