<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE reference PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.org:doctypes:dita:reference" "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.org:doctypes:dita:reference">
<reference
  id="referenceId">
  <title>MapBosReporter</title>
  <shortdesc>Generates a DITA map tree or full map bounded object set (BOS) report.</shortdesc>
  <refbody>
    <refsyn>
      <syntaxdiagram>
        <groupseq>
          <kwd>MapBosReport</kwd>
        </groupseq>
        <groupseq><groupcomp><delim>-</delim><kwd>i</kwd></groupcomp>
          <var>input map file</var></groupseq>
        <groupseq
          importance="optional"><groupcomp><delim>-</delim><kwd>o</kwd></groupcomp>
          <var>report file</var></groupseq>
        <groupseq
          importance="optional"><groupcomp><delim>-</delim><kwd>c</kwd></groupcomp>
          <var>XML catalog file</var></groupseq>
        <groupseq
          importance="optional">
          <groupcomp><delim>-</delim><kwd>m</kwd></groupcomp>
        </groupseq>
        <groupseq
          importance="optional"><groupcomp><delim>-</delim><kwd>d</kwd></groupcomp>
          <var>Ditaval file</var></groupseq>
      </syntaxdiagram>
    </refsyn>
    <properties
      spectitle="Parameters">
      <prophead>
        <proptypehd>Option</proptypehd>
        <propdeschd>Description</propdeschd>
      </prophead>
      <property>
        <proptype>-i</proptype>
        <propvalue>Path and filename of the root map to process</propvalue>
      </property>
      <property>
        <proptype>-o</proptype>
        <propvalue>(optional) Path and filename of the generated BOS report. If not specified,
          report is written to STDOUT.</propvalue>
      </property>
      <property>
        <proptype>-c</proptype>
        <propvalue>(optional) Path and filename of the XML catalog to use for resolving DTD and
          schema references. If not specified, and the DITA_HOME environment variable is set, the
            <filepath>catalog-dita.xml</filepath> file will be used, if found. If DITA_HOME is not
          set, then no catalogs are used.</propvalue>
      </property>
      <property>
        <proptype>-m</proptype>
        <propvalue>(optional) When specified, only the map tree, not the full BOS, is constructed
          and reported.</propvalue>
      </property>
      <property>
        <proptype>-d</proptype>
        <propvalue>(optional) Path and filename of the Ditaval file to use when determining the key
          space and constructing the BOS. If not specified, all elements are applicable.</propvalue>
      </property>
    </properties>
    <section
      spectitle="Usage">
      <p>To run from the command line, use a Java command like so (all on one
        line):<codeblock>java -Xmx512M -jar dita4publishers-mapbosreporter.jar 
  -i ~/workspace/dita_12_spec/dita1.2-complete.ditamap  
  -o bos-report.txt</codeblock></p>
      <p>As the BOS construction process builds DOMs of each document in the BOS, larger maps will
        require more Java memory, as specified by the <parmname>-Xmx</parmname> Java parameter. This
        example processes the DITA 1.2 full specification (architectural spec and language
        reference), consistent of 779 separate documents.</p>
      <p>The resulting report consists of the BOS report, listing the map tree and all the topics
        used from it (representing topics as children of maps) and all the dependencies of each
        topic (other topics or non-DITA resources linked to from the topic), followed by the key
        space report, listing all the key definitions in the map tree. If you specify <parmname
          >-m</parmname>, the BOS report reflects only the map tree, no topics.</p>
    </section>
  </refbody>
</reference>
