<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net/doctypes/dita/shakespear/dtd/act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-3">
   <title>ACT III</title>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  OLIVIA's garden.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter VIOLA, and Clown with a tabour</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>Save thee, friend, and thy music: dost thou live by</line>
            <line>thy tabour?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>No, sir, I live by the church.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>Art thou a churchman?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>No such matter, sir: I do live by the church; for</line>
            <line>I do live at my house, and my house doth stand by</line>
            <line>the church.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>So thou mayst say, the king lies by a beggar, if a</line>
            <line>beggar dwell near him; or, the church stands by thy</line>
            <line>tabour, if thy tabour stand by the church.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>You have said, sir. To see this age! A sentence is</line>
            <line>but a cheveril glove to a good wit: how quickly the</line>
            <line>wrong side may be turned outward!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>Nay, that's certain; they that dally nicely with</line>
            <line>words may quickly make them wanton.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>I would, therefore, my sister had had no name, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>Why, man?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Why, sir, her name's a word; and to dally with that</line>
            <line>word might make my sister wanton. But indeed words</line>
            <line>are very rascals since bonds disgraced them.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>Thy reason, man?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Troth, sir, I can yield you none without words; and</line>
            <line>words are grown so false, I am loath to prove</line>
            <line>reason with them.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>I warrant thou art a merry fellow and carest for nothing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Not so, sir, I do care for something; but in my</line>
            <line>conscience, sir, I do not care for you: if that be</line>
            <line>to care for nothing, sir, I would it would make you invisible.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>Art not thou the Lady Olivia's fool?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>No, indeed, sir; the Lady Olivia has no folly: she</line>
            <line>will keep no fool, sir, till she be married; and</line>
            <line>fools are as like husbands as pilchards are to</line>
            <line>herrings; the husband's the bigger: I am indeed not</line>
            <line>her fool, but her corrupter of words.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>I saw thee late at the Count Orsino's.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Foolery, sir, does walk about the orb like the sun,</line>
            <line>it shines every where. I would be sorry, sir, but</line>
            <line>the fool should be as oft with your master as with</line>
            <line>my mistress: I think I saw your wisdom there.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>Nay, an thou pass upon me, I'll no more with thee.</line>
            <line>Hold, there's expenses for thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Now Jove, in his next commodity of hair, send thee a beard!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>By my troth, I'll tell thee, I am almost sick for</line>
            <line>one;</line>
            <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>
            <line>though I would not have it grow on my chin. Is thy</line>
            <line>lady within?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Would not a pair of these have bred, sir?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>Yes, being kept together and put to use.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>I would play Lord Pandarus of Phrygia, sir, to bring</line>
            <line>a Cressida to this Troilus.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>I understand you, sir; 'tis well begged.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>The matter, I hope, is not great, sir, begging but</line>
            <line>a beggar: Cressida was a beggar. My lady is</line>
            <line>within, sir. I will construe to them whence you</line>
            <line>come; who you are and what you would are out of my</line>
            <line>welkin, I might say 'element,' but the word is over-worn.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>This fellow is wise enough to play the fool;</line>
            <line>And to do that well craves a kind of wit:</line>
            <line>He must observe their mood on whom he jests,</line>
            <line>The quality of persons, and the time,</line>
            <line>And, like the haggard, cheque at every feather</line>
            <line>That comes before his eye. This is a practise</line>
            <line>As full of labour as a wise man's art</line>
            <line>For folly that he wisely shows is fit;</line>
            <line>But wise men, folly-fall'n, quite taint their wit.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter SIR TOBY BELCH, and SIR ANDREW</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Save you, gentleman.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>And you, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>Dieu vous garde, monsieur.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>Et vous aussi; votre serviteur.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>I hope, sir, you are; and I am yours.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Will you encounter the house? my niece is desirous</line>
            <line>you should enter, if your trade be to her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>I am bound to your niece, sir; I mean, she is the</line>
            <line>list of my voyage.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Taste your legs, sir; put them to motion.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>My legs do better understand me, sir, than I</line>
            <line>understand what you mean by bidding me taste my legs.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>I mean, to go, sir, to enter.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>I will answer you with gait and entrance. But we</line>
            <line>are prevented.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter OLIVIA and MARIA</stagedir>
            <line>Most excellent accomplished lady, the heavens rain</line>
            <line>odours on you!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>That youth's a rare courtier: 'Rain odours;' well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>My matter hath no voice, to your own most pregnant</line>
            <line>and vouchsafed ear.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>'Odours,' 'pregnant' and 'vouchsafed:' I'll get 'em</line>
            <line>all three all ready.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>Let the garden door be shut, and leave me to my hearing.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt SIR TOBY BELCH, SIR ANDREW, and MARIA</stagedir>
            <line>Give me your hand, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>My duty, madam, and most humble service.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>What is your name?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>Cesario is your servant's name, fair princess.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>My servant, sir! 'Twas never merry world</line>
            <line>Since lowly feigning was call'd compliment:</line>
            <line>You're servant to the Count Orsino, youth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>And he is yours, and his must needs be yours:</line>
            <line>Your servant's servant is your servant, madam.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>For him, I think not on him: for his thoughts,</line>
            <line>Would they were blanks, rather than fill'd with me!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>Madam, I come to whet your gentle thoughts</line>
            <line>On his behalf.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>O, by your leave, I pray you,</line>
            <line>I bade you never speak again of him:</line>
            <line>But, would you undertake another suit,</line>
            <line>I had rather hear you to solicit that</line>
            <line>Than music from the spheres.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>Dear lady,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>Give me leave, beseech you. I did send,</line>
            <line>After the last enchantment you did here,</line>
            <line>A ring in chase of you: so did I abuse</line>
            <line>Myself, my servant and, I fear me, you:</line>
            <line>Under your hard construction must I sit,</line>
            <line>To force that on you, in a shameful cunning,</line>
            <line>Which you knew none of yours: what might you think?</line>
            <line>Have you not set mine honour at the stake</line>
            <line>And baited it with all the unmuzzled thoughts</line>
            <line>That tyrannous heart can think? To one of your receiving</line>
            <line>Enough is shown: a cypress, not a bosom,</line>
            <line>Hideth my heart. So, let me hear you speak.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>I pity you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>That's a degree to love.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>No, not a grize; for 'tis a vulgar proof,</line>
            <line>That very oft we pity enemies.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>Why, then, methinks 'tis time to smile again.</line>
            <line>O, world, how apt the poor are to be proud!</line>
            <line>If one should be a prey, how much the better</line>
            <line>To fall before the lion than the wolf!</line>
            <stagedir>Clock strikes</stagedir>
            <line>The clock upbraids me with the waste of time.</line>
            <line>Be not afraid, good youth, I will not have you:</line>
            <line>And yet, when wit and youth is come to harvest,</line>
            <line>Your were is alike to reap a proper man:</line>
            <line>There lies your way, due west.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>Then westward-ho! Grace and good disposition</line>
            <line>Attend your ladyship!</line>
            <line>You'll nothing, madam, to my lord by me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>Stay:</line>
            <line>I prithee, tell me what thou thinkest of me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>That you do think you are not what you are.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>If I think so, I think the same of you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>Then think you right: I am not what I am.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>I would you were as I would have you be!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>Would it be better, madam, than I am?</line>
            <line>I wish it might, for now I am your fool.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>O, what a deal of scorn looks beautiful</line>
            <line>In the contempt and anger of his lip!</line>
            <line>A murderous guilt shows not itself more soon</line>
            <line>Than love that would seem hid: love's night is noon.</line>
            <line>Cesario, by the roses of the spring,</line>
            <line>By maidhood, honour, truth and every thing,</line>
            <line>I love thee so, that, maugre all thy pride,</line>
            <line>Nor wit nor reason can my passion hide.</line>
            <line>Do not extort thy reasons from this clause,</line>
            <line>For that I woo, thou therefore hast no cause,</line>
            <line>But rather reason thus with reason fetter,</line>
            <line>Love sought is good, but given unsought better.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>By innocence I swear, and by my youth</line>
            <line>I have one heart, one bosom and one truth,</line>
            <line>And that no woman has; nor never none</line>
            <line>Shall mistress be of it, save I alone.</line>
            <line>And so adieu, good madam: never more</line>
            <line>Will I my master's tears to you deplore.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>Yet come again; for thou perhaps mayst move</line>
            <line>That heart, which now abhors, to like his love.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  OLIVIA's house.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter SIR TOBY BELCH, SIR ANDREW, and FABIAN</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>No, faith, I'll not stay a jot longer.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Thy reason, dear venom, give thy reason.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FABIAN</speaker>
            <line>You must needs yield your reason, Sir Andrew.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>Marry, I saw your niece do more favours to the</line>
            <line>count's serving-man than ever she bestowed upon me;</line>
            <line>I saw't i' the orchard.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Did she see thee the while, old boy? tell me that.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>As plain as I see you now.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FABIAN</speaker>
            <line>This was a great argument of love in her toward you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>'Slight, will you make an ass o' me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FABIAN</speaker>
            <line>I will prove it legitimate, sir, upon the oaths of</line>
            <line>judgment and reason.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>And they have been grand-jury-men since before Noah</line>
            <line>was a sailor.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FABIAN</speaker>
            <line>She did show favour to the youth in your sight only</line>
            <line>to exasperate you, to awake your dormouse valour, to</line>
            <line>put fire in your heart and brimstone in your liver.</line>
            <line>You should then have accosted her; and with some</line>
            <line>excellent jests, fire-new from the mint, you should</line>
            <line>have banged the youth into dumbness. This was</line>
            <line>looked for at your hand, and this was balked: the</line>
            <line>double gilt of this opportunity you let time wash</line>
            <line>off, and you are now sailed into the north of my</line>
            <line>lady's opinion; where you will hang like an icicle</line>
            <line>on a Dutchman's beard, unless you do redeem it by</line>
            <line>some laudable attempt either of valour or policy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>An't be any way, it must be with valour; for policy</line>
            <line>I hate: I had as lief be a Brownist as a</line>
            <line>politician.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Why, then, build me thy fortunes upon the basis of</line>
            <line>valour. Challenge me the count's youth to fight</line>
            <line>with him; hurt him in eleven places: my niece shall</line>
            <line>take note of it; and assure thyself, there is no</line>
            <line>love-broker in the world can more prevail in man's</line>
            <line>commendation with woman than report of valour.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FABIAN</speaker>
            <line>There is no way but this, Sir Andrew.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>Will either of you bear me a challenge to him?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Go, write it in a martial hand; be curst and brief;</line>
            <line>it is no matter how witty, so it be eloquent and fun</line>
            <line>of invention: taunt him with the licence of ink:</line>
            <line>if thou thou'st him some thrice, it shall not be</line>
            <line>amiss; and as many lies as will lie in thy sheet of</line>
            <line>paper, although the sheet were big enough for the</line>
            <line>bed of Ware in England, set 'em down: go, about it.</line>
            <line>Let there be gall enough in thy ink, though thou</line>
            <line>write with a goose-pen, no matter: about it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>Where shall I find you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>We'll call thee at the cubiculo: go.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit SIR ANDREW</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FABIAN</speaker>
            <line>This is a dear manikin to you, Sir Toby.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>I have been dear to him, lad, some two thousand</line>
            <line>strong, or so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FABIAN</speaker>
            <line>We shall have a rare letter from him: but you'll</line>
            <line>not deliver't?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Never trust me, then; and by all means stir on the</line>
            <line>youth to an answer. I think oxen and wainropes</line>
            <line>cannot hale them together. For Andrew, if he were</line>
            <line>opened, and you find so much blood in his liver as</line>
            <line>will clog the foot of a flea, I'll eat the rest of</line>
            <line>the anatomy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FABIAN</speaker>
            <line>And his opposite, the youth, bears in his visage no</line>
            <line>great presage of cruelty.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter MARIA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Look, where the youngest wren of nine comes.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>If you desire the spleen, and will laugh yourself</line>
            <line>into stitches, follow me. Yond gull Malvolio is</line>
            <line>turned heathen, a very renegado; for there is no</line>
            <line>Christian, that means to be saved by believing</line>
            <line>rightly, can ever believe such impossible passages</line>
            <line>of grossness. He's in yellow stockings.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>And cross-gartered?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>Most villanously; like a pedant that keeps a school</line>
            <line>i' the church. I have dogged him, like his</line>
            <line>murderer. He does obey every point of the letter</line>
            <line>that I dropped to betray him: he does smile his</line>
            <line>face into more lines than is in the new map with the</line>
            <line>augmentation of the Indies: you have not seen such</line>
            <line>a thing as 'tis. I can hardly forbear hurling things</line>
            <line>at him. I know my lady will strike him: if she do,</line>
            <line>he'll smile and take't for a great favour.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Come, bring us, bring us where he is.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  A street.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter SEBASTIAN and ANTONIO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SEBASTIAN</speaker>
            <line>I would not by my will have troubled you;</line>
            <line>But, since you make your pleasure of your pains,</line>
            <line>I will no further chide you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>I could not stay behind you: my desire,</line>
            <line>More sharp than filed steel, did spur me forth;</line>
            <line>And not all love to see you, though so much</line>
            <line>As might have drawn one to a longer voyage,</line>
            <line>But jealousy what might befall your travel,</line>
            <line>Being skilless in these parts; which to a stranger,</line>
            <line>Unguided and unfriended, often prove</line>
            <line>Rough and unhospitable: my willing love,</line>
            <line>The rather by these arguments of fear,</line>
            <line>Set forth in your pursuit.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SEBASTIAN</speaker>
            <line>My kind Antonio,</line>
            <line>I can no other answer make but thanks,</line>
            <line>And thanks; and ever oft good turns</line>
            <line>Are shuffled off with such uncurrent pay:</line>
            <line>But, were my worth as is my conscience firm,</line>
            <line>You should find better dealing. What's to do?</line>
            <line>Shall we go see the reliques of this town?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>To-morrow, sir: best first go see your lodging.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SEBASTIAN</speaker>
            <line>I am not weary, and 'tis long to night:</line>
            <line>I pray you, let us satisfy our eyes</line>
            <line>With the memorials and the things of fame</line>
            <line>That do renown this city.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>Would you'ld pardon me;</line>
            <line>I do not without danger walk these streets:</line>
            <line>Once, in a sea-fight, 'gainst the count his galleys</line>
            <line>I did some service; of such note indeed,</line>
            <line>That were I ta'en here it would scarce be answer'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SEBASTIAN</speaker>
            <line>Belike you slew great number of his people.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>The offence is not of such a bloody nature;</line>
            <line>Albeit the quality of the time and quarrel</line>
            <line>Might well have given us bloody argument.</line>
            <line>It might have since been answer'd in repaying</line>
            <line>What we took from them; which, for traffic's sake,</line>
            <line>Most of our city did: only myself stood out;</line>
            <line>For which, if I be lapsed in this place,</line>
            <line>I shall pay dear.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SEBASTIAN</speaker>
            <line>Do not then walk too open.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>It doth not fit me. Hold, sir, here's my purse.</line>
            <line>In the south suburbs, at the Elephant,</line>
            <line>Is best to lodge: I will bespeak our diet,</line>
            <line>Whiles you beguile the time and feed your knowledge</line>
            <line>With viewing of the town: there shall you have me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SEBASTIAN</speaker>
            <line>Why I your purse?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>Haply your eye shall light upon some toy</line>
            <line>You have desire to purchase; and your store,</line>
            <line>I think, is not for idle markets, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SEBASTIAN</speaker>
            <line>I'll be your purse-bearer and leave you</line>
            <line>For an hour.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>To the Elephant.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SEBASTIAN</speaker>
            <line>I do remember.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-4">
      <title>SCENE IV.  OLIVIA's garden.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter OLIVIA and MARIA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>I have sent after him: he says he'll come;</line>
            <line>How shall I feast him? what bestow of him?</line>
            <line>For youth is bought more oft than begg'd or borrow'd.</line>
            <line>I speak too loud.</line>
            <line>Where is Malvolio? he is sad and civil,</line>
            <line>And suits well for a servant with my fortunes:</line>
            <line>Where is Malvolio?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>He's coming, madam; but in very strange manner. He</line>
            <line>is, sure, possessed, madam.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>Why, what's the matter? does he rave?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>No. madam, he does nothing but smile: your</line>
            <line>ladyship were best to have some guard about you, if</line>
            <line>he come; for, sure, the man is tainted in's wits.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>Go call him hither.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit MARIA</stagedir>
            <line>I am as mad as he,</line>
            <line>If sad and merry madness equal be.</line>
            <stagedir>Re-enter MARIA, with MALVOLIO</stagedir>
            <line>How now, Malvolio!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>Sweet lady, ho, ho.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>Smilest thou?</line>
            <line>I sent for thee upon a sad occasion.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>Sad, lady! I could be sad: this does make some</line>
            <line>obstruction in the blood, this cross-gartering; but</line>
            <line>what of that? if it please the eye of one, it is</line>
            <line>with me as the very true sonnet is, 'Please one, and</line>
            <line>please all.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>Why, how dost thou, man? what is the matter with thee?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>Not black in my mind, though yellow in my legs. It</line>
            <line>did come to his hands, and commands shall be</line>
            <line>executed: I think we do know the sweet Roman hand.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>Wilt thou go to bed, Malvolio?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>To bed! ay, sweet-heart, and I'll come to thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>God comfort thee! Why dost thou smile so and kiss</line>
            <line>thy hand so oft?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>How do you, Malvolio?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>At your request! yes; nightingales answer daws.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>Why appear you with this ridiculous boldness before my lady?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>'Be not afraid of greatness:' 'twas well writ.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>What meanest thou by that, Malvolio?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>'Some are born great,'--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>Ha!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>'Some achieve greatness,'--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>What sayest thou?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>'And some have greatness thrust upon them.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>Heaven restore thee!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>'Remember who commended thy yellow stockings,'--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>Thy yellow stockings!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>'And wished to see thee cross-gartered.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>Cross-gartered!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>'Go to thou art made, if thou desirest to be so;'--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>Am I made?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>'If not, let me see thee a servant still.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>Why, this is very midsummer madness.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter Servant</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>Madam, the young gentleman of the Count Orsino's is</line>
            <line>returned: I could hardly entreat him back: he</line>
            <line>attends your ladyship's pleasure.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>I'll come to him.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit Servant</stagedir>
            <line>Good Maria, let this fellow be looked to. Where's</line>
            <line>my cousin Toby? Let some of my people have a special</line>
            <line>care of him: I would not have him miscarry for the</line>
            <line>half of my dowry.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt OLIVIA and MARIA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>O, ho! do you come near me now? no worse man than</line>
            <line>Sir Toby to look to me! This concurs directly with</line>
            <line>the letter: she sends him on purpose, that I may</line>
            <line>appear stubborn to him; for she incites me to that</line>
            <line>in the letter. 'Cast thy humble slough,' says she;</line>
            <line>'be opposite with a kinsman, surly with servants;</line>
            <line>let thy tongue tang with arguments of state; put</line>
            <line>thyself into the trick of singularity;' and</line>
            <line>consequently sets down the manner how; as, a sad</line>
            <line>face, a reverend carriage, a slow tongue, in the</line>
            <line>habit of some sir of note, and so forth. I have</line>
            <line>limed her; but it is Jove's doing, and Jove make me</line>
            <line>thankful! And when she went away now, 'Let this</line>
            <line>fellow be looked to:' fellow! not Malvolio, nor</line>
            <line>after my degree, but fellow. Why, every thing</line>
            <line>adheres together, that no dram of a scruple, no</line>
            <line>scruple of a scruple, no obstacle, no incredulous</line>
            <line>or unsafe circumstance--What can be said? Nothing</line>
            <line>that can be can come between me and the full</line>
            <line>prospect of my hopes. Well, Jove, not I, is the</line>
            <line>doer of this, and he is to be thanked.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter MARIA, with SIR TOBY BELCH and FABIAN</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Which way is he, in the name of sanctity? If all</line>
            <line>the devils of hell be drawn in little, and Legion</line>
            <line>himself possessed him, yet I'll speak to him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FABIAN</speaker>
            <line>Here he is, here he is. How is't with you, sir?</line>
            <line>how is't with you, man?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>Go off; I discard you: let me enjoy my private: go</line>
            <line>off.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>Lo, how hollow the fiend speaks within him! did not</line>
            <line>I tell you? Sir Toby, my lady prays you to have a</line>
            <line>care of him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>Ah, ha! does she so?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Go to, go to; peace, peace; we must deal gently</line>
            <line>with him: let me alone. How do you, Malvolio? how</line>
            <line>is't with you? What, man! defy the devil:</line>
            <line>consider, he's an enemy to mankind.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>Do you know what you say?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>La you, an you speak ill of the devil, how he takes</line>
            <line>it at heart! Pray God, he be not bewitched!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FABIAN</speaker>
            <line>Carry his water to the wise woman.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>Marry, and it shall be done to-morrow morning, if I</line>
            <line>live. My lady would not lose him for more than I'll say.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>How now, mistress!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>O Lord!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Prithee, hold thy peace; this is not the way: do</line>
            <line>you not see you move him? let me alone with him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FABIAN</speaker>
            <line>No way but gentleness; gently, gently: the fiend is</line>
            <line>rough, and will not be roughly used.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Why, how now, my bawcock! how dost thou, chuck?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>Sir!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Ay, Biddy, come with me. What, man! 'tis not for</line>
            <line>gravity to play at cherry-pit with Satan: hang</line>
            <line>him, foul collier!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>Get him to say his prayers, good Sir Toby, get him to pray.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>My prayers, minx!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>No, I warrant you, he will not hear of godliness.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>Go, hang yourselves all! you are idle shallow</line>
            <line>things: I am not of your element: you shall know</line>
            <line>more hereafter.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Is't possible?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FABIAN</speaker>
            <line>If this were played upon a stage now, I could</line>
            <line>condemn it as an improbable fiction.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>His very genius hath taken the infection of the device, man.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>Nay, pursue him now, lest the device take air and taint.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FABIAN</speaker>
            <line>Why, we shall make him mad indeed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>The house will be the quieter.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Come, we'll have him in a dark room and bound. My</line>
            <line>niece is already in the belief that he's mad: we</line>
            <line>may carry it thus, for our pleasure and his penance,</line>
            <line>till our very pastime, tired out of breath, prompt</line>
            <line>us to have mercy on him: at which time we will</line>
            <line>bring the device to the bar and crown thee for a</line>
            <line>finder of madmen. But see, but see.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter SIR ANDREW</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FABIAN</speaker>
            <line>More matter for a May morning.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>Here's the challenge, read it: warrant there's</line>
            <line>vinegar and pepper in't.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FABIAN</speaker>
            <line>Is't so saucy?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>Ay, is't, I warrant him: do but read.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Give me.</line>
            <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>
            <line>'Youth, whatsoever thou art, thou art but a scurvy fellow.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FABIAN</speaker>
            <line>Good, and valiant.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>  'Wonder not, nor admire not in thy mind,</line>
            <line>why I do call thee so, for I will show thee no reason for't.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FABIAN</speaker>
            <line>A good note; that keeps you from the blow of the law.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>  'Thou comest to the lady Olivia, and in my</line>
            <line>sight she uses thee kindly: but thou liest in thy</line>
            <line>throat; that is not the matter I challenge thee for.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FABIAN</speaker>
            <line>Very brief, and to exceeding good sense--less.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>  'I will waylay thee going home; where if it</line>
            <line>be thy chance to kill me,'--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FABIAN</speaker>
            <line>Good.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>  'Thou killest me like a rogue and a villain.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FABIAN</speaker>
            <line>Still you keep o' the windy side of the law: good.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>  'Fare thee well; and God have mercy upon</line>
            <line>one of our souls! He may have mercy upon mine; but</line>
            <line>my hope is better, and so look to thyself. Thy</line>
            <line>friend, as thou usest him, and thy sworn enemy,</line>
            <line>ANDREW AGUECHEEK.</line>
            <line>If this letter move him not, his legs cannot:</line>
            <line>I'll give't him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>You may have very fit occasion for't: he is now in</line>
            <line>some commerce with my lady, and will by and by depart.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Go, Sir Andrew: scout me for him at the corner the</line>
            <line>orchard like a bum-baily: so soon as ever thou seest</line>
            <line>him, draw; and, as thou drawest swear horrible; for</line>
            <line>it comes to pass oft that a terrible oath, with a</line>
            <line>swaggering accent sharply twanged off, gives manhood</line>
            <line>more approbation than ever proof itself would have</line>
            <line>earned him. Away!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>Nay, let me alone for swearing.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Now will not I deliver his letter: for the behavior</line>
            <line>of the young gentleman gives him out to be of good</line>
            <line>capacity and breeding; his employment between his</line>
            <line>lord and my niece confirms no less: therefore this</line>
            <line>letter, being so excellently ignorant, will breed no</line>
            <line>terror in the youth: he will find it comes from a</line>
            <line>clodpole. But, sir, I will deliver his challenge by</line>
            <line>word of mouth; set upon Aguecheek a notable report</line>
            <line>of valour; and drive the gentleman, as I know his</line>
            <line>youth will aptly receive it, into a most hideous</line>
            <line>opinion of his rage, skill, fury and impetuosity.</line>
            <line>This will so fright them both that they will kill</line>
            <line>one another by the look, like cockatrices.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter OLIVIA, with VIOLA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FABIAN</speaker>
            <line>Here he comes with your niece: give them way till</line>
            <line>he take leave, and presently after him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>I will meditate the while upon some horrid message</line>
            <line>for a challenge.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt SIR TOBY BELCH, FABIAN, and MARIA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>I have said too much unto a heart of stone</line>
            <line>And laid mine honour too unchary out:</line>
            <line>There's something in me that reproves my fault;</line>
            <line>But such a headstrong potent fault it is,</line>
            <line>That it but mocks reproof.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>With the same 'havior that your passion bears</line>
            <line>Goes on my master's grief.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>Here, wear this jewel for me, 'tis my picture;</line>
            <line>Refuse it not; it hath no tongue to vex you;</line>
            <line>And I beseech you come again to-morrow.</line>
            <line>What shall you ask of me that I'll deny,</line>
            <line>That honour saved may upon asking give?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>Nothing but this; your true love for my master.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>How with mine honour may I give him that</line>
            <line>Which I have given to you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>I will acquit you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>Well, come again to-morrow: fare thee well:</line>
            <line>A fiend like thee might bear my soul to hell.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Re-enter SIR TOBY BELCH and FABIAN</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Gentleman, God save thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>And you, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>That defence thou hast, betake thee to't: of what</line>
            <line>nature the wrongs are thou hast done him, I know</line>
            <line>not; but thy intercepter, full of despite, bloody as</line>
            <line>the hunter, attends thee at the orchard-end:</line>
            <line>dismount thy tuck, be yare in thy preparation, for</line>
            <line>thy assailant is quick, skilful and deadly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>You mistake, sir; I am sure no man hath any quarrel</line>
            <line>to me: my remembrance is very free and clear from</line>
            <line>any image of offence done to any man.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>You'll find it otherwise, I assure you: therefore,</line>
            <line>if you hold your life at any price, betake you to</line>
            <line>your guard; for your opposite hath in him what</line>
            <line>youth, strength, skill and wrath can furnish man withal.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>I pray you, sir, what is he?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>He is knight, dubbed with unhatched rapier and on</line>
            <line>carpet consideration; but he is a devil in private</line>
            <line>brawl: souls and bodies hath he divorced three; and</line>
            <line>his incensement at this moment is so implacable,</line>
            <line>that satisfaction can be none but by pangs of death</line>
            <line>and sepulchre. Hob, nob, is his word; give't or take't.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>I will return again into the house and desire some</line>
            <line>conduct of the lady. I am no fighter. I have heard</line>
            <line>of some kind of men that put quarrels purposely on</line>
            <line>others, to taste their valour: belike this is a man</line>
            <line>of that quirk.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Sir, no; his indignation derives itself out of a</line>
            <line>very competent injury: therefore, get you on and</line>
            <line>give him his desire. Back you shall not to the</line>
            <line>house, unless you undertake that with me which with</line>
            <line>as much safety you might answer him: therefore, on,</line>
            <line>or strip your sword stark naked; for meddle you</line>
            <line>must, that's certain, or forswear to wear iron about you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>This is as uncivil as strange. I beseech you, do me</line>
            <line>this courteous office, as to know of the knight what</line>
            <line>my offence to him is: it is something of my</line>
            <line>negligence, nothing of my purpose.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>I will do so. Signior Fabian, stay you by this</line>
            <line>gentleman till my return.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>Pray you, sir, do you know of this matter?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FABIAN</speaker>
            <line>I know the knight is incensed against you, even to a</line>
            <line>mortal arbitrement; but nothing of the circumstance more.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>I beseech you, what manner of man is he?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FABIAN</speaker>
            <line>Nothing of that wonderful promise, to read him by</line>
            <line>his form, as you are like to find him in the proof</line>
            <line>of his valour. He is, indeed, sir, the most skilful,</line>
            <line>bloody and fatal opposite that you could possibly</line>
            <line>have found in any part of Illyria. Will you walk</line>
            <line>towards him? I will make your peace with him if I</line>
            <line>can.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>I shall be much bound to you for't: I am one that</line>
            <line>had rather go with sir priest than sir knight: I</line>
            <line>care not who knows so much of my mettle.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Re-enter SIR TOBY BELCH, with SIR ANDREW</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Why, man, he's a very devil; I have not seen such a</line>
            <line>firago. I had a pass with him, rapier, scabbard and</line>
            <line>all, and he gives me the stuck in with such a mortal</line>
            <line>motion, that it is inevitable; and on the answer, he</line>
            <line>pays you as surely as your feet hit the ground they</line>
            <line>step on. They say he has been fencer to the Sophy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>Pox on't, I'll not meddle with him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Ay, but he will not now be pacified: Fabian can</line>
            <line>scarce hold him yonder.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>Plague on't, an I thought he had been valiant and so</line>
            <line>cunning in fence, I'ld have seen him damned ere I'ld</line>
            <line>have challenged him. Let him let the matter slip,</line>
            <line>and I'll give him my horse, grey Capilet.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>I'll make the motion: stand here, make a good show</line>
            <line>on't: this shall end without the perdition of souls.</line>
            <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>
            <line>Marry, I'll ride your horse as well as I ride you.</line>
            <stagedir>Re-enter FABIAN and VIOLA</stagedir>
            <stagedir>To FABIAN</stagedir>
            <line>I have his horse to take up the quarrel:</line>
            <line>I have persuaded him the youth's a devil.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FABIAN</speaker>
            <line>He is as horribly conceited of him; and pants and</line>
            <line>looks pale, as if a bear were at his heels.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>To VIOLA</stagedir>  There's no remedy, sir; he will fight</line>
            <line>with you for's oath sake: marry, he hath better</line>
            <line>bethought him of his quarrel, and he finds that now</line>
            <line>scarce to be worth talking of: therefore draw, for</line>
            <line>the supportance of his vow; he protests he will not hurt you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  Pray God defend me! A little thing would</line>
            <line>make me tell them how much I lack of a man.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FABIAN</speaker>
            <line>Give ground, if you see him furious.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Come, Sir Andrew, there's no remedy; the gentleman</line>
            <line>will, for his honour's sake, have one bout with you;</line>
            <line>he cannot by the duello avoid it: but he has</line>
            <line>promised me, as he is a gentleman and a soldier, he</line>
            <line>will not hurt you. Come on; to't.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>Pray God, he keep his oath!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>I do assure you, 'tis against my will.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>They draw</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Enter ANTONIO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>Put up your sword. If this young gentleman</line>
            <line>Have done offence, I take the fault on me:</line>
            <line>If you offend him, I for him defy you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>You, sir! why, what are you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>One, sir, that for his love dares yet do more</line>
            <line>Than you have heard him brag to you he will.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Nay, if you be an undertaker, I am for you.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>They draw</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Enter Officers</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FABIAN</speaker>
            <line>O good Sir Toby, hold! here come the officers.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>I'll be with you anon.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>Pray, sir, put your sword up, if you please.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>Marry, will I, sir; and, for that I promised you,</line>
            <line>I'll be as good as my word: he will bear you easily</line>
            <line>and reins well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Officer</speaker>
            <line>This is the man; do thy office.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Officer</speaker>
            <line>Antonio, I arrest thee at the suit of Count Orsino.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>You do mistake me, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Officer</speaker>
            <line>No, sir, no jot; I know your favour well,</line>
            <line>Though now you have no sea-cap on your head.</line>
            <line>Take him away: he knows I know him well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>I must obey.</line>
            <stagedir>To VIOLA</stagedir>
            <line>This comes with seeking you:</line>
            <line>But there's no remedy; I shall answer it.</line>
            <line>What will you do, now my necessity</line>
            <line>Makes me to ask you for my purse? It grieves me</line>
            <line>Much more for what I cannot do for you</line>
            <line>Than what befalls myself. You stand amazed;</line>
            <line>But be of comfort.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Officer</speaker>
            <line>Come, sir, away.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>I must entreat of you some of that money.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>What money, sir?</line>
            <line>For the fair kindness you have show'd me here,</line>
            <line>And, part, being prompted by your present trouble,</line>
            <line>Out of my lean and low ability</line>
            <line>I'll lend you something: my having is not much;</line>
            <line>I'll make division of my present with you:</line>
            <line>Hold, there's half my coffer.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>Will you deny me now?</line>
            <line>Is't possible that my deserts to you</line>
            <line>Can lack persuasion? Do not tempt my misery,</line>
            <line>Lest that it make me so unsound a man</line>
            <line>As to upbraid you with those kindnesses</line>
            <line>That I have done for you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>I know of none;</line>
            <line>Nor know I you by voice or any feature:</line>
            <line>I hate ingratitude more in a man</line>
            <line>Than lying, vainness, babbling, drunkenness,</line>
            <line>Or any taint of vice whose strong corruption</line>
            <line>Inhabits our frail blood.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>O heavens themselves!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Officer</speaker>
            <line>Come, sir, I pray you, go.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>Let me speak a little. This youth that you see here</line>
            <line>I snatch'd one half out of the jaws of death,</line>
            <line>Relieved him with such sanctity of love,</line>
            <line>And to his image, which methought did promise</line>
            <line>Most venerable worth, did I devotion.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Officer</speaker>
            <line>What's that to us? The time goes by: away!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>But O how vile an idol proves this god</line>
            <line>Thou hast, Sebastian, done good feature shame.</line>
            <line>In nature there's no blemish but the mind;</line>
            <line>None can be call'd deform'd but the unkind:</line>
            <line>Virtue is beauty, but the beauteous evil</line>
            <line>Are empty trunks o'erflourish'd by the devil.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Officer</speaker>
            <line>The man grows mad: away with him! Come, come, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>Lead me on.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit with Officers</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>Methinks his words do from such passion fly,</line>
            <line>That he believes himself: so do not I.</line>
            <line>Prove true, imagination, O, prove true,</line>
            <line>That I, dear brother, be now ta'en for you!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Come hither, knight; come hither, Fabian: we'll</line>
            <line>whisper o'er a couplet or two of most sage saws.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>He named Sebastian: I my brother know</line>
            <line>Yet living in my glass; even such and so</line>
            <line>In favour was my brother, and he went</line>
            <line>Still in this fashion, colour, ornament,</line>
            <line>For him I imitate: O, if it prove,</line>
            <line>Tempests are kind and salt waves fresh in love.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>A very dishonest paltry boy, and more a coward than</line>
            <line>a hare: his dishonesty appears in leaving his</line>
            <line>friend here in necessity and denying him; and for</line>
            <line>his cowardship, ask Fabian.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FABIAN</speaker>
            <line>A coward, a most devout coward, religious in it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>'Slid, I'll after him again and beat him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Do; cuff him soundly, but never draw thy sword.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>An I do not,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FABIAN</speaker>
            <line>Come, let's see the event.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>I dare lay any money 'twill be nothing yet.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>