<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net/doctypes/dita/shakespear/dtd/act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-1">
   <title>ACT I</title>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  DUKE ORSINO's palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter DUKE ORSINO, CURIO, and other Lords;
Musicians attending</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE ORSINO</speaker>
            <line>If music be the food of love, play on;</line>
            <line>Give me excess of it, that, surfeiting,</line>
            <line>The appetite may sicken, and so die.</line>
            <line>That strain again! it had a dying fall:</line>
            <line>O, it came o'er my ear like the sweet sound,</line>
            <line>That breathes upon a bank of violets,</line>
            <line>Stealing and giving odour! Enough; no more:</line>
            <line>'Tis not so sweet now as it was before.</line>
            <line>O spirit of love! how quick and fresh art thou,</line>
            <line>That, notwithstanding thy capacity</line>
            <line>Receiveth as the sea, nought enters there,</line>
            <line>Of what validity and pitch soe'er,</line>
            <line>But falls into abatement and low price,</line>
            <line>Even in a minute: so full of shapes is fancy</line>
            <line>That it alone is high fantastical.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CURIO</speaker>
            <line>Will you go hunt, my lord?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE ORSINO</speaker>
            <line>What, Curio?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CURIO</speaker>
            <line>The hart.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE ORSINO</speaker>
            <line>Why, so I do, the noblest that I have:</line>
            <line>O, when mine eyes did see Olivia first,</line>
            <line>Methought she purged the air of pestilence!</line>
            <line>That instant was I turn'd into a hart;</line>
            <line>And my desires, like fell and cruel hounds,</line>
            <line>E'er since pursue me.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter VALENTINE</stagedir>
            <line>How now! what news from her?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VALENTINE</speaker>
            <line>So please my lord, I might not be admitted;</line>
            <line>But from her handmaid do return this answer:</line>
            <line>The element itself, till seven years' heat,</line>
            <line>Shall not behold her face at ample view;</line>
            <line>But, like a cloistress, she will veiled walk</line>
            <line>And water once a day her chamber round</line>
            <line>With eye-offending brine: all this to season</line>
            <line>A brother's dead love, which she would keep fresh</line>
            <line>And lasting in her sad remembrance.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE ORSINO</speaker>
            <line>O, she that hath a heart of that fine frame</line>
            <line>To pay this debt of love but to a brother,</line>
            <line>How will she love, when the rich golden shaft</line>
            <line>Hath kill'd the flock of all affections else</line>
            <line>That live in her; when liver, brain and heart,</line>
            <line>These sovereign thrones, are all supplied, and fill'd</line>
            <line>Her sweet perfections with one self king!</line>
            <line>Away before me to sweet beds of flowers:</line>
            <line>Love-thoughts lie rich when canopied with bowers.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  The sea-coast.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter VIOLA, a Captain, and Sailors</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>What country, friends, is this?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Captain</speaker>
            <line>This is Illyria, lady.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>And what should I do in Illyria?</line>
            <line>My brother he is in Elysium.</line>
            <line>Perchance he is not drown'd: what think you, sailors?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Captain</speaker>
            <line>It is perchance that you yourself were saved.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>O my poor brother! and so perchance may he be.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Captain</speaker>
            <line>True, madam: and, to comfort you with chance,</line>
            <line>Assure yourself, after our ship did split,</line>
            <line>When you and those poor number saved with you</line>
            <line>Hung on our driving boat, I saw your brother,</line>
            <line>Most provident in peril, bind himself,</line>
            <line>Courage and hope both teaching him the practise,</line>
            <line>To a strong mast that lived upon the sea;</line>
            <line>Where, like Arion on the dolphin's back,</line>
            <line>I saw him hold acquaintance with the waves</line>
            <line>So long as I could see.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>For saying so, there's gold:</line>
            <line>Mine own escape unfoldeth to my hope,</line>
            <line>Whereto thy speech serves for authority,</line>
            <line>The like of him. Know'st thou this country?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Captain</speaker>
            <line>Ay, madam, well; for I was bred and born</line>
            <line>Not three hours' travel from this very place.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>Who governs here?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Captain</speaker>
            <line>A noble duke, in nature as in name.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>What is the name?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Captain</speaker>
            <line>Orsino.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>Orsino! I have heard my father name him:</line>
            <line>He was a bachelor then.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Captain</speaker>
            <line>And so is now, or was so very late;</line>
            <line>For but a month ago I went from hence,</line>
            <line>And then 'twas fresh in murmur,--as, you know,</line>
            <line>What great ones do the less will prattle of,--</line>
            <line>That he did seek the love of fair Olivia.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>What's she?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Captain</speaker>
            <line>A virtuous maid, the daughter of a count</line>
            <line>That died some twelvemonth since, then leaving her</line>
            <line>In the protection of his son, her brother,</line>
            <line>Who shortly also died: for whose dear love,</line>
            <line>They say, she hath abjured the company</line>
            <line>And sight of men.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>O that I served that lady</line>
            <line>And might not be delivered to the world,</line>
            <line>Till I had made mine own occasion mellow,</line>
            <line>What my estate is!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Captain</speaker>
            <line>That were hard to compass;</line>
            <line>Because she will admit no kind of suit,</line>
            <line>No, not the duke's.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>There is a fair behavior in thee, captain;</line>
            <line>And though that nature with a beauteous wall</line>
            <line>Doth oft close in pollution, yet of thee</line>
            <line>I will believe thou hast a mind that suits</line>
            <line>With this thy fair and outward character.</line>
            <line>I prithee, and I'll pay thee bounteously,</line>
            <line>Conceal me what I am, and be my aid</line>
            <line>For such disguise as haply shall become</line>
            <line>The form of my intent. I'll serve this duke:</line>
            <line>Thou shall present me as an eunuch to him:</line>
            <line>It may be worth thy pains; for I can sing</line>
            <line>And speak to him in many sorts of music</line>
            <line>That will allow me very worth his service.</line>
            <line>What else may hap to time I will commit;</line>
            <line>Only shape thou thy silence to my wit.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Captain</speaker>
            <line>Be you his eunuch, and your mute I'll be:</line>
            <line>When my tongue blabs, then let mine eyes not see.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>I thank thee: lead me on.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  OLIVIA'S house.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter SIR TOBY BELCH and MARIA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>What a plague means my niece, to take the death of</line>
            <line>her brother thus? I am sure care's an enemy to life.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>By my troth, Sir Toby, you must come in earlier o'</line>
            <line>nights: your cousin, my lady, takes great</line>
            <line>exceptions to your ill hours.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Why, let her except, before excepted.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>Ay, but you must confine yourself within the modest</line>
            <line>limits of order.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Confine! I'll confine myself no finer than I am:</line>
            <line>these clothes are good enough to drink in; and so be</line>
            <line>these boots too: an they be not, let them hang</line>
            <line>themselves in their own straps.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>That quaffing and drinking will undo you: I heard</line>
            <line>my lady talk of it yesterday; and of a foolish</line>
            <line>knight that you brought in one night here to be her wooer.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Who, Sir Andrew Aguecheek?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>Ay, he.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>He's as tall a man as any's in Illyria.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>What's that to the purpose?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Why, he has three thousand ducats a year.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>Ay, but he'll have but a year in all these ducats:</line>
            <line>he's a very fool and a prodigal.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Fie, that you'll say so! he plays o' the</line>
            <line>viol-de-gamboys, and speaks three or four languages</line>
            <line>word for word without book, and hath all the good</line>
            <line>gifts of nature.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>He hath indeed, almost natural: for besides that</line>
            <line>he's a fool, he's a great quarreller: and but that</line>
            <line>he hath the gift of a coward to allay the gust he</line>
            <line>hath in quarrelling, 'tis thought among the prudent</line>
            <line>he would quickly have the gift of a grave.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>By this hand, they are scoundrels and subtractors</line>
            <line>that say so of him. Who are they?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>They that add, moreover, he's drunk nightly in your company.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>With drinking healths to my niece: I'll drink to</line>
            <line>her as long as there is a passage in my throat and</line>
            <line>drink in Illyria: he's a coward and a coystrill</line>
            <line>that will not drink to my niece till his brains turn</line>
            <line>o' the toe like a parish-top. What, wench!</line>
            <line>Castiliano vulgo! for here comes Sir Andrew Agueface.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter SIR ANDREW</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>Sir Toby Belch! how now, Sir Toby Belch!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Sweet Sir Andrew!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>Bless you, fair shrew.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>And you too, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Accost, Sir Andrew, accost.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>What's that?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>My niece's chambermaid.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>Good Mistress Accost, I desire better acquaintance.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>My name is Mary, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>Good Mistress Mary Accost,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>You mistake, knight; 'accost' is front her, board</line>
            <line>her, woo her, assail her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>By my troth, I would not undertake her in this</line>
            <line>company. Is that the meaning of 'accost'?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>Fare you well, gentlemen.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>An thou let part so, Sir Andrew, would thou mightst</line>
            <line>never draw sword again.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>An you part so, mistress, I would I might never</line>
            <line>draw sword again. Fair lady, do you think you have</line>
            <line>fools in hand?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>Sir, I have not you by the hand.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>Marry, but you shall have; and here's my hand.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>Now, sir, 'thought is free:' I pray you, bring</line>
            <line>your hand to the buttery-bar and let it drink.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>Wherefore, sweet-heart? what's your metaphor?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>It's dry, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>Why, I think so: I am not such an ass but I can</line>
            <line>keep my hand dry. But what's your jest?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>A dry jest, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>Are you full of them?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>Ay, sir, I have them at my fingers' ends: marry,</line>
            <line>now I let go your hand, I am barren.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>O knight thou lackest a cup of canary: when did I</line>
            <line>see thee so put down?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>Never in your life, I think; unless you see canary</line>
            <line>put me down. Methinks sometimes I have no more wit</line>
            <line>than a Christian or an ordinary man has: but I am a</line>
            <line>great eater of beef and I believe that does harm to my wit.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>No question.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>An I thought that, I'ld forswear it. I'll ride home</line>
            <line>to-morrow, Sir Toby.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Pourquoi, my dear knight?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>What is 'Pourquoi'? do or not do? I would I had</line>
            <line>bestowed that time in the tongues that I have in</line>
            <line>fencing, dancing and bear-baiting: O, had I but</line>
            <line>followed the arts!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Then hadst thou had an excellent head of hair.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>Why, would that have mended my hair?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Past question; for thou seest it will not curl by nature.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>But it becomes me well enough, does't not?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Excellent; it hangs like flax on a distaff; and I</line>
            <line>hope to see a housewife take thee between her legs</line>
            <line>and spin it off.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>Faith, I'll home to-morrow, Sir Toby: your niece</line>
            <line>will not be seen; or if she be, it's four to one</line>
            <line>she'll none of me: the count himself here hard by woos her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>She'll none o' the count: she'll not match above</line>
            <line>her degree, neither in estate, years, nor wit; I</line>
            <line>have heard her swear't. Tut, there's life in't,</line>
            <line>man.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>I'll stay a month longer. I am a fellow o' the</line>
            <line>strangest mind i' the world; I delight in masques</line>
            <line>and revels sometimes altogether.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Art thou good at these kickshawses, knight?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>As any man in Illyria, whatsoever he be, under the</line>
            <line>degree of my betters; and yet I will not compare</line>
            <line>with an old man.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>What is thy excellence in a galliard, knight?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>Faith, I can cut a caper.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>And I can cut the mutton to't.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>And I think I have the back-trick simply as strong</line>
            <line>as any man in Illyria.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Wherefore are these things hid? wherefore have</line>
            <line>these gifts a curtain before 'em? are they like to</line>
            <line>take dust, like Mistress Mall's picture? why dost</line>
            <line>thou not go to church in a galliard and come home in</line>
            <line>a coranto? My very walk should be a jig; I would not</line>
            <line>so much as make water but in a sink-a-pace. What</line>
            <line>dost thou mean? Is it a world to hide virtues in?</line>
            <line>I did think, by the excellent constitution of thy</line>
            <line>leg, it was formed under the star of a galliard.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>Ay, 'tis strong, and it does indifferent well in a</line>
            <line>flame-coloured stock. Shall we set about some revels?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>What shall we do else? were we not born under Taurus?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>Taurus! That's sides and heart.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>No, sir; it is legs and thighs. Let me see the</line>
            <line>caper; ha! higher: ha, ha! excellent!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-4">
      <title>SCENE IV.  DUKE ORSINO's palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter VALENTINE and VIOLA in man's attire</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VALENTINE</speaker>
            <line>If the duke continue these favours towards you,</line>
            <line>Cesario, you are like to be much advanced: he hath</line>
            <line>known you but three days, and already you are no stranger.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>You either fear his humour or my negligence, that</line>
            <line>you call in question the continuance of his love:</line>
            <line>is he inconstant, sir, in his favours?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VALENTINE</speaker>
            <line>No, believe me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>I thank you. Here comes the count.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter DUKE ORSINO, CURIO, and Attendants</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE ORSINO</speaker>
            <line>Who saw Cesario, ho?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>On your attendance, my lord; here.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE ORSINO</speaker>
            <line>Stand you a while aloof, Cesario,</line>
            <line>Thou know'st no less but all; I have unclasp'd</line>
            <line>To thee the book even of my secret soul:</line>
            <line>Therefore, good youth, address thy gait unto her;</line>
            <line>Be not denied access, stand at her doors,</line>
            <line>And tell them, there thy fixed foot shall grow</line>
            <line>Till thou have audience.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>Sure, my noble lord,</line>
            <line>If she be so abandon'd to her sorrow</line>
            <line>As it is spoke, she never will admit me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE ORSINO</speaker>
            <line>Be clamorous and leap all civil bounds</line>
            <line>Rather than make unprofited return.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>Say I do speak with her, my lord, what then?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE ORSINO</speaker>
            <line>O, then unfold the passion of my love,</line>
            <line>Surprise her with discourse of my dear faith:</line>
            <line>It shall become thee well to act my woes;</line>
            <line>She will attend it better in thy youth</line>
            <line>Than in a nuncio's of more grave aspect.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>I think not so, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE ORSINO</speaker>
            <line>Dear lad, believe it;</line>
            <line>For they shall yet belie thy happy years,</line>
            <line>That say thou art a man: Diana's lip</line>
            <line>Is not more smooth and rubious; thy small pipe</line>
            <line>Is as the maiden's organ, shrill and sound,</line>
            <line>And all is semblative a woman's part.</line>
            <line>I know thy constellation is right apt</line>
            <line>For this affair. Some four or five attend him;</line>
            <line>All, if you will; for I myself am best</line>
            <line>When least in company. Prosper well in this,</line>
            <line>And thou shalt live as freely as thy lord,</line>
            <line>To call his fortunes thine.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>I'll do my best</line>
            <line>To woo your lady:</line>
            <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>
            <line>yet, a barful strife!</line>
            <line>Whoe'er I woo, myself would be his wife.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-5">
      <title>SCENE V.  OLIVIA'S house.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter MARIA and Clown</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>Nay, either tell me where thou hast been, or I will</line>
            <line>not open my lips so wide as a bristle may enter in</line>
            <line>way of thy excuse: my lady will hang thee for thy absence.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Let her hang me: he that is well hanged in this</line>
            <line>world needs to fear no colours.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>Make that good.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>He shall see none to fear.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>A good lenten answer: I can tell thee where that</line>
            <line>saying was born, of 'I fear no colours.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Where, good Mistress Mary?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>In the wars; and that may you be bold to say in your foolery.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Well, God give them wisdom that have it; and those</line>
            <line>that are fools, let them use their talents.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>Yet you will be hanged for being so long absent; or,</line>
            <line>to be turned away, is not that as good as a hanging to you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Many a good hanging prevents a bad marriage; and,</line>
            <line>for turning away, let summer bear it out.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>You are resolute, then?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Not so, neither; but I am resolved on two points.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>That if one break, the other will hold; or, if both</line>
            <line>break, your gaskins fall.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Apt, in good faith; very apt. Well, go thy way; if</line>
            <line>Sir Toby would leave drinking, thou wert as witty a</line>
            <line>piece of Eve's flesh as any in Illyria.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>Peace, you rogue, no more o' that. Here comes my</line>
            <line>lady: make your excuse wisely, you were best.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Wit, an't be thy will, put me into good fooling!</line>
            <line>Those wits, that think they have thee, do very oft</line>
            <line>prove fools; and I, that am sure I lack thee, may</line>
            <line>pass for a wise man: for what says Quinapalus?</line>
            <line>'Better a witty fool, than a foolish wit.'</line>
            <stagedir>Enter OLIVIA with MALVOLIO</stagedir>
            <line>God bless thee, lady!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>Take the fool away.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Do you not hear, fellows? Take away the lady.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>Go to, you're a dry fool; I'll no more of you:</line>
            <line>besides, you grow dishonest.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Two faults, madonna, that drink and good counsel</line>
            <line>will amend: for give the dry fool drink, then is</line>
            <line>the fool not dry: bid the dishonest man mend</line>
            <line>himself; if he mend, he is no longer dishonest; if</line>
            <line>he cannot, let the botcher mend him. Any thing</line>
            <line>that's mended is but patched: virtue that</line>
            <line>transgresses is but patched with sin; and sin that</line>
            <line>amends is but patched with virtue. If that this</line>
            <line>simple syllogism will serve, so; if it will not,</line>
            <line>what remedy? As there is no true cuckold but</line>
            <line>calamity, so beauty's a flower. The lady bade take</line>
            <line>away the fool; therefore, I say again, take her away.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>Sir, I bade them take away you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Misprision in the highest degree! Lady, cucullus non</line>
            <line>facit monachum; that's as much to say as I wear not</line>
            <line>motley in my brain. Good madonna, give me leave to</line>
            <line>prove you a fool.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>Can you do it?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Dexterously, good madonna.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>Make your proof.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>I must catechise you for it, madonna: good my mouse</line>
            <line>of virtue, answer me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>Well, sir, for want of other idleness, I'll bide your proof.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Good madonna, why mournest thou?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>Good fool, for my brother's death.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>I think his soul is in hell, madonna.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>I know his soul is in heaven, fool.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>The more fool, madonna, to mourn for your brother's</line>
            <line>soul being in heaven. Take away the fool, gentlemen.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>What think you of this fool, Malvolio? doth he not mend?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>Yes, and shall do till the pangs of death shake him:</line>
            <line>infirmity, that decays the wise, doth ever make the</line>
            <line>better fool.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>God send you, sir, a speedy infirmity, for the</line>
            <line>better increasing your folly! Sir Toby will be</line>
            <line>sworn that I am no fox; but he will not pass his</line>
            <line>word for two pence that you are no fool.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>How say you to that, Malvolio?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>I marvel your ladyship takes delight in such a</line>
            <line>barren rascal: I saw him put down the other day</line>
            <line>with an ordinary fool that has no more brain</line>
            <line>than a stone. Look you now, he's out of his guard</line>
            <line>already; unless you laugh and minister occasion to</line>
            <line>him, he is gagged. I protest, I take these wise men,</line>
            <line>that crow so at these set kind of fools, no better</line>
            <line>than the fools' zanies.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>Oh, you are sick of self-love, Malvolio, and taste</line>
            <line>with a distempered appetite. To be generous,</line>
            <line>guiltless and of free disposition, is to take those</line>
            <line>things for bird-bolts that you deem cannon-bullets:</line>
            <line>there is no slander in an allowed fool, though he do</line>
            <line>nothing but rail; nor no railing in a known discreet</line>
            <line>man, though he do nothing but reprove.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Now Mercury endue thee with leasing, for thou</line>
            <line>speakest well of fools!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter MARIA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>Madam, there is at the gate a young gentleman much</line>
            <line>desires to speak with you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>From the Count Orsino, is it?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>I know not, madam: 'tis a fair young man, and well attended.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>Who of my people hold him in delay?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>Sir Toby, madam, your kinsman.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>Fetch him off, I pray you; he speaks nothing but</line>
            <line>madman: fie on him!</line>
            <stagedir>Exit MARIA</stagedir>
            <line>Go you, Malvolio: if it be a suit from the count, I</line>
            <line>am sick, or not at home; what you will, to dismiss it.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit MALVOLIO</stagedir>
            <line>Now you see, sir, how your fooling grows old, and</line>
            <line>people dislike it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Thou hast spoke for us, madonna, as if thy eldest</line>
            <line>son should be a fool; whose skull Jove cram with</line>
            <line>brains! for,--here he comes,--one of thy kin has a</line>
            <line>most weak pia mater.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter SIR TOBY BELCH</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>By mine honour, half drunk. What is he at the gate, cousin?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>A gentleman.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>A gentleman! what gentleman?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>'Tis a gentle man here--a plague o' these</line>
            <line>pickle-herring! How now, sot!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Good Sir Toby!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>Cousin, cousin, how have you come so early by this lethargy?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Lechery! I defy lechery. There's one at the gate.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>Ay, marry, what is he?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Let him be the devil, an he will, I care not: give</line>
            <line>me faith, say I. Well, it's all one.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>What's a drunken man like, fool?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Like a drowned man, a fool and a mad man: one</line>
            <line>draught above heat makes him a fool; the second mads</line>
            <line>him; and a third drowns him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>Go thou and seek the crowner, and let him sit o' my</line>
            <line>coz; for he's in the third degree of drink, he's</line>
            <line>drowned: go, look after him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>He is but mad yet, madonna; and the fool shall look</line>
            <line>to the madman.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Re-enter MALVOLIO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>Madam, yond young fellow swears he will speak with</line>
            <line>you. I told him you were sick; he takes on him to</line>
            <line>understand so much, and therefore comes to speak</line>
            <line>with you. I told him you were asleep; he seems to</line>
            <line>have a foreknowledge of that too, and therefore</line>
            <line>comes to speak with you. What is to be said to him,</line>
            <line>lady? he's fortified against any denial.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>Tell him he shall not speak with me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>Has been told so; and he says, he'll stand at your</line>
            <line>door like a sheriff's post, and be the supporter to</line>
            <line>a bench, but he'll speak with you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>What kind o' man is he?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>Why, of mankind.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>What manner of man?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>Of very ill manner; he'll speak with you, will you or no.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>Of what personage and years is he?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>Not yet old enough for a man, nor young enough for</line>
            <line>a boy; as a squash is before 'tis a peascod, or a</line>
            <line>cooling when 'tis almost an apple: 'tis with him</line>
            <line>in standing water, between boy and man. He is very</line>
            <line>well-favoured and he speaks very shrewishly; one</line>
            <line>would think his mother's milk were scarce out of him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>Let him approach: call in my gentlewoman.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>Gentlewoman, my lady calls.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Re-enter MARIA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>Give me my veil: come, throw it o'er my face.</line>
            <line>We'll once more hear Orsino's embassy.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter VIOLA, and Attendants</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>The honourable lady of the house, which is she?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>Speak to me; I shall answer for her.</line>
            <line>Your will?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>Most radiant, exquisite and unmatchable beauty,--I</line>
            <line>pray you, tell me if this be the lady of the house,</line>
            <line>for I never saw her: I would be loath to cast away</line>
            <line>my speech, for besides that it is excellently well</line>
            <line>penned, I have taken great pains to con it. Good</line>
            <line>beauties, let me sustain no scorn; I am very</line>
            <line>comptible, even to the least sinister usage.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>Whence came you, sir?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>I can say little more than I have studied, and that</line>
            <line>question's out of my part. Good gentle one, give me</line>
            <line>modest assurance if you be the lady of the house,</line>
            <line>that I may proceed in my speech.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>Are you a comedian?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>No, my profound heart: and yet, by the very fangs</line>
            <line>of malice I swear, I am not that I play. Are you</line>
            <line>the lady of the house?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>If I do not usurp myself, I am.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>Most certain, if you are she, you do usurp</line>
            <line>yourself; for what is yours to bestow is not yours</line>
            <line>to reserve. But this is from my commission: I will</line>
            <line>on with my speech in your praise, and then show you</line>
            <line>the heart of my message.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>Come to what is important in't: I forgive you the praise.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>Alas, I took great pains to study it, and 'tis poetical.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>It is the more like to be feigned: I pray you,</line>
            <line>keep it in. I heard you were saucy at my gates,</line>
            <line>and allowed your approach rather to wonder at you</line>
            <line>than to hear you. If you be not mad, be gone; if</line>
            <line>you have reason, be brief: 'tis not that time of</line>
            <line>moon with me to make one in so skipping a dialogue.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>Will you hoist sail, sir? here lies your way.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>No, good swabber; I am to hull here a little</line>
            <line>longer. Some mollification for your giant, sweet</line>
            <line>lady. Tell me your mind: I am a messenger.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>Sure, you have some hideous matter to deliver, when</line>
            <line>the courtesy of it is so fearful. Speak your office.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>It alone concerns your ear. I bring no overture of</line>
            <line>war, no taxation of homage: I hold the olive in my</line>
            <line>hand; my words are as fun of peace as matter.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>Yet you began rudely. What are you? what would you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>The rudeness that hath appeared in me have I</line>
            <line>learned from my entertainment. What I am, and what I</line>
            <line>would, are as secret as maidenhead; to your ears,</line>
            <line>divinity, to any other's, profanation.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>Give us the place alone: we will hear this divinity.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt MARIA and Attendants</stagedir>
            <line>Now, sir, what is your text?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>Most sweet lady,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>A comfortable doctrine, and much may be said of it.</line>
            <line>Where lies your text?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>In Orsino's bosom.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>In his bosom! In what chapter of his bosom?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>To answer by the method, in the first of his heart.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>O, I have read it: it is heresy. Have you no more to say?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>Good madam, let me see your face.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>Have you any commission from your lord to negotiate</line>
            <line>with my face? You are now out of your text: but</line>
            <line>we will draw the curtain and show you the picture.</line>
            <line>Look you, sir, such a one I was this present: is't</line>
            <line>not well done?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Unveiling</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>Excellently done, if God did all.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>'Tis in grain, sir; 'twill endure wind and weather.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>'Tis beauty truly blent, whose red and white</line>
            <line>Nature's own sweet and cunning hand laid on:</line>
            <line>Lady, you are the cruell'st she alive,</line>
            <line>If you will lead these graces to the grave</line>
            <line>And leave the world no copy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>O, sir, I will not be so hard-hearted; I will give</line>
            <line>out divers schedules of my beauty: it shall be</line>
            <line>inventoried, and every particle and utensil</line>
            <line>labelled to my will: as, item, two lips,</line>
            <line>indifferent red; item, two grey eyes, with lids to</line>
            <line>them; item, one neck, one chin, and so forth. Were</line>
            <line>you sent hither to praise me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>I see you what you are, you are too proud;</line>
            <line>But, if you were the devil, you are fair.</line>
            <line>My lord and master loves you: O, such love</line>
            <line>Could be but recompensed, though you were crown'd</line>
            <line>The nonpareil of beauty!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>How does he love me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>With adorations, fertile tears,</line>
            <line>With groans that thunder love, with sighs of fire.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>Your lord does know my mind; I cannot love him:</line>
            <line>Yet I suppose him virtuous, know him noble,</line>
            <line>Of great estate, of fresh and stainless youth;</line>
            <line>In voices well divulged, free, learn'd and valiant;</line>
            <line>And in dimension and the shape of nature</line>
            <line>A gracious person: but yet I cannot love him;</line>
            <line>He might have took his answer long ago.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>If I did love you in my master's flame,</line>
            <line>With such a suffering, such a deadly life,</line>
            <line>In your denial I would find no sense;</line>
            <line>I would not understand it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>Why, what would you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>Make me a willow cabin at your gate,</line>
            <line>And call upon my soul within the house;</line>
            <line>Write loyal cantons of contemned love</line>
            <line>And sing them loud even in the dead of night;</line>
            <line>Halloo your name to the reverberate hills</line>
            <line>And make the babbling gossip of the air</line>
            <line>Cry out 'Olivia!' O, You should not rest</line>
            <line>Between the elements of air and earth,</line>
            <line>But you should pity me!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>You might do much.</line>
            <line>What is your parentage?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>Above my fortunes, yet my state is well:</line>
            <line>I am a gentleman.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>Get you to your lord;</line>
            <line>I cannot love him: let him send no more;</line>
            <line>Unless, perchance, you come to me again,</line>
            <line>To tell me how he takes it. Fare you well:</line>
            <line>I thank you for your pains: spend this for me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>I am no fee'd post, lady; keep your purse:</line>
            <line>My master, not myself, lacks recompense.</line>
            <line>Love make his heart of flint that you shall love;</line>
            <line>And let your fervor, like my master's, be</line>
            <line>Placed in contempt! Farewell, fair cruelty.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>'What is your parentage?'</line>
            <line>'Above my fortunes, yet my state is well:</line>
            <line>I am a gentleman.' I'll be sworn thou art;</line>
            <line>Thy tongue, thy face, thy limbs, actions and spirit,</line>
            <line>Do give thee five-fold blazon: not too fast:</line>
            <line>soft, soft!</line>
            <line>Unless the master were the man. How now!</line>
            <line>Even so quickly may one catch the plague?</line>
            <line>Methinks I feel this youth's perfections</line>
            <line>With an invisible and subtle stealth</line>
            <line>To creep in at mine eyes. Well, let it be.</line>
            <line>What ho, Malvolio!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter MALVOLIO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>Here, madam, at your service.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>Run after that same peevish messenger,</line>
            <line>The county's man: he left this ring behind him,</line>
            <line>Would I or not: tell him I'll none of it.</line>
            <line>Desire him not to flatter with his lord,</line>
            <line>Nor hold him up with hopes; I am not for him:</line>
            <line>If that the youth will come this way to-morrow,</line>
            <line>I'll give him reasons for't: hie thee, Malvolio.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>Madam, I will.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>OLIVIA</speaker>
            <line>I do I know not what, and fear to find</line>
            <line>Mine eye too great a flatterer for my mind.</line>
            <line>Fate, show thy force: ourselves we do not owe;</line>
            <line>What is decreed must be, and be this so.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>