<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:shakespear:dtd:act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-2">
   <title>ACT II</title>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  The sea-coast.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter ANTONIO and SEBASTIAN</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>Will you stay no longer? nor will you not that I go with you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SEBASTIAN</speaker>
            <line>By your patience, no. My stars shine darkly over</line>
            <line>me: the malignancy of my fate might perhaps</line>
            <line>distemper yours; therefore I shall crave of you your</line>
            <line>leave that I may bear my evils alone: it were a bad</line>
            <line>recompense for your love, to lay any of them on you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>Let me yet know of you whither you are bound.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SEBASTIAN</speaker>
            <line>No, sooth, sir: my determinate voyage is mere</line>
            <line>extravagancy. But I perceive in you so excellent a</line>
            <line>touch of modesty, that you will not extort from me</line>
            <line>what I am willing to keep in; therefore it charges</line>
            <line>me in manners the rather to express myself. You</line>
            <line>must know of me then, Antonio, my name is Sebastian,</line>
            <line>which I called Roderigo. My father was that</line>
            <line>Sebastian of Messaline, whom I know you have heard</line>
            <line>of. He left behind him myself and a sister, both</line>
            <line>born in an hour: if the heavens had been pleased,</line>
            <line>would we had so ended! but you, sir, altered that;</line>
            <line>for some hour before you took me from the breach of</line>
            <line>the sea was my sister drowned.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>Alas the day!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SEBASTIAN</speaker>
            <line>A lady, sir, though it was said she much resembled</line>
            <line>me, was yet of many accounted beautiful: but,</line>
            <line>though I could not with such estimable wonder</line>
            <line>overfar believe that, yet thus far I will boldly</line>
            <line>publish her; she bore a mind that envy could not but</line>
            <line>call fair. She is drowned already, sir, with salt</line>
            <line>water, though I seem to drown her remembrance again with more.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>Pardon me, sir, your bad entertainment.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SEBASTIAN</speaker>
            <line>O good Antonio, forgive me your trouble.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>If you will not murder me for my love, let me be</line>
            <line>your servant.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SEBASTIAN</speaker>
            <line>If you will not undo what you have done, that is,</line>
            <line>kill him whom you have recovered, desire it not.</line>
            <line>Fare ye well at once: my bosom is full of kindness,</line>
            <line>and I am yet so near the manners of my mother, that</line>
            <line>upon the least occasion more mine eyes will tell</line>
            <line>tales of me. I am bound to the Count Orsino's court: farewell.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTONIO</speaker>
            <line>The gentleness of all the gods go with thee!</line>
            <line>I have many enemies in Orsino's court,</line>
            <line>Else would I very shortly see thee there.</line>
            <line>But, come what may, I do adore thee so,</line>
            <line>That danger shall seem sport, and I will go.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  A street.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter VIOLA, MALVOLIO following</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>Were not you even now with the Countess Olivia?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>Even now, sir; on a moderate pace I have since</line>
            <line>arrived but hither.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>She returns this ring to you, sir: you might have</line>
            <line>saved me my pains, to have taken it away yourself.</line>
            <line>She adds, moreover, that you should put your lord</line>
            <line>into a desperate assurance she will none of him:</line>
            <line>and one thing more, that you be never so hardy to</line>
            <line>come again in his affairs, unless it be to report</line>
            <line>your lord's taking of this. Receive it so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>She took the ring of me: I'll none of it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>Come, sir, you peevishly threw it to her; and her</line>
            <line>will is, it should be so returned: if it be worth</line>
            <line>stooping for, there it lies in your eye; if not, be</line>
            <line>it his that finds it.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>I left no ring with her: what means this lady?</line>
            <line>Fortune forbid my outside have not charm'd her!</line>
            <line>She made good view of me; indeed, so much,</line>
            <line>That sure methought her eyes had lost her tongue,</line>
            <line>For she did speak in starts distractedly.</line>
            <line>She loves me, sure; the cunning of her passion</line>
            <line>Invites me in this churlish messenger.</line>
            <line>None of my lord's ring! why, he sent her none.</line>
            <line>I am the man: if it be so, as 'tis,</line>
            <line>Poor lady, she were better love a dream.</line>
            <line>Disguise, I see, thou art a wickedness,</line>
            <line>Wherein the pregnant enemy does much.</line>
            <line>How easy is it for the proper-false</line>
            <line>In women's waxen hearts to set their forms!</line>
            <line>Alas, our frailty is the cause, not we!</line>
            <line>For such as we are made of, such we be.</line>
            <line>How will this fadge? my master loves her dearly;</line>
            <line>And I, poor monster, fond as much on him;</line>
            <line>And she, mistaken, seems to dote on me.</line>
            <line>What will become of this? As I am man,</line>
            <line>My state is desperate for my master's love;</line>
            <line>As I am woman,--now alas the day!--</line>
            <line>What thriftless sighs shall poor Olivia breathe!</line>
            <line>O time! thou must untangle this, not I;</line>
            <line>It is too hard a knot for me to untie!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  OLIVIA's house.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter SIR TOBY BELCH and SIR ANDREW</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Approach, Sir Andrew: not to be abed after</line>
            <line>midnight is to be up betimes; and 'diluculo</line>
            <line>surgere,' thou know'st,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>Nay, my troth, I know not: but I know, to be up</line>
            <line>late is to be up late.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>A false conclusion: I hate it as an unfilled can.</line>
            <line>To be up after midnight and to go to bed then, is</line>
            <line>early: so that to go to bed after midnight is to go</line>
            <line>to bed betimes. Does not our life consist of the</line>
            <line>four elements?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>Faith, so they say; but I think it rather consists</line>
            <line>of eating and drinking.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Thou'rt a scholar; let us therefore eat and drink.</line>
            <line>Marian, I say! a stoup of wine!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter Clown</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>Here comes the fool, i' faith.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>How now, my hearts! did you never see the picture</line>
            <line>of 'we three'?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Welcome, ass. Now let's have a catch.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>By my troth, the fool has an excellent breast. I</line>
            <line>had rather than forty shillings I had such a leg,</line>
            <line>and so sweet a breath to sing, as the fool has. In</line>
            <line>sooth, thou wast in very gracious fooling last</line>
            <line>night, when thou spokest of Pigrogromitus, of the</line>
            <line>Vapians passing the equinoctial of Queubus: 'twas</line>
            <line>very good, i' faith. I sent thee sixpence for thy</line>
            <line>leman: hadst it?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>I did impeticos thy gratillity; for Malvolio's nose</line>
            <line>is no whipstock: my lady has a white hand, and the</line>
            <line>Myrmidons are no bottle-ale houses.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>Excellent! why, this is the best fooling, when all</line>
            <line>is done. Now, a song.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Come on; there is sixpence for you: let's have a song.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>There's a testril of me too: if one knight give a--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Would you have a love-song, or a song of good life?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>A love-song, a love-song.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>Ay, ay: I care not for good life.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Sings</stagedir>
            </line>
            <line>O mistress mine, where are you roaming?</line>
            <line>O, stay and hear; your true love's coming,</line>
            <line>That can sing both high and low:</line>
            <line>Trip no further, pretty sweeting;</line>
            <line>Journeys end in lovers meeting,</line>
            <line>Every wise man's son doth know.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>Excellent good, i' faith.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Good, good.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Sings</stagedir>
            </line>
            <line>What is love? 'tis not hereafter;</line>
            <line>Present mirth hath present laughter;</line>
            <line>What's to come is still unsure:</line>
            <line>In delay there lies no plenty;</line>
            <line>Then come kiss me, sweet and twenty,</line>
            <line>Youth's a stuff will not endure.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>A mellifluous voice, as I am true knight.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>A contagious breath.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>Very sweet and contagious, i' faith.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>To hear by the nose, it is dulcet in contagion.</line>
            <line>But shall we make the welkin dance indeed? shall we</line>
            <line>rouse the night-owl in a catch that will draw three</line>
            <line>souls out of one weaver? shall we do that?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>An you love me, let's do't: I am dog at a catch.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>By'r lady, sir, and some dogs will catch well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>Most certain. Let our catch be, 'Thou knave.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>'Hold thy peace, thou knave,' knight? I shall be</line>
            <line>constrained in't to call thee knave, knight.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>'Tis not the first time I have constrained one to</line>
            <line>call me knave. Begin, fool: it begins 'Hold thy peace.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>I shall never begin if I hold my peace.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>Good, i' faith. Come, begin.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Catch sung</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Enter MARIA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>What a caterwauling do you keep here! If my lady</line>
            <line>have not called up her steward Malvolio and bid him</line>
            <line>turn you out of doors, never trust me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>My lady's a Cataian, we are politicians, Malvolio's</line>
            <line>a Peg-a-Ramsey, and 'Three merry men be we.' Am not</line>
            <line>I consanguineous? am I not of her blood?</line>
            <line>Tillyvally. Lady!</line>
            <stagedir>Sings</stagedir>
            <line>'There dwelt a man in Babylon, lady, lady!'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Beshrew me, the knight's in admirable fooling.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>Ay, he does well enough if he be disposed, and so do</line>
            <line>I too: he does it with a better grace, but I do it</line>
            <line>more natural.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Sings</stagedir>  'O, the twelfth day of December,'--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>For the love o' God, peace!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter MALVOLIO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>My masters, are you mad? or what are you? Have ye</line>
            <line>no wit, manners, nor honesty, but to gabble like</line>
            <line>tinkers at this time of night? Do ye make an</line>
            <line>alehouse of my lady's house, that ye squeak out your</line>
            <line>coziers' catches without any mitigation or remorse</line>
            <line>of voice? Is there no respect of place, persons, nor</line>
            <line>time in you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>We did keep time, sir, in our catches. Sneck up!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>Sir Toby, I must be round with you. My lady bade me</line>
            <line>tell you, that, though she harbours you as her</line>
            <line>kinsman, she's nothing allied to your disorders. If</line>
            <line>you can separate yourself and your misdemeanors, you</line>
            <line>are welcome to the house; if not, an it would please</line>
            <line>you to take leave of her, she is very willing to bid</line>
            <line>you farewell.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>'Farewell, dear heart, since I must needs be gone.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>Nay, good Sir Toby.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>'His eyes do show his days are almost done.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>Is't even so?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>'But I will never die.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Sir Toby, there you lie.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>This is much credit to you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>'Shall I bid him go?'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>'What an if you do?'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>'Shall I bid him go, and spare not?'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>'O no, no, no, no, you dare not.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Out o' tune, sir: ye lie. Art any more than a</line>
            <line>steward? Dost thou think, because thou art</line>
            <line>virtuous, there shall be no more cakes and ale?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Yes, by Saint Anne, and ginger shall be hot i' the</line>
            <line>mouth too.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Thou'rt i' the right. Go, sir, rub your chain with</line>
            <line>crumbs. A stoup of wine, Maria!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>Mistress Mary, if you prized my lady's favour at any</line>
            <line>thing more than contempt, you would not give means</line>
            <line>for this uncivil rule: she shall know of it, by this hand.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>Go shake your ears.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>'Twere as good a deed as to drink when a man's</line>
            <line>a-hungry, to challenge him the field, and then to</line>
            <line>break promise with him and make a fool of him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Do't, knight: I'll write thee a challenge: or I'll</line>
            <line>deliver thy indignation to him by word of mouth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>Sweet Sir Toby, be patient for tonight: since the</line>
            <line>youth of the count's was today with thy lady, she is</line>
            <line>much out of quiet. For Monsieur Malvolio, let me</line>
            <line>alone with him: if I do not gull him into a</line>
            <line>nayword, and make him a common recreation, do not</line>
            <line>think I have wit enough to lie straight in my bed:</line>
            <line>I know I can do it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Possess us, possess us; tell us something of him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>Marry, sir, sometimes he is a kind of puritan.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>O, if I thought that I'ld beat him like a dog!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>What, for being a puritan? thy exquisite reason,</line>
            <line>dear knight?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>I have no exquisite reason for't, but I have reason</line>
            <line>good enough.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>The devil a puritan that he is, or any thing</line>
            <line>constantly, but a time-pleaser; an affectioned ass,</line>
            <line>that cons state without book and utters it by great</line>
            <line>swarths: the best persuaded of himself, so</line>
            <line>crammed, as he thinks, with excellencies, that it is</line>
            <line>his grounds of faith that all that look on him love</line>
            <line>him; and on that vice in him will my revenge find</line>
            <line>notable cause to work.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>What wilt thou do?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>I will drop in his way some obscure epistles of</line>
            <line>love; wherein, by the colour of his beard, the shape</line>
            <line>of his leg, the manner of his gait, the expressure</line>
            <line>of his eye, forehead, and complexion, he shall find</line>
            <line>himself most feelingly personated. I can write very</line>
            <line>like my lady your niece: on a forgotten matter we</line>
            <line>can hardly make distinction of our hands.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Excellent! I smell a device.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>I have't in my nose too.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>He shall think, by the letters that thou wilt drop,</line>
            <line>that they come from my niece, and that she's in</line>
            <line>love with him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>My purpose is, indeed, a horse of that colour.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>And your horse now would make him an ass.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>Ass, I doubt not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>O, 'twill be admirable!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>Sport royal, I warrant you: I know my physic will</line>
            <line>work with him. I will plant you two, and let the</line>
            <line>fool make a third, where he shall find the letter:</line>
            <line>observe his construction of it. For this night, to</line>
            <line>bed, and dream on the event. Farewell.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Good night, Penthesilea.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>Before me, she's a good wench.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>She's a beagle, true-bred, and one that adores me:</line>
            <line>what o' that?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>I was adored once too.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Let's to bed, knight. Thou hadst need send for</line>
            <line>more money.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>If I cannot recover your niece, I am a foul way out.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Send for money, knight: if thou hast her not i'</line>
            <line>the end, call me cut.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>If I do not, never trust me, take it how you will.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Come, come, I'll go burn some sack; 'tis too late</line>
            <line>to go to bed now: come, knight; come, knight.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-4">
      <title>SCENE IV.  DUKE ORSINO's palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter DUKE ORSINO, VIOLA, CURIO, and others</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE ORSINO</speaker>
            <line>Give me some music. Now, good morrow, friends.</line>
            <line>Now, good Cesario, but that piece of song,</line>
            <line>That old and antique song we heard last night:</line>
            <line>Methought it did relieve my passion much,</line>
            <line>More than light airs and recollected terms</line>
            <line>Of these most brisk and giddy-paced times:</line>
            <line>Come, but one verse.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CURIO</speaker>
            <line>He is not here, so please your lordship that should sing it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE ORSINO</speaker>
            <line>Who was it?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CURIO</speaker>
            <line>Feste, the jester, my lord; a fool that the lady</line>
            <line>Olivia's father took much delight in. He is about the house.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE ORSINO</speaker>
            <line>Seek him out, and play the tune the while.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit CURIO. Music plays</stagedir>
            <line>Come hither, boy: if ever thou shalt love,</line>
            <line>In the sweet pangs of it remember me;</line>
            <line>For such as I am all true lovers are,</line>
            <line>Unstaid and skittish in all motions else,</line>
            <line>Save in the constant image of the creature</line>
            <line>That is beloved. How dost thou like this tune?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>It gives a very echo to the seat</line>
            <line>Where Love is throned.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE ORSINO</speaker>
            <line>Thou dost speak masterly:</line>
            <line>My life upon't, young though thou art, thine eye</line>
            <line>Hath stay'd upon some favour that it loves:</line>
            <line>Hath it not, boy?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>A little, by your favour.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE ORSINO</speaker>
            <line>What kind of woman is't?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>Of your complexion.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE ORSINO</speaker>
            <line>She is not worth thee, then. What years, i' faith?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>About your years, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE ORSINO</speaker>
            <line>Too old by heaven: let still the woman take</line>
            <line>An elder than herself: so wears she to him,</line>
            <line>So sways she level in her husband's heart:</line>
            <line>For, boy, however we do praise ourselves,</line>
            <line>Our fancies are more giddy and unfirm,</line>
            <line>More longing, wavering, sooner lost and worn,</line>
            <line>Than women's are.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>I think it well, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE ORSINO</speaker>
            <line>Then let thy love be younger than thyself,</line>
            <line>Or thy affection cannot hold the bent;</line>
            <line>For women are as roses, whose fair flower</line>
            <line>Being once display'd, doth fall that very hour.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>And so they are: alas, that they are so;</line>
            <line>To die, even when they to perfection grow!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter CURIO and Clown</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE ORSINO</speaker>
            <line>O, fellow, come, the song we had last night.</line>
            <line>Mark it, Cesario, it is old and plain;</line>
            <line>The spinsters and the knitters in the sun</line>
            <line>And the free maids that weave their thread with bones</line>
            <line>Do use to chant it: it is silly sooth,</line>
            <line>And dallies with the innocence of love,</line>
            <line>Like the old age.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Are you ready, sir?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE ORSINO</speaker>
            <line>Ay; prithee, sing.</line>
            <stagedir>Music</stagedir>
         </speech>
         <subhead>SONG.</subhead>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Come away, come away, death,</line>
            <line>And in sad cypress let me be laid;</line>
            <line>Fly away, fly away breath;</line>
            <line>I am slain by a fair cruel maid.</line>
            <line>My shroud of white, stuck all with yew,</line>
            <line>O, prepare it!</line>
            <line>My part of death, no one so true</line>
            <line>Did share it.</line>
            <line>Not a flower, not a flower sweet</line>
            <line>On my black coffin let there be strown;</line>
            <line>Not a friend, not a friend greet</line>
            <line>My poor corpse, where my bones shall be thrown:</line>
            <line>A thousand thousand sighs to save,</line>
            <line>Lay me, O, where</line>
            <line>Sad true lover never find my grave,</line>
            <line>To weep there!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE ORSINO</speaker>
            <line>There's for thy pains.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>No pains, sir: I take pleasure in singing, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE ORSINO</speaker>
            <line>I'll pay thy pleasure then.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Truly, sir, and pleasure will be paid, one time or another.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE ORSINO</speaker>
            <line>Give me now leave to leave thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Now, the melancholy god protect thee; and the</line>
            <line>tailor make thy doublet of changeable taffeta, for</line>
            <line>thy mind is a very opal. I would have men of such</line>
            <line>constancy put to sea, that their business might be</line>
            <line>every thing and their intent every where; for that's</line>
            <line>it that always makes a good voyage of nothing. Farewell.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE ORSINO</speaker>
            <line>Let all the rest give place.</line>
            <stagedir>CURIO and Attendants retire</stagedir>
            <line>Once more, Cesario,</line>
            <line>Get thee to yond same sovereign cruelty:</line>
            <line>Tell her, my love, more noble than the world,</line>
            <line>Prizes not quantity of dirty lands;</line>
            <line>The parts that fortune hath bestow'd upon her,</line>
            <line>Tell her, I hold as giddily as fortune;</line>
            <line>But 'tis that miracle and queen of gems</line>
            <line>That nature pranks her in attracts my soul.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>But if she cannot love you, sir?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE ORSINO</speaker>
            <line>I cannot be so answer'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>Sooth, but you must.</line>
            <line>Say that some lady, as perhaps there is,</line>
            <line>Hath for your love a great a pang of heart</line>
            <line>As you have for Olivia: you cannot love her;</line>
            <line>You tell her so; must she not then be answer'd?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE ORSINO</speaker>
            <line>There is no woman's sides</line>
            <line>Can bide the beating of so strong a passion</line>
            <line>As love doth give my heart; no woman's heart</line>
            <line>So big, to hold so much; they lack retention</line>
            <line>Alas, their love may be call'd appetite,</line>
            <line>No motion of the liver, but the palate,</line>
            <line>That suffer surfeit, cloyment and revolt;</line>
            <line>But mine is all as hungry as the sea,</line>
            <line>And can digest as much: make no compare</line>
            <line>Between that love a woman can bear me</line>
            <line>And that I owe Olivia.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>Ay, but I know--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE ORSINO</speaker>
            <line>What dost thou know?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>Too well what love women to men may owe:</line>
            <line>In faith, they are as true of heart as we.</line>
            <line>My father had a daughter loved a man,</line>
            <line>As it might be, perhaps, were I a woman,</line>
            <line>I should your lordship.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE ORSINO</speaker>
            <line>And what's her history?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>A blank, my lord. She never told her love,</line>
            <line>But let concealment, like a worm i' the bud,</line>
            <line>Feed on her damask cheek: she pined in thought,</line>
            <line>And with a green and yellow melancholy</line>
            <line>She sat like patience on a monument,</line>
            <line>Smiling at grief. Was not this love indeed?</line>
            <line>We men may say more, swear more: but indeed</line>
            <line>Our shows are more than will; for still we prove</line>
            <line>Much in our vows, but little in our love.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE ORSINO</speaker>
            <line>But died thy sister of her love, my boy?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>VIOLA</speaker>
            <line>I am all the daughters of my father's house,</line>
            <line>And all the brothers too: and yet I know not.</line>
            <line>Sir, shall I to this lady?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DUKE ORSINO</speaker>
            <line>Ay, that's the theme.</line>
            <line>To her in haste; give her this jewel; say,</line>
            <line>My love can give no place, bide no denay.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-5">
      <title>SCENE V.  OLIVIA's garden.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter SIR TOBY BELCH, SIR ANDREW, and FABIAN</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Come thy ways, Signior Fabian.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FABIAN</speaker>
            <line>Nay, I'll come: if I lose a scruple of this sport,</line>
            <line>let me be boiled to death with melancholy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Wouldst thou not be glad to have the niggardly</line>
            <line>rascally sheep-biter come by some notable shame?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FABIAN</speaker>
            <line>I would exult, man: you know, he brought me out o'</line>
            <line>favour with my lady about a bear-baiting here.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>To anger him we'll have the bear again; and we will</line>
            <line>fool him black and blue: shall we not, Sir Andrew?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>An we do not, it is pity of our lives.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Here comes the little villain.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter MARIA</stagedir>
            <line>How now, my metal of India!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>Get ye all three into the box-tree: Malvolio's</line>
            <line>coming down this walk: he has been yonder i' the</line>
            <line>sun practising behavior to his own shadow this half</line>
            <line>hour: observe him, for the love of mockery; for I</line>
            <line>know this letter will make a contemplative idiot of</line>
            <line>him. Close, in the name of jesting! Lie thou there,</line>
            <stagedir>Throws down a letter</stagedir>
            <line>for here comes the trout that must be caught with tickling.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Enter MALVOLIO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>'Tis but fortune; all is fortune. Maria once told</line>
            <line>me she did affect me: and I have heard herself come</line>
            <line>thus near, that, should she fancy, it should be one</line>
            <line>of my complexion. Besides, she uses me with a more</line>
            <line>exalted respect than any one else that follows her.</line>
            <line>What should I think on't?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Here's an overweening rogue!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FABIAN</speaker>
            <line>O, peace! Contemplation makes a rare turkey-cock</line>
            <line>of him: how he jets under his advanced plumes!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>'Slight, I could so beat the rogue!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Peace, I say.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>To be Count Malvolio!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Ah, rogue!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>Pistol him, pistol him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Peace, peace!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>There is example for't; the lady of the Strachy</line>
            <line>married the yeoman of the wardrobe.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>Fie on him, Jezebel!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FABIAN</speaker>
            <line>O, peace! now he's deeply in: look how</line>
            <line>imagination blows him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>Having been three months married to her, sitting in</line>
            <line>my state,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>O, for a stone-bow, to hit him in the eye!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>Calling my officers about me, in my branched velvet</line>
            <line>gown; having come from a day-bed, where I have left</line>
            <line>Olivia sleeping,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Fire and brimstone!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FABIAN</speaker>
            <line>O, peace, peace!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>And then to have the humour of state; and after a</line>
            <line>demure travel of regard, telling them I know my</line>
            <line>place as I would they should do theirs, to for my</line>
            <line>kinsman Toby,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Bolts and shackles!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FABIAN</speaker>
            <line>O peace, peace, peace! now, now.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>Seven of my people, with an obedient start, make</line>
            <line>out for him: I frown the while; and perchance wind</line>
            <line>up watch, or play with my--some rich jewel. Toby</line>
            <line>approaches; courtesies there to me,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Shall this fellow live?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FABIAN</speaker>
            <line>Though our silence be drawn from us with cars, yet peace.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>I extend my hand to him thus, quenching my familiar</line>
            <line>smile with an austere regard of control,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>And does not Toby take you a blow o' the lips then?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>Saying, 'Cousin Toby, my fortunes having cast me on</line>
            <line>your niece give me this prerogative of speech,'--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>What, what?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>'You must amend your drunkenness.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Out, scab!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FABIAN</speaker>
            <line>Nay, patience, or we break the sinews of our plot.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>'Besides, you waste the treasure of your time with</line>
            <line>a foolish knight,'--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>That's me, I warrant you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>'One Sir Andrew,'--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>I knew 'twas I; for many do call me fool.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>What employment have we here?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Taking up the letter</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FABIAN</speaker>
            <line>Now is the woodcock near the gin.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>O, peace! and the spirit of humour intimate reading</line>
            <line>aloud to him!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>By my life, this is my lady's hand these be her</line>
            <line>very C's, her U's and her T's and thus makes she her</line>
            <line>great P's. It is, in contempt of question, her hand.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>Her C's, her U's and her T's: why that?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>  'To the unknown beloved, this, and my good</line>
            <line>wishes:'--her very phrases! By your leave, wax.</line>
            <line>Soft! and the impressure her Lucrece, with which she</line>
            <line>uses to seal: 'tis my lady. To whom should this be?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FABIAN</speaker>
            <line>This wins him, liver and all.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>
            </line>
            <line>Jove knows I love: But who?</line>
            <line>Lips, do not move;</line>
            <line>No man must know.</line>
            <line>'No man must know.' What follows? the numbers</line>
            <line>altered! 'No man must know:' if this should be</line>
            <line>thee, Malvolio?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Marry, hang thee, brock!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>
            </line>
            <line>I may command where I adore;</line>
            <line>But silence, like a Lucrece knife,</line>
            <line>With bloodless stroke my heart doth gore:</line>
            <line>M, O, A, I, doth sway my life.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FABIAN</speaker>
            <line>A fustian riddle!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Excellent wench, say I.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>'M, O, A, I, doth sway my life.' Nay, but first, let</line>
            <line>me see, let me see, let me see.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FABIAN</speaker>
            <line>What dish o' poison has she dressed him!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>And with what wing the staniel cheques at it!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>'I may command where I adore.' Why, she may command</line>
            <line>me: I serve her; she is my lady. Why, this is</line>
            <line>evident to any formal capacity; there is no</line>
            <line>obstruction in this: and the end,--what should</line>
            <line>that alphabetical position portend? If I could make</line>
            <line>that resemble something in me,--Softly! M, O, A,</line>
            <line>I,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>O, ay, make up that: he is now at a cold scent.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FABIAN</speaker>
            <line>Sowter will cry upon't for all this, though it be as</line>
            <line>rank as a fox.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>M,--Malvolio; M,--why, that begins my name.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FABIAN</speaker>
            <line>Did not I say he would work it out? the cur is</line>
            <line>excellent at faults.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>M,--but then there is no consonancy in the sequel;</line>
            <line>that suffers under probation A should follow but O does.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FABIAN</speaker>
            <line>And O shall end, I hope.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Ay, or I'll cudgel him, and make him cry O!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>And then I comes behind.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FABIAN</speaker>
            <line>Ay, an you had any eye behind you, you might see</line>
            <line>more detraction at your heels than fortunes before</line>
            <line>you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MALVOLIO</speaker>
            <line>M, O, A, I; this simulation is not as the former: and</line>
            <line>yet, to crush this a little, it would bow to me, for</line>
            <line>every one of these letters are in my name. Soft!</line>
            <line>here follows prose.</line>
            <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>
            <line>'If this fall into thy hand, revolve. In my stars I</line>
            <line>am above thee; but be not afraid of greatness: some</line>
            <line>are born great, some achieve greatness, and some</line>
            <line>have greatness thrust upon 'em. Thy Fates open</line>
            <line>their hands; let thy blood and spirit embrace them;</line>
            <line>and, to inure thyself to what thou art like to be,</line>
            <line>cast thy humble slough and appear fresh. Be</line>
            <line>opposite with a kinsman, surly with servants; let</line>
            <line>thy tongue tang arguments of state; put thyself into</line>
            <line>the trick of singularity: she thus advises thee</line>
            <line>that sighs for thee. Remember who commended thy</line>
            <line>yellow stockings, and wished to see thee ever</line>
            <line>cross-gartered: I say, remember. Go to, thou art</line>
            <line>made, if thou desirest to be so; if not, let me see</line>
            <line>thee a steward still, the fellow of servants, and</line>
            <line>not worthy to touch Fortune's fingers. Farewell.</line>
            <line>She that would alter services with thee,</line>
            <line>THE FORTUNATE-UNHAPPY.'</line>
            <line>Daylight and champaign discovers not more: this is</line>
            <line>open. I will be proud, I will read politic authors,</line>
            <line>I will baffle Sir Toby, I will wash off gross</line>
            <line>acquaintance, I will be point-devise the very man.</line>
            <line>I do not now fool myself, to let imagination jade</line>
            <line>me; for every reason excites to this, that my lady</line>
            <line>loves me. She did commend my yellow stockings of</line>
            <line>late, she did praise my leg being cross-gartered;</line>
            <line>and in this she manifests herself to my love, and</line>
            <line>with a kind of injunction drives me to these habits</line>
            <line>of her liking. I thank my stars I am happy. I will</line>
            <line>be strange, stout, in yellow stockings, and</line>
            <line>cross-gartered, even with the swiftness of putting</line>
            <line>on. Jove and my stars be praised! Here is yet a</line>
            <line>postscript.</line>
            <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>
            <line>'Thou canst not choose but know who I am. If thou</line>
            <line>entertainest my love, let it appear in thy smiling;</line>
            <line>thy smiles become thee well; therefore in my</line>
            <line>presence still smile, dear my sweet, I prithee.'</line>
            <line>Jove, I thank thee: I will smile; I will do</line>
            <line>everything that thou wilt have me.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FABIAN</speaker>
            <line>I will not give my part of this sport for a pension</line>
            <line>of thousands to be paid from the Sophy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>I could marry this wench for this device.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>So could I too.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>And ask no other dowry with her but such another jest.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>Nor I neither.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FABIAN</speaker>
            <line>Here comes my noble gull-catcher.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter MARIA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Wilt thou set thy foot o' my neck?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>Or o' mine either?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Shall I play my freedom at traytrip, and become thy</line>
            <line>bond-slave?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>I' faith, or I either?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Why, thou hast put him in such a dream, that when</line>
            <line>the image of it leaves him he must run mad.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>Nay, but say true; does it work upon him?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>Like aqua-vitae with a midwife.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MARIA</speaker>
            <line>If you will then see the fruits of the sport, mark</line>
            <line>his first approach before my lady: he will come to</line>
            <line>her in yellow stockings, and 'tis a colour she</line>
            <line>abhors, and cross-gartered, a fashion she detests;</line>
            <line>and he will smile upon her, which will now be so</line>
            <line>unsuitable to her disposition, being addicted to a</line>
            <line>melancholy as she is, that it cannot but turn him</line>
            <line>into a notable contempt. If you will see it, follow</line>
            <line>me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR TOBY BELCH</speaker>
            <line>To the gates of Tartar, thou most excellent devil of wit!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIR ANDREW</speaker>
            <line>I'll make one too.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>