<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net/doctypes/dita/shakespear/dtd/act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-1">
   <title>ACT I</title>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  Troy. Before Priam's palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter TROILUS armed, and PANDARUS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TROILUS</speaker>
            <line>Call here my varlet; I'll unarm again:</line>
            <line>Why should I war without the walls of Troy,</line>
            <line>That find such cruel battle here within?</line>
            <line>Each Trojan that is master of his heart,</line>
            <line>Let him to field; Troilus, alas! hath none.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>Will this gear ne'er be mended?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TROILUS</speaker>
            <line>The Greeks are strong and skilful to their strength,</line>
            <line>Fierce to their skill and to their fierceness valiant;</line>
            <line>But I am weaker than a woman's tear,</line>
            <line>Tamer than sleep, fonder than ignorance,</line>
            <line>Less valiant than the virgin in the night</line>
            <line>And skilless as unpractised infancy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>Well, I have told you enough of this: for my part,</line>
            <line>I'll not meddle nor make no further. He that will</line>
            <line>have a cake out of the wheat must needs tarry the grinding.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TROILUS</speaker>
            <line>Have I not tarried?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>Ay, the grinding; but you must tarry</line>
            <line>the bolting.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TROILUS</speaker>
            <line>Have I not tarried?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>Ay, the bolting, but you must tarry the leavening.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TROILUS</speaker>
            <line>Still have I tarried.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>Ay, to the leavening; but here's yet in the word</line>
            <line>'hereafter' the kneading, the making of the cake, the</line>
            <line>heating of the oven and the baking; nay, you must</line>
            <line>stay the cooling too, or you may chance to burn your lips.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TROILUS</speaker>
            <line>Patience herself, what goddess e'er she be,</line>
            <line>Doth lesser blench at sufferance than I do.</line>
            <line>At Priam's royal table do I sit;</line>
            <line>And when fair Cressid comes into my thoughts,--</line>
            <line>So, traitor! 'When she comes!' When is she thence?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>Well, she looked yesternight fairer than ever I saw</line>
            <line>her look, or any woman else.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TROILUS</speaker>
            <line>I was about to tell thee:--when my heart,</line>
            <line>As wedged with a sigh, would rive in twain,</line>
            <line>Lest Hector or my father should perceive me,</line>
            <line>I have, as when the sun doth light a storm,</line>
            <line>Buried this sigh in wrinkle of a smile:</line>
            <line>But sorrow, that is couch'd in seeming gladness,</line>
            <line>Is like that mirth fate turns to sudden sadness.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>An her hair were not somewhat darker than Helen's--</line>
            <line>well, go to--there were no more comparison between</line>
            <line>the women: but, for my part, she is my kinswoman; I</line>
            <line>would not, as they term it, praise her: but I would</line>
            <line>somebody had heard her talk yesterday, as I did. I</line>
            <line>will not dispraise your sister Cassandra's wit, but--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TROILUS</speaker>
            <line>O Pandarus! I tell thee, Pandarus,--</line>
            <line>When I do tell thee, there my hopes lie drown'd,</line>
            <line>Reply not in how many fathoms deep</line>
            <line>They lie indrench'd. I tell thee I am mad</line>
            <line>In Cressid's love: thou answer'st 'she is fair;'</line>
            <line>Pour'st in the open ulcer of my heart</line>
            <line>Her eyes, her hair, her cheek, her gait, her voice,</line>
            <line>Handlest in thy discourse, O, that her hand,</line>
            <line>In whose comparison all whites are ink,</line>
            <line>Writing their own reproach, to whose soft seizure</line>
            <line>The cygnet's down is harsh and spirit of sense</line>
            <line>Hard as the palm of ploughman: this thou tell'st me,</line>
            <line>As true thou tell'st me, when I say I love her;</line>
            <line>But, saying thus, instead of oil and balm,</line>
            <line>Thou lay'st in every gash that love hath given me</line>
            <line>The knife that made it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>I speak no more than truth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TROILUS</speaker>
            <line>Thou dost not speak so much.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>Faith, I'll not meddle in't. Let her be as she is:</line>
            <line>if she be fair, 'tis the better for her; an she be</line>
            <line>not, she has the mends in her own hands.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TROILUS</speaker>
            <line>Good Pandarus, how now, Pandarus!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>I have had my labour for my travail; ill-thought on of</line>
            <line>her and ill-thought on of you; gone between and</line>
            <line>between, but small thanks for my labour.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TROILUS</speaker>
            <line>What, art thou angry, Pandarus? what, with me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>Because she's kin to me, therefore she's not so fair</line>
            <line>as Helen: an she were not kin to me, she would be as</line>
            <line>fair on Friday as Helen is on Sunday. But what care</line>
            <line>I? I care not an she were a black-a-moor; 'tis all one to me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TROILUS</speaker>
            <line>Say I she is not fair?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>I do not care whether you do or no. She's a fool to</line>
            <line>stay behind her father; let her to the Greeks; and so</line>
            <line>I'll tell her the next time I see her: for my part,</line>
            <line>I'll meddle nor make no more i' the matter.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TROILUS</speaker>
            <line>Pandarus,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>Not I.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TROILUS</speaker>
            <line>Sweet Pandarus,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>Pray you, speak no more to me: I will leave all as I</line>
            <line>found it, and there an end.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit PANDARUS. An alarum</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TROILUS</speaker>
            <line>Peace, you ungracious clamours! peace, rude sounds!</line>
            <line>Fools on both sides! Helen must needs be fair,</line>
            <line>When with your blood you daily paint her thus.</line>
            <line>I cannot fight upon this argument;</line>
            <line>It is too starved a subject for my sword.</line>
            <line>But Pandarus,--O gods, how do you plague me!</line>
            <line>I cannot come to Cressid but by Pandar;</line>
            <line>And he's as tetchy to be woo'd to woo.</line>
            <line>As she is stubborn-chaste against all suit.</line>
            <line>Tell me, Apollo, for thy Daphne's love,</line>
            <line>What Cressid is, what Pandar, and what we?</line>
            <line>Her bed is India; there she lies, a pearl:</line>
            <line>Between our Ilium and where she resides,</line>
            <line>Let it be call'd the wild and wandering flood,</line>
            <line>Ourself the merchant, and this sailing Pandar</line>
            <line>Our doubtful hope, our convoy and our bark.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Alarum. Enter AENEAS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AENEAS</speaker>
            <line>How now, Prince Troilus! wherefore not afield?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TROILUS</speaker>
            <line>Because not there: this woman's answer sorts,</line>
            <line>For womanish it is to be from thence.</line>
            <line>What news, AEneas, from the field to-day?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AENEAS</speaker>
            <line>That Paris is returned home and hurt.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TROILUS</speaker>
            <line>By whom, AEneas?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AENEAS</speaker>
            <line>Troilus, by Menelaus.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TROILUS</speaker>
            <line>Let Paris bleed; 'tis but a scar to scorn;</line>
            <line>Paris is gored with Menelaus' horn.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Alarum</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AENEAS</speaker>
            <line>Hark, what good sport is out of town to-day!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TROILUS</speaker>
            <line>Better at home, if 'would I might' were 'may.'</line>
            <line>But to the sport abroad: are you bound thither?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AENEAS</speaker>
            <line>In all swift haste.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TROILUS</speaker>
            <line>Come, go we then together.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  The Same. A street.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter CRESSIDA and ALEXANDER</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>Who were those went by?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALEXANDER</speaker>
            <line>Queen Hecuba and Helen.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>And whither go they?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALEXANDER</speaker>
            <line>Up to the eastern tower,</line>
            <line>Whose height commands as subject all the vale,</line>
            <line>To see the battle. Hector, whose patience</line>
            <line>Is, as a virtue, fix'd, to-day was moved:</line>
            <line>He chid Andromache and struck his armourer,</line>
            <line>And, like as there were husbandry in war,</line>
            <line>Before the sun rose he was harness'd light,</line>
            <line>And to the field goes he; where every flower</line>
            <line>Did, as a prophet, weep what it foresaw</line>
            <line>In Hector's wrath.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>What was his cause of anger?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALEXANDER</speaker>
            <line>The noise goes, this: there is among the Greeks</line>
            <line>A lord of Trojan blood, nephew to Hector;</line>
            <line>They call him Ajax.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>Good; and what of him?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALEXANDER</speaker>
            <line>They say he is a very man per se,</line>
            <line>And stands alone.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>So do all men, unless they are drunk, sick, or have no legs.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALEXANDER</speaker>
            <line>This man, lady, hath robbed many beasts of their</line>
            <line>particular additions; he is as valiant as the lion,</line>
            <line>churlish as the bear, slow as the elephant: a man</line>
            <line>into whom nature hath so crowded humours that his</line>
            <line>valour is crushed into folly, his folly sauced with</line>
            <line>discretion: there is no man hath a virtue that he</line>
            <line>hath not a glimpse of, nor any man an attaint but he</line>
            <line>carries some stain of it: he is melancholy without</line>
            <line>cause, and merry against the hair: he hath the</line>
            <line>joints of every thing, but everything so out of joint</line>
            <line>that he is a gouty Briareus, many hands and no use,</line>
            <line>or purblind Argus, all eyes and no sight.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>But how should this man, that makes</line>
            <line>me smile, make Hector angry?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALEXANDER</speaker>
            <line>They say he yesterday coped Hector in the battle and</line>
            <line>struck him down, the disdain and shame whereof hath</line>
            <line>ever since kept Hector fasting and waking.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>Who comes here?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALEXANDER</speaker>
            <line>Madam, your uncle Pandarus.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter PANDARUS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>Hector's a gallant man.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALEXANDER</speaker>
            <line>As may be in the world, lady.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>What's that? what's that?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>Good morrow, uncle Pandarus.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>Good morrow, cousin Cressid: what do you talk of?</line>
            <line>Good morrow, Alexander. How do you, cousin? When</line>
            <line>were you at Ilium?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>This morning, uncle.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>What were you talking of when I came? Was Hector</line>
            <line>armed and gone ere ye came to Ilium? Helen was not</line>
            <line>up, was she?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>Hector was gone, but Helen was not up.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>Even so: Hector was stirring early.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>That were we talking of, and of his anger.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>Was he angry?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>So he says here.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>True, he was so: I know the cause too: he'll lay</line>
            <line>about him to-day, I can tell them that: and there's</line>
            <line>Troilus will not come far behind him: let them take</line>
            <line>heed of Troilus, I can tell them that too.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>What, is he angry too?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>Who, Troilus? Troilus is the better man of the two.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>O Jupiter! there's no comparison.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>What, not between Troilus and Hector? Do you know a</line>
            <line>man if you see him?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>Ay, if I ever saw him before and knew him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>Well, I say Troilus is Troilus.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>Then you say as I say; for, I am sure, he is not Hector.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>No, nor Hector is not Troilus in some degrees.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>'Tis just to each of them; he is himself.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>Himself! Alas, poor Troilus! I would he were.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>So he is.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>Condition, I had gone barefoot to India.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>He is not Hector.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>Himself! no, he's not himself: would a' were</line>
            <line>himself! Well, the gods are above; time must friend</line>
            <line>or end: well, Troilus, well: I would my heart were</line>
            <line>in her body. No, Hector is not a better man than Troilus.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>Excuse me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>He is elder.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>Pardon me, pardon me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>Th' other's not come to't; you shall tell me another</line>
            <line>tale, when th' other's come to't. Hector shall not</line>
            <line>have his wit this year.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>He shall not need it, if he have his own.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>Nor his qualities.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>No matter.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>Nor his beauty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>'Twould not become him; his own's better.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>You have no judgment, niece: Helen</line>
            <line>herself swore th' other day, that Troilus, for</line>
            <line>a brown favour--for so 'tis, I must confess,--</line>
            <line>not brown neither,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>No, but brown.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>'Faith, to say truth, brown and not brown.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>To say the truth, true and not true.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>She praised his complexion above Paris.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>Why, Paris hath colour enough.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>So he has.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>Then Troilus should have too much: if she praised</line>
            <line>him above, his complexion is higher than his; he</line>
            <line>having colour enough, and the other higher, is too</line>
            <line>flaming a praise for a good complexion. I had as</line>
            <line>lief Helen's golden tongue had commended Troilus for</line>
            <line>a copper nose.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>I swear to you. I think Helen loves him better than Paris.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>Then she's a merry Greek indeed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>Nay, I am sure she does. She came to him th' other</line>
            <line>day into the compassed window,--and, you know, he</line>
            <line>has not past three or four hairs on his chin,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>Indeed, a tapster's arithmetic may soon bring his</line>
            <line>particulars therein to a total.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>Why, he is very young: and yet will he, within</line>
            <line>three pound, lift as much as his brother Hector.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>Is he so young a man and so old a lifter?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>But to prove to you that Helen loves him: she came</line>
            <line>and puts me her white hand to his cloven chin--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>Juno have mercy! how came it cloven?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>Why, you know 'tis dimpled: I think his smiling</line>
            <line>becomes him better than any man in all Phrygia.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>O, he smiles valiantly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>Does he not?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>O yes, an 'twere a cloud in autumn.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>Why, go to, then: but to prove to you that Helen</line>
            <line>loves Troilus,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>Troilus will stand to the proof, if you'll</line>
            <line>prove it so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>Troilus! why, he esteems her no more than I esteem</line>
            <line>an addle egg.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>If you love an addle egg as well as you love an idle</line>
            <line>head, you would eat chickens i' the shell.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>I cannot choose but laugh, to think how she tickled</line>
            <line>his chin: indeed, she has a marvellous white hand, I</line>
            <line>must needs confess,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>Without the rack.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>And she takes upon her to spy a white hair on his chin.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>Alas, poor chin! many a wart is richer.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>But there was such laughing! Queen Hecuba laughed</line>
            <line>that her eyes ran o'er.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>With mill-stones.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>And Cassandra laughed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>But there was more temperate fire under the pot of</line>
            <line>her eyes: did her eyes run o'er too?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>And Hector laughed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>At what was all this laughing?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>Marry, at the white hair that Helen spied on Troilus' chin.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>An't had been a green hair, I should have laughed</line>
            <line>too.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>They laughed not so much at the hair as at his pretty answer.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>What was his answer?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>Quoth she, 'Here's but two and fifty hairs on your</line>
            <line>chin, and one of them is white.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>This is her question.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>That's true; make no question of that. 'Two and</line>
            <line>fifty hairs' quoth he, 'and one white: that white</line>
            <line>hair is my father, and all the rest are his sons.'</line>
            <line>'Jupiter!' quoth she, 'which of these hairs is Paris,</line>
            <line>my husband? 'The forked one,' quoth he, 'pluck't</line>
            <line>out, and give it him.' But there was such laughing!</line>
            <line>and Helen so blushed, an Paris so chafed, and all the</line>
            <line>rest so laughed, that it passed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>So let it now; for it has been while going by.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>Well, cousin. I told you a thing yesterday; think on't.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>So I do.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>I'll be sworn 'tis true; he will weep you, an 'twere</line>
            <line>a man born in April.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>And I'll spring up in his tears, an 'twere a nettle</line>
            <line>against May.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>A retreat sounded</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>Hark! they are coming from the field: shall we</line>
            <line>stand up here, and see them as they pass toward</line>
            <line>Ilium? good niece, do, sweet niece Cressida.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>At your pleasure.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>Here, here, here's an excellent place; here we may</line>
            <line>see most bravely: I'll tell you them all by their</line>
            <line>names as they pass by; but mark Troilus above the rest.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>Speak not so loud.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>AENEAS passes</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>That's AEneas: is not that a brave man? he's one of</line>
            <line>the flowers of Troy, I can tell you: but mark</line>
            <line>Troilus; you shall see anon.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>ANTENOR passes</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>Who's that?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>That's Antenor: he has a shrewd wit, I can tell you;</line>
            <line>and he's a man good enough, he's one o' the soundest</line>
            <line>judgments in whosoever, and a proper man of person.</line>
            <line>When comes Troilus? I'll show you Troilus anon: if</line>
            <line>he see me, you shall see him nod at me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>Will he give you the nod?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>You shall see.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>If he do, the rich shall have more.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>HECTOR passes</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>That's Hector, that, that, look you, that; there's a</line>
            <line>fellow! Go thy way, Hector! There's a brave man,</line>
            <line>niece. O brave Hector! Look how he looks! there's</line>
            <line>a countenance! is't not a brave man?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>O, a brave man!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>Is a' not? it does a man's heart good. Look you</line>
            <line>what hacks are on his helmet! look you yonder, do</line>
            <line>you see? look you there: there's no jesting;</line>
            <line>there's laying on, take't off who will, as they say:</line>
            <line>there be hacks!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>Be those with swords?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>Swords! any thing, he cares not; an the devil come</line>
            <line>to him, it's all one: by God's lid, it does one's</line>
            <line>heart good. Yonder comes Paris, yonder comes Paris.</line>
            <stagedir>PARIS passes</stagedir>
            <line>Look ye yonder, niece; is't not a gallant man too,</line>
            <line>is't not? Why, this is brave now. Who said he came</line>
            <line>hurt home to-day? he's not hurt: why, this will do</line>
            <line>Helen's heart good now, ha! Would I could see</line>
            <line>Troilus now! You shall see Troilus anon.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>HELENUS passes</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>Who's that?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>That's Helenus. I marvel where Troilus is. That's</line>
            <line>Helenus. I think he went not forth to-day. That's Helenus.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>Can Helenus fight, uncle?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>Helenus? no. Yes, he'll fight indifferent well. I</line>
            <line>marvel where Troilus is. Hark! do you not hear the</line>
            <line>people cry 'Troilus'? Helenus is a priest.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>What sneaking fellow comes yonder?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>TROILUS passes</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>Where? yonder? that's Deiphobus. 'Tis Troilus!</line>
            <line>there's a man, niece! Hem! Brave Troilus! the</line>
            <line>prince of chivalry!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>Peace, for shame, peace!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>Mark him; note him. O brave Troilus! Look well upon</line>
            <line>him, niece: look you how his sword is bloodied, and</line>
            <line>his helm more hacked than Hector's, and how he looks,</line>
            <line>and how he goes! O admirable youth! he ne'er saw</line>
            <line>three and twenty. Go thy way, Troilus, go thy way!</line>
            <line>Had I a sister were a grace, or a daughter a goddess,</line>
            <line>he should take his choice. O admirable man! Paris?</line>
            <line>Paris is dirt to him; and, I warrant, Helen, to</line>
            <line>change, would give an eye to boot.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>Here come more.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Forces pass</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>Asses, fools, dolts! chaff and bran, chaff and bran!</line>
            <line>porridge after meat! I could live and die i' the</line>
            <line>eyes of Troilus. Ne'er look, ne'er look: the eagles</line>
            <line>are gone: crows and daws, crows and daws! I had</line>
            <line>rather be such a man as Troilus than Agamemnon and</line>
            <line>all Greece.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>There is among the Greeks Achilles, a better man than Troilus.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>Achilles! a drayman, a porter, a very camel.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>Well, well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>'Well, well!' why, have you any discretion? have</line>
            <line>you any eyes? Do you know what a man is? Is not</line>
            <line>birth, beauty, good shape, discourse, manhood,</line>
            <line>learning, gentleness, virtue, youth, liberality,</line>
            <line>and such like, the spice and salt that season a man?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>Ay, a minced man: and then to be baked with no date</line>
            <line>in the pie, for then the man's date's out.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>You are such a woman! one knows not at what ward you</line>
            <line>lie.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>Upon my back, to defend my belly; upon my wit, to</line>
            <line>defend my wiles; upon my secrecy, to defend mine</line>
            <line>honesty; my mask, to defend my beauty; and you, to</line>
            <line>defend all these: and at all these wards I lie, at a</line>
            <line>thousand watches.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>Say one of your watches.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>Nay, I'll watch you for that; and that's one of the</line>
            <line>chiefest of them too: if I cannot ward what I would</line>
            <line>not have hit, I can watch you for telling how I took</line>
            <line>the blow; unless it swell past hiding, and then it's</line>
            <line>past watching.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>You are such another!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter Troilus's Boy</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Boy</speaker>
            <line>Sir, my lord would instantly speak with you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>Where?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Boy</speaker>
            <line>At your own house; there he unarms him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>Good boy, tell him I come.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit boy</stagedir>
            <line>I doubt he be hurt. Fare ye well, good niece.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>Adieu, uncle.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>I'll be with you, niece, by and by.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>To bring, uncle?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>Ay, a token from Troilus.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>By the same token, you are a bawd.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit PANDARUS</stagedir>
            <line>Words, vows, gifts, tears, and love's full sacrifice,</line>
            <line>He offers in another's enterprise;</line>
            <line>But more in Troilus thousand fold I see</line>
            <line>Than in the glass of Pandar's praise may be;</line>
            <line>Yet hold I off. Women are angels, wooing:</line>
            <line>Things won are done; joy's soul lies in the doing.</line>
            <line>That she beloved knows nought that knows not this:</line>
            <line>Men prize the thing ungain'd more than it is:</line>
            <line>That she was never yet that ever knew</line>
            <line>Love got so sweet as when desire did sue.</line>
            <line>Therefore this maxim out of love I teach:</line>
            <line>Achievement is command; ungain'd, beseech:</line>
            <line>Then though my heart's content firm love doth bear,</line>
            <line>Nothing of that shall from mine eyes appear.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  The Grecian camp. Before Agamemnon's tent.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Sennet. Enter AGAMEMNON, NESTOR, ULYSSES,
MENELAUS, and others</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AGAMEMNON</speaker>
            <line>Princes,</line>
            <line>What grief hath set the jaundice on your cheeks?</line>
            <line>The ample proposition that hope makes</line>
            <line>In all designs begun on earth below</line>
            <line>Fails in the promised largeness: cheques and disasters</line>
            <line>Grow in the veins of actions highest rear'd,</line>
            <line>As knots, by the conflux of meeting sap,</line>
            <line>Infect the sound pine and divert his grain</line>
            <line>Tortive and errant from his course of growth.</line>
            <line>Nor, princes, is it matter new to us</line>
            <line>That we come short of our suppose so far</line>
            <line>That after seven years' siege yet Troy walls stand;</line>
            <line>Sith every action that hath gone before,</line>
            <line>Whereof we have record, trial did draw</line>
            <line>Bias and thwart, not answering the aim,</line>
            <line>And that unbodied figure of the thought</line>
            <line>That gave't surmised shape. Why then, you princes,</line>
            <line>Do you with cheeks abash'd behold our works,</line>
            <line>And call them shames? which are indeed nought else</line>
            <line>But the protractive trials of great Jove</line>
            <line>To find persistive constancy in men:</line>
            <line>The fineness of which metal is not found</line>
            <line>In fortune's love; for then the bold and coward,</line>
            <line>The wise and fool, the artist and unread,</line>
            <line>The hard and soft seem all affined and kin:</line>
            <line>But, in the wind and tempest of her frown,</line>
            <line>Distinction, with a broad and powerful fan,</line>
            <line>Puffing at all, winnows the light away;</line>
            <line>And what hath mass or matter, by itself</line>
            <line>Lies rich in virtue and unmingled.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NESTOR</speaker>
            <line>With due observance of thy godlike seat,</line>
            <line>Great Agamemnon, Nestor shall apply</line>
            <line>Thy latest words. In the reproof of chance</line>
            <line>Lies the true proof of men: the sea being smooth,</line>
            <line>How many shallow bauble boats dare sail</line>
            <line>Upon her patient breast, making their way</line>
            <line>With those of nobler bulk!</line>
            <line>But let the ruffian Boreas once enrage</line>
            <line>The gentle Thetis, and anon behold</line>
            <line>The strong-ribb'd bark through liquid mountains cut,</line>
            <line>Bounding between the two moist elements,</line>
            <line>Like Perseus' horse: where's then the saucy boat</line>
            <line>Whose weak untimber'd sides but even now</line>
            <line>Co-rivall'd greatness? Either to harbour fled,</line>
            <line>Or made a toast for Neptune. Even so</line>
            <line>Doth valour's show and valour's worth divide</line>
            <line>In storms of fortune; for in her ray and brightness</line>
            <line>The herd hath more annoyance by the breeze</line>
            <line>Than by the tiger; but when the splitting wind</line>
            <line>Makes flexible the knees of knotted oaks,</line>
            <line>And flies fled under shade, why, then the thing of courage</line>
            <line>As roused with rage with rage doth sympathize,</line>
            <line>And with an accent tuned in selfsame key</line>
            <line>Retorts to chiding fortune.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ULYSSES</speaker>
            <line>Agamemnon,</line>
            <line>Thou great commander, nerve and bone of Greece,</line>
            <line>Heart of our numbers, soul and only spirit.</line>
            <line>In whom the tempers and the minds of all</line>
            <line>Should be shut up, hear what Ulysses speaks.</line>
            <line>Besides the applause and approbation To which,</line>
            <stagedir>To AGAMEMNON</stagedir>
            <line>most mighty for thy place and sway,</line>
            <stagedir>To NESTOR</stagedir>
            <line>And thou most reverend for thy stretch'd-out life</line>
            <line>I give to both your speeches, which were such</line>
            <line>As Agamemnon and the hand of Greece</line>
            <line>Should hold up high in brass, and such again</line>
            <line>As venerable Nestor, hatch'd in silver,</line>
            <line>Should with a bond of air, strong as the axle-tree</line>
            <line>On which heaven rides, knit all the Greekish ears</line>
            <line>To his experienced tongue, yet let it please both,</line>
            <line>Thou great, and wise, to hear Ulysses speak.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AGAMEMNON</speaker>
            <line>Speak, prince of Ithaca; and be't of less expect</line>
            <line>That matter needless, of importless burden,</line>
            <line>Divide thy lips, than we are confident,</line>
            <line>When rank Thersites opes his mastic jaws,</line>
            <line>We shall hear music, wit and oracle.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ULYSSES</speaker>
            <line>Troy, yet upon his basis, had been down,</line>
            <line>And the great Hector's sword had lack'd a master,</line>
            <line>But for these instances.</line>
            <line>The specialty of rule hath been neglected:</line>
            <line>And, look, how many Grecian tents do stand</line>
            <line>Hollow upon this plain, so many hollow factions.</line>
            <line>When that the general is not like the hive</line>
            <line>To whom the foragers shall all repair,</line>
            <line>What honey is expected? Degree being vizarded,</line>
            <line>The unworthiest shows as fairly in the mask.</line>
            <line>The heavens themselves, the planets and this centre</line>
            <line>Observe degree, priority and place,</line>
            <line>Insisture, course, proportion, season, form,</line>
            <line>Office and custom, in all line of order;</line>
            <line>And therefore is the glorious planet Sol</line>
            <line>In noble eminence enthroned and sphered</line>
            <line>Amidst the other; whose medicinable eye</line>
            <line>Corrects the ill aspects of planets evil,</line>
            <line>And posts, like the commandment of a king,</line>
            <line>Sans cheque to good and bad: but when the planets</line>
            <line>In evil mixture to disorder wander,</line>
            <line>What plagues and what portents! what mutiny!</line>
            <line>What raging of the sea! shaking of earth!</line>
            <line>Commotion in the winds! frights, changes, horrors,</line>
            <line>Divert and crack, rend and deracinate</line>
            <line>The unity and married calm of states</line>
            <line>Quite from their fixure! O, when degree is shaked,</line>
            <line>Which is the ladder to all high designs,</line>
            <line>Then enterprise is sick! How could communities,</line>
            <line>Degrees in schools and brotherhoods in cities,</line>
            <line>Peaceful commerce from dividable shores,</line>
            <line>The primogenitive and due of birth,</line>
            <line>Prerogative of age, crowns, sceptres, laurels,</line>
            <line>But by degree, stand in authentic place?</line>
            <line>Take but degree away, untune that string,</line>
            <line>And, hark, what discord follows! each thing meets</line>
            <line>In mere oppugnancy: the bounded waters</line>
            <line>Should lift their bosoms higher than the shores</line>
            <line>And make a sop of all this solid globe:</line>
            <line>Strength should be lord of imbecility,</line>
            <line>And the rude son should strike his father dead:</line>
            <line>Force should be right; or rather, right and wrong,</line>
            <line>Between whose endless jar justice resides,</line>
            <line>Should lose their names, and so should justice too.</line>
            <line>Then every thing includes itself in power,</line>
            <line>Power into will, will into appetite;</line>
            <line>And appetite, an universal wolf,</line>
            <line>So doubly seconded with will and power,</line>
            <line>Must make perforce an universal prey,</line>
            <line>And last eat up himself. Great Agamemnon,</line>
            <line>This chaos, when degree is suffocate,</line>
            <line>Follows the choking.</line>
            <line>And this neglection of degree it is</line>
            <line>That by a pace goes backward, with a purpose</line>
            <line>It hath to climb. The general's disdain'd</line>
            <line>By him one step below, he by the next,</line>
            <line>That next by him beneath; so every step,</line>
            <line>Exampled by the first pace that is sick</line>
            <line>Of his superior, grows to an envious fever</line>
            <line>Of pale and bloodless emulation:</line>
            <line>And 'tis this fever that keeps Troy on foot,</line>
            <line>Not her own sinews. To end a tale of length,</line>
            <line>Troy in our weakness stands, not in her strength.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NESTOR</speaker>
            <line>Most wisely hath Ulysses here discover'd</line>
            <line>The fever whereof all our power is sick.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AGAMEMNON</speaker>
            <line>The nature of the sickness found, Ulysses,</line>
            <line>What is the remedy?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ULYSSES</speaker>
            <line>The great Achilles, whom opinion crowns</line>
            <line>The sinew and the forehand of our host,</line>
            <line>Having his ear full of his airy fame,</line>
            <line>Grows dainty of his worth, and in his tent</line>
            <line>Lies mocking our designs: with him Patroclus</line>
            <line>Upon a lazy bed the livelong day</line>
            <line>Breaks scurril jests;</line>
            <line>And with ridiculous and awkward action,</line>
            <line>Which, slanderer, he imitation calls,</line>
            <line>He pageants us. Sometime, great Agamemnon,</line>
            <line>Thy topless deputation he puts on,</line>
            <line>And, like a strutting player, whose conceit</line>
            <line>Lies in his hamstring, and doth think it rich</line>
            <line>To hear the wooden dialogue and sound</line>
            <line>'Twixt his stretch'd footing and the scaffoldage,--</line>
            <line>Such to-be-pitied and o'er-wrested seeming</line>
            <line>He acts thy greatness in: and when he speaks,</line>
            <line>'Tis like a chime a-mending; with terms unsquared,</line>
            <line>Which, from the tongue of roaring Typhon dropp'd</line>
            <line>Would seem hyperboles. At this fusty stuff</line>
            <line>The large Achilles, on his press'd bed lolling,</line>
            <line>From his deep chest laughs out a loud applause;</line>
            <line>Cries 'Excellent! 'tis Agamemnon just.</line>
            <line>Now play me Nestor; hem, and stroke thy beard,</line>
            <line>As he being drest to some oration.'</line>
            <line>That's done, as near as the extremest ends</line>
            <line>Of parallels, as like as Vulcan and his wife:</line>
            <line>Yet god Achilles still cries 'Excellent!</line>
            <line>'Tis Nestor right. Now play him me, Patroclus,</line>
            <line>Arming to answer in a night alarm.'</line>
            <line>And then, forsooth, the faint defects of age</line>
            <line>Must be the scene of mirth; to cough and spit,</line>
            <line>And, with a palsy-fumbling on his gorget,</line>
            <line>Shake in and out the rivet: and at this sport</line>
            <line>Sir Valour dies; cries 'O, enough, Patroclus;</line>
            <line>Or give me ribs of steel! I shall split all</line>
            <line>In pleasure of my spleen.' And in this fashion,</line>
            <line>All our abilities, gifts, natures, shapes,</line>
            <line>Severals and generals of grace exact,</line>
            <line>Achievements, plots, orders, preventions,</line>
            <line>Excitements to the field, or speech for truce,</line>
            <line>Success or loss, what is or is not, serves</line>
            <line>As stuff for these two to make paradoxes.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NESTOR</speaker>
            <line>And in the imitation of these twain--</line>
            <line>Who, as Ulysses says, opinion crowns</line>
            <line>With an imperial voice--many are infect.</line>
            <line>Ajax is grown self-will'd, and bears his head</line>
            <line>In such a rein, in full as proud a place</line>
            <line>As broad Achilles; keeps his tent like him;</line>
            <line>Makes factious feasts; rails on our state of war,</line>
            <line>Bold as an oracle, and sets Thersites,</line>
            <line>A slave whose gall coins slanders like a mint,</line>
            <line>To match us in comparisons with dirt,</line>
            <line>To weaken and discredit our exposure,</line>
            <line>How rank soever rounded in with danger.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ULYSSES</speaker>
            <line>They tax our policy, and call it cowardice,</line>
            <line>Count wisdom as no member of the war,</line>
            <line>Forestall prescience, and esteem no act</line>
            <line>But that of hand: the still and mental parts,</line>
            <line>That do contrive how many hands shall strike,</line>
            <line>When fitness calls them on, and know by measure</line>
            <line>Of their observant toil the enemies' weight,--</line>
            <line>Why, this hath not a finger's dignity:</line>
            <line>They call this bed-work, mappery, closet-war;</line>
            <line>So that the ram that batters down the wall,</line>
            <line>For the great swing and rudeness of his poise,</line>
            <line>They place before his hand that made the engine,</line>
            <line>Or those that with the fineness of their souls</line>
            <line>By reason guide his execution.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NESTOR</speaker>
            <line>Let this be granted, and Achilles' horse</line>
            <line>Makes many Thetis' sons.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>A tucket</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AGAMEMNON</speaker>
            <line>What trumpet? look, Menelaus.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENELAUS</speaker>
            <line>From Troy.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter AENEAS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AGAMEMNON</speaker>
            <line>What would you 'fore our tent?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AENEAS</speaker>
            <line>Is this great Agamemnon's tent, I pray you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AGAMEMNON</speaker>
            <line>Even this.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AENEAS</speaker>
            <line>May one, that is a herald and a prince,</line>
            <line>Do a fair message to his kingly ears?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AGAMEMNON</speaker>
            <line>With surety stronger than Achilles' arm</line>
            <line>'Fore all the Greekish heads, which with one voice</line>
            <line>Call Agamemnon head and general.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AENEAS</speaker>
            <line>Fair leave and large security. How may</line>
            <line>A stranger to those most imperial looks</line>
            <line>Know them from eyes of other mortals?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AGAMEMNON</speaker>
            <line>How!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AENEAS</speaker>
            <line>Ay;</line>
            <line>I ask, that I might waken reverence,</line>
            <line>And bid the cheek be ready with a blush</line>
            <line>Modest as morning when she coldly eyes</line>
            <line>The youthful Phoebus:</line>
            <line>Which is that god in office, guiding men?</line>
            <line>Which is the high and mighty Agamemnon?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AGAMEMNON</speaker>
            <line>This Trojan scorns us; or the men of Troy</line>
            <line>Are ceremonious courtiers.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AENEAS</speaker>
            <line>Courtiers as free, as debonair, unarm'd,</line>
            <line>As bending angels; that's their fame in peace:</line>
            <line>But when they would seem soldiers, they have galls,</line>
            <line>Good arms, strong joints, true swords; and,</line>
            <line>Jove's accord,</line>
            <line>Nothing so full of heart. But peace, AEneas,</line>
            <line>Peace, Trojan; lay thy finger on thy lips!</line>
            <line>The worthiness of praise distains his worth,</line>
            <line>If that the praised himself bring the praise forth:</line>
            <line>But what the repining enemy commends,</line>
            <line>That breath fame blows; that praise, sole sure,</line>
            <line>transcends.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AGAMEMNON</speaker>
            <line>Sir, you of Troy, call you yourself AEneas?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AENEAS</speaker>
            <line>Ay, Greek, that is my name.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AGAMEMNON</speaker>
            <line>What's your affair I pray you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AENEAS</speaker>
            <line>Sir, pardon; 'tis for Agamemnon's ears.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AGAMEMNON</speaker>
            <line>He hears naught privately that comes from Troy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AENEAS</speaker>
            <line>Nor I from Troy come not to whisper him:</line>
            <line>I bring a trumpet to awake his ear,</line>
            <line>To set his sense on the attentive bent,</line>
            <line>And then to speak.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AGAMEMNON</speaker>
            <line>Speak frankly as the wind;</line>
            <line>It is not Agamemnon's sleeping hour:</line>
            <line>That thou shalt know. Trojan, he is awake,</line>
            <line>He tells thee so himself.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AENEAS</speaker>
            <line>Trumpet, blow loud,</line>
            <line>Send thy brass voice through all these lazy tents;</line>
            <line>And every Greek of mettle, let him know,</line>
            <line>What Troy means fairly shall be spoke aloud.</line>
            <stagedir>Trumpet sounds</stagedir>
            <line>We have, great Agamemnon, here in Troy</line>
            <line>A prince call'd Hector,--Priam is his father,--</line>
            <line>Who in this dull and long-continued truce</line>
            <line>Is rusty grown: he bade me take a trumpet,</line>
            <line>And to this purpose speak. Kings, princes, lords!</line>
            <line>If there be one among the fair'st of Greece</line>
            <line>That holds his honour higher than his ease,</line>
            <line>That seeks his praise more than he fears his peril,</line>
            <line>That knows his valour, and knows not his fear,</line>
            <line>That loves his mistress more than in confession,</line>
            <line>With truant vows to her own lips he loves,</line>
            <line>And dare avow her beauty and her worth</line>
            <line>In other arms than hers,--to him this challenge.</line>
            <line>Hector, in view of Trojans and of Greeks,</line>
            <line>Shall make it good, or do his best to do it,</line>
            <line>He hath a lady, wiser, fairer, truer,</line>
            <line>Than ever Greek did compass in his arms,</line>
            <line>And will to-morrow with his trumpet call</line>
            <line>Midway between your tents and walls of Troy,</line>
            <line>To rouse a Grecian that is true in love:</line>
            <line>If any come, Hector shall honour him;</line>
            <line>If none, he'll say in Troy when he retires,</line>
            <line>The Grecian dames are sunburnt and not worth</line>
            <line>The splinter of a lance. Even so much.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AGAMEMNON</speaker>
            <line>This shall be told our lovers, Lord AEneas;</line>
            <line>If none of them have soul in such a kind,</line>
            <line>We left them all at home: but we are soldiers;</line>
            <line>And may that soldier a mere recreant prove,</line>
            <line>That means not, hath not, or is not in love!</line>
            <line>If then one is, or hath, or means to be,</line>
            <line>That one meets Hector; if none else, I am he.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NESTOR</speaker>
            <line>Tell him of Nestor, one that was a man</line>
            <line>When Hector's grandsire suck'd: he is old now;</line>
            <line>But if there be not in our Grecian host</line>
            <line>One noble man that hath one spark of fire,</line>
            <line>To answer for his love, tell him from me</line>
            <line>I'll hide my silver beard in a gold beaver</line>
            <line>And in my vantbrace put this wither'd brawn,</line>
            <line>And meeting him will tell him that my lady</line>
            <line>Was fairer than his grandam and as chaste</line>
            <line>As may be in the world: his youth in flood,</line>
            <line>I'll prove this truth with my three drops of blood.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AENEAS</speaker>
            <line>Now heavens forbid such scarcity of youth!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ULYSSES</speaker>
            <line>Amen.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AGAMEMNON</speaker>
            <line>Fair Lord AEneas, let me touch your hand;</line>
            <line>To our pavilion shall I lead you, sir.</line>
            <line>Achilles shall have word of this intent;</line>
            <line>So shall each lord of Greece, from tent to tent:</line>
            <line>Yourself shall feast with us before you go</line>
            <line>And find the welcome of a noble foe.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt all but ULYSSES and NESTOR</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ULYSSES</speaker>
            <line>Nestor!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NESTOR</speaker>
            <line>What says Ulysses?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ULYSSES</speaker>
            <line>I have a young conception in my brain;</line>
            <line>Be you my time to bring it to some shape.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NESTOR</speaker>
            <line>What is't?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ULYSSES</speaker>
            <line>This 'tis:</line>
            <line>Blunt wedges rive hard knots: the seeded pride</line>
            <line>That hath to this maturity blown up</line>
            <line>In rank Achilles must or now be cropp'd,</line>
            <line>Or, shedding, breed a nursery of like evil,</line>
            <line>To overbulk us all.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NESTOR</speaker>
            <line>Well, and how?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ULYSSES</speaker>
            <line>This challenge that the gallant Hector sends,</line>
            <line>However it is spread in general name,</line>
            <line>Relates in purpose only to Achilles.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NESTOR</speaker>
            <line>The purpose is perspicuous even as substance,</line>
            <line>Whose grossness little characters sum up:</line>
            <line>And, in the publication, make no strain,</line>
            <line>But that Achilles, were his brain as barren</line>
            <line>As banks of Libya,--though, Apollo knows,</line>
            <line>'Tis dry enough,--will, with great speed of judgment,</line>
            <line>Ay, with celerity, find Hector's purpose</line>
            <line>Pointing on him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ULYSSES</speaker>
            <line>And wake him to the answer, think you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NESTOR</speaker>
            <line>Yes, 'tis most meet: whom may you else oppose,</line>
            <line>That can from Hector bring his honour off,</line>
            <line>If not Achilles? Though't be a sportful combat,</line>
            <line>Yet in the trial much opinion dwells;</line>
            <line>For here the Trojans taste our dear'st repute</line>
            <line>With their finest palate: and trust to me, Ulysses,</line>
            <line>Our imputation shall be oddly poised</line>
            <line>In this wild action; for the success,</line>
            <line>Although particular, shall give a scantling</line>
            <line>Of good or bad unto the general;</line>
            <line>And in such indexes, although small pricks</line>
            <line>To their subsequent volumes, there is seen</line>
            <line>The baby figure of the giant mass</line>
            <line>Of things to come at large. It is supposed</line>
            <line>He that meets Hector issues from our choice</line>
            <line>And choice, being mutual act of all our souls,</line>
            <line>Makes merit her election, and doth boil,</line>
            <line>As 'twere from us all, a man distill'd</line>
            <line>Out of our virtues; who miscarrying,</line>
            <line>What heart receives from hence the conquering part,</line>
            <line>To steel a strong opinion to themselves?</line>
            <line>Which entertain'd, limbs are his instruments,</line>
            <line>In no less working than are swords and bows</line>
            <line>Directive by the limbs.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ULYSSES</speaker>
            <line>Give pardon to my speech:</line>
            <line>Therefore 'tis meet Achilles meet not Hector.</line>
            <line>Let us, like merchants, show our foulest wares,</line>
            <line>And think, perchance, they'll sell; if not,</line>
            <line>The lustre of the better yet to show,</line>
            <line>Shall show the better. Do not consent</line>
            <line>That ever Hector and Achilles meet;</line>
            <line>For both our honour and our shame in this</line>
            <line>Are dogg'd with two strange followers.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NESTOR</speaker>
            <line>I see them not with my old eyes: what are they?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ULYSSES</speaker>
            <line>What glory our Achilles shares from Hector,</line>
            <line>Were he not proud, we all should share with him:</line>
            <line>But he already is too insolent;</line>
            <line>And we were better parch in Afric sun</line>
            <line>Than in the pride and salt scorn of his eyes,</line>
            <line>Should he 'scape Hector fair: if he were foil'd,</line>
            <line>Why then, we did our main opinion crush</line>
            <line>In taint of our best man. No, make a lottery;</line>
            <line>And, by device, let blockish Ajax draw</line>
            <line>The sort to fight with Hector: among ourselves</line>
            <line>Give him allowance for the better man;</line>
            <line>For that will physic the great Myrmidon</line>
            <line>Who broils in loud applause, and make him fall</line>
            <line>His crest that prouder than blue Iris bends.</line>
            <line>If the dull brainless Ajax come safe off,</line>
            <line>We'll dress him up in voices: if he fail,</line>
            <line>Yet go we under our opinion still</line>
            <line>That we have better men. But, hit or miss,</line>
            <line>Our project's life this shape of sense assumes:</line>
            <line>Ajax employ'd plucks down Achilles' plumes.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NESTOR</speaker>
            <line>Ulysses,</line>
            <line>Now I begin to relish thy advice;</line>
            <line>And I will give a taste of it forthwith</line>
            <line>To Agamemnon: go we to him straight.</line>
            <line>Two curs shall tame each other: pride alone</line>
            <line>Must tarre the mastiffs on, as 'twere their bone.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>