<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net/doctypes/dita/shakespear/dtd/act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-4">
   <title>ACT IV</title>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  Troy. A street.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter, from one side, AENEAS, and Servant with a
torch; from the other, PARIS, DEIPHOBUS, ANTENOR,
DIOMEDES, and others, with torches</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PARIS</speaker>
            <line>See, ho! who is that there?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEIPHOBUS</speaker>
            <line>It is the Lord AEneas.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AENEAS</speaker>
            <line>Is the prince there in person?</line>
            <line>Had I so good occasion to lie long</line>
            <line>As you, prince Paris, nothing but heavenly business</line>
            <line>Should rob my bed-mate of my company.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DIOMEDES</speaker>
            <line>That's my mind too. Good morrow, Lord AEneas.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PARIS</speaker>
            <line>A valiant Greek, AEneas,--take his hand,--</line>
            <line>Witness the process of your speech, wherein</line>
            <line>You told how Diomed, a whole week by days,</line>
            <line>Did haunt you in the field.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AENEAS</speaker>
            <line>Health to you, valiant sir,</line>
            <line>During all question of the gentle truce;</line>
            <line>But when I meet you arm'd, as black defiance</line>
            <line>As heart can think or courage execute.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DIOMEDES</speaker>
            <line>The one and other Diomed embraces.</line>
            <line>Our bloods are now in calm; and, so long, health!</line>
            <line>But when contention and occasion meet,</line>
            <line>By Jove, I'll play the hunter for thy life</line>
            <line>With all my force, pursuit and policy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AENEAS</speaker>
            <line>And thou shalt hunt a lion, that will fly</line>
            <line>With his face backward. In humane gentleness,</line>
            <line>Welcome to Troy! now, by Anchises' life,</line>
            <line>Welcome, indeed! By Venus' hand I swear,</line>
            <line>No man alive can love in such a sort</line>
            <line>The thing he means to kill more excellently.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DIOMEDES</speaker>
            <line>We sympathize: Jove, let AEneas live,</line>
            <line>If to my sword his fate be not the glory,</line>
            <line>A thousand complete courses of the sun!</line>
            <line>But, in mine emulous honour, let him die,</line>
            <line>With every joint a wound, and that to-morrow!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AENEAS</speaker>
            <line>We know each other well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DIOMEDES</speaker>
            <line>We do; and long to know each other worse.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PARIS</speaker>
            <line>This is the most despiteful gentle greeting,</line>
            <line>The noblest hateful love, that e'er I heard of.</line>
            <line>What business, lord, so early?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AENEAS</speaker>
            <line>I was sent for to the king; but why, I know not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PARIS</speaker>
            <line>His purpose meets you: 'twas to bring this Greek</line>
            <line>To Calchas' house, and there to render him,</line>
            <line>For the enfreed Antenor, the fair Cressid:</line>
            <line>Let's have your company, or, if you please,</line>
            <line>Haste there before us: I constantly do think--</line>
            <line>Or rather, call my thought a certain knowledge--</line>
            <line>My brother Troilus lodges there to-night:</line>
            <line>Rouse him and give him note of our approach.</line>
            <line>With the whole quality wherefore: I fear</line>
            <line>We shall be much unwelcome.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AENEAS</speaker>
            <line>That I assure you:</line>
            <line>Troilus had rather Troy were borne to Greece</line>
            <line>Than Cressid borne from Troy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PARIS</speaker>
            <line>There is no help;</line>
            <line>The bitter disposition of the time</line>
            <line>Will have it so. On, lord; we'll follow you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AENEAS</speaker>
            <line>Good morrow, all.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit with Servant</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PARIS</speaker>
            <line>And tell me, noble Diomed, faith, tell me true,</line>
            <line>Even in the soul of sound good-fellowship,</line>
            <line>Who, in your thoughts, merits fair Helen best,</line>
            <line>Myself or Menelaus?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DIOMEDES</speaker>
            <line>Both alike:</line>
            <line>He merits well to have her, that doth seek her,</line>
            <line>Not making any scruple of her soilure,</line>
            <line>With such a hell of pain and world of charge,</line>
            <line>And you as well to keep her, that defend her,</line>
            <line>Not palating the taste of her dishonour,</line>
            <line>With such a costly loss of wealth and friends:</line>
            <line>He, like a puling cuckold, would drink up</line>
            <line>The lees and dregs of a flat tamed piece;</line>
            <line>You, like a lecher, out of whorish loins</line>
            <line>Are pleased to breed out your inheritors:</line>
            <line>Both merits poised, each weighs nor less nor more;</line>
            <line>But he as he, the heavier for a whore.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PARIS</speaker>
            <line>You are too bitter to your countrywoman.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DIOMEDES</speaker>
            <line>She's bitter to her country: hear me, Paris:</line>
            <line>For every false drop in her bawdy veins</line>
            <line>A Grecian's life hath sunk; for every scruple</line>
            <line>Of her contaminated carrion weight,</line>
            <line>A Trojan hath been slain: since she could speak,</line>
            <line>She hath not given so many good words breath</line>
            <line>As for her Greeks and Trojans suffer'd death.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PARIS</speaker>
            <line>Fair Diomed, you do as chapmen do,</line>
            <line>Dispraise the thing that you desire to buy:</line>
            <line>But we in silence hold this virtue well,</line>
            <line>We'll but commend what we intend to sell.</line>
            <line>Here lies our way.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  The same. Court of Pandarus' house.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter TROILUS and CRESSIDA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TROILUS</speaker>
            <line>Dear, trouble not yourself: the morn is cold.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>Then, sweet my lord, I'll call mine uncle down;</line>
            <line>He shall unbolt the gates.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TROILUS</speaker>
            <line>Trouble him not;</line>
            <line>To bed, to bed: sleep kill those pretty eyes,</line>
            <line>And give as soft attachment to thy senses</line>
            <line>As infants' empty of all thought!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>Good morrow, then.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TROILUS</speaker>
            <line>I prithee now, to bed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>Are you a-weary of me?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TROILUS</speaker>
            <line>O Cressida! but that the busy day,</line>
            <line>Waked by the lark, hath roused the ribald crows,</line>
            <line>And dreaming night will hide our joys no longer,</line>
            <line>I would not from thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>Night hath been too brief.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TROILUS</speaker>
            <line>Beshrew the witch! with venomous wights she stays</line>
            <line>As tediously as hell, but flies the grasps of love</line>
            <line>With wings more momentary-swift than thought.</line>
            <line>You will catch cold, and curse me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>Prithee, tarry:</line>
            <line>You men will never tarry.</line>
            <line>O foolish Cressid! I might have still held off,</line>
            <line>And then you would have tarried. Hark!</line>
            <line>there's one up.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Within</stagedir>  What, 's all the doors open here?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TROILUS</speaker>
            <line>It is your uncle.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>A pestilence on him! now will he be mocking:</line>
            <line>I shall have such a life!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter PANDARUS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>How now, how now! how go maidenheads? Here, you</line>
            <line>maid! where's my cousin Cressid?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>Go hang yourself, you naughty mocking uncle!</line>
            <line>You bring me to do, and then you flout me too.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>To do what? to do what? let her say</line>
            <line>what: what have I brought you to do?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>Come, come, beshrew your heart! you'll ne'er be good,</line>
            <line>Nor suffer others.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>Ha! ha! Alas, poor wretch! ah, poor capocchia!</line>
            <line>hast not slept to-night? would he not, a naughty</line>
            <line>man, let it sleep? a bugbear take him!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>Did not I tell you? Would he were knock'd i' the head!</line>
            <stagedir>Knocking within</stagedir>
            <line>Who's that at door? good uncle, go and see.</line>
            <line>My lord, come you again into my chamber:</line>
            <line>You smile and mock me, as if I meant naughtily.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TROILUS</speaker>
            <line>Ha, ha!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>Come, you are deceived, I think of no such thing.</line>
            <stagedir>Knocking within</stagedir>
            <line>How earnestly they knock! Pray you, come in:</line>
            <line>I would not for half Troy have you seen here.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt TROILUS and CRESSIDA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>Who's there? what's the matter? will you beat</line>
            <line>down the door? How now! what's the matter?</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter AENEAS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AENEAS</speaker>
            <line>Good morrow, lord, good morrow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>Who's there? my Lord AEneas! By my troth,</line>
            <line>I knew you not: what news with you so early?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AENEAS</speaker>
            <line>Is not Prince Troilus here?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>Here! what should he do here?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AENEAS</speaker>
            <line>Come, he is here, my lord; do not deny him:</line>
            <line>It doth import him much to speak with me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>Is he here, say you? 'tis more than I know, I'll</line>
            <line>be sworn: for my own part, I came in late. What</line>
            <line>should he do here?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AENEAS</speaker>
            <line>Who!--nay, then: come, come, you'll do him wrong</line>
            <line>ere you're ware: you'll be so true to him, to be</line>
            <line>false to him: do not you know of him, but yet go</line>
            <line>fetch him hither; go.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter TROILUS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TROILUS</speaker>
            <line>How now! what's the matter?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AENEAS</speaker>
            <line>My lord, I scarce have leisure to salute you,</line>
            <line>My matter is so rash: there is at hand</line>
            <line>Paris your brother, and Deiphobus,</line>
            <line>The Grecian Diomed, and our Antenor</line>
            <line>Deliver'd to us; and for him forthwith,</line>
            <line>Ere the first sacrifice, within this hour,</line>
            <line>We must give up to Diomedes' hand</line>
            <line>The Lady Cressida.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TROILUS</speaker>
            <line>Is it so concluded?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AENEAS</speaker>
            <line>By Priam and the general state of Troy:</line>
            <line>They are at hand and ready to effect it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TROILUS</speaker>
            <line>How my achievements mock me!</line>
            <line>I will go meet them: and, my Lord AEneas,</line>
            <line>We met by chance; you did not find me here.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AENEAS</speaker>
            <line>Good, good, my lord; the secrets of nature</line>
            <line>Have not more gift in taciturnity.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt TROILUS and AENEAS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>Is't possible? no sooner got but lost? The devil</line>
            <line>take Antenor! the young prince will go mad: a</line>
            <line>plague upon Antenor! I would they had broke 's neck!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter CRESSIDA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>How now! what's the matter? who was here?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>Ah, ah!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>Why sigh you so profoundly? where's my lord? gone!</line>
            <line>Tell me, sweet uncle, what's the matter?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>Would I were as deep under the earth as I am above!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>O the gods! what's the matter?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>Prithee, get thee in: would thou hadst ne'er been</line>
            <line>born! I knew thou wouldst be his death. O, poor</line>
            <line>gentleman! A plague upon Antenor!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>Good uncle, I beseech you, on my knees! beseech you,</line>
            <line>what's the matter?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>Thou must be gone, wench, thou must be gone; thou</line>
            <line>art changed for Antenor: thou must to thy father,</line>
            <line>and be gone from Troilus: 'twill be his death;</line>
            <line>'twill be his bane; he cannot bear it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>O you immortal gods! I will not go.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>Thou must.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>I will not, uncle: I have forgot my father;</line>
            <line>I know no touch of consanguinity;</line>
            <line>No kin no love, no blood, no soul so near me</line>
            <line>As the sweet Troilus. O you gods divine!</line>
            <line>Make Cressid's name the very crown of falsehood,</line>
            <line>If ever she leave Troilus! Time, force, and death,</line>
            <line>Do to this body what extremes you can;</line>
            <line>But the strong base and building of my love</line>
            <line>Is as the very centre of the earth,</line>
            <line>Drawing all things to it. I'll go in and weep,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>Do, do.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>Tear my bright hair and scratch my praised cheeks,</line>
            <line>Crack my clear voice with sobs and break my heart</line>
            <line>With sounding Troilus. I will not go from Troy.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  The same. Street before Pandarus' house.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter PARIS, TROILUS, AENEAS, DEIPHOBUS, ANTENOR,
and DIOMEDES</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PARIS</speaker>
            <line>It is great morning, and the hour prefix'd</line>
            <line>Of her delivery to this valiant Greek</line>
            <line>Comes fast upon. Good my brother Troilus,</line>
            <line>Tell you the lady what she is to do,</line>
            <line>And haste her to the purpose.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TROILUS</speaker>
            <line>Walk into her house;</line>
            <line>I'll bring her to the Grecian presently:</line>
            <line>And to his hand when I deliver her,</line>
            <line>Think it an altar, and thy brother Troilus</line>
            <line>A priest there offering to it his own heart.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PARIS</speaker>
            <line>I know what 'tis to love;</line>
            <line>And would, as I shall pity, I could help!</line>
            <line>Please you walk in, my lords.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-4">
      <title>SCENE IV.  The same. Pandarus' house.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter PANDARUS and CRESSIDA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>Be moderate, be moderate.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>Why tell you me of moderation?</line>
            <line>The grief is fine, full, perfect, that I taste,</line>
            <line>And violenteth in a sense as strong</line>
            <line>As that which causeth it: how can I moderate it?</line>
            <line>If I could temporize with my affection,</line>
            <line>Or brew it to a weak and colder palate,</line>
            <line>The like allayment could I give my grief.</line>
            <line>My love admits no qualifying dross;</line>
            <line>No more my grief, in such a precious loss.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>Here, here, here he comes.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter TROILUS</stagedir>
            <line>Ah, sweet ducks!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>O Troilus! Troilus!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Embracing him</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>What a pair of spectacles is here!</line>
            <line>Let me embrace too. 'O heart,' as the goodly saying is,</line>
            <line>'--O heart, heavy heart,</line>
            <line>Why sigh'st thou without breaking?</line>
            <line>where he answers again,</line>
            <line>'Because thou canst not ease thy smart</line>
            <line>By friendship nor by speaking.'</line>
            <line>There was never a truer rhyme. Let us cast away</line>
            <line>nothing, for we may live to have need of such a</line>
            <line>verse: we see it, we see it. How now, lambs?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TROILUS</speaker>
            <line>Cressid, I love thee in so strain'd a purity,</line>
            <line>That the bless'd gods, as angry with my fancy,</line>
            <line>More bright in zeal than the devotion which</line>
            <line>Cold lips blow to their deities, take thee from me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>Have the gods envy?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>Ay, ay, ay, ay; 'tis too plain a case.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>And is it true that I must go from Troy?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TROILUS</speaker>
            <line>A hateful truth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>What, and from Troilus too?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TROILUS</speaker>
            <line>From Troy and Troilus.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>Is it possible?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TROILUS</speaker>
            <line>And suddenly; where injury of chance</line>
            <line>Puts back leave-taking, justles roughly by</line>
            <line>All time of pause, rudely beguiles our lips</line>
            <line>Of all rejoindure, forcibly prevents</line>
            <line>Our lock'd embrasures, strangles our dear vows</line>
            <line>Even in the birth of our own labouring breath:</line>
            <line>We two, that with so many thousand sighs</line>
            <line>Did buy each other, must poorly sell ourselves</line>
            <line>With the rude brevity and discharge of one.</line>
            <line>Injurious time now with a robber's haste</line>
            <line>Crams his rich thievery up, he knows not how:</line>
            <line>As many farewells as be stars in heaven,</line>
            <line>With distinct breath and consign'd kisses to them,</line>
            <line>He fumbles up into a lose adieu,</line>
            <line>And scants us with a single famish'd kiss,</line>
            <line>Distasted with the salt of broken tears.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AENEAS</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Within</stagedir>  My lord, is the lady ready?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TROILUS</speaker>
            <line>Hark! you are call'd: some say the Genius so</line>
            <line>Cries 'come' to him that instantly must die.</line>
            <line>Bid them have patience; she shall come anon.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PANDARUS</speaker>
            <line>Where are my tears? rain, to lay this wind, or</line>
            <line>my heart will be blown up by the root.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>I must then to the Grecians?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TROILUS</speaker>
            <line>No remedy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>A woful Cressid 'mongst the merry Greeks!</line>
            <line>When shall we see again?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TROILUS</speaker>
            <line>Hear me, my love: be thou but true of heart,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>I true! how now! what wicked deem is this?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TROILUS</speaker>
            <line>Nay, we must use expostulation kindly,</line>
            <line>For it is parting from us:</line>
            <line>I speak not 'be thou true,' as fearing thee,</line>
            <line>For I will throw my glove to Death himself,</line>
            <line>That there's no maculation in thy heart:</line>
            <line>But 'be thou true,' say I, to fashion in</line>
            <line>My sequent protestation; be thou true,</line>
            <line>And I will see thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>O, you shall be exposed, my lord, to dangers</line>
            <line>As infinite as imminent! but I'll be true.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TROILUS</speaker>
            <line>And I'll grow friend with danger. Wear this sleeve.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>And you this glove. When shall I see you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TROILUS</speaker>
            <line>I will corrupt the Grecian sentinels,</line>
            <line>To give thee nightly visitation.</line>
            <line>But yet be true.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>O heavens! 'be true' again!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TROILUS</speaker>
            <line>Hear while I speak it, love:</line>
            <line>The Grecian youths are full of quality;</line>
            <line>They're loving, well composed with gifts of nature,</line>
            <line>Flowing and swelling o'er with arts and exercise:</line>
            <line>How novelty may move, and parts with person,</line>
            <line>Alas, a kind of godly jealousy--</line>
            <line>Which, I beseech you, call a virtuous sin--</line>
            <line>Makes me afeard.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>O heavens! you love me not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TROILUS</speaker>
            <line>Die I a villain, then!</line>
            <line>In this I do not call your faith in question</line>
            <line>So mainly as my merit: I cannot sing,</line>
            <line>Nor heel the high lavolt, nor sweeten talk,</line>
            <line>Nor play at subtle games; fair virtues all,</line>
            <line>To which the Grecians are most prompt and pregnant:</line>
            <line>But I can tell that in each grace of these</line>
            <line>There lurks a still and dumb-discoursive devil</line>
            <line>That tempts most cunningly: but be not tempted.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>Do you think I will?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TROILUS</speaker>
            <line>No.</line>
            <line>But something may be done that we will not:</line>
            <line>And sometimes we are devils to ourselves,</line>
            <line>When we will tempt the frailty of our powers,</line>
            <line>Presuming on their changeful potency.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AENEAS</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Within</stagedir>  Nay, good my lord,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TROILUS</speaker>
            <line>Come, kiss; and let us part.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PARIS</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Within</stagedir>  Brother Troilus!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TROILUS</speaker>
            <line>Good brother, come you hither;</line>
            <line>And bring AEneas and the Grecian with you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>My lord, will you be true?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TROILUS</speaker>
            <line>Who, I? alas, it is my vice, my fault:</line>
            <line>Whiles others fish with craft for great opinion,</line>
            <line>I with great truth catch mere simplicity;</line>
            <line>Whilst some with cunning gild their copper crowns,</line>
            <line>With truth and plainness I do wear mine bare.</line>
            <line>Fear not my truth: the moral of my wit</line>
            <line>Is 'plain and true;' there's all the reach of it.</line>
            <stagedir>Enter AENEAS, PARIS, ANTENOR, DEIPHOBUS,
and DIOMEDES</stagedir>
            <line>Welcome, Sir Diomed! here is the lady</line>
            <line>Which for Antenor we deliver you:</line>
            <line>At the port, lord, I'll give her to thy hand,</line>
            <line>And by the way possess thee what she is.</line>
            <line>Entreat her fair; and, by my soul, fair Greek,</line>
            <line>If e'er thou stand at mercy of my sword,</line>
            <line>Name Cressida and thy life shall be as safe</line>
            <line>As Priam is in Ilion.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DIOMEDES</speaker>
            <line>Fair Lady Cressid,</line>
            <line>So please you, save the thanks this prince expects:</line>
            <line>The lustre in your eye, heaven in your cheek,</line>
            <line>Pleads your fair usage; and to Diomed</line>
            <line>You shall be mistress, and command him wholly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TROILUS</speaker>
            <line>Grecian, thou dost not use me courteously,</line>
            <line>To shame the zeal of my petition to thee</line>
            <line>In praising her: I tell thee, lord of Greece,</line>
            <line>She is as far high-soaring o'er thy praises</line>
            <line>As thou unworthy to be call'd her servant.</line>
            <line>I charge thee use her well, even for my charge;</line>
            <line>For, by the dreadful Pluto, if thou dost not,</line>
            <line>Though the great bulk Achilles be thy guard,</line>
            <line>I'll cut thy throat.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DIOMEDES</speaker>
            <line>O, be not moved, Prince Troilus:</line>
            <line>Let me be privileged by my place and message,</line>
            <line>To be a speaker free; when I am hence</line>
            <line>I'll answer to my lust: and know you, lord,</line>
            <line>I'll nothing do on charge: to her own worth</line>
            <line>She shall be prized; but that you say 'be't so,'</line>
            <line>I'll speak it in my spirit and honour, 'no.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TROILUS</speaker>
            <line>Come, to the port. I'll tell thee, Diomed,</line>
            <line>This brave shall oft make thee to hide thy head.</line>
            <line>Lady, give me your hand, and, as we walk,</line>
            <line>To our own selves bend we our needful talk.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt TROILUS, CRESSIDA, and DIOMEDES</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Trumpet within</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PARIS</speaker>
            <line>Hark! Hector's trumpet.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AENEAS</speaker>
            <line>How have we spent this morning!</line>
            <line>The prince must think me tardy and remiss,</line>
            <line>That sore to ride before him to the field.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PARIS</speaker>
            <line>'Tis Troilus' fault: come, come, to field with him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DEIPHOBUS</speaker>
            <line>Let us make ready straight.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AENEAS</speaker>
            <line>Yea, with a bridegroom's fresh alacrity,</line>
            <line>Let us address to tend on Hector's heels:</line>
            <line>The glory of our Troy doth this day lie</line>
            <line>On his fair worth and single chivalry.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-5">
      <title>SCENE V.  The Grecian camp. Lists set out.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter AJAX, armed; AGAMEMNON, ACHILLES, PATROCLUS,
MENELAUS, ULYSSES, NESTOR, and others</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AGAMEMNON</speaker>
            <line>Here art thou in appointment fresh and fair,</line>
            <line>Anticipating time with starting courage.</line>
            <line>Give with thy trumpet a loud note to Troy,</line>
            <line>Thou dreadful Ajax; that the appalled air</line>
            <line>May pierce the head of the great combatant</line>
            <line>And hale him hither.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AJAX</speaker>
            <line>Thou, trumpet, there's my purse.</line>
            <line>Now crack thy lungs, and split thy brazen pipe:</line>
            <line>Blow, villain, till thy sphered bias cheek</line>
            <line>Outswell the colic of puff'd Aquilon:</line>
            <line>Come, stretch thy chest and let thy eyes spout blood;</line>
            <line>Thou blow'st for Hector.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Trumpet sounds</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ULYSSES</speaker>
            <line>No trumpet answers.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ACHILLES</speaker>
            <line>'Tis but early days.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AGAMEMNON</speaker>
            <line>Is not yond Diomed, with Calchas' daughter?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ULYSSES</speaker>
            <line>'Tis he, I ken the manner of his gait;</line>
            <line>He rises on the toe: that spirit of his</line>
            <line>In aspiration lifts him from the earth.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter DIOMEDES, with CRESSIDA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AGAMEMNON</speaker>
            <line>Is this the Lady Cressid?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DIOMEDES</speaker>
            <line>Even she.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AGAMEMNON</speaker>
            <line>Most dearly welcome to the Greeks, sweet lady.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NESTOR</speaker>
            <line>Our general doth salute you with a kiss.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ULYSSES</speaker>
            <line>Yet is the kindness but particular;</line>
            <line>'Twere better she were kiss'd in general.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NESTOR</speaker>
            <line>And very courtly counsel: I'll begin.</line>
            <line>So much for Nestor.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ACHILLES</speaker>
            <line>I'll take what winter from your lips, fair lady:</line>
            <line>Achilles bids you welcome.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENELAUS</speaker>
            <line>I had good argument for kissing once.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PATROCLUS</speaker>
            <line>But that's no argument for kissing now;</line>
            <line>For this popp'd Paris in his hardiment,</line>
            <line>And parted thus you and your argument.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ULYSSES</speaker>
            <line>O deadly gall, and theme of all our scorns!</line>
            <line>For which we lose our heads to gild his horns.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PATROCLUS</speaker>
            <line>The first was Menelaus' kiss; this, mine:</line>
            <line>Patroclus kisses you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENELAUS</speaker>
            <line>O, this is trim!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PATROCLUS</speaker>
            <line>Paris and I kiss evermore for him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENELAUS</speaker>
            <line>I'll have my kiss, sir. Lady, by your leave.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>In kissing, do you render or receive?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PATROCLUS</speaker>
            <line>Both take and give.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>I'll make my match to live,</line>
            <line>The kiss you take is better than you give;</line>
            <line>Therefore no kiss.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENELAUS</speaker>
            <line>I'll give you boot, I'll give you three for one.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>You're an odd man; give even or give none.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENELAUS</speaker>
            <line>An odd man, lady! every man is odd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>No, Paris is not; for you know 'tis true,</line>
            <line>That you are odd, and he is even with you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENELAUS</speaker>
            <line>You fillip me o' the head.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>No, I'll be sworn.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ULYSSES</speaker>
            <line>It were no match, your nail against his horn.</line>
            <line>May I, sweet lady, beg a kiss of you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>You may.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ULYSSES</speaker>
            <line>I do desire it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>Why, beg, then.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ULYSSES</speaker>
            <line>Why then for Venus' sake, give me a kiss,</line>
            <line>When Helen is a maid again, and his.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CRESSIDA</speaker>
            <line>I am your debtor, claim it when 'tis due.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ULYSSES</speaker>
            <line>Never's my day, and then a kiss of you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DIOMEDES</speaker>
            <line>Lady, a word: I'll bring you to your father.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit with CRESSIDA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NESTOR</speaker>
            <line>A woman of quick sense.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ULYSSES</speaker>
            <line>Fie, fie upon her!</line>
            <line>There's language in her eye, her cheek, her lip,</line>
            <line>Nay, her foot speaks; her wanton spirits look out</line>
            <line>At every joint and motive of her body.</line>
            <line>O, these encounterers, so glib of tongue,</line>
            <line>That give accosting welcome ere it comes,</line>
            <line>And wide unclasp the tables of their thoughts</line>
            <line>To every ticklish reader! set them down</line>
            <line>For sluttish spoils of opportunity</line>
            <line>And daughters of the game.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Trumpet within</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ALL</speaker>
            <line>The Trojans' trumpet.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AGAMEMNON</speaker>
            <line>Yonder comes the troop.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter HECTOR, armed; AENEAS, TROILUS, and other
Trojans, with Attendants</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AENEAS</speaker>
            <line>Hail, all you state of Greece! what shall be done</line>
            <line>To him that victory commands? or do you purpose</line>
            <line>A victor shall be known? will you the knights</line>
            <line>Shall to the edge of all extremity</line>
            <line>Pursue each other, or shall be divided</line>
            <line>By any voice or order of the field?</line>
            <line>Hector bade ask.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AGAMEMNON</speaker>
            <line>Which way would Hector have it?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AENEAS</speaker>
            <line>He cares not; he'll obey conditions.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ACHILLES</speaker>
            <line>'Tis done like Hector; but securely done,</line>
            <line>A little proudly, and great deal misprizing</line>
            <line>The knight opposed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AENEAS</speaker>
            <line>If not Achilles, sir,</line>
            <line>What is your name?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ACHILLES</speaker>
            <line>If not Achilles, nothing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AENEAS</speaker>
            <line>Therefore Achilles: but, whate'er, know this:</line>
            <line>In the extremity of great and little,</line>
            <line>Valour and pride excel themselves in Hector;</line>
            <line>The one almost as infinite as all,</line>
            <line>The other blank as nothing. Weigh him well,</line>
            <line>And that which looks like pride is courtesy.</line>
            <line>This Ajax is half made of Hector's blood:</line>
            <line>In love whereof, half Hector stays at home;</line>
            <line>Half heart, half hand, half Hector comes to seek</line>
            <line>This blended knight, half Trojan and half Greek.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ACHILLES</speaker>
            <line>A maiden battle, then? O, I perceive you.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter DIOMEDES</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AGAMEMNON</speaker>
            <line>Here is Sir Diomed. Go, gentle knight,</line>
            <line>Stand by our Ajax: as you and Lord AEneas</line>
            <line>Consent upon the order of their fight,</line>
            <line>So be it; either to the uttermost,</line>
            <line>Or else a breath: the combatants being kin</line>
            <line>Half stints their strife before their strokes begin.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>AJAX and HECTOR enter the lists</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ULYSSES</speaker>
            <line>They are opposed already.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AGAMEMNON</speaker>
            <line>What Trojan is that same that looks so heavy?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ULYSSES</speaker>
            <line>The youngest son of Priam, a true knight,</line>
            <line>Not yet mature, yet matchless, firm of word,</line>
            <line>Speaking in deeds and deedless in his tongue;</line>
            <line>Not soon provoked nor being provoked soon calm'd:</line>
            <line>His heart and hand both open and both free;</line>
            <line>For what he has he gives, what thinks he shows;</line>
            <line>Yet gives he not till judgment guide his bounty,</line>
            <line>Nor dignifies an impure thought with breath;</line>
            <line>Manly as Hector, but more dangerous;</line>
            <line>For Hector in his blaze of wrath subscribes</line>
            <line>To tender objects, but he in heat of action</line>
            <line>Is more vindicative than jealous love:</line>
            <line>They call him Troilus, and on him erect</line>
            <line>A second hope, as fairly built as Hector.</line>
            <line>Thus says AEneas; one that knows the youth</line>
            <line>Even to his inches, and with private soul</line>
            <line>Did in great Ilion thus translate him to me.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Alarum. Hector and Ajax fight</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AGAMEMNON</speaker>
            <line>They are in action.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NESTOR</speaker>
            <line>Now, Ajax, hold thine own!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TROILUS</speaker>
            <line>Hector, thou sleep'st;</line>
            <line>Awake thee!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AGAMEMNON</speaker>
            <line>His blows are well disposed: there, Ajax!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DIOMEDES</speaker>
            <line>You must no more.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Trumpets cease</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AENEAS</speaker>
            <line>Princes, enough, so please you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AJAX</speaker>
            <line>I am not warm yet; let us fight again.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DIOMEDES</speaker>
            <line>As Hector pleases.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HECTOR</speaker>
            <line>Why, then will I no more:</line>
            <line>Thou art, great lord, my father's sister's son,</line>
            <line>A cousin-german to great Priam's seed;</line>
            <line>The obligation of our blood forbids</line>
            <line>A gory emulation 'twixt us twain:</line>
            <line>Were thy commixtion Greek and Trojan so</line>
            <line>That thou couldst say 'This hand is Grecian all,</line>
            <line>And this is Trojan; the sinews of this leg</line>
            <line>All Greek, and this all Troy; my mother's blood</line>
            <line>Runs on the dexter cheek, and this sinister</line>
            <line>Bounds in my father's;' by Jove multipotent,</line>
            <line>Thou shouldst not bear from me a Greekish member</line>
            <line>Wherein my sword had not impressure made</line>
            <line>Of our rank feud: but the just gods gainsay</line>
            <line>That any drop thou borrow'dst from thy mother,</line>
            <line>My sacred aunt, should by my mortal sword</line>
            <line>Be drain'd! Let me embrace thee, Ajax:</line>
            <line>By him that thunders, thou hast lusty arms;</line>
            <line>Hector would have them fall upon him thus:</line>
            <line>Cousin, all honour to thee!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AJAX</speaker>
            <line>I thank thee, Hector</line>
            <line>Thou art too gentle and too free a man:</line>
            <line>I came to kill thee, cousin, and bear hence</line>
            <line>A great addition earned in thy death.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HECTOR</speaker>
            <line>Not Neoptolemus so mirable,</line>
            <line>On whose bright crest Fame with her loud'st Oyes</line>
            <line>Cries 'This is he,' could promise to himself</line>
            <line>A thought of added honour torn from Hector.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AENEAS</speaker>
            <line>There is expectance here from both the sides,</line>
            <line>What further you will do.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HECTOR</speaker>
            <line>We'll answer it;</line>
            <line>The issue is embracement: Ajax, farewell.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AJAX</speaker>
            <line>If I might in entreaties find success--</line>
            <line>As seld I have the chance--I would desire</line>
            <line>My famous cousin to our Grecian tents.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DIOMEDES</speaker>
            <line>'Tis Agamemnon's wish, and great Achilles</line>
            <line>Doth long to see unarm'd the valiant Hector.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HECTOR</speaker>
            <line>AEneas, call my brother Troilus to me,</line>
            <line>And signify this loving interview</line>
            <line>To the expecters of our Trojan part;</line>
            <line>Desire them home. Give me thy hand, my cousin;</line>
            <line>I will go eat with thee and see your knights.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AJAX</speaker>
            <line>Great Agamemnon comes to meet us here.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HECTOR</speaker>
            <line>The worthiest of them tell me name by name;</line>
            <line>But for Achilles, mine own searching eyes</line>
            <line>Shall find him by his large and portly size.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AGAMEMNON</speaker>
            <line>Worthy of arms! as welcome as to one</line>
            <line>That would be rid of such an enemy;</line>
            <line>But that's no welcome: understand more clear,</line>
            <line>What's past and what's to come is strew'd with husks</line>
            <line>And formless ruin of oblivion;</line>
            <line>But in this extant moment, faith and troth,</line>
            <line>Strain'd purely from all hollow bias-drawing,</line>
            <line>Bids thee, with most divine integrity,</line>
            <line>From heart of very heart, great Hector, welcome.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HECTOR</speaker>
            <line>I thank thee, most imperious Agamemnon.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AGAMEMNON</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>To TROILUS</stagedir>  My well-famed lord of Troy, no</line>
            <line>less to you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENELAUS</speaker>
            <line>Let me confirm my princely brother's greeting:</line>
            <line>You brace of warlike brothers, welcome hither.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HECTOR</speaker>
            <line>Who must we answer?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AENEAS</speaker>
            <line>The noble Menelaus.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HECTOR</speaker>
            <line>O, you, my lord? by Mars his gauntlet, thanks!</line>
            <line>Mock not, that I affect the untraded oath;</line>
            <line>Your quondam wife swears still by Venus' glove:</line>
            <line>She's well, but bade me not commend her to you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MENELAUS</speaker>
            <line>Name her not now, sir; she's a deadly theme.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HECTOR</speaker>
            <line>O, pardon; I offend.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NESTOR</speaker>
            <line>I have, thou gallant Trojan, seen thee oft</line>
            <line>Labouring for destiny make cruel way</line>
            <line>Through ranks of Greekish youth, and I have seen thee,</line>
            <line>As hot as Perseus, spur thy Phrygian steed,</line>
            <line>Despising many forfeits and subduements,</line>
            <line>When thou hast hung thy advanced sword i' the air,</line>
            <line>Not letting it decline on the declined,</line>
            <line>That I have said to some my standers by</line>
            <line>'Lo, Jupiter is yonder, dealing life!'</line>
            <line>And I have seen thee pause and take thy breath,</line>
            <line>When that a ring of Greeks have hemm'd thee in,</line>
            <line>Like an Olympian wrestling: this have I seen;</line>
            <line>But this thy countenance, still lock'd in steel,</line>
            <line>I never saw till now. I knew thy grandsire,</line>
            <line>And once fought with him: he was a soldier good;</line>
            <line>But, by great Mars, the captain of us all,</line>
            <line>Never saw like thee. Let an old man embrace thee;</line>
            <line>And, worthy warrior, welcome to our tents.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AENEAS</speaker>
            <line>'Tis the old Nestor.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HECTOR</speaker>
            <line>Let me embrace thee, good old chronicle,</line>
            <line>That hast so long walk'd hand in hand with time:</line>
            <line>Most reverend Nestor, I am glad to clasp thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NESTOR</speaker>
            <line>I would my arms could match thee in contention,</line>
            <line>As they contend with thee in courtesy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HECTOR</speaker>
            <line>I would they could.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>NESTOR</speaker>
            <line>Ha!</line>
            <line>By this white beard, I'ld fight with thee to-morrow.</line>
            <line>Well, welcome, welcome! I have seen the time.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ULYSSES</speaker>
            <line>I wonder now how yonder city stands</line>
            <line>When we have here her base and pillar by us.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HECTOR</speaker>
            <line>I know your favour, Lord Ulysses, well.</line>
            <line>Ah, sir, there's many a Greek and Trojan dead,</line>
            <line>Since first I saw yourself and Diomed</line>
            <line>In Ilion, on your Greekish embassy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ULYSSES</speaker>
            <line>Sir, I foretold you then what would ensue:</line>
            <line>My prophecy is but half his journey yet;</line>
            <line>For yonder walls, that pertly front your town,</line>
            <line>Yond towers, whose wanton tops do buss the clouds,</line>
            <line>Must kiss their own feet.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HECTOR</speaker>
            <line>I must not believe you:</line>
            <line>There they stand yet, and modestly I think,</line>
            <line>The fall of every Phrygian stone will cost</line>
            <line>A drop of Grecian blood: the end crowns all,</line>
            <line>And that old common arbitrator, Time,</line>
            <line>Will one day end it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ULYSSES</speaker>
            <line>So to him we leave it.</line>
            <line>Most gentle and most valiant Hector, welcome:</line>
            <line>After the general, I beseech you next</line>
            <line>To feast with me and see me at my tent.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ACHILLES</speaker>
            <line>I shall forestall thee, Lord Ulysses, thou!</line>
            <line>Now, Hector, I have fed mine eyes on thee;</line>
            <line>I have with exact view perused thee, Hector,</line>
            <line>And quoted joint by joint.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HECTOR</speaker>
            <line>Is this Achilles?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ACHILLES</speaker>
            <line>I am Achilles.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HECTOR</speaker>
            <line>Stand fair, I pray thee: let me look on thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ACHILLES</speaker>
            <line>Behold thy fill.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HECTOR</speaker>
            <line>Nay, I have done already.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ACHILLES</speaker>
            <line>Thou art too brief: I will the second time,</line>
            <line>As I would buy thee, view thee limb by limb.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HECTOR</speaker>
            <line>O, like a book of sport thou'lt read me o'er;</line>
            <line>But there's more in me than thou understand'st.</line>
            <line>Why dost thou so oppress me with thine eye?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ACHILLES</speaker>
            <line>Tell me, you heavens, in which part of his body</line>
            <line>Shall I destroy him? whether there, or there, or there?</line>
            <line>That I may give the local wound a name</line>
            <line>And make distinct the very breach whereout</line>
            <line>Hector's great spirit flew: answer me, heavens!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HECTOR</speaker>
            <line>It would discredit the blest gods, proud man,</line>
            <line>To answer such a question: stand again:</line>
            <line>Think'st thou to catch my life so pleasantly</line>
            <line>As to prenominate in nice conjecture</line>
            <line>Where thou wilt hit me dead?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ACHILLES</speaker>
            <line>I tell thee, yea.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HECTOR</speaker>
            <line>Wert thou an oracle to tell me so,</line>
            <line>I'd not believe thee. Henceforth guard thee well;</line>
            <line>For I'll not kill thee there, nor there, nor there;</line>
            <line>But, by the forge that stithied Mars his helm,</line>
            <line>I'll kill thee every where, yea, o'er and o'er.</line>
            <line>You wisest Grecians, pardon me this brag;</line>
            <line>His insolence draws folly from my lips;</line>
            <line>But I'll endeavour deeds to match these words,</line>
            <line>Or may I never--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AJAX</speaker>
            <line>Do not chafe thee, cousin:</line>
            <line>And you, Achilles, let these threats alone,</line>
            <line>Till accident or purpose bring you to't:</line>
            <line>You may have every day enough of Hector</line>
            <line>If you have stomach; the general state, I fear,</line>
            <line>Can scarce entreat you to be odd with him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HECTOR</speaker>
            <line>I pray you, let us see you in the field:</line>
            <line>We have had pelting wars, since you refused</line>
            <line>The Grecians' cause.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ACHILLES</speaker>
            <line>Dost thou entreat me, Hector?</line>
            <line>To-morrow do I meet thee, fell as death;</line>
            <line>To-night all friends.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HECTOR</speaker>
            <line>Thy hand upon that match.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AGAMEMNON</speaker>
            <line>First, all you peers of Greece, go to my tent;</line>
            <line>There in the full convive we: afterwards,</line>
            <line>As Hector's leisure and your bounties shall</line>
            <line>Concur together, severally entreat him.</line>
            <line>Beat loud the tabourines, let the trumpets blow,</line>
            <line>That this great soldier may his welcome know.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt all except TROILUS and ULYSSES</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TROILUS</speaker>
            <line>My Lord Ulysses, tell me, I beseech you,</line>
            <line>In what place of the field doth Calchas keep?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ULYSSES</speaker>
            <line>At Menelaus' tent, most princely Troilus:</line>
            <line>There Diomed doth feast with him to-night;</line>
            <line>Who neither looks upon the heaven nor earth,</line>
            <line>But gives all gaze and bent of amorous view</line>
            <line>On the fair Cressid.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TROILUS</speaker>
            <line>Shall sweet lord, be bound to you so much,</line>
            <line>After we part from Agamemnon's tent,</line>
            <line>To bring me thither?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ULYSSES</speaker>
            <line>You shall command me, sir.</line>
            <line>As gentle tell me, of what honour was</line>
            <line>This Cressida in Troy? Had she no lover there</line>
            <line>That wails her absence?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>TROILUS</speaker>
            <line>O, sir, to such as boasting show their scars</line>
            <line>A mock is due. Will you walk on, my lord?</line>
            <line>She was beloved, she loved; she is, and doth:</line>
            <line>But still sweet love is food for fortune's tooth.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>