<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE task PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:task" "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:task">
<task id="taskId">
 <title>Generating EPUBs From OxygenXML</title>
 <shortdesc>You can configure a DITA transformation scenario in OxygenXML to generate EPUBs.</shortdesc>
  <prolog>
    <metadata>
      <keywords>
        <indexterm>OxygenXML<indexterm>generating EPUBs with</indexterm></indexterm>
        <indexterm>EPUB<indexterm>generating<indexterm>with OxygenXML</indexterm></indexterm></indexterm>
        <indexterm>transformation scenario</indexterm>
      </keywords>
    </metadata>
  </prolog>
 <taskbody>
    <context>
      <p>You must have the EPUB plugin deployed to the Open Toolkit used by OxygenXML, normally in the <filepath>frameworks/dita/DITA-OT</filepath> directory under Oxygen's installation directory. You can also use a different Toolkit by changing the value of the <parmname>dita.dir</parmname> Ant parameter.</p>
      <p>These instructions reflect Oxygen version 11.2 and 12.0.</p>
      <p>To set up an EPUB transformation scenario in OxygenXML, do the following.</p>
    </context>
    <steps
      id="steps_bd2ab97b-2b84-4975-b881-a037eff4c6dd">
      <step>
        <cmd>From either the main editing window or the DITA Maps Manager, open the "Configure Transformation Scenario" dialog (the little wrench and red arrow button in the toolbar).</cmd>
      </step>
      <step>
        <cmd>Select "DITA OT Transformation" from the <uicontrol>Scenario Type</uicontrol> pulldown.</cmd>
      </step>
      <step>
        <cmd>Select the "DITA Map XHTML" transform and press the <uicontrol>Duplicate</uicontrol> button.</cmd>
        <stepresult>
          <p>The "Edit Scenario" dialog should open.</p>
        </stepresult>
      </step>
      <step>
        <cmd>Change the scenario name to something like "DITA Map EPUB"</cmd>
      </step>
      <step>
        <cmd>Select the <uicontrol>Parameters</uicontrol> tab (it should be selected by default), add a new parameter named "transtype" and set its value to "epub".</cmd>
      </step>
      <step>
        <cmd>Select the <uicontrol>OK</uicontrol> button to save the scenario.</cmd>
        <stepresult>
          <p>You should see your new scenario in the list of available DITA OT transformation scenarios.</p>
        </stepresult>
      </step>
    </steps>
    <result>
      <p>The scenario should be ready to use. You can test it by applying it to any DITA map. The EPUB file is generated in whatever you've configured as the output directory using the normal output location configuration (as specified in the Output tab of the transformation scenario configuration dialog. </p>
      <p>If you select the "Open in browser" option in the transformation scenario's output options and you have an application associated with .epub files, such as Adobe Digital Editions, the newly-generated EPUB should open in that application. Note that in OxygenXML 12 you have the option of associating EPUB files with OxygenXML, which can open them in its Archive Browser. If you have that association, then doing "Open in browser" will open the EPUB in OxygenXML, not in an EPUB viewer.</p>
      <p>You can edit the scenario to add additional EPUB parameters as necessary. Simply open the scenario in the Scenario Editor, select the "add parameter" button, and create the parameter. The EPUB-specific parameters are documented in <xref
        href="epub-transtype-parameters-ref.xml#conceptId"
        format="dita"/>.</p>
    </result>
  </taskbody>
</task>
