<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:concept" "concept.dtd">
<concept id="conceptId">
 <title>Using Custom CSS Style Sheets</title>
 <shortdesc>You can include custom CSS styles sheets in your EPUB just as you can for HTML output generally.</shortdesc>
  <prolog>
    <metadata>
      <keywords>
        <indexterm>css<indexterm>custom</indexterm></indexterm>
      </keywords>
    </metadata>
  </prolog>
 <conbody>
    <note>At the moment, this mechanism only supports a single CSS file. A future enhancement will be to allow the copying of all the CSS files in a specified directory.</note>
   <p>The EPUB transformation type uses the same Ant parameters for CSS styles sheets as for the normal HTML transformation type. The difference is that you <i>must</i> copy the CSS files to the output since they need to be part of the EPUB package. Thus the <parmname>args.copycss</parmname> parameter is implicitly set to "yes" if you specify the <parmname>args.css</parmname> parameter.</p>
    <p>Likewise, the parameter <parmname>args.csspath</parmname> is ignored because the EPUB processor controls how the CSS files are referenced in the generated HTML files.</p>
    <p>You may specify the directory within the EPUB package to contain the CSS files using the parameter <parmname
      keyref="css.output.dir_refentry">css.output.dir</parmname>. By default it is the same as the topic output directory (which by default is "topics").</p>
    <p>The <parmname>args.css</parmname> parameter can be an absolute path to the CSS file or it can be a path relative to the value of the <parmname>args.cssroot</parmname> parameter.</p>
    <p>For example, if you have a custom CSS file <filepath>mystyle.css</filepath> in the directory <filepath>c:\projects\mydoc\css</filepath> and you want to use that CSS file in your EPUB you would specify the Ant parameter <parmname>args.css</parmname> with the value "c:\projects\mydoc\css\mystyle.css".</p>
    <p>If you have a common CSS source directory and you use different CSS files for different publications, you can specify both <parmname>args.cssroot</parmname> and <parmname>args.css</parmname> like so:<ul>
      <li><parmname>args.cssroot</parmname> as "c:\projects\mydoc\css"</li>
      <li><parmname>args.css</parmname> as "mystyle.css"</li>
      </ul></p>
    <p>If you want your CSS somewhere other than the topics directory, specify the <parmname>css.output.dir</parmname> parameter to the desired directory name, e.g. "css".</p>
    <p>The built-in CSS style sheets provided with the DITA Open Toolkit are always included in the EPUB in the CSS output directory and are always referenced in the HTML after any user-specified CSS style sheet.</p>
 </conbody>
</concept>
