<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.org:doctypes:dita:concept" "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.org:doctypes:dita:concept">
<concept id="conceptId">
 <title>Using Custom CSS Style Sheets</title>
 <shortdesc>You can include custom CSS styles sheets in your EPUB just as you can for HTML output generally.</shortdesc>
  <prolog>
    <metadata>
      <keywords>
        <indexterm>css<indexterm>custom</indexterm></indexterm>
        <indexterm>built-in CSS</indexterm>
      </keywords>
    </metadata>
  </prolog>
 <conbody>
    <note>At the moment, this mechanism only supports a single CSS file. You can use extensions to
      the copy graphics process to include additional resources in your EPUB, such as additional CSS
      style sheets, Javascript scripts, branding graphics, and so on.</note>
   <p>The EPUB transformation type uses the same Ant parameters for CSS styles sheets as for the normal HTML transformation type. The difference is that you <i>must</i> copy the CSS files to the output since they need to be part of the EPUB package. Thus the <parmname>args.copycss</parmname> parameter is implicitly set to "yes" if you specify the <parmname>args.css</parmname> parameter.</p>
    <p>You may specify the directory within the EPUB package to contain the CSS files using the
      regular XHTML parameter <parmname>args.csspath</parmname>. The value must be a path relative
      to the root of the EPUB container, e.g. "css".</p>
    <p>The <parmname>args.css</parmname> parameter can be an absolute path to the CSS file or it can be a path relative to the value of the <parmname>args.cssroot</parmname> parameter.</p>
    <p>For example, if you have a custom CSS file <filepath>mystyle.css</filepath> in the directory <filepath>c:\projects\mydoc\css</filepath> and you want to use that CSS file in your EPUB you would specify the Ant parameter <parmname>args.css</parmname> with the value "c:\projects\mydoc\css\mystyle.css".</p>
    <p>If you have a common CSS source directory and you use different CSS files for different publications, you can specify both <parmname>args.cssroot</parmname> and <parmname>args.css</parmname> like so:<ul>
      <li><parmname>args.cssroot</parmname> as "c:\projects\mydoc\css"</li>
      <li><parmname>args.css</parmname> as "mystyle.css"</li>
      </ul></p>
    <p>The built-in CSS style sheets provided with the DITA Open Toolkit are always included in the
      EPUB in the CSS output directory by default. You can omit the built-in CSS files by specifying
      "false" for the <parmname keyref="paramref-epub-copy-system-css"
        >epub.copy.system.css</parmname> parameter, which is true by default.</p>
 </conbody>
</concept>
