<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:shakespear:dtd:act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-2">
   <title>ACT II</title>
   <prologue id="act-2-prologue">
      <title>[Prologue]</title>
      <prologue-body>
         <stagedir>Enter GOWER</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>GOWER</speaker>
            <line>Here have you seen a mighty king</line>
            <line>His child, I wis, to incest bring;</line>
            <line>A better prince and benign lord,</line>
            <line>That will prove awful both in deed and word.</line>
            <line>Be quiet then as men should be,</line>
            <line>Till he hath pass'd necessity.</line>
            <line>I'll show you those in troubles reign,</line>
            <line>Losing a mite, a mountain gain.</line>
            <line>The good in conversation,</line>
            <line>To whom I give my benison,</line>
            <line>Is still at Tarsus, where each man</line>
            <line>Thinks all is writ he speken can;</line>
            <line>And, to remember what he does,</line>
            <line>Build his statue to make him glorious:</line>
            <line>But tidings to the contrary</line>
            <line>Are brought your eyes; what need speak I?</line>
            <subhead>DUMB SHOW.</subhead>
            <stagedir>Enter at one door PERICLES talking with CLEON; all
the train with them. Enter at another door a
Gentleman, with a letter to PERICLES; PERICLES
shows the letter to CLEON; gives the Messenger a
reward, and knights him. Exit PERICLES at one
door, and CLEON at another</stagedir>
            <line>Good Helicane, that stay'd at home,</line>
            <line>Not to eat honey like a drone</line>
            <line>From others' labours; for though he strive</line>
            <line>To killen bad, keep good alive;</line>
            <line>And to fulfil his prince' desire,</line>
            <line>Sends word of all that haps in Tyre:</line>
            <line>How Thaliard came full bent with sin</line>
            <line>And had intent to murder him;</line>
            <line>And that in Tarsus was not best</line>
            <line>Longer for him to make his rest.</line>
            <line>He, doing so, put forth to seas,</line>
            <line>Where when men been, there's seldom ease;</line>
            <line>For now the wind begins to blow;</line>
            <line>Thunder above and deeps below</line>
            <line>Make such unquiet, that the ship</line>
            <line>Should house him safe is wreck'd and split;</line>
            <line>And he, good prince, having all lost,</line>
            <line>By waves from coast to coast is tost:</line>
            <line>All perishen of man, of pelf,</line>
            <line>Ne aught escapen but himself;</line>
            <line>Till fortune, tired with doing bad,</line>
            <line>Threw him ashore, to give him glad:</line>
            <line>And here he comes. What shall be next,</line>
            <line>Pardon old Gower,--this longs the text.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </prologue-body>
   </prologue>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  Pentapolis. An open place by the sea-side.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter PERICLES, wet</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERICLES</speaker>
            <line>Yet cease your ire, you angry stars of heaven!</line>
            <line>Wind, rain, and thunder, remember, earthly man</line>
            <line>Is but a substance that must yield to you;</line>
            <line>And I, as fits my nature, do obey you:</line>
            <line>Alas, the sea hath cast me on the rocks,</line>
            <line>Wash'd me from shore to shore, and left me breath</line>
            <line>Nothing to think on but ensuing death:</line>
            <line>Let it suffice the greatness of your powers</line>
            <line>To have bereft a prince of all his fortunes;</line>
            <line>And having thrown him from your watery grave,</line>
            <line>Here to have death in peace is all he'll crave.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter three FISHERMEN</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Fisherman</speaker>
            <line>What, ho, Pilch!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Fisherman</speaker>
            <line>Ha, come and bring away the nets!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Fisherman</speaker>
            <line>What, Patch-breech, I say!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Fisherman</speaker>
            <line>What say you, master?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Fisherman</speaker>
            <line>Look how thou stirrest now! come away, or I'll</line>
            <line>fetch thee with a wanion.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Fisherman</speaker>
            <line>Faith, master, I am thinking of the poor men that</line>
            <line>were cast away before us even now.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Fisherman</speaker>
            <line>Alas, poor souls, it grieved my heart to hear what</line>
            <line>pitiful cries they made to us to help them, when,</line>
            <line>well-a-day, we could scarce help ourselves.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Fisherman</speaker>
            <line>Nay, master, said not I as much when I saw the</line>
            <line>porpus how he bounced and tumbled? they say</line>
            <line>they're half fish, half flesh: a plague on them,</line>
            <line>they ne'er come but I look to be washed. Master, I</line>
            <line>marvel how the fishes live in the sea.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Fisherman</speaker>
            <line>Why, as men do a-land; the great ones eat up the</line>
            <line>little ones: I can compare our rich misers to</line>
            <line>nothing so fitly as to a whale; a' plays and</line>
            <line>tumbles, driving the poor fry before him, and at</line>
            <line>last devours them all at a mouthful: such whales</line>
            <line>have I heard on o' the land, who never leave gaping</line>
            <line>till they've swallowed the whole parish, church,</line>
            <line>steeple, bells, and all.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERICLES</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  A pretty moral.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Fisherman</speaker>
            <line>But, master, if I had been the sexton, I would have</line>
            <line>been that day in the belfry.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Fisherman</speaker>
            <line>Why, man?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Fisherman</speaker>
            <line>Because he should have swallowed me too: and when I</line>
            <line>had been in his belly, I would have kept such a</line>
            <line>jangling of the bells, that he should never have</line>
            <line>left, till he cast bells, steeple, church, and</line>
            <line>parish up again. But if the good King Simonides</line>
            <line>were of my mind,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERICLES</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  Simonides!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Fisherman</speaker>
            <line>We would purge the land of these drones, that rob</line>
            <line>the bee of her honey.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERICLES</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  How from the finny subject of the sea</line>
            <line>These fishers tell the infirmities of men;</line>
            <line>And from their watery empire recollect</line>
            <line>All that may men approve or men detect!</line>
            <line>Peace be at your labour, honest fishermen.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Fisherman</speaker>
            <line>Honest! good fellow, what's that? If it be a day</line>
            <line>fits you, search out of the calendar, and nobody</line>
            <line>look after it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERICLES</speaker>
            <line>May see the sea hath cast upon your coast.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Fisherman</speaker>
            <line>What a drunken knave was the sea to cast thee in our</line>
            <line>way!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERICLES</speaker>
            <line>A man whom both the waters and the wind,</line>
            <line>In that vast tennis-court, have made the ball</line>
            <line>For them to play upon, entreats you pity him:</line>
            <line>He asks of you, that never used to beg.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Fisherman</speaker>
            <line>No, friend, cannot you beg? Here's them in our</line>
            <line>country Greece gets more with begging than we can do</line>
            <line>with working.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Fisherman</speaker>
            <line>Canst thou catch any fishes, then?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERICLES</speaker>
            <line>I never practised it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Fisherman</speaker>
            <line>Nay, then thou wilt starve, sure; for here's nothing</line>
            <line>to be got now-a-days, unless thou canst fish for't.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERICLES</speaker>
            <line>What I have been I have forgot to know;</line>
            <line>But what I am, want teaches me to think on:</line>
            <line>A man throng'd up with cold: my veins are chill,</line>
            <line>And have no more of life than may suffice</line>
            <line>To give my tongue that heat to ask your help;</line>
            <line>Which if you shall refuse, when I am dead,</line>
            <line>For that I am a man, pray see me buried.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Fisherman</speaker>
            <line>Die quoth-a? Now gods forbid! I have a gown here;</line>
            <line>come, put it on; keep thee warm. Now, afore me, a</line>
            <line>handsome fellow! Come, thou shalt go home, and</line>
            <line>we'll have flesh for holidays, fish for</line>
            <line>fasting-days, and moreo'er puddings and flap-jacks,</line>
            <line>and thou shalt be welcome.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERICLES</speaker>
            <line>I thank you, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Fisherman</speaker>
            <line>Hark you, my friend; you said you could not beg.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERICLES</speaker>
            <line>I did but crave.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Fisherman</speaker>
            <line>But crave! Then I'll turn craver too, and so I</line>
            <line>shall 'scape whipping.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERICLES</speaker>
            <line>Why, are all your beggars whipped, then?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Fisherman</speaker>
            <line>O, not all, my friend, not all; for if all your</line>
            <line>beggars were whipped, I would wish no better office</line>
            <line>than to be beadle. But, master, I'll go draw up the</line>
            <line>net.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit with Third Fisherman</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERICLES</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  How well this honest mirth becomes their labour!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Fisherman</speaker>
            <line>Hark you, sir, do you know where ye are?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERICLES</speaker>
            <line>Not well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Fisherman</speaker>
            <line>Why, I'll tell you: this is called Pentapolis, and</line>
            <line>our king the good Simonides.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERICLES</speaker>
            <line>The good King Simonides, do you call him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Fisherman</speaker>
            <line>Ay, sir; and he deserves so to be called for his</line>
            <line>peaceable reign and good government.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERICLES</speaker>
            <line>He is a happy king, since he gains from his subjects</line>
            <line>the name of good by his government. How far is his</line>
            <line>court distant from this shore?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Fisherman</speaker>
            <line>Marry, sir, half a day's journey: and I'll tell</line>
            <line>you, he hath a fair daughter, and to-morrow is her</line>
            <line>birth-day; and there are princes and knights come</line>
            <line>from all parts of the world to just and tourney for her love.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERICLES</speaker>
            <line>Were my fortunes equal to my desires, I could wish</line>
            <line>to make one there.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Fisherman</speaker>
            <line>O, sir, things must be as they may; and what a man</line>
            <line>cannot get, he may lawfully deal for--his wife's soul.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter Second and Third Fishermen, drawing up a net</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Fisherman</speaker>
            <line>Help, master, help! here's a fish hangs in the net,</line>
            <line>like a poor man's right in the law; 'twill hardly</line>
            <line>come out. Ha! bots on't, 'tis come at last, and</line>
            <line>'tis turned to a rusty armour.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERICLES</speaker>
            <line>An armour, friends! I pray you, let me see it.</line>
            <line>Thanks, fortune, yet, that, after all my crosses,</line>
            <line>Thou givest me somewhat to repair myself;</line>
            <line>And though it was mine own, part of my heritage,</line>
            <line>Which my dead father did bequeath to me.</line>
            <line>With this strict charge, even as he left his life,</line>
            <line>'Keep it, my Pericles; it hath been a shield</line>
            <line>Twixt me and death;'--and pointed to this brace;--</line>
            <line>'For that it saved me, keep it; in like necessity--</line>
            <line>The which the gods protect thee from!--may</line>
            <line>defend thee.'</line>
            <line>It kept where I kept, I so dearly loved it;</line>
            <line>Till the rough seas, that spare not any man,</line>
            <line>Took it in rage, though calm'd have given't again:</line>
            <line>I thank thee for't: my shipwreck now's no ill,</line>
            <line>Since I have here my father's gift in's will.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Fisherman</speaker>
            <line>What mean you, sir?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERICLES</speaker>
            <line>To beg of you, kind friends, this coat of worth,</line>
            <line>For it was sometime target to a king;</line>
            <line>I know it by this mark. He loved me dearly,</line>
            <line>And for his sake I wish the having of it;</line>
            <line>And that you'ld guide me to your sovereign's court,</line>
            <line>Where with it I may appear a gentleman;</line>
            <line>And if that ever my low fortune's better,</line>
            <line>I'll pay your bounties; till then rest your debtor.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Fisherman</speaker>
            <line>Why, wilt thou tourney for the lady?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERICLES</speaker>
            <line>I'll show the virtue I have borne in arms.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Fisherman</speaker>
            <line>Why, do 'e take it, and the gods give thee good on't!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Fisherman</speaker>
            <line>Ay, but hark you, my friend; 'twas we that made up</line>
            <line>this garment through the rough seams of the waters:</line>
            <line>there are certain condolements, certain vails. I</line>
            <line>hope, sir, if you thrive, you'll remember from</line>
            <line>whence you had it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERICLES</speaker>
            <line>Believe 't, I will.</line>
            <line>By your furtherance I am clothed in steel;</line>
            <line>And, spite of all the rapture of the sea,</line>
            <line>This jewel holds his building on my arm:</line>
            <line>Unto thy value I will mount myself</line>
            <line>Upon a courser, whose delightful steps</line>
            <line>Shall make the gazer joy to see him tread.</line>
            <line>Only, my friend, I yet am unprovided</line>
            <line>Of a pair of bases.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Fisherman</speaker>
            <line>We'll sure provide: thou shalt have my best gown to</line>
            <line>make thee a pair; and I'll bring thee to the court myself.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERICLES</speaker>
            <line>Then honour be but a goal to my will,</line>
            <line>This day I'll rise, or else add ill to ill.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  The same. A public way or platform leading to the lists. A pavilion by the side of it for the reception of King, Princess, Lords, &amp;c.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter SIMONIDES, THAISA, Lords, and Attendants</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIMONIDES</speaker>
            <line>Are the knights ready to begin the triumph?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>They are, my liege;</line>
            <line>And stay your coming to present themselves.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIMONIDES</speaker>
            <line>Return them, we are ready; and our daughter,</line>
            <line>In honour of whose birth these triumphs are,</line>
            <line>Sits here, like beauty's child, whom nature gat</line>
            <line>For men to see, and seeing wonder at.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit a Lord</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THAISA</speaker>
            <line>It pleaseth you, my royal father, to express</line>
            <line>My commendations great, whose merit's less.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIMONIDES</speaker>
            <line>It's fit it should be so; for princes are</line>
            <line>A model which heaven makes like to itself:</line>
            <line>As jewels lose their glory if neglected,</line>
            <line>So princes their renowns if not respected.</line>
            <line>'Tis now your honour, daughter, to explain</line>
            <line>The labour of each knight in his device.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THAISA</speaker>
            <line>Which, to preserve mine honour, I'll perform.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter a Knight; he passes over, and his Squire
presents his shield to the Princess</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIMONIDES</speaker>
            <line>Who is the first that doth prefer himself?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THAISA</speaker>
            <line>A knight of Sparta, my renowned father;</line>
            <line>And the device he bears upon his shield</line>
            <line>Is a black Ethiope reaching at the sun</line>
            <line>The word, 'Lux tua vita mihi.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIMONIDES</speaker>
            <line>He loves you well that holds his life of you.</line>
            <stagedir>The Second Knight passes over</stagedir>
            <line>Who is the second that presents himself?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THAISA</speaker>
            <line>A prince of Macedon, my royal father;</line>
            <line>And the device he bears upon his shield</line>
            <line>Is an arm'd knight that's conquer'd by a lady;</line>
            <line>The motto thus, in Spanish, 'Piu por dulzura que por fuerza.'</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>The Third Knight passes over</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIMONIDES</speaker>
            <line>And what's the third?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THAISA</speaker>
            <line>The third of Antioch;</line>
            <line>And his device, a wreath of chivalry;</line>
            <line>The word, 'Me pompae provexit apex.'</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>The Fourth Knight passes over</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIMONIDES</speaker>
            <line>What is the fourth?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THAISA</speaker>
            <line>A burning torch that's turned upside down;</line>
            <line>The word, 'Quod me alit, me extinguit.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIMONIDES</speaker>
            <line>Which shows that beauty hath his power and will,</line>
            <line>Which can as well inflame as it can kill.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>The Fifth Knight passes over</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THAISA</speaker>
            <line>The fifth, an hand environed with clouds,</line>
            <line>Holding out gold that's by the touchstone tried;</line>
            <line>The motto thus, 'Sic spectanda fides.'</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>The Sixth Knight, PERICLES, passes over</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIMONIDES</speaker>
            <line>And what's</line>
            <line>The sixth and last, the which the knight himself</line>
            <line>With such a graceful courtesy deliver'd?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THAISA</speaker>
            <line>He seems to be a stranger; but his present is</line>
            <line>A wither'd branch, that's only green at top;</line>
            <line>The motto, 'In hac spe vivo.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIMONIDES</speaker>
            <line>A pretty moral;</line>
            <line>From the dejected state wherein he is,</line>
            <line>He hopes by you his fortunes yet may flourish.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>He had need mean better than his outward show</line>
            <line>Can any way speak in his just commend;</line>
            <line>For by his rusty outside he appears</line>
            <line>To have practised more the whipstock than the lance.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>He well may be a stranger, for he comes</line>
            <line>To an honour'd triumph strangely furnished.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Lord</speaker>
            <line>And on set purpose let his armour rust</line>
            <line>Until this day, to scour it in the dust.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIMONIDES</speaker>
            <line>Opinion's but a fool, that makes us scan</line>
            <line>The outward habit by the inward man.</line>
            <line>But stay, the knights are coming: we will withdraw</line>
            <line>Into the gallery.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Great shouts within and all cry 'The mean knight!'</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  The same. A hall of state: a banquet prepared.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter SIMONIDES, THAISA, Lords, Attendants, and
Knights, from tilting</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIMONIDES</speaker>
            <line>Knights,</line>
            <line>To say you're welcome were superfluous.</line>
            <line>To place upon the volume of your deeds,</line>
            <line>As in a title-page, your worth in arms,</line>
            <line>Were more than you expect, or more than's fit,</line>
            <line>Since every worth in show commends itself.</line>
            <line>Prepare for mirth, for mirth becomes a feast:</line>
            <line>You are princes and my guests.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THAISA</speaker>
            <line>But you, my knight and guest;</line>
            <line>To whom this wreath of victory I give,</line>
            <line>And crown you king of this day's happiness.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERICLES</speaker>
            <line>'Tis more by fortune, lady, than by merit.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIMONIDES</speaker>
            <line>Call it by what you will, the day is yours;</line>
            <line>And here, I hope, is none that envies it.</line>
            <line>In framing an artist, art hath thus decreed,</line>
            <line>To make some good, but others to exceed;</line>
            <line>And you are her labour'd scholar. Come, queen o'</line>
            <line>the feast,--</line>
            <line>For, daughter, so you are,--here take your place:</line>
            <line>Marshal the rest, as they deserve their grace.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KNIGHTS</speaker>
            <line>We are honour'd much by good Simonides.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIMONIDES</speaker>
            <line>Your presence glads our days: honour we love;</line>
            <line>For who hates honour hates the gods above.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Marshal</speaker>
            <line>Sir, yonder is your place.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERICLES</speaker>
            <line>Some other is more fit.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Knight</speaker>
            <line>Contend not, sir; for we are gentlemen</line>
            <line>That neither in our hearts nor outward eyes</line>
            <line>Envy the great nor do the low despise.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERICLES</speaker>
            <line>You are right courteous knights.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIMONIDES</speaker>
            <line>Sit, sir, sit.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERICLES</speaker>
            <line>By Jove, I wonder, that is king of thoughts,</line>
            <line>These cates resist me, she but thought upon.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THAISA</speaker>
            <line>By Juno, that is queen of marriage,</line>
            <line>All viands that I eat do seem unsavoury.</line>
            <line>Wishing him my meat. Sure, he's a gallant gentleman.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIMONIDES</speaker>
            <line>He's but a country gentleman;</line>
            <line>Has done no more than other knights have done;</line>
            <line>Has broken a staff or so; so let it pass.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THAISA</speaker>
            <line>To me he seems like diamond to glass.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERICLES</speaker>
            <line>Yon king's to me like to my father's picture,</line>
            <line>Which tells me in that glory once he was;</line>
            <line>Had princes sit, like stars, about his throne,</line>
            <line>And he the sun, for them to reverence;</line>
            <line>None that beheld him, but, like lesser lights,</line>
            <line>Did vail their crowns to his supremacy:</line>
            <line>Where now his son's like a glow-worm in the night,</line>
            <line>The which hath fire in darkness, none in light:</line>
            <line>Whereby I see that Time's the king of men,</line>
            <line>He's both their parent, and he is their grave,</line>
            <line>And gives them what he will, not what they crave.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIMONIDES</speaker>
            <line>What, are you merry, knights?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Knights</speaker>
            <line>Who can be other in this royal presence?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIMONIDES</speaker>
            <line>Here, with a cup that's stored unto the brim,--</line>
            <line>As you do love, fill to your mistress' lips,--</line>
            <line>We drink this health to you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>KNIGHTS</speaker>
            <line>We thank your grace.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIMONIDES</speaker>
            <line>Yet pause awhile:</line>
            <line>Yon knight doth sit too melancholy,</line>
            <line>As if the entertainment in our court</line>
            <line>Had not a show might countervail his worth.</line>
            <line>Note it not you, Thaisa?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THAISA</speaker>
            <line>What is it</line>
            <line>To me, my father?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIMONIDES</speaker>
            <line>O, attend, my daughter:</line>
            <line>Princes in this should live like gods above,</line>
            <line>Who freely give to every one that comes</line>
            <line>To honour them:</line>
            <line>And princes not doing so are like to gnats,</line>
            <line>Which make a sound, but kill'd are wonder'd at.</line>
            <line>Therefore to make his entrance more sweet,</line>
            <line>Here, say we drink this standing-bowl of wine to him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THAISA</speaker>
            <line>Alas, my father, it befits not me</line>
            <line>Unto a stranger knight to be so bold:</line>
            <line>He may my proffer take for an offence,</line>
            <line>Since men take women's gifts for impudence.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIMONIDES</speaker>
            <line>How!</line>
            <line>Do as I bid you, or you'll move me else.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THAISA</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  Now, by the gods, he could not please me better.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIMONIDES</speaker>
            <line>And furthermore tell him, we desire to know of him,</line>
            <line>Of whence he is, his name and parentage.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THAISA</speaker>
            <line>The king my father, sir, has drunk to you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERICLES</speaker>
            <line>I thank him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THAISA</speaker>
            <line>Wishing it so much blood unto your life.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERICLES</speaker>
            <line>I thank both him and you, and pledge him freely.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THAISA</speaker>
            <line>And further he desires to know of you,</line>
            <line>Of whence you are, your name and parentage.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERICLES</speaker>
            <line>A gentleman of Tyre; my name, Pericles;</line>
            <line>My education been in arts and arms;</line>
            <line>Who, looking for adventures in the world,</line>
            <line>Was by the rough seas reft of ships and men,</line>
            <line>And after shipwreck driven upon this shore.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THAISA</speaker>
            <line>He thanks your grace; names himself Pericles,</line>
            <line>A gentleman of Tyre,</line>
            <line>Who only by misfortune of the seas</line>
            <line>Bereft of ships and men, cast on this shore.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIMONIDES</speaker>
            <line>Now, by the gods, I pity his misfortune,</line>
            <line>And will awake him from his melancholy.</line>
            <line>Come, gentlemen, we sit too long on trifles,</line>
            <line>And waste the time, which looks for other revels.</line>
            <line>Even in your armours, as you are address'd,</line>
            <line>Will very well become a soldier's dance.</line>
            <line>I will not have excuse, with saying this</line>
            <line>Loud music is too harsh for ladies' heads,</line>
            <line>Since they love men in arms as well as beds.</line>
            <stagedir>The Knights dance</stagedir>
            <line>So, this was well ask'd,'twas so well perform'd.</line>
            <line>Come, sir;</line>
            <line>Here is a lady that wants breathing too:</line>
            <line>And I have heard, you knights of Tyre</line>
            <line>Are excellent in making ladies trip;</line>
            <line>And that their measures are as excellent.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERICLES</speaker>
            <line>In those that practise them they are, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIMONIDES</speaker>
            <line>O, that's as much as you would be denied</line>
            <line>Of your fair courtesy.</line>
            <stagedir>The Knights and Ladies dance</stagedir>
            <line>Unclasp, unclasp:</line>
            <line>Thanks, gentlemen, to all; all have done well.</line>
            <stagedir>To PERICLES</stagedir>
            <line>But you the best. Pages and lights, to conduct</line>
            <line>These knights unto their several lodgings!</line>
            <stagedir>To PERICLES</stagedir>
            <line>Yours, sir,</line>
            <line>We have given order to be next our own.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERICLES</speaker>
            <line>I am at your grace's pleasure.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIMONIDES</speaker>
            <line>Princes, it is too late to talk of love;</line>
            <line>And that's the mark I know you level at:</line>
            <line>Therefore each one betake him to his rest;</line>
            <line>To-morrow all for speeding do their best.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-4">
      <title>SCENE IV.  Tyre. A room in the Governor's house.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter HELICANUS and ESCANES</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELICANUS</speaker>
            <line>No, Escanes, know this of me,</line>
            <line>Antiochus from incest lived not free:</line>
            <line>For which, the most high gods not minding longer</line>
            <line>To withhold the vengeance that they had in store,</line>
            <line>Due to this heinous capital offence,</line>
            <line>Even in the height and pride of all his glory,</line>
            <line>When he was seated in a chariot</line>
            <line>Of an inestimable value, and his daughter with him,</line>
            <line>A fire from heaven came and shrivell'd up</line>
            <line>Their bodies, even to loathing; for they so stunk,</line>
            <line>That all those eyes adored them ere their fall</line>
            <line>Scorn now their hand should give them burial.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ESCANES</speaker>
            <line>'Twas very strange.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELICANUS</speaker>
            <line>And yet but justice; for though</line>
            <line>This king were great, his greatness was no guard</line>
            <line>To bar heaven's shaft, but sin had his reward.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ESCANES</speaker>
            <line>'Tis very true.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter two or three Lords</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>See, not a man in private conference</line>
            <line>Or council has respect with him but he.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>It shall no longer grieve without reproof.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Lord</speaker>
            <line>And cursed be he that will not second it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>Follow me, then. Lord Helicane, a word.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELICANUS</speaker>
            <line>With me? and welcome: happy day, my lords.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>Know that our griefs are risen to the top,</line>
            <line>And now at length they overflow their banks.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELICANUS</speaker>
            <line>Your griefs! for what? wrong not your prince you love.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>Wrong not yourself, then, noble Helicane;</line>
            <line>But if the prince do live, let us salute him,</line>
            <line>Or know what ground's made happy by his breath.</line>
            <line>If in the world he live, we'll seek him out;</line>
            <line>If in his grave he rest, we'll find him there;</line>
            <line>And be resolved he lives to govern us,</line>
            <line>Or dead, give's cause to mourn his funeral,</line>
            <line>And leave us to our free election.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lord</speaker>
            <line>Whose death indeed's the strongest in our censure:</line>
            <line>And knowing this kingdom is without a head,--</line>
            <line>Like goodly buildings left without a roof</line>
            <line>Soon fall to ruin,--your noble self,</line>
            <line>That best know how to rule and how to reign,</line>
            <line>We thus submit unto,--our sovereign.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>All</speaker>
            <line>Live, noble Helicane!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELICANUS</speaker>
            <line>For honour's cause, forbear your suffrages:</line>
            <line>If that you love Prince Pericles, forbear.</line>
            <line>Take I your wish, I leap into the seas,</line>
            <line>Where's hourly trouble for a minute's ease.</line>
            <line>A twelvemonth longer, let me entreat you to</line>
            <line>Forbear the absence of your king:</line>
            <line>If in which time expired, he not return,</line>
            <line>I shall with aged patience bear your yoke.</line>
            <line>But if I cannot win you to this love,</line>
            <line>Go search like nobles, like noble subjects,</line>
            <line>And in your search spend your adventurous worth;</line>
            <line>Whom if you find, and win unto return,</line>
            <line>You shall like diamonds sit about his crown.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>To wisdom he's a fool that will not yield;</line>
            <line>And since Lord Helicane enjoineth us,</line>
            <line>We with our travels will endeavour us.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HELICANUS</speaker>
            <line>Then you love us, we you, and we'll clasp hands:</line>
            <line>When peers thus knit, a kingdom ever stands.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-5">
      <title>SCENE V.  Pentapolis. A room in the palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter SIMONIDES, reading a letter, at one door:
the Knights meet him</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Knight</speaker>
            <line>Good morrow to the good Simonides.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIMONIDES</speaker>
            <line>Knights, from my daughter this I let you know,</line>
            <line>That for this twelvemonth she'll not undertake</line>
            <line>A married life.</line>
            <line>Her reason to herself is only known,</line>
            <line>Which yet from her by no means can I get.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Knight</speaker>
            <line>May we not get access to her, my lord?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIMONIDES</speaker>
            <line>'Faith, by no means; she has so strictly tied</line>
            <line>Her to her chamber, that 'tis impossible.</line>
            <line>One twelve moons more she'll wear Diana's livery;</line>
            <line>This by the eye of Cynthia hath she vow'd</line>
            <line>And on her virgin honour will not break it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Third Knight</speaker>
            <line>Loath to bid farewell, we take our leaves.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt Knights</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIMONIDES</speaker>
            <line>So,</line>
            <line>They are well dispatch'd; now to my daughter's letter:</line>
            <line>She tells me here, she'd wed the stranger knight,</line>
            <line>Or never more to view nor day nor light.</line>
            <line>'Tis well, mistress; your choice agrees with mine;</line>
            <line>I like that well: nay, how absolute she's in't,</line>
            <line>Not minding whether I dislike or no!</line>
            <line>Well, I do commend her choice;</line>
            <line>And will no longer have it be delay'd.</line>
            <line>Soft! here he comes: I must dissemble it.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter PERICLES</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERICLES</speaker>
            <line>All fortune to the good Simonides!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIMONIDES</speaker>
            <line>To you as much, sir! I am beholding to you</line>
            <line>For your sweet music this last night: I do</line>
            <line>Protest my ears were never better fed</line>
            <line>With such delightful pleasing harmony.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERICLES</speaker>
            <line>It is your grace's pleasure to commend;</line>
            <line>Not my desert.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIMONIDES</speaker>
            <line>Sir, you are music's master.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERICLES</speaker>
            <line>The worst of all her scholars, my good lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIMONIDES</speaker>
            <line>Let me ask you one thing:</line>
            <line>What do you think of my daughter, sir?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERICLES</speaker>
            <line>A most virtuous princess.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIMONIDES</speaker>
            <line>And she is fair too, is she not?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERICLES</speaker>
            <line>As a fair day in summer, wondrous fair.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIMONIDES</speaker>
            <line>Sir, my daughter thinks very well of you;</line>
            <line>Ay, so well, that you must be her master,</line>
            <line>And she will be your scholar: therefore look to it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERICLES</speaker>
            <line>I am unworthy for her schoolmaster.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIMONIDES</speaker>
            <line>She thinks not so; peruse this writing else.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERICLES</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  What's here?</line>
            <line>A letter, that she loves the knight of Tyre!</line>
            <line>'Tis the king's subtlety to have my life.</line>
            <line>O, seek not to entrap me, gracious lord,</line>
            <line>A stranger and distressed gentleman,</line>
            <line>That never aim'd so high to love your daughter,</line>
            <line>But bent all offices to honour her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIMONIDES</speaker>
            <line>Thou hast bewitch'd my daughter, and thou art</line>
            <line>A villain.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERICLES</speaker>
            <line>By the gods, I have not:</line>
            <line>Never did thought of mine levy offence;</line>
            <line>Nor never did my actions yet commence</line>
            <line>A deed might gain her love or your displeasure.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIMONIDES</speaker>
            <line>Traitor, thou liest.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERICLES</speaker>
            <line>Traitor!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIMONIDES</speaker>
            <line>Ay, traitor.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERICLES</speaker>
            <line>Even in his throat--unless it be the king--</line>
            <line>That calls me traitor, I return the lie.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIMONIDES</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  Now, by the gods, I do applaud his courage.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERICLES</speaker>
            <line>My actions are as noble as my thoughts,</line>
            <line>That never relish'd of a base descent.</line>
            <line>I came unto your court for honour's cause,</line>
            <line>And not to be a rebel to her state;</line>
            <line>And he that otherwise accounts of me,</line>
            <line>This sword shall prove he's honour's enemy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIMONIDES</speaker>
            <line>No?</line>
            <line>Here comes my daughter, she can witness it.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter THAISA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERICLES</speaker>
            <line>Then, as you are as virtuous as fair,</line>
            <line>Resolve your angry father, if my tongue</line>
            <line>Did ere solicit, or my hand subscribe</line>
            <line>To any syllable that made love to you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THAISA</speaker>
            <line>Why, sir, say if you had,</line>
            <line>Who takes offence at that would make me glad?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIMONIDES</speaker>
            <line>Yea, mistress, are you so peremptory?</line>
            <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>
            <line>I am glad on't with all my heart.--</line>
            <line>I'll tame you; I'll bring you in subjection.</line>
            <line>Will you, not having my consent,</line>
            <line>Bestow your love and your affections</line>
            <line>Upon a stranger?</line>
            <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>
            <line>who, for aught I know,</line>
            <line>May be, nor can I think the contrary,</line>
            <line>As great in blood as I myself.--</line>
            <line>Therefore hear you, mistress; either frame</line>
            <line>Your will to mine,--and you, sir, hear you,</line>
            <line>Either be ruled by me, or I will make you--</line>
            <line>Man and wife:</line>
            <line>Nay, come, your hands and lips must seal it too:</line>
            <line>And being join'd, I'll thus your hopes destroy;</line>
            <line>And for a further grief,--God give you joy!--</line>
            <line>What, are you both pleased?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>THAISA</speaker>
            <line>Yes, if you love me, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERICLES</speaker>
            <line>Even as my life, or blood that fosters it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIMONIDES</speaker>
            <line>What, are you both agreed?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>BOTH</speaker>
            <line>Yes, if it please your majesty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>SIMONIDES</speaker>
            <line>It pleaseth me so well, that I will see you wed;</line>
            <line>And then with what haste you can get you to bed.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>