<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net/doctypes/dita/shakespear/dtd/act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-1">
   <title>ACT I</title>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  Antechamber in LEONTES' palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter CAMILLO and ARCHIDAMUS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARCHIDAMUS</speaker>
            <line>If you shall chance, Camillo, to visit Bohemia, on</line>
            <line>the like occasion whereon my services are now on</line>
            <line>foot, you shall see, as I have said, great</line>
            <line>difference betwixt our Bohemia and your Sicilia.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>I think, this coming summer, the King of Sicilia</line>
            <line>means to pay Bohemia the visitation which he justly owes him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARCHIDAMUS</speaker>
            <line>Wherein our entertainment shall shame us we will be</line>
            <line>justified in our loves; for indeed--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>Beseech you,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARCHIDAMUS</speaker>
            <line>Verily, I speak it in the freedom of my knowledge:</line>
            <line>we cannot with such magnificence--in so rare--I know</line>
            <line>not what to say. We will give you sleepy drinks,</line>
            <line>that your senses, unintelligent of our insufficience,</line>
            <line>may, though they cannot praise us, as little accuse</line>
            <line>us.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>You pay a great deal too dear for what's given freely.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARCHIDAMUS</speaker>
            <line>Believe me, I speak as my understanding instructs me</line>
            <line>and as mine honesty puts it to utterance.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>Sicilia cannot show himself over-kind to Bohemia.</line>
            <line>They were trained together in their childhoods; and</line>
            <line>there rooted betwixt them then such an affection,</line>
            <line>which cannot choose but branch now. Since their</line>
            <line>more mature dignities and royal necessities made</line>
            <line>separation of their society, their encounters,</line>
            <line>though not personal, have been royally attorneyed</line>
            <line>with interchange of gifts, letters, loving</line>
            <line>embassies; that they have seemed to be together,</line>
            <line>though absent, shook hands, as over a vast, and</line>
            <line>embraced, as it were, from the ends of opposed</line>
            <line>winds. The heavens continue their loves!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARCHIDAMUS</speaker>
            <line>I think there is not in the world either malice or</line>
            <line>matter to alter it. You have an unspeakable</line>
            <line>comfort of your young prince Mamillius: it is a</line>
            <line>gentleman of the greatest promise that ever came</line>
            <line>into my note.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>I very well agree with you in the hopes of him: it</line>
            <line>is a gallant child; one that indeed physics the</line>
            <line>subject, makes old hearts fresh: they that went on</line>
            <line>crutches ere he was born desire yet their life to</line>
            <line>see him a man.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARCHIDAMUS</speaker>
            <line>Would they else be content to die?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>Yes; if there were no other excuse why they should</line>
            <line>desire to live.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ARCHIDAMUS</speaker>
            <line>If the king had no son, they would desire to live</line>
            <line>on crutches till he had one.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-1-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  A room of state in the same.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter LEONTES, HERMIONE, MAMILLIUS,
POLIXENES, CAMILLO, and Attendants</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POLIXENES</speaker>
            <line>Nine changes of the watery star hath been</line>
            <line>The shepherd's note since we have left our throne</line>
            <line>Without a burthen: time as long again</line>
            <line>Would be find up, my brother, with our thanks;</line>
            <line>And yet we should, for perpetuity,</line>
            <line>Go hence in debt: and therefore, like a cipher,</line>
            <line>Yet standing in rich place, I multiply</line>
            <line>With one 'We thank you' many thousands moe</line>
            <line>That go before it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>Stay your thanks a while;</line>
            <line>And pay them when you part.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POLIXENES</speaker>
            <line>Sir, that's to-morrow.</line>
            <line>I am question'd by my fears, of what may chance</line>
            <line>Or breed upon our absence; that may blow</line>
            <line>No sneaping winds at home, to make us say</line>
            <line>'This is put forth too truly:' besides, I have stay'd</line>
            <line>To tire your royalty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>We are tougher, brother,</line>
            <line>Than you can put us to't.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POLIXENES</speaker>
            <line>No longer stay.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>One seven-night longer.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POLIXENES</speaker>
            <line>Very sooth, to-morrow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>We'll part the time between's then; and in that</line>
            <line>I'll no gainsaying.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POLIXENES</speaker>
            <line>Press me not, beseech you, so.</line>
            <line>There is no tongue that moves, none, none i' the world,</line>
            <line>So soon as yours could win me: so it should now,</line>
            <line>Were there necessity in your request, although</line>
            <line>'Twere needful I denied it. My affairs</line>
            <line>Do even drag me homeward: which to hinder</line>
            <line>Were in your love a whip to me; my stay</line>
            <line>To you a charge and trouble: to save both,</line>
            <line>Farewell, our brother.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>Tongue-tied, our queen?</line>
            <line>speak you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERMIONE</speaker>
            <line>I had thought, sir, to have held my peace until</line>
            <line>You have drawn oaths from him not to stay. You, sir,</line>
            <line>Charge him too coldly. Tell him, you are sure</line>
            <line>All in Bohemia's well; this satisfaction</line>
            <line>The by-gone day proclaim'd: say this to him,</line>
            <line>He's beat from his best ward.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>Well said, Hermione.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERMIONE</speaker>
            <line>To tell, he longs to see his son, were strong:</line>
            <line>But let him say so then, and let him go;</line>
            <line>But let him swear so, and he shall not stay,</line>
            <line>We'll thwack him hence with distaffs.</line>
            <line>Yet of your royal presence I'll adventure</line>
            <line>The borrow of a week. When at Bohemia</line>
            <line>You take my lord, I'll give him my commission</line>
            <line>To let him there a month behind the gest</line>
            <line>Prefix'd for's parting: yet, good deed, Leontes,</line>
            <line>I love thee not a jar o' the clock behind</line>
            <line>What lady-she her lord. You'll stay?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POLIXENES</speaker>
            <line>No, madam.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERMIONE</speaker>
            <line>Nay, but you will?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POLIXENES</speaker>
            <line>I may not, verily.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERMIONE</speaker>
            <line>Verily!</line>
            <line>You put me off with limber vows; but I,</line>
            <line>Though you would seek to unsphere the</line>
            <line>stars with oaths,</line>
            <line>Should yet say 'Sir, no going.' Verily,</line>
            <line>You shall not go: a lady's 'Verily' 's</line>
            <line>As potent as a lord's. Will you go yet?</line>
            <line>Force me to keep you as a prisoner,</line>
            <line>Not like a guest; so you shall pay your fees</line>
            <line>When you depart, and save your thanks. How say you?</line>
            <line>My prisoner? or my guest? by your dread 'Verily,'</line>
            <line>One of them you shall be.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POLIXENES</speaker>
            <line>Your guest, then, madam:</line>
            <line>To be your prisoner should import offending;</line>
            <line>Which is for me less easy to commit</line>
            <line>Than you to punish.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERMIONE</speaker>
            <line>Not your gaoler, then,</line>
            <line>But your kind hostess. Come, I'll question you</line>
            <line>Of my lord's tricks and yours when you were boys:</line>
            <line>You were pretty lordings then?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POLIXENES</speaker>
            <line>We were, fair queen,</line>
            <line>Two lads that thought there was no more behind</line>
            <line>But such a day to-morrow as to-day,</line>
            <line>And to be boy eternal.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERMIONE</speaker>
            <line>Was not my lord</line>
            <line>The verier wag o' the two?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POLIXENES</speaker>
            <line>We were as twinn'd lambs that did frisk i' the sun,</line>
            <line>And bleat the one at the other: what we changed</line>
            <line>Was innocence for innocence; we knew not</line>
            <line>The doctrine of ill-doing, nor dream'd</line>
            <line>That any did. Had we pursued that life,</line>
            <line>And our weak spirits ne'er been higher rear'd</line>
            <line>With stronger blood, we should have answer'd heaven</line>
            <line>Boldly 'not guilty;' the imposition clear'd</line>
            <line>Hereditary ours.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERMIONE</speaker>
            <line>By this we gather</line>
            <line>You have tripp'd since.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POLIXENES</speaker>
            <line>O my most sacred lady!</line>
            <line>Temptations have since then been born to's; for</line>
            <line>In those unfledged days was my wife a girl;</line>
            <line>Your precious self had then not cross'd the eyes</line>
            <line>Of my young play-fellow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERMIONE</speaker>
            <line>Grace to boot!</line>
            <line>Of this make no conclusion, lest you say</line>
            <line>Your queen and I are devils: yet go on;</line>
            <line>The offences we have made you do we'll answer,</line>
            <line>If you first sinn'd with us and that with us</line>
            <line>You did continue fault and that you slipp'd not</line>
            <line>With any but with us.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>Is he won yet?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERMIONE</speaker>
            <line>He'll stay my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>At my request he would not.</line>
            <line>Hermione, my dearest, thou never spokest</line>
            <line>To better purpose.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERMIONE</speaker>
            <line>Never?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>Never, but once.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERMIONE</speaker>
            <line>What! have I twice said well? when was't before?</line>
            <line>I prithee tell me; cram's with praise, and make's</line>
            <line>As fat as tame things: one good deed dying tongueless</line>
            <line>Slaughters a thousand waiting upon that.</line>
            <line>Our praises are our wages: you may ride's</line>
            <line>With one soft kiss a thousand furlongs ere</line>
            <line>With spur we beat an acre. But to the goal:</line>
            <line>My last good deed was to entreat his stay:</line>
            <line>What was my first? it has an elder sister,</line>
            <line>Or I mistake you: O, would her name were Grace!</line>
            <line>But once before I spoke to the purpose: when?</line>
            <line>Nay, let me have't; I long.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>Why, that was when</line>
            <line>Three crabbed months had sour'd themselves to death,</line>
            <line>Ere I could make thee open thy white hand</line>
            <line>And clap thyself my love: then didst thou utter</line>
            <line>'I am yours for ever.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERMIONE</speaker>
            <line>'Tis grace indeed.</line>
            <line>Why, lo you now, I have spoke to the purpose twice:</line>
            <line>The one for ever earn'd a royal husband;</line>
            <line>The other for some while a friend.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir> Too hot, too hot!</line>
            <line>To mingle friendship far is mingling bloods.</line>
            <line>I have tremor cordis on me: my heart dances;</line>
            <line>But not for joy; not joy. This entertainment</line>
            <line>May a free face put on, derive a liberty</line>
            <line>From heartiness, from bounty, fertile bosom,</line>
            <line>And well become the agent; 't may, I grant;</line>
            <line>But to be paddling palms and pinching fingers,</line>
            <line>As now they are, and making practised smiles,</line>
            <line>As in a looking-glass, and then to sigh, as 'twere</line>
            <line>The mort o' the deer; O, that is entertainment</line>
            <line>My bosom likes not, nor my brows! Mamillius,</line>
            <line>Art thou my boy?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MAMILLIUS</speaker>
            <line>Ay, my good lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>I' fecks!</line>
            <line>Why, that's my bawcock. What, hast</line>
            <line>smutch'd thy nose?</line>
            <line>They say it is a copy out of mine. Come, captain,</line>
            <line>We must be neat; not neat, but cleanly, captain:</line>
            <line>And yet the steer, the heifer and the calf</line>
            <line>Are all call'd neat.--Still virginalling</line>
            <line>Upon his palm!--How now, you wanton calf!</line>
            <line>Art thou my calf?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MAMILLIUS</speaker>
            <line>Yes, if you will, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>Thou want'st a rough pash and the shoots that I have,</line>
            <line>To be full like me: yet they say we are</line>
            <line>Almost as like as eggs; women say so,</line>
            <line>That will say anything but were they false</line>
            <line>As o'er-dyed blacks, as wind, as waters, false</line>
            <line>As dice are to be wish'd by one that fixes</line>
            <line>No bourn 'twixt his and mine, yet were it true</line>
            <line>To say this boy were like me. Come, sir page,</line>
            <line>Look on me with your welkin eye: sweet villain!</line>
            <line>Most dear'st! my collop! Can thy dam?--may't be?--</line>
            <line>Affection! thy intention stabs the centre:</line>
            <line>Thou dost make possible things not so held,</line>
            <line>Communicatest with dreams;--how can this be?--</line>
            <line>With what's unreal thou coactive art,</line>
            <line>And fellow'st nothing: then 'tis very credent</line>
            <line>Thou mayst co-join with something; and thou dost,</line>
            <line>And that beyond commission, and I find it,</line>
            <line>And that to the infection of my brains</line>
            <line>And hardening of my brows.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POLIXENES</speaker>
            <line>What means Sicilia?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERMIONE</speaker>
            <line>He something seems unsettled.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POLIXENES</speaker>
            <line>How, my lord!</line>
            <line>What cheer? how is't with you, best brother?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERMIONE</speaker>
            <line>You look as if you held a brow of much distraction</line>
            <line>Are you moved, my lord?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>No, in good earnest.</line>
            <line>How sometimes nature will betray its folly,</line>
            <line>Its tenderness, and make itself a pastime</line>
            <line>To harder bosoms! Looking on the lines</line>
            <line>Of my boy's face, methoughts I did recoil</line>
            <line>Twenty-three years, and saw myself unbreech'd,</line>
            <line>In my green velvet coat, my dagger muzzled,</line>
            <line>Lest it should bite its master, and so prove,</line>
            <line>As ornaments oft do, too dangerous:</line>
            <line>How like, methought, I then was to this kernel,</line>
            <line>This squash, this gentleman. Mine honest friend,</line>
            <line>Will you take eggs for money?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MAMILLIUS</speaker>
            <line>No, my lord, I'll fight.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>You will! why, happy man be's dole! My brother,</line>
            <line>Are you so fond of your young prince as we</line>
            <line>Do seem to be of ours?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POLIXENES</speaker>
            <line>If at home, sir,</line>
            <line>He's all my exercise, my mirth, my matter,</line>
            <line>Now my sworn friend and then mine enemy,</line>
            <line>My parasite, my soldier, statesman, all:</line>
            <line>He makes a July's day short as December,</line>
            <line>And with his varying childness cures in me</line>
            <line>Thoughts that would thick my blood.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>So stands this squire</line>
            <line>Officed with me: we two will walk, my lord,</line>
            <line>And leave you to your graver steps. Hermione,</line>
            <line>How thou lovest us, show in our brother's welcome;</line>
            <line>Let what is dear in Sicily be cheap:</line>
            <line>Next to thyself and my young rover, he's</line>
            <line>Apparent to my heart.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERMIONE</speaker>
            <line>If you would seek us,</line>
            <line>We are yours i' the garden: shall's attend you there?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>To your own bents dispose you: you'll be found,</line>
            <line>Be you beneath the sky.</line>
            <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>
            <line>I am angling now,</line>
            <line>Though you perceive me not how I give line.</line>
            <line>Go to, go to!</line>
            <line>How she holds up the neb, the bill to him!</line>
            <line>And arms her with the boldness of a wife</line>
            <line>To her allowing husband!</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt POLIXENES, HERMIONE, and Attendants</stagedir>
            <line>Gone already!</line>
            <line>Inch-thick, knee-deep, o'er head and</line>
            <line>ears a fork'd one!</line>
            <line>Go, play, boy, play: thy mother plays, and I</line>
            <line>Play too, but so disgraced a part, whose issue</line>
            <line>Will hiss me to my grave: contempt and clamour</line>
            <line>Will be my knell. Go, play, boy, play.</line>
            <line>There have been,</line>
            <line>Or I am much deceived, cuckolds ere now;</line>
            <line>And many a man there is, even at this present,</line>
            <line>Now while I speak this, holds his wife by the arm,</line>
            <line>That little thinks she has been sluiced in's absence</line>
            <line>And his pond fish'd by his next neighbour, by</line>
            <line>Sir Smile, his neighbour: nay, there's comfort in't</line>
            <line>Whiles other men have gates and those gates open'd,</line>
            <line>As mine, against their will. Should all despair</line>
            <line>That have revolted wives, the tenth of mankind</line>
            <line>Would hang themselves. Physic for't there is none;</line>
            <line>It is a bawdy planet, that will strike</line>
            <line>Where 'tis predominant; and 'tis powerful, think it,</line>
            <line>From east, west, north and south: be it concluded,</line>
            <line>No barricado for a belly; know't;</line>
            <line>It will let in and out the enemy</line>
            <line>With bag and baggage: many thousand on's</line>
            <line>Have the disease, and feel't not. How now, boy!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MAMILLIUS</speaker>
            <line>I am like you, they say.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>Why that's some comfort. What, Camillo there?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>Ay, my good lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>Go play, Mamillius; thou'rt an honest man.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit MAMILLIUS</stagedir>
            <line>Camillo, this great sir will yet stay longer.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>You had much ado to make his anchor hold:</line>
            <line>When you cast out, it still came home.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>Didst note it?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>He would not stay at your petitions: made</line>
            <line>His business more material.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>Didst perceive it?</line>
            <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>
            <line>They're here with me already, whispering, rounding</line>
            <line>'Sicilia is a so-forth:' 'tis far gone,</line>
            <line>When I shall gust it last. How came't, Camillo,</line>
            <line>That he did stay?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>At the good queen's entreaty.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>At the queen's be't: 'good' should be pertinent</line>
            <line>But, so it is, it is not. Was this taken</line>
            <line>By any understanding pate but thine?</line>
            <line>For thy conceit is soaking, will draw in</line>
            <line>More than the common blocks: not noted, is't,</line>
            <line>But of the finer natures? by some severals</line>
            <line>Of head-piece extraordinary? lower messes</line>
            <line>Perchance are to this business purblind? say.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>Business, my lord! I think most understand</line>
            <line>Bohemia stays here longer.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>Ha!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>Stays here longer.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>Ay, but why?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>To satisfy your highness and the entreaties</line>
            <line>Of our most gracious mistress.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>Satisfy!</line>
            <line>The entreaties of your mistress! satisfy!</line>
            <line>Let that suffice. I have trusted thee, Camillo,</line>
            <line>With all the nearest things to my heart, as well</line>
            <line>My chamber-councils, wherein, priest-like, thou</line>
            <line>Hast cleansed my bosom, I from thee departed</line>
            <line>Thy penitent reform'd: but we have been</line>
            <line>Deceived in thy integrity, deceived</line>
            <line>In that which seems so.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>Be it forbid, my lord!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>To bide upon't, thou art not honest, or,</line>
            <line>If thou inclinest that way, thou art a coward,</line>
            <line>Which hoxes honesty behind, restraining</line>
            <line>From course required; or else thou must be counted</line>
            <line>A servant grafted in my serious trust</line>
            <line>And therein negligent; or else a fool</line>
            <line>That seest a game play'd home, the rich stake drawn,</line>
            <line>And takest it all for jest.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>My gracious lord,</line>
            <line>I may be negligent, foolish and fearful;</line>
            <line>In every one of these no man is free,</line>
            <line>But that his negligence, his folly, fear,</line>
            <line>Among the infinite doings of the world,</line>
            <line>Sometime puts forth. In your affairs, my lord,</line>
            <line>If ever I were wilful-negligent,</line>
            <line>It was my folly; if industriously</line>
            <line>I play'd the fool, it was my negligence,</line>
            <line>Not weighing well the end; if ever fearful</line>
            <line>To do a thing, where I the issue doubted,</line>
            <line>Where of the execution did cry out</line>
            <line>Against the non-performance, 'twas a fear</line>
            <line>Which oft infects the wisest: these, my lord,</line>
            <line>Are such allow'd infirmities that honesty</line>
            <line>Is never free of. But, beseech your grace,</line>
            <line>Be plainer with me; let me know my trespass</line>
            <line>By its own visage: if I then deny it,</line>
            <line>'Tis none of mine.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>Ha' not you seen, Camillo,--</line>
            <line>But that's past doubt, you have, or your eye-glass</line>
            <line>Is thicker than a cuckold's horn,--or heard,--</line>
            <line>For to a vision so apparent rumour</line>
            <line>Cannot be mute,--or thought,--for cogitation</line>
            <line>Resides not in that man that does not think,--</line>
            <line>My wife is slippery? If thou wilt confess,</line>
            <line>Or else be impudently negative,</line>
            <line>To have nor eyes nor ears nor thought, then say</line>
            <line>My wife's a hobby-horse, deserves a name</line>
            <line>As rank as any flax-wench that puts to</line>
            <line>Before her troth-plight: say't and justify't.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>I would not be a stander-by to hear</line>
            <line>My sovereign mistress clouded so, without</line>
            <line>My present vengeance taken: 'shrew my heart,</line>
            <line>You never spoke what did become you less</line>
            <line>Than this; which to reiterate were sin</line>
            <line>As deep as that, though true.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>Is whispering nothing?</line>
            <line>Is leaning cheek to cheek? is meeting noses?</line>
            <line>Kissing with inside lip? stopping the career</line>
            <line>Of laughing with a sigh?--a note infallible</line>
            <line>Of breaking honesty--horsing foot on foot?</line>
            <line>Skulking in corners? wishing clocks more swift?</line>
            <line>Hours, minutes? noon, midnight? and all eyes</line>
            <line>Blind with the pin and web but theirs, theirs only,</line>
            <line>That would unseen be wicked? is this nothing?</line>
            <line>Why, then the world and all that's in't is nothing;</line>
            <line>The covering sky is nothing; Bohemia nothing;</line>
            <line>My wife is nothing; nor nothing have these nothings,</line>
            <line>If this be nothing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>Good my lord, be cured</line>
            <line>Of this diseased opinion, and betimes;</line>
            <line>For 'tis most dangerous.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>Say it be, 'tis true.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>No, no, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>It is; you lie, you lie:</line>
            <line>I say thou liest, Camillo, and I hate thee,</line>
            <line>Pronounce thee a gross lout, a mindless slave,</line>
            <line>Or else a hovering temporizer, that</line>
            <line>Canst with thine eyes at once see good and evil,</line>
            <line>Inclining to them both: were my wife's liver</line>
            <line>Infected as her life, she would not live</line>
            <line>The running of one glass.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>Who does infect her?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>Why, he that wears her like a medal, hanging</line>
            <line>About his neck, Bohemia: who, if I</line>
            <line>Had servants true about me, that bare eyes</line>
            <line>To see alike mine honour as their profits,</line>
            <line>Their own particular thrifts, they would do that</line>
            <line>Which should undo more doing: ay, and thou,</line>
            <line>His cupbearer,--whom I from meaner form</line>
            <line>Have benched and reared to worship, who mayst see</line>
            <line>Plainly as heaven sees earth and earth sees heaven,</line>
            <line>How I am galled,--mightst bespice a cup,</line>
            <line>To give mine enemy a lasting wink;</line>
            <line>Which draught to me were cordial.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>Sir, my lord,</line>
            <line>I could do this, and that with no rash potion,</line>
            <line>But with a lingering dram that should not work</line>
            <line>Maliciously like poison: but I cannot</line>
            <line>Believe this crack to be in my dread mistress,</line>
            <line>So sovereignly being honourable.</line>
            <line>I have loved thee,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>Make that thy question, and go rot!</line>
            <line>Dost think I am so muddy, so unsettled,</line>
            <line>To appoint myself in this vexation, sully</line>
            <line>The purity and whiteness of my sheets,</line>
            <line>Which to preserve is sleep, which being spotted</line>
            <line>Is goads, thorns, nettles, tails of wasps,</line>
            <line>Give scandal to the blood o' the prince my son,</line>
            <line>Who I do think is mine and love as mine,</line>
            <line>Without ripe moving to't? Would I do this?</line>
            <line>Could man so blench?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>I must believe you, sir:</line>
            <line>I do; and will fetch off Bohemia for't;</line>
            <line>Provided that, when he's removed, your highness</line>
            <line>Will take again your queen as yours at first,</line>
            <line>Even for your son's sake; and thereby for sealing</line>
            <line>The injury of tongues in courts and kingdoms</line>
            <line>Known and allied to yours.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>Thou dost advise me</line>
            <line>Even so as I mine own course have set down:</line>
            <line>I'll give no blemish to her honour, none.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>My lord,</line>
            <line>Go then; and with a countenance as clear</line>
            <line>As friendship wears at feasts, keep with Bohemia</line>
            <line>And with your queen. I am his cupbearer:</line>
            <line>If from me he have wholesome beverage,</line>
            <line>Account me not your servant.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>This is all:</line>
            <line>Do't and thou hast the one half of my heart;</line>
            <line>Do't not, thou split'st thine own.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>I'll do't, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>I will seem friendly, as thou hast advised me.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>O miserable lady! But, for me,</line>
            <line>What case stand I in? I must be the poisoner</line>
            <line>Of good Polixenes; and my ground to do't</line>
            <line>Is the obedience to a master, one</line>
            <line>Who in rebellion with himself will have</line>
            <line>All that are his so too. To do this deed,</line>
            <line>Promotion follows. If I could find example</line>
            <line>Of thousands that had struck anointed kings</line>
            <line>And flourish'd after, I'ld not do't; but since</line>
            <line>Nor brass nor stone nor parchment bears not one,</line>
            <line>Let villany itself forswear't. I must</line>
            <line>Forsake the court: to do't, or no, is certain</line>
            <line>To me a break-neck. Happy star, reign now!</line>
            <line>Here comes Bohemia.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter POLIXENES</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POLIXENES</speaker>
            <line>This is strange: methinks</line>
            <line>My favour here begins to warp. Not speak?</line>
            <line>Good day, Camillo.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>Hail, most royal sir!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POLIXENES</speaker>
            <line>What is the news i' the court?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>None rare, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POLIXENES</speaker>
            <line>The king hath on him such a countenance</line>
            <line>As he had lost some province and a region</line>
            <line>Loved as he loves himself: even now I met him</line>
            <line>With customary compliment; when he,</line>
            <line>Wafting his eyes to the contrary and falling</line>
            <line>A lip of much contempt, speeds from me and</line>
            <line>So leaves me to consider what is breeding</line>
            <line>That changeth thus his manners.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>I dare not know, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POLIXENES</speaker>
            <line>How! dare not! do not. Do you know, and dare not?</line>
            <line>Be intelligent to me: 'tis thereabouts;</line>
            <line>For, to yourself, what you do know, you must.</line>
            <line>And cannot say, you dare not. Good Camillo,</line>
            <line>Your changed complexions are to me a mirror</line>
            <line>Which shows me mine changed too; for I must be</line>
            <line>A party in this alteration, finding</line>
            <line>Myself thus alter'd with 't.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>There is a sickness</line>
            <line>Which puts some of us in distemper, but</line>
            <line>I cannot name the disease; and it is caught</line>
            <line>Of you that yet are well.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POLIXENES</speaker>
            <line>How! caught of me!</line>
            <line>Make me not sighted like the basilisk:</line>
            <line>I have look'd on thousands, who have sped the better</line>
            <line>By my regard, but kill'd none so. Camillo,--</line>
            <line>As you are certainly a gentleman, thereto</line>
            <line>Clerk-like experienced, which no less adorns</line>
            <line>Our gentry than our parents' noble names,</line>
            <line>In whose success we are gentle,--I beseech you,</line>
            <line>If you know aught which does behove my knowledge</line>
            <line>Thereof to be inform'd, imprison't not</line>
            <line>In ignorant concealment.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>I may not answer.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POLIXENES</speaker>
            <line>A sickness caught of me, and yet I well!</line>
            <line>I must be answer'd. Dost thou hear, Camillo,</line>
            <line>I conjure thee, by all the parts of man</line>
            <line>Which honour does acknowledge, whereof the least</line>
            <line>Is not this suit of mine, that thou declare</line>
            <line>What incidency thou dost guess of harm</line>
            <line>Is creeping toward me; how far off, how near;</line>
            <line>Which way to be prevented, if to be;</line>
            <line>If not, how best to bear it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>Sir, I will tell you;</line>
            <line>Since I am charged in honour and by him</line>
            <line>That I think honourable: therefore mark my counsel,</line>
            <line>Which must be even as swiftly follow'd as</line>
            <line>I mean to utter it, or both yourself and me</line>
            <line>Cry lost, and so good night!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POLIXENES</speaker>
            <line>On, good Camillo.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>I am appointed him to murder you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POLIXENES</speaker>
            <line>By whom, Camillo?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>By the king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POLIXENES</speaker>
            <line>For what?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>He thinks, nay, with all confidence he swears,</line>
            <line>As he had seen't or been an instrument</line>
            <line>To vice you to't, that you have touch'd his queen</line>
            <line>Forbiddenly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POLIXENES</speaker>
            <line>O, then my best blood turn</line>
            <line>To an infected jelly and my name</line>
            <line>Be yoked with his that did betray the Best!</line>
            <line>Turn then my freshest reputation to</line>
            <line>A savour that may strike the dullest nostril</line>
            <line>Where I arrive, and my approach be shunn'd,</line>
            <line>Nay, hated too, worse than the great'st infection</line>
            <line>That e'er was heard or read!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>Swear his thought over</line>
            <line>By each particular star in heaven and</line>
            <line>By all their influences, you may as well</line>
            <line>Forbid the sea for to obey the moon</line>
            <line>As or by oath remove or counsel shake</line>
            <line>The fabric of his folly, whose foundation</line>
            <line>Is piled upon his faith and will continue</line>
            <line>The standing of his body.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POLIXENES</speaker>
            <line>How should this grow?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>I know not: but I am sure 'tis safer to</line>
            <line>Avoid what's grown than question how 'tis born.</line>
            <line>If therefore you dare trust my honesty,</line>
            <line>That lies enclosed in this trunk which you</line>
            <line>Shall bear along impawn'd, away to-night!</line>
            <line>Your followers I will whisper to the business,</line>
            <line>And will by twos and threes at several posterns</line>
            <line>Clear them o' the city. For myself, I'll put</line>
            <line>My fortunes to your service, which are here</line>
            <line>By this discovery lost. Be not uncertain;</line>
            <line>For, by the honour of my parents, I</line>
            <line>Have utter'd truth: which if you seek to prove,</line>
            <line>I dare not stand by; nor shall you be safer</line>
            <line>Than one condemn'd by the king's own mouth, thereon</line>
            <line>His execution sworn.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POLIXENES</speaker>
            <line>I do believe thee:</line>
            <line>I saw his heart in 's face. Give me thy hand:</line>
            <line>Be pilot to me and thy places shall</line>
            <line>Still neighbour mine. My ships are ready and</line>
            <line>My people did expect my hence departure</line>
            <line>Two days ago. This jealousy</line>
            <line>Is for a precious creature: as she's rare,</line>
            <line>Must it be great, and as his person's mighty,</line>
            <line>Must it be violent, and as he does conceive</line>
            <line>He is dishonour'd by a man which ever</line>
            <line>Profess'd to him, why, his revenges must</line>
            <line>In that be made more bitter. Fear o'ershades me:</line>
            <line>Good expedition be my friend, and comfort</line>
            <line>The gracious queen, part of his theme, but nothing</line>
            <line>Of his ill-ta'en suspicion! Come, Camillo;</line>
            <line>I will respect thee as a father if</line>
            <line>Thou bear'st my life off hence: let us avoid.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>It is in mine authority to command</line>
            <line>The keys of all the posterns: please your highness</line>
            <line>To take the urgent hour. Come, sir, away.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>