<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:shakespear:dtd:act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-2">
   <title>ACT II</title>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  A room in LEONTES' palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter HERMIONE, MAMILLIUS, and Ladies</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERMIONE</speaker>
            <line>Take the boy to you: he so troubles me,</line>
            <line>'Tis past enduring.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lady</speaker>
            <line>Come, my gracious lord,</line>
            <line>Shall I be your playfellow?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MAMILLIUS</speaker>
            <line>No, I'll none of you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lady</speaker>
            <line>Why, my sweet lord?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MAMILLIUS</speaker>
            <line>You'll kiss me hard and speak to me as if</line>
            <line>I were a baby still. I love you better.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lady</speaker>
            <line>And why so, my lord?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MAMILLIUS</speaker>
            <line>Not for because</line>
            <line>Your brows are blacker; yet black brows, they say,</line>
            <line>Become some women best, so that there be not</line>
            <line>Too much hair there, but in a semicircle</line>
            <line>Or a half-moon made with a pen.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lady</speaker>
            <line>Who taught you this?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MAMILLIUS</speaker>
            <line>I learnt it out of women's faces. Pray now</line>
            <line>What colour are your eyebrows?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lady</speaker>
            <line>Blue, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MAMILLIUS</speaker>
            <line>Nay, that's a mock: I have seen a lady's nose</line>
            <line>That has been blue, but not her eyebrows.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lady</speaker>
            <line>Hark ye;</line>
            <line>The queen your mother rounds apace: we shall</line>
            <line>Present our services to a fine new prince</line>
            <line>One of these days; and then you'ld wanton with us,</line>
            <line>If we would have you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Lady</speaker>
            <line>She is spread of late</line>
            <line>Into a goodly bulk: good time encounter her!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERMIONE</speaker>
            <line>What wisdom stirs amongst you? Come, sir, now</line>
            <line>I am for you again: pray you, sit by us,</line>
            <line>And tell 's a tale.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MAMILLIUS</speaker>
            <line>Merry or sad shall't be?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERMIONE</speaker>
            <line>As merry as you will.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MAMILLIUS</speaker>
            <line>A sad tale's best for winter: I have one</line>
            <line>Of sprites and goblins.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERMIONE</speaker>
            <line>Let's have that, good sir.</line>
            <line>Come on, sit down: come on, and do your best</line>
            <line>To fright me with your sprites; you're powerful at it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MAMILLIUS</speaker>
            <line>There was a man--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERMIONE</speaker>
            <line>Nay, come, sit down; then on.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MAMILLIUS</speaker>
            <line>Dwelt by a churchyard: I will tell it softly;</line>
            <line>Yond crickets shall not hear it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERMIONE</speaker>
            <line>Come on, then,</line>
            <line>And give't me in mine ear.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter LEONTES, with ANTIGONUS, Lords and others</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>Was he met there? his train? Camillo with him?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>Behind the tuft of pines I met them; never</line>
            <line>Saw I men scour so on their way: I eyed them</line>
            <line>Even to their ships.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>How blest am I</line>
            <line>In my just censure, in my true opinion!</line>
            <line>Alack, for lesser knowledge! how accursed</line>
            <line>In being so blest! There may be in the cup</line>
            <line>A spider steep'd, and one may drink, depart,</line>
            <line>And yet partake no venom, for his knowledge</line>
            <line>Is not infected: but if one present</line>
            <line>The abhorr'd ingredient to his eye, make known</line>
            <line>How he hath drunk, he cracks his gorge, his sides,</line>
            <line>With violent hefts. I have drunk,</line>
            <line>and seen the spider.</line>
            <line>Camillo was his help in this, his pander:</line>
            <line>There is a plot against my life, my crown;</line>
            <line>All's true that is mistrusted: that false villain</line>
            <line>Whom I employ'd was pre-employ'd by him:</line>
            <line>He has discover'd my design, and I</line>
            <line>Remain a pinch'd thing; yea, a very trick</line>
            <line>For them to play at will. How came the posterns</line>
            <line>So easily open?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>By his great authority;</line>
            <line>Which often hath no less prevail'd than so</line>
            <line>On your command.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>I know't too well.</line>
            <line>Give me the boy: I am glad you did not nurse him:</line>
            <line>Though he does bear some signs of me, yet you</line>
            <line>Have too much blood in him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERMIONE</speaker>
            <line>What is this? sport?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>Bear the boy hence; he shall not come about her;</line>
            <line>Away with him! and let her sport herself</line>
            <line>With that she's big with; for 'tis Polixenes</line>
            <line>Has made thee swell thus.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERMIONE</speaker>
            <line>But I'ld say he had not,</line>
            <line>And I'll be sworn you would believe my saying,</line>
            <line>Howe'er you lean to the nayward.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>You, my lords,</line>
            <line>Look on her, mark her well; be but about</line>
            <line>To say 'she is a goodly lady,' and</line>
            <line>The justice of your bearts will thereto add</line>
            <line>'Tis pity she's not honest, honourable:'</line>
            <line>Praise her but for this her without-door form,</line>
            <line>Which on my faith deserves high speech, and straight</line>
            <line>The shrug, the hum or ha, these petty brands</line>
            <line>That calumny doth use--O, I am out--</line>
            <line>That mercy does, for calumny will sear</line>
            <line>Virtue itself: these shrugs, these hums and ha's,</line>
            <line>When you have said 'she's goodly,' come between</line>
            <line>Ere you can say 'she's honest:' but be 't known,</line>
            <line>From him that has most cause to grieve it should be,</line>
            <line>She's an adulteress.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERMIONE</speaker>
            <line>Should a villain say so,</line>
            <line>The most replenish'd villain in the world,</line>
            <line>He were as much more villain: you, my lord,</line>
            <line>Do but mistake.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>You have mistook, my lady,</line>
            <line>Polixenes for Leontes: O thou thing!</line>
            <line>Which I'll not call a creature of thy place,</line>
            <line>Lest barbarism, making me the precedent,</line>
            <line>Should a like language use to all degrees</line>
            <line>And mannerly distinguishment leave out</line>
            <line>Betwixt the prince and beggar: I have said</line>
            <line>She's an adulteress; I have said with whom:</line>
            <line>More, she's a traitor and Camillo is</line>
            <line>A federary with her, and one that knows</line>
            <line>What she should shame to know herself</line>
            <line>But with her most vile principal, that she's</line>
            <line>A bed-swerver, even as bad as those</line>
            <line>That vulgars give bold'st titles, ay, and privy</line>
            <line>To this their late escape.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERMIONE</speaker>
            <line>No, by my life.</line>
            <line>Privy to none of this. How will this grieve you,</line>
            <line>When you shall come to clearer knowledge, that</line>
            <line>You thus have publish'd me! Gentle my lord,</line>
            <line>You scarce can right me throughly then to say</line>
            <line>You did mistake.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>No; if I mistake</line>
            <line>In those foundations which I build upon,</line>
            <line>The centre is not big enough to bear</line>
            <line>A school-boy's top. Away with her! to prison!</line>
            <line>He who shall speak for her is afar off guilty</line>
            <line>But that he speaks.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERMIONE</speaker>
            <line>There's some ill planet reigns:</line>
            <line>I must be patient till the heavens look</line>
            <line>With an aspect more favourable. Good my lords,</line>
            <line>I am not prone to weeping, as our sex</line>
            <line>Commonly are; the want of which vain dew</line>
            <line>Perchance shall dry your pities: but I have</line>
            <line>That honourable grief lodged here which burns</line>
            <line>Worse than tears drown: beseech you all, my lords,</line>
            <line>With thoughts so qualified as your charities</line>
            <line>Shall best instruct you, measure me; and so</line>
            <line>The king's will be perform'd!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>Shall I be heard?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERMIONE</speaker>
            <line>Who is't that goes with me? Beseech your highness,</line>
            <line>My women may be with me; for you see</line>
            <line>My plight requires it. Do not weep, good fools;</line>
            <line>There is no cause: when you shall know your mistress</line>
            <line>Has deserved prison, then abound in tears</line>
            <line>As I come out: this action I now go on</line>
            <line>Is for my better grace. Adieu, my lord:</line>
            <line>I never wish'd to see you sorry; now</line>
            <line>I trust I shall. My women, come; you have leave.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>Go, do our bidding; hence!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit HERMIONE, guarded; with Ladies</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>Beseech your highness, call the queen again.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIGONUS</speaker>
            <line>Be certain what you do, sir, lest your justice</line>
            <line>Prove violence; in the which three great ones suffer,</line>
            <line>Yourself, your queen, your son.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>For her, my lord,</line>
            <line>I dare my life lay down and will do't, sir,</line>
            <line>Please you to accept it, that the queen is spotless</line>
            <line>I' the eyes of heaven and to you; I mean,</line>
            <line>In this which you accuse her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIGONUS</speaker>
            <line>If it prove</line>
            <line>She's otherwise, I'll keep my stables where</line>
            <line>I lodge my wife; I'll go in couples with her;</line>
            <line>Than when I feel and see her no farther trust her;</line>
            <line>For every inch of woman in the world,</line>
            <line>Ay, every dram of woman's flesh is false, If she be.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>Hold your peaces.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>Good my lord,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIGONUS</speaker>
            <line>It is for you we speak, not for ourselves:</line>
            <line>You are abused and by some putter-on</line>
            <line>That will be damn'd for't; would I knew the villain,</line>
            <line>I would land-damn him. Be she honour-flaw'd,</line>
            <line>I have three daughters; the eldest is eleven</line>
            <line>The second and the third, nine, and some five;</line>
            <line>If this prove true, they'll pay for't:</line>
            <line>by mine honour,</line>
            <line>I'll geld 'em all; fourteen they shall not see,</line>
            <line>To bring false generations: they are co-heirs;</line>
            <line>And I had rather glib myself than they</line>
            <line>Should not produce fair issue.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>Cease; no more.</line>
            <line>You smell this business with a sense as cold</line>
            <line>As is a dead man's nose: but I do see't and feel't</line>
            <line>As you feel doing thus; and see withal</line>
            <line>The instruments that feel.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIGONUS</speaker>
            <line>If it be so,</line>
            <line>We need no grave to bury honesty:</line>
            <line>There's not a grain of it the face to sweeten</line>
            <line>Of the whole dungy earth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>What! lack I credit?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>I had rather you did lack than I, my lord,</line>
            <line>Upon this ground; and more it would content me</line>
            <line>To have her honour true than your suspicion,</line>
            <line>Be blamed for't how you might.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>Why, what need we</line>
            <line>Commune with you of this, but rather follow</line>
            <line>Our forceful instigation? Our prerogative</line>
            <line>Calls not your counsels, but our natural goodness</line>
            <line>Imparts this; which if you, or stupefied</line>
            <line>Or seeming so in skill, cannot or will not</line>
            <line>Relish a truth like us, inform yourselves</line>
            <line>We need no more of your advice: the matter,</line>
            <line>The loss, the gain, the ordering on't, is all</line>
            <line>Properly ours.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIGONUS</speaker>
            <line>And I wish, my liege,</line>
            <line>You had only in your silent judgment tried it,</line>
            <line>Without more overture.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>How could that be?</line>
            <line>Either thou art most ignorant by age,</line>
            <line>Or thou wert born a fool. Camillo's flight,</line>
            <line>Added to their familiarity,</line>
            <line>Which was as gross as ever touch'd conjecture,</line>
            <line>That lack'd sight only, nought for approbation</line>
            <line>But only seeing, all other circumstances</line>
            <line>Made up to the deed, doth push on this proceeding:</line>
            <line>Yet, for a greater confirmation,</line>
            <line>For in an act of this importance 'twere</line>
            <line>Most piteous to be wild, I have dispatch'd in post</line>
            <line>To sacred Delphos, to Apollo's temple,</line>
            <line>Cleomenes and Dion, whom you know</line>
            <line>Of stuff'd sufficiency: now from the oracle</line>
            <line>They will bring all; whose spiritual counsel had,</line>
            <line>Shall stop or spur me. Have I done well?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>Well done, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>Though I am satisfied and need no more</line>
            <line>Than what I know, yet shall the oracle</line>
            <line>Give rest to the minds of others, such as he</line>
            <line>Whose ignorant credulity will not</line>
            <line>Come up to the truth. So have we thought it good</line>
            <line>From our free person she should be confined,</line>
            <line>Lest that the treachery of the two fled hence</line>
            <line>Be left her to perform. Come, follow us;</line>
            <line>We are to speak in public; for this business</line>
            <line>Will raise us all.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIGONUS</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>
            </line>
            <line>To laughter, as I take it,</line>
            <line>If the good truth were known.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  A prison.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter PAULINA, a Gentleman, and Attendants</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAULINA</speaker>
            <line>The keeper of the prison, call to him;</line>
            <line>let him have knowledge who I am.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit Gentleman</stagedir>
            <line>Good lady,</line>
            <line>No court in Europe is too good for thee;</line>
            <line>What dost thou then in prison?</line>
            <stagedir>Re-enter Gentleman, with the Gaoler</stagedir>
            <line>Now, good sir,</line>
            <line>You know me, do you not?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Gaoler</speaker>
            <line>For a worthy lady</line>
            <line>And one whom much I honour.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAULINA</speaker>
            <line>Pray you then,</line>
            <line>Conduct me to the queen.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Gaoler</speaker>
            <line>I may not, madam:</line>
            <line>To the contrary I have express commandment.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAULINA</speaker>
            <line>Here's ado,</line>
            <line>To lock up honesty and honour from</line>
            <line>The access of gentle visitors!</line>
            <line>Is't lawful, pray you,</line>
            <line>To see her women? any of them? Emilia?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Gaoler</speaker>
            <line>So please you, madam,</line>
            <line>To put apart these your attendants, I</line>
            <line>Shall bring Emilia forth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAULINA</speaker>
            <line>I pray now, call her.</line>
            <line>Withdraw yourselves.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt Gentleman and Attendants</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Gaoler</speaker>
            <line>And, madam,</line>
            <line>I must be present at your conference.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAULINA</speaker>
            <line>Well, be't so, prithee.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit Gaoler</stagedir>
            <line>Here's such ado to make no stain a stain</line>
            <line>As passes colouring.</line>
            <stagedir>Re-enter Gaoler, with EMILIA</stagedir>
            <line>Dear gentlewoman,</line>
            <line>How fares our gracious lady?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EMILIA</speaker>
            <line>As well as one so great and so forlorn</line>
            <line>May hold together: on her frights and griefs,</line>
            <line>Which never tender lady hath born greater,</line>
            <line>She is something before her time deliver'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAULINA</speaker>
            <line>A boy?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EMILIA</speaker>
            <line>A daughter, and a goodly babe,</line>
            <line>Lusty and like to live: the queen receives</line>
            <line>Much comfort in't; says 'My poor prisoner,</line>
            <line>I am innocent as you.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAULINA</speaker>
            <line>I dare be sworn</line>
            <line>These dangerous unsafe lunes i' the king,</line>
            <line>beshrew them!</line>
            <line>He must be told on't, and he shall: the office</line>
            <line>Becomes a woman best; I'll take't upon me:</line>
            <line>If I prove honey-mouth'd let my tongue blister</line>
            <line>And never to my red-look'd anger be</line>
            <line>The trumpet any more. Pray you, Emilia,</line>
            <line>Commend my best obedience to the queen:</line>
            <line>If she dares trust me with her little babe,</line>
            <line>I'll show't the king and undertake to be</line>
            <line>Her advocate to the loud'st. We do not know</line>
            <line>How he may soften at the sight o' the child:</line>
            <line>The silence often of pure innocence</line>
            <line>Persuades when speaking fails.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EMILIA</speaker>
            <line>Most worthy madam,</line>
            <line>Your honour and your goodness is so evident</line>
            <line>That your free undertaking cannot miss</line>
            <line>A thriving issue: there is no lady living</line>
            <line>So meet for this great errand. Please your ladyship</line>
            <line>To visit the next room, I'll presently</line>
            <line>Acquaint the queen of your most noble offer;</line>
            <line>Who but to-day hammer'd of this design,</line>
            <line>But durst not tempt a minister of honour,</line>
            <line>Lest she should be denied.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAULINA</speaker>
            <line>Tell her, Emilia.</line>
            <line>I'll use that tongue I have: if wit flow from't</line>
            <line>As boldness from my bosom, let 't not be doubted</line>
            <line>I shall do good.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>EMILIA</speaker>
            <line>Now be you blest for it!</line>
            <line>I'll to the queen: please you,</line>
            <line>come something nearer.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Gaoler</speaker>
            <line>Madam, if't please the queen to send the babe,</line>
            <line>I know not what I shall incur to pass it,</line>
            <line>Having no warrant.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAULINA</speaker>
            <line>You need not fear it, sir:</line>
            <line>This child was prisoner to the womb and is</line>
            <line>By law and process of great nature thence</line>
            <line>Freed and enfranchised, not a party to</line>
            <line>The anger of the king nor guilty of,</line>
            <line>If any be, the trespass of the queen.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Gaoler</speaker>
            <line>I do believe it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAULINA</speaker>
            <line>Do not you fear: upon mine honour,</line>
            <line>I will stand betwixt you and danger.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-2-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  A room in LEONTES' palace.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter LEONTES, ANTIGONUS, Lords, and Servants</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>Nor night nor day no rest: it is but weakness</line>
            <line>To bear the matter thus; mere weakness. If</line>
            <line>The cause were not in being,--part o' the cause,</line>
            <line>She the adulteress; for the harlot king</line>
            <line>Is quite beyond mine arm, out of the blank</line>
            <line>And level of my brain, plot-proof; but she</line>
            <line>I can hook to me: say that she were gone,</line>
            <line>Given to the fire, a moiety of my rest</line>
            <line>Might come to me again. Who's there?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Servant</speaker>
            <line>My lord?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>How does the boy?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Servant</speaker>
            <line>He took good rest to-night;</line>
            <line>'Tis hoped his sickness is discharged.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>To see his nobleness!</line>
            <line>Conceiving the dishonour of his mother,</line>
            <line>He straight declined, droop'd, took it deeply,</line>
            <line>Fasten'd and fix'd the shame on't in himself,</line>
            <line>Threw off his spirit, his appetite, his sleep,</line>
            <line>And downright languish'd. Leave me solely: go,</line>
            <line>See how he fares.</line>
            <stagedir>Exit Servant</stagedir>
            <line>Fie, fie! no thought of him:</line>
            <line>The thought of my revenges that way</line>
            <line>Recoil upon me: in himself too mighty,</line>
            <line>And in his parties, his alliance; let him be</line>
            <line>Until a time may serve: for present vengeance,</line>
            <line>Take it on her. Camillo and Polixenes</line>
            <line>Laugh at me, make their pastime at my sorrow:</line>
            <line>They should not laugh if I could reach them, nor</line>
            <line>Shall she within my power.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter PAULINA, with a child</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>You must not enter.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAULINA</speaker>
            <line>Nay, rather, good my lords, be second to me:</line>
            <line>Fear you his tyrannous passion more, alas,</line>
            <line>Than the queen's life? a gracious innocent soul,</line>
            <line>More free than he is jealous.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIGONUS</speaker>
            <line>That's enough.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Second Servant</speaker>
            <line>Madam, he hath not slept tonight; commanded</line>
            <line>None should come at him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAULINA</speaker>
            <line>Not so hot, good sir:</line>
            <line>I come to bring him sleep. 'Tis such as you,</line>
            <line>That creep like shadows by him and do sigh</line>
            <line>At each his needless heavings, such as you</line>
            <line>Nourish the cause of his awaking: I</line>
            <line>Do come with words as medicinal as true,</line>
            <line>Honest as either, to purge him of that humour</line>
            <line>That presses him from sleep.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>What noise there, ho?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAULINA</speaker>
            <line>No noise, my lord; but needful conference</line>
            <line>About some gossips for your highness.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>How!</line>
            <line>Away with that audacious lady! Antigonus,</line>
            <line>I charged thee that she should not come about me:</line>
            <line>I knew she would.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIGONUS</speaker>
            <line>I told her so, my lord,</line>
            <line>On your displeasure's peril and on mine,</line>
            <line>She should not visit you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>What, canst not rule her?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAULINA</speaker>
            <line>From all dishonesty he can: in this,</line>
            <line>Unless he take the course that you have done,</line>
            <line>Commit me for committing honour, trust it,</line>
            <line>He shall not rule me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIGONUS</speaker>
            <line>La you now, you hear:</line>
            <line>When she will take the rein I let her run;</line>
            <line>But she'll not stumble.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAULINA</speaker>
            <line>Good my liege, I come;</line>
            <line>And, I beseech you, hear me, who profess</line>
            <line>Myself your loyal servant, your physician,</line>
            <line>Your most obedient counsellor, yet that dare</line>
            <line>Less appear so in comforting your evils,</line>
            <line>Than such as most seem yours: I say, I come</line>
            <line>From your good queen.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>Good queen!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAULINA</speaker>
            <line>Good queen, my lord,</line>
            <line>Good queen; I say good queen;</line>
            <line>And would by combat make her good, so were I</line>
            <line>A man, the worst about you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>Force her hence.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAULINA</speaker>
            <line>Let him that makes but trifles of his eyes</line>
            <line>First hand me: on mine own accord I'll off;</line>
            <line>But first I'll do my errand. The good queen,</line>
            <line>For she is good, hath brought you forth a daughter;</line>
            <line>Here 'tis; commends it to your blessing.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Laying down the child</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>Out!</line>
            <line>A mankind witch! Hence with her, out o' door:</line>
            <line>A most intelligencing bawd!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAULINA</speaker>
            <line>Not so:</line>
            <line>I am as ignorant in that as you</line>
            <line>In so entitling me, and no less honest</line>
            <line>Than you are mad; which is enough, I'll warrant,</line>
            <line>As this world goes, to pass for honest.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>Traitors!</line>
            <line>Will you not push her out? Give her the bastard.</line>
            <line>Thou dotard! thou art woman-tired, unroosted</line>
            <line>By thy dame Partlet here. Take up the bastard;</line>
            <line>Take't up, I say; give't to thy crone.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAULINA</speaker>
            <line>For ever</line>
            <line>Unvenerable be thy hands, if thou</line>
            <line>Takest up the princess by that forced baseness</line>
            <line>Which he has put upon't!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>He dreads his wife.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAULINA</speaker>
            <line>So I would you did; then 'twere past all doubt</line>
            <line>You'ld call your children yours.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>A nest of traitors!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIGONUS</speaker>
            <line>I am none, by this good light.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAULINA</speaker>
            <line>Nor I, nor any</line>
            <line>But one that's here, and that's himself, for he</line>
            <line>The sacred honour of himself, his queen's,</line>
            <line>His hopeful son's, his babe's, betrays to slander,</line>
            <line>Whose sting is sharper than the sword's;</line>
            <line>and will not--</line>
            <line>For, as the case now stands, it is a curse</line>
            <line>He cannot be compell'd to't--once remove</line>
            <line>The root of his opinion, which is rotten</line>
            <line>As ever oak or stone was sound.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>A callat</line>
            <line>Of boundless tongue, who late hath beat her husband</line>
            <line>And now baits me! This brat is none of mine;</line>
            <line>It is the issue of Polixenes:</line>
            <line>Hence with it, and together with the dam</line>
            <line>Commit them to the fire!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAULINA</speaker>
            <line>It is yours;</line>
            <line>And, might we lay the old proverb to your charge,</line>
            <line>So like you, 'tis the worse. Behold, my lords,</line>
            <line>Although the print be little, the whole matter</line>
            <line>And copy of the father, eye, nose, lip,</line>
            <line>The trick of's frown, his forehead, nay, the valley,</line>
            <line>The pretty dimples of his chin and cheek,</line>
            <line>His smiles,</line>
            <line>The very mould and frame of hand, nail, finger:</line>
            <line>And thou, good goddess Nature, which hast made it</line>
            <line>So like to him that got it, if thou hast</line>
            <line>The ordering of the mind too, 'mongst all colours</line>
            <line>No yellow in't, lest she suspect, as he does,</line>
            <line>Her children not her husband's!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>A gross hag</line>
            <line>And, lozel, thou art worthy to be hang'd,</line>
            <line>That wilt not stay her tongue.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIGONUS</speaker>
            <line>Hang all the husbands</line>
            <line>That cannot do that feat, you'll leave yourself</line>
            <line>Hardly one subject.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>Once more, take her hence.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAULINA</speaker>
            <line>A most unworthy and unnatural lord</line>
            <line>Can do no more.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>I'll ha' thee burnt.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAULINA</speaker>
            <line>I care not:</line>
            <line>It is an heretic that makes the fire,</line>
            <line>Not she which burns in't. I'll not call you tyrant;</line>
            <line>But this most cruel usage of your queen,</line>
            <line>Not able to produce more accusation</line>
            <line>Than your own weak-hinged fancy, something savours</line>
            <line>Of tyranny and will ignoble make you,</line>
            <line>Yea, scandalous to the world.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>On your allegiance,</line>
            <line>Out of the chamber with her! Were I a tyrant,</line>
            <line>Where were her life? she durst not call me so,</line>
            <line>If she did know me one. Away with her!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAULINA</speaker>
            <line>I pray you, do not push me; I'll be gone.</line>
            <line>Look to your babe, my lord; 'tis yours:</line>
            <line>Jove send her</line>
            <line>A better guiding spirit! What needs these hands?</line>
            <line>You, that are thus so tender o'er his follies,</line>
            <line>Will never do him good, not one of you.</line>
            <line>So, so: farewell; we are gone.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>Thou, traitor, hast set on thy wife to this.</line>
            <line>My child? away with't! Even thou, that hast</line>
            <line>A heart so tender o'er it, take it hence</line>
            <line>And see it instantly consumed with fire;</line>
            <line>Even thou and none but thou. Take it up straight:</line>
            <line>Within this hour bring me word 'tis done,</line>
            <line>And by good testimony, or I'll seize thy life,</line>
            <line>With what thou else call'st thine. If thou refuse</line>
            <line>And wilt encounter with my wrath, say so;</line>
            <line>The bastard brains with these my proper hands</line>
            <line>Shall I dash out. Go, take it to the fire;</line>
            <line>For thou set'st on thy wife.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIGONUS</speaker>
            <line>I did not, sir:</line>
            <line>These lords, my noble fellows, if they please,</line>
            <line>Can clear me in't.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lords</speaker>
            <line>We can: my royal liege,</line>
            <line>He is not guilty of her coming hither.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>You're liars all.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>Beseech your highness, give us better credit:</line>
            <line>We have always truly served you, and beseech you</line>
            <line>So to esteem of us, and on our knees we beg,</line>
            <line>As recompense of our dear services</line>
            <line>Past and to come, that you do change this purpose,</line>
            <line>Which being so horrible, so bloody, must</line>
            <line>Lead on to some foul issue: we all kneel.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>I am a feather for each wind that blows:</line>
            <line>Shall I live on to see this bastard kneel</line>
            <line>And call me father? better burn it now</line>
            <line>Than curse it then. But be it; let it live.</line>
            <line>It shall not neither. You, sir, come you hither;</line>
            <line>You that have been so tenderly officious</line>
            <line>With Lady Margery, your midwife there,</line>
            <line>To save this bastard's life,--for 'tis a bastard,</line>
            <line>So sure as this beard's grey,</line>
            <line>--what will you adventure</line>
            <line>To save this brat's life?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIGONUS</speaker>
            <line>Any thing, my lord,</line>
            <line>That my ability may undergo</line>
            <line>And nobleness impose: at least thus much:</line>
            <line>I'll pawn the little blood which I have left</line>
            <line>To save the innocent: any thing possible.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>It shall be possible. Swear by this sword</line>
            <line>Thou wilt perform my bidding.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIGONUS</speaker>
            <line>I will, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>Mark and perform it, see'st thou! for the fail</line>
            <line>Of any point in't shall not only be</line>
            <line>Death to thyself but to thy lewd-tongued wife,</line>
            <line>Whom for this time we pardon. We enjoin thee,</line>
            <line>As thou art liege-man to us, that thou carry</line>
            <line>This female bastard hence and that thou bear it</line>
            <line>To some remote and desert place quite out</line>
            <line>Of our dominions, and that there thou leave it,</line>
            <line>Without more mercy, to its own protection</line>
            <line>And favour of the climate. As by strange fortune</line>
            <line>It came to us, I do in justice charge thee,</line>
            <line>On thy soul's peril and thy body's torture,</line>
            <line>That thou commend it strangely to some place</line>
            <line>Where chance may nurse or end it. Take it up.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIGONUS</speaker>
            <line>I swear to do this, though a present death</line>
            <line>Had been more merciful. Come on, poor babe:</line>
            <line>Some powerful spirit instruct the kites and ravens</line>
            <line>To be thy nurses! Wolves and bears, they say</line>
            <line>Casting their savageness aside have done</line>
            <line>Like offices of pity. Sir, be prosperous</line>
            <line>In more than this deed does require! And blessing</line>
            <line>Against this cruelty fight on thy side,</line>
            <line>Poor thing, condemn'd to loss!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit with the child</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>No, I'll not rear</line>
            <line>Another's issue.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter a Servant</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>Please your highness, posts</line>
            <line>From those you sent to the oracle are come</line>
            <line>An hour since: Cleomenes and Dion,</line>
            <line>Being well arrived from Delphos, are both landed,</line>
            <line>Hasting to the court.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>So please you, sir, their speed</line>
            <line>Hath been beyond account.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>Twenty-three days</line>
            <line>They have been absent: 'tis good speed; foretells</line>
            <line>The great Apollo suddenly will have</line>
            <line>The truth of this appear. Prepare you, lords;</line>
            <line>Summon a session, that we may arraign</line>
            <line>Our most disloyal lady, for, as she hath</line>
            <line>Been publicly accused, so shall she have</line>
            <line>A just and open trial. While she lives</line>
            <line>My heart will be a burthen to me. Leave me,</line>
            <line>And think upon my bidding.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>