<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:shakespear:dtd:act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-3">
   <title>ACT III</title>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I.  A sea-port in Sicilia.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter CLEOMENES and DION</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLEOMENES</speaker>
            <line>The climate's delicate, the air most sweet,</line>
            <line>Fertile the isle, the temple much surpassing</line>
            <line>The common praise it bears.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DION</speaker>
            <line>I shall report,</line>
            <line>For most it caught me, the celestial habits,</line>
            <line>Methinks I so should term them, and the reverence</line>
            <line>Of the grave wearers. O, the sacrifice!</line>
            <line>How ceremonious, solemn and unearthly</line>
            <line>It was i' the offering!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLEOMENES</speaker>
            <line>But of all, the burst</line>
            <line>And the ear-deafening voice o' the oracle,</line>
            <line>Kin to Jove's thunder, so surprised my sense.</line>
            <line>That I was nothing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DION</speaker>
            <line>If the event o' the journey</line>
            <line>Prove as successful to the queen,--O be't so!--</line>
            <line>As it hath been to us rare, pleasant, speedy,</line>
            <line>The time is worth the use on't.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLEOMENES</speaker>
            <line>Great Apollo</line>
            <line>Turn all to the best! These proclamations,</line>
            <line>So forcing faults upon Hermione,</line>
            <line>I little like.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DION</speaker>
            <line>The violent carriage of it</line>
            <line>Will clear or end the business: when the oracle,</line>
            <line>Thus by Apollo's great divine seal'd up,</line>
            <line>Shall the contents discover, something rare</line>
            <line>Even then will rush to knowledge. Go: fresh horses!</line>
            <line>And gracious be the issue!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  A court of Justice.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter LEONTES, Lords, and Officers</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>This sessions, to our great grief we pronounce,</line>
            <line>Even pushes 'gainst our heart: the party tried</line>
            <line>The daughter of a king, our wife, and one</line>
            <line>Of us too much beloved. Let us be clear'd</line>
            <line>Of being tyrannous, since we so openly</line>
            <line>Proceed in justice, which shall have due course,</line>
            <line>Even to the guilt or the purgation.</line>
            <line>Produce the prisoner.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Officer</speaker>
            <line>It is his highness' pleasure that the queen</line>
            <line>Appear in person here in court. Silence!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter HERMIONE guarded;
PAULINA and Ladies attending</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>Read the indictment.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Officer</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Reads</stagedir>            Hermione, queen to the worthy</line>
            <line>Leontes, king of Sicilia, thou art here accused and</line>
            <line>arraigned of high treason, in committing adultery</line>
            <line>with Polixenes, king of Bohemia, and conspiring</line>
            <line>with Camillo to take away the life of our sovereign</line>
            <line>lord the king, thy royal husband: the pretence</line>
            <line>whereof being by circumstances partly laid open,</line>
            <line>thou, Hermione, contrary to the faith and allegiance</line>
            <line>of a true subject, didst counsel and aid them, for</line>
            <line>their better safety, to fly away by night.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERMIONE</speaker>
            <line>Since what I am to say must be but that</line>
            <line>Which contradicts my accusation and</line>
            <line>The testimony on my part no other</line>
            <line>But what comes from myself, it shall scarce boot me</line>
            <line>To say 'not guilty:' mine integrity</line>
            <line>Being counted falsehood, shall, as I express it,</line>
            <line>Be so received. But thus: if powers divine</line>
            <line>Behold our human actions, as they do,</line>
            <line>I doubt not then but innocence shall make</line>
            <line>False accusation blush and tyranny</line>
            <line>Tremble at patience. You, my lord, best know,</line>
            <line>Who least will seem to do so, my past life</line>
            <line>Hath been as continent, as chaste, as true,</line>
            <line>As I am now unhappy; which is more</line>
            <line>Than history can pattern, though devised</line>
            <line>And play'd to take spectators. For behold me</line>
            <line>A fellow of the royal bed, which owe</line>
            <line>A moiety of the throne a great king's daughter,</line>
            <line>The mother to a hopeful prince, here standing</line>
            <line>To prate and talk for life and honour 'fore</line>
            <line>Who please to come and hear. For life, I prize it</line>
            <line>As I weigh grief, which I would spare: for honour,</line>
            <line>'Tis a derivative from me to mine,</line>
            <line>And only that I stand for. I appeal</line>
            <line>To your own conscience, sir, before Polixenes</line>
            <line>Came to your court, how I was in your grace,</line>
            <line>How merited to be so; since he came,</line>
            <line>With what encounter so uncurrent I</line>
            <line>Have strain'd to appear thus: if one jot beyond</line>
            <line>The bound of honour, or in act or will</line>
            <line>That way inclining, harden'd be the hearts</line>
            <line>Of all that hear me, and my near'st of kin</line>
            <line>Cry fie upon my grave!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>I ne'er heard yet</line>
            <line>That any of these bolder vices wanted</line>
            <line>Less impudence to gainsay what they did</line>
            <line>Than to perform it first.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERMIONE</speaker>
            <line>That's true enough;</line>
            <line>Through 'tis a saying, sir, not due to me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>You will not own it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERMIONE</speaker>
            <line>More than mistress of</line>
            <line>Which comes to me in name of fault, I must not</line>
            <line>At all acknowledge. For Polixenes,</line>
            <line>With whom I am accused, I do confess</line>
            <line>I loved him as in honour he required,</line>
            <line>With such a kind of love as might become</line>
            <line>A lady like me, with a love even such,</line>
            <line>So and no other, as yourself commanded:</line>
            <line>Which not to have done I think had been in me</line>
            <line>Both disobedience and ingratitude</line>
            <line>To you and toward your friend, whose love had spoke,</line>
            <line>Even since it could speak, from an infant, freely</line>
            <line>That it was yours. Now, for conspiracy,</line>
            <line>I know not how it tastes; though it be dish'd</line>
            <line>For me to try how: all I know of it</line>
            <line>Is that Camillo was an honest man;</line>
            <line>And why he left your court, the gods themselves,</line>
            <line>Wotting no more than I, are ignorant.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>You knew of his departure, as you know</line>
            <line>What you have underta'en to do in's absence.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERMIONE</speaker>
            <line>Sir,</line>
            <line>You speak a language that I understand not:</line>
            <line>My life stands in the level of your dreams,</line>
            <line>Which I'll lay down.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>Your actions are my dreams;</line>
            <line>You had a bastard by Polixenes,</line>
            <line>And I but dream'd it. As you were past all shame,--</line>
            <line>Those of your fact are so--so past all truth:</line>
            <line>Which to deny concerns more than avails; for as</line>
            <line>Thy brat hath been cast out, like to itself,</line>
            <line>No father owning it,--which is, indeed,</line>
            <line>More criminal in thee than it,--so thou</line>
            <line>Shalt feel our justice, in whose easiest passage</line>
            <line>Look for no less than death.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERMIONE</speaker>
            <line>Sir, spare your threats:</line>
            <line>The bug which you would fright me with I seek.</line>
            <line>To me can life be no commodity:</line>
            <line>The crown and comfort of my life, your favour,</line>
            <line>I do give lost; for I do feel it gone,</line>
            <line>But know not how it went. My second joy</line>
            <line>And first-fruits of my body, from his presence</line>
            <line>I am barr'd, like one infectious. My third comfort</line>
            <line>Starr'd most unluckily, is from my breast,</line>
            <line>The innocent milk in its most innocent mouth,</line>
            <line>Haled out to murder: myself on every post</line>
            <line>Proclaimed a strumpet: with immodest hatred</line>
            <line>The child-bed privilege denied, which 'longs</line>
            <line>To women of all fashion; lastly, hurried</line>
            <line>Here to this place, i' the open air, before</line>
            <line>I have got strength of limit. Now, my liege,</line>
            <line>Tell me what blessings I have here alive,</line>
            <line>That I should fear to die? Therefore proceed.</line>
            <line>But yet hear this: mistake me not; no life,</line>
            <line>I prize it not a straw, but for mine honour,</line>
            <line>Which I would free, if I shall be condemn'd</line>
            <line>Upon surmises, all proofs sleeping else</line>
            <line>But what your jealousies awake, I tell you</line>
            <line>'Tis rigor and not law. Your honours all,</line>
            <line>I do refer me to the oracle:</line>
            <line>Apollo be my judge!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>This your request</line>
            <line>Is altogether just: therefore bring forth,</line>
            <line>And in Apollos name, his oracle.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt certain Officers</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERMIONE</speaker>
            <line>The Emperor of Russia was my father:</line>
            <line>O that he were alive, and here beholding</line>
            <line>His daughter's trial! that he did but see</line>
            <line>The flatness of my misery, yet with eyes</line>
            <line>Of pity, not revenge!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter Officers, with CLEOMENES and DION</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Officer</speaker>
            <line>You here shall swear upon this sword of justice,</line>
            <line>That you, Cleomenes and Dion, have</line>
            <line>Been both at Delphos, and from thence have brought</line>
            <line>The seal'd-up oracle, by the hand deliver'd</line>
            <line>Of great Apollo's priest; and that, since then,</line>
            <line>You have not dared to break the holy seal</line>
            <line>Nor read the secrets in't.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CLEOMENES</speaker>
            <speaker>DION</speaker>
            <line>All this we swear.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>Break up the seals and read.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Officer</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Reads</stagedir> Hermione is chaste;</line>
            <line>Polixenes blameless; Camillo a true subject; Leontes</line>
            <line>a jealous tyrant; his innocent babe truly begotten;</line>
            <line>and the king shall live without an heir, if that</line>
            <line>which is lost be not found.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Lords</speaker>
            <line>Now blessed be the great Apollo!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>HERMIONE</speaker>
            <line>Praised!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>Hast thou read truth?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Officer</speaker>
            <line>Ay, my lord; even so</line>
            <line>As it is here set down.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>There is no truth at all i' the oracle:</line>
            <line>The sessions shall proceed: this is mere falsehood.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter Servant</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>My lord the king, the king!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>What is the business?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>O sir, I shall be hated to report it!</line>
            <line>The prince your son, with mere conceit and fear</line>
            <line>Of the queen's speed, is gone.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>How! gone!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>Is dead.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>Apollo's angry; and the heavens themselves</line>
            <line>Do strike at my injustice.</line>
            <stagedir>HERMIONE swoons</stagedir>
            <line>How now there!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAULINA</speaker>
            <line>This news is mortal to the queen: look down</line>
            <line>And see what death is doing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>Take her hence:</line>
            <line>Her heart is but o'ercharged; she will recover:</line>
            <line>I have too much believed mine own suspicion:</line>
            <line>Beseech you, tenderly apply to her</line>
            <line>Some remedies for life.</line>
            <stagedir>Exeunt PAULINA and Ladies, with HERMIONE</stagedir>
            <line>Apollo, pardon</line>
            <line>My great profaneness 'gainst thine oracle!</line>
            <line>I'll reconcile me to Polixenes,</line>
            <line>New woo my queen, recall the good Camillo,</line>
            <line>Whom I proclaim a man of truth, of mercy;</line>
            <line>For, being transported by my jealousies</line>
            <line>To bloody thoughts and to revenge, I chose</line>
            <line>Camillo for the minister to poison</line>
            <line>My friend Polixenes: which had been done,</line>
            <line>But that the good mind of Camillo tardied</line>
            <line>My swift command, though I with death and with</line>
            <line>Reward did threaten and encourage him,</line>
            <line>Not doing 't and being done: he, most humane</line>
            <line>And fill'd with honour, to my kingly guest</line>
            <line>Unclasp'd my practise, quit his fortunes here,</line>
            <line>Which you knew great, and to the hazard</line>
            <line>Of all encertainties himself commended,</line>
            <line>No richer than his honour: how he glisters</line>
            <line>Thorough my rust! and how his pity</line>
            <line>Does my deeds make the blacker!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Re-enter PAULINA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAULINA</speaker>
            <line>Woe the while!</line>
            <line>O, cut my lace, lest my heart, cracking it,</line>
            <line>Break too.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>What fit is this, good lady?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAULINA</speaker>
            <line>What studied torments, tyrant, hast for me?</line>
            <line>What wheels? racks? fires? what flaying? boiling?</line>
            <line>In leads or oils? what old or newer torture</line>
            <line>Must I receive, whose every word deserves</line>
            <line>To taste of thy most worst? Thy tyranny</line>
            <line>Together working with thy jealousies,</line>
            <line>Fancies too weak for boys, too green and idle</line>
            <line>For girls of nine, O, think what they have done</line>
            <line>And then run mad indeed, stark mad! for all</line>
            <line>Thy by-gone fooleries were but spices of it.</line>
            <line>That thou betray'dst Polixenes,'twas nothing;</line>
            <line>That did but show thee, of a fool, inconstant</line>
            <line>And damnable ingrateful: nor was't much,</line>
            <line>Thou wouldst have poison'd good Camillo's honour,</line>
            <line>To have him kill a king: poor trespasses,</line>
            <line>More monstrous standing by: whereof I reckon</line>
            <line>The casting forth to crows thy baby-daughter</line>
            <line>To be or none or little; though a devil</line>
            <line>Would have shed water out of fire ere done't:</line>
            <line>Nor is't directly laid to thee, the death</line>
            <line>Of the young prince, whose honourable thoughts,</line>
            <line>Thoughts high for one so tender, cleft the heart</line>
            <line>That could conceive a gross and foolish sire</line>
            <line>Blemish'd his gracious dam: this is not, no,</line>
            <line>Laid to thy answer: but the last,--O lords,</line>
            <line>When I have said, cry 'woe!' the queen, the queen,</line>
            <line>The sweet'st, dear'st creature's dead,</line>
            <line>and vengeance for't</line>
            <line>Not dropp'd down yet.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>The higher powers forbid!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAULINA</speaker>
            <line>I say she's dead; I'll swear't. If word nor oath</line>
            <line>Prevail not, go and see: if you can bring</line>
            <line>Tincture or lustre in her lip, her eye,</line>
            <line>Heat outwardly or breath within, I'll serve you</line>
            <line>As I would do the gods. But, O thou tyrant!</line>
            <line>Do not repent these things, for they are heavier</line>
            <line>Than all thy woes can stir; therefore betake thee</line>
            <line>To nothing but despair. A thousand knees</line>
            <line>Ten thousand years together, naked, fasting,</line>
            <line>Upon a barren mountain and still winter</line>
            <line>In storm perpetual, could not move the gods</line>
            <line>To look that way thou wert.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>Go on, go on</line>
            <line>Thou canst not speak too much; I have deserved</line>
            <line>All tongues to talk their bitterest.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>First Lord</speaker>
            <line>Say no more:</line>
            <line>Howe'er the business goes, you have made fault</line>
            <line>I' the boldness of your speech.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PAULINA</speaker>
            <line>I am sorry for't:</line>
            <line>All faults I make, when I shall come to know them,</line>
            <line>I do repent. Alas! I have show'd too much</line>
            <line>The rashness of a woman: he is touch'd</line>
            <line>To the noble heart. What's gone and what's past help</line>
            <line>Should be past grief: do not receive affliction</line>
            <line>At my petition; I beseech you, rather</line>
            <line>Let me be punish'd, that have minded you</line>
            <line>Of what you should forget. Now, good my liege</line>
            <line>Sir, royal sir, forgive a foolish woman:</line>
            <line>The love I bore your queen--lo, fool again!--</line>
            <line>I'll speak of her no more, nor of your children;</line>
            <line>I'll not remember you of my own lord,</line>
            <line>Who is lost too: take your patience to you,</line>
            <line>And I'll say nothing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>LEONTES</speaker>
            <line>Thou didst speak but well</line>
            <line>When most the truth; which I receive much better</line>
            <line>Than to be pitied of thee. Prithee, bring me</line>
            <line>To the dead bodies of my queen and son:</line>
            <line>One grave shall be for both: upon them shall</line>
            <line>The causes of their death appear, unto</line>
            <line>Our shame perpetual. Once a day I'll visit</line>
            <line>The chapel where they lie, and tears shed there</line>
            <line>Shall be my recreation: so long as nature</line>
            <line>Will bear up with this exercise, so long</line>
            <line>I daily vow to use it. Come and lead me</line>
            <line>Unto these sorrows.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-3-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  Bohemia. A desert country near the sea.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter ANTIGONUS with a Child, and a Mariner</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIGONUS</speaker>
            <line>Thou art perfect then, our ship hath touch'd upon</line>
            <line>The deserts of Bohemia?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Mariner</speaker>
            <line>Ay, my lord: and fear</line>
            <line>We have landed in ill time: the skies look grimly</line>
            <line>And threaten present blusters. In my conscience,</line>
            <line>The heavens with that we have in hand are angry</line>
            <line>And frown upon 's.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIGONUS</speaker>
            <line>Their sacred wills be done! Go, get aboard;</line>
            <line>Look to thy bark: I'll not be long before</line>
            <line>I call upon thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Mariner</speaker>
            <line>Make your best haste, and go not</line>
            <line>Too far i' the land: 'tis like to be loud weather;</line>
            <line>Besides, this place is famous for the creatures</line>
            <line>Of prey that keep upon't.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIGONUS</speaker>
            <line>Go thou away:</line>
            <line>I'll follow instantly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Mariner</speaker>
            <line>I am glad at heart</line>
            <line>To be so rid o' the business.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>ANTIGONUS</speaker>
            <line>Come, poor babe:</line>
            <line>I have heard, but not believed,</line>
            <line>the spirits o' the dead</line>
            <line>May walk again: if such thing be, thy mother</line>
            <line>Appear'd to me last night, for ne'er was dream</line>
            <line>So like a waking. To me comes a creature,</line>
            <line>Sometimes her head on one side, some another;</line>
            <line>I never saw a vessel of like sorrow,</line>
            <line>So fill'd and so becoming: in pure white robes,</line>
            <line>Like very sanctity, she did approach</line>
            <line>My cabin where I lay; thrice bow'd before me,</line>
            <line>And gasping to begin some speech, her eyes</line>
            <line>Became two spouts: the fury spent, anon</line>
            <line>Did this break-from her: 'Good Antigonus,</line>
            <line>Since fate, against thy better disposition,</line>
            <line>Hath made thy person for the thrower-out</line>
            <line>Of my poor babe, according to thine oath,</line>
            <line>Places remote enough are in Bohemia,</line>
            <line>There weep and leave it crying; and, for the babe</line>
            <line>Is counted lost for ever, Perdita,</line>
            <line>I prithee, call't. For this ungentle business</line>
            <line>Put on thee by my lord, thou ne'er shalt see</line>
            <line>Thy wife Paulina more.' And so, with shrieks</line>
            <line>She melted into air. Affrighted much,</line>
            <line>I did in time collect myself and thought</line>
            <line>This was so and no slumber. Dreams are toys:</line>
            <line>Yet for this once, yea, superstitiously,</line>
            <line>I will be squared by this. I do believe</line>
            <line>Hermione hath suffer'd death, and that</line>
            <line>Apollo would, this being indeed the issue</line>
            <line>Of King Polixenes, it should here be laid,</line>
            <line>Either for life or death, upon the earth</line>
            <line>Of its right father. Blossom, speed thee well!</line>
            <line>There lie, and there thy character: there these;</line>
            <line>Which may, if fortune please, both breed thee, pretty,</line>
            <line>And still rest thine. The storm begins; poor wretch,</line>
            <line>That for thy mother's fault art thus exposed</line>
            <line>To loss and what may follow! Weep I cannot,</line>
            <line>But my heart bleeds; and most accursed am I</line>
            <line>To be by oath enjoin'd to this. Farewell!</line>
            <line>The day frowns more and more: thou'rt like to have</line>
            <line>A lullaby too rough: I never saw</line>
            <line>The heavens so dim by day. A savage clamour!</line>
            <line>Well may I get aboard! This is the chase:</line>
            <line>I am gone for ever.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit, pursued by a bear</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Enter a Shepherd</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Shepherd</speaker>
            <line>I would there were no age between sixteen and</line>
            <line>three-and-twenty, or that youth would sleep out the</line>
            <line>rest; for there is nothing in the between but</line>
            <line>getting wenches with child, wronging the ancientry,</line>
            <line>stealing, fighting--Hark you now! Would any but</line>
            <line>these boiled brains of nineteen and two-and-twenty</line>
            <line>hunt this weather? They have scared away two of my</line>
            <line>best sheep, which I fear the wolf will sooner find</line>
            <line>than the master: if any where I have them, 'tis by</line>
            <line>the seaside, browsing of ivy. Good luck, an't be thy</line>
            <line>will what have we here! Mercy on 's, a barne a very</line>
            <line>pretty barne! A boy or a child, I wonder? A</line>
            <line>pretty one; a very pretty one: sure, some 'scape:</line>
            <line>though I am not bookish, yet I can read</line>
            <line>waiting-gentlewoman in the 'scape. This has been</line>
            <line>some stair-work, some trunk-work, some</line>
            <line>behind-door-work: they were warmer that got this</line>
            <line>than the poor thing is here. I'll take it up for</line>
            <line>pity: yet I'll tarry till my son come; he hallooed</line>
            <line>but even now. Whoa, ho, hoa!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter Clown</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Hilloa, loa!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Shepherd</speaker>
            <line>What, art so near? If thou'lt see a thing to talk</line>
            <line>on when thou art dead and rotten, come hither. What</line>
            <line>ailest thou, man?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>I have seen two such sights, by sea and by land!</line>
            <line>but I am not to say it is a sea, for it is now the</line>
            <line>sky: betwixt the firmament and it you cannot thrust</line>
            <line>a bodkin's point.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Shepherd</speaker>
            <line>Why, boy, how is it?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>I would you did but see how it chafes, how it rages,</line>
            <line>how it takes up the shore! but that's not the</line>
            <line>point. O, the most piteous cry of the poor souls!</line>
            <line>sometimes to see 'em, and not to see 'em; now the</line>
            <line>ship boring the moon with her main-mast, and anon</line>
            <line>swallowed with yest and froth, as you'ld thrust a</line>
            <line>cork into a hogshead. And then for the</line>
            <line>land-service, to see how the bear tore out his</line>
            <line>shoulder-bone; how he cried to me for help and said</line>
            <line>his name was Antigonus, a nobleman. But to make an</line>
            <line>end of the ship, to see how the sea flap-dragoned</line>
            <line>it: but, first, how the poor souls roared, and the</line>
            <line>sea mocked them; and how the poor gentleman roared</line>
            <line>and the bear mocked him, both roaring louder than</line>
            <line>the sea or weather.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Shepherd</speaker>
            <line>Name of mercy, when was this, boy?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Now, now: I have not winked since I saw these</line>
            <line>sights: the men are not yet cold under water, nor</line>
            <line>the bear half dined on the gentleman: he's at it</line>
            <line>now.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Shepherd</speaker>
            <line>Would I had been by, to have helped the old man!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>I would you had been by the ship side, to have</line>
            <line>helped her: there your charity would have lacked footing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Shepherd</speaker>
            <line>Heavy matters! heavy matters! but look thee here,</line>
            <line>boy. Now bless thyself: thou mettest with things</line>
            <line>dying, I with things newborn. Here's a sight for</line>
            <line>thee; look thee, a bearing-cloth for a squire's</line>
            <line>child! look thee here; take up, take up, boy;</line>
            <line>open't. So, let's see: it was told me I should be</line>
            <line>rich by the fairies. This is some changeling:</line>
            <line>open't. What's within, boy?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>You're a made old man: if the sins of your youth</line>
            <line>are forgiven you, you're well to live. Gold! all gold!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Shepherd</speaker>
            <line>This is fairy gold, boy, and 'twill prove so: up</line>
            <line>with't, keep it close: home, home, the next way.</line>
            <line>We are lucky, boy; and to be so still requires</line>
            <line>nothing but secrecy. Let my sheep go: come, good</line>
            <line>boy, the next way home.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Go you the next way with your findings. I'll go see</line>
            <line>if the bear be gone from the gentleman and how much</line>
            <line>he hath eaten: they are never curst but when they</line>
            <line>are hungry: if there be any of him left, I'll bury</line>
            <line>it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Shepherd</speaker>
            <line>That's a good deed. If thou mayest discern by that</line>
            <line>which is left of him what he is, fetch me to the</line>
            <line>sight of him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Marry, will I; and you shall help to put him i' the ground.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Shepherd</speaker>
            <line>'Tis a lucky day, boy, and we'll do good deeds on't.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>