<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE act
  PUBLIC "urn:pubid:dita4publishers.sourceforge.net:doctypes:dita:shakespear:dtd:act" "act.dtd">
<act id="act-4">
   <title>ACT IV</title>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-1">
      <title>SCENE I</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter Time, the Chorus</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Time</speaker>
            <line>I, that please some, try all, both joy and terror</line>
            <line>Of good and bad, that makes and unfolds error,</line>
            <line>Now take upon me, in the name of Time,</line>
            <line>To use my wings. Impute it not a crime</line>
            <line>To me or my swift passage, that I slide</line>
            <line>O'er sixteen years and leave the growth untried</line>
            <line>Of that wide gap, since it is in my power</line>
            <line>To o'erthrow law and in one self-born hour</line>
            <line>To plant and o'erwhelm custom. Let me pass</line>
            <line>The same I am, ere ancient'st order was</line>
            <line>Or what is now received: I witness to</line>
            <line>The times that brought them in; so shall I do</line>
            <line>To the freshest things now reigning and make stale</line>
            <line>The glistering of this present, as my tale</line>
            <line>Now seems to it. Your patience this allowing,</line>
            <line>I turn my glass and give my scene such growing</line>
            <line>As you had slept between: Leontes leaving,</line>
            <line>The effects of his fond jealousies so grieving</line>
            <line>That he shuts up himself, imagine me,</line>
            <line>Gentle spectators, that I now may be</line>
            <line>In fair Bohemia, and remember well,</line>
            <line>I mentioned a son o' the king's, which Florizel</line>
            <line>I now name to you; and with speed so pace</line>
            <line>To speak of Perdita, now grown in grace</line>
            <line>Equal with wondering: what of her ensues</line>
            <line>I list not prophecy; but let Time's news</line>
            <line>Be known when 'tis brought forth.</line>
            <line>A shepherd's daughter,</line>
            <line>And what to her adheres, which follows after,</line>
            <line>Is the argument of Time. Of this allow,</line>
            <line>If ever you have spent time worse ere now;</line>
            <line>If never, yet that Time himself doth say</line>
            <line>He wishes earnestly you never may.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-2">
      <title>SCENE II.  Bohemia. The palace of POLIXENES.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter POLIXENES and CAMILLO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POLIXENES</speaker>
            <line>I pray thee, good Camillo, be no more importunate:</line>
            <line>'tis a sickness denying thee any thing; a death to</line>
            <line>grant this.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>It is fifteen years since I saw my country: though</line>
            <line>I have for the most part been aired abroad, I</line>
            <line>desire to lay my bones there. Besides, the penitent</line>
            <line>king, my master, hath sent for me; to whose feeling</line>
            <line>sorrows I might be some allay, or I o'erween to</line>
            <line>think so, which is another spur to my departure.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POLIXENES</speaker>
            <line>As thou lovest me, Camillo, wipe not out the rest of</line>
            <line>thy services by leaving me now: the need I have of</line>
            <line>thee thine own goodness hath made; better not to</line>
            <line>have had thee than thus to want thee: thou, having</line>
            <line>made me businesses which none without thee can</line>
            <line>sufficiently manage, must either stay to execute</line>
            <line>them thyself or take away with thee the very</line>
            <line>services thou hast done; which if I have not enough</line>
            <line>considered, as too much I cannot, to be more</line>
            <line>thankful to thee shall be my study, and my profit</line>
            <line>therein the heaping friendships. Of that fatal</line>
            <line>country, Sicilia, prithee speak no more; whose very</line>
            <line>naming punishes me with the remembrance of that</line>
            <line>penitent, as thou callest him, and reconciled king,</line>
            <line>my brother; whose loss of his most precious queen</line>
            <line>and children are even now to be afresh lamented.</line>
            <line>Say to me, when sawest thou the Prince Florizel, my</line>
            <line>son? Kings are no less unhappy, their issue not</line>
            <line>being gracious, than they are in losing them when</line>
            <line>they have approved their virtues.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>Sir, it is three days since I saw the prince. What</line>
            <line>his happier affairs may be, are to me unknown: but I</line>
            <line>have missingly noted, he is of late much retired</line>
            <line>from court and is less frequent to his princely</line>
            <line>exercises than formerly he hath appeared.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POLIXENES</speaker>
            <line>I have considered so much, Camillo, and with some</line>
            <line>care; so far that I have eyes under my service which</line>
            <line>look upon his removedness; from whom I have this</line>
            <line>intelligence, that he is seldom from the house of a</line>
            <line>most homely shepherd; a man, they say, that from</line>
            <line>very nothing, and beyond the imagination of his</line>
            <line>neighbours, is grown into an unspeakable estate.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>I have heard, sir, of such a man, who hath a</line>
            <line>daughter of most rare note: the report of her is</line>
            <line>extended more than can be thought to begin from such a cottage.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POLIXENES</speaker>
            <line>That's likewise part of my intelligence; but, I</line>
            <line>fear, the angle that plucks our son thither. Thou</line>
            <line>shalt accompany us to the place; where we will, not</line>
            <line>appearing what we are, have some question with the</line>
            <line>shepherd; from whose simplicity I think it not</line>
            <line>uneasy to get the cause of my son's resort thither.</line>
            <line>Prithee, be my present partner in this business, and</line>
            <line>lay aside the thoughts of Sicilia.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>I willingly obey your command.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POLIXENES</speaker>
            <line>My best Camillo! We must disguise ourselves.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-3">
      <title>SCENE III.  A road near the Shepherd's cottage.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter AUTOLYCUS, singing</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>When daffodils begin to peer,</line>
            <line>With heigh! the doxy over the dale,</line>
            <line>Why, then comes in the sweet o' the year;</line>
            <line>For the red blood reigns in the winter's pale.</line>
            <line>The white sheet bleaching on the hedge,</line>
            <line>With heigh! the sweet birds, O, how they sing!</line>
            <line>Doth set my pugging tooth on edge;</line>
            <line>For a quart of ale is a dish for a king.</line>
            <line>The lark, that tirra-lyra chants,</line>
            <line>With heigh! with heigh! the thrush and the jay,</line>
            <line>Are summer songs for me and my aunts,</line>
            <line>While we lie tumbling in the hay.</line>
            <line>I have served Prince Florizel and in my time</line>
            <line>wore three-pile; but now I am out of service:</line>
            <line>But shall I go mourn for that, my dear?</line>
            <line>The pale moon shines by night:</line>
            <line>And when I wander here and there,</line>
            <line>I then do most go right.</line>
            <line>If tinkers may have leave to live,</line>
            <line>And bear the sow-skin budget,</line>
            <line>Then my account I well may, give,</line>
            <line>And in the stocks avouch it.</line>
            <line>My traffic is sheets; when the kite builds, look to</line>
            <line>lesser linen. My father named me Autolycus; who</line>
            <line>being, as I am, littered under Mercury, was likewise</line>
            <line>a snapper-up of unconsidered trifles. With die and</line>
            <line>drab I purchased this caparison, and my revenue is</line>
            <line>the silly cheat. Gallows and knock are too powerful</line>
            <line>on the highway: beating and hanging are terrors to</line>
            <line>me: for the life to come, I sleep out the thought</line>
            <line>of it. A prize! a prize!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter Clown</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Let me see: every 'leven wether tods; every tod</line>
            <line>yields pound and odd shilling; fifteen hundred</line>
            <line>shorn. what comes the wool to?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>
            </line>
            <line>If the springe hold, the cock's mine.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>I cannot do't without counters. Let me see; what am</line>
            <line>I to buy for our sheep-shearing feast? Three pound</line>
            <line>of sugar, five pound of currants, rice,--what will</line>
            <line>this sister of mine do with rice? But my father</line>
            <line>hath made her mistress of the feast, and she lays it</line>
            <line>on. She hath made me four and twenty nose-gays for</line>
            <line>the shearers, three-man-song-men all, and very good</line>
            <line>ones; but they are most of them means and bases; but</line>
            <line>one puritan amongst them, and he sings psalms to</line>
            <line>horn-pipes. I must have saffron to colour the warden</line>
            <line>pies; mace; dates?--none, that's out of my note;</line>
            <line>nutmegs, seven; a race or two of ginger, but that I</line>
            <line>may beg; four pound of prunes, and as many of</line>
            <line>raisins o' the sun.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>O that ever I was born!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Grovelling on the ground</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>I' the name of me--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>O, help me, help me! pluck but off these rags; and</line>
            <line>then, death, death!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Alack, poor soul! thou hast need of more rags to lay</line>
            <line>on thee, rather than have these off.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>O sir, the loathsomeness of them offends me more</line>
            <line>than the stripes I have received, which are mighty</line>
            <line>ones and millions.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Alas, poor man! a million of beating may come to a</line>
            <line>great matter.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>I am robbed, sir, and beaten; my money and apparel</line>
            <line>ta'en from me, and these detestable things put upon</line>
            <line>me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>What, by a horseman, or a footman?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>A footman, sweet sir, a footman.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Indeed, he should be a footman by the garments he</line>
            <line>has left with thee: if this be a horseman's coat,</line>
            <line>it hath seen very hot service. Lend me thy hand,</line>
            <line>I'll help thee: come, lend me thy hand.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>O, good sir, tenderly, O!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Alas, poor soul!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>O, good sir, softly, good sir! I fear, sir, my</line>
            <line>shoulder-blade is out.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>How now! canst stand?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Picking his pocket</stagedir>
            </line>
            <line>Softly, dear sir; good sir, softly. You ha' done me</line>
            <line>a charitable office.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Dost lack any money? I have a little money for thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>No, good sweet sir; no, I beseech you, sir: I have</line>
            <line>a kinsman not past three quarters of a mile hence,</line>
            <line>unto whom I was going; I shall there have money, or</line>
            <line>any thing I want: offer me no money, I pray you;</line>
            <line>that kills my heart.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>What manner of fellow was he that robbed you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>A fellow, sir, that I have known to go about with</line>
            <line>troll-my-dames; I knew him once a servant of the</line>
            <line>prince: I cannot tell, good sir, for which of his</line>
            <line>virtues it was, but he was certainly whipped out of the court.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>His vices, you would say; there's no virtue whipped</line>
            <line>out of the court: they cherish it to make it stay</line>
            <line>there; and yet it will no more but abide.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>Vices, I would say, sir. I know this man well: he</line>
            <line>hath been since an ape-bearer; then a</line>
            <line>process-server, a bailiff; then he compassed a</line>
            <line>motion of the Prodigal Son, and married a tinker's</line>
            <line>wife within a mile where my land and living lies;</line>
            <line>and, having flown over many knavish professions, he</line>
            <line>settled only in rogue: some call him Autolycus.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Out upon him! prig, for my life, prig: he haunts</line>
            <line>wakes, fairs and bear-baitings.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>Very true, sir; he, sir, he; that's the rogue that</line>
            <line>put me into this apparel.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Not a more cowardly rogue in all Bohemia: if you had</line>
            <line>but looked big and spit at him, he'ld have run.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>I must confess to you, sir, I am no fighter: I am</line>
            <line>false of heart that way; and that he knew, I warrant</line>
            <line>him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>How do you now?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>Sweet sir, much better than I was; I can stand and</line>
            <line>walk: I will even take my leave of you, and pace</line>
            <line>softly towards my kinsman's.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Shall I bring thee on the way?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>No, good-faced sir; no, sweet sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Then fare thee well: I must go buy spices for our</line>
            <line>sheep-shearing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>Prosper you, sweet sir!</line>
            <stagedir>Exit Clown</stagedir>
            <line>Your purse is not hot enough to purchase your spice.</line>
            <line>I'll be with you at your sheep-shearing too: if I</line>
            <line>make not this cheat bring out another and the</line>
            <line>shearers prove sheep, let me be unrolled and my name</line>
            <line>put in the book of virtue!</line>
            <stagedir>Sings</stagedir>
            <line>Jog on, jog on, the foot-path way,</line>
            <line>And merrily hent the stile-a:</line>
            <line>A merry heart goes all the day,</line>
            <line>Your sad tires in a mile-a.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
   <scene id="act-4-scene-4">
      <title>SCENE IV.  The Shepherd's cottage.</title>
      <scene-body>
         <stagedir>Enter FLORIZEL and PERDITA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLORIZEL</speaker>
            <line>These your unusual weeds to each part of you</line>
            <line>Do give a life: no shepherdess, but Flora</line>
            <line>Peering in April's front. This your sheep-shearing</line>
            <line>Is as a meeting of the petty gods,</line>
            <line>And you the queen on't.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERDITA</speaker>
            <line>Sir, my gracious lord,</line>
            <line>To chide at your extremes it not becomes me:</line>
            <line>O, pardon, that I name them! Your high self,</line>
            <line>The gracious mark o' the land, you have obscured</line>
            <line>With a swain's wearing, and me, poor lowly maid,</line>
            <line>Most goddess-like prank'd up: but that our feasts</line>
            <line>In every mess have folly and the feeders</line>
            <line>Digest it with a custom, I should blush</line>
            <line>To see you so attired, sworn, I think,</line>
            <line>To show myself a glass.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLORIZEL</speaker>
            <line>I bless the time</line>
            <line>When my good falcon made her flight across</line>
            <line>Thy father's ground.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERDITA</speaker>
            <line>Now Jove afford you cause!</line>
            <line>To me the difference forges dread; your greatness</line>
            <line>Hath not been used to fear. Even now I tremble</line>
            <line>To think your father, by some accident,</line>
            <line>Should pass this way as you did: O, the Fates!</line>
            <line>How would he look, to see his work so noble</line>
            <line>Vilely bound up? What would he say? Or how</line>
            <line>Should I, in these my borrow'd flaunts, behold</line>
            <line>The sternness of his presence?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLORIZEL</speaker>
            <line>Apprehend</line>
            <line>Nothing but jollity. The gods themselves,</line>
            <line>Humbling their deities to love, have taken</line>
            <line>The shapes of beasts upon them: Jupiter</line>
            <line>Became a bull, and bellow'd; the green Neptune</line>
            <line>A ram, and bleated; and the fire-robed god,</line>
            <line>Golden Apollo, a poor humble swain,</line>
            <line>As I seem now. Their transformations</line>
            <line>Were never for a piece of beauty rarer,</line>
            <line>Nor in a way so chaste, since my desires</line>
            <line>Run not before mine honour, nor my lusts</line>
            <line>Burn hotter than my faith.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERDITA</speaker>
            <line>O, but, sir,</line>
            <line>Your resolution cannot hold, when 'tis</line>
            <line>Opposed, as it must be, by the power of the king:</line>
            <line>One of these two must be necessities,</line>
            <line>Which then will speak, that you must</line>
            <line>change this purpose,</line>
            <line>Or I my life.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLORIZEL</speaker>
            <line>Thou dearest Perdita,</line>
            <line>With these forced thoughts, I prithee, darken not</line>
            <line>The mirth o' the feast. Or I'll be thine, my fair,</line>
            <line>Or not my father's. For I cannot be</line>
            <line>Mine own, nor any thing to any, if</line>
            <line>I be not thine. To this I am most constant,</line>
            <line>Though destiny say no. Be merry, gentle;</line>
            <line>Strangle such thoughts as these with any thing</line>
            <line>That you behold the while. Your guests are coming:</line>
            <line>Lift up your countenance, as it were the day</line>
            <line>Of celebration of that nuptial which</line>
            <line>We two have sworn shall come.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERDITA</speaker>
            <line>O lady Fortune,</line>
            <line>Stand you auspicious!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLORIZEL</speaker>
            <line>See, your guests approach:</line>
            <line>Address yourself to entertain them sprightly,</line>
            <line>And let's be red with mirth.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter Shepherd, Clown, MOPSA, DORCAS, and
others, with POLIXENES and CAMILLO disguised</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Shepherd</speaker>
            <line>Fie, daughter! when my old wife lived, upon</line>
            <line>This day she was both pantler, butler, cook,</line>
            <line>Both dame and servant; welcomed all, served all;</line>
            <line>Would sing her song and dance her turn; now here,</line>
            <line>At upper end o' the table, now i' the middle;</line>
            <line>On his shoulder, and his; her face o' fire</line>
            <line>With labour and the thing she took to quench it,</line>
            <line>She would to each one sip. You are retired,</line>
            <line>As if you were a feasted one and not</line>
            <line>The hostess of the meeting: pray you, bid</line>
            <line>These unknown friends to's welcome; for it is</line>
            <line>A way to make us better friends, more known.</line>
            <line>Come, quench your blushes and present yourself</line>
            <line>That which you are, mistress o' the feast: come on,</line>
            <line>And bid us welcome to your sheep-shearing,</line>
            <line>As your good flock shall prosper.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERDITA</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>To POLIXENES</stagedir>                  Sir, welcome:</line>
            <line>It is my father's will I should take on me</line>
            <line>The hostess-ship o' the day.</line>
            <stagedir>To CAMILLO</stagedir>
            <line>You're welcome, sir.</line>
            <line>Give me those flowers there, Dorcas. Reverend sirs,</line>
            <line>For you there's rosemary and rue; these keep</line>
            <line>Seeming and savour all the winter long:</line>
            <line>Grace and remembrance be to you both,</line>
            <line>And welcome to our shearing!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POLIXENES</speaker>
            <line>Shepherdess,</line>
            <line>A fair one are you--well you fit our ages</line>
            <line>With flowers of winter.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERDITA</speaker>
            <line>Sir, the year growing ancient,</line>
            <line>Not yet on summer's death, nor on the birth</line>
            <line>Of trembling winter, the fairest</line>
            <line>flowers o' the season</line>
            <line>Are our carnations and streak'd gillyvors,</line>
            <line>Which some call nature's bastards: of that kind</line>
            <line>Our rustic garden's barren; and I care not</line>
            <line>To get slips of them.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POLIXENES</speaker>
            <line>Wherefore, gentle maiden,</line>
            <line>Do you neglect them?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERDITA</speaker>
            <line>For I have heard it said</line>
            <line>There is an art which in their piedness shares</line>
            <line>With great creating nature.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POLIXENES</speaker>
            <line>Say there be;</line>
            <line>Yet nature is made better by no mean</line>
            <line>But nature makes that mean: so, over that art</line>
            <line>Which you say adds to nature, is an art</line>
            <line>That nature makes. You see, sweet maid, we marry</line>
            <line>A gentler scion to the wildest stock,</line>
            <line>And make conceive a bark of baser kind</line>
            <line>By bud of nobler race: this is an art</line>
            <line>Which does mend nature, change it rather, but</line>
            <line>The art itself is nature.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERDITA</speaker>
            <line>So it is.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POLIXENES</speaker>
            <line>Then make your garden rich in gillyvors,</line>
            <line>And do not call them bastards.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERDITA</speaker>
            <line>I'll not put</line>
            <line>The dibble in earth to set one slip of them;</line>
            <line>No more than were I painted I would wish</line>
            <line>This youth should say 'twere well and only therefore</line>
            <line>Desire to breed by me. Here's flowers for you;</line>
            <line>Hot lavender, mints, savoury, marjoram;</line>
            <line>The marigold, that goes to bed wi' the sun</line>
            <line>And with him rises weeping: these are flowers</line>
            <line>Of middle summer, and I think they are given</line>
            <line>To men of middle age. You're very welcome.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>I should leave grazing, were I of your flock,</line>
            <line>And only live by gazing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERDITA</speaker>
            <line>Out, alas!</line>
            <line>You'd be so lean, that blasts of January</line>
            <line>Would blow you through and through.</line>
            <line>Now, my fair'st friend,</line>
            <line>I would I had some flowers o' the spring that might</line>
            <line>Become your time of day; and yours, and yours,</line>
            <line>That wear upon your virgin branches yet</line>
            <line>Your maidenheads growing: O Proserpina,</line>
            <line>For the flowers now, that frighted thou let'st fall</line>
            <line>From Dis's waggon! daffodils,</line>
            <line>That come before the swallow dares, and take</line>
            <line>The winds of March with beauty; violets dim,</line>
            <line>But sweeter than the lids of Juno's eyes</line>
            <line>Or Cytherea's breath; pale primroses</line>
            <line>That die unmarried, ere they can behold</line>
            <line>Bight Phoebus in his strength--a malady</line>
            <line>Most incident to maids; bold oxlips and</line>
            <line>The crown imperial; lilies of all kinds,</line>
            <line>The flower-de-luce being one! O, these I lack,</line>
            <line>To make you garlands of, and my sweet friend,</line>
            <line>To strew him o'er and o'er!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLORIZEL</speaker>
            <line>What, like a corse?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERDITA</speaker>
            <line>No, like a bank for love to lie and play on;</line>
            <line>Not like a corse; or if, not to be buried,</line>
            <line>But quick and in mine arms. Come, take your flowers:</line>
            <line>Methinks I play as I have seen them do</line>
            <line>In Whitsun pastorals: sure this robe of mine</line>
            <line>Does change my disposition.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLORIZEL</speaker>
            <line>What you do</line>
            <line>Still betters what is done. When you speak, sweet.</line>
            <line>I'ld have you do it ever: when you sing,</line>
            <line>I'ld have you buy and sell so, so give alms,</line>
            <line>Pray so; and, for the ordering your affairs,</line>
            <line>To sing them too: when you do dance, I wish you</line>
            <line>A wave o' the sea, that you might ever do</line>
            <line>Nothing but that; move still, still so,</line>
            <line>And own no other function: each your doing,</line>
            <line>So singular in each particular,</line>
            <line>Crowns what you are doing in the present deed,</line>
            <line>That all your acts are queens.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERDITA</speaker>
            <line>O Doricles,</line>
            <line>Your praises are too large: but that your youth,</line>
            <line>And the true blood which peepeth fairly through't,</line>
            <line>Do plainly give you out an unstain'd shepherd,</line>
            <line>With wisdom I might fear, my Doricles,</line>
            <line>You woo'd me the false way.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLORIZEL</speaker>
            <line>I think you have</line>
            <line>As little skill to fear as I have purpose</line>
            <line>To put you to't. But come; our dance, I pray:</line>
            <line>Your hand, my Perdita: so turtles pair,</line>
            <line>That never mean to part.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERDITA</speaker>
            <line>I'll swear for 'em.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POLIXENES</speaker>
            <line>This is the prettiest low-born lass that ever</line>
            <line>Ran on the green-sward: nothing she does or seems</line>
            <line>But smacks of something greater than herself,</line>
            <line>Too noble for this place.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>He tells her something</line>
            <line>That makes her blood look out: good sooth, she is</line>
            <line>The queen of curds and cream.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Come on, strike up!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DORCAS</speaker>
            <line>Mopsa must be your mistress: marry, garlic,</line>
            <line>To mend her kissing with!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOPSA</speaker>
            <line>Now, in good time!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Not a word, a word; we stand upon our manners.</line>
            <line>Come, strike up!</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Music. Here a dance of Shepherds and
Shepherdesses</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POLIXENES</speaker>
            <line>Pray, good shepherd, what fair swain is this</line>
            <line>Which dances with your daughter?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Shepherd</speaker>
            <line>They call him Doricles; and boasts himself</line>
            <line>To have a worthy feeding: but I have it</line>
            <line>Upon his own report and I believe it;</line>
            <line>He looks like sooth. He says he loves my daughter:</line>
            <line>I think so too; for never gazed the moon</line>
            <line>Upon the water as he'll stand and read</line>
            <line>As 'twere my daughter's eyes: and, to be plain.</line>
            <line>I think there is not half a kiss to choose</line>
            <line>Who loves another best.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POLIXENES</speaker>
            <line>She dances featly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Shepherd</speaker>
            <line>So she does any thing; though I report it,</line>
            <line>That should be silent: if young Doricles</line>
            <line>Do light upon her, she shall bring him that</line>
            <line>Which he not dreams of.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter Servant</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>O master, if you did but hear the pedlar at the</line>
            <line>door, you would never dance again after a tabour and</line>
            <line>pipe; no, the bagpipe could not move you: he sings</line>
            <line>several tunes faster than you'll tell money; he</line>
            <line>utters them as he had eaten ballads and all men's</line>
            <line>ears grew to his tunes.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>He could never come better; he shall come in. I</line>
            <line>love a ballad but even too well, if it be doleful</line>
            <line>matter merrily set down, or a very pleasant thing</line>
            <line>indeed and sung lamentably.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>He hath songs for man or woman, of all sizes; no</line>
            <line>milliner can so fit his customers with gloves: he</line>
            <line>has the prettiest love-songs for maids; so without</line>
            <line>bawdry, which is strange; with such delicate</line>
            <line>burthens of dildos and fadings, 'jump her and thump</line>
            <line>her;' and where some stretch-mouthed rascal would,</line>
            <line>as it were, mean mischief and break a foul gap into</line>
            <line>the matter, he makes the maid to answer 'Whoop, do me</line>
            <line>no harm, good man;' puts him off, slights him, with</line>
            <line>'Whoop, do me no harm, good man.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POLIXENES</speaker>
            <line>This is a brave fellow.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Believe me, thou talkest of an admirable conceited</line>
            <line>fellow. Has he any unbraided wares?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>He hath ribbons of an the colours i' the rainbow;</line>
            <line>points more than all the lawyers in Bohemia can</line>
            <line>learnedly handle, though they come to him by the</line>
            <line>gross: inkles, caddisses, cambrics, lawns: why, he</line>
            <line>sings 'em over as they were gods or goddesses; you</line>
            <line>would think a smock were a she-angel, he so chants</line>
            <line>to the sleeve-hand and the work about the square on't.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Prithee bring him in; and let him approach singing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERDITA</speaker>
            <line>Forewarn him that he use no scurrilous words in 's tunes.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit Servant</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>You have of these pedlars, that have more in them</line>
            <line>than you'ld think, sister.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERDITA</speaker>
            <line>Ay, good brother, or go about to think.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Enter AUTOLYCUS, singing</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>Lawn as white as driven snow;</line>
            <line>Cyprus black as e'er was crow;</line>
            <line>Gloves as sweet as damask roses;</line>
            <line>Masks for faces and for noses;</line>
            <line>Bugle bracelet, necklace amber,</line>
            <line>Perfume for a lady's chamber;</line>
            <line>Golden quoifs and stomachers,</line>
            <line>For my lads to give their dears:</line>
            <line>Pins and poking-sticks of steel,</line>
            <line>What maids lack from head to heel:</line>
            <line>Come buy of me, come; come buy, come buy;</line>
            <line>Buy lads, or else your lasses cry: Come buy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>If I were not in love with Mopsa, thou shouldst take</line>
            <line>no money of me; but being enthralled as I am, it</line>
            <line>will also be the bondage of certain ribbons and gloves.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOPSA</speaker>
            <line>I was promised them against the feast; but they come</line>
            <line>not too late now.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DORCAS</speaker>
            <line>He hath promised you more than that, or there be liars.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOPSA</speaker>
            <line>He hath paid you all he promised you; may be, he has</line>
            <line>paid you more, which will shame you to give him again.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Is there no manners left among maids? will they</line>
            <line>wear their plackets where they should bear their</line>
            <line>faces? Is there not milking-time, when you are</line>
            <line>going to bed, or kiln-hole, to whistle off these</line>
            <line>secrets, but you must be tittle-tattling before all</line>
            <line>our guests? 'tis well they are whispering: clamour</line>
            <line>your tongues, and not a word more.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOPSA</speaker>
            <line>I have done. Come, you promised me a tawdry-lace</line>
            <line>and a pair of sweet gloves.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Have I not told thee how I was cozened by the way</line>
            <line>and lost all my money?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>And indeed, sir, there are cozeners abroad;</line>
            <line>therefore it behoves men to be wary.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Fear not thou, man, thou shalt lose nothing here.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>I hope so, sir; for I have about me many parcels of charge.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>What hast here? ballads?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOPSA</speaker>
            <line>Pray now, buy some: I love a ballad in print o'</line>
            <line>life, for then we are sure they are true.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>Here's one to a very doleful tune, how a usurer's</line>
            <line>wife was brought to bed of twenty money-bags at a</line>
            <line>burthen and how she longed to eat adders' heads and</line>
            <line>toads carbonadoed.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOPSA</speaker>
            <line>Is it true, think you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>Very true, and but a month old.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DORCAS</speaker>
            <line>Bless me from marrying a usurer!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>Here's the midwife's name to't, one Mistress</line>
            <line>Tale-porter, and five or six honest wives that were</line>
            <line>present. Why should I carry lies abroad?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOPSA</speaker>
            <line>Pray you now, buy it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Come on, lay it by: and let's first see moe</line>
            <line>ballads; we'll buy the other things anon.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>Here's another ballad of a fish, that appeared upon</line>
            <line>the coast on Wednesday the four-score of April,</line>
            <line>forty thousand fathom above water, and sung this</line>
            <line>ballad against the hard hearts of maids: it was</line>
            <line>thought she was a woman and was turned into a cold</line>
            <line>fish for she would not exchange flesh with one that</line>
            <line>loved her: the ballad is very pitiful and as true.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DORCAS</speaker>
            <line>Is it true too, think you?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>Five justices' hands at it, and witnesses more than</line>
            <line>my pack will hold.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Lay it by too: another.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>This is a merry ballad, but a very pretty one.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOPSA</speaker>
            <line>Let's have some merry ones.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>Why, this is a passing merry one and goes to</line>
            <line>the tune of 'Two maids wooing a man:' there's</line>
            <line>scarce a maid westward but she sings it; 'tis in</line>
            <line>request, I can tell you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOPSA</speaker>
            <line>We can both sing it: if thou'lt bear a part, thou</line>
            <line>shalt hear; 'tis in three parts.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DORCAS</speaker>
            <line>We had the tune on't a month ago.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>I can bear my part; you must know 'tis my</line>
            <line>occupation; have at it with you.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>SONG</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>Get you hence, for I must go</line>
            <line>Where it fits not you to know.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DORCAS</speaker>
            <line>Whither?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOPSA</speaker>
            <line>O, whither?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DORCAS</speaker>
            <line>Whither?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOPSA</speaker>
            <line>It becomes thy oath full well,</line>
            <line>Thou to me thy secrets tell.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DORCAS</speaker>
            <line>Me too, let me go thither.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOPSA</speaker>
            <line>Or thou goest to the orange or mill.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DORCAS</speaker>
            <line>If to either, thou dost ill.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>Neither.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DORCAS</speaker>
            <line>What, neither?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>Neither.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>DORCAS</speaker>
            <line>Thou hast sworn my love to be.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>MOPSA</speaker>
            <line>Thou hast sworn it more to me:</line>
            <line>Then whither goest? say, whither?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>We'll have this song out anon by ourselves: my</line>
            <line>father and the gentlemen are in sad talk, and we'll</line>
            <line>not trouble them. Come, bring away thy pack after</line>
            <line>me. Wenches, I'll buy for you both. Pedlar, let's</line>
            <line>have the first choice. Follow me, girls.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit with DORCAS and MOPSA</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>And you shall pay well for 'em.</line>
            <stagedir>Follows singing</stagedir>
            <line>Will you buy any tape,</line>
            <line>Or lace for your cape,</line>
            <line>My dainty duck, my dear-a?</line>
            <line>Any silk, any thread,</line>
            <line>Any toys for your head,</line>
            <line>Of the new'st and finest, finest wear-a?</line>
            <line>Come to the pedlar;</line>
            <line>Money's a medler.</line>
            <line>That doth utter all men's ware-a.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Re-enter Servant</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>Master, there is three carters, three shepherds,</line>
            <line>three neat-herds, three swine-herds, that have made</line>
            <line>themselves all men of hair, they call themselves</line>
            <line>Saltiers, and they have a dance which the wenches</line>
            <line>say is a gallimaufry of gambols, because they are</line>
            <line>not in't; but they themselves are o' the mind, if it</line>
            <line>be not too rough for some that know little but</line>
            <line>bowling, it will please plentifully.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Shepherd</speaker>
            <line>Away! we'll none on 't: here has been too much</line>
            <line>homely foolery already. I know, sir, we weary you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POLIXENES</speaker>
            <line>You weary those that refresh us: pray, let's see</line>
            <line>these four threes of herdsmen.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>One three of them, by their own report, sir, hath</line>
            <line>danced before the king; and not the worst of the</line>
            <line>three but jumps twelve foot and a half by the squier.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Shepherd</speaker>
            <line>Leave your prating: since these good men are</line>
            <line>pleased, let them come in; but quickly now.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Servant</speaker>
            <line>Why, they stay at door, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Here a dance of twelve Satyrs</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POLIXENES</speaker>
            <line>O, father, you'll know more of that hereafter.</line>
            <stagedir>To CAMILLO</stagedir>
            <line>Is it not too far gone? 'Tis time to part them.</line>
            <line>He's simple and tells much.</line>
            <stagedir>To FLORIZEL</stagedir>
            <line>How now, fair shepherd!</line>
            <line>Your heart is full of something that does take</line>
            <line>Your mind from feasting. Sooth, when I was young</line>
            <line>And handed love as you do, I was wont</line>
            <line>To load my she with knacks: I would have ransack'd</line>
            <line>The pedlar's silken treasury and have pour'd it</line>
            <line>To her acceptance; you have let him go</line>
            <line>And nothing marted with him. If your lass</line>
            <line>Interpretation should abuse and call this</line>
            <line>Your lack of love or bounty, you were straited</line>
            <line>For a reply, at least if you make a care</line>
            <line>Of happy holding her.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLORIZEL</speaker>
            <line>Old sir, I know</line>
            <line>She prizes not such trifles as these are:</line>
            <line>The gifts she looks from me are pack'd and lock'd</line>
            <line>Up in my heart; which I have given already,</line>
            <line>But not deliver'd. O, hear me breathe my life</line>
            <line>Before this ancient sir, who, it should seem,</line>
            <line>Hath sometime loved! I take thy hand, this hand,</line>
            <line>As soft as dove's down and as white as it,</line>
            <line>Or Ethiopian's tooth, or the fann'd</line>
            <line>snow that's bolted</line>
            <line>By the northern blasts twice o'er.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POLIXENES</speaker>
            <line>What follows this?</line>
            <line>How prettily the young swain seems to wash</line>
            <line>The hand was fair before! I have put you out:</line>
            <line>But to your protestation; let me hear</line>
            <line>What you profess.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLORIZEL</speaker>
            <line>Do, and be witness to 't.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POLIXENES</speaker>
            <line>And this my neighbour too?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLORIZEL</speaker>
            <line>And he, and more</line>
            <line>Than he, and men, the earth, the heavens, and all:</line>
            <line>That, were I crown'd the most imperial monarch,</line>
            <line>Thereof most worthy, were I the fairest youth</line>
            <line>That ever made eye swerve, had force and knowledge</line>
            <line>More than was ever man's, I would not prize them</line>
            <line>Without her love; for her employ them all;</line>
            <line>Commend them and condemn them to her service</line>
            <line>Or to their own perdition.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POLIXENES</speaker>
            <line>Fairly offer'd.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>This shows a sound affection.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Shepherd</speaker>
            <line>But, my daughter,</line>
            <line>Say you the like to him?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERDITA</speaker>
            <line>I cannot speak</line>
            <line>So well, nothing so well; no, nor mean better:</line>
            <line>By the pattern of mine own thoughts I cut out</line>
            <line>The purity of his.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Shepherd</speaker>
            <line>Take hands, a bargain!</line>
            <line>And, friends unknown, you shall bear witness to 't:</line>
            <line>I give my daughter to him, and will make</line>
            <line>Her portion equal his.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLORIZEL</speaker>
            <line>O, that must be</line>
            <line>I' the virtue of your daughter: one being dead,</line>
            <line>I shall have more than you can dream of yet;</line>
            <line>Enough then for your wonder. But, come on,</line>
            <line>Contract us 'fore these witnesses.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Shepherd</speaker>
            <line>Come, your hand;</line>
            <line>And, daughter, yours.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POLIXENES</speaker>
            <line>Soft, swain, awhile, beseech you;</line>
            <line>Have you a father?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLORIZEL</speaker>
            <line>I have: but what of him?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POLIXENES</speaker>
            <line>Knows he of this?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLORIZEL</speaker>
            <line>He neither does nor shall.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POLIXENES</speaker>
            <line>Methinks a father</line>
            <line>Is at the nuptial of his son a guest</line>
            <line>That best becomes the table. Pray you once more,</line>
            <line>Is not your father grown incapable</line>
            <line>Of reasonable affairs? is he not stupid</line>
            <line>With age and altering rheums? can he speak? hear?</line>
            <line>Know man from man? dispute his own estate?</line>
            <line>Lies he not bed-rid? and again does nothing</line>
            <line>But what he did being childish?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLORIZEL</speaker>
            <line>No, good sir;</line>
            <line>He has his health and ampler strength indeed</line>
            <line>Than most have of his age.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POLIXENES</speaker>
            <line>By my white beard,</line>
            <line>You offer him, if this be so, a wrong</line>
            <line>Something unfilial: reason my son</line>
            <line>Should choose himself a wife, but as good reason</line>
            <line>The father, all whose joy is nothing else</line>
            <line>But fair posterity, should hold some counsel</line>
            <line>In such a business.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLORIZEL</speaker>
            <line>I yield all this;</line>
            <line>But for some other reasons, my grave sir,</line>
            <line>Which 'tis not fit you know, I not acquaint</line>
            <line>My father of this business.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POLIXENES</speaker>
            <line>Let him know't.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLORIZEL</speaker>
            <line>He shall not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POLIXENES</speaker>
            <line>Prithee, let him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLORIZEL</speaker>
            <line>No, he must not.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Shepherd</speaker>
            <line>Let him, my son: he shall not need to grieve</line>
            <line>At knowing of thy choice.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLORIZEL</speaker>
            <line>Come, come, he must not.</line>
            <line>Mark our contract.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POLIXENES</speaker>
            <line>Mark your divorce, young sir,</line>
            <stagedir>Discovering himself</stagedir>
            <line>Whom son I dare not call; thou art too base</line>
            <line>To be acknowledged: thou a sceptre's heir,</line>
            <line>That thus affect'st a sheep-hook! Thou old traitor,</line>
            <line>I am sorry that by hanging thee I can</line>
            <line>But shorten thy life one week. And thou, fresh piece</line>
            <line>Of excellent witchcraft, who of force must know</line>
            <line>The royal fool thou copest with,--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Shepherd</speaker>
            <line>O, my heart!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>POLIXENES</speaker>
            <line>I'll have thy beauty scratch'd with briers, and made</line>
            <line>More homely than thy state. For thee, fond boy,</line>
            <line>If I may ever know thou dost but sigh</line>
            <line>That thou no more shalt see this knack, as never</line>
            <line>I mean thou shalt, we'll bar thee from succession;</line>
            <line>Not hold thee of our blood, no, not our kin,</line>
            <line>Far than Deucalion off: mark thou my words:</line>
            <line>Follow us to the court. Thou churl, for this time,</line>
            <line>Though full of our displeasure, yet we free thee</line>
            <line>From the dead blow of it. And you, enchantment.--</line>
            <line>Worthy enough a herdsman: yea, him too,</line>
            <line>That makes himself, but for our honour therein,</line>
            <line>Unworthy thee,--if ever henceforth thou</line>
            <line>These rural latches to his entrance open,</line>
            <line>Or hoop his body more with thy embraces,</line>
            <line>I will devise a death as cruel for thee</line>
            <line>As thou art tender to't.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERDITA</speaker>
            <line>Even here undone!</line>
            <line>I was not much afeard; for once or twice</line>
            <line>I was about to speak and tell him plainly,</line>
            <line>The selfsame sun that shines upon his court</line>
            <line>Hides not his visage from our cottage but</line>
            <line>Looks on alike. Will't please you, sir, be gone?</line>
            <line>I told you what would come of this: beseech you,</line>
            <line>Of your own state take care: this dream of mine,--</line>
            <line>Being now awake, I'll queen it no inch farther,</line>
            <line>But milk my ewes and weep.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>Why, how now, father!</line>
            <line>Speak ere thou diest.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Shepherd</speaker>
            <line>I cannot speak, nor think</line>
            <line>Nor dare to know that which I know. O sir!</line>
            <line>You have undone a man of fourscore three,</line>
            <line>That thought to fill his grave in quiet, yea,</line>
            <line>To die upon the bed my father died,</line>
            <line>To lie close by his honest bones: but now</line>
            <line>Some hangman must put on my shroud and lay me</line>
            <line>Where no priest shovels in dust. O cursed wretch,</line>
            <line>That knew'st this was the prince,</line>
            <line>and wouldst adventure</line>
            <line>To mingle faith with him! Undone! undone!</line>
            <line>If I might die within this hour, I have lived</line>
            <line>To die when I desire.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLORIZEL</speaker>
            <line>Why look you so upon me?</line>
            <line>I am but sorry, not afeard; delay'd,</line>
            <line>But nothing alter'd: what I was, I am;</line>
            <line>More straining on for plucking back, not following</line>
            <line>My leash unwillingly.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>Gracious my lord,</line>
            <line>You know your father's temper: at this time</line>
            <line>He will allow no speech, which I do guess</line>
            <line>You do not purpose to him; and as hardly</line>
            <line>Will he endure your sight as yet, I fear:</line>
            <line>Then, till the fury of his highness settle,</line>
            <line>Come not before him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLORIZEL</speaker>
            <line>I not purpose it.</line>
            <line>I think, Camillo?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>Even he, my lord.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERDITA</speaker>
            <line>How often have I told you 'twould be thus!</line>
            <line>How often said, my dignity would last</line>
            <line>But till 'twere known!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLORIZEL</speaker>
            <line>It cannot fail but by</line>
            <line>The violation of my faith; and then</line>
            <line>Let nature crush the sides o' the earth together</line>
            <line>And mar the seeds within! Lift up thy looks:</line>
            <line>From my succession wipe me, father; I</line>
            <line>Am heir to my affection.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>Be advised.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLORIZEL</speaker>
            <line>I am, and by my fancy: if my reason</line>
            <line>Will thereto be obedient, I have reason;</line>
            <line>If not, my senses, better pleased with madness,</line>
            <line>Do bid it welcome.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>This is desperate, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLORIZEL</speaker>
            <line>So call it: but it does fulfil my vow;</line>
            <line>I needs must think it honesty. Camillo,</line>
            <line>Not for Bohemia, nor the pomp that may</line>
            <line>Be thereat glean'd, for all the sun sees or</line>
            <line>The close earth wombs or the profound sea hides</line>
            <line>In unknown fathoms, will I break my oath</line>
            <line>To this my fair beloved: therefore, I pray you,</line>
            <line>As you have ever been my father's honour'd friend,</line>
            <line>When he shall miss me,--as, in faith, I mean not</line>
            <line>To see him any more,--cast your good counsels</line>
            <line>Upon his passion; let myself and fortune</line>
            <line>Tug for the time to come. This you may know</line>
            <line>And so deliver, I am put to sea</line>
            <line>With her whom here I cannot hold on shore;</line>
            <line>And most opportune to our need I have</line>
            <line>A vessel rides fast by, but not prepared</line>
            <line>For this design. What course I mean to hold</line>
            <line>Shall nothing benefit your knowledge, nor</line>
            <line>Concern me the reporting.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>O my lord!</line>
            <line>I would your spirit were easier for advice,</line>
            <line>Or stronger for your need.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLORIZEL</speaker>
            <line>Hark, Perdita</line>
            <stagedir>Drawing her aside</stagedir>
            <line>I'll hear you by and by.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>He's irremoveable,</line>
            <line>Resolved for flight. Now were I happy, if</line>
            <line>His going I could frame to serve my turn,</line>
            <line>Save him from danger, do him love and honour,</line>
            <line>Purchase the sight again of dear Sicilia</line>
            <line>And that unhappy king, my master, whom</line>
            <line>I so much thirst to see.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLORIZEL</speaker>
            <line>Now, good Camillo;</line>
            <line>I am so fraught with curious business that</line>
            <line>I leave out ceremony.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>Sir, I think</line>
            <line>You have heard of my poor services, i' the love</line>
            <line>That I have borne your father?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLORIZEL</speaker>
            <line>Very nobly</line>
            <line>Have you deserved: it is my father's music</line>
            <line>To speak your deeds, not little of his care</line>
            <line>To have them recompensed as thought on.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>Well, my lord,</line>
            <line>If you may please to think I love the king</line>
            <line>And through him what is nearest to him, which is</line>
            <line>Your gracious self, embrace but my direction:</line>
            <line>If your more ponderous and settled project</line>
            <line>May suffer alteration, on mine honour,</line>
            <line>I'll point you where you shall have such receiving</line>
            <line>As shall become your highness; where you may</line>
            <line>Enjoy your mistress, from the whom, I see,</line>
            <line>There's no disjunction to be made, but by--</line>
            <line>As heavens forefend!--your ruin; marry her,</line>
            <line>And, with my best endeavours in your absence,</line>
            <line>Your discontenting father strive to qualify</line>
            <line>And bring him up to liking.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLORIZEL</speaker>
            <line>How, Camillo,</line>
            <line>May this, almost a miracle, be done?</line>
            <line>That I may call thee something more than man</line>
            <line>And after that trust to thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>Have you thought on</line>
            <line>A place whereto you'll go?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLORIZEL</speaker>
            <line>Not any yet:</line>
            <line>But as the unthought-on accident is guilty</line>
            <line>To what we wildly do, so we profess</line>
            <line>Ourselves to be the slaves of chance and flies</line>
            <line>Of every wind that blows.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>Then list to me:</line>
            <line>This follows, if you will not change your purpose</line>
            <line>But undergo this flight, make for Sicilia,</line>
            <line>And there present yourself and your fair princess,</line>
            <line>For so I see she must be, 'fore Leontes:</line>
            <line>She shall be habited as it becomes</line>
            <line>The partner of your bed. Methinks I see</line>
            <line>Leontes opening his free arms and weeping</line>
            <line>His welcomes forth; asks thee the son forgiveness,</line>
            <line>As 'twere i' the father's person; kisses the hands</line>
            <line>Of your fresh princess; o'er and o'er divides him</line>
            <line>'Twixt his unkindness and his kindness; the one</line>
            <line>He chides to hell and bids the other grow</line>
            <line>Faster than thought or time.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLORIZEL</speaker>
            <line>Worthy Camillo,</line>
            <line>What colour for my visitation shall I</line>
            <line>Hold up before him?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>Sent by the king your father</line>
            <line>To greet him and to give him comforts. Sir,</line>
            <line>The manner of your bearing towards him, with</line>
            <line>What you as from your father shall deliver,</line>
            <line>Things known betwixt us three, I'll write you down:</line>
            <line>The which shall point you forth at every sitting</line>
            <line>What you must say; that he shall not perceive</line>
            <line>But that you have your father's bosom there</line>
            <line>And speak his very heart.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLORIZEL</speaker>
            <line>I am bound to you:</line>
            <line>There is some sap in this.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>A cause more promising</line>
            <line>Than a wild dedication of yourselves</line>
            <line>To unpath'd waters, undream'd shores, most certain</line>
            <line>To miseries enough; no hope to help you,</line>
            <line>But as you shake off one to take another;</line>
            <line>Nothing so certain as your anchors, who</line>
            <line>Do their best office, if they can but stay you</line>
            <line>Where you'll be loath to be: besides you know</line>
            <line>Prosperity's the very bond of love,</line>
            <line>Whose fresh complexion and whose heart together</line>
            <line>Affliction alters.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERDITA</speaker>
            <line>One of these is true:</line>
            <line>I think affliction may subdue the cheek,</line>
            <line>But not take in the mind.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>Yea, say you so?</line>
            <line>There shall not at your father's house these</line>
            <line>seven years</line>
            <line>Be born another such.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLORIZEL</speaker>
            <line>My good Camillo,</line>
            <line>She is as forward of her breeding as</line>
            <line>She is i' the rear our birth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>I cannot say 'tis pity</line>
            <line>She lacks instructions, for she seems a mistress</line>
            <line>To most that teach.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERDITA</speaker>
            <line>Your pardon, sir; for this</line>
            <line>I'll blush you thanks.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLORIZEL</speaker>
            <line>My prettiest Perdita!</line>
            <line>But O, the thorns we stand upon! Camillo,</line>
            <line>Preserver of my father, now of me,</line>
            <line>The medicine of our house, how shall we do?</line>
            <line>We are not furnish'd like Bohemia's son,</line>
            <line>Nor shall appear in Sicilia.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>My lord,</line>
            <line>Fear none of this: I think you know my fortunes</line>
            <line>Do all lie there: it shall be so my care</line>
            <line>To have you royally appointed as if</line>
            <line>The scene you play were mine. For instance, sir,</line>
            <line>That you may know you shall not want, one word.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>They talk aside</stagedir>
         <stagedir>Re-enter AUTOLYCUS</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>Ha, ha! what a fool Honesty is! and Trust, his</line>
            <line>sworn brother, a very simple gentleman! I have sold</line>
            <line>all my trumpery; not a counterfeit stone, not a</line>
            <line>ribbon, glass, pomander, brooch, table-book, ballad,</line>
            <line>knife, tape, glove, shoe-tie, bracelet, horn-ring,</line>
            <line>to keep my pack from fasting: they throng who</line>
            <line>should buy first, as if my trinkets had been</line>
            <line>hallowed and brought a benediction to the buyer:</line>
            <line>by which means I saw whose purse was best in</line>
            <line>picture; and what I saw, to my good use I</line>
            <line>remembered. My clown, who wants but something to</line>
            <line>be a reasonable man, grew so in love with the</line>
            <line>wenches' song, that he would not stir his pettitoes</line>
            <line>till he had both tune and words; which so drew the</line>
            <line>rest of the herd to me that all their other senses</line>
            <line>stuck in ears: you might have pinched a placket, it</line>
            <line>was senseless; 'twas nothing to geld a codpiece of a</line>
            <line>purse; I could have filed keys off that hung in</line>
            <line>chains: no hearing, no feeling, but my sir's song,</line>
            <line>and admiring the nothing of it. So that in this</line>
            <line>time of lethargy I picked and cut most of their</line>
            <line>festival purses; and had not the old man come in</line>
            <line>with a whoo-bub against his daughter and the king's</line>
            <line>son and scared my choughs from the chaff, I had not</line>
            <line>left a purse alive in the whole army.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>CAMILLO, FLORIZEL, and PERDITA come forward</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>Nay, but my letters, by this means being there</line>
            <line>So soon as you arrive, shall clear that doubt.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLORIZEL</speaker>
            <line>And those that you'll procure from King Leontes--</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>Shall satisfy your father.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERDITA</speaker>
            <line>Happy be you!</line>
            <line>All that you speak shows fair.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>Who have we here?</line>
            <stagedir>Seeing AUTOLYCUS</stagedir>
            <line>We'll make an instrument of this, omit</line>
            <line>Nothing may give us aid.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>If they have overheard me now, why, hanging.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>How now, good fellow! why shakest thou so? Fear</line>
            <line>not, man; here's no harm intended to thee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>I am a poor fellow, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>Why, be so still; here's nobody will steal that from</line>
            <line>thee: yet for the outside of thy poverty we must</line>
            <line>make an exchange; therefore discase thee instantly,</line>
            <line>--thou must think there's a necessity in't,--and</line>
            <line>change garments with this gentleman: though the</line>
            <line>pennyworth on his side be the worst, yet hold thee,</line>
            <line>there's some boot.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>I am a poor fellow, sir.</line>
            <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>
            <line>I know ye well enough.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>Nay, prithee, dispatch: the gentleman is half</line>
            <line>flayed already.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>Are you in earnest, sir?</line>
            <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>
            <line>I smell the trick on't.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLORIZEL</speaker>
            <line>Dispatch, I prithee.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>Indeed, I have had earnest: but I cannot with</line>
            <line>conscience take it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>Unbuckle, unbuckle.</line>
            <stagedir>FLORIZEL and AUTOLYCUS exchange garments</stagedir>
            <line>Fortunate mistress,--let my prophecy</line>
            <line>Come home to ye!--you must retire yourself</line>
            <line>Into some covert: take your sweetheart's hat</line>
            <line>And pluck it o'er your brows, muffle your face,</line>
            <line>Dismantle you, and, as you can, disliken</line>
            <line>The truth of your own seeming; that you may--</line>
            <line>For I do fear eyes over--to shipboard</line>
            <line>Get undescried.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>PERDITA</speaker>
            <line>I see the play so lies</line>
            <line>That I must bear a part.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>No remedy.</line>
            <line>Have you done there?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLORIZEL</speaker>
            <line>Should I now meet my father,</line>
            <line>He would not call me son.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>Nay, you shall have no hat.</line>
            <stagedir>Giving it to PERDITA</stagedir>
            <line>Come, lady, come. Farewell, my friend.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>Adieu, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLORIZEL</speaker>
            <line>O Perdita, what have we twain forgot!</line>
            <line>Pray you, a word.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  What I do next, shall be to tell the king</line>
            <line>Of this escape and whither they are bound;</line>
            <line>Wherein my hope is I shall so prevail</line>
            <line>To force him after: in whose company</line>
            <line>I shall review Sicilia, for whose sight</line>
            <line>I have a woman's longing.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>FLORIZEL</speaker>
            <line>Fortune speed us!</line>
            <line>Thus we set on, Camillo, to the sea-side.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>CAMILLO</speaker>
            <line>The swifter speed the better.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt FLORIZEL, PERDITA, and CAMILLO</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>I understand the business, I hear it: to have an</line>
            <line>open ear, a quick eye, and a nimble hand, is</line>
            <line>necessary for a cut-purse; a good nose is requisite</line>
            <line>also, to smell out work for the other senses. I see</line>
            <line>this is the time that the unjust man doth thrive.</line>
            <line>What an exchange had this been without boot! What</line>
            <line>a boot is here with this exchange! Sure the gods do</line>
            <line>this year connive at us, and we may do any thing</line>
            <line>extempore. The prince himself is about a piece of</line>
            <line>iniquity, stealing away from his father with his</line>
            <line>clog at his heels: if I thought it were a piece of</line>
            <line>honesty to acquaint the king withal, I would not</line>
            <line>do't: I hold it the more knavery to conceal it;</line>
            <line>and therein am I constant to my profession.</line>
            <stagedir>Re-enter Clown and Shepherd</stagedir>
            <line>Aside, aside; here is more matter for a hot brain:</line>
            <line>every lane's end, every shop, church, session,</line>
            <line>hanging, yields a careful man work.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>See, see; what a man you are now!</line>
            <line>There is no other way but to tell the king</line>
            <line>she's a changeling and none of your flesh and blood.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Shepherd</speaker>
            <line>Nay, but hear me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Nay, but hear me.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Shepherd</speaker>
            <line>Go to, then.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>She being none of your flesh and blood, your flesh</line>
            <line>and blood has not offended the king; and so your</line>
            <line>flesh and blood is not to be punished by him. Show</line>
            <line>those things you found about her, those secret</line>
            <line>things, all but what she has with her: this being</line>
            <line>done, let the law go whistle: I warrant you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Shepherd</speaker>
            <line>I will tell the king all, every word, yea, and his</line>
            <line>son's pranks too; who, I may say, is no honest man,</line>
            <line>neither to his father nor to me, to go about to make</line>
            <line>me the king's brother-in-law.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Indeed, brother-in-law was the farthest off you</line>
            <line>could have been to him and then your blood had been</line>
            <line>the dearer by I know how much an ounce.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  Very wisely, puppies!</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Shepherd</speaker>
            <line>Well, let us to the king: there is that in this</line>
            <line>fardel will make him scratch his beard.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  I know not what impediment this complaint</line>
            <line>may be to the flight of my master.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Pray heartily he be at palace.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>
               <stagedir>Aside</stagedir>  Though I am not naturally honest, I am so</line>
            <line>sometimes by chance: let me pocket up my pedlar's excrement.</line>
            <stagedir>Takes off his false beard</stagedir>
            <line>How now, rustics! whither are you bound?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Shepherd</speaker>
            <line>To the palace, an it like your worship.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>Your affairs there, what, with whom, the condition</line>
            <line>of that fardel, the place of your dwelling, your</line>
            <line>names, your ages, of what having, breeding, and any</line>
            <line>thing that is fitting to be known, discover.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>We are but plain fellows, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>A lie; you are rough and hairy. Let me have no</line>
            <line>lying: it becomes none but tradesmen, and they</line>
            <line>often give us soldiers the lie: but we pay them for</line>
            <line>it with stamped coin, not stabbing steel; therefore</line>
            <line>they do not give us the lie.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Your worship had like to have given us one, if you</line>
            <line>had not taken yourself with the manner.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Shepherd</speaker>
            <line>Are you a courtier, an't like you, sir?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>Whether it like me or no, I am a courtier. Seest</line>
            <line>thou not the air of the court in these enfoldings?</line>
            <line>hath not my gait in it the measure of the court?</line>
            <line>receives not thy nose court-odor from me? reflect I</line>
            <line>not on thy baseness court-contempt? Thinkest thou,</line>
            <line>for that I insinuate, or toaze from thee thy</line>
            <line>business, I am therefore no courtier? I am courtier</line>
            <line>cap-a-pe; and one that will either push on or pluck</line>
            <line>back thy business there: whereupon I command thee to</line>
            <line>open thy affair.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Shepherd</speaker>
            <line>My business, sir, is to the king.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>What advocate hast thou to him?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Shepherd</speaker>
            <line>I know not, an't like you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Advocate's the court-word for a pheasant: say you</line>
            <line>have none.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Shepherd</speaker>
            <line>None, sir; I have no pheasant, cock nor hen.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>How blessed are we that are not simple men!</line>
            <line>Yet nature might have made me as these are,</line>
            <line>Therefore I will not disdain.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>This cannot be but a great courtier.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Shepherd</speaker>
            <line>His garments are rich, but he wears</line>
            <line>them not handsomely.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>He seems to be the more noble in being fantastical:</line>
            <line>a great man, I'll warrant; I know by the picking</line>
            <line>on's teeth.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>The fardel there? what's i' the fardel?</line>
            <line>Wherefore that box?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Shepherd</speaker>
            <line>Sir, there lies such secrets in this fardel and box,</line>
            <line>which none must know but the king; and which he</line>
            <line>shall know within this hour, if I may come to the</line>
            <line>speech of him.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>Age, thou hast lost thy labour.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Shepherd</speaker>
            <line>Why, sir?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>The king is not at the palace; he is gone aboard a</line>
            <line>new ship to purge melancholy and air himself: for,</line>
            <line>if thou beest capable of things serious, thou must</line>
            <line>know the king is full of grief.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Shepard</speaker>
            <line>So 'tis said, sir; about his son, that should have</line>
            <line>married a shepherd's daughter.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>If that shepherd be not in hand-fast, let him fly:</line>
            <line>the curses he shall have, the tortures he shall</line>
            <line>feel, will break the back of man, the heart of monster.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Think you so, sir?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>Not he alone shall suffer what wit can make heavy</line>
            <line>and vengeance bitter; but those that are germane to</line>
            <line>him, though removed fifty times, shall all come</line>
            <line>under the hangman: which though it be great pity,</line>
            <line>yet it is necessary. An old sheep-whistling rogue a</line>
            <line>ram-tender, to offer to have his daughter come into</line>
            <line>grace! Some say he shall be stoned; but that death</line>
            <line>is too soft for him, say I draw our throne into a</line>
            <line>sheep-cote! all deaths are too few, the sharpest too easy.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Has the old man e'er a son, sir, do you hear. an't</line>
            <line>like you, sir?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>He has a son, who shall be flayed alive; then</line>
            <line>'nointed over with honey, set on the head of a</line>
            <line>wasp's nest; then stand till he be three quarters</line>
            <line>and a dram dead; then recovered again with</line>
            <line>aqua-vitae or some other hot infusion; then, raw as</line>
            <line>he is, and in the hottest day prognostication</line>
            <line>proclaims, shall be be set against a brick-wall, the</line>
            <line>sun looking with a southward eye upon him, where he</line>
            <line>is to behold him with flies blown to death. But what</line>
            <line>talk we of these traitorly rascals, whose miseries</line>
            <line>are to be smiled at, their offences being so</line>
            <line>capital? Tell me, for you seem to be honest plain</line>
            <line>men, what you have to the king: being something</line>
            <line>gently considered, I'll bring you where he is</line>
            <line>aboard, tender your persons to his presence,</line>
            <line>whisper him in your behalfs; and if it be in man</line>
            <line>besides the king to effect your suits, here is man</line>
            <line>shall do it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>He seems to be of great authority: close with him,</line>
            <line>give him gold; and though authority be a stubborn</line>
            <line>bear, yet he is oft led by the nose with gold: show</line>
            <line>the inside of your purse to the outside of his hand,</line>
            <line>and no more ado. Remember 'stoned,' and 'flayed alive.'</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Shepherd</speaker>
            <line>An't please you, sir, to undertake the business for</line>
            <line>us, here is that gold I have: I'll make it as much</line>
            <line>more and leave this young man in pawn till I bring it you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>After I have done what I promised?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Shepherd</speaker>
            <line>Ay, sir.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>Well, give me the moiety. Are you a party in this business?</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>In some sort, sir: but though my case be a pitiful</line>
            <line>one, I hope I shall not be flayed out of it.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>O, that's the case of the shepherd's son: hang him,</line>
            <line>he'll be made an example.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>Comfort, good comfort! We must to the king and show</line>
            <line>our strange sights: he must know 'tis none of your</line>
            <line>daughter nor my sister; we are gone else. Sir, I</line>
            <line>will give you as much as this old man does when the</line>
            <line>business is performed, and remain, as he says, your</line>
            <line>pawn till it be brought you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>I will trust you. Walk before toward the sea-side;</line>
            <line>go on the right hand: I will but look upon the</line>
            <line>hedge and follow you.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Clown</speaker>
            <line>We are blest in this man, as I may say, even blest.</line>
         </speech>
         <speech>
            <speaker>Shepherd</speaker>
            <line>Let's before as he bids us: he was provided to do us good.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exeunt Shepherd and Clown</stagedir>
         <speech>
            <speaker>AUTOLYCUS</speaker>
            <line>If I had a mind to be honest, I see Fortune would</line>
            <line>not suffer me: she drops booties in my mouth. I am</line>
            <line>courted now with a double occasion, gold and a means</line>
            <line>to do the prince my master good; which who knows how</line>
            <line>that may turn back to my advancement? I will bring</line>
            <line>these two moles, these blind ones, aboard him: if he</line>
            <line>think it fit to shore them again and that the</line>
            <line>complaint they have to the king concerns him</line>
            <line>nothing, let him call me rogue for being so far</line>
            <line>officious; for I am proof against that title and</line>
            <line>what shame else belongs to't. To him will I present</line>
            <line>them: there may be matter in it.</line>
         </speech>
         <stagedir>Exit</stagedir>
      </scene-body>
   </scene>
</act>